<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Rea∣der greeting.</title>
           <author>D., E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113555_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B12309</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6163.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113555</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Rea∣der greeting.</title>
                 <author>D., E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A memento for Christians : In some short meditations on the third verse of the thirteenth chapter of the Epistle vnto the Hebrewes [...] Published by the author, for the comfort of all those that mourne in Sion, and very fit to be seene in the hands of all men in these troublesome dayes of the Churches sorrow</title>
                 <author>Doolittle, E.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Clifton, Fulke</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 85, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Christian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der greeting.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Vrteous Reader, vnto whom this litle Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise in particular is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated, if you bee in Christ, and so a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church; and therefore I doubt not, but that it shall finde free acceptance with thee. I presuming to honour thee with that, which men ordinarily designe to their chiefest friends, euen the dedication of a booke, neither respecting ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour nor greatnesse, nor pompe and dignity, which the world ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lookes after; but finding in thee ioyntly all whatsoeuer is worthie due respect: I haue fastened mine
<pb facs="5"/> eyes (by reason of my affection) full vpon thee; as I presume there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore on thy louing acceptance, so I desire thee to make claime vnto it, for it is thine by right; not onely in respect of the drift of the matter, but also in the intention of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor; it is dedicated vnto thee: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if thou wilt not shew thy selfe inhumane, receiue it louingly, reade it diligently, consider it weightily, and respect it worthily. The matter concernes as thy selfe, so the whole Church of God: it intreates of a dutie inioyned vs by God; which is, to remember those that are in bonds as bound with them, and them that are in affliction, as if wee were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted in the body; for considering with my selfe, the troubles of the Church, not onely at home more couertly, but also abroade more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly: insomuch that it may iustly take vp that cōplaint of the Church in the Lamentations of <hi>Ier.</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no way able to releeue it, I could
<pb facs="5"/> do no lesse then shew my affection towards it, by stirring vp all Gods people to remember it: the which I could not more forcibly do then in the words of God himselfe, wherein he calles vpon all men to remember those that are in bonds. Wherein I obserue the Lord first exhorting vs to a duty. 2. directing vs in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how to doe the same. In the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation I obserue the earnestnesse of it in the word, Remember; in the direction I obserue the strictnes of it in these words, As though you were bound with them. Next I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue the words in particular, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I note first what wee are to doe, To remember. Secondly, who; those in bonds, Thirdly, how, As though wee were bound with them. And lastly from the words in generall, I obserue the great loue of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his afflicted seruants, in calling vpon all his people as it were by open proclamation to remember them. In this Treatise, wee haue
<pb facs="6"/> shewed also how we are to perform holy duties, that wee may doe the will of God on earth as it is done in heauen; For wee must haue respect to the manner, as well as to the matter, in the performing of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly duties: as the reuealed Will of God must bee our ground for the matter, so the holines of God must be our rule for the manner, seeing the Lord is as strict in directing vs how, as earnest in exhorting vs what to doe. Also I haue endeauoured to answer some questions: as first, how wee are to <hi>remember those in bonds.</hi> Secondly, why the Lord suffers his to bee in such bonds and afflictions. And thirdly, how the godly may know that the Lord loues them; notwithstanding they are in great affliction, which is, by entring into the Sanctuary of God; also I haue shewed what the Sanctuary is, and how they may behold God walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therein for their greater com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <p>Now considering also the weight of the word <hi>Remember,</hi> that it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empts none: for if the Lord should haue saide, Releeue them, many haue it not: if hee should haue saide, speak for them, many are bard from it with <hi>Hester,</hi> vnlesse they venture <note place="margin">Hest. 4. 16.</note> their liues or liberty: if hee should haue said, fight for them, many may not; if hee should haue said, deliuer them, many cannot; and therfore he saith, Remember them, which euery one may; for this breakes through all lettes, neither farrenesse of place, nor opposition of power, nor difficulty of danger can let, but eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one may remember them. None can complaine of the poorenesse of their estate, the weakenesse of their bodies, the disability of their nature, nor the tendernesse of their sexe: for euery one may remember them by praying for them, sighing for them, groaning for them, and so mourning and suffering with them. This will stretch euen from the city of <hi>Shushā</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/> throughout al the 127. Prouinces of the King <hi>Ahashuerose:</hi> the opposition of great <hi>Haman</hi> cannot let, nor the presentnesse of their danger preuent it, nor the tendernesse of <hi>Hesters</hi> sexe hinder it. We may many times want eyes to see them, or times to visite them, or opportunity or meanes to minister vnto them; but wee shall neuer want occasion nor meanes to remember them, if we be not wanting in affection towards them. And therefore seeing my abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity could not doe that I would, I thought it my duty to doe that I could, and therein haue endeauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to stirre vp others that are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter able, to doe what they should; whether in the Kings Court with <note place="margin">Nehe. 1. 4. Hest. 5. 2. 1 Sam. 20. 4. Ier. 38. 7, 8. Act. 5. 34. Ier. 9. 1. Psal. 74.</note>
      <hi>Nehemiah;</hi> or in the Kings fauour with <hi>Hester;</hi> or of the Kings seede with <hi>Ionathan;</hi> or one of the <hi>Eunuchs</hi> with <hi>Ebedmelech,</hi> or one of the coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel with <hi>Gamaliel;</hi> whether they are Prophets of the Lord with <hi>Ieremiah,</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/> or Gouernours of Common-weales with <hi>Dauid:</hi> not doubting but this motiue shall haue good successe, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are not my words, but the words of the Lord of hosts, euen the God of heauen and earth that doth require it; and seeing that the dutie is weightie, though the performance bee easie, and yet euery one by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture backeward hereunto. Let this present Treatise be a meanes to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke others who are far more able, to set penne to paper, and to shew thereby not onely their remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of those in bonds, but also to stirre vp others according to their place to mind the same, seeing the State of the Church calles for it like that in <hi>Ieremy, Lamen.</hi> 1. 12. And thus not longer hindering of thee from the worke it selfe, (wherein if you finde any benefite, giue God the prayse, and let me haue the benefite of thy prayers,) I leaue it to thy holy meditations, and thy selfe
<pb facs="8"/> to Gods gracious visitations, wishing as much good to thy soule as thou canst desire prosperity to thy body.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell in the Lord, In whom I rest euer thine, if thou be his.</salute>
      <signed>E. D.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>