<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Faults escaped in the Authors absence, by reason they wer not perfect in the English tongue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113033_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07957</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18326</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113033</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Faults escaped in the Authors absence, by reason they wer not perfect in the English tongue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Our Ladie hath a new sonne</title>
                 <author>C. N.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>—Recusant</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 80, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>Faults escaped in the Authors absence, by reason they wer not perfect in the English tongue.</head>
   <div type="part">
      <head>In the Epistle Dedicatorie.</head>
      <p>For Benoin read Benoni.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>In the Epistle to the Reader.</head>
      <p>Page 1. and line 4. for disfigured, reade adisciphered, and in the 21 line, for giuing 2. ntiquities, read prouing antiquities.</p>
      <p>P. and 11. line, first confirmeth, read first he confirmeth.</p>
      <p>in the note for ad Philan, read ad Philad,</p>
      <p>5. p. and third line, vppon his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, read vpon this commandement.</p>
      <p>7. p. and is line, for Simion read Simeon.</p>
      <p>8. p. and 19 line, for Antonie read Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine.</p>
      <p>Lib. 3. lit. cap. 25. read Lib. 3. Tit. 1. cap. 15. in the 11. line for Ierus read Ferus.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>In the discourse.</head>
      <p>5. p. for wert bidden, read art bidden.</p>
      <p>7. p. and 13. line for expresse them, reade, oppresse thee.</p>
      <p>10. p. and 14. line, for no men but, reade, no men, what then but,</p>
      <p>15. p. and 18. line, for nursed thee with read nursed thee, with.</p>
      <p>heauines, she fled read beauines she fled.</p>
      <p>18. p. and 23. his flight, read his slight?</p>
      <p>e 19. p. and 14 line for whether shall I end ad where shall I end.</p>
      <p>b 23. p. and the leaueth line, for wicked argaine, read wicked bargaine?</p>
      <pb facs="11"/>
      <p> 26 p, and 7, line for that therby they, read that they.</p>
      <p>27. p. and 17 line for die yee shall, reade die he shall</p>
      <p>28 and 9. line gaue him read giue him.</p>
      <p>29 22 for lightning read lighting,</p>
      <p>31. p: and 5 line for yeeldeth hee read yet yeldeth he, forced and constrained, reade constrained.</p>
      <p>33 p. and the 13 line for profits read pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth.</p>
      <p>34 p, and 6, line for if one offence, reade is one offence,</p>
      <p>36 p. and 2. line no other death, reade no death,</p>
      <p>38 and the 2, line for game read gaine,</p>
      <p>49 p, and 1 line for great shame, reade with so great shame,</p>
      <p>52, p and 2, line for acquite he, read ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite him, he for although the reade as though the, for of them as read of, then as for called from the earth, read exalten frō the earth,</p>
      <p>61 p, and 4 line for meane ey the, reade meane by the, for durest not, read dooest not, for or other wise she, reade as other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise she.</p>
      <p>69 pa, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, line for all God, read all good,</p>
      <p>72 p, and 12 line, for my walkes, reade my walles.</p>
      <p>73 p, and 23 line, for a eteranall reade an eternall,</p>
      <p>78 p. and 20 line for that he had, reade that she had.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>