<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS HONORA∣BLE FRIEND, THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL Sir IOHN BAKER Ba∣ronet, Grace, Mer∣cy, and Peace.</title>
           <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113006_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11014</idno>
           <idno type="STC">59.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113006</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS HONORA∣BLE FRIEND, THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL Sir IOHN BAKER Ba∣ronet, Grace, Mer∣cy, and Peace.</title>
                 <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The holinesse of Chrisian [sic] churches, or A sermon preached at the consecration of the chappell of Sr. Iohn Baker : of Sussing-herst in Cranbrooke in Kent, Baronet: upon I Cor. II. 22. By Robert Abbot, vicar of the same parish</title>
                 <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Paine (Payne), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <distributor>Meredith, Christopher</distributor>
                            <distributor>Stephens, Philemon</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 35, 3 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Art and architecture</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HIS HONORA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE FRIEND, THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL Sir IOHN BAKER Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronet, Grace, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and Peace.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon is yours by occasion, and request: and though, in respect of it selfe, it deserves not to appeare in publick; yet <hi>for your sake,</hi> whose name it must beare, I desire it might continue to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steritie.</p>
   <p>Too few <hi>yong and noble</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>gentlemen, shew a pious care, and conscience to religion. The <hi>lusts of the eyes, the lusts of the flesh, and the pride of life,</hi> consume their dayes with vanity and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ednesse. But God of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>hath seasoned</hi> you with a better spirit, and <hi>so stated</hi> you in good, that I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, neither I, nor others shall ever see you altered. I rejoyce, and <hi>it is my crowne,</hi> to see some deepe stamped <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters</hi> in you. I have known you from your infancy, and (from your constant love) have beene no stranger from your house: yet did I never heare you <hi>(blessed be God)</hi> either in passion, or out, to <hi>sweare the least oath,</hi> no nor so much <hi>as once</hi> to use the
<pb facs="3"/>strong and too much tossed Asseverations of <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Troth;</hi> you are constant, <hi>day by day,</hi> at your private devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to <hi>blesse</hi> all your occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, to <hi>prepare</hi> you <hi>for God</hi> whensoever hee shall call, and in the meane time to keepe your sweete acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with heaven. You are so resolved an observer of <hi>Gods solemne worship on the Lords day,</hi> in comming with the first (as you can) and going with the last <hi>(like a doore keeper in the house of your God,)</hi> that, <hi>by your good will,</hi> you would not, <hi>on any season,</hi> loose any part of publike prayer, preaching, catechizing, or Sacraments, <hi>so oft</hi> as they are tendred, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>to the last blessing.</hi> And
<pb facs="4"/>now, <hi>Sir,</hi> because of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance betwixt your house and your Church, and because you would avoid not onely the guilt, but the suspicion of <hi>Clandestine</hi> and unwarrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able courses, you have obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by <hi>Royall</hi> and <hi>Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall</hi> order a consecrated Chappell in your owne house; In which you have, not onely <hi>daily prayers</hi> according to the lawes of our blessed Church; but also you doe <hi>sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the defects</hi> of publike worship, which long waies, and foule weather doe bring upon you, and your blessed family in you.</p>
   <p>How happy is it, <hi>Sir,</hi> for you, and yours, that you had such <hi>Religious Parents</hi> to learne you to beare the sweete
<pb facs="4"/>yoake of <hi>Christ</hi> from your youth! How happie that <hi>God</hi> hath graciously sanctified their care, and your submissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and observance so, as that you goe on <hi>to sow your good seede in this your morning, and doe not yet let your hand rest,</hi> when your yeares speake a full, and ripe young man! Lastly, how happy that God hath given you a <hi>religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lady,</hi> whom you dearely love, and who closeth with you in Love, Mercy, and the devout acts of worship both in publick and private! Long may you live together in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugal love, and pious affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to <hi>God, goodnesse,</hi> and <hi>good people!</hi> And as you have begunne, and hitherto continued, to be <hi>good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>to all my flocke in good workes, and frequenting the house of your God: so that you may still live, and die in such indeavours, resolutions, and practises, shall be the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest prayers of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships in all Christian observance ROBERT ABBOT.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>