<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A COPPIE OF THE ANSWERE TO THE LET∣ter afore-going.</title>
           <author>H., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113265_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03350</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13470</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113265</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A COPPIE OF THE ANSWERE TO THE LET∣ter afore-going.</title>
                 <author>H., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A quartron of reasons of Catholike religion, with as many briefe reasons of refusall: By Tho. Hill</title>
                 <author>Hill, Edmund Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>—Recusant</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 159, 1, 160-187 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>A COPPIE OF THE ANSWERE TO THE LET<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter afore-going.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y DEERE AND</hi> louing friendes, the <hi>23.</hi> of Octob. Ann. <hi>1599.</hi> I receiued your Letter, dated the <hi>13.</hi> of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember of the same yere. In it you giue me to vnderstand, how that my Parents, with other of my kindred, as also you your selues do greatly grieue for that you are frustrated of the hope, and expectation, you had of my worldly abilitie in time to come, with many other profes, of my blinde opinion, selfe-willed conceites, crossing my good fortune, of disgrace among my kindred, banishement, pouerty, and of other such like. All which wordes I count but as winde, or
<pb facs="5"/>
as vaine florishes, the more for that I see all your affection towardes me to be meere car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and that you loue me, <hi>Amore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiscentiae,</hi> rather than <hi>Amore amici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,</hi> seeking your owne good thereby, as may appeare by your owne writing, yet doe I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster all in the best manner. And whatsoeuer you write or say, I knowe doth proceede from loue and affection, and from true amity, but yet sauoring meerly of fleshe and bloode. I knowe my Parents to be kinde and louing, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as nature giueth to them the instinct so to be, and I for my part am ready, &amp; euer haue beene to yeelde to them all duty of an obedient Sonne, as also to you the offices re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in a kinde friende. But this I must entreat both them and you, to giue me leaue to serue and to honour God Almighty, who is Father of all Fathers, and therefore more to be harkened vnto than any kindred, yea or creature whatsoeuer. Which thing I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe but by cleauing to this Religion, wherein I was Borne, Baptised, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, and which I am most strongly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded in my vnderstanding and conscience, to be the onely true Religion. Which setled perswasion and assurance of Faith is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooueable
<pb facs="5"/>
by any humane meanes, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in vaine doe you write such letters vnto me, and in vaine doe my Parentes grieue at my course, for I more lament your state and theirs, than you doe mine. Assure your selfes that I can neuer be perswaded but that I take the only way to gaine Heauen, and so to saue my soule, and only for that ende doe I take this course of life, as God Almighty best knoweth, and mee thinketh you should not deeme it to be any discredite or disgrace so to doe, considering I cleaue to the Religion of all our Auncestours and Forefathers, which hath beene Vniuersall ouer all Christendome, for aboue these thowsand yeeres, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot disgrace me, but it must disgrace the whole Christian worlde also. Indeede if I tooke or helde any newe opinions, as of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritanisme, Brownisme, Martinisme, or of Family of Loue, or such like newe-sprung conceits, you might both iustly condemne my course, &amp; be vtterly ashamed of such a brain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke fellowe as should crosse his worldly wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare by such sottishnesse, and selfe-wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. To satisfie my Parents and your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest, I haue heere written and sent you a Quartron of Reasons of Religion, not intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="6"/>
thereby to perswade you or others there, to this religion which I professe, because I know that to be daungerous, as prohibited by the lawes of the land wherein you liue; but onlie to shewe to them who wishe mee well, what groundes, and reasons I haue for my doinges. I could haue yeelded you so many (if I had thought it fit so to haue done) as would haue made vp a iust volume, and yet haue left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde me infinite moe: but I thought these to suffice, for that I know you haue not leasure, or at the least are vnwilling to trouble your selues with reading ouermuch of such matter. I tearme them a quartron of reasons, because that number is vsuall here in this Countrie, signifying the fourth part, or quarter of an hundred; for when they will name any num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as we vsually doe when we say a dozen, a scoare, &amp;c. they say vnquartron, and by that number they commōly buy buttons, lace, &amp;c. as we doe by dozens in England. Take them in good part my deare friendes, and assure your selues that wheresoeuer I liue, I will still carrie a true English hart with mee, by euer bearing a sacred &amp; reuerent respect towards my Soueraigne Princesse, and my deare coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie; as also a dutifull and obedient minde to
<pb facs="6"/>
my louing Parents, and a friendlie affection towardes you: for I would not haue you to thinke, that liuing out of my Countrie for my conscience, doth any way hinder the duties a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid: for I call God to witnesse, who is the searcher of all hearts, that (my Religion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued) I be are all loyaltie, affection, &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie, which a poore Subiect ought to doe, towards our Soueraigne Queene Elizabeth, (whom I pray God bountifully to blesse, and allaue affection towardes my natiue Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, with duty to Parents, and loue to kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as is aforesaid. And thus desiring my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; mothers blessing, with many humble commendations to them, and no fewer to you, I leaue you to our Lord, who send vs all of his heauenly grace. From my Chamber at Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lempyne this <hi>16.</hi> of Februarie Anno <hi>1600.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your very louing friend. T. H.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>