<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST mightie Monarch, and puissant Prince, IAMES, of England, Scotland, France, and Ireland, King, defender of the Faith, &amp;c. Grace, Mercie, and Peace from him, which was, and which is, and which is to come.</title>
           <author>Thorne, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113932_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13745</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24041</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113932</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST mightie Monarch, and puissant Prince, IAMES, of England, Scotland, France, and Ireland, King, defender of the Faith, &amp;c. Grace, Mercie, and Peace from him, which was, and which is, and which is to come.</title>
                 <author>Thorne, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Esoptron basilikon. Or A kenning-glasse for a Christian king : Taken out of the 19. chapter of the gospell of Saint Iohn, the 5. verse, in the words 3 Behold the man. And treated on by William Thorne, Deane of Chichester, and his Maiesties Hebrew reader in the Vniuersity of Oxford</title>
                 <author>Thorne, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 <publisher>Harrison, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Read, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 68 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST mightie Monarch, and <hi>puissant Prince,</hi> IAMES, of England, Scotland, France, and <hi>Ireland, King, defender of the</hi> Faith, &amp;c. Grace, Mercie, and <hi>Peace from him, which was,</hi> and which is, and which <hi>is to come.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Praesume not (Dread Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne) in this <hi>praefixed Title,</hi> to praescribe praecepts politike to any Christian Prince, much lesse vnto your Sacred Maiestie. Should I attempt any such ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, it would appeare in me <hi>Annibalem Phormio,</hi> as the Adage is, and I were much out of mine Element. This is a proiect more fitting, so high, and Mightie a Prince, as you are,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his <hi>Apop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thegms.</hi>
      </note> and alreadie in that your <hi>Kinglie Gift</hi> to a King most absolutely performed. As <hi>Plutarch</hi> said of that very same word: so may we of that your worke, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. What is it then, which in this <hi>Inscription</hi> of mine I would
<pb facs="3"/> so faine insinuate to my Lord, and King? VVhat but that he alwayes be like himselfe? that he read himselfe as it were, &amp; rule out of his owne booke? Admit then (most Christian King) thou surpas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sedst in perfection (as I pray God thou maiest) all Christian Princes vpon earth; admit no man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained, whom thou mightest imitate;<note n="*" place="margin">August: <hi>on these words;</hi> The Iust shall see, &amp;c. Psal. <hi>52.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Ipse Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus tibi remanet;</hi> there remaines yet for thee <hi>The Imitation of Christ. Beholde the man.</hi> Loe here is<note n="‖" place="margin">A Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-Glasse for a Christian King. <hi>Hom: Iliad</hi> 1. <hi>Val: Mar:</hi> 3.</note>
      <hi>A Kenning-Glasse for a Christian King.</hi> As out of those three verses of <hi>Homer</hi> the Author therof expressed (he said) the very liuing <hi>Image</hi> of Ioue</p>
   <p>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, and so forth: So <hi>this Inscription</hi> I extract out of these three words of<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Iohn</hi> 19.5. The first Booke. <hi>Deutr.</hi> 17.18.19. &amp;c. <hi>Luke.</hi> 16.2.</note>
      <hi>Iohn;</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>Behold the man.</hi> As thou art a Christian, so is this a <hi>Common Glasse</hi> to thee (O King) with all other Christians, as in the first Diuision of the third generall Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of this text, and third distinction I haue de-declared: As thou art a King, so doth it (out <hi>of thine ovvne mouth</hi>) more properlie concerne thee; Aswell for that a <hi>King is to compute</hi> vnto God for each Christian soule in his whole Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale: as that <hi>the</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Isai. <hi>24.2.</hi> Ecclus. <hi>10.2.3.</hi> Hierō: ad Helio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor. Plat. in polit. Regis ad exempū, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Cl. Claud: de <hi>4.</hi> consulat. Henorij.</note>
      <hi>vvhole Common-vveale</hi> is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallie conformed vnto the customes of her King. And therefore of choise I consecrate it vnto thy Christian, and Kinglie calling. Accept then in good part (most Gracious King) this thy poore Schollers praesent. <hi>Christus tibi liber exemplaris est.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ioh. <hi>13.15.</hi>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Constant. ad Sanctorum coetum Orat. c. <hi>12.</hi> in Eusebius.</note> I haue giuen thee (saith Christ) an <hi>example.</hi> He is an <hi>euerlasting example</hi> for thee: Imitate him, and thy subiects will imitate thee. He is a most<note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, Phalereus <hi>to</hi> Ptolome <hi>in</hi> Plutarch.</note>
      <hi>Exemplar states-booke</hi> for thee: Read him,
<pb facs="3"/> and thy Subiects will reade thee. He is a <hi>Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of Magistrates</hi> for thee, <hi>A Kenning-Glasse for Kings:</hi> assimilate thy selfe vnto him, and thy sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects will assimilate themselues vnto thee.<note place="margin">Chrysost:</note> And this is, the Office and vse of this <hi>Glasse.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>JAMES the Minor</hi> (saith one) was very,<note place="margin">Ludolph: de vita Iesu Christi, part. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>59</hi> Galat. <hi>1.19</hi> frater Iesu Ioseph: <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>20.</hi> Euseb: Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiast: hist: <hi>2.1.</hi>
      </note> very like <hi>Christ in face:</hi> and for that cause espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially (the said writer surmizeth) he was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Lords brother.</hi> I dispute not of the one, or the other, of, or on. It seemes he was well seene in this <hi>Spirituall Glasse:</hi> Else whence in his face are those rayes of virtues? his <hi>Humilitie?</hi> for he vvas called<note n="*" place="margin">Iacobus Minor Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolph: <hi>as afore. So</hi>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> in Damas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen.</note>
      <hi>IAMES the lesse.</hi> His <hi>Iustice?</hi> for he was called<note n="‖" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Ex Hegesipp: comment. <hi>5.</hi> Euseb. <hi>2.23</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>IAMES the iust.</hi> His all manner of virtues? for so I suppose, when Christ said vnto him;<note place="margin">
         <hi>Matt.</hi> 11.29. <hi>Iames</hi> 1.23 <hi>Iames</hi> 2.1.4.9. <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.14.15.</note>
      <hi>Learne of me,</hi> for I am humble and meeke: he learned him with humilitie all manner of vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues.</p>
   <p>Good King, will it please thee to consider not sleightly, as did <hi>that man</hi> in Saint <hi>Iames</hi> his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall face, but seriouslie thy <hi>Spirituall face</hi> in this <hi>Glasse,</hi> as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> did? wilt thou compare, and compose the cariage of thy whole life according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie? <hi>Thy Greatnesse</hi> must vouchsafe to do then, as this <hi>Iames</hi> the <hi>Minor,</hi> as this <hi>James the Iust</hi> did: thou must out of thy Iustice distributiue go on in Gods name, as thou hast begun: thou must, as <hi>A iust STEƲƲARD,</hi> diuide aequallie; to thy selfe thine owne, to the Common weale her owne, to the Church her owne, <hi>impartiallie,</hi> without <hi>accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of persons:</hi> thou must scourge out all <hi>Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polye-mongers,</hi> and such like monsters out of thy common-weale: as <hi>Christ did those Money-chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> out of his Church: thou must suppresse all
<pb facs="4"/> Church-robbing-Christ-robbing Satans,<note place="margin">Th' Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles in <hi>VV: Rufus. Iames</hi> 1.27 <hi>Isaiah.</hi> 49.23. <hi>August. de Ciuit: Dei.</hi> 5 24.25. &amp;c. <hi>Iames</hi> 2.8. <hi>Iames.</hi> 4.10 Of <hi>Iames</hi> of Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem, <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Euseb: Hist: Ecclesiast.</hi> 2.23. <hi>De Imitat: Christi</hi> W: Th: <hi>à cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis.</hi> 3.55. 1. <hi>Sa.</hi> 15.17 <hi>Psa.</hi> 82.6.7 <hi>Amos</hi> 6.12 13.</note> suggest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee; <hi>So svveete is the bread of Christ:</hi> and a daintie foode for Kings. To be <hi>a Father vnto the fatherlesse,</hi> an husband to the widowes, <hi>a Foster-father</hi> vnto the Church of Christ, <hi>Hae tibi erunt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes;</hi> — Here is thy glorie (O King) <hi>Si Iustus imperas,</hi> if thou fulfill the <hi>Royall lavve.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Out of thy Humilitie likewise, thou must continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>cast dovvne thy selfe,</hi> and <hi>kneele,</hi> and <hi>Camell</hi> thy <hi>knees</hi> before the Lord thy maker, for thy sinnes, and for the sinnes of thy people: thou must ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steeme thy selfe <hi>so much, and no more,</hi> as God aestee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth thee; thou must be <hi>little</hi> in thine owne eyes. In short thou must reiect thy many flatterers, that will say; <hi>Thou art a God;</hi> and respect thy fewe friends, that will tell thee; <hi>Thou art a man.</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. — I haue said; <hi>Yee are Gods,</hi> but yee shall dye like men. This is indeed to be <hi>James the lesse,</hi> this is the way to be <hi>James the Great,</hi> this is indeed to be <hi>James the Iust.</hi> Doe this, and thou dost rightlie, <hi>Behold the man:</hi> do this, and thou dost rightly contemplate Christ. This is that then, which I was so faine to insinuate vnto thee, my Liege Lord, and King, induced hereto, in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, as your subiect, in speciall, as your Priest, and Scholler: As a Priest in way of conscience I chose to do this, as knowing <hi>Amaziah</hi> of old, what he said vnto <hi>Amos; O, thou the Seer,</hi> go, flee thou away into the land of <hi>Judah,</hi> and there eate thy bread, and Prophesie there. But Prophesie no more at <hi>Beth—el.</hi> For it is <hi>the Kings Chappell,</hi> and <hi>the Kings Court.</hi> As your Scholler in all conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Kings</hi> 1.39.40.</note> I could not choose but doe this; Amidst our <hi>great</hi> Oxford <hi>Hosanna</hi> to adde <hi>my Aramites
<pb facs="4"/> crie</hi> to, <hi>Malco legnolemin cheife;</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.4. 1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 1.31 <hi>Prou:</hi> 8.15. <hi>Prou.</hi> 21.1.</note> God saue <hi>my Lord King James</hi> for euer.</p>
   <p>Now the very God of heauen, and earth (<hi>in vvhose hands</hi> are Kingdoms, and the hearts of Kings) confirme your <hi>Maiesties Throne,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal:</hi> 89.36.37.</note> as the <hi>Sunne</hi> in heauen, and the <hi>Throne</hi> of your <hi>Sonne,</hi> as <hi>the Moone</hi> for euermore. Direct your hearts and handes,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 78.71.72.</note> that you may <hi>seede your peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in Jacob,</hi> according to the Simplicitie of your hearts, and guide your <hi>inheritance in Israel</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the discretion of your hands:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.15. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 17.14 &amp; 19.16.</note> and graunt you both Grace, and your seed after you, alwayes to haue this <hi>Kenning-Glasse</hi> afore your eyes; Euen <hi>The King of Kings,</hi> and Lord of Lords.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Highnesse most</hi> humble Scholler, <hi>William Thorne.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>