<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the moost myghtye, and moste excel∣lent Prince Edwarde the syxte, by the grace of God Kynge of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, defen∣dor of the faithe, and in earth Supreme head of the churche of England and Irelande Bernardinus Ochinus Senensis wisheth all feli∣citie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1549</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113413_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08448</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18770</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113413</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the moost myghtye, and moste excel∣lent Prince Edwarde the syxte, by the grace of God Kynge of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, defen∣dor of the faithe, and in earth Supreme head of the churche of England and Irelande Bernardinus Ochinus Senensis wisheth all feli∣citie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A tragoedie or dialoge of the vniuste vsurped primacie of the Bishop of Rome, and of all the iust abolishyng of the same, made by master Barnardine Ochine an Italian, [and] translated out of Latine into Englishe by Master Iohn Ponet Doctor of Diuinitie, neuer printed before in any language</title>
                 <author>Ochino, Bernardino</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Lynne (Lin), Walter (Gualter, Wouter van)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1549</date>
                 <publisher>Hill (Hyll, van den Berghe, Montanus), Nicholas (Niko—laos).</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>212 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶To the moost myghtye, and moste excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Prince Edwarde the syxte, by the grace of God Kynge of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of the faithe, and in earth Supreme head of the churche of England and Irelande Bernardinus Ochinus Senensis wisheth all feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough god of his mere goodnes hath geuē to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie moste rich treasures, moste large kingdomes, speciall grace and loue of al people, moste high nobilitie of bludde, moste singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler ornamentes bothe of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and of the minde, partely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng onely of God, and partely through hys fauour obtayned also by your industry, beside other innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable graces, whiche it hathe pleased god to endue youre hyghenes withall: Yet neuertheles all these thinges ought not, nor cannot bee compared to that benefite, whiche he hathe shewed vnto you, in geuing vnto you in such a darke world, and in so tendre age, suche clere light of Christ, that albeit in thys worlde he was poore, lowe, dispiced, and crucified, and your Maiestie is so riche, so highe, in so great honour, and all kyndes of felicitie, Yet not only you knowleadge and take hym for youre Lorde and maister, but also you loue hym, and that in suche sorte, that for the loue, whiche you beare vnto hym, you haue suche a godly hatred to his enemies, that folowing the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed memory of your father, fyrste with the fauour of
<pb facs="2"/>
god, and than with the aduise of your most derest vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle the lorde Protector, and of other youre trusty and faithfull Counseylours, you haue dryuen hym out of your Realmes and Dominions hym, who among all the wicked hathe the highest place, and is moste ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersary to Christ, and therfore is he, and may wour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely be called Antichriste. Now remayneth nothing behinde, but that with hym you dryue away also (as you haue begon) his lyes, errours, Hypocrisy, Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monye, Robbery, supersticion, Idolatrye and all wickednes. And than if Pirrus, Alexander magnus, Anibal, Scipio Affricanus, and Iulius Cesar had noble victories and tryumphes in thys world, howe much more shall your noble actes farre passe al them, and theyr actes in the sight of God, aungelles, and men, for asmuch as you (being yet but almost a babe) shall ouerthrowe the most mighty, most crafty, most wycked, and cruell tyraunte, that euer was, or euer shalbe in the worlde, deliuering your subiectes from a longe and miserable bondage, and captiuitie.</p>
   <p>And yet forasmuche as many (suche as bee blynd, and doe take hym for theyr god in erthe, where as they ought most hyghly to commende youre Maies<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for your godly proceadinges,) peraduenture will speake euill of so excellent an acte, I thought it my parte, for the duetye that I owe to god, and to your Maiestie to shewe vnto such men the beginnynge of thys their Papacie, and howe it encreased, and came into so hyghe estimacion amonge the blinde people: So that they perceauinge theyr weake, false, rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouse, and deuilishe foundacion, maye leaue theyr fayt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, whiche they haue in hym, and geue glorye to God and to your Maiestie, to whome I praye god to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>unte a longe and moste blessed lyfe.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>