<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113297_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04410</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14529</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113297</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exact and sound discovery of the chiefe mysteries of jesuiticall iniquity</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 <publisher>Jaggard, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Paxton (Packston), Peter</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>102 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His short en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, wil serue as the key, to let thee in to the whole treasury of Iesui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall villany. It was lent me by one of the most Learned, Graue, and Wisest Papistes that breaths that Ayre. He will tell vs, that all diuision and distraction is not found
<pb facs="5"/>in Amsterdam, or in our Church, since all other or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders are here against the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suites, and the Iesuites a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Pope. He (though a stranger) will inform our miserably-seduced Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, what good Angels the Iesuites are, whom they so much adore; and to what trusty shepheards they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit their souls: whose blind obedience and deuotion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made a sacrifice to Iesui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall ambition, and their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion an onely meanes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray the cause of God, their King, and country, haue had their merite thus Crowned
<pb facs="5"/>with an Italian Prouerbe: <hi>Achimanca vn asino fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia metter la sella adosso vn Catolico Inglese. He that wants an Asse, let him set the saddle vpon an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Catholike.</hi> Poore Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suite-ridden soules, whome we cannot but pitty, while Romanists thus deride thē. God so shine into their hearts by the light of his Spirit, that euen the pen of this Papist, may work in them their own soules conuersion, and the confusion of their Enemies. And that it may teach them to consider, how monstrous the whole Body of Poperie
<pb facs="6"/>must needs bee, when these cheefe heads thereof the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suites, how euer outwardly shewing so strict Discipline and Deuotion, yet are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly composed of nought but damned Matcheuilisme and vnhallowed Ambition.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>