<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Venerable, Religious, and deuout sister, DAME FRANCIS GAWEN, Of the holie Order of S. BENET, and first Abbesse of the cloister of our Ladie of comfort in Cambray.</title>
           <author>Batt, Antonie</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113802_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08952</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1923</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113802</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Venerable, Religious, and deuout sister, DAME FRANCIS GAWEN, Of the holie Order of S. BENET, and first Abbesse of the cloister of our Ladie of comfort in Cambray.</title>
                 <author>Batt, Antonie</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A rule of good life: written by the mellifluous doctor S. Bernard (monke and abbot of the holie order of S. Benet) especiallie for virgins, and other religious woemen; and may profitably be read likewise by all others, that aspire to Christian perfection. Faithfully translated into English by the R. Father Antonie Batt, monke of the holie order afore-said, of the Congregation of England</title>
                 <author>Bernard, of Clairvaux, Saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kellam, Laurence 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 483, that is 479, 1 page, 16°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Venerable, Religious, and deuout sister, DAME FRANCIS GAWEN, Of the holie Order of S. BENET, and first Abbesse of the cloister of our Ladie of comfort in Cambray.</head>
   <p>THE rule of our bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Sauiour (right re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and deuout spouse of Christ Iesus) ordaineth <hi>that we giue not that which is holy to dogges, nor cast
<pb facs="3"/> pearles before swine. Ma. 7.</hi> I persuade my selfe, that I obserue this rule of our Lord, by dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating this holie Treatise, this heauenly pearle, this perfect Institution of a virginal life, to one that is totallie dedicated to Christ, as desiring to be not vnworthy of the name of his done, his loue, his spouse. To such a soule ought such pearles to be addressed. As for dogged hearts, that teare in peeces those that endeauour to feed them with celestial documents:
<pb facs="3"/> or swinish soules, who delight onely in the draught and durt of vanitie and vice: <hi>I</hi> know full well, that such lecture as this is, will be vnsauerie and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome vnto thē; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my thoughts neuer dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted it that way. To you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (religious and deuout Dame) do I addresse it, who by your owne practice, both in your owne selfe, and in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of other soules, can best iudge of it, and most contently sauour it. Vouchsafe to receiue
<pb facs="4"/> it as a remembrance of an old seruant and well-willer of your familie, particularlie obliged to your worthy brother; and by spiritual generatiō become now</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your vnworthy, but most louing brother, in Christ Iesus. Bro: ANTONIE BATT.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>