<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the right Honorable, Robert, Lord Cecill, Baron of Esingdon, Vicecount Crambourne, Earle of Sarum, prin∣cipall Secretarie to the most high and magnificent Prince, IAMES, King of Great Brittaine, France, and Ireland, Master of his Ma∣iesties Wards &amp; Liueries, of his Ma∣iesties most Honorable priuy Councell, and Knight of the most noble Order of the Garer.</title>
           <author>Norden, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113314_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08310</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18639</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113314</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the right Honorable, Robert, Lord Cecill, Baron of Esingdon, Vicecount Crambourne, Earle of Sarum, prin∣cipall Secretarie to the most high and magnificent Prince, IAMES, King of Great Brittaine, France, and Ireland, Master of his Ma∣iesties Wards &amp; Liueries, of his Ma∣iesties most Honorable priuy Councell, and Knight of the most noble Order of the Garer.</title>
                 <author>Norden, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The surueyors dialogue : Diuided into fiue bookes: very profitable for all men to peruse, that haue to do with the reuenues of land, or the manurance, vse, or occupation thereof, both lords and tenants: as also and especially for such as indeuor to be seene in the faculty of surueying of mannors, lands, tenements, &amp;c. By I.N</title>
                 <author>Norden, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 244, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧ To the right Honorable, Robert, Lord Cecill, Baron of Esingdon, Vicecount Crambourne, Earle of Sarum, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Secretarie to the most high and magnificent Prince, <hi>IAMES,</hi> King of Great Brittaine, France, and Ireland, Master of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties Wards &amp; Liueries, of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties most Honorable priuy Councell, and Knight of the most noble Order of the Gar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Earth (right Honorable) was giuen to man: and man (after diuine) was enioyned the care of earthly things: euery mā in seuerall place, qualitie and state, the greatest recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thence greatest dignities, euen to be called <hi>Princes of the earth.</hi> So, is it not the least regard, that men of whatsoeuer title or place, should haue of the lawfull and iust meanes of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation and increase of their earthly reuenues.
<pb facs="3"/>
And that especially, by iustly atchieuing, and rightly vsing Dominion and Lordship▪ which principally grow, (omitting publique office and authoritie) by Honors, Mannors, Lands, and Tenants: for, according to the largenesse of reuenues, are the meanes to enable the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, to shelter the vertuous distressed, and to cherish such as by desert may challenge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard: And according to their will and power therein, is the vulgar reputation of their Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence▪ But (my good Lord) as mine inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor in this rude Dialogue, tendeth but, as it were, to the plow: So I omit to wade into the impassable censure of Honor and Dignitie, wishing it euer deserued reuerence. And as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Land-reuenues, wherwith many are (but especially the Honorable are, or ought to be principally) endowed, I presume onely in this simple Treatise to discourse: So farre (according to my sle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>der capacitie, and weake experience) as concerneth the ordinary necessary meanes of the maintenance &amp; increase of Land-reuenues. And because the true and exact Surueying of Land, is the principall: I haue herein indeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, more of Desire, then of Power, (for the vse and benefite of all sorts of men, hauing to deale with land, both Lords and Tenants,) to shew the necessitie, and simple method thereof, Most humbly intreating your good Lordship (the fruites of whose, and of your honorable Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers fauours, I haue many wayes tasted) to
<pb facs="3"/>
vouchsafe me your Honorable pardon for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suming, and your like patience in accepting at my hands, this little mite; which, were it as great, as any wel-wishing hart can intend good, it were (together with my poore selfe) in truest seruice vnfainedly your Lordships. It may ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore please the same to accept it: so shall others the more willingly embrace it, or the lesse dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace it, humbly recommending it to your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious fauour.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>At my poore house at Hendon,</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>prime Ianuar.</hi> 1607.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Lordships euer to be commanded, <hi>Io. Norden.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>