<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST EXCELLENT, MIGH∣TIE, PVISSANT, WISE, AND VERTVOVS PRINCE, IAMES: by the grace of God, King of great Brit∣taine, France, and Ireland, defender of the Faith, &amp;c. T. B. wisheth all celestiall Honour, and eternall Blisse.</title>
           <author>Bedle, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113620_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07557</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1794</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113620</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST EXCELLENT, MIGH∣TIE, PVISSANT, WISE, AND VERTVOVS PRINCE, IAMES: by the grace of God, King of great Brit∣taine, France, and Ireland, defender of the Faith, &amp;c. T. B. wisheth all celestiall Honour, and eternall Blisse.</title>
                 <author>Bedle, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The princelie progresse of the chvrch militant : marching forth by the steps of the flocke to her triumphant bridegrome Christ Iesvs. Encovntered with an erronius army, turned aside from Iesus to the Ieesitcall [sic] faction, to fight with the lambe, and make warre with the saints. As it appeareth in the ensuing opposition. With an addition demonstrating the abolishing of Antichrist, supreme head of heretickes, and vniuersall maintainer of treason. Written by Thomas Bedle</title>
                 <author>Bedle, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Archer, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 115, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST EXCELLENT, MIGH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIE, PVISSANT, WISE, AND VERTVOVS PRINCE, <hi>IAMES:</hi> by the grace of God, King of great Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, France, and Ireland, defender of the Faith, &amp;c. <hi>T. B.</hi> wisheth all celestiall <hi>Honour, and eternall Blisse.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST mightie Monarch.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>In the infancie of the precious bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>Church,</hi> planted by the <hi>perfection</hi> of <hi>beauty</hi> vpon the <hi>earth, Lucifer</hi> in his <hi>instruments</hi> roared against it: <hi>Christianos ad leonem: non licet esse Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anos.</hi> In the <hi>reigne</hi> of <hi>Queene Mary,</hi> the haire then being growne as white as the <hi>bloome</hi> of the <hi>Almonde tree; Christianos ad ignem: non li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet esse Christianos.</hi> In the reigne of <hi>Queene Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>either <hi>Lyon</hi> nor <hi>Fire</hi> te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rified <hi>Gods children,</hi> he hastened to <hi>Rome,</hi> s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nt away
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Perillus</hi> brasen <hi>Bull,</hi> to see if any <hi>Phalaris</hi> would, or could torment <hi>Gods children</hi> therein. But when none of power could be found, he (knowing that the <hi>Children</hi> of the Church plaied stil about the <hi>mouth</hi> of the <hi>Bull,</hi> as vpon the <hi>hole</hi> of the <hi>Aspe</hi>) poasted from <hi>Rome</hi> to this little <hi>Paradise;</hi> to try if he could by speaking to your Maiestie in Popish bookes, and peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, procure your <hi>Grace</hi> to the <hi>Churches</hi> sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersion, to eate of the forbidden fruite. But herein likewise failing, he mustereth vp <hi>Cay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas knights,</hi> that they might besiege the <hi>Church</hi> by compassing the <hi>tents</hi> of the <hi>Saints about,</hi> and the beloued <hi>citty</hi> (inhabiting as a glorious <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch,</hi> liuing vnder your <hi>gracious</hi> and <hi>royall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment</hi>) in the <hi>Parliament house;</hi> to the end shee might (as the <hi>Chariot</hi> of <hi>Light,</hi> there imployed to Gods glory) be ouerturned by those <hi>Phaë<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons,</hi> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s <hi>instrumentall surtes:</hi> in whom he euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more roareth <hi>Nemo nostrûm frug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>esto.</hi> But see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (right royall Soueraigne) the all-seeing <hi>Deity</hi> (that made them cry, <hi>Deus venit in castra, vae no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>is</hi>) hath preuented the same, to the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of vs you Maiesty as a <hi>King</hi> not amongst vs before; once more in all humilitie, as vpon a second <hi>Coronation,</hi> I do present vnto your <hi>Highnesse,</hi> these <hi>liuely Oppositions,</hi> shewing the diff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rence betweene the <hi>truth</hi> preached by
<pb facs="3"/> the Lords <hi>Ambassadours:</hi> and the <hi>falshood</hi> by <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish instruments,</hi> which <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> vnworthy of that stile, would with so much bloud set vp. Thus crauing pardon of your <hi>gracious Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mencie</hi> for my boldnesse herein, In all humility, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>God</hi> to blesse your <hi>Maiestie,</hi> your <hi>vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Queene,</hi> and <hi>royall progeny,</hi> with the glorious <hi>beatitude</hi> of this <hi>life,</hi> and the <hi>blisse</hi> of <hi>eternity;</hi> I humbly take my leaue,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Maiesties poore Subiect in all humble and dutifull o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience,</hi> Thomas Bedle.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>