<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113991_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08906</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19182</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113991</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The secrets of physick and philosophy : divided into two bookes: in the first is shewed the true and perfect order to distill, or draw forth the oyles of all manner of gummes, spices, seedes, roots, and hearbs, with their perfect taste, smell and vertues. In the second is shewed the true and perfect order to prepare, calcine, sublime, and dissolue all manner of minerals, and how ye shall draw forth their oyles and salts, which are most wonderfull in their operations, for the health of mans bodie. First written in the German tongue by the most learned Theophrastus Paraselsus, and now published in the English tongue, by Iohn Hester, practitioner in the art of distillation</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 <publisher>Lugger (Luggard), William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 196, 16 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="63"/>
   <pb n="103" facs="63"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Booke (welbeloved Reader) I have taken upon mee to set foorth, the true and worthy cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the distillation of Mineralles, that is, of those things which are found in the Mines, as all
<pb n="104" facs="64"/>manner of Salts, Allums, Vitrioll, Sulphur, Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and such like Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talles, as <hi>Saturnus, Iupiter, Mars, Sol, Luna, Venus.</hi> And how you shall get the liquor or moisture out of them. And all that which appertaineth to the health of man. The which I meane by the grace of God to set foorth in this Booke, with a number of Alchy mistes preparations of the said things, the which worketh wonderfully in mans body: so that it seemeth to divers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons myraculous.</p>
   <pb n="105" facs="64"/>
   <p>Therfore (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) peruse this Booke with discretion, and then if thou seest it stand to thy minde, set thy hand to the plough and be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in the worke, so that thou mayest know the proofe, and feele the ready commoditie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, for yee shall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand that there is no me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine in the world that can be found of so quicke operation as the Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls are, if they bee truely prepared and as I will shew you here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after: but if they be not well prepared they
<pb n="106" facs="65"/>are very hurtfull, and not to bee allowed. Therefore looke that ye prepare them as I shall shew you, and then you shall wonder at their working.</p>
   <p>And although the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy science of <hi>Alchimie</hi> is come in such disdaine through lewd persons, that it seemeth lyes and fables, and no true sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: Yet that ought not to hinder or derogate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing to our purpose, as long as our matter is against the abuse of it, as for example:</p>
   <p>The <hi>Alchymistes</hi> have
<pb n="107" facs="65"/>wrought in this worke, to the intent they might have of Lead and Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Gold and Silver, or the meane to make them of all other simples or slight mettalles. But whether God hath given them that gift I know not: therefore I leave it to the Masters of that Arte. And albeit wee have seene many won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull things in that Arte: yet will I not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that it is possible to be done, for it seemeth vnreasonable, that a man in so short time should doe that thing the which
<pb n="108" facs="66"/>nature doth in many yeares. And that men should presume to doe that which God doth only himselfe, and not any of his creatures. Wee therefore will not affirme it to bee true or possible, nor yet will wee deny it vtterly or condemne it as untrueth. But wee will leave the answer to those that take it to be done.</p>
   <p>But heere in this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise wee will set foorth that which we have seen and wrought, and proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and are expert therein: And although it
<pb n="109" facs="66"/>bee sprung out of the Arte of <hi>Alchymie,</hi> yet it is not to that intent, for it serveth not to transmute Mettalles, but it serveth to helpe those diseased both inwardly and outwardly, who of the common sort of Chirurgions are counted uncurable, and also given over of the Physitians. Those Patients shall be holpen through the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den mysteries &amp; heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly secrets of this science.</p>
   <p>And forasmuch as it is unpossible to prepare these things without the Arte of <hi>Alchymie:</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="110" facs="67"/>we must praise this art through our preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons above al other scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that maketh for the health of man, for they preserue a man only tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and afflicted with slight wounds and griefes on his body, and that with much paine and much adoe. But this Arte giveth unto man his health againe in short time, and with smal paine unto the patient, be he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so desperately sicke, and to mans thinking past cure: for I have seene myracles therein.</p>
   <p>And insomuch that it
<pb n="111" facs="67"/>is all prepared with fire: the meane man calleth it <hi>Alchymia.</hi> Howbeit the intent of the <hi>Alchymist</hi> is farre from our intent. But call it what you will, it maketh not much mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the name. For I am sure there is nothing in all Physicke that mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>streth eyther better or readier helpe to cure mans body, then this sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of preparing mettals with fire rightly. I say rightly prepared, not as the unskilfull <hi>Apoticaries</hi> have ordered them, or as the unlearned Physitians have occupied them, for
<pb n="112" facs="68"/>the <hi>Apoticary</hi> is no other then a servant in the kitchin (as I may terme him) and no master Cooke, so long as hee knoweth not these pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, which I will shew you.</p>
   <p>In like maner it is to be thought of the Physitian that hath no skill in these preparations. For wee have seene and prooved divers times, that the first vapour or smoake of any Herbe or Spice is the best that is therein, and yet our learned Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitians commaund it to be boyled untill halfe be
<pb n="113" facs="68"/>consumed, &amp;c. Then note if the best flie away in boyling, what strength can the Medicine have. Therefore I say that the Physitian without this Arte of preparation is little or nothing worth, although they take the patients money. For he goeth to worke blindly with a blinde leader, which is the Apoticary. But the Physitian that is expert in this Science, and doeth prepare his Medicines truely, hee is to be praysed above all other. For a man cannot buy with any money
<pb n="114" facs="69"/>that which is got by long carefull travell. Therefore is the Arte of <hi>Alchymie</hi> worthy to be praised, and the <hi>Alchymist</hi> to bee praised also, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they attaine not to their first intention, yet they have opened the way through the which this excellent cunning of preparation was knowne and found, and through the which there are a number of wonderfull secrets opened, the which without this Arte were all unknown, to the great hinderance of the sicke and diseased persons.
<pb n="115" facs="69"/>Therfore I wil not speak against it, but hold it in great estimation to our intention, that is the help of the sicke and diseased person, and to prepare the Mineralles where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you may doe that which cannot bee done with any other Hearbs, or simples, or spices And heerewith will we finish this preface, and write of the names of the simples, which are occupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this Arte.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>