<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Postscript]</title>
           <author>Chibald, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113998_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08926</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19204</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113998</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Postscript]</title>
                 <author>Chibald, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The copie of a late decree of the Sorbone at Paris, for the condemning of that impious and hæreticall opinion, touching the murthering of princes : generally maintained by the Iesuites, and amongst the rest, of late by Ioannes Mariana, a Spaniard: together, with the arres of the Parliament, for the confirmation of that decree, and the condemning of the said Marianas booke, to be publiquely burnt by the executioner. Taken out of the Register of the Parliament, and translated into English</title>
                 <author>Université de Paris</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barker, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="postscript">
   <pb facs="19"/>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat you be not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> of one particular occasion of these pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings against <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anas</hi> booke (which my friend in his Preface hath not touched) concurring with the generall detestation of that impious do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of murther, the practise whereof wee haue seene vpon the persons of two late Kings of France, HENRY the third and fourth: you shall vnderstand that <hi>Rauillac,</hi> the villaine, who gaue that accursed stroke, which hath made all France to bleed, being (as in his Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions he deliuered) a long time in delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ere he could resolue, that it was law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to kill the King: falling vpon that booke of <hi>Mariana,</hi> he found his conscience (as he said) cleared of all scruple in that point, and himselfe fully resolued to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake
<pb facs="20"/>it. And certainely the cordiall doctrine, which he from thence receiued, so setled his resolution before hand, so steeled his heart in the execution, and after the deed seared and mortified his consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in such sort, as that hee was so farre from any remorse of the fact, as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science and comfort therof seemed to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den him against all sense of his punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For being vrged by torture to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse the trueth by whome he was set on worke, I will giue you a taste of one or two of his confessions, as I receiued them from thence. At one time being examined vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the racke, who were his perswaders to that accursed deed: he desired to be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and hee would confesse the trueth: which being done, and he set on his feet, he stretching out himselfe, tolde them: <hi>The trueth was, that now he found himselfe at much more ease, then before, when he was on the torture.</hi> And this was all the trueth, he would at that time confesse. At ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time <hi>President Iannin</hi> being appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to examine him, and pressing him ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="20"/>straightly to confesse, who had incited him to this fact: hee bad the Clerke set downe that <hi>President Iannin</hi> had incited him therunto: who detesting the villaines desperate audaciousnesse therein: he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied againe; <hi>Well Sir, if I should say so much at my death, I beleeue it would trouble you.</hi> These things being aduertised from thence, I thought fit to impart vnto you, as arguments of the Caitises impenitency, and finall obduration, touching that exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable fact, grounded vpon the doctrine so condemned: the first sparkes whereof being (as appeareth) kindled in France a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two hundred yeeres since, were then trode vnder foote by the <hi>Sorbone</hi> and the Councell of Constance: but since haue bene reuiued by the Iesuites (the most in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrious purueyours for the Popes Court) and by their Lectures and bookes nourished and brought to those flames that now wee see: as it hath beene not seldome obiected vnto them, but neuer yet by them wel denied; I am sure the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine neuer publikely condemned by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="21"/>resolution of their schooles, as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and of late by the Colledge of <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone.</hi> So as whosoeuer put the knife into the villaines hand, it is euident, that the mettall wherof it was made, (I meane the aforesaid doctrine) was tempered in their forge, and their bookes (as it is confessed) gaue edge vnto it. Neither to say trueth, can it euer be imagined, that these wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched soules (such as this <hi>Rauillac</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him <hi>Iohn Chastel</hi>) being perplexed in conscience, and almost brought to the pit of despaire, with remorse of some sinnes of frailtie, durst euer haue aduentured vpon a malicious and deliberate purpose of murther, especially of their Soueraigne; had they not bene resolued in conscience by their ghostly fathers, (which office the Iesuits haue almost ingrossed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues) that howsoeuer it were a very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous sinne to murther a priuate person: yet was it a merite, able to redeeme a world of former sinnes, to kill a king, such a one, as they should point out vnto them. But whatsoeuer the ground may be, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb facs="21"/>it is, there is a very hard opinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of them in <hi>France</hi> touching the late murther of the King, as may appeare by a briefe <hi>Pasquill</hi> set vp in <hi>Paris</hi> to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, the occasion whereof was this. After the <hi>Iesuites</hi> had stood a while bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed by the <hi>Arrest</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> it is too well knowen how the late King (though against the generall wish of the whole State, and the aduise of many his loyall seruants) repealed that <hi>Arrest,</hi> defaced the Marble Pillar, wherein their banish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the causes thereof were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded, recalled them home into his Realme (all men wondering to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose it might be, vnlesse it were to that, which since hath happened) tooke some of them too neere his bosome, and that he might assure (if it were possible) their loyaltie vnto him, erected for their societie a stately Colledge in <hi>la Flesche,</hi> the place where he himselfe was borne. These re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious persons, in exchange of such his gracious fauours towards them, bare him likewise so zealous an affection, as they
<pb facs="22"/>were neuer satisfied, vntill they had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten his heart into their hands (the richest treasure hee could haue endowed them withall) to initiate therewith the Chappel of their new erected Colledge. Which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obtained, and deliuered vnto them in a boxe of Siluer, layed on a pillow of red Veluet, they receiued with solemne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, to carry in triumph to their said Colledge. At whose departure it is by the way reported, that a chiefe President of <hi>París,</hi> let fall a question vnto them, comming to take their leaue: Whether the Kings tooth which <hi>Chastel</hi> stroke out, were likewise enclosed in the boxe with the heart. This fauour of obtaining the Kings heart to burie in their Colledge, gaue occasion (amongst many other) of this Pasquill:
<q>
         <lg>
            <l>
               <hi>Ce n'est, qu'a vous (trouppe sacrée)</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Quo'n doibt bailler le Coeur des Roys:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Quand les grands Cerfs sont aux abboys,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>On en doibt aux chiens la</hi> Cureé.</l>
         </lg>
         <pb facs="22"/>
         <lg>
            <l>T'is you alone (you sacred crue)</l>
            <l>To whom the hearts of Kings are due.</l>
            <l>When the great Harts are hunted hard,</l>
            <l>The entrailes are the Hounds reward.</l>
         </lg>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>The riddle may perhaps seeme at the first somewhat obscure, but I know you wil reade it without a Light. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I spare my paines to expound it, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing already done more then I could well doe, to turne it in rime. And so hauing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted you with those aduertisements which came to my handes touching this businesse, being certified hither by a very credible Author, which I haue to shew; I cease to trouble you.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>J. W.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>