<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113712_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10341</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20620</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113712</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A replye answering a defence of the sermon, preached at the consecration of the bishop of Bathe and Welles, by George Downame, Doctor of Divinitye : In defence of an answere to the foresayd sermon imprinted anno 1609</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 <publisher>Thorp, Giles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Thorp, Giles</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 293, 11, 164 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was well said of <note n="†" place="margin">Lib. de ira. Vtrique parti acti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes dares, dares tempus, nō semel audires: magis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim veritas elucet, quò saepius ad manū ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit.</note>
      <hi>Seneca,</hi> that in matters of controversy, <hi>each party should have time to trie his actiō, &amp; be heard more then once;</hi> &amp; the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son therof aswel givē by him: <hi>because the ofte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the truth cōmeth to hād,</hi> (to be scanned) <hi>the more the light thereof appeareth.</hi> Seing therfore, it hath pleased the (Chr. Rea.) with some paciēce to heare M. D. in defence of his sermon, against the answer to it; I hope thou wilt vouchsafe the Refut: the reading of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie, for the justifying of it. When I first read that pretēded defeni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of his, &amp; sawe the strange &amp; palpable vanitie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and how it was but like an overblowne bladder, that would burst of it selfe, and vent the wind thereof with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any pricking; I thought it needles, to intreat on our part any further audience; but afterwards hearing the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mō fame was, that it was so learnedly and absolutely done, that it gave all men satisfaction (refractaries onely excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) and that no man would ever be able, to make any sound reply to it: I thought it good to take a second view thereof, and when (as before) I found litle or nothing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but calumniations, sarcasmes, or bitter scoffes, slanders, vntruthes, contradictions to himselfe, the question conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually begged; yea both assertions and questions (first pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in his sermon) changed; and his proofes large for what was never doubted of, and fewe or none for the maine point in question, either from his text, or other scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or any ancient and sound writers: and yet all outfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with strange professions, protestatiōs, braggs &amp; boasts of victorie: I conceived with my selfe, that common bruite must needs arise from such (as fayling in that rule of Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca) had read litle thereof, and taking lesse paines in exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and comparing it, eyther with his sermon &amp; it selfe;
<pb facs="3"/> or the Refuters answer; and therefore deemed it necessary to call the reader back, to a better consideration of the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sines, out of perswasion, that vpon a new surveigh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, his second thoughts (which ought to be more wise) would give a righter sentence, concerning both the D. weake and insufficient dealing therein; (to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ay no worse of it) and his owne rash and vnadvised verdict (if I may so call it) of the cause in triall. Now, to give the reader some inckling, aswell, concerning the proceeding of the one in his defence; as of the other in this replye, be he adverti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and let the marginall notes, direct him.</p>
   <p>First cōcerning his bitte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> scoffs &amp; raylings, that he shall th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> especially meet with them, whē being at a nō-plus, he letts the point in questiō alone; so that we may truely <hi>suppose of him,</hi> (as <note n="*" place="margin">Hierō: ad Helvid: A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> bitror te veritate su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratū, ad maledicta converti. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>Ad vers. Ruff: apol. 3. quid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert, si cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sa cadis &amp; criminesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>res?</note> one did of another) <hi>that overcome of the truth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e fell to evill speaking:</hi> but the advised reader, will wisely consider and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ay with the same<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> father, <hi>it nothing boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a man, if he lett his cause fall to the ground, though he overcome in such dealing.</hi> Had M. D. met with an answerer of his owne humor; he mought have beene sure, (as one <note n="''" place="margin">Salust: Si quā volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>dicendo cenisti, eā ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endo amit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas.</note> sayd to Tully) <hi>to have lost the pleasure he tooke in speaking e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, by hearing evill againe:</hi> but his happ is better, he that nowe hath him in hand, hath not so learned Christ, as to recompence evill for evill, and so to <hi>plunge himselfe</hi> into the same condemnation, (as one <note n="†" place="margin">Amb. lib. de offic. 1. c. 5. Si referas contume liam, dicitur, ambo conviciati sunt, vterque condemnatur, nemo absolvitur.</note> saith) with his adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie; knowing that no man (wise at least;) will so much as assay <hi>to</hi>
      <note n="‡" place="margin">oude is kako, kakon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ata<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>heale one evil with another,</hi> and deeming it <note n="*" place="margin">kakos a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ouein kreisson he le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> kakos</note>
      <hi>much better to heare evil then to speak evill.</hi> And therefore as one <note n="†" place="margin">Quam me pudet ne quitiae tuae, cujus teipsum n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n pudet. saith Tully to Anthony. Phil. 2.</note>
      <hi>ashamed of that, whereat perhapps, the D. blushed not;</hi> raking them vnder the ashes rather then abroad, he overpasseth thē save that now &amp; then he remembreth him of his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
<pb facs="3"/> and willeth him to take home, what he vnjustly cast abro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d.</p>
   <p>Secondly concerning his vntruthes and slanders, (if I may speak in the words of another man <note n="†" place="margin">Aug. epis. 164. miro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> si habe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> in corpore sanguinē, qui ad haec verba non erubescit.</note>) I mervayle <hi>that having any blood in his body he blushed not at them;</hi> and the rather doe I merveyll; because they are not onely simple slaunders and vntruthes; but (to make the reader beleeve the contrary) coloured over by him with other slanders and vntruthes: and those so grosse, that a man <hi>may feele them with his</hi>
      <note n="''" place="margin">Hieron: ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t. Vel manibus palpari possunt, et caecus sit oportet, qui se mē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiri non cernat.</note>
      <hi>fingers, and cannot but be blinded</hi> (on that side) <hi>that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eeth them not.</hi> The Refuter (I doubt not) <note n="'†" place="margin">Amb. li. 1. cap 1. 15 Bene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>bi conscius, non debet falsis mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veri; ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> aestimare plus pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deris esse in alieno conviti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, quam in suo testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monio.</note>
      <hi>privie to his owne innocencie, will not be moved with those falshoods; but esteeme the testimonie of his owne conscience more worth then so;</hi> having learned, that the <note n="*" place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>g. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>etil l. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 8. Nec ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scientiam sanat praeconium laudan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>is, nec bonam vulnerat, conviciantis opprobrium.</note>
      <hi>reproach of the slaunderer can no more wound the good conscience, then the praise of the flatterer can heale the evill;</hi> and that false calumniations shall no more fasten vpon the innocent, then blowes vpon the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent; as one wittily insinuated, speaking of one that rayled on him: <note n="'*" place="margin">Me paronta kai tupteto me.</note>
      <hi>let him beat me being absent:</hi> yea I perswade my self that he <hi>findeth</hi>
      <note n="'" place="margin">Cyprian de bapt. nequaquam sub hoc onere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> tudinem, sed quietem invenimus.</note>
      <hi>rest rather then wearines vnder the burdē of them;</hi> and with holy Iob <note n="''" place="margin">Cap. 31. 36.</note> hath taken <hi>them: vpon his shoulder and bownd</hi> them as a <hi>crowne vnto him;</hi> knowing that the D. <note n="','" place="margin">Aug. co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t. Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>l. lib. 3. c. 7. volens detrahit fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eae. nolens addit mercedi.</note>
      <hi>detracting so willingly from his fame, hath added a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst his will to his reward.</hi> There was no neede therefore in regard of himselfe to free him frō the D. slaunders, the <hi>testimonie</hi>
      <note n="†" place="margin">Aug. ad frat. in Ere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ihi quidē sufficit conscientia mea, vobis aut necessaria est <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ama mea.</note>
      <hi>of his owne conscience being enough to him,</hi> but for so much as <hi>his good name is necessarie for others;</hi> his slanders are not therefore alwaise passed by; but sometimes mett
<pb facs="4"/> with and proved so to be, and that not the Refuter but the D. is the slanderer yea such an one, as to colour one hath not blushed to make two. Wherefore it shall be good for him to follow the counsell of an ancient <note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>asil, ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>unom: he apalei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pson sou ta remata he me ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou ten asebeian.</note> father, in his next writing vz▪ to <hi>blot out his slanders, or to cōfesse his iniquity.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thirdly as touching his shiftings &amp; windings in and out, let it be observed, how in his defense, he turneth his whole sermon vpside downe, not onely wandring from the question, but changing and subverting the state thereof; yea changing his assertions and points of his sermon, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them neyther <hi>eadem,</hi> nor <hi>eodem numero.</hi> The which (not to mention how he altereth, clippeth, &amp; perverteth, his Refut: both words and purpose) vvhat are they, but <note n="'" place="margin">Misera kres<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>geta seu tergi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versantis effugia.</note>
      <hi>miserable starting holes,</hi> &amp; scape-doores for him to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lie out at, that turneth his back vpon the cause, and dareth not stand to it? <hi>To conceale</hi> (saith <note n="'†" place="margin">Aug. quaest. vet. test. 14. Qui ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba suppri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stionis, au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> imperitus est, aut ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giversatu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, qui ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniae magis stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deat, quā doctrinae</note> one) <hi>or suppresse the words of the question, argueth either want of skill,</hi> (vvhich must not be imputed to the D. for vve knovv vvhat he professeth of his ovvne skill in judging of an argument) <hi>or a wrangling spirit more studious to cavill, then desirous to teach or learne.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Fourthly, hovvever the state of the question standeth, as he hath layd it dovvne in his sermon or defence, looke vve to his proofes, and it vvill appeare, that as in his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon he scarcely assaied to prove the same, by any vvord of his text: so vvith so little successe hath he travailed in his defence to dravv it, or any other scriptures to the justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying thereof; that I dare boldly say, he hath no one place of scripture, vnder the shadovv vvhereof, he can find any shelter, to shrowd his episcopal fūctiō, as a <hi>divine ordināce.</hi> Novv vvho knoweth not that in al questiōs of this nature, no other testimony or argumēt, cā strike the stroke to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>svvade the cōsciēce, but the authentical records of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost; or some inevitable consequence grounded vpon
<pb facs="4"/> them. For as one vvell saith: <note n="''" place="margin">Chris<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>st. in Psal. 95. ad finem. Si quid dicatur absque scriptura, and itorum cogitatio claudicat: nunc ann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> haesitans, et interdum sermonem ut frivolū aversans, interdum ut proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilem reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piens: ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum vbi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> scriptura vocis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dijt testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monium: et loquentis sermonem, &amp; audien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis animā. confirmat.</note>
      <hi>If any thing be spoken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out scripture the minde of the hearers halteth, now stooping to it, now sticking at it, sometimes turning frō it as frivolous, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times turning to it, as probable: but whē the testimony of the spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker cōmeth from divine scripture; it confirmeth both the speach of the speaker, and mind of the hearer.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The vvhich had the D. regarded so carefully as he ought, much labour might have bene spared, both to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, his Refuter, and Reader; for as all that he hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged from the scriptures (both in his sermon and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence) being dravven togither, vvould scarsely amount to so many lines as he hath filled leaves: so vvould it have bene of more force (then all his councells and fathers) to inforce the conscience, had it made but halfe so much for his advantage as he supposeth. For vvho is not of their minde vvho thought <note n="†" place="margin">Panor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit: in cap sig. extrv. de elect. Gers. part. 1. de ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> doctr.</note> it meet, that <hi>one poore lay-man</hi> (right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) <hi>alleadging a text of the old or new testament, ought to be preferred before the generall councels.</hi> The vvhich, because the D. hath not done, he hath done nothing to the purpose; for hovvever he and his Bps. be (as one <note n="''," place="margin">Bishop Barlow. se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> in Act. 29. 28.</note> of them saith) <hi>no Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadians, to fetch their pedegre from beyonde the moone:</hi> yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the D. can prove their calling to be a divine ordinance, he must fetch it from the divine scriptures, farre beyond his councels and Fathers alleadged.</p>
   <p>Fiftly I graunt indeed, he alleadgeth scriptures asvvell as other testimonies; but they are such as prove vvhat vvas never doubted of, or such as prove those points that directly conclude not his assertions, but referred by him to questions besides the question, or else (to let passe hovv he taketh one part of the question to prove another) such as are meere begging of the question, tvvise 20. times at the least. Wherefore though he had <hi>againe and againe</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Etiam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> millies repeteret, nihil quam Sisiphi saxum volveret, nec hilum pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eret.</note>
      <hi>a 1000. times after the</hi> same manner gone over <hi>them, what hath he
<pb facs="5"/> else done but turned the stone of Sisiphus,</hi> and left it vvhere he found it, vv<seg rend="sup">th</seg> out profit to his cause, or hurt to his adversary.</p>
   <p>Sixtly, vvhich is yet more, the reader may see hovv foule he falleth (and often) vpon his ovvne ancres; for he is almost as full of contradictions to himselfe, as of beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings of the question; so that the saying of the Orator <note n="†" place="margin">Phil. 2. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m eras excors, ut tota in ora tione tecū ipse pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nares, ut non solum non cohae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>entia inter se diceres; sed maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè disiun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta et con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traria, ut non tanta mecum, quanta tibi tecū esset contentio.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Anthony, as fitly agreeth to him, as if it had bene first spoken to him; he <hi>being indeed throughout his whole dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course at such odds with himselfe that he hath not onely vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed things not hanging togither; but so different and contrarie, that he is at greater variance with himself, thē with his adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</hi> The which what can it else argue, but that as he is a mā <note n="*" place="margin">epilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>menos heactou.</note>
      <hi>forgetful of himself, and not likely to be agreed with,</hi> that dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeth so much with himself; so he is not a little pus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed in in the cause; but vnabble to mainteyne it. Now that vve may knovve vvhat to stand to, be he intreated, against his next vvriting, to settle himselfe upon one and the same ground. If vve may judge of that vvhich is to come, by that vvhich is past, it is likely he vvill streine the best of his vvits for some distinctions, to recōcile those differences, &amp; cure those botches; but let him deale more sincerely, then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly he hath done, least his Cataplasmes prove such so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phismes (too many vvhereof the reader may meet vvith in his defense) as vvil make the soare vvorse rather then bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and him to loose more peace at home, then gaine vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie abroade.</p>
   <p>Seventhly, all his former proceedings notvvithstanding, it is a vvonder to see, vvith vvhat strange boldnes &amp; boasts of victorie, he marcheth on from the beginning to the end? Verily such, as if all his proofes, vvere such <note n="''" place="margin">
         <hi>anantir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retas,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones omni exceptione majores.</note>
      <hi>evident demō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strations,</hi> as are above all <hi>exception, admitting no contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> such Achillean arguments and <hi>forcible</hi>
      <note n="†" place="margin">ischuroi logoi, meden diakrinomen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>reasons,</hi> as are not to <hi>be resisted or doubted of;</hi> and as he hath great store of
<pb facs="5"/> them even <hi>(huper ek perissou)</hi> more then enough; so (if wee may beleeve him) there is no one of them, which is not of the nature of the Popes sentēce (penitus definitiva) abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely definitive, not liable to exception or appeale. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is ready <note n="†" place="margin">Tous anti <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>gontas elegchein.</note>
      <hi>sharply to censure all gainsayers,</hi> hovv lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, iudicious, &amp; orthodoxal divines soever) and to charge them that doe <hi>(heterodidaskalein)</hi> teach othervvise, vvith misinterpreting both of scriptures and fathers, yea &amp; vvith other crimes, little better then blasphemy. Wherein, though it vvere no great presumptiō for him to take liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty so, to abuse his refuter considering the base conceite, he hath of him; yet seing he hath acknovvledged others, vvhome he hath shutt up under the same sentences, to be both learned and orthodoxall divines, and are such indeed, as both he and all men ought to reverence; he ought cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teynly to have dealt <note n="*" place="margin">Cum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis bene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agier oportet, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>Tully. Phil. 3. cur eos quos om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, solus oppugnas?</note> better with them, the heathen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Iudge.</p>
   <p>But let not the Doctor think, so to carry the matter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: I hope the wise and judicious reader studious of the truth, wilbe able to discerne <note n="''" place="margin">Aug. ad Petil l. 2. c. 10. non so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum inani sonitu, sed in capite vestro cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puerint.</note> that <hi>his blowne sentences with so many vaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>racks, are broken upon his owne head;</hi> and that this lofty lifting up of his head (in a cause that liveth so much upon begging and by shifts), is both unworthy a man of his note, and such as vvill <note n="†" place="margin">Evagrius. <hi>deinon est<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> mega p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nein, mikr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> pratto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note> never bring grace to him. It vvould in all likelihood, have argued him to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of good proof; if he had in more humility hung dovvn his head like an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>are of good corne, then to stand so bolt upright as he doth.</p>
   <p>Eightly, concerning the course taken in this replie; be the Reader advertised. 1. that therin nothing is dealt vvith, but the Doctors text, and other places of scripture pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, excepting such vvriters as are alleaged for interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of them, and the clearing of the Refuter from the
<pb facs="6"/> slanders layd upon him for misalleadging them. And the reason is, both because the scriptures onely can (and are alone sufficient) to decide the maine controversy concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the right of the episcopall function; and also for that the Doctor rejecteth all nevve vvriters as parties and incō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent, for the same cause for vvhich, the refuter might as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvel reject the old, were they (as they are not) such Bishops and of his side, as he pretendeth. 2. The D. is not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed stepp by stepp in his ovvne order throughout his vvhole book, but that vvhich lieth straggling here &amp; there, is dravvne togither into one tracte, asvvell concerning his text, as the rest of the scriptures alleadged by him 3. nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are the 5. pointes of his sermon handled in the same order; for, the first of them concerning the Eldership, is put off to the last place, it being proved to perteyn nothing to the maine question. 4. The vvhole is divided into three partes; in the first vvhereof are 3. bookes, the first concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Refuters preface, the 2. concerning the fitnes of the Doctors choise of his text, the division &amp; analysis thereof, togither vvith the state of the question, &amp;c. the 3. concerning the true and genuine sense of his text, and whatsoever he speaketh of it. In the 2. part, first, all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther scriptures alleadged by him for proof of the question are dealt with; and then the Refuter is cleared of falsifying and misapplying many testimonies of humane writers, wherewith the Doctor often chargeth him; by occasion whereof it is made manifest, that many of the D. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were neyther such Bishops, nor yet of the D. opinion concerning the pointe in question, as he affirmeth. In the third part is handled that first point of his, concerning the Eldershippe.</p>
   <p>Lastly, to end with a suite or two, 1. Let me intreat M. D, that ne pulchrum sibi ducat esse Davum in hac fabula,
<pb facs="6"/> imò unguem in vlcere ecclesiae; the which if I may not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne, but upon his third thoughts he remaine the man that he professeth to be in his second, and that I have to doe with the <note n="*" place="margin">Tully. Phil. 2. Non est mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi cum eo hoste cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamen, cū quo aliqua pacis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicio esse possit.</note> Orators adversarie, one that will receive no condition of peace, but upon yeelding him the cause against truth; I desire him, that, leaving all by-matters and amending such faults as he is justly taxed with, in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, he would follow the truth in love, vvithout gall, and bitternes, as he tendreth peace at home, and desireth to bring this controversie to an happy and speedy issue. 2. As for the reader, I pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e him, that looking rather into the matter, then enquiring after the authour, he would not (like the schollers of Pithagoras) builde aforehand, on the opinion of the teacher (whether the D. or Refuter) but <note n="†" place="margin">Amb. de fide. lib. 1. c. 7. Imperiti legunt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ut in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligant.</note> reade all, seriously studie, ponder and examine all, that both parties have sayd in the whole carriage of this busynes: &amp; then judge as God shall give vnderstanding; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring what folly and shame it is for any (as Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon saith <note n="‡" place="margin">Prov. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>8, 13.</note>) to answer (or give sentence of) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> matter, before he heare it; wherein I perswade my selfe too many have much fayled, aswel in praejudging the author of the answer, as the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or cause in question</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>