<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113793_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09265</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1958</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113793</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Plaine euidences : The Church of England is apostolicall, the separation schismaticall. Directed against Mr. Ainsworth the Separatist, and Mr. Smith the Se-baptist: both of them seuerally opposing the booke called the Separatists schisme. By Richard Bernard, preacher of the word of God at Worsop. ... Set out by authoritie. Anno. 1610</title>
                 <author>Bernard, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 <distributor>Weaver (Wever), Edmund</distributor>
                            <distributor>Welby, William</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 338, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>AVTHORS of new deuices are selfe pleasing, they are concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and like onely their owne inuentions: I perceiue it is in vaine to perswade. Easier it is to draw a profane person from Hell gates, then to remoue an opinion from a wilfull minde. Schisme is the Ship whereon goe aboard malecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, the Windes that set it forward are violent pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, Will is the Rudder, Obstinacie the Anchor. Schismatickes are headstrong, they will not see eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent conuiction: selfe-loue maketh them iudge the best of themselues, but their want of Charitie very badly of others. They beguile themselues with shew of pietie, heat of affection, and with a strong appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension of things greatly amisse in others. These can they see with both eyes, themselues with neither. No Church can passe them, wherein they cannot see a rocke of offence, and a stone to stumble at. They keepe a loofe off from all, they leaue one Church, and come not at another; alone they loue to be; singulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is their path-way. The common roade of the best
<pb facs="7"/> reformed Churches is too foule for their sinceritie. Our arguments against them are paper shot, as they hold: but their weakest reasons against vs (if them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues may iudge) are shot of Cannon. They despise euery mans endeauour against them, and are in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration with their owne workes. Let any conferre with them, and they shall heare it, I my selfe suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently haue experience of it. By this might I be moued to cease this second labour; but I am not hopelesse to hold some men back, &amp; to gaine some also, though I cannot recouer what is wholie already lost. If I might speed in both I would be glad, if but in one, I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent: in both to loose my labour, I cannot doubt.</p>
   <p>Thou hast here (gentle Reader) an Answere of mine, and also a Reply vnto an Answere made by one by M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Ainsworth</hi> the Doctor, so called, of the Schismaticall Church of <hi>Brounists</hi> at <hi>Amsterdam.</hi> His answere is, to my booke called the <hi>Separatists Schisme:</hi> what wee both say, I pray thee iudge after tryall. Let it please thee to reade my former booke, to discerne what I hold, and here still maintaine. If thou hast hap to light vpon this Answerers booke, so read it, as thou also compare mine and it together. Much hath he omitted in my booke, the <hi>Epistle</hi> wholy, and all <hi>the Counsels of Peace:</hi> wherein are somethings, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture, in the reading whereof thou shalt not iudge time lost. This Answerer in his booke onely once doth mention them, but with this his Comment vpon me, that <hi>perhaps I knew no more then</hi> CAIPHAS <hi>what I said.</hi> It is well yet, that the worke is approued, though hee iudge the Author ignorant of his owne
<pb facs="7"/> inuented labour. He hath also passed ouer very much in the matter of the Booke, touching the chiefe points betweene vs and them: and therefore the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to iudge of his answere, and to see the truth, read my other Booke.</p>
   <p>I obserue an humour in men arising of idlenesse, or of carelesnesse, or of loue onely of nouelties, or of them all, to reade the last onely, and to neglect what before hath bene written, so take they opinions without tryall, iudge without searching, but so can hold nothing certaine. A reason to disswade men from writing in matters of controuersie, except wee doe write all on both sides, and make a great volume of a penny Pamphlet, which is too toylesome, and also superfluous, when bookes may be compared to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
   <p>When I was writing ouer my reply to this M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Ainsworth:</hi> which I had thought should haue gone forth so alone, I receiued by Gods good prouidence the <hi>Se-baptists</hi> booke, I meane M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Smiths</hi> answere al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, that so it might not boast like an <hi>Heathenish Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias,</hi> against Gods Church, without an encounter, I haue therfore placed him, and ranked him in his due order as he came, &amp; made answere therto as is meet, lest this <hi>wofull man</hi> should still mislead others, as he doth his owne selfe, by his braine-sicknesse: I heare of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Robinsons</hi> answere also; if it had come in, hee should also haue beene replyed vpon. Though I be a weake man, and my weapons be against these three Captaines of three Companies, and but a stone in a sling, yet shall Israel preuaile: the truth
<pb facs="8"/> is strong against all enemies whosoeuer they be.</p>
   <p>They would ouer-loade me with number, but as <hi>Elisha</hi> said, <hi>moe are with vs then against vs.</hi> Indeede I want the help of my brethren: yet I neither doe nor will bid, curse <hi>Meroz,</hi> the Lord forgiue them their<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5. 23.</note> carelesnesse, if not the hypocrisie of men herein. If we be the Lords people, why suffer we the Lord to be blasphemed by these men? if we be not, why halt we betweene two opinions? If our standing be of God, let vs maintaine it; if these men be in the true &amp; one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way, let vs make a seperation; why stand wee idle in the market place? Here is worke, let vs labour in the Lords Vineyard, if (in our iudgement) it be the Lords Vineyard; els let vs be going. If I were not perswaded in my soule, that here is the true Church of God, I professe vnfainedly (by Gods help) that I would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce my standing, whatsoeuer wicked and vnchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hearts censure to the contrary.</p>
   <p>But say some, these men will neuer be answered. No more will the great Aduersarie (hee and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments are importunate) yet must hee and they be euer resisted, till they flye from vs. Men feare the end, before they beginne: remoue carelesnesse and idlenesse, and behold the issue. If thou wilt not be publike, write in priuate. They raile (some say) and abuse men, what then? God will be auenged on <hi>Rabshakehs:</hi> and their cause gaineth nothing by their bitternesse. For my part, I will endeuour to further the truth, as farre as I shall be able to giue answere to what may be said against it; for their ill carriage, I will as well as I may beare it patiently. I hope I haue
<pb facs="8"/> in this, published sufficiently to the world my Faith and resolution, in this particuler truth of the Church, in contending with these our aduersaries. In time, if time may be granted me, I haue a purpose to set downe, so the truth of this point, concerning a true, and a false Church, by definitions, and distributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, declaring the properties and priuiledges of the Church inuisible and visible, and so of the militant and triumphant, as the order with the seuerall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof shall require: and thereto as an euident plainenesse of the same to all, I will adde an Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical narration of the Church out of the Scriptures, from the creation of the world, and so farre as the Scriptures euidently declare it: wherein I will, by Gods help, obserue the <hi>matter of the Church,</hi> the <hi>Worship,</hi> the <hi>Gouernment,</hi> and the <hi>Gouernours of the same,</hi> as may giue indifferent men a godly satisfaction in this point of controuersie, if other more fit for this, doe not performe it. In the meane space, I iudge that herein I haue performed on my behalfe, what I ought, and what was expected at my hands to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, for the honour of God, the reuerence of our Church, the credit of mine owne ministerie, the veritie of my vndertaken cause against these Schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes, and withall for a iust defence of mine owne person, wickedly traduced by some. I looke not to satisfie the <hi>Separatists,</hi> much lesse the strange man M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Smith</hi> the <hi>Se-baptist;</hi> how can a man quiet them that loue contention? I haue endeuoured to performe a duety, whereunto I haue beene iustly called, as I haue shewed in my former Booke; what men may
<pb facs="9"/> imagine I know not; how they will iudge of my good purpose, I much reckon not; let conscience acquite mee, though all condemne me, I much care not, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit I desire the approbation euer of thee a godly and iudicious Reader: if so thou beest.</p>
   <p>I leaue thee friend to peruse this labour, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the cause, as of great moment, to thy consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration: weigh well the matter, iudge of our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, answeres, and the reply without partialitie; let thine vpright heart effect, as thy right knowledge in euery thing shall settle thy iudgement and conuince thy conscience. I leaue euery one to their owne liking, approue or disallow, doe their owne wils, so will men in these dayes, I am one in my selfe, to them indifferent: let Truth preuaile and God receiue glory.</p>
   <closer>Amen. Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>