<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull, Master William Halliday, Al∣derman and Sheriffe of London, all happines.</title>
           <author>N., N.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S113834_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06051</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1645</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S113834</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull, Master William Halliday, Al∣derman and Sheriffe of London, all happines.</title>
                 <author>N., N.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A letter written by Mr. Paul Bayne, minister of Gods word, lately deceased. Effectually instructing, and earnestly prouoking to true repentance, loue, and new obedience. Very profitable for euery one that would proceede on in the constant course of a godly life, shewing the way vnto it, and seriously exciting vnto more perfection therein</title>
                 <author>Baynes, Paul</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 90 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull, Master <hi>William Halliday,</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman and Sheriffe of London, all happines.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, this small, but holy trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, being gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen mee by him, vnto whom it was written, to send it forth more publikely into the world. And knowing what euill and iniurious enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement Orphans often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times receiue in the world, except they haue some spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial friend to countenance them, I am bold to adresse
<pb facs="3"/> my selfe vnto you with this Religious child of a godly learned (but deceased) father for shelter: and indeed vnto whom could I with more assured hope dedicate it for harbour, then to your selfe, vnder whose roofe I and mine are harbored? and therefore that so in som part I might manifest my loue and gratefulnes vnto you, I present this with my selfe alwaies ready to doe you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good seruice,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours humbly N. N.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>