<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Computation after Christ.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114788_Fr1_14</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09632</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19900</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114788</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Computation after Christ.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An houreglasse : contayning I a computation from the beginning of time to Christ by X. articles. II A confirmation of the same for the times controuersed before Christ: as also that there wanteth a yeare after Christ, in the vsuall computation. With other matters, offered to the iudgement of the learned, and vse of the studious in chronologie and historie. By Thomas Pie Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Pie, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Robinson, Robert</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 98, 8 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="computation">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>The Computation <hi>after Christ.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He yeare of the world <hi>4020.</hi> and the Incarnation of Christ began iust together. But the vulgar and vsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Computation from the Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Christ, vsed in this Realme and other places, doth not reach to Christs true In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, and the beginning of the yeare, <hi>4020.</hi> by one whole yeare: but beginneth the first day of the yeare of the world, <hi>4021.</hi> Wherefore in redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing that vulgar computation to the true computa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Christs Incarnation, and then consequently by it to the yeares of the world, you must euer first adde one to the yeare of that vulgar computation, which also must bee done to the computations of the church of Rome from the Natiuitie or <hi>25.</hi> of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember, and of the Citie of Rome and Astronomers
<pb facs="7"/>
from the Circumcision or first of Ianuarie: between the Incarnation or twentie fiue of March, and the said daies of Natiuitie and Circumcision following. But the first quarter of their said computation run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth iumpe with the last quarter of the same yeare of his true incarnation. As thus, Februarie second, one thousand fiue hundred ninetie fiue, according to the computation of Rome and the Astronomers, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so Februarie second, one thousand fiue hundred nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie fiue, according to the true computation of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation. But the first day of Aprill, one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand fiue hundred ninetie fiue, according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Rome, is the first of Aprill, one thousand fiue hundred ninetie sixe, after the true computation of Christs Incarnation. See more of this in the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course following.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>