<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND, AND RELIGIOVS LADY, BARBARA VVISEMAN, ABBESSE OF THE ENGLISH MONASTERY OF SION IN LISBONE, OF THE HOLY ORDER OF S. BRIGIT. AND TO THE REST OF THE RELIGIOVS SISTERS OF THAT HOLY HOVSE, AND FAMILY.</title>
           <author>W., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114703_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09668</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19938</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114703</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND, AND RELIGIOVS LADY, BARBARA VVISEMAN, ABBESSE OF THE ENGLISH MONASTERY OF SION IN LISBONE, OF THE HOLY ORDER OF S. BRIGIT. AND TO THE REST OF THE RELIGIOVS SISTERS OF THAT HOLY HOVSE, AND FAMILY.</title>
                 <author>W., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The mirrour of religious perfection : deuided into foure bookes. Written in Italian by the R. F. Lucas Pinelli, of the Society of Iesus. And translated into English by a Father of the same Society</title>
                 <author>Pinelli, Luca</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 560 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND, AND RELIGIOVS LADY, <hi>BARBARA VVISEMAN,</hi> ABBESSE OF THE ENGLISH MONASTERY OF SION IN LISBONE, OF THE HOLY ORDER <hi>OF S. BRIGIT.</hi> AND TO THE REST OF THE RELIGIOVS SISTERS OF THAT HOLY HOVSE, AND FAMILY.</head>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT REVEREND LADY, AND RELIGIOVS SISTERS,</salute>
   </opener>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>ID not the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectfull Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to your holy House and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ouercome the distance of Place, or my small Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; I should not commend this little Treatise of RELI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GIOVS PERFECTION to a Patronage so far remote from our Natiue Countrey: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther seeke a Protectour neerer home. But seing so much Land, as lyeth betweene, doth not hinder the Fame of your Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
<pb facs="4"/>
Example &amp; austere Life, from passing into these parts: so neither shall the seas drowne my Desires of your continuall Progresse, nor stay them from aduenturing with this Present, to make them knowne vnto you.</p>
   <p>In this RELIGIOVS MIRROVR, you may behould rare Vertues, and accordingly draw in your selues the forme of highest Perfection. Heere shall you find whatsoeuer may help to the spirituall Aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your soules: and by reading attentiuely, reape con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digne fruites of your deuout Labours. The Method is easy, the Stile plaine, the Treasure
<pb facs="4"/>
thereof infinitely rich, and the Author well knowne through the world by his worthy Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises of Piety, and Deuotion: Wherof this One may seem, by Gods speciall Prouidence, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted for fuell to increase the fire of Deuotion in your Brests; thereby to inflame the Harts of many Worthy Perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages, to an holy Emulation of your Example.</p>
   <p>I will not trouble your Ladiship, nor the rest of your vertuous Family with a longer Epistle; but end, with many harty wishes of spirituall Light to your soules by this resplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent MIRROVR, and of Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines to our afflicted Countrey
<pb facs="5"/>
by your returne to your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient SION, now forlorne and desolate by your Absence. At least, that I may meet with you in the Heauenly SION, with all Respectfullnes I craue your holy prayers. This feast of the Glorious Virgin SAINT BRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GIT, resting euer,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your La. deuoted seruant, I. VV.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>