<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114055_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16174</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3098</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114055</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A reproofe of M. Doct. Abbots defence, of the Catholike deformed by M. W. Perkins : Wherein his sundry abuses of Gods sacred word, and most manifold mangling, misaplying, and falsifying, the auncient Fathers sentences,be so plainely discouered, euen to the eye of euery indifferent reader, that whosoeuer hath any due care of his owne saluation, can neuer hereafter giue him more credit, in matter of faith and religion. The first part. Made by W.P.B. and Doct. in diuinty</title>
                 <author>Bishop, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>—Recusant</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>287 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="Bishop_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OOD CHRISTIAN READER,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>I doe volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily confesse, that after I had seene <hi>M. Abbots</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere to my Epistle vnto his Majesty, I was a long time vnwilling to reply vpon it; not for that I estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it to containe any such extraordinary learning, as be too too fondly vaunteth off (for I dare be bold to say, that in a skilful mans judgement, there are more pregnant proofes of their new doctrine in two leaues of <hi>M. Perkins</hi> booke, then in tenne of his:) but cleane contrary, I finde so little substance in his worke, and so great store of impertinent and vile stuffe, such super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity of idle amplifications, so many vnciuil and foule wordes; that I could not thinke the time wel bestowed, which should be spent in so friuolous and paine an altercation. Notwithstanding being often admonished by my friendes, that diuers Protestants much commended <hi>M. Abbots</hi> discourse, some for the stile, and his cunning and confident carriage in it; others for that they saw it thicke interlaced with sundry ancient Authors sentences: and thereby thought and gaue out, that he refused not to deale with vs at our owne weapons. Herevpon I resolued at length to afford it some an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere, specially for such good peoples sake, who are desirous to bolt out that truth of God, which only can saue their soules, and are not willing to be deceiued with fine tricks, nor doe wittingly suffer themselues to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away with faire glozing speeches, or stout brags, when they finde no correspondence of sound and wel grounded matter. To giue the man his due, I acknowledge that he inditeth not amisse, if he did not defile and poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son his penne with so huge a multitude of ougly, venimous, and vnsauoury
<pb n="4" facs="3"/> tearmes. But what account is to be made of choise, picked, and pleasing wordes, when they be imployed not only to abuse and beguile simple soules, but also to disgrace the sincere verity of Gods word? surely for the deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of controuersies in religion, plaine vsual speeches without painting or superfluity, haue alwaies beene taken by the learned for most decent and expediēt, according to that ancient Adage: <hi>simplex est veritatis oratio, the stile of truth is simple and plaine.</hi> And where much colouring and flourishing is vsed, there is no smal suspition of a badde cause and fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent dealing. What neede bad <hi>M. Abbot</hi> to fil vp thirty sheetes of paper, to giue answere vnto one sheete and halfe of mine? doth it not argue to a man of vnderstanding, that what he could not answere vnto directly in few wordes, he would at least cloake with long circumstances, and cast a mist before the Readers eies with gay glorious phrases, that he might not see and discerne the truth?</p>
   <p>Touching his frequent disgraceful and odious tearmes, and most bitter rayling against the best sort of men on our side, I would gladly learne how it can stand with Christian charity and modesty. Sure I am, that it consorteth ful euil with that sacred rule of the Apostle:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>vers.</hi> 24.</note>
      <hi>The ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of our Lord must not wrangle, but be milde towardes al men, apt to teach, patient, with modesty admonishing them that resist the truth.</hi> And <hi>S. Peter</hi> telleth vs, that the natural property of a true Christian is,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. <hi>vers.</hi> 9.</note>
      <hi>To be modest and humble, and not so much as to render euil for euil, or curse for curse:</hi> so farre off was he from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging any man to reuile and raile at them, who neuer gaue him any one foule word in al their liues, yea whome he neuer saw. And he further biddeth vs to follow the example of Christ our great master, <hi>who did not reuile, when he was reuiled:</hi> but hath in expresse wordes forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vs to vse any contemptuous or opprobrious speeches against our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren, assuring vs before hand, that he<note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 5. <hi>vers.</hi> 23.</note>
      <hi>Who shal say to his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian brother (thou foole) shal be guilty of hel fire.</hi> This and an hundred times more to the same purpose, being set downe in the diuine Scriptures against bitter and barbarous speeches; yet <hi>M. Abbot</hi> a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed Diuine, seemeth to take a special delight in them, and to esteeme them no smal ornaments of a Diuines stile: otherwise he would not so often vse them. I wote wel that the most milde and sweet pen-men, are some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times through zeale of the truth, or by the ouerthwart dealing of their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersary, moued to let slip now and then a hard word or two; but ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or vpon euery smal occasion to fal into a fit of rayling, and to vomit vp
<pb n="5" facs="3"/> most rustical and ruffianlike taunts, cannot but discouer a very corrupt and venimous stomacke. In this one discourse of <hi>M. Abbots,</hi> a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent scauenger may rake together wel-neare a tumbrel ful of them. I doe intreate the gentle Reader not to be offended with me, if I doe here for ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification of what I say, trouble him with the view of some few of them. The Bishop of Rome is seldome called by his right name, but <hi>Antichrist,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Page</hi> 118. 124 146. 150. 162.</note>
      <hi>the man of sinne, that harpie of Rome, filthy harlot, filthy and vnnatural strumpet, the whoore of Babilon,</hi> and such like. Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious men he tearmeth <hi>idle lossels and filthy belly-gods, swarmes of Locusts, Romish vermine, ful gorged Friers,</hi> and so foorth. My selfe and others my bretheren, <hi>False harlots, witlesse sophisters, blind Doctors, abhominable hypocrites, lewd caytifs, the seede of the Deuil, vncleane beasts, foule mouthed dogs, like vnto other swine of his fraternity, base fugitiues, false traytors, the villany of our profession,</hi> and innumerable others; which cannot but conuince and demonstrate <hi>M. Abbot</hi> to be one of them, whome the spirit of God hath liuely described, when he wrote:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. <hi>vers.</hi> 13.</note>
      <hi>Their throat is an open sepulchre, with their tongues they deale deceitfully, the venim of serpents is vnder their lips, their mouth is ful of malediction and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, their feete swift to shedde bloud, destruction and infelicity is in their waies, and the way of peace they haue not knowne, there is no feare of God before their eies.</hi> And if <hi>M. Abbot</hi> scorne to be aduised by me his aduersary to forgoe this rude rhetorike of brabling and scolding women, in latin called <hi>Canina eloquentia;</hi> let him follow the graue counsel of that sage Lawier <hi>S<seg rend="sup">r.</seg> Edward Cooke,</hi> whose booke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e citeth, wherein is said:<note place="margin">In the preface of his fift of reportes.</note>
      <hi>That controuersies in religion are to be handled with al candor and charity, and not with bitter inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiues, like men transported with fury.</hi> To end this point, if he hold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n that course of scurrility, he wil driue me and others to giue him ouer in the plaine field, for a foule-mouthed wrangler that deserueth no answere. Thus much by the way of the manner of his inditing.</p>
   <p>Now to the matter of his booke, which doth principally consist in allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Authors, and applying their sentences to his purpose. How insuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently he hath behaued himselfe therein, shal be particularly discyphered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> their proper places: I wil here only for a tast of his judgement, and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>erity therein, giue a touch vnto some general heades thereof. First, doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> not euidently proue great want of judgement and discretion, to alleage <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> vpright witnesses in matters of controuersie, such authors as are knowne
<pb n="6" facs="4"/> to al the world, to be professed parties of the same side? If I should cite for confirmation of the Catholike cause; <hi>D<seg rend="sup">oct.</seg> Harding, D<seg rend="sup">oct.</seg> San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, D<seg rend="sup">oct.</seg> Stapleton,</hi> or any other Catholike late writer; would not the vnpassionate reader take me for very simple, if I thought that any man would the sooner beleeue me for their opinions, that were men (though most learned and right honest) yet not indifferent, because they were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed aduocates of the same cause? Euen so a man of any wit, cannot but maruaile where <hi>M. Abbots</hi> senses were, when he so commonly and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently for proofe of any doubt, doth produce the authority of <hi>Bale,</hi> (a late Irish Apostata Frier, whome be sometime also calleth <hi>Balaeus,</hi> to make him seeme two worshipful authors, that is not worthy to be halfe one) <hi>Fox,</hi> Iewel, <hi>Humphrey,</hi> Holinshed, <hi>S<seg rend="sup">r.</seg> Edward Cooke,</hi> the <hi>Magde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgenses,</hi> Kemnitius, <hi>Illyricus,</hi> Sleidan, <hi>Hospinian,</hi> and many others open and professed aduersaries of the Catholike Roman Church, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no vpright and fit witnesses against it. He without doubt may garnish his margent with variety of quotations, that blusheth not to cite so fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently as <hi>M. Abbot</hi> doth, such partial writers. But no man (I hope) wil be so foolish, as to giue credit vnto any thing that is no better verified, then by the verdict of such false witnesses. For to cal one of them to giue testimony is no better, then (after our English prouerbe) to hidde a man aske one of his fellowes, whether he be a theefe or no.</p>
   <p>Againe, there is another circumstance in the citing of his late partial authors, which maketh it yet more absurd and ridiculous. For he sticketh not to produce the credit of a seely writer of this last hundred yeares, for verification of a matter done more then a thousand yeares before he was borne. For example, to proue that Pope <hi>Eleutherius</hi> acknowledged <hi>Lucius</hi> (King of our Country <hi>1400.</hi> yeares past) to be supreame gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in causes Ecclesiastical,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Page</hi> 26.</note>
      <hi>M. Abbot</hi> alleageth <hi>Holinshed</hi> a Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cler of our age: what a jest is this? how knew this late writer what passed so long before his owne time? was there not any one Hystoriographer more ancient then he, neither Latin nor English, that could tel any tidings of such a matter? And yet <hi>M. Abbot</hi> is so il aduised, as to perswade vs to receiue it vpon his seely poore credit. Of the like stuffe is that in another place of his booke,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Page</hi> 60.</note> to wit, that <hi>Syritius</hi> Bishop of Rome (who liued about <hi>1200.</hi> yeares agoe) was a noueller, and that by the worshipful verdict of <hi>Polidore Virgil:</hi> who liued eleauen hundred yeares after him. What, are learned men growne so carelesse of their credit, that they dare let passe to the print such doting follies, and so grosse absurdities? this
<pb n="7" facs="4"/> may serue for a note of his ouersight, in alleadging his owne pew-fellowes for vpright and indifferent vmpeers, and late moderne authors for the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainety of ancient matters.</p>
   <p>Now to his citations of the more authentike approued writers, whome he doth greatly abuse in diuers and sundry fashions. The first and most gentle is, when he doth cite their wordes truly, but doth apply them cleane contrary to their meaning. For example, in his Epistle to the Kinges Majesty be approueth his Highnesse course for the answering of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like bookes, producing for it this sentence out of <hi>S. Bernard: That though thereby the Heretike arise not from his filth, yet the Church may be confirmed in her faith: M. Abbot</hi> meaning as the sequele of his speech doth import, that if thereby men of the Roman reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion wil not be conuerted from their errors, yet the good Protestants may be confirmed in their new faith: which is very farre wide from <hi>S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardes</hi> expresse declaration; as else-where, so in that very place. For that deuout holy Father was so farre off from disswading any man from the Roman faith, that he wisheth al men to make their recourse vnto the See of Rome, for resolution of al doubts in faith: these be his wordes to Pope Innocentius. <hi>We must referre to your Apostleship,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Epist.</hi> 190.</note>
      <hi>al the scandals and perils vvhich may fal in matter of faith specially, because the defects of faith must be holpen where faith cannot faile: for to what other See was it euer said,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Luc.</hi> 22. <hi>vers.</hi> 31.</note>
      <hi>I haue prayed for thee</hi> Peter, <hi>that thy faith doe not faile.</hi> See then what Church <hi>S. Bernard</hi> would confirme in her faith, not the Protestant but the Roman. Moreouer, in that very discourse out of which <hi>M. Abbot</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>icketh the former sentence,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Serm.</hi> 66.</note>
      <hi>S. Bernard</hi> doth in particuler describe those Heretikes, whome he perswaded to arise from their filth, to be such as <hi>held the Church not to haue beene visible for many yeares, but to haue lyen hidde in corners.</hi> Item, <hi>that vvould not beleeue, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hat any soules departed went to Purgatory, but either to heauen or to hel presently; and so defrauded the dead of the prayers of the liuing. Also such as vvould disswade from praying to the Saints:</hi> these and such like are those Heretikes by <hi>S. Bernardes</hi> judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whome he would haue to rise from the drosse and dregs of such erronious opinions, and returne vnto the Roman Catholike faith. Now judge with what conscience <hi>M. Abbot</hi> could cul some wordes out of the same discourse, to perswade men by the countenance of <hi>S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> to forsake praying to Saints, and for the dead, and the whole
<pb n="8" facs="5"/> Roman religion so strongly established by that reuerend religious Father in the very same place. This may suffice for a proofe of his misapplying the Fathers sentences, wherein he offendeth as often and as grieuously (I thinke) as euer did any Christian writer, as shal be hereafter shewed.</p>
   <p>Now to another tricke of his no lesse shameful, which is the miscon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struing of their wordes: let this serue for a paterne. Against the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipping of Images he produceth the authority of <hi>S. Gregory</hi> Bishop of Rome,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Page</hi> 104.</note>
      <hi>Commending</hi> (as he fableth) <hi>the zeale of</hi> Serenus <hi>Bishop of Massilia, who could not endure that any thing should be worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped that is made with handes; and telleth him, that he should for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidde the people the worshipping of them, &amp;c.</hi> Here are many foule faults: for <hi>S. Gregory</hi> did not commend but reprehend the vndi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>screet zeale of that Bishop, who did breake some pictures set in the Church, because some late conuerted Heathens not yet wel instructed in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian religion, did adore them as if they had beene Gods. <hi>S. Gregory</hi> telleth him plainely, <hi>That that should not be broken, which was not set vp in the Church to be adored, but only to instruct them that were ignorant.</hi> Secondly, though <hi>S. Gregory</hi> forbidde Images to be adored as Gods, yet doth he teach them to be worshipped as representations of most holy personages: which may be seene plainely (to omit diuers other places) by his letters vnto <hi>Secundinus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>v. <hi>7.</hi> Epist. <hi>53.</hi> ad Secūd.</note> To <hi>whome he sent the Images of our Sauiour, of the blessed Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>and of the holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles</hi> S. Peter <hi>and</hi> S. Paul; telling him first, <hi>that his petition to haue those Images, did greatly please him: for</hi> (saith he) <hi>thou doest loue him with al thy hart and whole intention, whose Image thou desirest to haue before thine eies,</hi> and straight after addeth: <hi>I know that thou doest not therefore desire to haue our Sauiours Image, that thou maiest worship it as a God; but for a remembrance of the Sonne of God, that thou maiest waxe warme in his loue, whose Image thou doest behold: and we truly doe cast our selues downe before the said Image, not as before a God-head, but vve adore him whome by the Image we remember to haue beene borne, or suffered, or to sit in his throne.</hi> Can any thing be more manifest, then that <hi>S Gregory</hi> approued both the hauing of Images, which be sent to his friend; and setting them in Churches for the instruction of the vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and also worshipping of them, euen so farre-foorth as humbly to kneele before them? which he himselfe as wel practised in his owne person, as also taught others so to doe: which is al that we Catholikes doe defend,
<pb n="9" facs="5"/> as greatly condemning (as the Protestants themselues) that any Christian should adore them as Gods, or giue any Godly honour vnto them. How wrongfully then did <hi>M. Abbot</hi> alleage <hi>S. Gregories</hi> wordes? and how shamefully hath he misconstrued them cleane besides that most holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers meaning, with whom in faith and doctrine we doe fully agree?</p>
   <p>But let vs yet goe one step further, more euidently to discouer, how per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiously <hi>M. Abbot</hi> doth deale with those ancient and most holy Doctors. He is not ashamed to cite them sometimes in confirmation of those errors, the which they doe expresly confute in the very same place: take this for an assay. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> (saith he) <hi>an Easterne Bishop,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Page</hi> 62.</note>
      <hi>euen in the time of</hi> Hierome, <hi>acknowledgeth for true those wordes of</hi> Socrates, <hi>that the Priests and Bishops thereof, were not forced by any law to forbeare their wiues, and that many of them whiles they were Bishops, had children borne vnto them by their lawfull married wiues:</hi> and quoteth <hi>Epiphanius</hi> against the <hi>59.</hi> Heresie of the Cathary; where in deede he handleth that matter, but after another manner. These he his wordes: <hi>Indeede the holy preaching of God, doth not since Christs comming admit them to take holy orders, who haue mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried againe after their first wiues death, in respect of the excellent dignity of Priest-hood: and this doth the Church of God ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue sincerely,</hi> (but so doth not the Church of the Protestants: <hi>ergo,</hi> it is not the Church of God.) Then he commeth to our present purpose, and saith: <hi>The same Church of God doth not admit and receiue a man that hath a wife liuing, and that getteth children, to be a Bishop, Priest, Deacon, or Subdeacon; but him that either abstaineth from the company of his wife, or else liueth widdower, and that specially where the Ecclesiastical Canons be sincere and not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted.</hi> Hitherto <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> as flat contrary to <hi>M. Abbots</hi> report of him as can be: for he reported, that whiles they were Bishops they had children borne vnto them, and there was no law that forced them to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eare their wiues. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> telleth vs otherwise: <hi>That the Canons of the Church</hi> (which are Ecclesiastical lawes) <hi>did not suffer any to be Bishop or Priest, that kept company with their wiues.</hi> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hich maketh the fault the more palbable, <hi>Epiphanius</hi> addeth an obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, vpon which it seemeth <hi>M. Abbot</hi> grounded his assertion: <hi>But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hou vvilt say that in some places, Subdeacons, Deacons, and Priests, doe yet get children</hi> (note by the way that in no place how cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>upt soeuer, Bishops so did, as <hi>M. Abbot</hi> reporteth:) <hi>but this</hi> (answereth
<pb n="10" facs="6"/> holy Epiphanius) <hi>is not according vnto the Canon, but after the minde of men, that in tract of time fainted,</hi> and so foorth. Where he proueth abstinence from marriage, or continual continency, to be not only decent for the high and holy calling of Clergie men; but also necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for their daily praiers, and for the suddaine occasions of their sacred function: so that finally <hi>S. Epiphanius</hi> is found to confute that directly, which <hi>M. Abbot</hi> reports him to acknowledge for true. And if this be not most wilful corruption, and falsification of these learned Fathers sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, I know not what may be.</p>
   <p>Because this is a point, that toucheth euery Christian that hath care of his saluation so neare,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Page</hi> 122.</note> I wil insist more vpon it. <hi>Is not this</hi> (saith M. Abbot) <hi>a horrible impiety, that standeth written in their law, our Lord God the Pope:</hi> and then doubleth it, saying; <hi>To beleeue that our Lord God the Pope could not so decree, as he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, should be accounted heresie.</hi> In the Canon law (which he calleth our law) is no such horrible impiety, but in his report is a double lie. The former is, to auouch that to stand in the law, which is only writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the glosse; which is no law as al men know. The second and the more shameful is, that it standeth not in the glosse neither, but he belieth both the one and the other:<note place="margin">Extrauag. Ioan. <hi>22.</hi> cum inter, in glossa.</note> let any man turne to the place quoted by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, and there towardes the end, vpon the word, <hi>declaramus,</hi> he shal finde only <hi>Dominum nostrum Papam, our Lord the Pope;</hi> and the word <hi>(God)</hi> is foisted in by <hi>M. Abbot,</hi> to make vp that horrible impiety of which he speaketh. As very a lie is it, which he citeth out of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretals of Pope <hi>Gregory,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Page</hi> 119.</note> that (forsooth) <hi>the Pope is not a meere man:</hi> whereas the Canon hath,<note place="margin">De translat. Episco. cap. Quanto.</note>
      <hi>Non puri hominis, sed veri Dei vicem gerit,</hi> that is, <hi>The Pope is the vicegerent or vicar, not of a meere man, but of true God:</hi> to wit of Christ, who is both God and Man. No more truth is in that assertion of his out of venerable <hi>Bede,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Page</hi> 199.</note> our very holy and most learned country-man: <hi>Then were the Scriptures in foure seueral languages, of so many seueral nations in this land;</hi> whereas he signifieth the plaine contrary: that the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures were only in the Latin tongue among them, and that therefore many of each language learned the Latin tongue, that they might by the helpe thereof vnderstand, meditate, and study the Scriptures: these be <hi>S. Bedes</hi> wordes.<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> hyst. Aug. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>This Iland at that time, did study and confesse one and the same knowledge of truth, in fiue sundry languages, to vvit: in the English, Briton, Scottish, Picts,
<pb n="11" facs="6"/> and Latin tongue, vvhich Latin by study of the Scriptures, vvas made common to al the rest.</hi> Note how for to study the holy Scriptures, men of the other foure seueral languages were faine to learne the Latin tongue; which they needed not to haue done, if the Scriptures had beene then translated into their owne mother language, as <hi>M. Abbot</hi> reporteth. Another notorious vntruth, and most ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious slaunder, doth be cast out in the next precedent page, against the blessed Bishop <hi>S. Augustine,</hi> our English Apostle:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Page</hi> 198.</note>
      <hi>That</hi> (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sooth) <hi>because he could not gette the Britons to obey him, he therefore prouoked</hi> Ethelbert <hi>King of Kent, (a very good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian) to procure the death of two thousand Monkes of Bangor, besides many other more innocent men;</hi> whereas that holy Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Father, was dead and buried many yeares before that slaughter hapned: which was also committed, not by <hi>Ethelbert</hi> King of Kent,<note place="margin">Beda lib. <hi>2.</hi> hyst. cap. <hi>2.</hi>
      </note> but by <hi>Ethelfride</hi> a Pagan Prince of the North parts, and that not for any quarrel of religion neither, but to enlarge his Dominions, and to be reuenged on his enemies. Neither can <hi>M. Abbot</hi> or any other Protestant, produce one ancient and approued author, to justifie that <hi>S. Augustine</hi> was any way accessary to that wicked fact; but is glad to shroude himselfe vnder the shrubbe of an old namelesse Cronicle, (and therefore Apocryphal) cited by the Arch-lier, and late partial writer <hi>Iewel:</hi> fit witnesses for such a palbable and spiteful slander.</p>
   <p>But if I would stand here to make a Catalogue of <hi>M. Abbots</hi> corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions, falsifications, and other odde trickes, which he vseth in alleage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Fathers, and other approued authors; I should reduce the greatest part of his booke to this place, which chiefly consisteth in such paltry shifts, and vnchristianlike dealing: this that I haue here decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, cannot but suffice to discredit him with al indifferent men. For if he hath wittingly misreported such worthy authors, of purpose to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile his credulous reader, as it is most like (for he wil not be taken for a man that citeth the Fathers by heare-say, without looking in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o their workes) then he hath a most seared and corrupt conscience, vnworthy the name of a Diuine, and walking aliue is dead in conscience, and consequently in credit with al men that loue the truth:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Sapient.</hi> 1. <hi>vers.</hi> 11.</note>
      <hi>For the tongue that lieth, killeth the soule.</hi> But let vs suppose the most that may be said in his fauour, that he hath not wittingly and of purpose to deceiue the simple, cited the holy Fathers sentences wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, but taking them vp vpon the credit of some other of his companions,
<pb n="12" facs="7"/> without looking into the Doctors owne workes, whether they were true or no, and being deceiued himselfe, doth afterwardes beguile others: this I say being of courtesie admitted, which is the best excuse that can be truly made for him; yet no meane wise man can euer hereafter trust him, that so confidently without any qualification, auerreth such false tales: for his vntruthes are so plaine and palbable, that you neede no more, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare his reports with the authors wordes, and at the first sight any meane scholler shal finde his cosenage and deceit.</p>
   <p>I come now vnto the last kinde of abuse, that <hi>M. Abbot</hi> offereth vnto the sacred senate of those most renowmed ancient Fathers, wherein he doth more ingeniously, discouer and lay open the right humour of a true Protestant: which is to deny their authority flatly, to controle and censure them as simple men, to accuse them of error and falshood; yea and finally, to preferre olde rotten Heretikes opinions before the best of them. To be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne with <hi>Eusebius</hi> Bishop of Caesarea a most famous Hystoriographer, that liued in the daies of <hi>Constantine</hi> the great, because he doth more mannerly reprehend him, and saith:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Page</hi> 177.</note>
      <hi>That we must giue him leaue, to censure</hi> Eusebius <hi>of an injuditious and presumed explication of</hi> Constantines <hi>minde and purpose.</hi> Truly I see no cause why we should giue him any such leaue: for who can be so simple, as to thinke that <hi>M. Abbot</hi> (borne <hi>1200.</hi> yeares after <hi>Constantines</hi> death) should know more of his minde then <hi>Eusebius,</hi> who conuersed with him most familiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and was of his priuy Councel in such affaires, and a man otherwise very learned and juditious. Secondly, he taxeth the most holy and reuerend Patriarke of Constantinople <hi>S. Chrysostome,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Page</hi> 175.</note>
      <hi>for playing the ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and enforcing that in one place for true, which in another place he himselfe denieth:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Page</hi> 176.</note>
      <hi>and for reporting that of</hi> Constantines <hi>Sonne, which is much different from the certaine story.</hi> In like manner be standereth <hi>S. Augustine,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Page</hi> 54.</note>
      <hi>for writing against</hi> Iouinian <hi>the Heretike, whose opinions</hi> (saith <hi>M. Abbot</hi> very audatiously) S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine <hi>knew only by heare-say, and not of any certainty.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Page</hi> 60.</note>
      <hi>Though</hi> Augustine <hi>doth not breake into those rude and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decent speeches against marriage, as</hi> Hierome <hi>did; yet he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued where he said, that no Priests embraced</hi> Iouinians <hi>heresie.</hi> I wil omit, how they note <hi>S. Hierome</hi> (that most vertuous, zealous, and learned Doctor) with a blacke cole,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Page</hi> 57.</note>
      <hi>For writing with al indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and stomacke, for railing, and false doctrine;</hi> because I make hast to acquaint the reader with the most shamelesse pranke of al others,
<pb n="13" facs="7"/> which is: that they in expresse tearmes preferre the most infamous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned Heretikes, euen in the very points of their errors; before the most juditious, learned, and sincere Doctors of the Church.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Page</hi> 73.</note>
      <hi>It it manifest</hi> (saith M. Abbot) <hi>that Hierome</hi> (one of the foure principal Doctors of the Latin Church) <hi>was deceiued, and that Vigilantius,</hi> (a loose and lewde Heretike) <hi>had just cause to say as he did.</hi> Againe, <hi>Aërius</hi> (a damned Arrian) <hi>spake against praier for the dead,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Page</hi> 86.</note>
      <hi>with greater reason then</hi> Epiphanius (a most ancient, learned, and holy Greeke fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) <hi>hath defended it. Iouinian</hi> (a notable audatious and ignorant Heretike, as both <hi>S. Augustine, S. Hierome,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Vincent. Lyr. cap. <hi>15.</hi> do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. ranke Iouini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an in the nū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of pestilēt Heretikes.</note> and <hi>Vincentius Lyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nensis</hi> doe testifie, though by reason of his later standing he was vnknowne to <hi>Epiphanius:</hi>) this Heretike I say, <hi>Did teach</hi> (as <hi>M. Abbot</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports <hi>page 56.) the doctrine of</hi> Paul <hi>in Rome, against the super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitious conceit of the holynesse of Virginity, before the holynesse in Marriage:</hi> which notwithstanding was maintained by <hi>S. Augustine</hi> and <hi>S. Hierome,</hi> with the whole court of Rome at those daies; as be him selfe confesseth in the same place. Doth not this (to omit much more of the same kinde) conuince and demonstrate, vnto al vnpassionate Christians of any vnderstanding, that the poore miserable Protestants be exceeding blindly bent vnto the defence of their errors, who seing them most plainly condemned by the best and most learned of the primitiue Church, and pure antiquity (to which they would sometime in great confidence seeme to appeale,) had notwithstanding rather consort themselues, and follow very base, vnlearned, and wretched Heretikes, and with them to band against the inuincible troupes of the ancient holy Fathers, and most renowmed Doctors? wil it any whit auaile them to say, that those men of condemned memory, did in their opinions better agree with the word of God, and therefore are to be preferred before the rest, though otherwise better schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers then they? surely nothing at al with the juditious; because this is but a scar-crow to amate the simple. For whether were more like to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand better the sacred word of God, either <hi>Augustine, Hierome, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius, Chrysostome,</hi> and such others, who indued with excellent wits, and wel furnished with al other kinde of learning, had most dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently studied both the old and new Testament, as by their translations, and most learned Commentaries and explications, they haue testified to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>orld? or <hi>Aërius, Vigilantius,</hi> or <hi>Iouinian,</hi> who haue not left any one monument of learning, wit, or honesty behinde them? and <hi>Iouinian</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted of those three the most sufficient) was so insufficient and vnlettered,
<pb n="14" facs="8"/> that he could not so much as indite in the Latin tongue congruously, and so as he might be vnderstood,<note place="margin">Hieron. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cont. Iouin. in initio.</note> as <hi>S. Hierome</hi> proueth. To finish this point, seing that <hi>M. Abbot</hi> doth not only misapply the auncient Doctors sentences, but doth also misconster, corrupt, and falsifie them; yea, doth plainly and roundly deny their graue and sacred authority, preferring the confessed and condemned errours of notorious reproued Heretikes, before their vniforme and approued doctrine: they must needes confesse themselues to haue beene a little deceiued, who tooke him to haue beaten the Papists with their owne weapons, that is, to haue brought better testimony out of pure antiquity in fauour of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants opinions, then the Catholikes doe for theirs; whereas in truth he handleth those sacred Fathers, euen as <hi>Caluin</hi> reporteth the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine to deale with the holy Scriptures.<note place="margin">In instruct. aduers. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert. cap. <hi>9.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>These loose men</hi> (saith he) <hi>vvhen vve presse them with the Scriptures, doe not much dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble, that they esteeme no better of them, then of fables: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding they in the meane season doe not let to vse them, if they finde any place that they can wrest vnto their owne mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; not that they themselues doe giue any credit to it, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that they may thereby trouble the vnlearned, and so daunt and stagger them, that they may at length the more easily draw them to like of their errors:</hi> thus farre <hi>Caluin.</hi> Euen so plaieth <hi>M. Abbot</hi> with the glorious Doctors of the Church, whom how little he regardeth, doth appeare by his often abusing their wordes, by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting their authority, and setting lesse by them, then by ignorant ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure and abject persons: yet knowing that al sober Christians doe highly esteeme, and make great account of their graue authority, as of the principal lights of Christs Church since the Apostles times, they doe greedily catch hold of any broken sentence of theirs, that doth any way sound in fauour of their heresie; not that they themselues giue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny credit thereunto, but to astonish and deceiue the simple reader, and thereby to perswade him to like the better of their errours. Thus much in general, of the abuses which <hi>M. Abbot</hi> offereth vnto the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers.</p>
   <p>But doth be behaue himselfe more reuerently towardes the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and sacred word of God? one example I wil giue here, by which you may take a scantling of the rest; and not to seeke farre, it shal be the very first in his booke: these be his wordes.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Page</hi> 6.</note>
      <hi>This is the thing that</hi> M. Bishop <hi>labours for, seeking vvith</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 8.</note> Elimas <hi>the Sorcerer to
<pb n="15" facs="8"/> peruert the straight vvaies of the Lord: and vvhereas his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty hath made profession to aduance the honour of Christ, he vvould in steede thereof drawe him to aduance the Idol</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Dan.</hi> 11. <hi>vers.</hi> 38. 2.</note> Mauzzin, <hi>the God of Antichrist, and to establish damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble heresies by him priuily brought in, vvhereby his agents and factors through<note place="margin">
            <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>vers.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.</note> couetousnesse, with fained wordes doe make marchandize of the soules of men, speaking thinges which they ought not for filthy<note place="margin">
            <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. <hi>vers.</hi> 11.</note> lucres sake.</hi> Here you see his text enriched, and his margent garnished with a gay shew of Gods word, and yet here is not one whole sentence of holy Scripture to any purpose, but diuers wordes picked out of sundry places, and by the new Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>list <hi>M. Abbot</hi> made a new peece of vn-holy scripture; which prety deuise if it should passe for currant, any hadde matter might be graced with the glosse of Scripture: so that the first fault committed by <hi>M. Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot</hi> herein, is the dismembring of Gods word, and renting of it in peeces at his pleasure, with which peeces afterwardes odly and idly patched together, he maketh vp (as it were) a poore beggers cloke, rather then any testimony of Scripture. Secondly, the wordes hang togither very vntowardly, one of them not agreing with the other: for if his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty should be perswaded to aduance the <hi>Idol</hi> Mauzzin, <hi>the God of Antichrist,</hi> he could not <hi>establish heresies priuily brought in;</hi> for that false God wil wholy oppose himselfe against Christ, and not suffer any other God besides himselfe to be adored: so that he wil not establish heresies, which are errours defended by them which professe Christ and doe adore the true God; neither wil be priuily bring in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>esies, but openly professe Idolatry, and compel al others to doe the same. Thirdly, these wordes are most falsly and fondly applied to vs Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Priests: for first that false God of Antichrist shal not be aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the Romans, but fought against, and foiled by them, as it is cleare in the very text.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Dan.</hi> 11. <hi>vers.</hi> 30.</note>
      <hi>The Gallies and Romans shal come vpon him, and he shal be strooken and turned backe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And lastly, how il aduised was <hi>M. Abbot,</hi> to charge poore seminary Priests <hi>with couetousnesse, and speaking of thinges which they ought not for filthy lucres sake?</hi> whereas it is manifest vnto al men, women, and children almost, that they who become such Priests, are so farre off from seeking after any temporal gaine thereby, that they doe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly forgoe al hope of benefices, and al other whatsoeuer commodities and dignities in their country, which they might perhaps aswel attaine vnto
<pb n="16" facs="9"/> as some others, if they would follow the current of the time: Yea, they doe also debarre themselues of landes, legacies, annuities, and al other profits and commodities whatsoeuer, which might accrew vnto them, from their parents, kinsfolkes, and friendes; being content to liue vpon Gods prouidence, and that poore pittance which the impouerished estate of some few Catholikes wil afford them. The Protestant Ministers, who by their profession are capable of fat benefices, headships of houses, Deana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and such like dignities and commodities, may be truly suspected to bend their studies that way, and to maintaine heresies in hope of gaine and promotion: and they who cannot be satisfied with two or three of those great liuings joyned togither, or with one Bishoprick alone, but would haue Bishoprickes and Deanaries vnited; such men may indeede rightly be suspected, to make marchandize of mens soules for filthy lucres sake: but to impute couetousnesse vnto seminary Priests, who haue debarred them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues of al preferment both spiritual and temporal, which their Country yeeldeth to men of their profession, and can looke for no other promotion there, then a halter at Tyburne, was no lesse shameful then witlesse im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudency. Briefly, <hi>M. Abbot</hi> by tearing Gods wordes in peeces, and patching it vp againe with his owne wordes ful il-fauouredly, and by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying it most absurdly, is found to offer as great injury to it, as he hath done vnto those holy ancient learned Fathers aforesaid; who were by the spirit of God selected to be the principal expounders of it. So that finally, whether you regard the handling of Scriptures or Fathers, you shal sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome light vpon any Diuine that doth performe it more insufficiently (shal I say) or more perfidiously: neuerthelesse he sets such a brasen face on the matter; speaketh so confidently; conueieth it so cunningly; and doth gild it ouer so artificially, that the credulous and vnwary reader would thinke him to be some jolly fellow, and a rare flourishing writer. But be that wil not take vaine wordes for good paiment, nor tricks and shifts for sufficient proofes; but wil weigh his arguments wel, and diligently exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine his testimonies: he shal quickly discouer <hi>M. Abbots</hi> weakenesse, and finde him to be one of the most shallow and beggerliest writers of these daies: for he like a mount-banke indeede (to returne his owne wordes vpon him) setteth out for fresh and new marchandize, the very rif-raf and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse of other Protestant authors, and that which hath beene an hundred times answered vnto by the learned on our side. In him therefore is truly verified that witty obseruation of <hi>S. Augustine,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1</hi> cont. Gaud. c. <hi>39.</hi>
      </note> vttered against the Donatist <hi>Gaudentius: Nihil assert praeter lassum &amp; quassum,
<pb n="17" facs="9"/> he bringeth nothing that hath not beene already</hi> (by his owne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>nions) <hi>wearied out,</hi> and (as it were) tired by ouer often vsing; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> our party so shaken, battered, and beaten, that it cannot be but a foule <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sgrace among the learned to put into light, and to set to sale so base, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>erworne, thrid-bare, and ragged stuffe.</p>
   <p>This I hope wil suffice for a preamble, to aduertise the indifferent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ader what opinion he is to conceiue and carry of <hi>M. Abbots</hi> writings, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e rest I remit to the Treatise it selfe; desiring the juditious reader to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>are with those manifold difficulties, which we that liue in the land haue in this time of persecution, both to compose and to print our bookes: which duly considered, he wil not greatly blame our slownesse, if our workes come not foorth so speedily, as he may wel expect, and we doe greatly desire. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God whose glory we seeke, and for whom we labour in the conuersion and right instruction of Christian soules, vouchsafe to send his heauenly blessing on our poore trauailes, and vpon al them who with good intention shal reade them ouer.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>