<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Dedication]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114074_Fr1_2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09031</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19319</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114074</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Dedication]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A plaine exposition vpon the whole 8. 9. 10. 11. chapters of the Epistle of Saint Paul to the Romans : Wherein the text is diligently and methodically resolued, the sence giuen: and many doctrines thence gathered, are by liuely vses applyed, for the benefit of Gods children performed with much variety, and conuenient breuitie: being the substance of neere foure yeeres weekedayes sermons.: By Elnathan Parr, Bachelor in Diuinity, and preacher of Gods Word</title>
                 <author>Parr, Elnathan</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 <publisher>Man, Samuel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 305, 1, 138, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR;</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> PRESENT to your No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleness these my poore la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors; which shall be much honoured, if you will vouchsafe as gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious an eye to them writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, as you did a reuerent eare to them vttered by voice.</p>
   <p>As a picture attaines not the life; so neither can wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting expresse that liuely <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nergie</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>of the voice, which consists in Vtterance and Action, the two Ladies of Speech: yet as the picture of a friend is much estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for the representati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; so I cannot but hope of your fauourable appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall of the Copy, to whom the principal was so accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
   <p>The stile must needs lose something, because I haue endeuoured to abbreuiate many things in vvriting; which I tooke more liberty in speaking to deliuer. And yet, I hope, that nor I, nor my labours, shall for this lose with the Iudicious: for <hi>Timantes,</hi> a famous Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (as your selfe, if any, know) was the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended; because by his pictures, more was to bee vnderstood, then vvas ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>As all that knowe your Noblenes, haue experience of your Religious mind; so haue I also of your deepe iudgement, by whom no Author can lose; you bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able (and vsing) accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately to examine euerie vvord, wherein any excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent thing may bee cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. If I were able to write learnedly, I would vvish such a Reader: as I am</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>