<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ADVERTISEMENT to the Readers.</title>
           <author>H., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114948_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03332</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13452</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114948</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ADVERTISEMENT to the Readers.</title>
                 <author>H., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The apology of Theophilus Higgons lately minister, now Catholique : VVherein the letter of Sir Edvv. Hoby Knight, directed vnto the sayd T.H. in answere of his first motiue, is modestly examined, and clearely refuted</title>
                 <author>Higgons, Theophilus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Machuel, Jean</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 55, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="52" facs="31"/>
   <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT to the Readers.</head>
   <p>BEENEVOLOVS READERS; perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture you haue meruayled very much, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
      <hi>Why my Answere vnto Sir</hi> EDWARD HOBYES <hi>Letter, hath been so long in comming?</hi> and will mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> more, <hi>Why, being now come, it is so short?</hi> Vnto both theis demands, I will giue you a sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction; brief, and true.</p>
   <p>Concerning the FIRST then; you must vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, that, whereas Sir <hi>Edwards</hi> Letter was published in <hi>Iune</hi> last, and had <note n="❀" place="margin">In his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist. to the <hi>Ladies.</hi>
      </note> direction, frō him, to salute me at S. <hi>Omers;</hi> I departed thēce in <hi>May</hi> before, and trauayled into <hi>France:</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re I had the first notice of this Letter, about the middest of <hi>Iuly</hi> following, but had no sight thereof till about the end of that moneth; ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sually also, as it passed, by me in <hi>Roan,</hi> vnto a Doctour in <hi>Paris:</hi> so that I could not then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn it, aboue 8. howres, in my hands. And though I gaue present order vnto a Post, to bring me a copie from <hi>London,</hi> yet he fayled me; and so I was constrayned (vpon his retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne) to borrow the former copie; which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in <hi>September;</hi> but, for some impedimēts, it lay by me, vntill <hi>October;</hi> when (according to the small portion of time, which I could allot vnto such affayres) I beganne to addresse my answere.</p>
   <pb n="53" facs="31"/>
   <p>Whereby, as the Reader may perceiue the causes of this delay, so Sir <hi>Edward</hi> himself may see the little courtesy of the LADIES to him, in recompēce of his great <note n="†" place="margin">In his sayd <hi>Letter</hi> vnto them.</note> kindnesse to them; who would not vouchsafe him the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, or (to vse his owne word) yeald him so much <hi>boone,</hi> as to procure <hi>the deliuery of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closed</hi> Letter vnto me, at S. <hi>Omers;</hi> whither (as farr, as I can learne) it was neuer convaighed by their meanes.</p>
   <p>Concerning the SECOND; it may please you to vnderstand farther, that, as I prouided my answere vnto the whole Letter (digested, by the Authout, into SIX PARAGRAPHS; as you haue already seene in my <hi>Preface</hi>) and had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed a very small parcell thereof, I was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by a Catholick Gentleman (comming lately, out of <hi>England,</hi> into theis parts) that my ANSWERE vnto Sir <hi>Edward Hoby</hi> (and special<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the <hi>morall points,</hi> in his <hi>sifting Paragraph</hi>) was earnestly expected, both by my friends, &amp; aduersaries; amongst whom, Maister L. D. (a Minister, and sometimes kindly affected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me) bestowing his liberality vpon M. <hi>Humfrey Leech,</hi> and me, pretended, that I nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther durst, nor could answere the KNIGHT; and, that my long silence was a sufficient proof.</p>
   <p>For this respect then, I am inforced to send away this <hi>First Part</hi> of my <hi>Apology</hi> with speed, and to make it the harbenger of the rest. A se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond reason also of this single, and hasty birth, is, in regard of the news (truly, and justly grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous
<pb n="54" facs="32"/> vnto my heart) which was brought vnto me, by the sayd Cath. Gentleman, concerning my late, honourable Lord, the L. Bishopp of <hi>London,</hi> lying sick, &amp; in eminēt perill of death. Wherefore, hauing <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Pag.</hi> 4.12.</note> appealed vnto his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipp, as being a most competent witnesse for my defence, I desired, that (if it were possible) this poore schedule might be presented vnto his view, before his passadge out of this world. And, if my heartiest prayers could preuayle any thing with him, who hath souereigne power ouer vs all, for <hi>Life,</hi> &amp; <hi>Death,</hi> for <hi>Body,</hi> and <hi>Soule,</hi> he knoweth, that <hi>clamaui de profundis</hi> &amp;c. I haue called, and I haue cried vnto him, out of the depth of my soule, for my sayd louing Maister; either to grant him a longer life heere, or an happier elswhere. His affection toward me de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued this requitall from me; as you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by his owne words; viz. <hi>I wish M. Hig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons better, then any man in England; I except not his owne Father,</hi> &amp;c. which he <note n="†" place="margin">Fulham <hi>house.</hi> 9. <hi>August.</hi> 1609.</note> wrote vnto a very honorable Gentleman; <hi>avowing</hi> vnto him far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>vpon his credit,</hi> that <hi>he neither knew, nor heard of Sir Edward Hobies booke, till he saw it in print.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thus you haue (good Readers) a satisfactiō vnto each demand. It may please you now fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to vnderstand, that the residue of my <hi>Apology</hi> (wherein, I am sory that the Knight doth prouoke me to incounter his <hi>weake, vntrue,</hi> and <hi>scandalous</hi> exceptions) shall come foorth, in due time, accompanied with a <hi>Reply</hi> vnto D. <hi>Mortons Answere;</hi> which he calleth a <hi>direct</hi> one; but he shall see it <hi>corrected,</hi> to his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefitt,
<pb n="55" facs="32"/> if he will, or to his losse, though he would not. If the delay shall prooue more te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, then will contēt you, and the discourse more rude, then will becomme me; you must remember, that, as my <hi>Trauaile</hi> was, and is, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for other vses, then to write, so it doth not affoord either leysure, or meanes, which are requisite in this behalf.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Fare you well.</salute>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Roan.</hi>
         <date>Decemb. 24. 1609.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your T. H.</signed>
   </closer>
   <epigraph>
      <q>
         <p>Dilige Deum, amicos in Deo, inimicos propter Deum.</p>
         <bibl>S. AVGVST.</bibl>
      </q>
   </epigraph>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>