<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO ALL GODLY, zealous, religious, sancti∣fied, and Christian-minded People, who expect and vnfai∣nedly desire the comming of our Lord Iesus Christ, fru∣ition thereof, to the euer∣lasting ioy of their Soules.</title>
           <author>G., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114442_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68977</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3580</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114442</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO ALL GODLY, zealous, religious, sancti∣fied, and Christian-minded People, who expect and vnfai∣nedly desire the comming of our Lord Iesus Christ, fru∣ition thereof, to the euer∣lasting ioy of their Soules.</title>
                 <author>G., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The prodigals teares. With a heavenly new yeeres gift sent to the soule; contayning many most zealous and comfortable prayers, with deuout meditations: both worthie the acceptance of all Christians, and their expence of time to peruse. By H. G. preacher of the most sacred Word of God</title>
                 <author>Brathwait, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Bernard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Browne, John 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 238, that is 258, 2, 299, 298-313, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO ALL GODLY, zealous, religious, sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and Christian-minded</hi> People, who expect and vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly desire the comming of our Lord Iesus Christ, fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition thereof, to the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting ioy of their Soules.</head>
   <l>PEruse mee, Will you please?</l>
   <l>Then finde helpe for each Disease:</l>
   <l>Soule and Body I apply,</l>
   <l>And cure both their Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</l>
   <l>Such good meanes not dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine,</l>
   <l>When to thee so friendly sent;</l>
   <l>Lest in sicknesse thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine,</l>
   <l>And thy folly doe repent.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="12"/>Had I wist, breedes much woe,</l>
   <l>Gentle Patient be no foe</l>
   <l>To the health and happie states</l>
   <l>Of such peerelesse louing Mates.</l>
   <l>Farewell, good Soule, till wee meet</l>
   <l>In Heauens Blisse, each to greet:</l>
   <l>Expect wee doe, and dayly pray;</l>
   <l>Lord graunt to vs that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie day.</l>
   <p>CHristian and conscionable Reader, thou mayest now iustly, with <hi>Apelles,</hi> reprooue and deride me, who thus haue presumed to diuulge and diue into the height of all Learning, Arts, Sciences, Knowledge, Wit and Skill, whose vnskilfulnesse in all of them recommands me
<pb facs="12"/>
to the lowest degree that may be to be abased. I know it is but lost labour to cast water into the Ocean; an vnthankefull respect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse Gift, to cast a Sheaue of Wheat into a rich mans <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> or to put a small Bunch of Grapes into a <hi>vaste Wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse,</hi> small encrease thereof can issue. Yet seeing I am cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and sent into my Heauenly Lord and Masters Haruest, hired and sent to his Ʋine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, in both to worke, and not to loyter; That I haue in both endeuoured, I present thee good Christian friends, this little of my hard labour, and gleaned Corne, obtained by following o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of my fellow Labourers: Though theirs was pure, yet mine not without Chaffe: receiue my Grapes, though not without some soure and sharpe distaste, altogether disliking your Pallat,
<pb facs="13"/>
and disappointing your expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Lord of the Ʋine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard hath sent by me some Bread and Wine, to strengthen and comfort you withall: eate a morsell thereof, and draw out your Wine, for his sake that sent it, and doe not refuse or dislike both, for the meanenesse of the Messenger, that brings &amp; now presents his Lords affected loue expressed to you therein. If you accept thereof thankefully and gladly, I shall returne my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster intelligence, and thinke my paines well bestowed, rest well satisfied, and account my selfe most bountifully by you to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, if my suit be graunted; namely, your kind acceptance therof from my vnworthy hands.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine at all times, to bring thee to my Lord and Master Iesus Christ his Courts.
<hi>H. G.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>