<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Shute, W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114453_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07280</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17676</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114453</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Shute, W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The trivmphs of Nassav: or, A description and representation of all the victories both by land and sea, granted by God to the noble, high, and mightie lords, the Estates generall of the vnited Netherland Prouinces : Vnder the condvct and command of his excellencie, Prince Maurice of Nassav. Translated out of French by W. Shvte Gent</title>
                 <author>Orlers, Jan Janszn</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 165, 170-392, 4 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Is errors and blots who transcribes the actions of an Age past-by out of sight, are almost indiscernable, at least incorrigible: Antiquitie of whom, and posteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to whom he speakes, lye at his mercie, the same of the one, and faith of the other, often suffering mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serably vnder him. But he that speakes to the face of a Time present, must either speake truely, or make roome in his patience to receiue the lie, and vndergoe a shamefull detecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Of this second kind is mine Author, who tells thee little but what perhaps thou hast alreadie heard from the mouth of the canon, or, if the crampe of feare benumb'd not thy spirits, hadst an hand in: So that thou mayest securely hearken to him, since thy knowledge will not be so vnkind as looke on and see thy beleefe abused. Let not any mans ignorance per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suade thee that it is superfluous to read ouer this Copie, hauing the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall in thy memorie: thou must lay it neerer to thee than thy memorie, in thine vnderstanding. Againe, not to endure the rehersall of thine owne actions, is an argument of their deformitie; else thou wouldst asmuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to looke in this booke, as a faire woman in her glasse, or on her pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture. This I can safely promise, That if thy judgement can reach them, among these leaues, thou mayest find much fruit worth the tasting. In the noble and prosperous familie of <hi>Nassau</hi> thou mayest obserue, That a vertuous sonne makes an immortall father in despite of treacherie and death. In the whole course of the warre, how that deluge of bloud wherewith her enemies hoped to haue drowned the Netherlands, did like the inundation of Nile but fatten and inrich them. By the basseling and coudgelling that proud Armada, that vnlesse the Lord of Hosts be
<pb facs="4"/>
the Godfather, the name of inuincible is improper and ridiculous to any humane armie. By the Hollanders marine expeditions, that vertue like the heauenlie Spheares must neuer stand still, and that whiles shee goes not forward, she becommeth retrograde. In the English, who brake the ice of Nauigation to them and had the wind of same of them in that art, idlenesse striking the sailes of their industrie, are fallen much to Lee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in reputation, perhaps in sufficiencie. In the late treatie of peace, that they who beat the furnace for Innocents, are oftentimes so ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reacht by their owne flames, that they are faine to quench them in their derided t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ares. In all, that art and discipline are more potent than mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, but a iust cause than both. Those escapes either of mine owne or the printers which thou shalt meet with all, furnish thee with good oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to requite my paines taken for thee, by fauourably correcting them.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Farewell. W. SHVTE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>