<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER, that asketh, what, when, and where, was this Battaile of LEPANTO?</title>
           <author>H., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114142_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03455</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13579</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114142</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER, that asketh, what, when, and where, was this Battaile of LEPANTO?</title>
                 <author>H., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Hollandi post-huma : A funerall elegie of King Iames: With a congratulatory salve to King Charles. An elegie of the magnanimous Henry Earle of Oxford. A description of the late great, fearefull and and [sic] prodigious plague: and divers other patheticall poemes, elegies, and other lines, on divers subiects. The post-humes of Abraham Holland, sometimes of Trinity-Colledge in Cambridge. The authors epitaph, made by himselfe</title>
                 <author>Holland, Abraham</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Holland, Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>128 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="50"/>
   <pb facs="50"/>
   <head>TO THE READER, that asketh, what, when, and where, was this Battaile of LEPANTO?</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the yeare of CHRIST IESVS, 1571. His o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Arch-Enemie the Great <hi>Turke,</hi> having had many Victories by Land in sundry Nations, as well in subduing whole Countries as in taking ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny strong Cities and Castles from the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,</hi> which confined neere his Territories, enforcing the <hi>Christians</hi> either to renounce their holy Faith, or to endure unspeakeable Slavery themselues, their Wiues and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, beeing daily bought and solde in open Markets, like Horses, Oxen, and Asses.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="51"/>The <hi>Turke</hi> by this time had Conquered many Ilands and Cities bordering upon the Sea: by meanes whereof hee was greatly enriched and strengthened with Gallies and other maine Forces. And in this yeare, 1571. knowing a Division amongst divers <hi>Christian</hi> Princes, as well for matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion as for affaires of State: Vpon hope of which advantage, hee assembled and furnished a mightie Armie of Gallies, presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming thereby to become Soveraigne of the Sea, and Lord of the Land, at one instant.</p>
   <p>But such was the great Mercy of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie GOD that he stirred up the hearts of many <hi>Christian</hi> Princes, (the Queene of <hi>Englands</hi> ayde beeing not wanting) who conjoyned together, and furnished a very strong defensible Navie of Ships, Gallies, and Galliasses: And encountred with the <hi>Turkes</hi> at <hi>Lepanto</hi> (which lyeth in part of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bania</hi> in <hi>Turkie:</hi>) And at the time of Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile, the Winde changed on the <hi>Turkes</hi> side, and came on the backe of the <hi>Christian</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie, and carried the smoke of all their Shot upon the <hi>Turkes</hi> Gallies, Foists, and Brigan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines: so as they could not well see how to
<pb facs="51"/>
defend themselues or offend their Enemies: which the <hi>Christians</hi> well observing, with all religious Resolution, right brauely gaue Charge and chase upon the Miscreants; and sunke and tooke of <hi>Turkish</hi> Gallies full Two hundred and thirtie, and at that Fight slew aboue Thirtie thousand <hi>Mahometists,</hi> besides a great number of Prisoners taken by the <hi>Christians</hi>: and aboue Twelue thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand redeemed by force from <hi>Turkish</hi>-slaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. In this blessed Victorie, the <hi>Christians</hi> lost not aboue seven or eight Gallies, nor of them aboue Eight thousand persons slaine.</p>
   <p>This Overthrow to CHRISTS Enemies was done, the Sixt day of October, 1571.</p>
   <p>And the Ninth of November following, amongst other <hi>Christian</hi> Princes the Newes being brought over land to Queene ELI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZABETH (of ever blessed and immortall memory.) Shee commanded the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> to giue Almightie GOD hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and heartie thankes, <hi>Her Sacred selfe</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the same: The <hi>Londoners</hi> also made Bonfires, and showed other pleasant signes of rejoycing.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="52"/>
Now followeth the Patheticall-poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Description of the same:</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Vale.</hi> H. H.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>