<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Obseruations for gardening, by Fa∣ther Kinke of Tibolds.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114964_Fr1_9</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20583</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6988</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114964</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Obseruations for gardening, by Fa∣ther Kinke of Tibolds.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Rams little Dodeon [sic] : A briefe epitome of the new herbal, or history of plants. Wherein is contayned the disposition and true declaration of the phisike helpes of all sortes of herbes and plants, vnder their names and operations, not onely of those which are here in this our Countrey of England growing but of all others also of other realmes, countreyes and nations vsed in phisike: Collected out of the most exquisite newe herball, or history of plants, first set forth in the Dutch or Almayne tongue, by ... D. Reinbert Dodeon, ... and lately translated into English by Henry Lyte, ... and now collected and abbridged by William Ram, Gent. Pandit oliua suos Ramos</title>
                 <author>Dodoens, Rembert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <publisher>Stafford, Simon.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>43, 213 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="observations">
   <head>Obseruations for gardening, by Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Kinke of Tibolds.</head>
   <p>TRench and leuell your ground in summer, if it be not alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die broken in winter.</p>
   <p>Then may you sowe all maner winter herbes, for Sallets, and for the Kitchin.</p>
   <p>Foureséene dayes before <hi>Bartholmew-tide,</hi> set knots of all maner herbes, and borders, with double Wall-flowres, Gilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowres, Pinks, and such like.</p>
   <p>If the ground be readie, sow Endiue to make white, foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>séene dayes before Midsummer, and sow at euery wane vnto Hallownetyde.</p>
   <p>Then must you take them vp in a drie time, and set or lay them as close as you may, that the earth come not among them.</p>
   <p>At <hi>Bartholmew</hi> time is good sowing of white Cabage.</p>
   <p>Take them vp in Ianuarie, in the wane of the Moone, or in Februarie, and replant them two foote asunder, and they will be readie to eate about Midsummer.</p>
   <p>Sowe of the same Cabage again about Februarie, then shall you doe as aboue-said, and they will bee readie about Hollomas and Christmas.</p>
   <p>Sowe about Februarie Cabage Lettice, in the wane of the Moone.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="21"/>Sowe in March all herbes for the Kitchen.</p>
   <p>Sowe in May, Turneps, Reddish, and Carrets, to serue for winter.</p>
   <p>Cut your knots and borders in the spring of the Moone, to make them grow apace.</p>
   <p>Do the like by all quickset bedges.</p>
   <p>If you will haue them to grow softly, cut them in the wane, and it will be the longer before they shall be cut againe.</p>
   <p>Set and lay red and damaske Roses, and strawberries, after Bartholmewtide.</p>
   <p>Beginne to remoue all sorts of trées for fruites, at Hallown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide.</p>
   <p>In the latter end of Aprill, or the beginning of May, pricke in the groūd, Bazel, Margerā, Melons, Pumpeons, Cucumers, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>Lay your Cucumer and Melon séedes in milke to soke, a day and a night before you pricke them in the ground, in the wane of the Moone.</p>
   <p>For seare of frost couer them in the night with pottes, and for seare of snayles.</p>
   <p>Cut your vine in Ianuarie or in Februarie, in the wane of the Moone, or at the beginning of March, two or three ioynts: but in May cut it not too neere, for feare it bléede and hinder the vine.</p>
   <p>If it be a yong vine, cut but two ioynts, and cut it betwéene the ioynts, not too neere any ioynt, and it will beare very well.</p>
   <p>Set vines in Ianuarie or Februarie.</p>
   <p>If in the end of Aprill, or the beginning of May, you will cut a branch of a vine, it will bléede verie much: you may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue that water in a glasse for your eyes.</p>
   <p>Eather all fruit to last, in the wane of the moone, next before or after Michaelmas, and lay them in a close chamber, vpon heapes.</p>
   <p>In distilling of any waters, when your glasse is full, put in a Still full of Roses, or of other things that you mind to still, and put your glasse into your Still vncouered, &amp; let it stand till that be stilled: then close vp your glasse, and neuer set it in the sunne.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="21"/>To graffe in the Shield, is to be done in Iune and Iuly, with the rynde.</p>
   <p>To graffe in te Stochin, is to be done in March and Aprill, in the new Moone, or a day or two before the change. First pare the skinnes readie to put in the stocke, before you cleaue the stocke: straight put in your skins, and clay them sure: for if the sap of a Plumme trée take wind, it then will not prosper.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Kinke of Tibolds.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>