<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Author to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Ram, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114964_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20583</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6988</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114964</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Author to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Ram, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Rams little Dodeon [sic] : A briefe epitome of the new herbal, or history of plants. Wherein is contayned the disposition and true declaration of the phisike helpes of all sortes of herbes and plants, vnder their names and operations, not onely of those which are here in this our Countrey of England growing but of all others also of other realmes, countreyes and nations vsed in phisike: Collected out of the most exquisite newe herball, or history of plants, first set forth in the Dutch or Almayne tongue, by ... D. Reinbert Dodeon, ... and lately translated into English by Henry Lyte, ... and now collected and abbridged by William Ram, Gent. Pandit oliua suos Ramos</title>
                 <author>Dodoens, Rembert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <publisher>Stafford, Simon.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>43, 213 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Author to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ouing &amp; most naturall countrymen: I haue bestowed some tyme, in reducing the most exquisit new herball or history of plants (first set forth in Dutch and Almayne tongue, by the learned and worthy man, of famous memory, D. <hi>Reinbert Dodeon,</hi> Phisicion to the Emperour, and translated into English by Master <hi>Henry Lyte,</hi> Esquire) into a briefe and short Epitome: wherein is contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the disposition and true declaration of the phisike helps of all sorts of herbes and plants, vnder their seueral names &amp; titles, not onely of those which are here in this our countrey of England growing, but also of others of foreine realmes, countreys, and nations, vsed in Phisike, (being nowe brought into a very small volume) So as where the geat booke at large is not to be had, but at a great price, which cānot be procured by the pooret sort, my endeuor herein hath bin chiefly, to make the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of so good, necessary, and profitable a worke, to be brought within the reach and compasse aswell of you my poore Countrymen &amp; women, whose liues, healths, ease and welfare is to be regarded with the rest, at a smal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler price, then the greater Volume is: wherein I haue made declaration of certayne dangerous Plants, with their corrections; onely drawing them into a special Title by themselues, which before were dispersed in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. This onely obseruation I gaue thee, that where, in many titles of cures, all, or the most part of the herbs or simples for such cure, are drawn within this direct, it is not to be intēded, that all those simples should be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded together in the vse of Phisike, but that euery of them
<pb facs="4"/>by themselues are to be ministred for the cure of the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease vnder their seuerall tytles: and that this Caracter or marke,—which you shall finde in many places of this book, is to giue the right vnderstanding of the herbe (by which it is set) by some other more familiar name, then in his first place: And as it pleased that famous and worthy man, D. <hi>Reinbert Dodeon,</hi> the Patrone of so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and necessary a woorke, to offer the same into the world: And as the sayde worshipfull gentleman, master <hi>Henry Lyte,</hi> by his diligence hath translated the same into our English tongue, for the benefit of all his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen, to the end the light thereof might not be hidden or extinguished, to their great prayse and cōmendations: Euen so, my poore talent of endeuor hath byn to none other end, but only to draw that into a handfull, which before was in the compas of a great garden: or else to bring that into a little Gardē, which before was (as to be looked for in many fields and disperced places) not to be found but by great labour and industry: my onely and greatest care hath byn of long tyme, to knowe or thinke, how and vpon whome to bestow the dedication of this my small labor: And in the penning of this my letter, my Affections are satisfied with the dedication thereof to thee my poore and louing coūtryman whosoeuer, and to whose hands soeuer it may come: For whose sake I haue desired publicatiō of the same, beseeching Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God to blesse vs all.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>VVilliam Ram.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>