<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Perkins, W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114458_Fr9_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09339</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19646</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114458</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Perkins, W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A golden chaine: or The description of theologie : containing the order of the causes of saluation and damnation, according to Gods word. A view whereof is to be seene in the table annexed. Hereunto is adioyned the order which M. Theodore Beza vsed in comforting afflicted consciences</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Jackson (Jacson), Ralph 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Thomas 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Porter, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 184, 14, 185-524, 4, 525-570, 2, 571-684, 2, 685-711, 3, 713-771, 3, 773-830, 4, 831-906, 4, 907-1057, 1 page, 7 leavesof plates, tables, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="443"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>IT is the common sinne of men at this day, and that in the very places of learning, that <hi>Christ crucified</hi> is not knowne as he ought. The right knowledge of whome, is not to make often men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his death and passion, and to call him our Sauiour, or to handle the whole mysterie of God incarnate soundly and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly, though that be a worthie gift of God: but first of all, by the consideration of the passion to be touched with an inward and a liuely feeling of our sinnes, for which our Redeemer suffered the pangs of hell, and to grow to a through dislike of our selues and our liues past for them, and from the groūd of the heart to purpose a reformation and a conformitie with Christ in all good duties that concerne man: secondly in the Passion, as in a myrrour, to behold and in behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to labour to comprehend the length, the breadth, the height, the depth of the loue of the Father that gaue his owne deare Sonne to death, and the goodnes of the Sonne that loued his enemies more then himselfe, that our hearts might be rooted and grounded in the same loue, and be further inflamed to loue God againe.</p>
   <p>To further this true manner of knowing <hi>Christ crucified,</hi> I haue penned these few lines, read them at thy leisure, and haue care to put them in practise: otherwise, thou art but an enemie of the crosse of Christ, though thou professe his name neuer so much.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>Ian. 3. 1596.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>W. Perkins.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>