<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE WORTHY AND LIVELY Patterne of a good OLD-AGE, Mr. Doctor CHADERTON, all the blessed comforts of it: and after it, everlasting happinesse.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114120_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12087</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22391.8</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114120</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE WORTHY AND LIVELY Patterne of a good OLD-AGE, Mr. Doctor CHADERTON, all the blessed comforts of it: and after it, everlasting happinesse.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Vindiciæ senectutis, or, A plea for old-age : which is senis cujusdam Cygnea cantio. And the severall points on parts of it, are laid downe at the end of the follovving introduction. By T.S. D.D</title>
                 <author>Sheafe, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>25, 210, 11 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE WORTHY AND LIVELY Patterne of a good OLD-AGE, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Doctor CHADERTON, all the blessed comforts of it: and after it, everlasting happinesse.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Reverend SIR:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Meditations here in this Treatise pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to you, are at their highest pitch of ambition, if they may obtaine, that your judicious eyes (at your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient
<pb facs="3"/>
leasure) shall passe over them. I suppose, it will be asked why they solicit you rather then any other, for this favour. It is, first for your many yeares with which GOD hath crowned you: and then also in respect of your experience in your owne particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, of what in this Tract is deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd: that is, of GODS free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this age from the Imputations cast (in a generality) upon it: and his deyning you above many others, the blessed and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble priviledges, of which it is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, and for which it hath the best helps, and most opportunities. I desire not to be made knowne un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you. It sufficeth, that to me you
<pb facs="3"/>
are well knowne: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>hat, not by heare-say (though with that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ointment, a good-name <hi>Eccles 7.</hi> you are renowned) but cheefely out of my many obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, when I was a Student in the Vniversity, and for a long time, one of your Auditors. Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way you ratifie and make good this <hi>Encomium SENECTV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIS.</hi> And therefore yours it is, and to you it comes, both to bee corrected and disposed of, incase it may seeme in any degree, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy your so much paines. And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely, should I cause my thoughts to range abroad among the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies that are knowne unto me; none would be found that might
<pb facs="4"/>
give so ample testimonie to what you shall heere reade, or be so li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an example of it, as your selfe. This (I hope) will excuse my presumption, and prevaile with you for your paines in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Discourse, though it should not with your judgement for approving it. I beseech the <hi>ANCIENT OF DAIES,</hi> to continue and increase unto you, the good your many yeeres have possessed you of; that as they are found in the way of righteousnes, so they may be to you a crowne of glory, <hi>Prov. 16.</hi> and a crowne of righteousnesse, <hi>2 Tim. 4▪</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>