<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the good and gentle Reader in all places wheresoeuer, but especially, to my louing countrimen of En∣lande, hartie salutations, and greetyng euer.</title>
           <author>Derricke, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114109_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20313</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6734</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114109</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the good and gentle Reader in all places wheresoeuer, but especially, to my louing countrimen of En∣lande, hartie salutations, and greetyng euer.</title>
                 <author>Derricke, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The image of Irelande : with a discouerie of vvoodkarne, wherin is moste liuely expressed, the nature, and qualitie of the saied wilde Irishe woodkarne, their notable aptnesse, celeritie, and pronesse to rebellion, and by waie of argumente is manifested their originall, and ofspryng, their descent and pedigree: also their habite and apparell, is there plainly showne. The execrable life, and miserable death of Rorie Roge, that famous archtraitour to God and the croune (otherwise called Rorie Oge) is like wise discribed. Lastlie the commyng in of Thyrlaghe Leonaghe the greate Oneale of Irelande, with the effecte of his submission, to the right honourable Sir Henry Sidney (Lorde Deputie of the saied lande) is thereto adioyned. Made and deuised by Ihon Derricke, anno 1578. and now published and set forthe by the saied authour this present yere of our Lorde 1581. for pleasure and delight of the well disposed reader</title>
                 <author>Derricke, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Day, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>100 pages, 12 plates, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>¶ To the good and gentle Reader in all places wheresoeuer, but especially, to my louing countrimen of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, hartie salutations, and greetyng euer.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Iuers were the causes (good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) that moued me first to take in hande, the caruyng forthe of this Image, and lastly to commende it to thy gentle deuotion, hoping, that as with no small labour, and trauel I haue finishte, and brought it to this perfection, and with no lesse willyng consent, and single mynde haue made it seruiceable at thy good pleasure to vse, so likewise on thy part, thou wilte freendly accept the same, entertainyng it as a straunger, or messenger come from a farre Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, simplie to report, and deliuer vnto thee, the state and condition of his saied Countremen the Woodkarne, without any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paryng of their credites, the more notable members of the same, who differyng from theim, in their rusticall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>udenesse, doe agree wholie with vs, in all laudable discipline. Touching whiche causes, though thei bee many, and as I saied before di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse, twoo yet especially, I thought good to signifie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the one came of a duetifull affection, and vnfarned good will (drawne of long continuaunce through graces receiued) to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes his persone, whiche vndoubtedly I honor, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a bounden duetie, (through loue inseparable) towardes my natiue Countrey: Or whiche twoo, though either of them were sufficient to moue any man (if he were not a forgetfull persone) to like indeuer, yet seeyng thei are variable, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>he of them so laudable, I might in no wise slacken my pretended
<pb facs="6"/>
purpose, but shewe my hartie good will, bothe to freende and countrie. If you therefore (my beloued countrimen) for whose sakes (as I saied before partely I framed it, and for whose greater delight, I haue clothed it with varietie, shall deeme it worthie of your custodie, or receiue thereby any profitable, pleasure, I obtaine not onely my expectation, touchyng suche courtesie, but also full recompence, of all my whole charges, (who doubtlesse accoumpte theim nothyng, to pleasure either partie). And if (by waie of digression) some peraduenture (whose iudgementes are parciall in other mennes labours) shall cauill at this my imprinted Image, or impugne the thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges therein contained (as reportyng matters of vntrouthe) especially the third lease of this discouered Woodkarne, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng no suche rudenesse, in these our daies to bee practised with the rudeste of that moste barbarous Nacion, to suche I replie (crauyng their pacience) saiyng, that it is not our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glishe Pale, whiche in any respecte I haue touched, nor yet those of the Southe, whom I haue impeched, nor yet of the Weste, whom I haue nipped, but a people out of the Northe, whose vsages I beholde after the fashon there sette doune, and those are thei whom I haue detected, shadowyng notwithstandyng parte of their maners with flowres of that Countrey, and least peraduenture ye might muse whom I meante, I will not be curious in dischargyng my conscience, lettyng you vnderstande, that thei are a people sprong from <hi>Macke Swine,</hi> a barbarous ofspring, come from that Nation, whiche maie bee perceiued by their Hoggis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e fashion: So as my beloued countrimen, and well desposed Reader, if wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse blinde not the fightes of your iudgementes) it manifest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeareth, and maie easely bee coniectured, that it is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainste any one good member of this Common wealthe of Irelande, that I haue made my discouerie, but onely against the pernicious Uipers of the saied lande, whiche thing I wish hartely eche one to beleue, and credite, knowyng (for example sake) that warre is not waged, against the Queenes freendes, not yet a battell fought, saue onely against her enemies, which
<pb facs="7"/>
if you so credite, and therewithall accepte of my trauelles, (whiche do represent my vnfained good will) I leaue not this simplie as a pledge of a further beneuolence with you, but therewithall doe paune euen my credite, for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishyng my promesse, till whiche tyme farewell as your hartes can desire.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours as his owne Ihon Derricke.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>