<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A short Discourse of the most excellent Do∣ctour and Knight, Master Leonardo Phiorauanti, Bolognesse, vpon Chirurgerie; With a declaration of ma∣ny things necessary to be knowne: neuer written before in this order. Whereunto is added a number of notable Secrets found out by the said Author.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114243_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00756</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10882</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114243</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A short Discourse of the most excellent Do∣ctour and Knight, Master Leonardo Phiorauanti, Bolognesse, vpon Chirurgerie; With a declaration of ma∣ny things necessary to be knowne: neuer written before in this order. Whereunto is added a number of notable Secrets found out by the said Author.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discourse vpon chyrurgery: written by that famous doctour and knight, Signior Leonardo Phiorauanti, Bolognese. VVith a declaration of many wonderfull matters necessary to be knowne; with most notable secret found out by the said authour. Translated out of Italian by Iohn Hester, and now newly published and augmented, for the benefite of this country: by Richard Booth, Gent</title>
                 <author>Fioravanti, Leonardo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 117, that is 118, 6 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="discourse">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb n="5" facs="5"/>
   <head>A short Discourse of the most excellent Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour and Knight, Master <hi>Leonardo Phiorauanti,</hi> Bolognesse, vpon Chirurgerie; With a declaration of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things necessary to be knowne: neuer written before in this order. Whereunto is added a number of notable Secrets found out by the said Author.</head>
   <head type="sub">The Proheme.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is to be vnderstood, that when the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ghtie Creator had made the world, hee also created all manner of beasts, as well on earth as in the water, with other foules, after which saith the holy Scripture, he created man after his owne Image and similitude, and to him gaue power ouer all things created, and with the same grace and reason. Through the which he was apte to rule and haue knowledge of all through the spirit of God, as to haue knowledge of all things whereunto he gaue his minde and vnderstanding, as it is at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to be séene among men in the world, that haue knowledge of diuers and sundrie things, all necessarie for those that will line in the world with honour: For some vnderstand the art of husbandry, which was the first art vsed in the world, for so much as without it we cannot well liue as it is plainely séene. There are other that haue knowledge in kéeping beasts of all kinds apt or méete for mans body, as Goats, Kyne, Hogges, Hens, Géese, Horse, Mules, and such like. There are other haue knowledge in Nauigation, without the which also the world would be vnperset, as it is seene
<pb n="6" facs="6"/>by experience. There be other that haue knowledge in <hi>Gosmographie,</hi> whereby they kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>w <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> parts of the world whether men may trauaile. There be other that haue knowledge in the art of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> they may helpe to defend their Prince and Countries, in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Iustice. There be other that vnderstand <hi>Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie,</hi> by the which they know the course of the Planets and their effects. Other vnderstand the <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> whereby they measure land and other things: Other studie <hi>Musicke,</hi> to accord voyces together, and other vnderstand <hi>Phisicke,</hi> to helpe the deseased bodies of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane creatures, and also animales of diuers and sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie infirmities. There be other that vnderstand Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgerie, to helpe all manner of fozes that happen vnto men: vpon which Chirurgerie, wee will write a briefe discourse and pleasant reason, and will leaue apart the science that is doubtfull, because there is no science in the world wherewith a man may doe good if therewith be no practise or experience, as a man may say: The which experience is master of all things, as it is plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly séene, and therefore we will give you to vnderstand which of those parts be best or most necessary in this Chirurgerie, either to helpe those that are hurt, or the science, or experience. And we will show the méers truth without any dissimulation or fraude, as I haue alwayes done in my workes which are Printed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> at this present doe intend to doe, if almightie God giue me grace, and quicken my spirits or wits in writing that which shall be to his honour, and pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>te to the world.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>