<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the godly and Chri∣stian Reader, the daily increase of that true godlinesse, which hath the promise of the life present, and of that that is to come, 1. Tim. 4.8.</title>
           <author>Bownde, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114771_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16525</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3438</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114771</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the godly and Chri∣stian Reader, the daily increase of that true godlinesse, which hath the promise of the life present, and of that that is to come, 1. Tim. 4.8.</title>
                 <author>Bownde, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The holy exercise of fasting : Described largely and plainly out of the word of God: with all the parts and causes, and seuerall kinds of the same: together with the most fit times, and conuenient seasons, when and how long it should be held: with the manifold fruite and commoditie that redoundeth to vs thereby: and the whole nature and order thereof. In certaine homilies or sermons, for the benefit of all those, that with care and conscience intend at any time publikely or priuately to put in practise the same. By Nicolas Bownde Doctor of diuinitie. Perused and allowed by publike authoritie</title>
                 <author>Bownd, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waterson, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 361, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>To the godly and <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader, the daily increase of that</hi> true godlinesse, which hath the promise <hi>of the life present, and of that that is</hi> to come, 1. Tim. 4.8.</head>
   <p>WHen as of late this holy exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of fasting, was by publike authoritie, not without iust cause imposed vpō vs (welbeloued fathers and brethren) I thought it conuenient, or rather necessarie for that people, which then I had to deale with (and haue still) first of all to make them acquainted with the nature of it, not so much by preaching of fasting out of some one text, (which could not very fitly haue beene done) as by deliuering vnto them in sundrie sermons the whole doctrine of it orderly, out of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places of holy Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>pture, or rather out of the whole word of God indifferently. That so they might be the more willing to submit themselues vnto it, when they did see cleerely what they should doe, and
<pb facs="7"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lso that they doe it in some good measure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cceptable to God, and comfortably to thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, when they perceaued after what manner they should doe it. And thus in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of these short treatises and Homilies at the first I had respect only vnto them. Since I cōsidering on the one side the great ignorance that is in most places, as of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther partes of gods seruice which are ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary so most of all this, which is extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, especially because it is, and hath beene so much out of vse: and then waying on the other side, that there may be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after great cause offered vnto vs againe of vsing this holy &amp; excellent ordinance of god, either publikely in many places, or priuately in more, seeing that this visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiō of the plague doth so linger, like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the leaprosy which sometime did hang long in the howses of the Iewes, and soe doth very shortly, or not at all wholy depart from some places: besides those new chastisements, which we know not how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny or how soone they may come vpon vs: I thought since, that both for these, and for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="8"/> causes these my labours might be not wholly vnprofitable to all those, that are well minded. And thought I cannot be ignorant that there are many and godly and learned sermons and treatises, both in english and latine, already extant of this argument, and so my indeauour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them may seeme superfluous: yet all things considered, I doubt not, but that some may stand in neede of these also. For as I must needes confesse, that I haue read the former, &amp; indeauoured to follow some of thē: so I leaue the learneder sort to such of them, as themselues shall best like: only this for the more ignorant sort I haue ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at, to make the whole doctrine of fas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting easy and plaine, that they might with facility vnderstand what god requireth of them in the day of fast, and how they ought to behaue them selues therein: And to that end I haue set downe euery thing orderly, &amp; at large, &amp; therefore the more clearly: and not scholastically and shortly (as some haue done) and by that meanes the more obscurely, especially vnto the vulgar sort:
<pb facs="8"/> and I haue shewed the practise of euery particular, out of the Scripture, setting downe at large the wordes of euery text for the capacity of the simplest, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for the more easines and plainnes, hauing recourse of purpose to the selfe same texts, rather then making choise of new, which vainly might happily haue bread some obscuritie Which kind of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting if it may seeme to bring tediousnes vnto the learned eares, they must consider, that first I preached these sermons to the meaner sort, men not brought vp in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and so did apply my selfe in hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of this doctrine vnto their capacity, leading them on in it according to their owne pace (which is rightly to diuide the word of God: and in his howse (as a wise steward) to giue vnto euery one of them their owne food in due season) and since, euen as they were then preached, I haue published them for their sakes especially, and so haue deliuered them as milke, for all those that are but babes and children in Christ. And therefore if any of these
<pb facs="9"/> shall receiue any benefit by them, I haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained vnto the end of my labours, though the other sort be not holpen by them one whit. For which I will pray vnto God, euen as I desire all you, to whome these presents shall come, to pray for me: and the Lord heare vs all for our selues, and one of vs for an other: and his well beloued sonne Iesu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Christ our only mediatour for vs all: that we may liue and dye in his faith and in his feare: that so the same Christ may be vnto vs life, and in death aduantage. Norton, in Suffolke.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your louing brother in the Lord Nicolas Bownd.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>