<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Authors Aduer∣tisement to the Reader.</title>
           <author>C., E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114411_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17444</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4264.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114411</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Authors Aduer∣tisement to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>C., E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An A.B.C. or holy alphabet : conteyning some plaine lessons gathered out of the word, to the number of the letters in the English alphabet, to enter young beginners in the schoole of Christ</title>
                 <author>E. C.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Norton, John 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Sheffard, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 125, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>The Authors</hi> Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisement to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Rosse IGNO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RANCE, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with supine NEGLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GENCE, in pursuite of sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>Knowledge,</hi> I haue, not without griefe, obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, by experience now of twenty yeares exercise of my <hi>Ministrie,</hi> still to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine,
<pb facs="3"/> &amp; euen raigne both in the <hi>Country</hi> and <hi>Citie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This hath made me wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in desire to become <hi>all to all,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.22</note> and with an ayme of doing good, chiefly to them of mine owne <hi>Country charge,</hi> and <hi>younger people</hi> especially, (in whom my <hi>Ministry</hi> through <hi>Gods mercy</hi> hath euer most reioyced) to collect this <hi>A. B. C.</hi> or <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabet</hi> (as I haue thought meete to terme it, the<note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Elementa prima. Heb. <hi>5.12.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles phrase,</hi> sounding to such a title) to initiate young be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginners in the most necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie grounds of godlinesse.</p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>Which labour (howso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer some perhaps may sleight it, as too vulgar, or meane a proiect, or deeme not so necessary) may I trust yeeld direction and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement by Gods blessing to some of his weaker ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants; the matter hereof being, for the most part, onely plaine places, and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected sentences, seruing pregnantly for speciall pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses, of holy Scripture, wherein Saint <hi>Austin</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">In eis quae apertè in scriptura posita sunt, continen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur illa om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia quae cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem mores<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que viuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di. <hi>De doct. Christ.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
      </note> hath auouched to bee <hi>contayned all things,</hi> concerning <hi>faith and manners;</hi> and no <hi>weapon</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/> being like to this<note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Ephes</hi> 6.17</note>
      <hi>sword of the spirit,</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">2 <hi>Co.</hi> 10 4</note>
      <hi>mighty through God to cast downe holdes,</hi> and to<note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12</note>
      <hi>cut off</hi> sinne from the very soule: Nor any<note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.109.</note>
      <hi>Lamp</hi> or <hi>Torch</hi> for conueying hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly <hi>light,</hi> to be compared with this, which goeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der those glorious titles, <hi>of</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">
         <hi>Psa.</hi> 19.7.</note>
      <hi>the perfect law of the Lord, conuerting the soule,</hi> and <hi>sure testimony, making wise the simple.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Onely this I must adde, (that the promise seeme not more then the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance) how it is not in the purpose or compasse of this
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>Alphabet,</hi> to meddle much with matters of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> already established in our Christian Church, nor yet to touch vpon all particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of <hi>Christian Practise:</hi> neither shall I seeke to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest these directions into any <hi>artificiall frame</hi> or <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod,</hi> as others haue profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably endeauoured in their exact Treatises, therein more accommodated to learned and iudicious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
   <p>All here aymed at is, (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable to the <hi>prefixed title</hi>) to deliuer some <hi>rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/> that may yeeld <hi>instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> to poore <hi>ignorant</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (of whom the world is yet full, for all our learned and elaborate preaching) and set forward <hi>young be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginners,</hi> not capable for their weakenesse of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of any artificiall <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod,</hi> in that their holy course, whereinto they are entred towards <hi>Gods</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Kingdome.</p>
   <p>Which desired and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for <hi>fruit,</hi> such, I assure my selfe, shall, by Gods blessing, not faile to finde, that shall take paines, both
<pb facs="5"/> seriously to acquaint them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues with the <hi>directions</hi> in <hi>generall,</hi> and in <hi>speciall</hi> tye themselues to commit to memory those mayne and <hi>Capitall</hi> places of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, laid downe, as it were the <hi>Text,</hi> in euery <hi>title,</hi> and by the <hi>letter</hi> differenced frō the rest in euery <hi>section.</hi> Since these, in as much as they be the plaine words of <hi>Scripture,</hi> being once made their owne, will in such sort continually sticke by them, and (more then any the things of men) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile with them; as that
<pb facs="6"/> thereby they shall still haue lodged within them, grounds of <hi>Pietie,</hi> and store of <hi>knowledge,</hi> for their spirituall good, and daily growth in those wayes of <hi>godlinesse,</hi> which are the wayes to endlesse <hi>happinesse;</hi> which <hi>God</hi> graunt.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>E. C.</signed>
   </closer>
   <epigraph>
      <bibl>1 PET. 2.2.</bibl>
      <q>As new borne babes, desire the sincere milke of the word, that yee may grow thereby.</q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>