<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE VNIVERSALL READER.</title>
           <author>P., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114035_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09040</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19333</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114035</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE VNIVERSALL READER.</title>
                 <author>P., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The mastiue, or Young-whelpe of the olde-dogge : Epigrams and satyrs</title>
                 <author>Parrot, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <distributor>Jones, Thomas 2</distributor>
                            <distributor>Meighen, Richard</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>70 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE VNIVERSALL <hi>READER.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle, or if Churlish howsoeuer its no great matter, (though I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade my selfe there are not many amongst you can be so dogged as will but offer to bite at me, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if ye knew how loath I would bee knowne to become your Debtors, aboue all others.) But to the purpose; I promised not long since, to busie my selfe no more with these ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stard kinde of commodities, mary t'was with a <hi>Prouiso,</hi> vnles I otherwise were vrg'd by such, as fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themselues perhaps agreeued, that I last forgot them, will now perforce incite mee therevnto, for more assured manifestation of my remembrance: Whome but to point at in particular, were to lay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen their imperfections, whose viler partes (for olde acquaintance) I rather may be thought to take pittie of: (and yet could I wish to haue your <hi>Clarke</hi> distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished frō your
<hi>Sexton,</hi> by more then wearing a pen in his eare) <hi>Sed praestat tacere, suadeas.</hi> For any other more barbarous or fowle-mouthed
<hi>Mungrells,</hi> that haue bin lowder barking then the rest: Ile not defile my hands by giuing such the least of chastisement, <pb facs="3"/>but leaue them peremptorily to the lashing <hi>Dogge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whipper</hi> for those <hi>Curres</hi> prouided.</p>
   <p>But now, may some guilty-conceited-<hi>Cooks-combe</hi> take himselfe wilfully by the bottle-Nose, saying: I ayme at him particularly; and so haue colour for what I doe.</p>
   <p>If any such will needes so gald-backt prooue, as cannot choose but kick and wince without rubbing, or but at the sound of a Curry-combe only, let them (by my consent) bee sadled for Iades, without dres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, &amp; get the Scratches, till the <hi>Farrier</hi> giue them ouer. In briefe, I would be thought as guiltlesse of blaming, as I was carelesse of the lines composing: Which if they please; why so: if otherwise, I will not warrant them to bee better worth: and so Fare-well.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>H. P.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>