<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MIR∣ROR OF GOOD FEL∣LOWSHIP, THE PAT∣terne of true Friendship, and the onely nonparallell of iouiall En∣tertainment; Mr. Andrew Hilton, at the signe of the horshooe, at Daintree; I. Taylor wisheth dayly increase of good Guests, tue payment, hearts content in this life, and afterward as much happines as his soule can desire.</title>
           <author>Taylor, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1147_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13463</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23768</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1147</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MIR∣ROR OF GOOD FEL∣LOWSHIP, THE PAT∣terne of true Friendship, and the onely nonparallell of iouiall En∣tertainment; Mr. Andrew Hilton, at the signe of the horshooe, at Daintree; I. Taylor wisheth dayly increase of good Guests, tue payment, hearts content in this life, and afterward as much happines as his soule can desire.</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The scourge of basenesse. Or, The old lerry with a new kicksey, and a new cum twang with the old winsye : VVherein Iohn Taylor hath curried or clapperclawed, neere a thousand of his bad debters, who will not pay him vpon his returnes from Scotland, Germany, Bohemia, the voyages of the paper boate, and his nauigations to Yorke and Salsbury with Oares</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Walbancke, Matthew</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MIR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ROR OF GOOD FEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LOWSHIP, THE PAT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of true Friendship, <hi>and the onely nonparallell of iouiall En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment;</hi> Mr. <hi>Andrew Hilton,</hi> at the <hi>signe of the horshooe, at</hi> Daintree; I. Taylor wisheth dayly increase of good Guests, tue <hi>payment, hearts content in this life, and afterward</hi> as much happines as his soule can desire.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Ind Sir, I haue seene of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes men offering to snusfe a candle, haue against their wills put it cleane out; and an vnskilfull Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgian
<pb facs="3"/>
taking a small greene wound in hand, hath brought it to an old Vlcer. I would be loath, for my part, to imitate either of these examples; for my intent is, confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the wrong I did you: and an endeauour to make amends. I doe confesse that I did you wrong in print, in my booke of my Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels to Scotland, and now in print, I doe make you a publike satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; For, I protest to God, that I haue heard so much good report of you, that I am double sorry that I was so mistaken, and that I haue
<pb facs="3"/>
beene so long time before I haue printed my recantatiō. It was your Tapsters want of wit and manners, and my want of discretion, that was the grounds of my too much credulity and temerity. For his part I wish him no more harme, but that chalke may bee his best pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Thunder may sowre his Hogsheads, Rats gnaw out his spigots at midnight, and himselfe to commit his witte to the keeping of a foole or a knaue while heliues; And your hostlers, for gaping so greedily like gudgeons vpon mee,
<pb facs="4"/>
I pray that they may euery day mourne in litter and horse-dung. But these are but Iests by the way, for as many as knowes you, haue told mee that if you had beene at home, my entertainment had been better: if it had beene so, it had bin more then you owed me, and more then I at that time could haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired: but I would haue stretched my wit vpon the tenters of Inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the praise of Innes and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers; I would haue put the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfull world in minde of the good seruice that <hi>Rahab</hi> the Inne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper
<pb facs="4"/>
did at <hi>Iericho,</hi> in hiding and preseruing the spyes that were sent by <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Ioshua;</hi> I would haue made the obliuious logger-headed Age remember, that the Redeemer of the world did grace an Inne with his blessed birth: What place then but an Inne was the High Court of Heauen and Earth, the residence &amp; lodging of the immortall King, of neuer-ending eternity? This and more I would haue done, but what is past cannot be recalled, and it is too late to put olde omittings to new committings. And so my no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="5"/>
and thrice worthy hoste of hostes, I omit not to commit you and yours to the protection of him that made you, desiring you to take this merry Pamphlet in good part, or in earnest of my better amends, and as a qualifier of your Iust an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the best of his eudeauours to be commanded, <hi>IOHN TAYLOR.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>