<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE GENEROVS MINDED MILITARY SOCIETIE.</title>
           <author>Taylor, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114873_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13562</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23857</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114873</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE GENEROVS MINDED MILITARY SOCIETIE.</title>
                 <author>Taylor, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The valevv of true valour, or, The probation and approbation of a right military man : Discouered in a sermon preached Iuly 25. before the worthy gentlemen of the military company. By Thomas Taylor Doctor of Divinitie, and pastor of St. Mary Aldermanbury, London</title>
                 <author>Taylor, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 <publisher>Jones, Thomas 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 28, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE GENEROVS MINDED MILITARY SOCIETIE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle-men, that I should in your ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment speake that which you with so vnanimous consent importuned me, not to Preach only, but to publish: I cannot ascribe (next vnto Gods perswasion) to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other cause, then the concurrence of our mutuall affections to the noble exercise of <hi>Armes;</hi> which you and I professe. You to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage: I to honour. Yet was I sorry your importunitie pitched on so slender an obiect. It was in vaine
<pb facs="3"/>
to pleade the worthlesnesse of these notes; and how meritoriously they deserued the darke: Or to tell you that it was against my mind and manner to send out single Sermons into publicke view; especially, in a subiect so vnwonted. J see that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary men thinke their booty often richer then it proueth, and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times win by force, what right might deny. And therefore as one vnder <note place="margin">Sponte it, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendus tamen nisi eat.</note> command goes of himselfe where he would not: because else he knoweth he must be drawen: so haue I conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended to this your second desire. J was not willing to encrease it in bulke: but rather to contract what might haue been enlarged. Iudicious <note place="margin">Moneta opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma quae precij &amp; ponderis plurimum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet in parva mole.</note> readers, esteeme of bookes as of coines, whereof those are most preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<pb facs="3"/>
which haue most weight and worth in the smallest quantity.</p>
   <p>The onely addition I entended was if I might adde a graine. To the honor, encrease and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your company. The prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity whereof euery good man (in these threatning times) cannot but aduance. For as it is in the <hi>natural,</hi> so is it in the <hi>nationall</hi> body. Though the head may aduise well; the eye see clearly, the tong discourse discreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet if the armes and limbes bee lame, it can neither defend it selfe, nor offend the enemy: so neither can prudent counsell in the head of the kingdome; nor cleare doctrine and direction in the eyes of the Church; nor lawes sharpely pleaded, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, secure our State: if martiall
<pb facs="4"/>
men and affaires be lame, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynted. Euery man knowes the postes of a meane house had neede be heart of oake: and much more the studs of so great a State, and pondrous fabricke as ours is, had need bee strong, like to <hi>Iacin</hi> and <note place="margin">1. King. 7. 21.</note>
      <hi>Boaz</hi> the two pillars of the porch of that great Temple. The great God of spirits put great spirits in you, and the rest of your noble pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession. That with the valour of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> the might of <hi>Sampson,</hi> the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of <hi>Gideon,</hi> and the successe of <hi>Ioshua,</hi> you may in Gods cause, and your coūtries seruice atchieue great and noble works for the defence of the Gospell, the safety of our King, the honour of the Kingdome: the taking of the prey out of the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="4"/>
mouth; and the rescuing of the oppressed from the mighty man. And let all faithfull subiects and sonnes of valour say, Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>The louer of your valour, and vertue, THO: TAYLOR.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>