<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>B., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114791_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04284</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1440</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114791</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>B., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The true guide to glory : A sermon preached at Plympton-Mary in Deuon, at the funerals of the right vvorshipfull, and truely Religious Lady, the Lady Strode of Newingham. By Io. Barlovv</title>
                 <author>Barlow, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 51, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist</hi> was not amisse compared to a mourner: for his attire was hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; his foode locusts and wilde hony; and his Doctrine, to flesh and blood, sounded harshly: So may all my Sonnes, and that not vnfitly, be stiled the subiects of sorrow; for the weedes, wherein they be wrapped, are blacke; their faces, eyes, cheekes represent death, iudgement, the graue; and their tongues tell of heauy and terrible tidings. Notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, doe not thou too rashly condemne their father; for their mother, Time, was womanfull of great infirmities; in whose wombe they were conceiued; so that he gaue them not all, but part of their being. Are not these the dayes of danger, times of perill, so long agone fore-told, prophesied? Shall wee then expect issue of Peace, or sonnes of Laughter? Nay rather looke for a sorrowfull seede and cruell Posterity.</p>
   <p>Yet this I would haue thee to vnderstand, that (though their heads be hanging, their lookes lowring, and this Motto imprinted in their Brow, <hi>Woe to the wicked inhabitants of the Earth:</hi>) thou hast no iust cause to shut thy doores, veile thine eyes, or to deny them a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entertainement; for they, in many things, doe resemble
<pb facs="3"/> thy selfe, beare the ingrauen image of thy person, and truely declare, what, before long, shall certainely befall thee. They speake rudely, bluntly, yet truely; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in censure them not ouer-suddenly: for it's their fathers language; of him they haue learned it; so that it's become their naturall Dialect: And he taught them all, and first of all, this impartiall lesson; <hi>That, in their progresse and speech, they should value all men alike, of what cloath soeuer their coates be cut on, vntill a New birth had put a difference.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I easily conceiue the murmurings of many, mumbling: What? is not the world full of such children? I haue often seene, that such as haue no seede of their owne, sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome affect the posterity of another: Or, peraduenture, some (who are past begetting any) may obiect or cauell; Why, this is not the same, I was present at his birth. My good friend, know (if it were so) that a better coate changeth not the subiect; neither doth a new patch alter the forme of an old garment; for then <hi>Ioseph</hi> in his Princely Robes, had beene another man, and <hi>Zebede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> his old nets had become new by mending. Shall we conclude, that when an Hebraisme, by our Lord an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Disciples, is turned into a Graecisme, that the Scripture is wrested or altered? But these persons are like the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren wombe, in a double respect; they are vnfruitfull, and yet with foaming out their owne shame, and spetting innocent infants in the face, they be neuer satisfied. Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit his Father, suspect thy owne censure: for when thou sawest him first, he was running; and thine eye might easily deceiue thee: now he is sitting, thou maist take a more certaine view of him, and see him as he is.</p>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <p>He that will iudge wine for colour, in the powring; or mens suites on their backes, running; may easily deeme amisse in his forward censuring. But handle the one, and see the other in a glasse setled, so shalt thou not be at all deluded: In like manner, words vttered are in moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the Eare cannot so well receiue them, as being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed in papers, the Eye will apprehend them: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, be swift to heare, slow to speake; and then iudge righteous iudgement.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From my study in</hi> Ply<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mouth.</dateline>
      <signed>Thy Christian friend, I. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>