<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114738_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01491</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11617.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114738</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Societie of the Rosary. Newly augmented</title>
                 <author>Garnet, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Fr. Garnet’s Second Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44, 168, 12, 169-231, 1, 19, 5 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>FTER the generall deluge and innuda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the wholle worlde in the time of Noë,<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>6.</hi>
      </note> Almightie GOD placed in the cloudes his Rainbow, as a token and obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that he would no more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy the world with water. How generall a deluge of heresie and of all maner of iniquitie our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable countrey hath these late yeeres susteined we yet feele by the experience of the calamitie therof: and it is to pitifull to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how many soules haue already perished therby. Neither doe we see any other reliefe in so
<pb facs="3"/>great distresses: than to make our humble recourse vnto our merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Lord, and earnestly to desire of his soueraigne greatnesse: that shutting vp the deapth of hellish lakes,<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>8.</hi>
      </note> and the mighty cataracks of his heauie displeasure; these deadly fluddes may cease from the earth, and all creatures be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored to their former saftie. One singuler occasion of hope wee might haue of so greate a benefit: if it would please him but once to shew this signe of his Testamēt with mankind, his gloriouse rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow, which discouering vnto the worlde most bewtifull coulers might signifie the caulme &amp; faire weather, which were at hand: This rainbow I meane to be the glorious Virgin, a most beutifull signe of Gods frenship with men, and such a token of his singuler
<pb facs="3"/>mercie, that when he hath often times loaded the skies with the heauie cloudes of his iminentiven gence, he neuerthelesse looking vpon so glorious &amp; beloued a cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ature, not appointed by him for wrath and anger, but chosen for a figure of mercy and peace, and therfore most worthely called the mother of mercy: forgerting our iniquities, and as it were in a maner his owne Iustice; with-hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth his seuere punishments, and in steede of brimstone and fire, which those cloudes should send vpon vs, leadeth vs <hi>In nube diei,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. <hi>77</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>&amp; tota nocte in illuminatione ignis</hi> by the cloudes of his mercie in the day; and all the night by the comforte of his heauenly lights. I could here discourse at large how worthely this B. Virgin may be called a rainbow, &amp; how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="4"/>excelent comparisons may be made therof vnto her: of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of her vertues, of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of her greate excelencies figured in roūdnes,<note place="margin">Apoc. <hi>4.</hi>
      </note> of the stateli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of that seate which God did choose in her for his owne person But sufficient it is for our purpose, that she is in speciall maner a rain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bow against Heretickes: wher-as the Church generally singeth, she hath destroied all heresies in the wholle world, and therfore is a perticuler signe and aboade of the ceassing thereof: From this bow there goeth none but chosē arrowes taken forth of the quiuer of God him selfe, yea arrowes of the saluatiō of our Lord, arrowes of saluation against <hi>Siria;</hi> that is, arrowes of saluation both in tran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quillity of the Church; and also a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all the enimies of Israel, &amp;
<pb facs="4"/>the Church of God in the time of tentation and disturbance. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wanteth it a misterie, that this bow is bēt vpwards towards heauen:<note place="margin">Cant. <hi>4</hi>
      </note> for it not only recerueth the strength from God, to whom it looketh: but wounding first the hart of God him-selfe, from thēce receiueth all comfort for his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes and confusion at the last for his wicked enimies.</p>
   <p>This whē I consider, &amp; waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing also with my selfe, how trew it is of her which is spoken of the wisdome of God, with which she was so aboundantlye endowed; that she preuenteth those which desire her for to shewe her selfe first vnto them: that she seeketh with great diligēce for those that are worthy of her,<note place="margin">Sap. <hi>6</hi>
      </note> and sheweth her selfe in the waies pleasantly vnto them: and with all prouidēt
<pb facs="5"/>care runneth to meete thē. I fully perswade my selfe, that it is in our owne power to winne her, and to obtaine frō heauen a new rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow: which being a signe of god, cannot signifie falsely, but most certainely fore-tell our comforte and reliefe. It is in our power. I say: yet not except we desire her: she seeketh for vs but so, if we be worthy of her: she sheweth her selfe pleasant, but vnto those that she meeteth in the waies to seeke her: for whom she boūtifully pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uideth all maner of good.</p>
   <p>I present therefore vnto my most deare coūtry with the same loue and affection with which I would if so it pleased God presēt it my blood, a singuler meane of winning this Virgins fauour, and such a meane as by her selfe hath here tofore bene presented vnto
<pb facs="5"/>the worlde, and now vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly by her self also not vnmind full of her aunciēt Dowry, is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto our country the Society of the holy Rosary: an auncient meanes euen from <hi>S. Domincks</hi> time of rooting out of heresie. Which albeit both in time past, and now of late yeres it hath ben embraced in our countrey, with great deuotion: yet neither hath it hitherto bene so generally vsed neither the nature and profit ther of so perfitly knowne, as for so greate a good were required. for (as the scripture saith) A hidden wisdome, &amp; an vnseene treasure,<note place="margin">Eccl. <hi>20</hi>
      </note> what profite is there in thē both? Wherfore I thought it my parte, knowing what opportunitie our countrey men may haue to be ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted vnto the participation of this treasure, diligently to search
<pb facs="6"/>out &amp; breifly to set down what so euer either necessarily doth belōg or any waie might be profitable to the enioying of the same: fully perswading my selfe that as spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall men in these Catholicke countreies are wont to say of thē selues; so the beades must be to our afflicted brethren, in steed of all maner of armour or weapons: for the weapons of our warfare are not carnall, but mighty to God,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1</note> vnto the distruction of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions, distroying Councelles, and all loftines extolling it selfe a gainst the knowledge of God. Which perswasion of mine vnto those which shall duely weigh the perfection and excelencies of this most glorious Virgin, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not any way be iudged false: for therfore is she called a well setled array of a pitched armie, because
<pb facs="6"/>she mightily ouercometh,<note place="margin">Cant. <hi>6.</hi>
      </note> not on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly her owne, but also her deuout clients aduersaries. Which singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler protection we can no waie de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>serue more cōueniently: then by such seruice as her selfe hath ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and cōmended vnto vs, and of it selfe doth yeeld vs such com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities as in the treatise shall appeare. Yet this must I cōfesse, that I haue for the most part fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med my selfe, vnto the simpler sorte: for such are they which most please our Lady, &amp; in which she-most delighteth: my intent hauing bene in this litle treatise, that as the beades are the vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned mans booke; so also such per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sons might here find whatsoeuer is necessary for their deuotion. And yet doubt I not, but any Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke minde will iudge the same worke not to be vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="7"/>vnto whosoeuer of neuer so greate knowledge with a certain spice of hereticall pride, will not contemne ordinarye Catholicke helpes of deuotion. Accept ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (gentle Reader) this my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent: &amp; with conuenient diligēce and study vse the same. Which if thou doest: I doubt not, but how<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>soeuer it may displease curiouse eies, it will not be displeasing to our B. Lady, not without vnspeak<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>able profite to our wholle coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, thē the which two things next vnto Gods glory I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire nothing more. Fare-well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>