<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL AND RE∣LIGIOVS GENTLEWOMAN Mistresse ELIZABETH FOLIAMBE.</title>
           <author>Hume, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114146_Bo1_8</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03839</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13954</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114146</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL AND RE∣LIGIOVS GENTLEWOMAN Mistresse ELIZABETH FOLIAMBE.</title>
                 <author>Hume, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Ieuues deliuerance out of Babylon, and the mystery of our redemption : plainely demonstrated in ten sermons, vpon the 126. Psalme, viz. 1. Sions saluation. 2. The saints securitie. 3. The free-mans frankincense. 4. The atheists acknowledgement. 5. Gods goodnesse. 6. The godlies gladnesse. 7. The prisoners petition. 8. The commoditie of the crosse. 9. The captiues case. 10. The Christians comfort. Preached in Yorkshire, by Iohn Hvme, Minister of the Word; and now published by authoritie</title>
                 <author>Hume, John, minister of religion in Yorkshire</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Sparke (Sparkes, Wreichionen), Michael 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 124, 2, 125-173, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="65"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL AND RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIGIOVS GENTLEWOMAN Mistresse ELIZABETH FOLIAMBE.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Noble and vertuous Mistresse,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I called to mind, the great losse ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny receiued by the death of that worthie personage (your noble Aunt, my most honoured Ladie) in whose hearing some of these drie Sermons were preached: whose gracious attention, secmed to giue unto them some fauourable approbation. And now, being publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed to the open view of the world; and withall depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of her Countenance, from whence they should haue receiued their true lustre: I had once resolued to haue let them passe without a Mistresse: yet, whilest I was musing of <hi>Salomons</hi> proposition,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Prou.</hi> 31.10.</note>
      <hi>Who can find a vertuous Woman?</hi> And at last remembring, how you haue hitherto shewed your selfe, not onely a Niece, but a Child of hers; no lesse affectionate to the Word; no lesse thirsting after Grace: to vse the Apostles words,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.4.</note>
      <hi>I reioyced greatly that I had found of her
<pb facs="66"/>Children walking in the trueth:</hi> and so, thought myselfe bound in equitie to commend that vnto you, which I was indebted to consecrate to her. Moreouer, the great respect I haue euer receiued from your noble Husband, doth oblige mee thereunto: yet, am I silent of his courtesies, lest by verball thankefulnesse I should seeme to craue new fauours.<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 2.</note> Now hee that doubled the Spirit of <hi>Eliah</hi> vpon <hi>Elisha,</hi> redouble in you these vertues which were in that <hi>Elect LADIE,</hi> that heereafter it may be said of you, as it may now be truely affirmed of her, <hi>Many daughters haue done vertuously, but shee surpassed them all.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships, and your noble Husbands to command in all Ministeriall duties, <hi>IOHN HVME.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>