<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114781_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68490</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18330</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114781</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An epistle of a Catholicke young gentleman, (being for his religion imprisoned.) To his father a Protestant : Who commaunded him to set downe in writing, what were the motiues that induced him to become a Catholicke</title>
                 <author>N. N.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>—Recusant</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England ; France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 40 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>I No sooner had perused this short Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, then I had an earnest desire it might bee Published in Print, as well for that I obserued the groundes which this young Gentleman had layde downe to his Father to bee both sncsinct and Learned! as also for that I am well perswaded the promulgation thereof, would (God assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting) giue much good satisfaction to any iudicious Reader, and for that I neuer had any acquaintance with the Author, I mooued secretly a very Friend of mine (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate with him) to perswade him (if pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible) to put it to the Presse: which motion hee not onely absolutely refused, but was also infinitely displeased with the Moouer, wherefore to preuent (what in him lay) the printing and publishing of the said Epistle, he not onely refused vtterly to giue Coppies thereof, but also ecclipsed it from the view of all men. But the Father more prodigall then the Sonne himselfe, carried the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall continually about him, making no dainty at all to shew it in St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> the Pawne, <hi>Youngs</hi> Ordinary in Corne-hill, and in many other places at his pleasure, he making it his common Table-discourse <pb facs="3"/> in Tauernes and Ordinaries: by which meanes I obtained a Coppy, which (though long after) I sent ouer Seas to a Friend, desiring him to cause it to bee Printed. Reade it through with good attention, and if thou reape any profite thereby; forget not to render due thankes to GOD, and then in thy Prayers remember both the Author and the Publisher.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>