<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PREFACE OF M. IOHN FOX, To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114273_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09659</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19929</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114273</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PREFACE OF M. IOHN FOX, To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A godlie exposition vpon certeine chapters of Nehemiah, written by that worthie byshop and faithfull pastor of the Church of Durham Master James Pilkington. And now newlie published. In the latter end, because the author could not finish that treatise of oppression which he had begonne, there is added that for a supplie, which of late was published by Robert Some, D. in Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Pilkington, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thomas, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>3, 75, that is 82 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>A PREFACE OF M. IOHN FOX, To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>AS it is greatlie to be reioyced, and the Lord highlie to be praised for the happy enterprise of the Godlie worke of Nehemiah, begonne by the reucrent and vigilant Pastour of Christ his Church of famous memorie M. Iames Pilkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Bishop of Duresme: So againe it were to be wished, that if the lord had thought it so good, his dayes might haue continued to the full per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiting of the same, which now is left vnperfect, onelie containing fine Chapters by him expounded'. For the setting out where of being reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted hereunto, I thought to adde these few lines in recommending the same to the godlie reader, trusting no lesse, then that whosoever will take paines in reading thereof, the same shall finde his labour therein not altogether lost. And that for diuers causes. First for the better explaining of the Chapters whereof he intreateth. Secondlie for the opening of auncient hystories intermixed withall, much needfull to be knowen. Thirdlie for the opportunitie of the tyme well serving for the purpose present. For as Nehemiah then by gods prouidence was set up for the reedifying of the materiall Tomple of Hierusalem destroyed by the Babylontans, so in like sort the spirituall Church of Christ, in this spirituall Babylonicall capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie, being a long time in ruine and decay, standeth in great need of Godlie helpers, and good workemen, as blessed be the Lord, some we haue seene, and doe see, right zealouslie occupied to the shedding of their blood in repayring Christ his temple. Yet notwithstanding the matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of so great importance, and the time so daungerous, it shall not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse in these our dayes to be taught by the time before vs. First, that
<pb facs="3"/>
the outward temple in Hierusalem destroyed by the Babylonians, did lie wast for manie yeares, it cannot be denied. Which being graunted, it must needs follow, that eyther the sayd materiall temple doth beare no representation of the spirituall Church of Christ (which cannot be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) or else that the same Church of Christ must necessarilie suffer some captiuitie, &amp; Apostasie for a time by certaine spirituall Babilonians inlat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter times: which being so, then must it likewise follow consequently, that as that former temple of God in Hierusalem after long captiuitie at length was restored againe by the mighty hand of God, so the like is to be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plished in Christ his Church, after long wracke and decay, to be repayred againe, as we see now come to passe. For what oppression, what tyrany, what darkenes hath ouerwhelmed the poore Church of Christ these manie yeares by the Romish Assyrians, who is so blind that seeth not? wherfore much deceiued be these our Pope holiepretensed Catholikes, who drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in their fantasies no other true Church to be in earth but onlie their holy church of Rome, falslie so perswade them-selues, because the outward state of their Romish church, so gloriouslie, and richlie shineth in the world, and therfore the true Church of Christ is at no time to be blemished with ignoraunce and darkenesse, but continuallie florisb with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out spot or wrincle in the eyes of men, neuer to suffer any wrack, or decay, but perpetually to be preserued from all ruine or distresse. By which ruine if they meane the perpetual, or finall desolation of the true Church of Christ, true it is that the same shall neuer sinallie be for saken nor ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, but for a time the same to suffer vioience and oppression by ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies it cannot be denied. For Antichrist, by the secret permission of God, must haue his owne course, and raigne here in the church for a time, in which time by the assured Testimonie of S. Paules Epistle there must come a defection and Apostasie, wherby is signified no doubt a spirituall &amp; as it were a generall departing from the right faith of the gospell, for a time and space, till it shall please the Lord againe to giue his booke to the mouth of his Prophets, and to send downe by his Angell his measuring reede to measure the wasted temple of the Lord' for the reedifying againe. as we read, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>: 10. 11.</p>
   <p>Howsoeuer Antichrist in the meant space doth florish in this world, sitting in the Temple of God, boasting him-selfe as God, and drawing the faith of the people from God to him-selse; Certainlie with the true Church of Christ it standeth much otherwise, which must be brought down by Antichrist not to final destruction, but for a time to be oppressed, till it shall please God againe to repaire it, as we by experience haue good proofe to declare. Wherefore let no man meruaile at the decaied state
<pb facs="3"/>
of Christ his Church, which hath bene solong time continued, nor thinks the worse of the Gospell non preached, as though it were a new faith or a new Religion lately erected. If this gispell now preached were not taught by Christ him-selfe, by Paule, and other Apostles, let it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> for new. If the Popes doctrine be not agreeing to the same, then let euery man iudge which is new, and which is old. Brieflie, let vs take example of the auncient tabernacle or house of God, first set vp by Moses, afterward more magnifically <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> to the like proportion in timber, &amp; stone by Salomon: which house or tabernacle the Lord promised to stand for euer: yet notwithstanding the same temple of God (exemplifying no dout the spirituall Church of Christ here in earth) was vtterly ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne by the Babilonians for a certaine space, and afterward repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againe by Gods people with much difficulty, and hardnes of times: and after that the same againe miserablie dispoyled, and destroyed by wicked Antiochus. In like manner the spirituall Church of Christ, although it haue the true promise of Christ to endure for euer, as it doth and euer shall doe, yet lacketh not her Babilonians, her Anticchus, her ouerthrowers, &amp; temporall oppressours: yet not so oppressed, but at length, by labourers, and artificers of God, is to be repayred againe, albeit sent in great sharpnes of time, we see it now come to passe.</p>
   <p>Which being so, let vs therefore, comparing time with time, looke well to the matter euery man what he hath to doe. Such as be builders may take example of those good builders therof, whome we read that with one hand they builded, and with the other they held their weapon, that is the spirituall sword of Gods word to keepe of the enemie. Such workmen the Lord send into his vineyard to be diligent labourers, not loyterers: nor braulers, but builders, labouring, and working, not with one hand, but with both hands occupied. And likewise vpon these labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers the Lord send good ouerseers, such as this good Nehemiah, who not regarding his owne priuate charges, and expenses, bestowed all his care in tendring and setting forward the erection of the Lords house, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the workemen, to prouide for their necessities, to defena them from enemies, to keepe them in good order from strife and variance. For as euery good building there best goeth forward, when the workmen in one consent ioyne them-selues together: So contrariwise nothing more hindreth the setting vp of any worke, as when the workmen are deuided among them-selues. Albeit during the time of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> we sinde no great sturs among the people, or if there were any, it was seene composed by the wise handling of that good gouernour, as in the fift chapter may appeare. wherefore for the better example to le taken of these distressed
<pb facs="4"/>
dales, I thought it not amisse in this so daungerous building vp of Christs Church in the perillous latter times, this treatise of Nehemiah, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled by the right reuerend and famous prelate M. Iames Pilkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton of blessed memory, to be published and commended to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian readers, wherby all good labourers, and ouerseers of Christ his Church may receiue some fruitfull ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertisement to consider in these soe great affayres of the Lord his busines what is to be done and looked vnto.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>