<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HIGH AND MIGHTIE HENRIE, ELDEST SONNE OF our Soveraigne Lord the KING, Prince of Wales, DVKE of CORNWALL and ROTHSAY and Knight of the most noble order of the GARTER.</title>
           <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114357_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09202</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19511</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114357</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HIGH AND MIGHTIE HENRIE, ELDEST SONNE OF our Soveraigne Lord the KING, Prince of Wales, DVKE of CORNWALL and ROTHSAY and Knight of the most noble order of the GARTER.</title>
                 <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Minerua Britanna or A garden of heroical deuises : furnished, and adorned with emblemes and impresa's of sundry natures, newly devised, moralized, and published, by Henry Peacham, Mr. of Artes</title>
                 <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dight, Walter</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>15, 100, 4, 101-212, 1 page, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HIGH AND MIGHTIE HENRIE, ELDEST SONNE OF our Soveraigne Lord the KING, Prince of Wales, <hi>DVKE</hi> of <hi>CORNWALL</hi> and <hi>ROTHSAY</hi> and Knight of the most noble order of the GARTER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST EXELLENT PRINCE.</hi> Hauing by more then ordinarie sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, tasted h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eretofore of your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious favour: and evidently knowen your <hi>Princely</hi> and <hi>Generous</hi> inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to all good Learning and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie. I am emboldened once aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, to offer vp at the Altar of your gratious acceptance these mine <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemes:</hi> a weake (I confesse,) and a worthlesse Sacrifice, though an assured pledge, of that Zeale and Duetie, I shall for ever most Religiouslie owe vnto your Highnes: shewing herein rather a will to desire, then worth to deserue, so peerelesse a patronage. Howsoever the world shall esteeme them in regard of their rude and homely attire, for the most part they are Roially discended, and repaire into your owne bosome (farre from the reach of Envie) for their protection. For in truth they are of right your owne, and no other then the substance of those Divine Instructions, his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie</hi> your Royall <hi>Father</hi> praescribed vnto you, your guide (as that golden branch to <hi>AENEAS,</hi>
      <note place="margin">AEneid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 6.</note>) to a vertuous &amp; true hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py life. It is now two yeares since I presēted vnto your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes some of them, then done by me into Latine verse, with their pictures drawen and limned by mine owne hand in their liuely coulours; wherein, as neere as I could, I obserued the <hi>Method</hi> of his <hi>Maiesties BASILICON DORON,</hi> but by reason of the great number I had since that, newly invented: with some others collected, (tieng my inven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>on to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o one
<pb facs="3"/>
Subiect as before) I am here constrained aswell of Necessitie as for varietie sake, to intermixe (as it were <hi>promiscuè</hi>) one with the other in one entire volume, the rather because of their affinitie &amp; end, which is one and the selfe same, that is, the fashioning of a vertuous minde. I dare not discourse at large vnto your Highnes, of the manifold Vse, Nature, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, and ever esteemed exellencie of this kind of <hi>Poesie:</hi> it being the rarest, and of all others the most ingenious, and wherein, the greatest <hi>Princes</hi> of the world, many times haue most happily exercised their Invention: because I doubt not, but your Highnes already knoweth whatsoever I might speak herein. Onely what I haue done, I most humbly offer vp the same vnto your gratious view, and protection. Desiring of <hi>GOD</hi> to beautifie and enrich your most hopefull &amp; Heroique minde, with the divinest giftes of his grace, and knowledge, heartily wishing, there were any thing in me, worthy of the least favour, and respect of so excellent a <hi>Prince.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>To your Highnes, The most sincerely and affectionately devoted in all dutie and service.
<signed>HENRY PEACHAM.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>