<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, HIS VERY ESPECIAL GOOD LORD, THOMAS Baron of Buckhurst, Lord Treasurer of Eng∣land, one of the LL. of her Maiesties most Honorable privie Counsaile, Knight of the Honorable Order of the Garter, and Chauncellour of the Ʋniversitie of Oxford, I.P. wisheth encrease of honour and eternall faelicitie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114574_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09490</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19773</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114574</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, HIS VERY ESPECIAL GOOD LORD, THOMAS Baron of Buckhurst, Lord Treasurer of Eng∣land, one of the LL. of her Maiesties most Honorable privie Counsaile, Knight of the Honorable Order of the Garter, and Chauncellour of the Ʋniversitie of Oxford, I.P. wisheth encrease of honour and eternall faelicitie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first part of the consideration of hvmane condition : vvherin is contained the morall consideration of a mans selfe: as what, who, and what manner of man he is. Written by I.P. Esquier</title>
                 <author>Perrott, James, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Barnes, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Barnes, Joseph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Broome (Brome), Joan</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, HIS VERY ESPECIAL GOOD LORD, THOMAS Baron of Buckhurst, Lord Treasurer of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, one of the LL. of her Maiesties most Honorable privie Counsaile, Knight of the Honorable Order of <hi>the Garter, and Chauncellour of the Ʋniversitie of Oxford,</hi> I.P. <hi>wisheth encrease of honour and eternall faelicitie.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the fore-front of this small and slender building, many thinges are wanting (Right Honorable, and my most honored Lord) which through the distraction of busines, the short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of time, and the vnskilfulnes of the builder could not be finished, as it was purposed. For the same for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune falleth out many times vnto writers of bookes, as doth vnto Builders of houses: when as in both, at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the worke, they, which frame the first founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and plot, doe propose vnto themselues lesse labor and expence of time, then in the ende they must bestow, before it be fully finished: So, sometimes they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained to leaue their well-begunne labours without any ende, or else rudely and roughly to finish the same. Such is the conclusion in the first part of this poore cottage of <hi>Consideration,</hi> which I haue builded like an vnexperien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced workeman, and which I haue presumed humbly to
<pb facs="3"/>offer vnto your Lordships Honorable patronage, not so much for the worth of the worke, as to testifie the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of my most zealous faith and affection vnto your Lordshippe, being therevnto bound by your Lordships honorable favour and furtheraunces. For which I can yeelde no other offering, but the fruits of this my yet vnperfected labours, with the continuance of my vowed devotion (next to my most gracious Soveraigne) to doe your Lordship service. And so I humbly end, with my praiers for your Lordships preservation and increase of honours.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Haroldston</hi>
         <date>the 16. <hi>of Novemb.</hi> 1600.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Lordships most bounden, and ever to be commaunded, <hi>I.P.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>