<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE,
AND MOST WORTHY OF
ALL HONORS, AND
ALL TITLES,</title>
           <author>Grimeston, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114485_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07363</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17747</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114485</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE,
AND MOST WORTHY OF
ALL HONORS, AND
ALL TITLES,</title>
                 <author>Grimeston, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The generall historie of Spaine : containing all the memorable things that haue past in the realmes of Castille, Leon, Nauarre, Arragon, Portugall, Granado, &amp;c. and by what meanes they were vnited, and so continue vnder Philip the third, King of Spaine, now raigning; written in French by Levvis de Mayerne Turquet, vnto the yeare 1583: translated into English, and continued vnto these times by Edvvard Grimeston, Esquire</title>
                 <author>Mayerne, Louis Turquet de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Islip, Adam.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 1380, 28 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE,
AND MOST WORTHY OF
ALL HONORS, AND
ALL TITLES,</head>
   <head type="sub">ROBERT Earle of Salis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie,
Lord High Treasurer of
England, &amp;c.</head>
   <head type="sub">THOMAS Earle of Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke,
Lord Chamberlaine to
his Maiestie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y most Honoured Lords, I might
iustly feare, that my continuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire
to acknowledge my dutie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
your LL. by some acceptable
kind of seruice, would be held im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie,
if your Noble disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
and mine owne experience
in particular of your Honours
gratefull acceptance of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest
seruice that is well meant, had not freed me from that
feare, and enabled my weake faculties to adde this vnto the
rest of my oblations; which I consecrate vnto your LL. vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the Altar of my deuotion. I must confesse that your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorable
reception of my French and Netherland Histories
hath added courage to my will, to passe the Pyrenee Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,
and to take a suruey of this Historie of Spaine: the
which I held (in my weake judgement) for many respects,
as worthie the knowledge of our Nation, as any other. It is
a generall Historie of all the Continent of Spaine, wherein
the seuerall Histories of those seuerall Kingdomes, as they
were in former times distinctly diuided and gouerned by
<pb facs="3"/>
diuers Princes, are vnited; being collected out of all the best
authors that haue written of that subiect. These considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
I say, were the inspiring meanes to moue me to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take
the traduction of this Historie of Spaine, and haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
me resolution, and constancie to finish it, and to send
it forth to the view of the world. The worke I hope will giue
good content, it being a faithful relation of so many variable
and strange accidents as haue happened in those Countries,
during the manie alterations and changes of that State, and
the long and cruell wars betwixt the Moores &amp; Spaniards.
If I, in my plaine maner of translation, haue not giuen it that
grace which a more eloquent penne might haue done, I
most humbly craue pardon, and intreat that my desire to
benefit others, may giue satisfaction for my disabilitie
and defects. I haue presumed to shroud the fruites of my
poore endeuors, vnder your LL. countenance and
protection; desiring to leaue a testimonie to
all posteritie how much I am</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your LL. deuoted in all
duetie and seruice,
EDVVARD GRIMESTON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>