<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MIGH∣TIE, HIGH-BORNE, VERTVOVS, AND MOST excellent Princesse: ANNE, by the grace of God, Queene of great Brittaine, France and Ireland.</title>
           <author>Hopkins, I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114087_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03640</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13768</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114087</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MIGH∣TIE, HIGH-BORNE, VERTVOVS, AND MOST excellent Princesse: ANNE, by the grace of God, Queene of great Brittaine, France and Ireland.</title>
                 <author>Hopkins, I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon preached before the queenes maiestie at Hampton Court, on Sunday the 16. day of October: By I. Hopkins, one of his maiesties chaplaines in ordinarie</title>
                 <author>Hopkins, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>46 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE MIGH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIE, HIGH-BORNE, VERTVOVS, AND MOST excellent Princesse: ANNE, by</hi> the grace of God, Queene of great <hi>Brittaine, France and Ireland.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Maiesties atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue hearing, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious approouing this plaine Sermon, when it was preached before your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, mine own experience of your religious deuotion in frequenting the seruice of God: and your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb facs="3"/>godly affection to goodbooks, and dailie reading them, which hath been often testified by such as are acquainted with your Maiesties studies: haue emboldned mee to print this Sermon, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent it to your Maiestie, earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie desiring that it may bee as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for the increase of godlines in such as reade it, as it will be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to manie, being graced with your Maiesties name and patronage.</p>
   <p>The Lord of heauen and earth so blesse your Maiesty with a dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie increase of his graces, that as your Highnesse hath the happines to be the most worthie and famous Queene of Europe, so after manie
<pb facs="3"/>yeeres enioying your Crowne vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, you may bee crowned with eternal glory in heauen. For which none shall more heartily pray, then</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties most humble seruant, <hi>I. HOPKINS.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>