<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO AL THE BRETHREN DISPER∣sed here and there, that fauoure and loue the Gospell, Augustine Marlorate, wisheth grace, mercy, and peace, from God the father through the Lorde Iesus.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1570</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114262_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06985</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17404</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114262</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO AL THE BRETHREN DISPER∣sed here and there, that fauoure and loue the Gospell, Augustine Marlorate, wisheth grace, mercy, and peace, from God the father through the Lorde Iesus.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A catholike and ecclesiasticall exposition of the holy Gospell after S. Mathewe, gathered out of all the singuler and approued deuines (whiche the Lorde hath geuen to his Churche) by Augustine Marlorate. And translated out of Latine into Englishe by Thomas Tymme, mynister. Sene and allowed according to the order appointed</title>
                 <author>Marlorat, Augustin</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1570</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 446, 446-758, 9 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO AL THE BRETHREN DISPER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed here and there, that fauoure and loue the Gospell, <hi>Augustine Marlorate,</hi>
      </hi> wisheth grace, mercy, and peace, from God the father through the Lorde Iesus.</head>
   <epigraph>
      <q>
         <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen as, all men so long as they liue in this present life, ought to leuell, as at a Butte, at the knowledge of the truthe whiche maye nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishe them in the hope of the true and eternall lyfe, those men are to bee iudged vnworthy vtterly the name of Christians, whiche being contente with some arte or science, whereby to get their liuing, either do lightly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde, or els altogether neglecte the knowledge of heauenly matters, the onely meanes to attayne saluation.</q>
   </epigraph>
   <p>Neither can there be found any greater ingratitude among men, then whē they do not endeuour to the vtmoste of their power to know God alone, whiche hath not only created, fashioned, and nourished them as a father in this life, but incessantly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them to the immortall, and incorruptible heritage whiche is prepared for all them, whome that celestiall father hath eng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>fted by faithe into the body of his onely begotten sonne. Moreouer a true and singuler waye to attayne saluation, is by God propounded to vs, namely, if wee beleue his promises, whiche waye iustefieth before God mankynde, by nature prone vnto sinne, and maketh hym the heyre of God, and fellowe heyre with Christe. I meane faithe, not suche as veyne men and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites boast of when they chaunce to conceiue some slender opinion of God: but that whiche alone deserueth the name of faithe, and vndoubtedly taketh holde of the righteousnes offered in the Gospell, and so stayeth on the foundatiō of free remission of synnes, that it cānot be perswaded any other thing than that whiche is certainly knowen to procede out of the mouthe of the Lorde: for faythe commeth by hearing,<note place="margin">
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>a.</hi> 10. <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>r.</hi> 1.</note> but hearing by the woorde of God, who at sundrye tymes, and in diuers manners spake in the olde tyme to our fathers by Prophetes, but in these laste dayes he hath spoken to vs by his sonne. On whome he hath powred out his spirit most plentifully, in so much, that whosoeuer shall heare him teaching, and imbrace his doctrine by faythe, they may assure them selues to haue bene rightly instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the wysedome of God it selfe, and to be setled out of all peryll of errour.</p>
   <p>Nowe, when his vocation required that after he had opened the veritie to his electe, and finished al thinges, for the whiche he came into this worlde, then he should retourne to his father, he woulde not that his spouse the Churche should lacke that incomparable treasure of the Gospell, whiche he hym selfe brought down from heauen. For seing the cause of his comming was to builde agayne the taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacle of Dauid whiche was fallen downe,<note place="margin">
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>s.</hi> 9.</note> and to repaire the ruine therof (that is to say, that he might erecte and stablishe his kyngdome in the middest of his Churche, whiche according to the oracles of the Prophetes, he should gather together out of all people and tongues) he thought it not sufficient to offer the happy and gladde tidinges of the Gospell to thē which were at hand, (namely to the Iewes) but he would haue the benefite of the heauenly calling offered to them also whiche were farre of (to witte,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 3.</note> the Gentiles). For God had also determined from the beginning that the Gentiles shoulde be heyres knit in one body &amp; fellowship of the promises in Christe through the preaching of the Gospell.</p>
   <p>Christe therefore rysing as a conquerer from death, cōmaunded his Apostels, being endewed with heauenly vertue,<note place="margin">
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>h.</hi> 28.</note> to go into all the worlde, and preache the Gospell to all creatures, teaching the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles to obserue all thinges that he had commaunded them. But, because the nomber of twelue did not suffice for so great a multitude of men, as the king of all kinges had decreed to call to saluation by the shryll trumpe of his Gospell: after he had obtained of his father, and that the holy Ghoste was sente downe on his Apostels, he enriched, encreased, and adorned his Churche with men indewed with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly wisdome, whose ministery he would vse to the ende of the worlde, in feading the flocke redemed by the sheading of his bloude. Therefore he ordeined some Apostlels, some Prophetes, some Pastors, some Teachers,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> 4.</note> to the gathering together of the sainctes to the woorke of the ministery, and to the ede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of Christes body.</p>
   <p>But (alas) after the departing of those watchemen, there was in all the worlde so great scarsitie of faythfull ministers, that those heauenly ryches wherewith the Churche was beautified, were not on euery part so plainely set forth as the worthynes of the thing it selfe did require. For it was brought to passe by the wilines of Sathan that fearce enemy of the Euangelicall truthe, that in stede of faithfull Pastors, innumerable gredy and rauening Wolues did craftely insinuate or wynde in them selues in to the flocke of Christe: whiche straightwaye being disguised with those worthy titles of Pastors, did vnder that pretence defraude the poore shepe of the holy foode of Gods worde, and in stede of the same, brought into the world certaine stinking and vayne traditions, whiche they had drawen out of the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy puddel of carnall reason, and would haue them accompted (suche was their arrogancy) for deuine oracles: Moreouer, men were growen to suche madnes &amp; vnfaithful dealing, that whatsoeuer pleased
<pb facs="3"/>
them, the same also they did perswade the kynges &amp; rulers of the worlde, whose duty it was to watche for the safetie of all the people, and before all thnges to take hede that they did not degenerate from the true worship of God. But in this horrible waste and confusion of thinges the celestiall father vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched safe to preserue his Churche by a certayne miraculous working, not to be attained by our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, for he daily calleth backe his electe out of the bottomles pitte of ignoraunce, and transposeth them into the kingdome of his welbeloued sonne, that being partakers of the light of the Gospell, or rather being made light it selfe in the Lorde, they might walke as children of the light, &amp; submitte them selues wholy vnder his obedience,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</note> whiche called them out of darkenes into a wonderfull cleare light.</p>
   <p>Whiche worthy and incomparable benefite is daily offered not onely to priuate men here and there dispersed, but also vnto kinges &amp; rulers, so often as God doth styrre vp in their Costes, faithfull Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors, though neuer so cruell persecutions storme euery where, &amp; Sathan with his ministers, raginge, do bende all the force of their strengthe to hinder the course of the Gospel, either by mans authoritie, or els to breake it of by the feare &amp; intollerable wayght of afflictions. Therefore seing through the grace of God we haue here free libertie vnder right Christian princes to enioye the light of the Gospell, whē as many other nations of the worlde are as yet buried in the depe dungeon of ignoraunce, and seing it hath pleased God of his free mercy, certayne yeares paste to snatche vs out of the iawes of Antechrist, that we might heare the swete voyce of Christe continually sounding in the Churche, wee should bee twyse ingratefull, if we should not wyshe with ardent petitions that oure brethren might obt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>e the like grace and fauour, or if we shoulde not reatche out our hande to helpe them whiche make haste to gette the same libertie. But there can no waye be founde out more commodious to further their salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then if beside our daily prayers in whiche we commende them to the Lorde, we reatche as it were into their handes some thing whereby they might well fortefie them selues against their enemies, and be able to reproue and conuince suche as resiste the truthe.</p>
   <p>Neither do we nede any great consultation to determine what this thing should be, whē as nothing can be more profitable vnto them than the sounde, syncere, &amp; playne exposition of the holy Scriptures, which heretofore was so obscured by the fonde commentaries &amp; preposterous interpretations of those that knewe not (truely) the very elementes of Christian religion, so that the worde of God gaue place to prophane wryters, so farre was it from retaining the force and authoritie which of right she ought to haue among men. For who knoweth not, that those (who neglecting the authoritie of the worde of God, did cite <hi>Plato, Aristotel, Cicero,</hi> and other prophane wryters of that sorte, in their pulpettes) were had in great estimation and counted for chiefe deuines in comparison of those that propounded the worde of God simply and sincerety.</p>
   <p>I therefore (wyshing to satisfie their desier whiche long earnestly for the sounde and playne expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition of the Scriptures, lefte vnto vs by the Prophetes and Apostles) applied <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>y mynde before these fewe yeares to collecte and gather out of the doctours (suche as might be gotten) bothe olde and newe, whatsoeuer semed to helpe to the exacte knowledge of the newe testament, hoping hereafter (if the Lorde graunt me strengthe) to bestowe the like diligence in the olde testament, to the ende, that as the whole body of the Scripture is set forth vnto vs by diuers organes of the holy Ghoste, so beinge beutified with a plaine and perfecte exposition collected out of sondry interpretours, it might be redde of all the godly to the glory of God and saluation of men.</p>
   <p>Neither yet do we thinke that this our labour shalbe improued by any, saue onely by suche as mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like all godly and deuine thinges. For seing many with earnest affection desier to knowe the opiniōs of suche as interprete the holy Scriptures: and oftentimes it chaunceth that what by one is preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, that is spoken by an other, and contrariwyse: yea, but fewe haue the multitude and varietie of bookes, many also cannot enioye them without perill: Who I beseche you can condemne these oure painefull studies and good intent, but that also he shall seme to improue their indeuour which would profite willingly by reading or hearing sondry interpretours of the Scriptures.</p>
   <p>Moreouer, if their diligence be commended (and not vndeseruedly) whiche out of the lectures and Sermons of the preachers of Gods worde, note and gather what they can and geue it to be printed, to the ende the whole Churche might reape a commoditie of that whiche was spoken out of a Pulpet to a fewe in nomber: why should it not be laweful to collecte and chuse whatsoeuer semeth to pertaine to the explictation of the sacred Scriptures out of their commentaries, whome God hathe made ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seers of his flocke to feede and teache them, and hath enriched them with many giftes to the common edifying of his Churche.</p>
   <p>And as for suche as thinke them selues so spiritual that being contente with the volume of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble onely do carelesly and frowardly reiecte all commentaries, those men I iudge not worthy any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation. For that whiche they vaynely babble tendeth to no other ende (except perhappes they knowe not them selues) but vtterly to abholishe the ministery of the worde, that it might be lawfull for euery one to dreame or vtter vnaduisedly what he liste of Gods high misteries, when neuertheles the Lord him selfe commendeth prophecie before other thinges,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</note> in so muche that the Apostell Paule doth not doubte to preferre the same before certayne other giftes of the holy Ghoste, otherwyse moste excellent.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>And in an other place he sayth, Despise not prophecies, trie all thinges, kepe that whiche is good. <hi>Solomon</hi> also doth witnes in playne wordes that where prophecying doth fayle the people must nedes bee scattered abroade.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Pro.</hi> 29.</note>
   </p>
   <p>Let them therefore either bring to passe that all men may speake Hebrewe and Greeke, and that euery mēber may be replenished with the fulnes of the spirite (whiche thing is peculiar to Christiās) or els let them suffer the Churche to enioye the communion &amp; participation of giftes whiche Christe distributeth to eche man as semeth good vnto him selfe.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>he reason of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e Title.</note>As touching the tittle of the booke, we thought it good to call it an Ecclesiasticall exposition for a double respect: first, because it is gathered out of those wrytinges whiche were employed and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate to the Churche it selfe by holy men, whiche bestowed all their labour and study to enlarge the true faith: and for that cause they may well be termed Ecclesiasticall wryters: Secondly, because it appertayneth of dutie to the Churche to knowe the familiar voyce of their spouse who speaketh vnto her sitting in the heauens, and that by the helpe of his seruauntes (to wytte, faithfull ministers) who for that same cause are called in the Scriptures the interpretours of Gods wyll,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</note> and the messengers whiche bryng fidinges of the reconciliation betwene God and man.</p>
   <p>But we call it Catholike, (that is, vniuersall) because it is gathered vniuersally out of all the most appro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ed deuines. And for because (welbeloued brethren in Christe, you whiche yet grone vnder the yoake o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ntechriste dispersed here and there) you desier with ardent affectiōs to knowe those things whiche may guyde you to the perfect vnitie and certaintie of faythe: I moste earnestly request you, that as the Churches restored to their integritie enioye the sacred sermons, lectures, communication, and publique conference of the selfe same men whiche haue enriched this woorke with their labours, so you also vse gladly and cherefully this exposition of the newe Testament, that your fayth may haue the better successe, and Christes spirite by the reading of the Scriptures may in suche wyse mortefie whatsoeuer concupiscence of the fleshe is remayning in you, that we may all speake, thinke, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande one thyng being one whole body.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Corint.</hi> 1.</note>
   </p>
   <p>Flie therefore all peregrine &amp; straunge doctrines, and geue attentiue eare to the moste swete voyce of that great shepehearde of the shepe Christe Iesus, who by his Apostels and Euangelistes teacheth you moste playnly the way to saluation. Despise with a stoute courage the forged tales and traditiōs of men, by whiche your consciences are snared, and imbrace the libertie achieued by Christe, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely set forth in this newe Testament: whereof you haue here an exposition, no lesse sounde than playne, and euident. Not that this interpretation is so perfect &amp; absolute in euery point that nothinge may be added thereto pertayning to doctrine and edification: for who can examine or interprete any one place of Scripture so happely and dilligently that no man shalbe able to expresse the same more playnely, or obserue in it somewhat more helping either to teache, exhorte, or reconcile other places. Neither was it my intente to vrge the studentes in holy Scriptures to kepe silence, but rather not onely to exhorte all the Godly, but also to desier them for Gods sake, that if they haue attayned anye thing, either by reuelation of the spirite, or by the commentaries of other whome we haue not sene, to brynge it, and make it commen, so that it be briefe and fitte to edefie: whiche howe necessary it is in se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious matters, there is none but wyll confesse. For ouer and besides the newe bookes whiche come forth dayly, whereby this worke might bee enlarged, I am fully perswaded that the authours them selues, out of whose wrytinges I haue taken this exposition, are so farre from ambition and emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that they desier nothing more, than that they to whome the gifte of prophecie is graunted, shoulde not defraude the Churche thereof, for whose sake they haue receiued that whiche they haue. I sought therefore to profite them onely whiche with vpright conscience seke the symple and peculiar sence of the Scriptures, leauing vnto the Church (whom God endeweth euery day with marueilous giftes) libertie to adde according to tyme and place, what semeth to belonge to the common edifyinge of the godly, as is wont to be done in the holy assembles and metinge: where the Godly communing of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine matters, haue libertie to bringe forth or alleage in the middest of the company that whiche they haue receiued of the father of lightes,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</note> so that if it be reuealed to an other sitting by, the firste doth wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly kepe silence, as the Apostell commaundeth.</p>
   <p>Nowe as concerning the authours out of whose commentaries or annotation vppon the Gospell after Mathewe this exposition is collected, we haue declared their names in the next leafe following. And leaste the often repetition of their whole names should trouble the readers, we haue signified thē by their first letters, although that thing semed once vnto me not greatly necessary, if this one admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of my frēdes had not prouoked me thereto, who tolde me that it would fall out that some would reproue me of a lye, for because this woorke being intituled a Catholyke exposition collected out of sondrye interpretours, should neuertheles appeare to be one discourse, neither would they beleue any other, except we did note by letters euery particuler mans woordes. But where I my selfe did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to that parte, not to discrie the authours names by letters, I was led hereby because I feared the disposition of some, who being addicted to men, do for the moste part measure, approue, and reiect the interpretations according to the authoritie and estimation of the man, rather considering the men,
<pb facs="4"/>
than what the holy Ghoste pronounced by them to the common erudition of the Churche.</p>
   <p>Moreouer, the readers peraduenture will marueyle that I note so fewe woordes out of some au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours: but let them vnderstande this, that when I finde one that sayth the same that almoste all the reste do, whether it be in fewe woordes, or many, so it be in more playne woordes, his woordes I haue chosen, yet as it were weauing to or vniting out of other, that whiche he had either omitted or lefte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spoken: for one man can not speake of all thinges, for want of memory, neither is occasion offered, If at any tyme a diuers or contrary exposition happen to be founde among the authours, I haue so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed the same, that I haue noted what the reader should followe. Neither shall there be founde in this booke a hotche potche of opinions, (if wee maye so terme it) whereby the Reader myght bee troubled, not edefied: but sounde and true doctrine, and the same throughout the whole booke, guy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vs to the father and Iesus Christe his sonne.</p>
   <p>Therefore (good brethren) accepte, and according to goodnes and equitie allowe his dilligence, whiche together with you wysheth before all thinges, the increase of Christes kyngdome, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of Antechriste. Do you also your endeuour with earnest &amp; ardent zeale to, professe Christes Gospell, neither (as some falsely termed Christians do) be you ashamed of it, by constant confession whereof the glorious sentence of Christe is onely to be hoped for,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 10.</note> who shall approue the same before his heauenly father, and electe Angels.</p>
   <p>And verely no man is able worthely to commende the excellency and frute of the eternall wysdome of God whiche is opened in the Gospell. For the Gospell is,</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 4.</note>
      <hi>The light vvhiche the people that vvalked in darkenes did see, and vvhiche sprang vp to them vvhich sate in the region of the shadovve of death.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>It is the kyngdome of God vvhich approched to vs, vvhich vvere the bondslaues of synne, and heires of eternall death.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Luke.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>It is that happy and ioyfull tidinges vvhich exempteth vs from all feare and bringeth occasiō of incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible ioye, because it tolde of his comming vvhiche came to seke and to saue that vvhiche vvas lost.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.</note>
      <hi>For God so loued the vvorlde that he gaue his onely begotten sonne to the ende that all vvhiche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue in him should not perishe, but haue life euerlasting.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 20.</note>
      <hi>It is that moste riche treasury vvhiche conteyneth vvhatsoeuer Moses and the Prophetes haue vvrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, vvherein is opened vnto vs all the counsell of God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 1. <hi>Corint.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>It is the povver of God to saluation to as many as b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap> to the Ievve first and to the Gentile.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>It is the preaching of the crosse, vvhiche vnto those <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>erishe is foolishenes, but vnto vs that are saued, the povver of God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</note>
      <hi>It is that Myrror of the deuine glorie, in vvhiche vve all beholding the glory of the Lorde vvith vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered face, are chaunged into the same Image from glory to glory as by the spirite of the Lorde.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>The doctrine also of the Gospell is so certayne, and in euery pointe so absolute, that although an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell from heauen should preache any other thing but the same he ought to be counted accurssed.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3.</note>
      <hi>It is the vnsearcheable misteries of Christe, vvhiche in other ages vvas not knovven to the sonnes of men, as it is novve reuealed to his holy Apostels and Prophetes by the spirite.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>It is the vvoorde of lyfe vvith vvhiche all the godly must holde out in the middest of a naughty and croked nation.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Colos.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>It is also the vvorde of truthe vvhich is not onely come among vs, but also doth fructefie and increase through the vvhole vvorlde in spight of the resistance of Sathan and his ministers.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Thes.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>It is that holy and true saying vvhiche is vvorthy to be receiued of all men, not as the vvorde of men, but (as it is in dede) for the vvorde of God, vvhiche also vvorketh effectually and mightely in those that beleue.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Thes.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>It is the spirite of the mouth of the Lorde, vvhich shal slea that vvicked sonne of perditiō Antechrist, vvho shall seduce them that perishe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>It is that faithfull saying, and vvorthy by all meanes to be receiued, that Iesus Christe came into the vvorlde to saue synners.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>This is the same Gospell, vvhereby Christe the sonne of God comming into this vvorlde, hath abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished death, and hath brought life and immortalitie vnto light.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Titus.</hi> 3.</note>
      <hi>For it teacheth hovve vvee being iustefied by the grace of God are heires according to the hope of eternall lyfe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Phile.</note>
      <hi>It is moreouer that immortall and incorruptible sede, vvhereby he vvhiche vvas before vvicked and vnprofitable, is made a nevve creature in the Lorde.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.</note>
      <hi>It is the liuely vvorde of God mighty in operation, and sharper than any tvvo edged svverde, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth through euē vnto the deuiding a sonder of the soule and of the spirit, and of the ioyntes and mary, and is a discerner of the thoughtes and intentes of the harte.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>It is that pure vvord vvhich being receiued vvith mekenes and grafted in vs, is able to saue our soule.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">1. <hi>Petr.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>It is that holy vvorde of the Lorde against vvhich, almoste all the vvorlde is bente, and yet it endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for euer.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.</note>
      <hi>It is also that Scripture vvhiche is geuen by inspiration from heauen vvhich they that are vnlearned, and vnstable, peruerte to their ovvne destruction.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>It is that inuiolable vvorde, vvhiche vvhosoeuer kepeth, in him is the vvorde of God perfecte in dede.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">2. <hi>Iohn.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>It is the doctrine vvhiche vve must only imbrace, so that if there come any to preache vnto vs, and bring not this, he ought not to be receyued of vs, no nor yet saluted.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>3.</hi> Iohn. Inde.</note>
      <hi>It is the vvorde of saluation and veritie, vvhose faithfull preachers ought courteously to be receyued.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Contrarivvyse, the contemners and scorners of the same shalbe greuously punished by Gods iust iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Apoca.</hi> 14.</note>
      <hi>And to conclude, it is the eternall Gospell vvhiche must be published vnto them that inhabit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> on the earth to euery nation and kynred, and tongue, and people.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Those men therefore are vnhappy which set light by this vnuiolable Gospell of Christe, but farre more vnhappy are they whiche haue and persecute the ministers and fauourers thereof, and moste vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy of all are suche as deny and reiecte frowardly that whiche otherwyse they knowe to be true: of whiche sorte many are founde among the Papistes, for whome it had bene better not to haue knowne the waye of righteousnes than when they haue knowen it to retourne from that whiche was set forthe by Gods commaundement. But it falleth out with them according to the true prouerbe: The dogge is returned to his owne vomet, and the Sowe that was wasshed to wallowe in the myer. I beseche you moste dearely beloued brethren in Christe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e from suche as are worse than the Dogge or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pente, and reade ouer this booke whiche is offered vnto you with great dilligence: you shall finde in it (I trust) wherewithall to confirme your myndes in Christe our Sauiour aboundauntly, among so many and so great troubles of this curssed worlde. To hym be glory, honor, and dominion for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell in the Lorde,</salute>
      <dateline>
         <hi>At Viuiacum</hi> in <date>the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendes of Ianuary. 1559.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>