<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO ALL ENGLISH Catholicks, that are faithfull sub∣iects to Queene ELIZABETH, our most dread Soueraigne: The Secular Priests that are diuersly afflicted, doe wish all prosperitie, iustice, peace, ioy, and happines in our Lord Iesus Christ.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114185_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09135</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19449</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114185</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO ALL ENGLISH Catholicks, that are faithfull sub∣iects to Queene ELIZABETH, our most dread Soueraigne: The Secular Priests that are diuersly afflicted, doe wish all prosperitie, iustice, peace, ioy, and happines in our Lord Iesus Christ.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Iesuites catechisme. Or Examination of their doctrine. Published in French this present yeere 1602. and nowe translated into English. VVith a table at the end, of all the maine poynts that are disputed and handled therein</title>
                 <author>Pasquier, Etienne</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 238, 2 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_English_Catholics">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO ALL ENGLISH Catholicks, that are faithfull sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects to Queene ELIZABETH, <hi>our most dread Soueraigne: The</hi> Secular Priests that are diuersly afflicted, doe wish all prosperitie, iustice, peace, ioy, and happines in our Lord Iesus Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T cannot be vnknowne vnto you all (very reuerend and deere Catholicks) what great and bitter contention (raised vp from hell no doubt through the malignitie of sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than) hath lately fallen out amongst vs, who are your spirituall guides, and ought to haue beene vnto you examples of humilitie, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, vnitie, pietie, and a whole schoole of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious vertues. And we are fully perswaded, that the consideration of it, doth very greatlie moue &amp; perplex your catholick harts with manifold griefes: especially, seeing we are on both sides so confident in our owne so contrarie courses.</p>
   <p>The Iesuits say vnto vs: <hi>Woe be to that man, by whom the scandale commeth:</hi> We the secular Priests, say vnto them; <hi>Woe be vnto him by whom the scandale commeth.</hi> Now whether they apply the words of our Sauiour Christ more rightly to vs, or we to them, therein ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the doubt, and that is the difficultie: Wee both doe pleade for our selues: and you with the Church; must iudge betwixt vs both as vmpiers of our cause. The woe is of a large extent, &amp; will be too heauie to be vndergone by any. <hi>Expedit ei,</hi> (as the text saith) <hi>it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, or farre better it were</hi> (say some) <hi>for such a man, that a mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone were hanged about his necke, and he drowned in the bottom of the Sea.</hi> In such a contrary application of this so terrible a woe, you (our auncient children and faithfull Catholicks) shall shewe your selues right worthie of these honourable titles, and greatly benefit both vs the Secular priests, and the others the esteemed religious Iesuits, to
<pb facs="3"/>the preuenting in part of this heauie censure; if you continue sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fast in the doctrine which you haue receiued of vs, conioyned in one a like vnitie of fayth, hope and charitie; and shall take no offence at these our quarrells &amp; vnbrotherly garboyles. For as S. <hi>Hierom</hi> saith; <hi>Qui scandalizatur parvulus est: He that is scandalized is but a weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. Maiores enim scandala non accipiunt: sound and resolute Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks doe not take scandale at anything.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>There was long since an earnest disputation amongst the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, <hi>who among them should be greater:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math. 18.</note> &amp; Christ himselfe was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen by them as vmpire and Iudge paramount to determine the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie. Who accordingly hearing the matter, propounded vnto him in these wordes: <hi>Quis putas maior est &amp;c: who thinkest thou is greater?</hi> decided their iarre, with some sharpnesse in this sort as the text reporteth. <hi>Iesus calling vnto him a little child, set him in the midst of them and said: Amen I say vnto you, vnlesse you be conuerted and become as children,</hi> (that is saith <hi>Lyra</hi> in the glosse vppon that place) <hi>vnlesse you be couerted ab elatione scil: superbiae et ambitione maiorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, from pride and ambitious affectation of greatnes, and become hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and simple without malice or gall of sinne, you shall neuer enter into the kingdome of God.</hi> And furthermore, foreseeing in his diuine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, how such contention for superioritie might proue verie dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous in the Church, and wound the tender consciences of manie weake nouices in the catholicke faith: this most wise Arbitrator <hi>(in whom be all the treasures of wisedome and knowledge bid)</hi> doth conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue his commination to the better suppressing of that so dangerous an enormitie: saying, <hi>Hee that shall scandalize one of these little ones, that beleeue in me, it is expedient for him that a Milstone be hanged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his necke, and that he be drowned in the depth of the sea.</hi> Vppon which words the said <hi>Lyra</hi> writeth in this manner, <hi>Et si hoc generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dicit contra omnes: tamen hic specialiter contra Apostolos, qui hic de dignitate vidētur contendere, et in hoc poterant alios perdere: Although Christ speaketh these words generally to all: yet he speaketh them heere specially against his Apostles, who doe seeme to contend here for digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: and therein might haue ouerthrowne many a soule no doubt, and harmelesse hart.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Of these things wee haue thought good to put you that be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks in minde; that thereby you may consider how the chiefest seruaunts and children of God haue beene subiect to this ambitious humour of affecting soueraigntie, and seeking for superioritie, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, and precedencie. <hi>Iohn</hi> the Patriarch of Constantinople, (though otherwise a worthie Prelate in the church of God) did cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende for the supremacie with Saint <hi>Gregorie,</hi> that peerelesse pastor, prince, prelate, and pope of Rome. And heere at home it is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to those that haue read or heard our English histories, what stirre and hart-burning there hath beene in former times, betwixt the
<pb facs="3"/>Archbishops of Canterburie and Yorke about such matters, being in other respects all of them verie notable men. But neuer was there such an attempt in our opinions for superioritie amongst Catholiques, (for wee will not at this time meddle with any heretiques) since the first preaching of the Gospell of Christ, as now lately is set on foot vnhappily by the Iesuits mischieuous practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses. Their order is declared by <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> to be the fifth order, <hi>Mendicantium predicatorum, Of the begging Preachers or Friers. Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius</hi> their founder, pretended to haue thē called <hi>Fratres minimi, The lowest, least, or meanest sort of Friers:</hi> and termed this company,<note place="margin">Io. Osorus obitu Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natij.</note>
      <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etatem minimam, The meanest or least Societie:</hi> not in regard that they were few in number at the first: but as a great Iesuit saith, <hi>To signifie thereby, that his Societie should yeeld honour to all other sorts of religious persons as to their elder brethrē, ac plane patribus, &amp; as indeed to their Fathers.</hi> But tell vs we pray you; haue these Minimes &amp; begging Friers taken this course? We wish with all our harts they had takē it.</p>
   <p>That the Apostles before they were fully instructed by the holy Ghost, should haue contended amongst themselues, who should be the greatest, being euerie one of them in so high fauour with their Maister Christ, as they were: it might haue admitted some tollerable excuse, had not our Sauiours <hi>Woe</hi> beene mentioned in the Scriptures, and denounced plainly against them, as a dreadful doome by a sharpe censure of a sorrowfull clause. There wanted not some probable pretences; why Patriarches and Archbishops might grow into variable oppositions for the prerogatiues of their places, themselues being personages by calling of some equalitie. But that the meanest, least, and lowest order of begging Friers should con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, not among themselues who should be the greatest: but with their elder brethren, auncients and fathers, the most Reuerenced, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected, and Religious persons of euerie profession: and not that onely, but ouer and besides all this, to striue to bring vnder their girdles the Secular Cleargy, the chiefe state of Priestly preheminency is a wonder as we thinke, the like whereof was neuer heard before amongst Catholiques, Ecclesiasticall, Religious or Temporall, since Christs time till of late daies, that the Iesuits are growne to such a stubborne and vnbridled head, as we feare will breed great mischiefe in the Church of God, before they be well reformed and brought into order againe.</p>
   <p>In the other contentions before mentioned, there was no fault as we takeit, eyther in Saint <hi>Peter</hi> for defending his supremacie, or in Saint <hi>Gregorie</hi> the great, for mayntaining the dignitie of the Sea Apostolique: or yet in the Archbishops of Canterburie, for standing vpon their right and interest, granted before vnto them by sundrie of Saint <hi>Peters</hi> successors, for the chiefe primacy in and ouer the Church and ecclesiasticall State in England; but in those that sought to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne
<pb facs="4"/>them, was all the offence that was committed. And that is our case iust: who being Secular Priests now in England and else-where, doe stand at this present in a strong opposition against the Iesuits. We labour not for any extraordinarie superioritie ouer them, not emulate in euill sense any of their vertues or good inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours (if any happily be in them:) nor intrude our selues into their haruest, nor prie into their actions more then we are compelled, nor insinuate our selues into their fauours, nor desire to haue any dealing at all with them. Onely we would be glad to keepe our owne pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Church of Christ, (which we and all our predecessors Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Priests haue euer held, since the first propagation of the Gospell of Christ and Christian Catholique faith and religion, by the holy Apostles after our Sauiours ascension:) and that now these beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Friers by faction and false pretences might not tyrannise o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs.</p>
   <p>It is strange to consider how mightily they are possessed, with pride and ambition, and how farre they haue thereby preuailed. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men of learning, they scorne to be subiect to the orders of any Vniuersitie: being preachers, they will be exempted from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolement of all or any Bishops: being Friers, you kill them, if you tell them of any cloysters, or wish them to liue retired like right re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious men indeed, or to keepe the generall statutes and rules of all other religious orders. Being naturall borne subiects in many coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries where they remayne, no ciuill Magistrate, Prince, or Potentate, must controll them, nor once seeme to call them to the least ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for any of their proceedings. And that which is most, being men that professe such zeale, charitie, &amp; inward mortification, such humilitie and godlines: Nay, being men forfooth of perfection (<hi>Est enim hoc institutum virorū plane perfectorum: this our institution,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iohn Oso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius.</note> as the said Iesuit saith: <hi>is of such men as are indeed perfect:</hi>) they refuse not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding to accompanie the rest of the Cleargie both Secular Regular, and religious, and the whole Church of God in one of her most soleme and publique seruices done to his diuine Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, which we call our great and solemne processions: because that by the custome of the Church, they being the youngest and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest, or minimes of all Mendicants or begging Friers, were to haue come last behind all the rest in that most honourable seruice.</p>
   <p>But to come to our selues, &amp; to their affectation of superioritie ouer vs, and that in these dismal daies, &amp; in the middest of our other domesticall calamities. The Romane Colledge, for the bringing vp of students to become Priests for England, was no sooner erected, but by sleights and false calumniations, they got the superioritie and gouernement of it. Vpon their comming into England, how they laboured to creepe into mens consciences: to insinuate themselues into Nobles and great persons estates, and to discredit vs, many Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques
<pb facs="4"/>doe know: Wee our selues from time to time did easily find the smart and inconueniene of it: and many of vs to our friends haue oft bewayled and complayed with sighs and teares of such their vnchristian dealing with vs. Our brethren then prisoners at Wisbish, who for their vertue, constancie and most Christian Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique conuersation, &amp; maner of charitable proceeding in all their actions, had worthily merited the name, not onely of the visible, but also of the most afflicted Catholique Church in England: continued in that honour and reputation with all men, euen from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their duresse vntill some seauen or eight yeeres agon, that Frier <hi>Weston</hi> a Iesuit would needs be their superiour. Frier <hi>Garnet</hi> the prouinciall of the Iesuits in England, was in reasonable tune with some of our brethren (verie auncient, reuerend, and learned Priests) vntill they seemed to dislike this attempt of Frier <hi>Westons:</hi> and then he brake with them in such bitternes as he discouered himselfe verie manifestly: saying, <hi>That he saw no cause why the Secular Priests might not content themselues well ynough to be subiect to the Fathers of the Societie of Iesus,</hi> and added some loose reasons of that his asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. When both he and his subiect Frier <hi>Weston</hi> perceiued, that their plot was dasned at <hi>Wisbish,</hi> and how odious a thing it grew to be, that men who professe religiō should aspire to such an vnheard of superioritie; they wrought with their grand Captaine Frier <hi>Parsons,</hi> that what they could not worke one way, they might in effect com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe it by an other. And thence insued the authoritie of our R. Arch-Priest, procured by most indirect, vnlawfull and dishonest meanes. Which authoritie is so limited to the directions of the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suits, and as it were confined to their platformes, as whilest he is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ruled by them, and they by Frier <hi>Pasons:</hi> it had beene peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture better for vs in regard of our quietnes &amp; commoditie, that they thēselues had bin appointed our Commaunders, Gouernors &amp; good Maisters: for so hauing attayned directly to that which they aymed at, it is likely they would haue beene content. Whereas now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they want but onely the bare name of our Arch-Prelats; their minds are so inflamed against vs, as when we tooke exception at the manner of our Arch-Priests aduancement ouer vs, and held that course therein, which hath euer hitherto beene approued in the Church of God: who but the Iesuits that are wholly exmpted from our Arch-Priest authoritie, and ought to haue beene straungers in our affaires (had it not beene vnder-hand, their owne cause) did then, and euer since oppose themselues with might and mayne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst vs in that action?</p>
   <p>A principall Iesuit in Spayne telleth vs diuers straunge tales of this his Societie,<note place="margin">Iohn Oso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, in obi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu Ignatii.</note> which to our vnderstanding seeme to smell of worse matter, then we are willing to reueale at this present. Hee saith that: <hi>Ignace their founder, is the Angell of whom Saint</hi> Iohn <hi>spake, when he
<pb facs="5"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb facs="5"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb facs="6"/>said: Quintus Angelus tuba cecinit, The fift Angell sounded his trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet.</hi> Furthermore, alluding to another Text, he saith: <hi>That</hi> Ignatius <hi>is the wearie and weake Aegyptian, whom</hi> Dauid <hi>toke vp to fight the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels of our Lord:</hi> and addeth, that therefore, <hi>as the souldiers cried: Haec est praeda</hi> Dauid: <hi>this is the pray of</hi> Dauid: <hi>Ita nunc societas Vniuersa, quae a munds tyrannide liberata est, non praeda</hi> Ignatij; <hi>sed</hi> Dauidis <hi>dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, non societas</hi> Ignatij, <hi>sed societas Iesu nuncupatur: so now the whole Societie being deliuered from the tyrannie of the world, is not called the pray of</hi> Ignatius <hi>but of</hi> Dauid: <hi>not the Societie of</hi> Ignatius, <hi>but of Iesus.</hi> And the reason followeth: <hi>Quia eos in socios Christus admise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, because Christ had admitted them to be his fellowes.</hi> Afterwards also: <hi>Nemo ergo dicat: ego sum</hi> Pauli: <hi>ego sum Apollo: sed ego sum Christs: Let no man say, I hold of</hi> Paule: <hi>I of</hi> Apollo, <hi>but I hold of Christ. And let vs call our selues, the fellowes, not of</hi> Ignatius <hi>but of Christ.</hi> Also the same great Father affirmeth: that <hi>the Iesuits in Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugall, haue alreadie obtained the name of Apostles, and that this Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, hath so worthly laboured in Christ his vineyard: Vt Catholici omnes Iesuitae dicantur, eo quod Iesuitae eorum omnium duces ac Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistri sint: As that in these Northren parts of the world, al Catholiques are called Iesuits, because the Iesuits are the leaders of them all, and their Maisters.</hi> In like sort he is of opinion: that the fathers of this Societie, <hi>are the Angels Clouds, and Doues, whereof the Prophet</hi> Esay <hi>writeth,</hi> saying▪ <hi>Qui sunt isti qui vt nubes volant; &amp; quasi columbae ad fenestras suas? What Angels, are these that flie like Clouds, and as Doues to their windowes?</hi> And againe he saith: <hi>They are called Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, Angels, that is, Messengers: Eo quod maximarū rerum legatione fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantur: because they are Ambassadors of the greatest things or affairs amongst mortall men: Nubes, Clouds, for their swift obedience: and Columbae, Doues, quia fellis acerbitate caret haec pacifica societas Iesu, quo nihil admirabilius: for that this peaceable Societie of Iesus, hath no gall: asmuch to say, as it wanteth all bitternes of gall, splene, ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, malice and reuenge: which is as great a wonder as may be.</hi> But you will say: <hi>quorsum haec:</hi> what of all this: are you sillie men the persons that eyther wil or dare take vpon you to confute these things thus published in print by a Spaniard: nay, by so worthie a Iesuit: and preached for an intro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ction to make <hi>Ignatius</hi> a Saint, or at the least to paint him out for a man fit to be a Saint? Surely whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer we can or dare doe (if these follies doe not confute themselues sufficiently) we will not at this time expresse, as not intending to deale with many of them. But how true it is, that the name of Christians is abolished in these Northren Regions, and that we are all now termed Iesuits: and whether all other orders of Religion that retaine the names of their founders, are not here verie shrewdly taxed, and brought to be within the Apostles prohibition: we leaue it to your further consideration. Onely for the present we say thus
<pb facs="6"/>much: that let the Iesuits be trumpets, <hi>Dauids</hi> pray, Iesus compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, Angels and Clouds, or what else this fellow of theirs the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Iesuit would haue them, we much regard not: so as againe for our sakes he will be pleased to strike out the word Doues. For not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all the Texts, we doe not find them men of such Doue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like mindes, and speciall mortification as they doe make shew of, but haue their passions and distempered humors aswell as some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue. Marke we beseech you,<note place="margin">Ma. Lister.</note> how one of these Doues (if you will needs haue them so termed) doth write against vs in a little treatise not past two sheets of paper: because we onely forbore our obedience to our R. Arch-Priests verie straunge authoritie (as we then thought) till we might be further informed of his Holines plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure. He calleth vs <hi>Schismatikes, and men</hi> (by one of his inferences) <hi>to be cast into hell:</hi> factious persons, deiected with the griefe of our owne ruine: and saith that we haue lost our places amongst Priests: that we are banished from the holy alter and ministerie of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: that our iudgements are to be contemned, and that we are condemned of the holy Apostolique Church He termeth vs triflers, younglings in Diuinitie, fooles not to be regarded what we say: men that gather not with Christ: Newters, that doe belong to the diuided kingdome, which shall be destroyed, and rebels against the kingdome of Christ. He affirmeth further, that we are become Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks and prophane laicall persons: that we ought to be shunned and auoyded, as the Iewes did shunne in times past the publicans, notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; knowne sinners; and that we are infamous persons, nothing better then south sayers, wisards, &amp; Idolaters. And whereas amongst other things we alleadged, that his Holines, in erecting our Arch-Presbitership was misinformed: <hi>O mendacium: O notable lie</hi> (saith this milde Doue) and therwithall comes vpon vs againe. <hi>Quid?</hi> What (saith hee) <hi>Numquid factiosis istis licebit in re grauissima tam impune, tamque impudenter mentiri? Shall it be lawful for these factious persons, in a matter of most importance to lie so impudently and go vnpunished?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>There are also diuers other Pidgeons of this flight, that out of question eyther haue galles, or some other verie bitter matter in them, that is equiualent to any gall whatsoeuer: Frier <hi>Holthy</hi> in his long and tedious letter to a verie vertuous Catholique Ladie written against vs: Frier <hi>Garnet</hi> in sundrie of his letters both to some of vs, and also to others: Also Frier <hi>Parsons</hi> in his late Apologie: but es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in his (as we take it) last booke intituled: <hi>A manifestation of the great folly, and bad spirit of certaine Secular Priests, &amp;c.</hi> Some little taste we will giue you heere of these good Fathers mortified humour and verie meeke spirit, out of the said last booke. You haue heard the title of it: whereunto that the whole discourse might be sutable, he insinuateth directly in this preface, <hi>That we are in a sort possessed with many wicked spirits.</hi> And to seeme to
<pb facs="7"/>haue some authoritie for it: hee applieth these words of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Christ vnto vs, where he saith thus. <hi>The vncleane spirit went forth, &amp; brought with him seuen other spirits more wicked then him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, and all entring, dwelt there: and the ending of those men was worse then the beginning.</hi> Of sixe of these diuels the chiefe substance of all his booke doth consist; and therefore he nameth them direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before he commeth to his discourse, and setteth them downe in expresse words. for the contents of his treatise. Wherein his whole drift is, to slaunder more honest men then himselfe, and to mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leade and seduce you: as though whatsoeuer the Secular Priests haue written, in such bookes, as they haue beene inforced this yeere past to publish, for their owne iust defence against the Iesuits calumniations, and bad dealings with them, did proceed onely from their folly: accompanied alwaies with one of these sixe lying spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. For example, and to vse his owne words: <hi>From their manifest folly &amp; bad spirit: from their folly &amp; passionate spirirt: from their folly and presumptuous spirit: from their folly and vnshamefast spirit: from their folly and malignant spirit, and from their folly and decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued spirit.</hi> With this folly and these sixe wicked spirits, he raiseth vp tempests against vs by Sea and land, and playeth the Exorcist: in such sort throughout his whole discourse: as if hee had beene Frier <hi>Weston</hi> (another Pidgeon of the same Doue-coate) at Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, when the time was (whereof wee feare a straunge rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) and so dealeth with our said brethren, as though eyther hee himselfe or they (good men) were diuels indeed. And shall wee say that this man hath no gall in him, but in mildnesse of his speech and simplicitie of his heart is like a Doue? Hee that shall with anie iudgement read his said treatise, will rather thinke he was brought vp in a Crowes-nest. Some men are much deceiued, if both he and many of his crue: might not for their stinging and poysoned writings, be better resembled to Hornets and Dragons, then to so milde a fowle as a Doue is reported to be, by all that write of her.</p>
   <p>But certaine persons will say vnto vs: you see not that part of the wallet that hangs at your owne backes. It is true, that wee are not ignorant how greatly some of our said brethren are blamed, and Maister <hi>Watson</hi> chiefely by many of you (how iust soeuer their cause bee) for the bitternesse of their stile; and we wish with all our hearts, that they had tempered their pennes better, not in respect of the Iesuits, but of your weakenes. God forgiue vs all our sinnes. <hi>In multis enim offendimus omnes: For in many things wee offend all. Si quis in verbo non offendit hic perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus est vir: If any offend nor in his speeches, he is a perfect man.</hi> But yet some further defence may be made of our brethrens said bitternes: mens generall imperfections alwaies considered, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we often stayne euen our best actions.</p>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <p>It must bee confessed by all men that are of any vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, that sharpenesse eyther of speech or style, is not alwaies to bee disliked. The olde Prophets, Christ himselfe, his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, many holy Saints and Fathers; haue vsed this kind of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes and sharpe writing when they saw cause. To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose much might be alleadged, as also to shewe that oftentimes, wounds are better then kisses, fretting tents, corasiues, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisions, more needfull then gentle, milde, lenitiue, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hastie skinning plaisters. So as hereof there being no question amongst vs, or any other of discretion: the doubt then is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Iesuits or we haue the better cause: and consequently, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of vs may better pretend the testimonie of Gods Spirit, a good conscience, true zeale, perfect charitie, and the practise of Christ, of his Apostles, and of many auncient fathers, for the sharpenes of our writings.</p>
   <p>Maister <hi>Parsons</hi> speaketh (in his said manifestation) of his owne long and accustomed practise and experience: where he saith: <hi>That an euill argument may sometimes by cunning and smooth handling, or by shewing wit &amp; learning, of zeale or modesty, be made plausible to the vulgar Reader.</hi> And indeed therein he hath an especiall gift aboue all men that we know. For no mans writings are generally more spightfull and galling then his. But it is mixt with such stoods of Crocodils teares, when he guirdeth most, as that, he then alwaies pretendeth such deuotion and charitie, as though euerie hard word he vseth, went to his verie heart: and that hee would not deale so roughly with any of his brethren for his life, were it not, that (for their good and amendement) hee were driuen thereunto of meere necessitie. And with these fayre pretences, the simpler sort are greatly blinded. But by his leaue, it is also as certain, that if a true cause be cleerely and at the full deliuered, although it be done with no such hypocritical skill, but with some choller and heat of humour (as zeale sometime is tearmed:) he is but likewise a verie vulgar Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and of a shallow reach, that will therefore be led to discredit the truth vpon so light a ground. Men of sound iudgement will alwaies looke to the issue of the matter in question, and not to the manner of pleading. More therefore of the cause it selfe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon this doubt before mentioned doth arise. Wee hope we may truly say it, as in the sight of God, and without all pharisaical ostenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that we are not ambitious: that we seeke no exemptions from our lawfull superiour: that we honour discipline and embrace it: that we craue to haue Bishops to ouer-see, punish, &amp; control vs whē we doe amisse: and that we labour chiefly in these disastrous quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels, to withstand so great an innouation &amp; general disgrace to all the Seculer Cleargie in Christendome, as neuer yet hapned, if we should yeeld to be at the checke and direction either of Frier <hi>Garnet,</hi> Frier
<pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>Parsons,</hi> or any, or all the Iesuits in the world. And wee are the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther so earnest against both them and their plottings to this purpose: because we likewise know their further practises and most wicked designements, against both our Prince and country, &amp; how they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged thēselues with the Spaniards, her Maiesties professed enemies. So as might the Iesuits once beare rule ouer al both Priests &amp; people (as let the state look to it in time, for they haue further preuailed here in alreadie then we are glad of:) it would not be long before this kingdom were brought into a general cōbustion. Is our cause then so iust, and theirs so impious, and should we be silent? Doe they say vnto vs with <hi>Tobias</hi> the Ammonite: <hi>That do what you can, a Foxe shall be able to ouerthrow all your opposition:</hi>
      <note place="margin">z. Esdras. 4.</note> The <hi>Infanta</hi> of Spaine shall be your Queene, and that sooner then you looke for: and shall we not say as it is there in the Text? <hi>Auds Deus noster quia facti su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus despectui: conuerte opprobrium super caput eorum, &amp; da eos in des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectionem in terra captiuitatis. Heare vs O our God, heare vs: and because they doe despise vs and our endeuours, to maintayne both the Church and our countrey against their machinations, giue them ouer that they may be a despised and contemptible generation throughout all the world if in time they repent not.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Can any true harted English Catholick, seeing how the case nowe standeth betwixt vs and these men, be iustly offended with this our zeale? Hath God made vs annoynted priests here amongst you, <hi>and shal we see a sword drawne out against this Land, and not sounde out our trumpet to sumon you to battell?</hi> One telleth you verie plainlie in his Latine Appendix (and we suppose it is our R. Arch-priest him selfe) <hi>that Cardinall Allen and Father Parsons, as Moses and Iosue, iam diu proculdubio occupassent promissionis terram: had long since out of doubt possessed this Realme of England: nisi quorundam inobedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia atque ingratissimum obstitisset murmur: had not the disobedience of some, and theyr most displeasing murmuring hindred it.</hi> It is the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of our English Iesuits, and of such as are Iesuited, neuer to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Frier <hi>Parsons</hi> trecheries, but they ioyne that good Cardinall with him, to mittigate the odiousnes of his proceedings. But howe coulde they haue gotten this land of Promise into their fingers? Meane they by their attempt 1588? or had they before this time layd violent hands vpon her Maiestie? or what had they else doone, if some such impediment as they speake of had not hapned? Blessed was that disobedience, and happy was that murmuring, that deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this kingdome from such vncatholick and most trayterous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signements. Rather content your selues deere Catholicks to goe &amp; dwell in Babilon: then euer seeke to obtaine the Land of Canaan by such cruell, barbarous, and Turkish stratagems. Are not such Iesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its or persons whatsoeuer Iesuited, worthy to be detested, that dare publish their dislike of such disobedience and murmure, as hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented
<pb facs="8"/>such a Chaos of all mischiefes, as the conquering of our lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle land of promise would haue brought with it? Or if we haue been too sharpe in our encountering of the Gyants (as they falsly terme vs) are we not to be excused?</p>
   <p>And as wee woulde haue you to iudge of vs and the rest of our brethren, that whatsoeuer they haue written, it proceeded of theyr loue and zeale both to our Church and Countrie: so our hartie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire is, that you would thinke and iudge the like of those right zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Catholicks of other Countries, that haue written against the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suits in the like respect, much more sharply then any of our brethren hetherto haue done. For howe highlie soeuer the Iesuits are yet in our bookes, because you know them not throughlie: yet are they alreadie become an odious generation in manie places. In the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Swecia, their verie names are detested. The Cleargie of Spayne is in great dislike of them. The religious men generallie in all countries doe hate them. At this instant, there is a great &amp; most dangerous contention in particuler, betwixt them and the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans, about a speciall point of grace. At their first attempt to come into Fraunce, it was fore-seen by the graue Sorbonists of Paris, what mischiefe they would work if they were admitted there. Afterwards, they crept into that countrie like Foxes by little and little, and so in processe of time behaued thēselues, as not long since they haue been banished thence, as men of most pernitious, wicked, and dangerous conuersation. You haue heard in a word or two, out of <hi>Osorius</hi> the Spaniard, what the Iesuits thinke of themselues: it woulde make a large volume to recount the praises which they haue else-where hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped vppon their founder, their societie, &amp; their fellowes; according as the saying is: Claw me and I will claw thee. You also vnderstand as well by the premises, as by our bretherens seuerall treatises, what estimation we haue of them, and some haue beene offended vvith them for their plainenes therein. But now wee humbly intreate you to obserue, howe roundly they haue beene taken vp in Fraunce for halting, by men of no small credite in that State; for theyr yeres ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie auncient, for their experience verie wise, and for their soundnes in the Catholicke Romane religion, neuer impeached by any but Iesuits, who condemne all men eyther for Newters or schismaticks, or hereticks, or at the least for cold and luke-warme Catholicks, that disclose their impieties.</p>
   <p>Maister <hi>Anthony Arnold,</hi> counsellour in parliament, and heereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore counsellor and Atturney generall to the late deceased Queene mother, a man throughlie acquainted with the proceedings of the Iesuits in Fraunce, writeth as followeth, both of them,<note place="margin">By this the Iesuits are discouered to be not onely the fore-runners but also the chiefe cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of Antechrist; out of whose societie or sect, it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry probable <hi>homo peccati,</hi> that man of sin shall rise, ere all be ended be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular priests &amp; them the saide secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Iesuits, though for the present they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke.</note> and somwhat of their Founder. <hi>Ignatius</hi> (saith he) through the help of the deuill, hatched this cursed conspiracie of the Iesuits: who haue beene the causes of such ruine as Fraunce hath receiued. They are a vvicked
<pb facs="9"/>race, borne to the ruine &amp; desolation of mankinde. In their fourth vowe to their Generall, they goe thus farre, that in him they must acknowledge Christ present, as it were, If Iesus Christ should com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund to goe and kill, they must doe so. The Generall of the Iesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its is alwayes a Spanyard, and chosen by the King of Spayne. <hi>Loyola</hi> their first Generall was a Spanyard, <hi>Laynes</hi> the second a Spanyard also. The third, <hi>Euerardus,</hi> was a Fleming, a subiect of the King of Spayne. <hi>Borgia,</hi> the fourth, was a Spanyard. <hi>Aquauiua</hi> the fift, now liuing, is a Neopolitane, subiect to the King of Spayne. If their Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Generall commaund them to murther, or cause the King of Fraunce to be murthered, they must of necessity do it. They shoote at no other matter, but to establish the tyrannie of Spaine in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. All the Iesuits in the world, are bound to pray for the King of Spayne, and that once a day, as his affayres doe require. They haue stirring fellowes to be placed in all quarters, to execute whatsoeuer may tend to the good and aduauncement of Spayne. They had no other marke during the warres in Fraunce: but to make the King of Spaine Monarch ouer all Christendome. The common prouerbe of these hypocrits is: one God, one Pope: and one king of Spaine, the great King catholick and vniuersall. All their thoughts, all their purposes, all their Sermons, all their cōfessions, haue no other white they ayme at, but to bring all Europe vnder the subiection of Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish gouernment. The Ambassadour of Fraunce, when hee was in Spayne and Italie, neuer found matter of weight wherein they had not an oare. There was neuer Letter intercepted during the warres, wherein there was anie pernicious point, but a Iesuits singer was in it. In their confessions and without witnesses, they paint not the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but the harts of their schollers, with the tincture of Rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their princes and naturall Soueraignes.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Mathew</hi> a Iesuit, was the principal instrument of the League 1585. And from that yeere 1585. they would giue no absolution to the Gentry of Fraunce, vnlesse they would vow &amp; promise to band themselues against their Soueraigne (<hi>Henry</hi> the third) being a most catholick King. <hi>Barnard</hi> and <hi>Commolet,</hi> (the yere before the sayde League) called the King <hi>Holofornes, Moab,</hi> and <hi>Nero:</hi> maintaining that the kingdome of Fraunce was electiue, and that it belonged to the people to establish kings: &amp; alledging this text of the old Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: <hi>Thou shalt chuse thy brother for King.</hi> Thy brother (say they) that is to say, not of the same linage, or of the selfe same Nation, but of the same Religion, as is this great catholick king, this great King of Spaine. The said <hi>Commolet</hi> was so impudent and bold, as to say verie blasphemously, that vnder these words: <hi>Deliuer me O Lord out of the myer, that I may not sticke in it: Dauid</hi> vnderstood pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetically, the rooting out of the house of Burbon. The same Iesuit also, <hi>Commolet,</hi> preaching at the Bastile before the Gentlemen that
<pb facs="9"/>were then prisoners in the beginning of the yeere 1589, saide vnto them, after a thousand impudent blasphemies: that he that had been their King, was not their King, plotting from thence the murther which they executed afterwards. What voyce is sufficient to expresse the secrete counsells, the most horrible conspiracies, more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous then the conspiracies of <hi>Cateline,</hi> which were holden in the Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>suits Colledge in S. <hi>Iames</hi> streete? Where did the Agents and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadours of Spayne, <hi>Mendoza, Daguillon, Diego, Dinarra, Taxis, Feria,</hi> and others, hold their secret meetings and assemblies, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Iesuits? Where did <hi>Lowchard. Ameliue, Cruce, Crome,</hi> &amp; such like notorious manquellers and murtherets, build their conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies but amongst the Iesuits? Who made that bloody aunswere to the catholick Apologie, but the Iesuits? Where did the two Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals which termed themselues Legats in Fraunce assemble theyr counsels but onely amongst the Iesuits? Where was it that <hi>Mendo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za</hi> (the Embassadour of Spayne) vpon All-hollow day, in the yeere 1589. (at what time the King entred the Fauxburges) helde his counsaile, of Sixteene, but in the Colledge of the Iesuits? Who was President of the counsell (afterwards) of those Sixteene murtherers, but <hi>Commolet, Bernard,</hi> and Father <hi>Ode Pickenar</hi> the vilest Tygar in all Paris? <hi>Commelet</hi> preaching in S. <hi>Bartholmewes</hi> church after the murther of the King, exalted and placed among the Angels this Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, this deuill incarnate, <hi>Iames Clement,</hi> the murderer. Who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed all their studies to speake against the person and right of his Maiestie that now raigneth, as false and slaunderous matters, as pos<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sibly their wicked heads could deuise, but the Iesuits? <hi>Commol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s</hi> the Iesuit (when he preached at Saint <hi>Bartholmes,</hi> as is aforesaid) tooke for his theame the third chapter of the booke of Iudges, where it is reported, that <hi>Ehud</hi> slew the king of Moab, and escaped away: and after that he had discoursed at large vpon the death of their late king (and commended <hi>Iames Clement</hi>) he fell into a great exclamation: saying, we haue neede of an <hi>Ehud,</hi> we haue neede of an <hi>Ehud:</hi> were he a Frier, were he a souldier, were he a lackie, were he a shepard, it made no great matter. Needs wee must haue an <hi>Ehud:</hi> One blowe would settle vs fully in the state of our affaires, as we most desire.</p>
   <p>Alas, their purpose and burning zeale is, to murder the King li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. Was it not in the Colledge of Iesuits at Lyons, and also in the Colledge of Iesuits in Paris, that the resolution was last taken to murder the King in August 1593? Are not the depositions of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riere</hi> (executed at Melun) notorious to all the world? Was it not <hi>Varade,</hi> Principall of the Iesuits, that exhorted and incouraged this murtherer; assuring him that he could not do a more merritorious worke in the worlde, then to murther the King though hee were a Catholick: and that for this deede he should goe straight to Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise? And to confirme him the more in this mischieuous resolution,
<pb facs="10"/>did hee not cause him to be confessed by an other Iesuit? Did not these impious, godlesse, and execrable murderers, giue this <hi>Baerriere</hi> the blessed sacrament, imploying the most holy, most precious, and most sacred misterie of our Christian religion, towards the murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the chiefest King in Christendome.</p>
   <p>As long as the Iesuits remaine in Fraunce, the king of Spaines murtherers, may be exhorted, confessed, housled and incouraged. Their minds are bloodie, &amp; altogether imbrued with the blood of the late murthered king. They filled the pulpits with fire, with blood, with blasphemies: making the people belieue that God was a murtherer of kings, &amp; attributing to heauen, the stroke of a knife forged in hell. The highest poynt of their honour, standeth in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting of murthers, terming them Martyrs which haue spent their liues therein. They are mischieuous counsailors, traytors, wicked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntors, firebrands of mischiefe, hypocrits, monsters, watchfull in mischiefe, diligent in wickednes, wretched caytiffes, manquellers, serpents, pernicious, and dangerous vermine, and haue no fellowes in all sorts of wickednes.</p>
   <p>And hetherto Maister <hi>Arnold</hi> dispersedly. Vnto whom wee may adde a short, but a notable description of the Iesuits ordinary ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons (as we take it) out of <hi>Petrus Gregorius Tholossanus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pet. Greg de Repub. lib. <hi>13.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi>
      </note> (a great Lawier and a sound Catholick:) which doth so expresly and pithilie set them out vnto vs, nay to all posteritie, and that in so few words, their dispositions, pride and furie, as hee that shall diligently reade them, and throughlie digest them, may euer carrie with him (if his memorie be not verie dull) the right Idea of a perfect Iesuit. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he cōmeth to this description, he first setteth downe the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God against all such kinde of persons, out of king <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> and the prophet <hi>Ezechiell. Abominatio est Domini, omnis arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantia. All that are arrogant</hi> (without exception) <hi>are abhominable vnto our Lord.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Prou. 16.</note>
      <hi>Contritionem praecedit superbia &amp;c. Pride goeth before contrition or destruction: and a high minde before vtter ruine. Vae pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storibus Israell:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ezech. 34.</note>
      <hi>woe be to the Sheppards of Israell, &amp;c. That which was weake ye haue not strengthened: that which was sicke, ye haue not hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: that which was broken, yee haue not bound vp: &amp; That which was abiected, yee haue not brought againe: and that which was lost ye haue not sought: sed cum austeritate imperabatis eis et cum potentia: but ye did rule ouer them with austeritie and force or potencie.</hi> Secondly, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing made this way plaine to his purpose, then hee sheweth further what manner of men the Cleargie, by the testimonies of S. <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; S. <hi>Paule</hi> should be: and how farre from such haughtines of minde, such pride and crueltie: and with what diligence, mildnes, &amp; gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, they ought to proceede in the actions and proceedings which doe belong to their calling. <hi>Feede</hi> (saith S. <hi>Peter</hi>) <hi>the flocke of Christ which is amongst you: ouerseeing them not by constraint, but willingly
<pb facs="10"/>according to God: neither for filthie lucre sake, but voluntarily.</hi> And S. <hi>Paule: The seruaunt of God must not wrangle, but be mild towards all men, apt to teach, patient, with modestie, admonishing them that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist the truth, least sometimes God giue them repentance to knowe the truth. &amp;c.</hi> Against which Apostolicall rules, hee declareth that the Iesuits (of whom we thinke he speaketh) be great practitioners, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sorting themselues in the ranke of those that <hi>Salomon</hi> and the prophet <hi>Ezechiell</hi> before spake of, then of the true Pastors of Gods people.</p>
   <p>These are his words: <hi>In quo hodie maxime peccant noui quidā Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logastri, et zelo se traduci mentiuntur: qui in cathedris non verba mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destie au: verba dei, sed fulgura, tonitrua vomunt: dicteria, s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ōmata, gladios, ignes, furores, Megaras, cruenta, neces debacchantur: vt potius maledicos, furiosos, dementes coniuratores, seditiosos, inuidos pacis chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianae, milites, praedones, latrones, quam Euangelicae veritatis predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores, et enarratores dixeris: similes pastoribus ijs, qui austeritate impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re volunt, qui putant oues potius necandas, quam adgregem cum leni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate reuocandas: cum tamen dictum sit de eodem Euangelio, (cuius se enarratores esse mentiuntur eadem superbia) quod ea sit lex gratiae, et cū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misericordia Christique beneficio et bonitate publicata. Sed nihil est im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudentius arrogantiae rusticorum qui garrulitatem Authoritatem putant, et parati ad lites tumidi in subiectos intonant. Hoc habet proprium doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trina arrogantium: vt humiliter nesciant inferre, quod docent: et recta quae sapiunt, recte ministare non possint &amp;c. Atque statutum, seditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narios nunquam ordinandos clericos, et ordinatoi deijciend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s.</hi> Wherein (that is to say, both against the prophets and Apostles doctrine) cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine new smattering Diuines now adaies, doe verie greatlie offend, who falslie pretend that they are led by zeale, who in their pulpits &amp; Lectures cast out, not words of modestie, or of the word of God, but lightnings and thunderings: who as outragious men in rayling, vtter nothing but taunts, scoffes, swords, fires, rages, furies of hell, matters of blood and murtherings. So as a man may rather terme them cursed speakers, furious persons, mad men, traytors, seditious declamers, enemies of Christian peace, souldiers, robbers, the eues, then preachers and expounders of the Euangelicall truth, being like those pastors that will commaund with seueritie, that rather think it meete to haue their sheepe killed, then to haue them with mildnes recalled to the flocke. VVhereas notwithstanding it is saide of the gospell (whereof lyinglie they call themselues expositors with the same pride) that it is a lawe of grace and published with the mercie, bountie, &amp; goodnes of Christ. But there is nothing more impudent then the arrogancie of base companions, who account their prating a kind of authoritie, and being readie to quarrell, they tyrannise o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer such as are subiect vnto them. The doctrine of arrogant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons hath this property, that they cannot deliuer with humilitie those
<pb facs="11"/>things which they teach; nor minister rightly their honest conceits. Now there is a statute, that stirrers vp of sedition should not be made Clergie men: and that such as are made alreadie, should be degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And thus <hi>Peter Gregorius.</hi> Whereby you may see, that wee are not the onely men that haue whetted their penns against the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suits: nor yet that we haue written halfe so bitterlie as others haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them. It is to be wished, that you woulde take these thinges to hart, &amp; apply them to the Iesuits proceedings vnderhand in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, but more apparantlie in Ireland. There is an old lesson which children learne among their rules in Schoole, and is fit for all persons, times and seasons: <hi>Foelix quem faciunt aliena pericula cantum:</hi> hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie are they whom other mens harmes doe make to beware. Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>Arnold,</hi> and <hi>Pet: Gregorius,</hi> haue saide sufficient to make all the states in Europe that are not hispanized, to take heede of these fellowes and of their designements. And yet such is their plotting, and Fox-like wilines, as by swearing and forswearing, by fawning and flattering, &amp; by a thousand other sleights, they so inueigle men and women that be of any good or honorable disposition: that an other very singuler wise man of high authoritie, and a sound Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, hath thought it very necessarie, to adde much to that which Maister <hi>Arnold,</hi> and <hi>Pet: Greg.</hi> haue written: that thereby all men, especiallie of state and action, may be inexcusable, if either they themselues, or the state wherein they serue, doe euer heereafter take harme by the Iesuits.</p>
   <p>The treatise which hee hath written to this purpose, is intituled, THE IESVITS CATECHISME; so termed as wee thinke, to distinguish their newe deuises, instructions, &amp; plottings, from the sinceritie of the auncient and approued forme of Christes Catechisme, which the Church of Rome hetherto hath taught. In this discourse, the Iesuits and their proceedings are more throughlie sifted, and that <hi>ab incunabilis,</hi> from their verie cradle. By reason whereof, all these things falling out at the beginning so badly, and sorting still from worse to worse; the Author of this Treatise is dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen oftentimes in the heate of his zeale, to lay aside his skill in Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick (which is very excellent:) and for the discharge of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science to God, and the dutie he oweth to his countrey, as also for a caueat vnto all other countries, to deale very plainly: calling men and matters by their owne names, without any circumlocution or ambigu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie. He that hath eates to heare, let him heare. This gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman is farre from the said Spanish Iesuits conceit, either of <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> himselfe, or of his Order.</p>
   <p>As touching <hi>Ignatius,</hi> he saith, <hi>that although for his learning hee was but an Asse:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Fol. 42.</note>
      <hi>yet otherwise, he was one of the cūningst worldlings that this our latter age hath brought sorth: &amp; in deed a very Imposture.</hi> And vvhereas great account is made of his illuminations,<note place="margin">Fol. 39.</note> visions,
<pb facs="11"/>inspirations, extasies, (wherein the blessed Virgin and Christ him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe talked with him,) diuine instructions, (opening to him the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries of the blessed Trinitie, and of the holy Scriptures:) all these contēplations (saith he) <hi>Were meere mummeries or illusions of the diuell,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Fol. 29.</note>
      <hi>who desired to present vs with such a man, as might by his ignorance trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the whole state of the Church.</hi> The said <hi>Osorius</hi> the Iesuit, hauing in the largest size commended <hi>Ignatius</hi> his founder: ascribeth it as a speciall point of appertayning to his further praise, that he left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him schollers of his owne mould, who like waxe, frame them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to beare his expresse image. To which purpose there is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie fit Text sought out in these words: <hi>Mortuus est pater eius,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eccles. 30.</note>
      <hi>&amp; quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>si non est mortuus, similem enim reliquit sibi post se. His father it dead, and yet he is as if he were not dead, because he hath left bebind him one like to himselfe.</hi> According to which Text, the said Gentleman in his sense sheweth very apparantly the great resemblance bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wixt <hi>Ignatius</hi> and his ofspring, and writeth of them, their whole order, their qualities, and proceedings, as heere in part it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sueth.</p>
   <p>They are of the Societie of Iesus, as <hi>Iudas</hi> was amongst the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles: so many Iesuits, so many <hi>Iudases,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Fol. 23.</note> readie to betray their Princes or their countries whensouer occasion serues to doe it. What will you giue vs, will be the burthen of their song to those Princes that haue most money, and we will deliuer our Liege-Lord into your hands, or trouble his State, that it may be yeelded to you? Iesuitisme breeds many complaints among the people: many iarres,<note place="margin">Fol. 13.</note> dissentions, contentions, rebellions, and sundry schismes.<note place="margin">Fol. 10.</note> There was neuer any sect more dangerous to Christian Religion then this of the Iesuits. The diuell vnder the habit of the Iesuits, doth goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to circumuent all the world. The Sect of the Iesuits is,<note place="margin">Fol. 48.</note> a ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stard religion, and a verie hoch-poch of all religious orders,<note place="margin">Fol. 55.</note> without any thing pure in it, or any point of the auncient Church. The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine seruice of their Church, is diuided from ours,<note place="margin">Fol. 13.</note> their priuiledges make a diuision betweene the Bishops and them, the Monasteries and them: the Vniuersities and them: the diuines of Paris and them. Their propositions, make a diuision betweene the holy Sea and Princes. Their Colledges are trappes to catch youth: there confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, subornations: their Sermons Mountebanks Markets.<note place="margin">Fol. 106.</note> Their whole profession is nothing else but a particular coozning of our pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate families, and a generall villany in all the countries where they inhabit.</p>
   <p>To receiue Iesuits into a kingdome, is to receiue in a vermine: which at length will gnaw out the heart of the State both spirituall and temporall.<note place="margin">Fol 62.</note> They worke vnder-hand the ruines of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes where they dwell,<note place="margin">Fol. 59.</note> and the murther of whatsoeuer Kings and Princes it pleaseth them. The name of the Iesuits,<note place="margin">Fol. 20.12.</note> ought to be odious
<pb facs="12"/>amongst all Christians: and they blaspheme against the honour of God, when they so intitle themselues. Without wrong to the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the holy Sea,<note place="margin">Fol. 56.</note> you may call the Iesuits, Papelards, and their Sect, Pape-lardy: that is, hypocrites, and their order hypocrisie. The Iesuits are Fox-like,<note place="margin">Fol 76.</note> &amp; Lion-like. Al their worthy works are but cooz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages. In all their negotiations in France,<note place="margin">Fol. 79.</note> an Asle &amp; a Fox haue been tied together.<note place="margin">Fol. 17.</note> Iesuits when they lie, doe say, it is to bee borne with: because it is to a good end.<note place="margin">Fol 41.</note> All things (saith the Iesuit) are to be taken for good,<note place="margin">Fol. 82.</note> that are done to a good end. It is a Iesuiticall priuiledge, to vnderset their slanders with the time,<note place="margin">Fol. 19.</note> by new cogs. In euery matter be it neuer so smal, the Iesuit cannot go by without lying &amp; disguising. The Iesuits neuer lacke new lying inuentions to aduance their owne credit.<note place="margin">Fol. 21.</note> One <hi>Iustinian</hi> a Iesuit, being found in Rome to be a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfait, it marred the Iesuits cookery there: for when they did speak of a facer out of matters and an impostor, they were wont to call him, a second <hi>Iustinian</hi> the Iesuit.</p>
   <p>Much more might be here added of the particular heresies wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he chargeth the Iesuits: also his freenes of speech, <hi>in tearming the first ten Iesuits,</hi> Ignatius &amp; <hi>his nine fellowes, to haue bin in their times verie cheaters:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Fol. 39.</note> and likewise how he proueth, <hi>that in the first allowance of their whole order, and the getting since of their priuiledges, they euer vsed cooznage,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Fol. 38.</note>
      <hi>obreption, and surreption.</hi> But this may suffice to be inserted in a Letter dedicatorie,<note place="margin">Fol. 103.</note> aswell to giue you a glympse what the demerits, of the Iesuits are in France, &amp; how they are esteemed of amongst the Catholiques there, that draw not with the line of Spaine against their Soueraigne: as also in a sort, to stop their clamorous mouthes and pens that crie out and write so eagerly, against the tartnes of all the bookes which haue beene lately set out by some of our brethren: and especially the <hi>Quodlibets:</hi> as though neuer learned men, being good Catholiques, had vsed the like sharpenes of stile be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them: or euer would vse after them. Which immoderate cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, both of the Iesuits, and of their adherents, together with the consident iustification of all the proceedings which hane beene plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and executed against vs and our brethren, by Frier <hi>Parsons:</hi> Frier <hi>Garnet,</hi> our R. Arch-Priest, and other their Iesuited clawbacks, (as though they were indeed Apostolical men sent lately from God that could not erre (in a manner in their course) by reason of a certaine subordination, and sundrie illuminations that are talked of among them:) caused vs when we met with this discourse, and with a trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of it: after that we had perused the translation, and amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it in diuers parts, not onely to put it to the presse, but to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it also vnto you (that without new fanglenes are truly Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques) with this our Preface or Epistle dedicatorie.</p>
   <p>The author of this <hi>Iesuiticall Catechisme,</hi> is for his vertue, graui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, experience, wisedome, Catholique zeale, and great learning, in
<pb facs="12"/>these causes, so imminent, where he is best knowne: and this his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course is so sutable to such his vertues, so substantiall for the matter, so eloquent for the phrase, so artificially compiled for the method, as neyther of them both haue any need, eyther of ours or any other mens commendation. If the translation doe content you: if the publishing of it may benefit you: if this our Apologeticall preface, or the booke it selfe, or both, may be a sufficient warning, eyther to you, or to the state, or to her Maiesties subiects generally; or to all, or to any good men in particular (that loue their Queene and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey:) to take heed in time of the Iesuits: to beleeue them by des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, to trust them no further then they see them: to detest their statizing: to loath their detractions, and to beware of their Forges: (that are euer occupied in hammering out stratageme after stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageme, the second still more pestilent then the first:) it is all wee looke for, besides your Catholique supportation due to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Priests in times of necessitie, &amp; your daily and Christian pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: whereunto we commend our selues, and you all, by our daily supplications, to Gods mercifull gouernment for your protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to all his heauenly graces for your direction, progression, and happie consummation through our Lord Iesus Christ. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your friends alwaies readie <hi>to doe you seruice.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>