<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PROEME.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114484_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18909</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5331</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114484</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PROEME.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Bibliotheca theologica: or, a librarye theological : containinge, 1. A generall analysis or resolution: 2. A breife elucidation off the most sacred chapters off Elohim his Bible: drawen for the vse of yonge Christians, specially off the poorer sorte, vnable to purchase variety off holy-men theyr wrytinges: by Henoch Clapham. Nihil primum perfectum</title>
                 <author>Clapham, Henoch</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 28 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PROEME.</head>
   <p>HAlfe A yeare togither was I ernestly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>ted to vndergoe the <hi>Analysinge</hi> of God his sacred Booke / and that but for the first heads off the Chapters. For so long tyme I refused that attempt / though much was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for promouinge the work / yet that helpe beinge cut off / I finally tooke pen and did som what soc. But then thinkinge with my selfe that such A generall <hi>Diuision</hi> wold litle helpe without som <hi>Sub-diuision,</hi> I therefore sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuided som chapters. Yet me thought / it shold litle to edify / except from obscure places in the text were made cleare / where vpon I finally drewe an <hi>Elucidation</hi> / such as it is.</p>
   <p>At this my work I looke that may shold storme: disdayners off all mens wrytinges but theyr owne: specially / the Hereticall sort off people: and no Maruel though Satā bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loe from theyr mouths / seinge my Pen is as A Goade in his sudes. Carpers do prophane and snatch som times at <hi>Manner,</hi> somtymes at <hi>Matter.</hi> For the Manner / I expect theyr snar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings specially at the Diuision: som curiously as tyingme me to <hi>Dichotomie</hi> or <hi>partition into tvvo:</hi> others that lesse delite in that <hi>forme,</hi> fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge me for vsing it somuch. Betwene them both I haue here walked / that so I might sans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sy both <hi>partly,</hi> whome I knewe it to be impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible to satisfy <hi>vvholy.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For the <hi>Matter,</hi> som will snarle at som fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we <hi>vvords,</hi> som at <hi>Doctrine.</hi> Off such doth <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rasmus</hi> speake thus in his <hi>Antidore</hi> on <hi>Hieroms</hi> epistle to <hi>Heliodore: His mos est, è toto libro quatuor aut quinque verba decerpere &amp;c. It is the manner off these persons to pick 4. or 5. vvords out off A vvhole booke, and in thes to shoe by calumnie the excellency off theyr Ingene. They animaduert not in vvhat tymes, to vvome, ō vvhat occasion, vvith vvhat mynde that man vvrit; nor do they conferre vvhat preceded, vvhat folovves, vvhat in another place is vvriten on the same mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Only they vrge and presse them 4. vvords: Against them they moue all their syllogisticall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines: they vvrythe, depraue, and somtimes speak euell of the thinges they vnderstand not.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Off this which <hi>Erasmus</hi> speakes / I off ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience can speake this: In my <hi>Bibles</hi> breife / I said that <hi>Elohim</hi> was the plurall off <hi>El:</hi> and to the proper Name <hi>Ehjeh,</hi> I suffired, <hi>I AM.</hi> In Scotland the learned excepted not against it that I heard of: Mr. <hi>Brought on</hi> as sufficient for the holy tongue as any publikely knowen off in <hi>Europe</hi> / he also could read it without stumblinge: but 2. or 3. englis he youths som off them hardly knowinge <hi>Beth</hi> from A Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le dor / they behinde my hath because of them two words / did labour the disgrace off Author and his booke.</p>
   <p>They (for I will not turne my speach to them though I speake off them) did not for the first vnderstand (or wold not vnderstand) what like scholers and Christians charitable / they might haue vnderstood. When Hebrue <hi>Lexicons</hi> or Grammarians do say that <hi>Iehouah</hi> is deriued off <hi>hajah, To be,</hi> do they speak properly? <hi>Hajah</hi> is not properly <hi>to be:</hi> but <hi>he hath bene:</hi> yet euery scholer knoweth what the speach meaneth: so thei might haue thought that I ment <hi>Elohim</hi> the plurall came off <hi>El</hi> his Roote: off which <hi>El</hi> commeth also <hi>Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ha</hi> his singular. That <hi>Elohim</hi> is said to com off <hi>El</hi> in english <hi>Strong,</hi> it so giues vs rightly to conceiue both <hi>Elohlm</hi> and <hi>Eloha</hi> his singular in direct forme off Declenson. And as I spoke it / it helped to the vnderstanding off Gen 17. 1. where tis <hi>El-shaddai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> God alsufficient: not <hi>Eloah-shaddaj:</hi> and so off many other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The Declenson-deriual / no Child that had bene two days lessoned in his Declensons could de possibly ignorant off.</p>
   <p>And whereas they wold haue <hi>Ehjeh</hi> to be the future tyme / <hi>I vvill,</hi> not the present tense <hi>I am:</hi> then babble they knoe not what. <hi>Ehjeh</hi> cā neither be restrained to tyme to com, tyme present / or tyme past: for as it is A pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per name off God / it is off all thre tymes: and therefore (as Vatablus wel obserueth) <hi>Iohn in Apoc. 1. 4.</hi> he expoundeth it by / <hi>vvhich was vvhich is, and vvhich is to come. <hi>The</hi> Thal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudists</hi> so vnderstand it: and all Hebrues do by <hi>Ehieh</hi> vnderstand the eternity of God. The <hi>Septuagint</hi> turne <hi>Ehjeh asher Ehieh</hi> in Exod. 3. 14. thus: <hi>Ego Eimi ho <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n:</hi> and theyr Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter, <hi>Ego sum qui sum. Tremellius, Arias</hi> and such as translate it, <hi>I VVIL BE.</hi> they do it not for tyinge men to that: and that they shoe by the other translation in theyr margen-an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notations. <hi>Hierom</hi> in his tennanes off God / and in his Bibles version / and all aancients do expresse it as I haue. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ff A mā set dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne one off the 3. tymes and not all. 3. let the learned iudge iff <hi>I AM</hi> agre not rather with the nature off God / to whome thing preter it and future are present / then I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>DE BEE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NE / or I WIL BE. And let the how sober spirited also iudge (for the spirit of the prophets must be subiect to the prophets) if my annotatiō there vpon <hi>Ehjeh,</hi> do not more fully set downe the nature off God / then the future tyme wold. Let the foolishnes past cawse them be more sparinge in censouringe hereafter off <hi>vvords.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For <hi>Doctrine</hi> / as it is either Literall or Mysticall / so also theyr Calumnie wilbe two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fole. The Literall or Grammaticall doctrine I here meane to be that which at next had ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth from Open text. At such doctrine I looke
<pb facs="3"/> to heare off thunderclaps▪ from our english <hi>Dona<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap>es, Anabaptistes, Arrians, and Sec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> off all sortes: and no maruell / for / as I la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to hold fast / so they labour to transgresse the bounds off the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>: except off aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent heresy / which they a newe fur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ish. Against such doctrine they haue made an insurrection / since my publishinge off the XII. <hi>Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Axioms:</hi> nor was my <hi>Bibles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>r.</hi> fre from theyr enuenonied tongue. I therein (from the consideration off / 2. Cor. 3.) did affirme that the <hi>Iudicial, Moral, Ceremonial</hi> lawes were peculiar to <hi>Canaan:</hi> but to vs the letter remoued / yet equity and spirit thereoff re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayninge, Som bere (who wold only haue <hi>Moses</hi> his Iudiciall lawes established) did wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly giue out that thereby I shut the maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate out off the Church etc. For Ceremoniall lawes they knew that euery one holds them abolished. For the Morall / the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>leainge let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter off them two tables is abolished / the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer scripture teacheth: and so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>. <hi>Beza</hi> with others Old and New vnderstand it. As for the state off the Iudiciall / I knoe none / that is not madly fond / but he graunts they were peculiar to <hi>Ganaan. Mr. Caluin</hi> in his Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions / <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ib. 4. ch. 20. he teacheth it at lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge: and in the 16. section he vseth the word <hi>peculiar</hi> which they cary at in me.</p>
   <p>For Doctrine mysticall / more reasonable sprites (it may be) will say somthinge: and the rather because som late holy writers haue disliked off Mysticall interpretation. Theyr reason is: Bapistes vse it much for establishing theyr matters. This reason indeed is no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son: for the Papists vse asmuch the Letter for theyr purposes: and neither <hi>Donatist, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptist, Arrian &amp;c.</hi> but they call to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and the letter of the Bible for only discus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>singe theyr matters. Shold we therefore reject the Bibles Such slender reason hath caused late factions Spirits to reject the auntient ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly writers: because <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>omanistes vse them: and such insufficient collection / hath caused the <hi>Svvenkfeldians</hi> to cast the Bible vnderfonte / and to lissen to the priuate motions off theyr owne fleshly sprite.</p>
   <p>An / tis damgerous medlinge with mysti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call expositions: true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s so. Tis damgerous medlinge with two edged instruments (and the word off God is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> two edged sword) and damgerous to meddle with the Bibles bare letter. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> or yongones cā hardly med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le with the letter but with perill. Learne that off the Iues and our ages Donatistes. And I wold with <hi>Pithagoras</hi> his scholers they wold at first be fiue yeares silent: more redy to he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are and slower to speak. Euery one shold knoe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eyr measure off faith and keepe themselues within theyr limits / not medlinge with things to hy for them: Yet him that hath som know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge how to handle A two edged sword / this is no barre to his medlinge with it.</p>
   <p>One and the same spirit administreth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersly: to som aboundance in the sence Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical or literall: vnto others A rauishment ut the sence mysticall: nor ought the One to despise the other. Yet this always vnderstood / the Mysterie can neuer be builded safely / except the Grammer sence be first rightly laid: for the Letter is the Ground and foundation to the Mysterie. Which is greene heads did well looke into / they wold not easly wade in <hi>Allegoricall, Tropological,</hi> and <hi>anagogicall</hi> constructions / surder then first is by sad discreet sprites admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistred vnto them.</p>
   <p>For Mysticall sences necessarily lyinge hid vnder the letter or Historie / I wold men wold not only read Greek and Latin Fathers / who herein solaced theyr sowles: but also word go heare what reasons <hi>Moses Bar-kepha Syrian</hi> Bishop off <hi>Bethrawan</hi> in his Commentary off paradise hath concluded for repulsinge such Calumnie: where / amōgst the rest he writes so: <hi>Except therein lay mysticall senses, from vvhence coulde the aunciēt Fathers, Prophets &amp; other holy men off old knoe Christ to com: &amp; therein be so solaced? Finally, iff yre shold vvith these here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes be so mynded, off a troth vve fall into Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daisme: for the lues (vvho are voyd off the holy sprite) they embrace no senses but vvhat is corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall &amp; grosse.</hi> And indeede to vnderstand the scripture only literally / it is but grosse Iudais<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> not liftinge it vp hyer then A humai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Cronicle / that containes no further wisdom then bare letter affordeth. <hi>Paul</hi> drawinge <hi>Sarah</hi> and <hi>Hagar, Ismael</hi> and <hi>Isaac</hi> into Allegorn / he vnderstood otherwise: and the Author to the Hebrues / who calls the <hi>Lavv A shadovve off good thinges to com: Iohn</hi> in his Apocal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ps: the Prophets on Moses / and the Apostles on All / they conceiued off scripture otherwise. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much for Aduerse Spirits.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>As for Freindly Spirits / som off them it may be / wilbe makinge question touchinge Manner and Matter: but not as the former with purpose to abuse the work. A godly Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Scotland hearinge that my foresaid <hi>Breif-booke</hi> had english Verses in it / she for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> season refused to read it: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n som such like inough will here be stumblinge at the Chapters Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments because they are verse. For the proud Donatist that termed them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ymes ād Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeries (though I could justly twite such to the iudgment off theyr owne faction) etc. and for the english Anabaptist that called them Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eclike thinges / I will not answer the foole ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to his foolishnes least I be like vnto
<pb facs="3"/> him: but to the holy spirited I speak thus: The learned do knoe that sondry bookes off scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are off Poeticall shape / consistinge off apt Nomber and som off Kythmed forme But where our language admitteth the Kythme in the end off A Measure / that holy tongue giues it in the begininge. One Instance do take in the 119 psalme. First / it is diuided into 22. parts according to the nomber off the Hebrue Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>et / euery part answeringe to one Letter: secon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dly / euery part consisteth off 8. verses / and euery verse with the same Letter with which that <hi>Octouary</hi> beginneth. So that herein (as also in other places) there is not only verse / but also Kythme / and that with admirable ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy These therfore that condemne Poetry because som prophane it / they may for like abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se aswell reject other excellent guiftes off the Spirit.</p>
   <p>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t my forme off Diuision the Learned may say som thinge / because it vttereth no Art: but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Diuision it self is homely / so the braunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hes thereoff not vttered in Logicall termes. These must knoe / that I write specially for the erudition off vnlearned Christians: by whome I haue somtimes bene s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>bd for speakinge so darkly. Nor do I expect otherwise to be intre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated off som such (though godly) to whome I must also say: though I writ specially for them / yet not only for them. And therefore / what vnto them semeth difficill at first / that shalbe made vnto them more easy by more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adinge. As for wordes in anotherr language / let them leap ouer such / and iff they be vnengli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed after / the thing concerneth them not much.</p>
   <p>Touchinge the Matter / it is but an vnbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wellinge off the sacred booke off <hi>Elohim:</hi> and that is don first by comparinge scripture with scripture: secondly / by introducinge the Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient holy writers for confirmatiō off my iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in thinges of most waighte: that so it may not be demed myne owne priuate fancy. And least I shold play the Theyfe to wisdome (for so <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus. 1. Stromatôn</hi> calleth such) I haue ordinarily put downe his name from whome I borowed it. I could with O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue passed by them vnmentioned / and so haue flowen abroad with other mens fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as iff they had bene my owne: but I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test that payde to be thought to walk alone. Our Ages heretikes that are vnto me contrary mynded / they for theyr alone walkinge do commonly alleadge <hi>Elijah:</hi> sayinge he was somtymes alone. But iff the lyers wold serch the scriptures they shold knoe / that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standinge he se himselff alone in <hi>Israel,</hi> yet he could not be ignorant that the state was other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise in <hi>Iudah:</hi> for then good <hi>Iosaphat</hi> raigned. Nor yet in <hi>Israel</hi> was the hali seede extinguisht / as the Lord doth teach the Prophet / but many there were that did neither inward nor outwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de homage vnto <hi>Baal.</hi> To say that the Church off God many age hath bene holy invisible / it is A dayngerous introduction to all heresy.</p>
   <p>The Auncient Fathers (Greeke and Latine for the first 600. Years, but specially for the first 400.) they are vnto me so deare / as (after all the tryall and knowledge I haue taken off, all Sects) I cannot se how I ought to swarne from them in anye one poynt essentiall. what heresy is there in these days whose grounds they then ouerturnd not? Our English Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisme is but flat Donatisme: he that knoes the Son may fetch the Father out by his face in the Arguments off <hi>Parmeneanus, Petilianus, Cresconius</hi> the Grammarian / and such other Vermine strangled longe synce by holy <hi>August<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine.</hi> Large Anabaptisme grewe also out off <hi>Donatus:</hi> for makinge all other ministry voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de besides theyrs / it must then folowe that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly themselues could administer Baptisme. The holy Father then tels <hi>Parmenean lib. 2.</hi> cap. 12. that they ought aswell make voyde the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment off ministeriall <hi>ordination</hi> (for iff th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>one was good / both stood good: iff the one voyd / the other also) and so <hi>Donatus</hi> and his sectary Ministry / who had and could haue no other Ordination then first they from them / that also shold be voyde: and so themselues deliuer no baptisme rightly. Our Donatistes must le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arne also / iff theyr Ordination in the English church be fully frustrate / then also theyr Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme: If Baptisme remaine good / then also the Ordination. And iff the Ordination be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nothinge / then they are like for euer to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister without Ordination: except priuate lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nien may impose hands: which is flatly false▪ as I haue shewed in Our booke off In Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusions.</p>
   <p>As for Artianisme / Iudaisme and other our Factions theyr doctrines / not only <hi>Augus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> but many others haue cut the stringe off theyr bowe: that iff the Deuel were not on men / theyr Bowe shold haue bene burnt or euer it had bene stroong againe. But not to digresse farre from the purpose of my Proeme: the holy Reader must not be offended / though in this Matter off Matters I consult with those Auncient my Betters: who haue so vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly fought the Lord Battels / and sealed the sanctifying truth with theyr latest breathinge. There is not A Sectary in these days but he reionceth in the writinges off his owne faction: and why shold not the faith full be as carefull to vphold the Men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ornall off the just. Let vs be faithles hereyn / yet God will haue his owne Captaynes (though dead) theyr Ensignes displayd in his temple / when the memoriall
<pb facs="4"/> off the wicked shall rotte. Shewe me One off <hi>Arrius,</hi> or <hi>Donatus,</hi> or <hi>Pelagins,</hi> or any off the sophisticall auncient Heretikes theyr Bookes iff now can. No / God hath cased them from the fate off the earth: that were it not the holy Fathers do mention them and theyr stuffe (as the sacred scriptures remember <hi>Achan, Iudas</hi> and theyr stealth) we shold not haue knowen somuch as theyr rotten Names. This Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (iff there were no more) it vrgeth me to celebrate the Memoriall of the anncient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>igh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous: verily here withall beleiuinge / that my writings (though off thowsands most vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy) they shall ourline the Fartions: and be as an Aegles fether to other fethers / A finall consumption: For euery plant our heauenly father hath not plained / it shalbe pulled vp by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ootes.</p>
   <p>Whereas somtimes I alleadg som Iewe or prophane writer / it is but in such A case as the parti may without prejudice be a fit witnes. <hi>Hierom</hi> (or <hi>serom,</hi> all is one) beinge off <hi>Ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nus</hi> vnto <hi>Magnus</hi> charged with the like as with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ryme / he vnto the Romayne Grator alleadgeth <hi>Pauls</hi> practise / there withall sainge / that he first (according to the lawe) pareth theyr nailes / washeth them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> and then why may he not matry with the captine of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles: and also by occasion take by <hi>Goliahs</hi> sword for cuttinge off the vncircumcised head off the Owner. what he might say / I also for my selfe may say: whereunto I adde: vnto the pure are all things pure / but vnto them that are defiled and vnbeleuinge / nothing is pure: but euen theyr myndes and consciences are defiled.</p>
   <p>The Scriptures I here alleadge for <hi>Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall,</hi> they are thes off the Old and new testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which are vsually off Protestant Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches receiued for the Only <hi>Canon</hi> or <hi>Rule</hi> off Faith. For the Olde testaments bookes there is cheifest cōtrouersie and discontētment. Som off the Bookes called <hi>Apocrypha</hi> are by Rome and som others made regular for Faith: off vs not: and good reason why. <hi>Iosephus</hi> in his first booke againstte <hi>Appion</hi> hath this, <hi>There are not vvih vs thovvsands of bookes discrepant and figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge in themselues, but only bare tvvo and tvven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> And then A litle after he tels the Atheist <hi>Appion,</hi> that the writings from <hi>Arrayezxes</hi> ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me till then (<hi>these vvere our Apocrypha</hi>) there was not like faith to be giuen vnto them / as vnto the former 22, because with them the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re was not like certaine successiō of Prophets. <hi>Origen</hi> on ps. 1. and <hi>Eusebius</hi> from him / do wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes that the Hebrues only acknowledged, 22. <hi>Hierom</hi> not inferiour to any for Hebrues iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments he in his <hi>Prologo Galeato</hi> doth tell vs the same / sainge that the 22. bookes (answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe the 22. letters) they were thus called▪ and into thre Orders disposed.</p>
   <p>
      <table>
         <row>
            <cell>1. Breshith.</cell>
            <cell>Eenes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>2. Velleshemoth.</cell>
            <cell>Erod.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>3. Vaijkta.</cell>
            <cell>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>euit.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>4. Vaidabber.</cell>
            <cell>Nomb.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>5. Elleh haddebarim.</cell>
            <cell>Dent.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>6. Iehoshuag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en-Nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</cell>
            <cell>Ios.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>7. Shophtim.</cell>
            <cell>Iudges</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>8. Shemuel.</cell>
            <cell>Ruth.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>9. Melacim.</cell>
            <cell>Sam. 1. and 2.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>10. Ieshagniah.</cell>
            <cell>Kings 1. and 2.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>11. Iirmiah.</cell>
            <cell>Isa.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>12. Iechezekel.</cell>
            <cell>Ier.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>13. Tere-gnasar.</cell>
            <cell>Ezek.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>14. Iob.</cell>
            <cell>the 12.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>15. Dauid.</cell>
            <cell>lesse proph.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>16. Mishle.</cell>
            <cell>Psal.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>17. Koheleth.</cell>
            <cell>Prou.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>18. Shir hasharim.</cell>
            <cell>Eccl.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>19. Daniel.</cell>
            <cell>Cant.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>20. Dibre haiamim.</cell>
            <cell>Chro.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>21. Gnezra.</cell>
            <cell>Esrah.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>22. Ester.</cell>
            <cell>Nehem.</cell>
         </row>
      </table>
   </p>
   <p>Vnder the which he suffireth: <hi>Quicquid extra hos est &amp;c.</hi> whatsoeuer is besides the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se bookes / they are to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ut amongst the <hi>Apocrypha.</hi> And touchinge the <hi>Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phal</hi> writinges / <hi>Augustine</hi> thus writeth in his 15. booke off the City off ap. God and ch. 23. <hi>Omittamus igitur earum scripturatum fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las quae Apocryphae noninantur &amp;c. Let vs passe by the fables of those Scriptures vvhich are called Apocryphal, because that theyr hidde begininge appeared not to the Fathers, from vvhome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs the Authority of the true-speaking Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, by most sure and euident succession hath com. For in the Apocrypha, although there be found som verity: yet by reason of many vntrut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hes, they are not of Canonical Authority. Ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finus</hi> in his exposition off the Symbole / affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the former bookes to be the Canon off the old testament / from whose fountaine we were to drawe the drinck of God. Som off thy rest he saith were Ecclasiasticall / but not Canomicall.</p>
   <p>But touching this poynt I neede say no more / seinge our <hi>vvhitakres</hi> in his first off the six Questions controuerted with <hi>Bella<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mine,</hi> hath set such A fyre in theyr Coate / as I troe they shall neuerin <hi>Englande</hi> but smell off the smo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke hereafter. But had neither late nor auncient Christian writers euer disclamed them / it is sufficient that <hi>Zion</hi> (mother church off the Gentiles) she neuer Named them. <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ers</hi> ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue they knewe not, <hi>Iudah</hi> nor <hi>Israel</hi> euer cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cised
<pb facs="4"/> them: nor had the Apostles euer co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> baptise them. Som off them as <hi>Ecclesiasticus, VVisdome, Baruch, Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bees,</hi> they may be vsed well / prouided not for rule off faith: but for <hi>Esdras, Tobit: Susanna, Bel, ludeth,</hi> I knoe not iff so they be dreames: and for the fragmentes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rep in vnder the name off <hi>Manasse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, Ester</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi> they openly shoe themselues to be straingers in <hi>Israel.</hi> The Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciēt Church neuer Acknowledged: the New testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Church hath lesse cawse to receiue them.</p>
   <p>As for the Newe testaments bookes there is betwixt Protestant and Papist no contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersie. Both then and we receiue as the holy Fathers receiued / the 4. <hi>Euangels, Acts, Paul</hi> his 13. Epistles: to the <hi>Hebr. 1. Iames</hi> one Ep: two off <hi>Peter: 3.</hi> off <hi>Iohn:</hi> one off <hi>Iude:</hi> and the booke off <hi>Apocalyps</hi> which is the seale off the whole. Our vnity for the bookes one: god graunt that his spirit may once for the sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re thereoff cawse both off vs therein to be <hi>One.</hi> For <hi>Arrians, E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tychians, Anabaptistes,</hi> and the residue off those dregges and most filthy off washinges off the Church off the Gentiles / they reiect som off the lynks off God his gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den chayne / or else trample both the sacred bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celets vnderfoote. The Papists adde vnto the <hi>Canon</hi> (A more tollerable transgression) these <hi>detract</hi> or vtterly <hi>destroy</hi> the Booke off <hi>Elohim,</hi> A transgression intollerable: fitter to be scour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with that lash wherewithall Iesus whipped the theiues out off his fathers howse / then to be reasoned about pro and coir, as our sauiour did with the Temples Doctors at another sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. To answer such accordinge to theyr foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishnes / it doth first make them proud: second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly / it rawseth vs seme foolish. They will hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re no Auncient Christian writer speake: what hope haue we they will heare vs. They can turne all Auntients by / in sayinge: <hi>yovv pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound vnto vs the iudgments of men:</hi> I answer them: <hi>But of such men as had the spirit of God.</hi> Do not they propound to vs the iudgments of Men? Yea / off hereticall <hi>Arrius, Manes, Donatus, Serueitus &amp;c.</hi> The <hi>Svvenkfeldians</hi> ran say: All is but the indgements off men / ād so they will heare no man: but listen to the sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestion off theyr owne spirit. We set no mans iudgment aboue the scripture / but reuerrnce theyr interpretations who haue the Spirit off the scripentes. We knoe that the best Man hath his Ignorance and errour / but hauinge the spirit off Iesus he holds A true foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and finally conquers: whereas the Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> slip from the Corner stone Iesus and are ground vnto powder. Such we must answer in Sword: <hi>The spirit of the Prophets, must be subiect to the prophets, and that is semelynes and Order: if any vvilbe contentious, the Church of God hath no such Custome: but he that is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, let him be more ignorant: 1. Cor. 14.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>A yeare and A halfes labour I haue taken about the 5. bookes off Moses. That I haue to communicate vnto God his Church here and there dispersed / iff Such be the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure off God. About the residue I am not idle: but Moses wilbe sufficient for one reasonable volume. I haue laboured because it sholde passe the presse for publike vtility / but I smell now at the very begining off the bookes out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate / that not only <hi>Sectaries,</hi> but Sectarie <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourits</hi> wilbe no furtherance herein. What then My God he knoweth that I herein seck the Glory. off his name / in the edifiyng his poore people / by propounding to them / what first he hath manifested to me. And he knoes that I wold haue euery work off myne to perish as an vntimely byrth / the continuance whereoff might prejudice his Church: the yssue therefore off all / I referre to his will / his fatherly will. I labour to discharge duty imposed vpon me / iff others not only neglect duty enjoyned on them / but also shall oppose to duty in others: I say no more but this: <hi>the Lord rebuke Satan.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If any good Christian except at the work for ouer weak and vnworthy so excellent A su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bicet / I answer: Euery one off <hi>Israel</hi> cannot cast at an puch with <hi>Beniamin. Dauid</hi> had thre worthies beyond the rest: and 30. more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent then the multitude / but inferiour to the 3: iff I bringe but som what with the meanest off the lower rank / god will accept off it as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy / though in my selfe vnworthy. Som offred to the Tabernacles work Gold / som Gemnies / and othersom but Badgers skynnes and Goa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes haire / so my offringe serue to any <hi>Holy</hi> vse: though not to the <hi>most Holy,</hi> I shalbe glad: for I had leuer to stand on that howse his threshold then to dwell in the Tabernacle off vngodlines.</p>
   <p>This I knoe / that sad discreet and humbled sprites / they will value the Labour by the mynd off the Labourer / who more wold / iff more he coulde: as for our <hi>Britanick</hi> sectaries / I only yet knoe / that whatsoeuer they snarle at secretly / they dare controuert nothinge openly. So my trauels may be approued off the Lord his people I haue that I wold: though wherein it is possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble / I couet peace with the worlde. Let the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous smite me / it shalbe A benefit: let him / rebuke me and it shalbe as Sontraygne oyle not lost on my head. Not but I haue else learned / that <hi>Shimeyes</hi> railinges shalbe tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto the best of such as are called according to God his purpose.</p>
   <p>But in the heele off my proeme / let me vnto the yong Christian Student exhibit som Direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion / for profitinge by readinge myne ād others theyr writinges.</p>
   <p n="1">1. It is ordinarie with People to giue them sel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> after Nouelty in writinges humayne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="5"/> diuine: but without any great paynes takinge in the holy booke of God: or else through a proud disdayne of vsinge other holy men theyr hands and helpes / they only cast ey vnto the holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nō. The first errour procedeth of <hi>Prophanenesse:</hi> the second off <hi>proud superstition.</hi> Betwene these two vices cōsisteth <hi>Vertue:</hi> A right vse of Both. And this is dō / first by hauinge a recourse to the holy Bible: secōdly by reading other mens wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges: humaine / for humanity: diuine for Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. And off writers diuyne: first to se what? o holy friend writeth / secondly what an vnholy aduersary concludeth: for without readinge the Aduersary / thow shalt want much assurance / what and how to think and speak off such.</p>
   <p n="2">2. But thus readinge / all shalbe but a gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe of falshood and a loosinge off Truth / iff first in humility thow ron not by Prayer vnto the God off truth Ad Light. The poore ād hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble spirited / he will fill theyr hād and hart with euery good thing / but the proud ād rich he will sēd empty away. The lack of this orderly course is cawse / that euery Heretike thinketh his here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sy in the Bible: whereas the blessed word is wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thout shadowe off chainge / as God himself is: Yet most off that hellish broode cry / scripture / scripture / and nothinge but scripture: although it is far inough frō purposinge to play the Bau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to proud harlot heresy. Others sekinge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues in Ecclesiasticall writers / they neyther haue better successe: for Rome against <hi>Luther,</hi> He against them / ād others against them both / they thinke the godly Fathers make for them. If men can bend God his golden reed / no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell though they can bowe ād break the Leaden squ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e of men. Cōsideringe the dainger so many ron into / I troe men need to pray before they reade / that so with the Bee they may from that f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oure drawe <hi>hony,</hi> from whēce the <hi>Spider</hi> drag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth his <hi>poyson.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>He that Reades / Notes / Mediates without much prayer / is much his owne Foe: ād he that attempts it without all prayer / he is passinge prophane. This hath cawsed me more then once to wonder at som men: who (cōsideringe theyr judgmēt) me thinks in theyr Library they shold not pray: and yet considering theyr otherga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes cariage / methinks they shold pray: specially seinge they study from writers Old an New / Popish and Protestant etc. The opinion off such is this: viz. It is symply vnlawfull to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ach or Pray in Synagogues / and yet make no scruple to study for theyr church exercises / and that in A Synagogues Library: which booke cloyster must be as deeply in Idolatry (iff not deper) as any part off the Temple. Pray there methinks they shold / and yet consideringe the former opinion / methinkes they should not. For my part (I praise God for it) I still haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned / that <hi>all the Creatures of God are to me sācti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the vvord and prayer: and therefore laufull to hold vp pure hands euery vvhere, and that vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout vvrath and doubtinge: as also that is is A doctrine of Deuels to say, touch not, tast not, hā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle not, all vvhich perish vvith the vsinge: hauinge indeed A shevve of vvisdome, but not to be obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of those that are risen vvith Christ from vnder the povvre of the Lavv.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>As thow Couets therefore to haue God his spirit to guide the in tryinge off all thinges to retaine that is good / do pray wheresoeuer thow reades / studies / meditates ād that to this effect.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Heauenly Father, I sinning togither vvith my Parents Adam and Heuah, I so brought A Vale of darknes &amp; spirituall blyndnes vpon my mynd, the ey of my sovvle: and the ey being dark, hovv gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at must be my darknes? For thy Sons sake my bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed sauiour Christ Iesus, do by the povvre of thy sprite (thy illuminatinge and sanctifying sprite) dispell this Egiptian like darknes and foggie mys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that hinder my poore sovvle in the vvork of my nevv-byrth. Call Light out of my Darknes, and fix in the firmament of my heart, Light for the Day, and Light for the Night, that so I may be able to discerne tymes, seasōs: spirits, doctrine: vvhereby I thy poore Creature may be enabled to glorify the my Creator. For if, svveet father, thy spirit do not leade me into truth, I shall but pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and prophane all the meanes of sauing knov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and holynes: for Christ thy Son his sake, do not therefore leaue me novv to myne ovvne sence and coll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ction, for then I perish and vanish avvay in myn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>vvne imaginations: but as thovv haste promised to be found, to opē and to giue to them that seek, knock and craue: so be vvith me novv thy ovvne handy-vvorke, vvho seeke, knock and craue in the name of Iesus remission of all my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvorthinesses, and A beinge further enlightned in the knovvledge of thy vvill and vvorks, for the furtherance of that Nevv-vvork thou in fre-mercy hast begon in me. Amen. Svveet fathèr, Amen. for the glory of thy Sons name put vpō me, Amē.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>To like effect pray / or else do holde thy leud eyes back from polluting the words / ād works off our God. Nor do thow pray / but fyrst pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge thy heart: for the pure in heart shall se god: as for the sacrifice off the wicked / it is abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to the Lord. And so besuchinge the Lord his blessinge to accompany my labours / I commit the Sequel to the reading off well dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed spirits / whome the Lord do guide vnto good for euer: Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>