<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the right Honourable Sir Frauncesse Knowles Knight, Maister Treasurer of the Queenes Maiesties house∣holde, and of her Hignesse most ho∣nourable priuie Councell. &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Fletcher, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114474_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A22871</idno>
           <idno type="STC">936</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114474</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the right Honourable Sir Frauncesse Knowles Knight, Maister Treasurer of the Queenes Maiesties house∣holde, and of her Hignesse most ho∣nourable priuie Councell. &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Fletcher, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An introduction to the looue of God. Accoumpted among the workes of S. Augustine, and translated into English, by the right reuerend father in God, Edmund, Bishop of Norvvitch, that nowe is, and by him dedicated to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie, to the glorie of God, and comfort of his chosen. And newlie turned into Englishe meter : by Robert Fletcher. 1581</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>110 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the right Honourable Sir <hi>Frauncesse Knowles</hi> Knight, <hi>Maister</hi> Treasurer of the Queenes Maiesties house<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, and of her Hignesse most ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable priuie Councell. &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath beene the vsuall course of</hi> Writers (right Honourable) to pleade pardon by aucthoritie, when they thinke or knowe them-selues farre from intent of offending, either by example of the migh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie King of <hi>Persia,</hi> for his freendlie accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a small gift, esteeming the good will of the giuer: or else by comparing their ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, by the example of some graue Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sopher. I doo not so, but confesse my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption in two sortes committed, the one to your Honour, the other to the honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and reuerend Father in God, my Lorde Bishop of <hi>Norwitch,</hi> that now is, beeing the Translator of this Booke, and hauing dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated the same to the Queenes most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Maiestie, beeing called, <hi>An Introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the looue of God,</hi> and so it maie right
<pb facs="3"/>
well be called. My presumptiō to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is, in pressing your name in print, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I knew your Honours pleasure therin, for which, most hūbly I craue your honors pardon. My presumption to his Lordship is, in taking vpon me to alter the course and nature of to excellent and profitable a prose, but I hope to haue his good Lordships fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour for the same, when he shal vnderstand the cause of my so dooing, considering the prose is still exstaunt, to the profite of the Readers, and my meter now instaunt to the pleasure of the Readers, for so I accoumpt it, hauing therein followed the example of diuers godlie minded, which haue turned into Englishe meter many Bookes out of the Bible, beeing sacred and canonicall, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pithie Pamphlettes; beeing prophane and Historicall, yet to good purposes, as well appeareth by their writinges, which so meant them: the parties with their Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlettes, as impertinent to my purpose, I o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte to repeate. But as his Lordshippe did make her Maiesty patronesse of the matter,
<pb facs="3"/>
so I thought it my duetie, to make your Honour Patrone of the Meter: assuring your Honour not to haue committed any error therein, my presumption onelie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, nor haue not altred the sence of the matter, more then the nature of the meter must of necessitie compell me. The causes mouing me to sollicite your Honour with this <hi>Introduction to the looue of God,</hi> was for that I haue beholden the same most boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifullie bestowed, not onelie in your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours owne person, but also in your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours bothe honourable and VVorshipful off-spring and posteritie, in your owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, the feare and looue of God with seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in Iustice (according to your Honours calling) and precise rule, and lawes of God, which I my selfe haue not onelie beholden, but also beene beholden vnto. In your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours off-spring, that vertuous, Noble, and towardlie young Gentleman, the Earle of <hi>Essex,</hi> dooth shewe himselfe a liuelie graffe and goodlie member of so good a Grandfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which together with your Honour, I
<pb facs="4"/>
beseeche God long to blesse and continew, he onelie maie serue to confirme the looue of God towardes your Honour: although his gracious blessings be apparauntlie mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied in the rest your Honors, bothe good and godlie Children. For the continuance whereof, I shall not cease to beseeche al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, to send your Honour long and honourable life, in this life, but after the same ended, eternall happinesse, in the life to come.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
   <closer>
      <signed>¶ Your Honours most humble <hi>and duetifull bounden,</hi> Robert Fletcher.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>