<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE PRINCE.</title>
           <author>Markham, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114265_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06901</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17332</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114265</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE PRINCE.</title>
                 <author>Markham, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Fiue decades of epistles of vvarre. By Francis Markham</title>
                 <author>Markham, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 200 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE PRINCE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I consider (Greatest of Princes and my most gracious Prince) that all men which passe their dayes in this World, with loose and vntyed Endes; (neither binding thē to the Kings Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, their Countries Profit, nor their owne particular aduancement) doe but wander and goe astray like wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Trauellers lost on some wilde and vntract wildernes, and cannot be said to Iourney but to Toyle. And when J see that an idle man is nothing else but the Deuils cushion, on which wickednes sits, whilest Sloath sleepes on his bosome, I could not then chuse but rouze vp my spirits to vndertake some labour, which might both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer me from this errour, and (by calling backe the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of my first times) shew that there is something in me in the present which with a constant faithfulnes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires to doe your Hignesse and my Countrey seruice.</p>
   <p>Warre (gracious Sir) hath been euer my Mistresse, and though I could not get so neere her as J wisht, yet I haue euer loued her as J ought: and though I haue not been worthy to participate with her Glory, yet she hath been pleased to daigne me her bloody fauours, and to fixe them so sure, that (whilst I am) the Scarres will neuer part from my body. Hence it comes, that I bring this<pb facs="3"/>sacrifice to her Altar, and only desire I may offer it vp before your Goodnes, making you (as you are) the great Captaine of this honourable Band, which howsoeuer I heere haue rankt their Names, yet doubtlesse in their hearts wil continually be a noble emulation who shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch you nearest in the feruencie of true Loue, or the height of a worthie Admiration. The Subiect (though peraduenture darkned by my blunt Language) is worthy your most Princely attention: for <hi>Warre</hi> is onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to Princes, since they (and none but they) may (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God) defend their owne by the Sword, relieue their oppressed neighbours with the Sword, cut downe all tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous and rebellious weeds vnder the Sword: and last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, acquire great Conquests, &amp; enioy true Fame through the Sword; for indeed but they for themselues, and others by their Authoritie, none else may draw the Sword.</p>
   <p>Jt is true (mightie Sir) that your thrice worthy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my dread Soueraigne hath sheathed his Sword, and by his sacred Wisedome saued the blood of many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, all his leuels (as by his owne vnimitable pen is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tested) are at true Pietie, and God which is best pleased with Peace, hath crownd his daies with such Peace, that Warre could not bring any of his progenitors the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to his glory: his Peace and Patience (in the dayes of our admired <hi>Elizabeth</hi>) made his passage smooth &amp; easie to his lawfull Inheritance, &amp; he entred the Throne with such an vniuersall Ioy, and applause of his people, that the admiring
<hi>French</hi> cried out in amazement, <hi>What without a Blow, O wonder!</hi> But this was God, and by him hath his Maiestie shut vp euery backe
<pb facs="3"/>dore that could let in Diuision: yet how long this Peace shall continue God in his wisdome (not man) is able to reckon. I know though
<hi>Licurgus</hi> made his Laws constāt by <hi>War,</hi> yet <hi>Numa</hi> made his more happy by <hi>Peace,</hi> &amp; though the first may indure yet the later shalbe more eternall, and both of necessitie must still lodge neere to remembrance. It was <hi>Iosephs</hi> counsel, In plentie to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for dearth, and in peaceable times to secure Armes is no needles consideration. It is not doubted but a wise Prince may gouern the worlde with an Oliue Branch (for so did the <hi>Romans</hi>) yet when the sword comes, the bough must yeld; for the leafe can but perswade, tis the Steele which must enforce, and where both are vnited, there euer is Tranquility most faire &amp; most flourishing; Your Highnes is an Heire of many kingdoms, and may iustly haue occasion to command many swords, either to recouer your right in forain parts, or relieue your friēds in other parts; and though we inioy the sweetnesse of Peace, and pray continually for the preseruation of the same peace, yet must not Warre be made altogether a stranger: but as it is said of Death, <hi>To prepare for it, giues no approach vnto it:</hi> so to prepare &amp; be ready at all times for war, is no frost that can nip the pleasant blossoms of peace, for both are the handmaids of Kings, the one beares his Commandements, the other his Loue, the one makes him powerfull amongst his neighbors, the other rich amongst his owne people: So that taking the true poize of this Subiect, to whom can J better offer this Tribute, then to your gracious selfe (not as an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to your knowledge (farre be such arrogance) but as an Aduocate to plead my dutie) in whō all perfections<pb facs="4"/>flow to so entire an excellence, that Art and Nature haue left in themselues no power to promise any thing beyond you: Be therefore (Gracious Sir) pleased to protect this poore endeauour of your plaine Souldier, and how euer it comes (like Truth) naked into the world, yet let it finde shelter in the Shadow of your Royall Countenance; First in respect you are the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Heire of my dread King, and so J your vas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall owe you all my Goodnes; next, in regard
<hi>Warre</hi> is my subiect, whose Triumphs J hope shall euermore attend you; and lasty, for your owne deare vertues sake which is the Foode, Life and Soule of euery Souldier. To this and only this great Senate of your diuine perfections J humbly submit my Labours, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeching the God of Heauen and Earth to blesse your Highnesse with all true and perfect happines to the Glory of his greate name, the good of his Church, and the vnspeakeable Comfort of the King, and vs that are his People.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Euer vowed to your Highnes in all dutifull seruice. FRANCIS MARKHAM.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>