<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To all those that faythfully loue the lord Iesus, and vnfainedly desire the flowrishing estate of Sion, together vvith the vtter razing of vvhatsoeuer obscureth the perfect beutie therof: &amp; namely, to such of my brethren and countrimen, as the Lord hath enlighte∣ned with a true knowledge, the ioy of an vpright and comfortable profession, with the encrease of all other the Lords good graces, be multiplyed in Iesus Christe our LORD.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114394_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09300</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19613</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114394</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To all those that faythfully loue the lord Iesus, and vnfainedly desire the flowrishing estate of Sion, together vvith the vtter razing of vvhatsoeuer obscureth the perfect beutie therof: &amp; namely, to such of my brethren and countrimen, as the Lord hath enlighte∣ned with a true knowledge, the ioy of an vpright and comfortable profession, with the encrease of all other the Lords good graces, be multiplyed in Iesus Christe our LORD.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A viewe of some part of such publike wants &amp; disorders as are in the seruice of God, within her Maiesties countrie of VVales : togither vvith an humble petition, vnto this high Court of Parliament for their speedy redresse. Wherein is shevved, not only the necessitie of reforming the state of religion among that people, but also the onely way, in regarde of substaunce, to bring that reformation to passe</title>
                 <author>Penry, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Warwickshire--Coventry</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 83, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To all those that faythfully loue <hi>the lord Iesus, and vnfainedly desire the</hi> flowrishing estate of Sion, together <hi>vvith the vtter razing of vvhatsoeuer obscureth the</hi> perfect beutie therof: &amp; namely, to such of my brethren and countrimen, as the Lord hath enlighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with a true knowledge, the ioy of an vpright and comfortable profession, with the encrease of all other the Lords good graces, be multiplyed in Iesus Christe our LORD.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>I Am not ignoraunt (beloued in the</hi> Lord) hovv many and great causes there are, vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the very least might seeme to haue bene sufficiently able to discourage me from this enterprise, vvhich vnder the holy hand of my God I haue novv vndertaken. J am guiltie vnto my selfe of great corruption and vveakenes. The glory of God is not so regarded amongest men as it ought to be. The Parliament hath hytherto reiected this cause: The enemies thereof are many and strong. But as the discouragements are not a fevve, so J confesse my self to be dravvn back vvith none more, then vvith the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration of my selfe. For looking into mine ovvn hart, I do from the bottom therof protest, so sinful, base, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible, and euery vvay so vveak a vvretch as J am, to be the vnfittest instrument vnder heauen, to deale in so vvaighty a cause. Jt commeth into my minde, that the Lord in iust iudgments tovvards my sinnes, should deny any blessing vnto my endeuors. J knovv that my vveak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in handling the cause, might disgrace the same. And inasmuch as states for the most part, looke vvith fleshly eyes; It commeth into my minde, that the suit, by reason of my base estate should be reiected and cast off. But all those likelihoods notvvithstanding: yet I see that the <pb facs="3"/> Lord vvill haue the cause once againe brought vnto the Parliament in my hands, to try vvhether men vvill not acknovvledge the Gopell, and the gouernment of his son; to vvit, the scepter, vvhereby alone Christ Iesus ruleth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, to be vvorth the entertaynment in their as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblies, thogh it be not accompanied vvith that vvorld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maiesty, vvhervvith vvhen it pleaseth him, he is able to countenance it. And hereby it is in deed, that men do truly sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>vv themselues to tremble before the son of God, and to stoop vnto his royall Scepter, vvhen they are not ashamed of his vvord, hovv base soeuer they be that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come suiters in the behalfe therof.</p>
   <p>For mine ovvne part, hovvsoeuer I haue iust occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to lament mine ovvne great corruptions, yet J may boldly say in the presence of God, &amp; al those, vnto vvhose consideration these labors of mine are offred, publish thus much, that this cause, as near as I could, is altogither se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from those foul staines, vvhervvith J acknovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my selfe to be defiled. And J hope, that it so offereth it selfe vnto the publike vievv and consideration of the Parliament, as they haue no iust cause by reason of my great vveaknes and base estate, to reiect the same. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is any man to maruell, that J being charged of late, by M. Doct. <hi>Some</hi> in publike vvriting, to be not onely a defender of many blasphemous errors, but also an vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miner of the ciuill State, durst presume to become a su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor vnto the high Court of Parliament, before J had first cleared my selfe of those crimes. For my purpose being to haue published an ansvvere to M.D. <hi>Some,</hi> before this cause should be made knovvn; I vvas dravvne vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I vvould or no, to take the opportunity of setting out this, vvhich I thought to be most vvaighty; least that if I had deferred it vntill th'other had come forth, I might <pb facs="3"/> haue bin preuented of the means to publish it in any due time. Besides the
<hi>185.</hi> page, line <hi>2.</hi> &amp; <hi>30.</hi> of M.D. <hi>Somes</hi> booke, vvherein he hath freely graunted me the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie betvveene vs; vvhich is, that vnpreaching ministers, are no ministers, and consequently, not to be communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated vvith: do euidently shevv, that he did not vvell knovv himselfe vvhat he did in charging me, so far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond christian modesty, for defending nothing els in these points, but that vvhich his ovvne vvritings do publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vvitnes against him to be Gods truth. So that of al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other causes, his bare (and by his ovvne vvitnes, for the most part false) accusations, ought least of all to disvvade me from this labour, though I neuer ment to aunsvvere him. But by the grace of God he shalbe ansvvered, and that very shortly.</p>
   <p>And the Petition being in the behalfe of Gods honor, and the good of his Church, the small regard that the Parliament hath had heretofore vnto such suites, ought not greatly to discourage me, the nomber, might, povver, and authoritie of the enemies of the cause, much lesse. He that ruleth the harts of men, can encline them to the setting forth of his ovvne glory vvhen he thinketh good. That vvhich the Lord, for some cause seeming good vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his vvisdome, doth not grant at one time, he (being for the promoting of his honor) lightly bringeth to passe at some other season. And the attempts of his children for the buylding of his Church, haue not alvvayes that suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse vvhich they vvish vnder their hands. For he vseth the endeuors of some, not to finish the building, but to be a preparation vnto that vvorke which he meaneth to effect by the hand of others.
<hi>Zerubabel</hi> and <hi>Ezra</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored very hardly in the building of Ierusalem; the Lord did not finish the vvorke by their means: and yet that
<pb facs="4"/> vvhich they did, vvas a great furtherance vnto <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> vvhose hands the Lord vsed in ioyning the vvall. So the endeuors of Gods children in our dayes, may haue their effect to the glory of God, and the comfort of his Church amongst our posterities.</p>
   <p>It vvas a common demaund the last Parliament, vvhere the cause of reformation (being then labored for) vvas <hi>26.</hi> or <hi>28.</hi> years agone, and vvherfore after so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years of the Gospell, enioyed in this land, the motion of altering the outvvard state of the Church, in the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and officers therof? Came it so out of time to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered off? Least the like obiection should be vsed in the ages to come; behold, the mountayns of ƲƲales, do novv in the <hi>31.</hi> yeare of the raign of Queen <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> call heauen and earth to vvitnes, that they are vveary of their dumb ministers, nonresidents, Lord Bishops, &amp;c. and that they desire to be vvatered by the devve of Christs holy Gospell, and to be compassed about, vvith that beautifull vvall of his holy gouernment. Be it then granted, that the Lord in anger tovvards our sins, doth not account vs novv liuing, vvorthy to be inuited by hir right excellent Maiesty and the state, as Jsrael vvas somtimes, by the godly king
<hi>Hezekiah;</hi> to giue the hand to the Lord,<note place="margin">2. Chro.
31.8</note> and to come vnto the Sanctuary vvhich he hath chosen, &amp; serue the Lord our God, that the fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his vvrath should turne avvay from vs: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvithstanding, least it should be preiudiciall vnto our children, that vve neuer claymed any interest vnto the trueth of the Gospell, and neuer desired to be vnburde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of our blinde and tyrannicall guydes: This Petition of mine shalbe a vvitnes that both hath bin labored for. VVhosoeuer they be then, that vvould vvish men, not to trouble themselues in that cause, vvherein in their <pb facs="4"/> iudgements, they can see no hope of preuayling; doe not consider, that thereby they bereaue our posterities of a great means, to come by that vvhich the children of God novv liuing, vvould so vvillingly obtaine. And they do not consider, that as the Lord hath appointed some to lay the foundation, &amp; make vp the buylding of his Church; so he hath ordayned others, to prepare, and as it vvere, to clense the place vvhere he meaneth to buyld his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
   <p>The aduersaries of this cause may be many, and of great countenance; but vve knovve that the Lord hath committed all povver in heauen, and in earth, not vnto man, but vnto his ovvne sonne Christe Jesus, the alone head and king ouer his Church.<note place="margin">Math. 28.18</note> The cause therefore in hand being his, in vvhose hands is all povver and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; vvhy should vve feare any thing that earth can inuent against the same? And if the question vvere, vvho ought to be terrified in this matter, they by vvhom the Petition is promoted, or they vvho oppugne the same: it shall be found that the aduersaries hereof, haue no other cause, but to be stroken vvith a desperate and vncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable feare: ƲƲhereas on the other side, the patrons of the suite may be euery vvay exceedingly comforted. For vvhat els do the enemies hereof, <hi>but</hi> (after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the vvicked mencioned in the booke of <hi>IOB) say vnto the Almighty, depart thou from vs?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Chap. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.13 15.</note>
      <hi>Because we desire not the knowledge of thy wayes,</hi> any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then it may stand vvith the vpholding of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions receaued and mayntained in our Church, by the consent of the State. Yea, and in their practize they say, vvho is the Almighty that vve should serue him; if he be so strickt in his vvorshipp, that he cannot abide a Church gouernment to be mayntained, vvhich may be
<pb facs="5"/> changeable, at the pleasure of the ciuill State? ƲƲho is the Almighty that vve should serue him; if none must he in our ministery, but such as both for their gifts and faythfulnes, do in deed shevv themselues to be his true messengers? ƲƲho is the Almighty that vve should serue him; if men for the bettering of their outvvard state, may not be Lords ouer their brethren, and ioyn li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vvith liuing, that they may be able to maynayne a part vnbeseeming their calling. And I vvould they did not say, vvhat profit is there, if vve did stoup so lovv vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, as vvithout delay, there should nothing be in our Church, vvhich might svvarue from that seuere rule of his vvord? Should Gods children then feare least these men should haue the vpper hand ouer them, and the Lords cause vvhich they mayntayn. Nay, I tell you, that although such aduersaries, vvere of that povver and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that it might be demaunded, ƲƲho they vvere that durst presume to declare their euill vvayes vnto their faces: yet should they vndoutedly be made as stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before the vvind, and as the chaff, vvhich the storm caryeth avvay. For this cause and euery one, that in the sincerity of his hart, seeketh the prosperous successe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, may boldly say vvith <hi>IOB: Mine enemie shalbe as the wicked;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iob.
27.7. &amp; 20.27. &amp; 21.10.</note>
      <hi>and he that riseth against me, as the vnrighteous, the heauens shall declare his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednesse, and the earth shall rise vp against him. The encrease of his house shall go away, it shall flowe away in the day of his wrath, his eyes shall see his destruction, and he shall drinke of the wrath of the Almightie.</hi> This shalbe the portion of as many as to the end, oppose themselues against the cause of reformation novv labored for. Jt is not a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of dalliance, to vvithstand the povverfull ordinance <pb facs="5"/> of God, in the gouerment of his Church, especially vvhen in the steede thereof, the marchandize of shamelesse Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon is maintayned. Jt is but folly to fight against the lambe, in the defence of her pleasant things; For the lamb shall ouercome, because he is the king of kings, and the Lord of Lords, and they that are of his side, chosen, and called, and faythfull. Great Babylon the mother, that mighty harlot, being in her ful strength in this land, vvas not able to stand against him; vvhat then shall it boote the vveake daughter to striue? And let them feare and take heede, vvho defend the daughters fornication, least they be made partakers of the punishment denounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them, vvho committed adultery vvith the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Themselues they may hurt, but their practizes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Gods trueth and his Sayntes, ought not to discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the Lords chosen, from standing to the cause of their master. Be they then neuer so many, neuer so povverfull, neuer so flovvrishing, neuer of so great authority in the eyes of the vvorld, vvho cannot abide that the Gospell should haue such a free passage in this kingdome, as the heat thereof shoulde melt vvhatsoeuer is amisse in our state; yet the Lorde not being of their side in this poynt, they shall not be able to preuaile. For this is that cause a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst vvhich, neuer man as yet striued and prospered. J knovve there vvill be many in this Parliament, vvho questionlesse fauor the cause of God from their heart, &amp; vvould be forvvard in pleading for the soueraigntie of Christ Iesus, if they savv not their endeuors crossed and vvithstood, by many of high place and authoritye. All those vvhosoeuer they be, J do from the bottome of mine heart earnestly beseech, that they vvould consider, that in dealing for the putting dovvne of the dumbe ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for the abolishing of Nonresidency, and the rooting out of Lord Archb. and Lord Bishops, and vvhatsoeuer
<pb facs="6"/> els the right hand of the Lord hath not planted: and in seeing that the vvorde preached, may freely sound tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowout this kingdome, they do therby nothing els, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire that the God of heauen and earth may be acknoled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and accounted vvorthy alone to rule in his Church vvithin this land. The consideration vvhereof, ought so to mooue and stir them vp, as no creature vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen should be able to dismay them, in this their Petition and request. They seeke that he may rule his Church by his vvord and lavves alone, at vvhose reproffe the<note n="a" place="margin">2 Iob.
21.12</note> pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of heauen do tremble and quake. They seeke that he may be acknovvledged for the onely Sauiour and redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of men, and for the onely lavvgiuer in his Church, vvho hath protested that he vvil not abide to impart the glory thereof vnto any other. And vvhom should they then feare in this suite? The Lorde hath promised, that none vvho trust in him shall perish, Psal. <hi>34.22.</hi> And he hath promised, that although the vvicked vvatch to slay the righteous, yet he vvill not leaue him in his hand, psal.
<hi>37.32.</hi> Yea, he hath promised to be vvith those that fear him, vvhen they<note place="margin">Esay. 48.1.2.</note> passe through the vvaters, that they should not be ouerflovven; and vvhen they vvalke tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the fire, that they should not be burnt. VVherefore then, shold they fear man, whose breath is in his nostrels, as long as they sincerely stand to the cause of their God. Though they be but a fevv in nomber, yet the Lord vvith legions of Angels standeth on their side, to d scomfite all those that contende vvith him. Oh J vvould that the vvords of the Lord spoken by
<hi>Isaiah</hi> the Prophet, vvere thoroughly vvritten in the hearts of as many in this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable assembly, as for the feare of man vvill be the hardliar dravvn, throughly to stand to the cause of their God. For thus comfortably the Prophet, Chap. <hi>51</hi> of his prophesie, speaketh vnto all those that vvith an vpright <pb facs="6"/> heart seeke the honor of the Lord. <hi>Heare me, ye that follow after righteousnes, and ye that seeke the Lord, looke to the rocke whence you are hewen, and to the hole of the pitt whence you are dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. Consider Abraham your father, and Sarah that bare you; for I called him alone and blessed him, and encreased him. Hearken vnto me, yee that know righteousnes, and the people in whose hearts is my law, fear ye not the reproch of men, neither be you afraide of their rebukes: I, euen I am he that comfort you. Who art thou that thou shouldest feare a mortall man, and the sonne of man, which shalbe made as grasse, and forgettest the Lorde thy maker, which hath spredd out the heuens, &amp; layd the foundations of the earth, &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Novv then, vvhosoeuer they be, that are timerous in the cause of God, (as alasse, vvhat flesh and blood is not too too feareful) here is a stedfast rocke for them to leane vnto; here is a defender for them, vnder the shadovv of vvhose vvings, they might be bold to contemne vvhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer their aduersaries can bring against them. Are they but a fevv in nomber, let them looke vnto Abraham, he vvas called alone, and yet the Lord blessed him, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased him. Are they afrayd of the rebukes of man? vvhy they seeke the righteous vvayes of the Lord, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he commandeth them not to feare. Are they povv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull and mighty, by vvhom the suit is d scountenaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced: yea, but notvvithstanding they are but mortall, &amp; they shalbe made as grasse, and the time vvill come, vvherein it shalbe demanded; ƲƲhere are they novv that vvithstood the cause of God in the Parliament of England? Js not their memory vvritten in vvater, and their hope perished together vvith them? To desire the free passage of the Gospell in this land, together vvith <pb facs="7"/> the speedie remoouing of all that hindereth the same, is to plead the cause of that God, vvho hath controlled kings and great Monarches, yea quite ouerthrovvne them &amp; their kingdomes, for denying the free vse of his seruice vvithin their dominions. Euen the cause of that God, vvho hath not onely brideled the rage of tyrants, enten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the suppression of his trueth, but also turned that, vnto the great good of his Church, vvhereby they sought to vvorke the ruine thereof. Pharaoh, Achitophel, Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherib, Haman, came to the graue vvith blood, vvhen in the eyes of men, the most of them vvere likeliest to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle, and the cause of God and his children vnlikeliest to stand. The Lord in this kingdom can do the like vvhen he thinketh good.<note place="margin">Ezra.
4.7.8. &amp; 5.3. Cap. 6.7. &amp; 7.23.</note> The accusations and slanders of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thridath, Tabeel, Rehum, Shimsai, Shetherboznai, vvith their companions, did seeme likely once and againe, to hinder the buylding of the holy citie: but at the length it broght frō Darius, a most sure &amp; strong commandement for the furtherance of the work, clean contrary to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of the enemie. And vvho knovveth vvhether the Lord at this Parliament, vvill not stir vp the spirits of the Sates, and especially, of her R. excellent Maiestie, that they may say vnto the enemies of this cause, as Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius did vnto the men aforenamed. Therefore Tatnai, captaine beyond the riuer, &amp; Shetherboznai vvith their companions; be ye far from them. Suffer the vvorke of this house of God to go forvvard. And<note n="a" place="margin">Ezra. 7.23.</note> vvhatsoeuer is by the commandement of the God of heauen, let it be done speedely for the house of the God of heauen; for vvhy should he be vvroth against the realm, &amp;c. vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beloued, vvhosoeuer you be, that at any time shalbe imployed, eyther as Parliament or othervvise, in the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forvvard of the cause of reformation, stand man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in defence of the truth, &amp; the liberty of his Church</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>The practises of the aduersaries, I mean of our bishops, shevv manifestly, that these reliques of cursed Babylon, vvhich they maintayne among vs, must needs go avvay vvith a noyse, as the rest vvas ouerthrovvne. They vvill not yeelde to the trueth, hovvsoeuer it hath gotten the vpper hande of them. The Lord must vse violence to throvv them out, as he did against the caterpillers their forefathers. Reuel. <hi>18.19.</hi> They haue manifested hitherto, hovv desperate and past recouery, the cause vvhich they defend is become, in that they haue denyed, to yeelde a quiet and a brotherly conference or disputation, vvith those vvho are contrary minded vnto them. Jf J may but procure this vvith our BB. in ƲƲales, I vvill loose my life, if they be not ouerthrovven: vvhich I speake not, vvithout the humble acknovvledgement of myne ovvne vveaknes. And let me not be thought by any, to deale too confidently, for J deale in a sure and a confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent cause, vvhich is not timerously to be delt in, but in the feare of God, vvith all boldnes to be stood to, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouched. And whensoeuer they or any of theirs, shal but aduenture their places against my life; they shall perceiue by the grace of God, that there is strength in the cause, which hitherto they haue withstood to their smal gaine.</p>
   <p>Yea, but I might haue dealt more sparingly against them. It vvere pity in deed, but J should intreat the high court of Parliament to heale the disease of my countrie, but so notvvithstanding, as they vvould suffer the cause of the griefe and misery thereof still to remaine. The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament should be sued vnto for helpe, against the disease and bane of the country of ƲƲales, but so as they vvould fauor the causes thereof. And vvhat malladie is there J pray you in our Church, vvhereof the dumbe ministers, nonresidents, our Lord BB. vvith the rest of that vngodly generation are not the cause. J should spare them vvho spare not the Church, and in vvhose eyes the glory of God <pb facs="8"/> is not esteemed, and yet the Lord knovveth, I hate them no farther then they are Gods enemies. Their fauor I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire not, as long as they continue to be the aduersaries of the Church. If they vvould yeeld peace vnto it, I vvould be soon brought to lay dovvn my complaints against thē.</p>
   <p>Concerning you my deare countrimen, vvhom God of his infinit goodnes and mercy, hath translated out of the kingdome of darknes, vnto the blessed possession of the heauenly Ierusalem; I beseech you very earnestly, that you vvould be carefull to walk vvorthy the Gospel of christ. Be carefull hereof, vvhether your abode be in England or in VVales, and at any hand, endeuor to liue vvhere you may enioy the meanes of the vvord. And be carefull to haue the Lord purely vvorshipped in your families. Take heed of the profanenes, vvhereby the most novve liuing, are dravvn to contemne Gods iudgements against their sinnes. The time vvil come, wherin it shalbe made known that your hope vvas not in vaine. Labor diligently, as far as your callings vvill suffer you, to be a means to conuay that treasure vnto your country, vvhereof you your selues haue bin made partakers. Particularly, let me here put you in minde, R. honourable and vvorshipfull, vvho of my countrye are in this Parliament, to acquaint this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable court, vvith the miseries of our country, and to be earnest for a redresse. And you my brethren, vvho ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing fit gifts, and are employed in the ministery, either in your ovvn countrie or in England, forget not I pray you, to be remembrancers of Sion, giue the Lord no rest, vntill the righteousnes thereof breake foorth as the light, and the saluation thereof as a burning lampe. J vvould to God that I might ioyne vvith you, and you vvith me, in some endeuor, vvhereby the means of saluation might be had in our natiue countrie; it is my harty desire. The God of peace, who hath called vs to his eternall glory by Christ Iesus, make vs perfect, confirme, strengthen and stablish vs to the ende, Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>