<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PRINTER TO THE READERS IN GENERALL.</title>
           <author>Browne, David</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114999_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07662</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18053</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114999</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PRINTER TO THE READERS IN GENERALL.</title>
                 <author>Browne, David</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Honours academie. Or The famous pastorall, of the faire shepheardesse, Iulietta : A vvorke admirable, and rare, sententious and graue: and no lesse profitable, then pleasant to pervse. VVherein are many notable discourses, as well philosophicall, as diuine: most part of the seuen liberall sciences, being comprebended [sic] therein: with diuers comicall, and tragicall histories, in prose, and verse, of all sorts. Done into English, by R.T. Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Montreux, Nicolas de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Matthew</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 86, 2, 93, pages 92, pages 91, 88-162, 123-163, 158-166, 165-227, pages 622, 227-237, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE PRINTER TO THE READERS IN GENERALL.</head>
   <p>GEntle Readers, brieflie and ingeniouslie (in a word) thus. This Booke hath beene kept from the Translator heereof a long time, since when (vntill it was in a manner throughlie Printed) hee neuer had sight of it, and therefore could not possiblie pervse it ouer, as his desire was, meaning to haue corrected, what you perhaps may finde amisse. Some faults (no doubt there be) especially in the Verses, and to speake truth, how could it be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, when he wrote all this Volume, (as it were) Cursorily, and in hast: Neuer hauing so much leisure, as to ouer-looke one leafe, after he had scribbled out the same. It therefore must needs be lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle better then a confused <hi>Chaos, Rudis indigesta{que} Moles,</hi> not much vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the Beares vglie whelpe, before it be licked ouer by the dambe.</p>
   <p>But there is no remedie now, but patience, hee can be but sorie for the same. And yet to speake indifferently, the errours heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in committed, are not so grosse and so many, but that they may be easily let slippe, and passe vnespied: and this is the petition, which I am bold to put vp vnto you; which if my Fortune be so good, as it may passe, and be graunted amongst you, you shall animate the Gentleman hence-forward, to be more carefull to please you, and binde me in double bands with him, to labour hereafter, in what I may, to make some better satisfaction, for this your kinde pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence towards vs both. And so I rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Alwayes yours to by poore power,</hi> T. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>