<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the worthy and renowned Company of Students and professors of the excellent science of Phisicke, Iohn Fage wisheth health.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114685_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00527</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10665</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114685</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the worthy and renowned Company of Students and professors of the excellent science of Phisicke, Iohn Fage wisheth health.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Speculum ægrotorum. The sicke-mens glasse : or, A plaine introduction wherby one may giue a true, and infallible iudgement, of the life or death of a sicke bodie, the originall cause of the griefe, how he is tormented and afflicted, what thinges are medicinable to the diseased person: and the day and houre in which he shall recouer, or surrender his vitall breath. Whereunto is annexed a treatise of the foure humors, and how they are ingendered and distributed in our humane bodies: with certaine and manifest signes to discerne of what complexion any man is: and the operation that eating, drinking rest and exercise, worketh in euery person: with certaine speciall preseruatiues for the eye-sight. Composed by Iohn Fage, student in phisicke, and practitioner in astrologie</title>
                 <author>Fage, John, student in phisicke</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lugger (Luggard), William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the worthy and renowned Company of</hi> Students and professors of the excellent science of Phisicke, <hi>Iohn Fage</hi> wisheth <hi>health.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Vdicious Doctors and professors of the famous and laudable science of Phisicke (in token of the inesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable loue &amp; good will I beare to this worthy faculty) I haue vnto you (as the chiefe patrons thereof,) committed this little Glasse of sick men: wherein you may beholde the state and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the diseased person (soe truely and infallibly, as the Arte of Astrologie can certifie) being aswel cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>respondent and agreeable to the sayings of auncient and approoued Authors, as by experience and dayly obseruations verified, whereof I my selfe haue made sufficient triall (as many of my familiar friendes and associates can testifie) insomuch that hee which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth these documents with the iudicials of vrine, shall thereby not onely decerne and perceiue the true cause of the disease, but also the augmentation, relax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, continuance and alteration thereof to good or euill (both to the praise and estimation of the arte, &amp;
<pb facs="3"/>
also the credit &amp; profit of the expert Physition) assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring you that heerein is nothing written, but onely that which hath been taken out of the groundes of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strologie, and agreeable to the sentences of the moste excellentest Physitions. And although peraduenture this methode and manner of iudgement dooth seeme hard and difficile to some men at the first aparance, yet let no mā be discouraged, for with a little reading and perusing, it wil soone appeare both plaine &amp; ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, which being once obtained, the commoditie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of will bee verie delectable and profitable. And so to conclude, if this my labour be acceptable to your learned eares, it will encourage me (to endeauour to the vtermost of my power) both to examplefie this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction, and also to supply you with another trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise which shall fully and largely detect and lay open this manner of Iudicials: so in the meane time I commit you (and your industri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous actions) to the protection of the Almightie. At <hi>Midhurst</hi> this 24. of Aprill. 1606. {inverted ⁂}</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>