<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Bloys, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114171_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16215</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3140</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114171</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Bloys, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Meditations upon the XLII. Psalme. By William Bloys esquire</title>
                 <author>Bloys, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Young (Junius), Robert</publisher>
                    <distributor>Latham (Lathum, Lautham), George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 354, 2 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the Apostles rule,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.15.</note>
      <hi>Be ready alwayes to give an answer to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man, that asketh you a reason of the hope that is in you, with meeknesse and feare.</hi> The multitude of my thoughts thereof, have constrained me to give some publicke testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, whereby to absolve my selfe from any sinister a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buse of that retired privacy which I have hitherto injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. I chuse rather to have my life embrightened by use, than consumed by the
<pb facs="3"/> rust of ease. There is no kind of life so meane and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy as that of the voluptuous man, who filleth himselfe with vaine delights, as with the wind, and hath no other pleasure than that which is common to the creatures, yea more proper to them than unto man; not deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to be called a life, for such as live in pleasure are dead while they live. Other professions, as they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable in themselves, so being rightly used, they may become helpfull unto us, in making our calling and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction sure. There is a bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing bestowed upon the Peace-maker, which labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to destroy that bitter roote of dissention, and to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stablish
<pb facs="3"/> goodwil among men: But let him consider how miserable an estate he is in, though hee hath beene an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument of concord, and a meanes of charity, if hee wants this inward peace of a good conscience; and the perfect assurance that God is reconciled unto him in Christ Iesus. The Ruler must remember how inexcusable he is, if he condemneth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, in doing the same things wherein hee judgeth another: How can hee pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish swearing and drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in other men, when himselfe doth deserve to be smitten five or six times, even till hee bee consumed, with the arrowes of Gods ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, because of his trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressions?
<pb facs="4"/> The Advocate that seekes for the temporall benefit of another man, with such vehemency, may be put in minde to sue for his owne spirituall good, with greater importunity: If hee bee so diligent to obtaine a corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible reward, then hee ought to bee much more carefull to obtaine an incorruptible crowne, which is more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious than gold or silver; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing given unto us by Christ our Mediator, who pleadeth for us, and in whom wee also have boldnesse and accesse with confidence unto the throne of grace. The Soule-physitian must first heale himselfe, before he can cure the infirmities of other men: And his chiefe care and feare
<pb facs="4"/> must bee, lest that by any meanes, having preached un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to others, he himselfe should be a cast away: Thus should the soule bee lifted up in all our employments. But the common course of the world is to lanch forth into the deepe, not having Christ to bee their Pilot; where they are exceedingly tossed by stormy winds, and mighty tempests, and in danger to fall into quick-sands, or at least to bee prevented by the winter of sicknesse and death, so that their voyage is with much hurt and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage; and sometime they make ship-wracke of faith and a good conscience. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the true beleever hath ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at the faire havens of
<pb facs="5"/> blessednesse and tranquility: Hee onely is rapt up to such an height, that hee is exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the harmfull vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of thunder and raine. His understanding is not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-clouded with darke ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance: Hee is not carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about with every winde of inconstancy, But having found by comfortable expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that it is good being upon this holy hill; hee hath there pitched his tent, and fixed his habitation. From whence God suffereth him to looke downe, upon the Gomorrah of this rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious people, this sinfull world: The cry of whose grievous sinnes, being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great, doth ascend up like a vapour, and will cause
<pb facs="5"/> the Lord to showre downe his judgements.</p>
   <p>The good man that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon God alone,<note place="margin">Pro. 14.14.</note> and is satisfied from himselfe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving full contentment in the portion received, is to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steemed of all men most hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py. Were not the deceitfull heart like that bag with holes (whereof the Prophet spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth) which can never be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,<note place="margin">Haggai 1.6.</note> this competent estate, for which Agur prayed, and for which we ought to give thankes, might bring abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant satisfaction, and cause us to seeke more devoutly for heavenly blessings. The chiefe contentment I have found in framing this small worke, may be expressed in the words of Iacob, though
<pb facs="6"/> with plainer truth, The Lord thy God brought it to my hand: My speciall benefit which I intend, is to bind my selfe to a vigilant observati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of those things, which I have thought meet and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to prescribe unto others: If hereby any glory doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound unto God, I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the prize for which I runne: As for any fame unto my selfe, I neither deserve nor expect it: And though it were never so well beautified by Art, and adorned with Rhetorick, I would shake it off as the dust, and tread it under foot, rather than be seduced with fond affectation of empty praise. I regard not mans day, nor will I hearken unto the voyce of man,
<pb facs="6"/> when (as I hope) God himselfe hath called there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>From my Study at Grundesburgh in Suffolke. <hi>WILLIAM BLOYS.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>