<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right honorable, and his very good Lord, Ambrose Earle of Warwicke, Baron Lisley, mai∣ster of her Maiesties ordenance, knight of the most honorable or der of the Garter, and one of her highnes priuy Councell, H. D. wisheth all prosperitie in this life, with increase of honour, and in the life to come eternall felicitie, in the heauenly hierarchie by Iesus Christ.</title>
           <author>D., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114042_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19743</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6168</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114042</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right honorable, and his very good Lord, Ambrose Earle of Warwicke, Baron Lisley, mai∣ster of her Maiesties ordenance, knight of the most honorable or der of the Garter, and one of her highnes priuy Councell, H. D. wisheth all prosperitie in this life, with increase of honour, and in the life to come eternall felicitie, in the heauenly hierarchie by Iesus Christ.</title>
                 <author>D., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A godlie and fruitfull treatise of faith and workes. Wherein is confuted a certaine opinion of merit by workes, which an aduersary to the gospell of Christ Iesu, held in the conference, had in the Tower of London</title>
                 <author>H. D.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Seton, Gregory</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>104 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right honorable, and his very good <hi>Lord, Ambrose Earle of Warwicke, Baron Lisley,</hi> mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster of her Maiesties ordenance, knight of the most honorable or der of the Garter, and one of her highnes priuy Councell, H. D. wisheth all prosperitie in this life, with increase of honour, and in the life to come eternall felicitie, in the heauenly hierarchie by Iesus Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T what time Right honorable, I had finished these my slender la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, containing such holesome doctrine, I trust, as may semeneces sary for the time. Certein of good iudgement ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing per used the same made some perswasion to suffer the impression thereof, which at the firste, considering my own weakenes, the slender hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of so weightie a matter, the pretence in the beginning for my priuate exercise, I disassented to their desire. But being somewhat pressed to do some good to the Church, how litle soeuer, and to cast forth some publike stone to the repairing of the building, leauing the successe to almightye God, I was in the ende contented to yeeld, and imboldened to commit this litle treatise to the printe. The first and onely occasion of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting wherof, was an argument which an aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary of the truth held in the cōferēce, had in the Tower of London, the force whereof seemed to me so weake, as that I thought my simple skill, might easely confute the same, wherefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>
that argument to memory, I applied my endeuour to the confutation therof. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though arte, &amp; the eloquent order, &amp; forme of the learned herin be wanting, yet I doubt not but done according to the truth. Yet iudge I this my labour litle worth, and smally, or nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to preuaile against the cauils, and slaunders of the aduersary, vnlesse your honorable L. were patrone thereof, to whom I do dedicate both my good hart, and worke also, not as to teach your L. ought contained in this treatise, whose honor aboundes both in Zeale, and knowledge of this doctrine, but by your authoritie, to get it the more fauourable intertainement with others, when they shall behold this simple discourse, shrowded vnder the protection of your honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble good L. Thus being bold in all humilitie to prostrate this litle booke before your honour, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruing the examples of others in like oblations, for the better defence thereof. I pray to the Lord Iesus long to preserue you, in much honour, and felicitie,</p>
   <trailer>Amen,</trailer>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your honors most humble to commaund, <hi>H. D.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>