<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PROHEME</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114387_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14934</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25242</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114387</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PROHEME</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The sea-lavv of Scotland : shortly gathered and plainly dressit for the reddy vse of all seafairingmen</title>
                 <author>Welwood, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>34 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE PROHEME</head>
   <head type="sub">Bearand the origin of the Sea law, the groūd of this treatie and the occasions theroff.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He daily traffike on the sea constrainit the Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians of auld to dytte lawis in the Mediter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rane Sea / and not very lang since the Olonois to set furth thair lawis in the Ocean. Quhilks lawis / the singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar skill of baith peiple sa commendit and equitie sa approuit / that not only hes the Rhodian law be a speciall ordinance (<note n="1" place="margin">l libellus 8▪ ad l rhod.</note>) bin imbraced throghout the Romaine dominion / and sicklike / a great part of the reulis of Olon fellowit in our quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Ocean: bot are also baith recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit in the maist part of the quarter fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said / at lest / sa far as they are commonly knawin be peiple. Quhilk knawledge
<pb facs="4"/>
becaus I haife commonly found to be very litle in this cuntry / notwithstanding that all men be bound to ken the law / <note n="2" place="margin">l leges C de legib.</note> namely thair awne common lawe / <note n="3" place="margin">bart in l non fatetur nu: 6 &amp; 12. de confes. gloss. in l libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorum verb. non juris de his qui not. infam.</note> notwithstanding also the worthines and daily neide thairof / in this great incresse of traffick quhilke ruin of auld was ay haulden to tende till a great Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. <note n="4" place="margin">l <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> ‡ licet vers quia ad summam de ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cercit.</note> Therfoir a 13. yeirs since / out of al the wrets authorizit be our nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I collectit briefly▪ not onely the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains of the Rhodian lawe / as it is left interpret to vs be the Romaine lawers / with the reulis of Olon rcceauit be our cuntrey men / bot also the acts of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament / with vthers rests of the Romain law concernand the Seafairing. And hes now / I trow / in a conueuient tyme at the earnest desire of sundrie orderlie digest / &amp; publishir the samin / for the reddier v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage to all Scafairing men / luking vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for gud occasion at thair hands of far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther trauell in this turne afterward / as God the great lawgiuer sall bestowe mair light on me / quha mot blesse this present labour to my Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey men / </p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>