<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the fauourable and Chri∣stian
Reader.</title>
           <author>Barnes, Barnabe</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114396_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04549</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1467</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114396</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the fauourable and Chri∣stian
Reader.</title>
                 <author>Barnes, Barnabe</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A divine centurie of spirituall sonnets</title>
                 <author>Barnes, Barnabe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>62 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the fauourable and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue published (curteous Reader) an
hundreth Quatorzaines in honour of
the greatest disposer of all great hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours;
wherin, if through secret, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seperable
combat betwixt earth and
my spirite, the priuie motions, and
sting of diuers wounds, as they did
succeede and grieue my soule, manifested appeare: Let
them (though not in these, that singular vertue to contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion,
may mouingly perswade and stirre vp your Spirite
to Diuine contemplation of your Ghostly comfort) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine
yet as remembrancers to kindle more gracious and
rich spirits of zeale and pure holinesse in your more Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious
and Facile prepared wittes &amp; natures: Which only
as they be in respect of all other creatures reasonable, and
most Diuine; so ought they to bee (likewise) in all reason
imployed to the propagation, honour and mightinesse of
his Diuinitie; whose vertue abundantly moueth vpon all
vnworthie creatures of his handes: but vpon vs (the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels
of his similitude, &amp; liknes) in that large measure, which
as it is ineffable, so doth it by nature enioyne vs to glorifie
the singular operations, of his omnipotent handes.</p>
   <p>The glorious subiect, as it is matchlesse, and incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
for Tytles and Mightinesse, so woulde it (in some
richer &amp; more copious Inuentions) rayse the tryumphant
charyot of your sacred Muses, aboue the starre-bearing


<pb facs="4"/>
firmament, &amp; vpō the spirituall Pegasus of celestiall poesie
in diuine harmonie of spirite beare the writer to that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesticall
Throane, and Hemicycle of incomparable state
and comfortable dignitie where he should (with consent
and assistaunce of Angelles and heauenly Spirites, to the
musicall stringes of royall crowned Harper's) for euer sing
ALLELVYA, Saluation, Honor, Glory, Renowne
and Eternitie bee ascribed alwayes to the greatest God of
gods, King of kinges, Lorde of lordes, onely victorious,
tryumphant, mercifull and gracious: And if any man feele
in himselfe (by the secret fire of immortall Entheusiasme
the learned motions of strange and diuine passions of spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite,
let him refine and illuminate his numerous Muses
with the most sacred splendour of the holy Ghost, &amp; then
he shall (with diuine Salust the true learned frenche Poet)
finde that as humane furie maketh a man lesse then a man,
and the very same with wilde vnreasonable beastes: so di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine
rage and sacred instinct of a man maketh more then
man, and leadeth him (from his base terrestriall estate) to
walke aboue the starres with Angelles immortally.</p>
   <p>The seuerall passions of comforte &amp; ghostly combates,
albeit they stand in my booke confused, &amp; peraduenture
therefore may to some readers seeme disordered and
straunge, as in their vnequall coherence of praises, peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
and fearefull afflictions, yet vpon some especiall oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions
and in earnest true motions of the spirite were
they deuised: and I therefore in this respecte implore
your generall fauours. Reade I beseeche you, and with
singlenesse of zeale and true spirit giue censure according
to my good will and indeuours.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Farewell.
<hi>Bar. Barnes.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>