<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Errata]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114055_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16174</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3098</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114055</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Errata]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A reproofe of M. Doct. Abbots defence, of the Catholike deformed by M. W. Perkins : Wherein his sundry abuses of Gods sacred word, and most manifold mangling, misaplying, and falsifying, the auncient Fathers sentences,be so plainely discouered, euen to the eye of euery indifferent reader, that whosoeuer hath any due care of his owne saluation, can neuer hereafter giue him more credit, in matter of faith and religion. The first part. Made by W.P.B. and Doct. in diuinty</title>
                 <author>Bishop, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>—Recusant</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>287 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="145"/>
   <p>
      <hi>COVRTEOVS READER,</hi> I must needes acquaint thee with a notable legerdemaine, which by perusing the Authour I found out, after the rest was printed. <hi>M. Abbot</hi> to proue that the Pope had no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in Scotland <hi>1200.</hi> yeares after Christ, auerreth:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Page</hi> 117.</note> that <hi>Alexander</hi> the second vtterly for-badde the Popes Legate to enter within his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; which is not true. For his Authour <hi>Mathew Paris</hi> declareth:<note place="margin">In Hērico <hi>30</hi> page <hi>667.</hi>
      </note> that the King indeede did at the first oppose himselfe against that visita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Kingdome, to be made by the said Legate: not for that he did not acknowledge the Popes supreme authority in those Ecclesiastical causes; but because it was needlesse, the matters of the Church being (as he said) in good order, and for feare of ouer-great charges. Nay further, the said King did write a large letter vnto the Pope himselfe, as the very same Authour recordeth: where he first acknowledgeth,<note place="margin">In Hērico <hi>30</hi> page <hi>873.</hi>
      </note> that very person to be his Holinesse Legate, as wel in Scotland as in England and Ireland. Moreouer the King confesseth, that he himselfe, his heires and subjects, were and would be obedient vnto the Popes jurisdiction and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, with much more to the same purpose. Which alone is sufficient to conuince <hi>M. Abbot,</hi> to be so perfidious and without al conscience in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaging auncient Authours, that no man who wil not willingly be blindly ledde by him, can repose any trust in his allegations.</p>
   <p>Good Reader beare with faultes in printing, which besides false poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, be not many. The principal that I remember are these:</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Page 169 line 21 For</hi> Constantius <hi>the fourth,</hi> reade Constantine <hi>the fourth; and so in al that matter following treating of Pope</hi> Agatho <hi>his obedience to the said Emperour. Page 170 line 32 though Emperour,</hi> reade <hi>although an Emperour. Page 186 line 21 for</hi> Concilij Praesidijs, <hi>reade</hi> Concilij Praesidibus. <hi>page 198 line 8 in the allegation of</hi> S. Leo, <hi>there wants in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, the quotation of his 23. Epistle to</hi> Martianus Augustus, <hi>for the vvorship of Relikes. Pag. 213 lin. 27 for</hi> passed, <hi>reade</hi> possessed. <hi>pag. 261 line 25 for</hi> and ego, <hi>reade</hi> an ego. <hi>page 272 line 16 for Vndoubtly,</hi> reade <hi>Vndoubtedly.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>