<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE CONTAINING THE CAVSES AND REASONS OF this nevv edition, as also a detection of the foule and false dealing of M. Edm. Buny Minister, in his late edition of the for∣mer booke.</title>
           <author>Daunce, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114169_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09063</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19354.1</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114169</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE CONTAINING THE CAVSES AND REASONS OF this nevv edition, as also a detection of the foule and false dealing of M. Edm. Buny Minister, in his late edition of the for∣mer booke.</title>
                 <author>Daunce, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A Christian directorie : guiding men to their saluation. Deuided into three bookes. The first vvherof apperteining to resolution, is only conteined in this volume, deuided into tvvo partes, and set forth novv againe vvith many corrections, and additions by th'authour him self, vvith reprofe of the corrupt and falsified edition of the same booke lately published by M. Edm. Buny. Ther is added also a methode for the vse of al; with two tables, and a preface to the reader, which is necessarie to be reade</title>
                 <author>Parsons, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Fr. Parsons’ Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>23 leaves, 883, 21 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>
      <hi>THE PREFACE CONTAINING THE CAVSES AND REASONS OF</hi> this nevv edition, as also a detection of the foule and false dealing of M. Edm. Buny Minister, in his late edition of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer booke.</head>
   <head type="sub">With certaine instructions very profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the reader.</head>
   <p>WHEN of late I had taken in hand to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish and send vnto thee (deare Christian reader) th' other two <note place="margin">The reason of printing againe this first booke of Resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> bookes, that were promised of this worke, I meane thos two which should treate of the right entrance and faithful perseuerance in the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of almightie God: I was moued by diuers frendes, first of al to put againe in print (in some better order then before) the first booke ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petteining to resolution. Wherunto I was the more easie to be induced, for that I perceaued many monethes before, that al the first copies of the said former booke, (though not so wel
<pb facs="5"/>
done as iustely I might haue wished) were vvholy dispersed and none remaining to be had.</p>
   <p>Secondly, it being now purposed that thes second and third bookes should passe forth in better print, paper, and character, then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer did, (wherin by some errour, as also by difficultie of the time, greate defect was found:) it seemed meere and requisice, that this first booke (of which th' other two doe depēd) should be made correlpondent vnto them in thes respectes also, and for that consideration to be reprinted.</p>
   <p>Wherunto when I had yelded; I resolued in like manner, to take the same first booke into my handes againe, &amp; to bestow a short renew vpon that which alredy was done, as wel to polish and fil vp some thinges, whetin before for want of leasure and time, I could not geue to my self any reasonable conteatation, as also to a dioine certaine new chapters, which part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in mine owne concept, and partly also vpon <note place="margin">Nevv ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</note> information of others, I thought not vnmeet for the furnishing of this first argument and subiect of Resolution. And standing determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vpon this, as also comprehending in mind and cogitation, the whole general corps of that which was to ensue in th' other two boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes: <note place="margin">The vvho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le vvorke deuided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to tvvo vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes.</note> I wel saw that I should not be able (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my first designement) to compact the whole, in one reasonable volume; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I resolued to deuide the same into two. Waerof the first should conteine matter of <note place="margin">1. Speculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue.</note> discourse, know edge, speculation, and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, to moue vs to resolue; the second should handle things appetteining to exercise, <note place="margin">2. Practive.</note> vse, and practise, for putting in execution our
<pb n="5" facs="5"/>
good desires after resolution.</p>
   <p>This being my cogitation, and the matter now wel forward for the print; I was enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of two other editions come forth of my <note place="margin">Tvvo edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the booke of Resolution vvithout the authors knowledge.</note> forsaid booke without my knowiedge, the one by a Catholique (as it seemeth) who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceuing ai copies of the former print to be spēt; for satisfying of them that desired the booke, procured the same to be set forth againe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit somewhat incorrected, and very disordre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not hauing the consent or aduise of such, as therin should haue geuen him best direction. The second was published by one Edmund Bany minister at Bolton Percy (as he writeth) <note place="margin">M. Ed. Bany.</note> in the liberties of Yorke; who with publicke licence vnder my Lord Archbishop of Yorke his protection, set forth the same to the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of his brethren; but yet so punished and plumed, (which he termeth purged;) as I could hardly by the face discerne it for mine, when it came vnto my handes, and I tooke no smale compassiō to see how pitifully the poore thing had bene handled.</p>
   <p>Of this edition then of M. Buny, (letting <note place="margin">Of M. Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies edition.</note> passe th' other as a matter onely of a discretion without malice,) I haue to a laertise the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der some few things, as wel for mine own dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, wherin I am charged by him, as also for the readers admonishment, not to thinke in deed that booke to be mine, which in my name this preacher hath published. And for vttering that which I haue to say in some kinde of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <note place="margin">Fovver pointes of this prefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce.</note> and conueniencie of methode; I shal touch breefly in this preface thos principal pointes insuing.</p>
   <p>First, how this booke came foorth from me <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> in the first edition.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="6"/>
Secondly, how it was set foorth afterwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> by M. Edm. Buny.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, what he meaneth by his treatise <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> annexed therunto, tending (as he saith) to paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, how the same booke commeth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> foorth at this present, and how the discret rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may vse it to his best commoditie.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>of the first edition.</head>
      <p>TO shew how this booke came foorth at the first; it shalbe requisite, perhaps, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peate breefly ī this place, the things that I saied in my first preface &amp; induction; which preface and induction, M. Buny hath left out in his edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, protesting, <hi>That he durst not in conscience and</hi>
         <note place="margin">In his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the reader.</note>
         <hi>in dutie tovvardes God, commend the same in my vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des vnto the reader.</hi> And yet trulie was ther no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in effect therin (Gentle reader) but that which here in this place shalbe repeated. First, that the primatiue occasion, inducing me to thinke vpon this worke, was the sight of a booke intituled, <hi>The excrcise of a Christian life,</hi> writen in Italian by Doctor Loartes of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie <note place="margin">The first occasion of setting so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orth the booke of Resolution.</note> of IESVS, and translated some years since by a vertuous learned gentilman of our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. Which booke for that I vnderstood of certaintie to haue profited many, towardes pietie and deuotion: I was moued to cause the same to be printed againe, with certaine am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple additions to the furnishing of some mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which that author had omitted: deuiding my whole purpose into three seueral bookes, wherof the first was to persuade mē vnto true resolution; the secōd to instruct vs how righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to beginne; the third, how a man may hould
<pb n="6" facs="6"/>
but and perseuer. Secondly I shewed, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing entred into the worke, and hauing set downe an other order and method to my self, then that treatise of D. Loartes did obserue; and hauing begunao the first booke touching resolution, whereof no part was handled in that other treatise: I found by experience, that I could not wel conioine th' one with th' other, if I would satisfie either th' order or argument by me conceaued: and therfore that I was infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to resolue vpon a further labour then at the first I had intended, and this was, to draw out the whole three bookes my self, not omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any thing that was in the said exercise, or other like good treatisses to this effect.</p>
      <p>And al this to the end, that our countrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men might haue some one sufficient directiō, for matters of spirit and vertuous life, among so many bookes of controuersies as haue bene writen &amp; are in writing daily. Which bookes (said I) albeit in thes our troblesome and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relous <note place="margin">Bookes of deuotion more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to good life thē bookes of controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies.</note> times, they be necessary for defence of our faith against so manie seditious innoua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as now daily are attempted: yet help they litle oftentimes to good life, but rather doe fil the heades and hartes of men with a spirit of contradiction and contention, which for the most part doe hinder deuotion, which deuotion is nothing els, but, <hi>A quiet, calme, and peacable state of our soule, induced <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> a iotful prompt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi>
         <note place="margin">The descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion.</note>
         <hi>and alacritis to the diligent execution of al things that doe or may apperteine to the honour and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of almightbe God.</hi> For which cause, the holie Apostle dehorted greatly his scholer Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie <note place="margin">2. Timot. 2.</note> from this contention and contradiction of wordes, affirming clearly, that it was profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to nothing but to subuect the hearers.</p>
      <p>
         <pb facs="7"/>
I affirmed further, that our forfathers were most happie in respect of vs, who receauing <note place="margin">Our fathers happie that builded, and contended not about the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> with humilitie one vniforme faith without contention or contradiction, from their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the holie Catholique Church, did attend onlie to build vpon that foundatiō good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes and vertuous life, as holie scripture com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth vs to doe; wheras we, spending now al our time in iangling about this first founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">1. Co. 3.</note> of faith, haue no leasure to build either gould or siluer theron, as th' Apostle exhorteth vs, but doe weary out our selues and our owne contentious spirits, without commoditie; dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with much labour and litle profit, with great disquiet and smale reward. For which cause I exhorted the discret reader of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer religion and faith he were, to moderate this heate and passion of contention, and to enter into the careful studie and exercise of good deedes, which are alwayes better among true Christians, then wordes; assuring him that this is the right way to obteine at Gods hāds, the light of true beleefe if he were amisse. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaging for example therof, the most famous conuersion of Cornelius the Gentile, whos ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous life, praiers, and almouse deedes, obtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at the hands of almightie God, (as S. Luke doth testifie) that S. Peter was sent vnto him for his instruction and establishment in right <note place="margin">Act. 10.</note> faith.</p>
      <p>I adioined moreouer, that ther being two parts of Christiā diuinitie, the one Theorike or speculatiue, belonging principally to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <note place="margin">Tvvo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian aiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisie.</note> discours, and beleefe; the second called practique or actiue, appertaining cheefly to action and execution: the first is more easy and common, then the second, bicause it is more
<pb n="7" facs="7"/>
easy to know then to doe; to discourse then to <note place="margin">Speculation easier then practise.</note> worke; to beleeue as we ought, then to liue as we should: and the things that a man hath to beleeue, are fewer then the things he hath to doe; learned in shorter time and with lesse dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie, thé the other are executed. Euen as we see by experience, that a breefe Cathechisme instructeth a man sufficiently in his faith; but al the bookes and sermons that we can read and heare, can not persuade the least part of men to performe so much in life, as by their voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is required. For which cause I said, that both our Saucour and his Apostles did treate much more in their speaches and writings of things to be done, then of things to be known; of vertuous liuing, then of right beleeuing. The like I saied, of Holie fathers and Doctours in the Church after them, as it may be sene in their homilies, sermons, exhortations, treati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, commentaries, and expositions.</p>
      <p>For this cause I saied also, that I had cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen to say some thing of this second part of Christian diuinitie appertaining to manners and direction of life, allotting to my self three principal pointes to be handled therin, and to be treated in three seueral bookes. The first wherof, to conteine the reasons and motiues <note place="margin">The three bookes of this Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiā directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, vvith their argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</note> which may stir vp a Christian man to make a firme and sound resolution. The secōd to pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe the particular meanes, how a man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out errour may put in vre and practise his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution made. The third, to declare certaine helpes and instructions, wherby to be able to perseuer vnto the end. The first of thes bookes, was then set downe and published. The secōd and third vpon necessarie causes were deferred for a time. And this is the summarie of al that
<pb facs="8"/>
was writen in my former preface and Induc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, suppressed now by M. Buny for meere conscience sake as he protesteth Wherin not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding I doe not easilie see, what may be accompted either so heinous or intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as his scrupulous conscience should be a fraide to let the same passe vnto the readers eare, except it were for that in a certaine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertisement, I desired eche Catholique to pray for our persecutours; or for that (perhaps) in the lines before repeated, I doe affirme faith, and beleef to be more common and easy then vertuous life; which notwithstanding I thinke, many Protestants in England wil confesse to be true; and wil easilie proue the same by the liues and actions of their own preachers and ministers. So much then for this: now let vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, how M. Buny hath set foorth the same booke with his purgation.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>of M. Bunis edition.</head>
      <p>M. Buny hauing taken this booke into his correction, as also into my Lord Archbishop of Yorke his protection; geueth it this title, <note place="margin">A title gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by M. Buny.</note>
         <hi>A booke of Christian exercise &amp;c. Perused and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied vvith a treatise tending to pacification, by Edm. Buny.</hi> And vnder the title, he writeth this sentence of scripture. <hi>IESVS Christ yester day and</hi>
         <note place="margin">Heb. 13.</note>
         <hi>to day and the same for euer.</hi> The misterie why he set thes wordes ther, him self alone (as I thinke) vnderstandeth and hard it were for other men to coniectare. If he had taken the wordes immediatly following in the same sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of S. Paul; they had bene more cleare, if not more also to the purpose. For they ar thes, <hi>Be not caried avvay vvith variable and strange doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines.</hi>
         <pb n="8" facs="8"/>
But let vs permit M. Buny to folow his <note place="margin">An old trick of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques to abuse sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple people vvith obs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure places of scripture. <hi>See Epiph. cont. heres. and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Quod vult Deum.</hi>
         </note> kinde. The holie fathers that write against auncient heretiques, doe note it for an old tricke of thos companions, to delight them selues, and deceue others with obscure places of scripture. And S. Peter expresly signifieth of the same men, that principally they vsed to take the said obscure sentences out of S. Paul, whence this by M. Buny is also cited. And this for the first page.</p>
      <p>In the next page, he placeth my Lord of Yorkes armes, accompanied with a paire of goodly crosse keyes, and a croune set ouer thé. Vnder which he writeth two latin verses, that <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.</note> say thus much in English, <hi>Thes armes haue bene</hi>
         <note place="margin">My L. of yorkes ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</note>
         <hi>noble in times past by ancient gentry and commendation of learning; but novv they are made more noble by the honour of Peter adioined vnto them.</hi> So that now (as ye see) it is both good doctrine, and very commendable in my Lords grace of Yorke to clame both keyes &amp; croune, from Peters seat, which in the Byshop of Rome is made so hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, and so bitterly inueighed against daily.</p>
      <p>After the armes, insueth the dedication of the whole booke, (treating of mortification <note place="margin">The epistle dedicaterie.</note> and contempt of the world) vnto his good Lordship. The reason of which dedication, M. Buny vttereth in thes wordes, <hi>For that hauing</hi>
         <note place="margin">In his Ep. dedicat.</note>
         <hi>had</hi> (saieth he) <hi>so longe experience of the vvorld as your Lordship haue, very liklihood teacheth that nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des you must grovve more and more from the loue therof. And it is sufficiently knovvn vnto al, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing</hi>
         <note place="margin">My L. of yorkes mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificatiō and calling vpō others.</note>
         <hi>found this mercy your self, you haue in like sort in this long course that God hath geuen you, much called on others to doe the like.</hi> In which wordes, we see, that touching the first pointe of my Lords wearines of this world, M. Buny proueth it
<pb facs="9"/>
very slenderly, by a bare likelihood only. Albeit in the second, of his Graces calling vpon others to like mortification, he alleageth the commō and sufficient knowledge of al, wherunto in reason eche man must yeld. And in truth I haue heard, how ther want not of diuers sortes and <note n="*" place="margin">His L. ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stise of Don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caster. Sir Robert Stapleton &amp; others.</note> sexes also, who can witnesse by experience of my Lordes good mortification, and how hotely he hath poursued them of late, for such affaires; and therfore (no doubt) but that this booke was very fitly dedicated to his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships protection.</p>
      <p>After the epistle dedicatorie vnto my Lord, ther foloweth a preface to the reader, wherin <note place="margin">The prefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to the reader.</note> M. Buny saieth, <hi>That by the litle that he hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stovvedin the studie of schole men, he vvil perceaueth that this booke vvas gathered out of them; vvho liuing in the corrupter time of the Church (as he speaketh) did most of al, by that occasion, treate of reformation of life, vvhen as others vvere rather occupied in controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies.</hi> To which I answer, that by the litle which <note place="margin">M Banies ignorance.</note> M. Buny here vttereth, he sheweth him self scarse worthy to be my Lord Archbishops chaplaine, (albeit to that dignitie much lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning be not required,) for that whosoeuer shal looke vpon the homilies, sermons, commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and other workes of S. Ambrose, Augustin, Gregorie, Maximus, Bede, Bernard, Anselme, and other that were not scholemen; and shal compare the same (touching exhortation and instruction to good life.) With the questions, distinctions, speculations and subtilties of Peter Lumbard, Hales, Scotus, Durand, Iandun Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preolus and others of that profession; shal ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily see, that in this matter ther is no compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son: and consequently that M. Bunis litle studie in the scholemen is lesse then nothing at al, not
<pb n="9" facs="9"/>
knowing so much as the very subiect and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument which they handle, or the manner how they handle the same. But al this was spoken <note place="margin">M. Bunies vanitie.</note> by M. Buny, for a vaine florish, and to persuade his reader, that as him self was very learned, so al that was in this booke being taken out of Dunsies (as now in England they tearme scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemen,) might appeare more contemptible in euery mans iudgement, and so in reason stand the more subiect to M. Bunis learned censure, to put out, cut of, mangle, change &amp; pare away whatsoeuer it pleased him. Yet protesteth he forsooth, very solemly, <hi>That he allovveth vvel of the matter in general, and that he is glad that some of</hi>
         <note place="margin">Ep. Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate.</note>
         <hi>vs also, haue taken paines in this kinde of labour, and that others of our prosession are sometimes occupied in reading such bookes.</hi> As who would say, that this were a strange and rare matter in our behalfe, either to write or reade bookes of this quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or argument.</p>
      <p>But here I would demande of M. Buny in sincerite, where or when, any of his religion did either make or set forthe (of them selues) any one treatise of this kinde or subiect? I mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, <note place="margin">Only Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques vvrite boo kes of deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> of deuotion pietie and contemplation? Of ours I can name infinite both of times past and present. As in times past S. Bernard, S. Bonauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, S. Auselme, Iohn Gerson, Thomas de kem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis, Dionisius Cathusianus, and others, whom no man wil deny to haue bene al of our reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. For this time present, the most excellent writinges of <hi>Ludouicus de Granada, Diegostella, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancus, Angerius,</hi> and this present booke with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite others, writen in this kinde doe testifie that this argument is not strange among Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques, but rather proper and peculier vnto them alone, seing that M. Buny is not able to
<pb facs="10"/>
name one on his side, from the first heretique that cuer wrote, vnto this daie, which of his owne accorde hath employed him self in this subiect, except it were of enuie and malice to defile and corrupt an other mans labours, to the end they should not worke that good ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, which otherwise they would, as M. Buny hath now done mine, and as one Rogers an other like companion (whom also he nameth) hath corrupted in englishe the most excellent <note place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 line">
               <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
            </gap> bookes.</note> worke of Thomas de Kempis of the imitation of Christ, striking out without conscience, whatsoeuer he pleaseth; whereas the same booke before, was truly set forth in our natiue tongue by a Catholique. An other also of the same crue, hath vsed the like violence vnto the holie meditations of S. Augustin and Saint Bernard, putting out and in what liked him best, and making thos blessed men to speake like protestātes, against whom they were most opposite enimies.</p>
      <p>The same hath M. Buny done vnto me, throughout my whole booke, and to most of the ancient Fathers therin named also, as after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward shalbe declared. And this shameles shift of corrupting other mens bookes, is an old oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation of heretiques from the beginning, as may appeare by the often complaintes of most ancient fathers, whos workes they were not ashamed to infect and corrupt whiles they were yet liuing. In respect of which impuden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie the holie Apostle S. Paul, wel prophetied of them to his scholer Timothie, that they should haue, <hi>cauteriatam conscientiam,</hi> a seared and yron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burned cōscience. And againe; that they should <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.</note> sinne wilfully and damnably in their owne <note place="margin">Tit. 3.</note> knowledge and iudgement. So we reade that
<pb n="10" facs="10"/>
old heretiques aduentured to corrupt not only priuate mens workes and treatises; but also the holic Canons of general Councels them selues, wherof therwere so many witnesses yet liuing to controle them. This may appeare by the greuous complaint which holie Athanasius <note place="margin">Athanas. apolog. 2. tp ad felic.</note> made in his time against the Arians for cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting the first Nicen Councel, and other fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers after him, for like heretical attemptes in their times; especially against the sacred text of diuine scripture, in corrupting whereof, al he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques from time to time haue bene most malepert, bold, and impudent, for shadowing their sectes with some shew of holie write.</p>
      <p>And to the ende M. Buny may not here eskape, and tel his reader that this was a spirit <note place="margin">That pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testātes doe follovv the same spirit of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note> of heretiques in old time, and not to be found in the protestantes of thes daies: I doe referre him not only to the collections which diuers Catholiques of this age haue gathered against them, touching thes attemptes; but also to the testimonies, confessions, and accusatiōs of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testantes them selues, one against and other for like impudencie. Especially against the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries, or thos that folowed th' opinion of Zuinglius (wherof I thinke M. Buny wil not deny him self to be one,) whom Martin Luther the father of al protestantes doth affirme, to be the most horrible corrupters of other mens bookes, that euer were; concluding his whole inuectiue against them with this sentēce, <hi>Their opinion of the Sacrament they began vvith lies, and</hi>
         <note place="margin">Luth. in Lipist. ad Ioan. Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uagium ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pogra. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent.</note>
         <hi>vvith lies they do desend the same; and they broch it abrode by the vvicked fraude of corrupting other mens bookes.</hi> The like he saieth and much more, of their corrupting the holie scriptures in diuers places.</p>
      <p>
         <pb facs="11"/>
But what? was Martin Luther him self ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reprehensible <note place="margin">
            <hi>The nevv brethrens testimonies, the one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the other.</hi> Zuing. li. de Sacra. fol. 412. 10. 2. Bez. in resp. ad defens. Castal. Itē in prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. Test. an 1556.</note> in this pointe, wherin he accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth so vehemently the Sacramentaries? No truly if we beleeue Zuinglius, who termeth him, both, <hi>A foule corruptour and horrible salsifier of Gods vvord, one that folovved the Marcionistes and Arians that rased out such places of holie vvrite as vvere against them.</hi> Beza accuseth Occolampa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius together with al his brethren the diuines of Basile for great impietie ī abusing the sacred scriptures traslated by them. The like he doth, but with much more vehemencie against Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stalio, an other brother, affirming his dealing with holie scripture, to be both <hi>bold, pestilent, sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious and ethnical.</hi> Carolus Molineus was a brother also of the same blood, and yet he cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesseth <note place="margin">Mol in trá. Test. noni. part. 11. fol. 110. Item part. 64. 65. 66. 74. 99.</note> of Caluin, <hi>That he made the text of the Gospel to leape vp and dovvne at his pleasure; that he vsed violence to the same, and added of his ovvne to the very sacred letter, for dravving it to his purpose.</hi> This same authour testifieth and crieth out of Beza, <hi>quod de facto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> mutat,</hi> that actually he is not ashamed to change in his translations the very text of holie scripture, when it maketh against his purpose.</p>
      <p>I might passe on further in stirring this euil sauoured sinke, of heretical iniquitie, discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and moued by their owne brethren, (for such is alwaies the agreement of like mates) were it not that the matter it self is vnfit for thes pages, and the dealiag of M Buny with me in this booke, shal easilie dec are their spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit <note place="margin">M. Bunies particuler dealing in editiō of the booke of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution.</note> and practise, if nothing therin were alleaged besides. Now then I come to shewe how dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terously he hath behaued him self in this edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my booke.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>FIRST IN A L</hi> places wher conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently
<pb n="11" facs="11"/>
he maye, he maketh me speake after <note place="margin">B V N. first deuise. To MAKE his aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries speake like Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantes.</note> the phrase of Protestantes; as for example, page 204. of his booke, wher I talke of Catholique preestes that heare confessions; he maketh me saie, <hi>men that be skilful to giue Counsail, &amp;c.</hi> Againe page 229. wher I saie out of holie scripture, <hi>here hence doe proceede al thos large promises, to virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, chastitie, voluntarie pouertie, &amp;c.</hi> he maketh me saie; <hi>hence doe procede thos promises to mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and nevvnes of life;</hi> &amp; he striketh out the scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures which I alleage for the other. In like maner page 368. when I saie, <hi>penance &amp; satissa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi> He maketh me saie, <hi>toile of amendment.</hi> And so in infinite other places (which were to long here to recite) M. Buny maketh me to speake like a good minister of England. Neither dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth he only thus with me; but ī like maner also with the ancient fathers, so long as by that meanes he can hold in with them, and when he can not, then he breaketh of and biddeth them a dieu.</p>
      <p>Let one or two examples serue for al; page 374. he ronneth on a whole halfe lease with S. Augustine, turning euery wher the wordes <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and satisfaction</hi> into repentance, vntil at <note place="margin">S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine taught to speake by M. Buny.</note> légth S. Augustine saieth, that this penāce must be inioined to the penitent by the preest: and ther M. Buny leapeth ouer that, but yet after a line or two, ioineth with him familiarly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and so runneth on, vntil he cometh to an other blocke, that cā not be remoued, wher he is inforced againe to leape ouer. So in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner page 209. wher S. August. recounteth the storie of S. Antonie the monke of Egipt; M. Buny leaueth out the name Monke, and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth S. Augustine to say; <hi>S Antonie that had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed a priuate and solitarie life in Egipt.</hi> And then
<pb facs="12"/>
wher S. Augustin writeth, <hi>that ther vvas a Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie of the same monkes, norished by S. Ambrose vvithout the vvalles of Millan;</hi> M. Buny maketh him to leaue out the names of Monkes &amp; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasterie, as also the name and almes of S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brose, &amp; to say onlie <hi>that others (as he then heard) did the like, euen in Millan it self.</hi> And finally, he frameth euery mans speech (wher he can) to such a stile as though he had bene trained vp in Iohn Caluins schole.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>SECONDLY,</hi> when he hath not commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie to change the very wordes, or els dareth <note place="margin">BVNY se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise. To INSERT parenthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses.</note> not for that they are scripture: then seeketh he to salue the matter with inserting some paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thesis, as though the same were of th' authour him self. So page 39. I say, that our Sauiour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing demanded by a certaine prince, how he might be saued; would geue him no other hope albeit he were a prince, but, <hi>if thou vvilt enter into life, kepe the commandementes.</hi> Wher M. Buny hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth <note place="margin">Math. 18. Marc 10. Luc. 19.</note> the matter out with this parenthesis, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>He vvould geue him no other hope (so long as he sought saluation by his vvorkes) but keepe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandementes, &amp;c.</hi> As though this prince had sought his saluation erroniously, &amp; that Christ had answered him in his error, &amp; so deceaued him. In like maner page 229. wher I alleage out of S. Paul and out of the reuelations, that men shalbe crowned in heauen according to their <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2. Apoc. 2.</note> fight in this life: M. Buny bodgeth in this pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renthesis (in some good measure) therby to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite the Holie Ghost in his meaning. Sembla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, page 229. when I alleage plainly the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of scripture, <hi>No man knovveth vvhether he be vvorthie of loue or hatred in Gods sight.</hi> He addeth <note place="margin">Eccle. 9.</note> this parenthesis (by outward things) as who would say, that by inward things ech man
<pb n="12" facs="12"/>
might know the same, which the Holie Ghost in this place did not forsee.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>THIRDLY</hi> when he can not accōmodate <note place="margin">BVN. third shift. MAROI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal annota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers fortes.</note> the matter ether by changing the wordes, or by putting in a parenthesis; then maketh he often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times certaine amotations in the margent; wherof certaine be idle and foolish, some be ridiculous and absurd, and other be wicked and tending to impietie.</p>
      <p>Of the first kinde, you may see examples page 171. wher, for that I saie, that our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <note place="margin">Annotatiōs fonde.</note> passions moderated, may serue vs to vertue; he maketh a longe and fond annotation, that we doe hold that the soule doth follow the temperature of the body, and thervpon doe grounde that our Lady was borne without ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal sinne; and other such docttines, which is neither so no so; nor the good man vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standeth what he saieth in this point nor what we hold, albeit (if you will beleeue him) he hath studied the schoelmen. Page 228. wher I saie that ther was no reason in our fight, whie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God should so much abuse his owne only sonne in this world, as to suffer so many indignities as he did: this man saith in a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical note, <hi>that ther vvas great reason in it.</hi> And so consequently, doth bring the inscrutable mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie of the sonne of God his abasement, (wherat S. Paul so often times wondered, and wherat the very Angels remaine astonished;) within the compasse of humane wit &amp; reason, which euery simple man by nature may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend.</p>
      <p>Of the second kinde, which are absurde, you may finde examples page 153. wherby a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal <note place="margin">2. Annotatiōs absurd.</note> note he discrediteth the beleefe of S. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian about the knowledge, that we shal haue
<pb facs="13"/>
of our fathers, mothers, and other acquaintan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce in heauen; as though one Cyprian with Christian men of reason, weighed not more in the affaires of our soule, then ten coople of Bunis, were they neuer so vendible. So againe page 214. vpon the religious rule of life which S. Augustine reporteth to haue bene reuealed to his mother for him to follow, M. Buny wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, <hi>That it vvas but a more careful indeuour in the</hi>
         <note place="margin">Aug. lib.8. confes. cap. 12.</note>
         <hi>vvay of godlines.</hi> And page 212. he addeth to the same, <hi>That it vvas but such, as vve al</hi> (saieth he) <hi>are bound vnto.</hi> But yet he that shal reade either S. Augustine him self, or els Possidonius his scholler declaring the particulers of that rule, <note place="margin">Possid. in vita Aug.</note> which he saw S. Augustine obserue in life, and prescribe vnto others: he wil easily confesse (I thinke) that how soeuer the ministers of England may be bounde therunto by M. Bunis word in this annotation, yet that they doe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue but few partes therof in conuersation: especially touching wiuing, I am of opinion, that M. Buny wil not denie S. Augustins rule to containe some-what more, thē he and his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes at this day doe practise. To like fond absurditie appertaineth that which is noted by him, page 300. wher I affirming that Gods se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret iudgement of ech mans particuler pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destination, is vncertaine to vs, he noteth in the margent, <hi>that calling and iustifying are very plaine and infallible tokens therof, and so far is it not vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the faithful;</hi> as who would saie, that it were an easie mater for him that hath faith, to know who are so called or iustified, as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite to assure a man of his particuler prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stination: whereas notwithstanding, Christ saith of the first, <hi>that many are called vvhich are not cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen,</hi> and of the second, S. Paul saith in him self
<pb n="13" facs="13"/>
         <hi>that he vvas guiltie of nothing, and yet therby he vvas not iustified.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Of the third kinde of annotations, which <note place="margin">3. Annota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</note> are both wicked &amp; impious, ther might many examples be alleaged, but thes few insuing shal suffise to discouer M. Bunies spirite. First then, page 212. as concerning the life of that holie and most wonderful man S. Antonie the first monke of AEgipt, whom al antiquitie so much <note place="margin">Athanas. in vita Anton. Aug lib. 8. cōfes. c. 12.</note> admired, and whom S. Athanafius in writing his life, so highely extolled, and whos doinges S. Augustin so hartely reuerenced, as he made the same a principal motiue &amp; paterne to his owne conuersion; (especially for that he tooke thos wordes of our Sauiour, <hi>Goe and sel al thou</hi>
         <note place="margin">Mat. 19.</note>
         <hi>hast and geue to the poore,</hi> as spoken to him self in particuler:) vpon this mans conuersion (I say) &amp; most wonderful life, M. Buny maketh this scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neful &amp; irreligious note, <hi>that it may vvel be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi>
         <note place="margin">Against S. Antonie.</note>
         <hi>vvhether he had in that place sufficient ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvorke of thos his doings, vnles he had some other special motion besides.</hi> Condemning herin not only S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonie, but also S. Athanasius, S. Hierome, S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine &amp; al other fathers, that so highely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend S. Antonie for putting in execution thos wordes of our Sauiour.</p>
      <p>To like purpose or rather more vvickedlie, he maketh an other annotation page 308. vpon <note place="margin">Against S. Augustine.</note> the most famous conuersion of S. Augustin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded by the pen of that holy father him self, to vvit, <hi>that some pointes of the storie vvhich S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin vvriteth, are such, as a man may as vvel doubt they proceeded of Sathan as of God;</hi> therby to bring in question that excellent mans cōuersion. But of al other, that annotation of his, is most ridieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <note place="margin">Against our B. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> die.</note> and yet blasphemous, wher he wil needes bring in our blessed Ladie to haue brokē fower
<pb facs="14"/>
seueral commandemēts (forsooth) at one clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe, for that she defended not her sonne vpō the Crosse. For, page 369. wher I in commendation of the confessiō which the theefe made, said in my booke, that it was at such a time, when al the world abādoned our Sauiour, and the very Apostles thē selues either doubted or lost their faith of his Godhead: this man noteth in the margēt, <hi>that the blessed Virgin likevvise vvas by, and saied nothing (that vve reade of) in his defence: a plaine breach (saieth he) of the first, fist, sixt, &amp; ninth cōmando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</hi> A strange matter, that thes men should be so desirous to skore vp &amp; make Catalogues of our Ladies sinnes which she neuer commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. But let vs see with what shew of reason.</p>
      <p>He saith that she brake fower commandementes at one time; Let vs then examine them what they are. The first commandemēt (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <note place="margin">Aug. quest. 71. in Exo. &amp; con. 1. in Psal. 32.</note> as S. Augustine in old time, &amp; Catholiques now a daies are accustomed to number them) is; <hi>Thou shalt haue no strāge Godes before me, nor make vnto thy self any grauen Idole to adore the same.</hi> The fift is, <hi>Thou shalt not kil.</hi> The sixt, <hi>Thou shalt not commit adulterie.</hi> The ninth, <hi>Thou shalt not couet thy neighbours wife.</hi> And this, as Catholiques doe number the commandementes. But according as some protestantes wil recon the same, The fift is, <hi>Honor thy father &amp; thy mother.</hi> The sixt, <hi>Thou shalt not kil.</hi> The ninth, <hi>Thou shalt not beare false vvitnes against thy neighbour.</hi> Now thē (gentle rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) consider with indifferencie, how in reason <note place="margin">Great ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surditie &amp; impietie of M. Buny.</note> it may be said, that the blessed Virgin, the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred mother of God, for not defending her sonne vpon the Crosse, against the Magistrates &amp; soldiers, did breake any of thes fower com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandementes; that is to say, did either make vnto her self any strange God or Idole, or did
<pb n="14" facs="14"/>
dishonour her father and mother; or did cōmit <note place="margin">Maruelous absurdities.</note> murder or adulterie; or did beare false witnes against her neighbour; or did couet her neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours mate; whether (I say) it be credible, that in not defending her sonne at that instant, she committed any one of thes hainous &amp; mortal crimes, and much more, whether she cōmitted fower of them together, as M. Buny affirmeth? Let (I say) the indifferent and Christian reader iudge of this accusation, as also consider, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">M. Bun. the. diuels pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor.</note> M. Buny be not worthio of a very good fee at the deuils hādes, for indeuoring to bring into his clawes, so rich a pray, as was the most excellēt pure &amp; sacred mother of our Sauiour, by accusing her of fower deadlie sinnes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</p>
      <p>
         <hi>AND THVS</hi> much of annotations; pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing ouer diuers other thinges that might be <note place="margin">BVN. third snift. THEV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting out.</note> examined if time and place did not prohibite. But the greatest shift of al others which M. Buny hath to ridde his handes, when nether changing of the wordes, not putting in of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reutheses, nor annotations in the margent wil cleare and pacific the matter; is, to strike and thrust out what so euer he misliketh, whether they be my wordes, or els the discourses of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient fathers, yet authorities them selues of sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred scripture. For vnderstanding wherof it is to be cōsidered, that first, generally whersoeuer he findeth the mētion of certaine thinges that please him not, as of abstinence, fasting, chaste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the bodie, penance, satisfaction, virginitie, merit, hier, gayning of heauen, laboring for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, or the like: he commonly striketh al out together with th' Authours that treat therof, or els so mangleth the same as is pitiful to behold.</p>
      <p>Secōdly whatsoeuer authoritie commeth in
<pb facs="15"/>
his way, which he cānot mangle, out it goeth <note place="margin">Impudent dealing in striking out. Monkes.</note> without redēption, be it Father, Doctor, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel or Scripture. Herof you may see exāples, Page 29. of his booke, wher he thrusteth out S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome and Ioannes Cassianus, for that they mē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō Mōkes of the primatiue Church. So againe page 98. he thrusteth out S. Cyprian &amp; Possido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, for that they geue testimonie of an appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritiō <note place="margin">Apparitiōs of Christ.</note> which Christ our Sauiour made to a godly man at his death. In like maner, Page 109. he trusteth out S. Ambros, S. Augustin, S. Gregorie and S. Bernard together, for that they persuade men by their examples to be affeard of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie. Further, Page 98. he striketh out S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin. <note place="margin">Purgatorie.</note> S Gregorie and venerable Bede, with their large discourses which they make concerning appatitions of certaine Angels to godlie peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. So againe, Page 305. he thrusteth out the <note place="margin">Apparitiōs of Angels.</note> exāple of S. Paul the first heremite with the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of S. Hierome that wrote his life. And this in hatred of Monkes and heremites. After <note place="margin">Neremites.</note> that againe, Page 374. he thrusteth out S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin with al that he cā alleage about satissactiō <note place="margin">Satisfactiō. Penance.</note> and final penance. Page 60. he thrusteth out the weping, fasting, watching, lying on the ground, wearing of sack clothe and other bodilie pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishmētes <note place="margin">Bodily af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction.</note> that King Dauid vsed vpon him self, albeit they be recorded and set downe in holie scripture. Page 169. he thrustath out the exāple of S. Paul th' Apostle how he was assisted &amp; made <note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.</note> able by Gods holie grace, to resist &amp; ouercome the temptatiōs of the flash, to the end (by like) <note place="margin">Resisting of temptatiōs.</note> that no man should take courage by that exā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to fight &amp; resist thes temptations as he did. Page 2. he striketh out the promisses made in scripture to virginitie, chastetie, golding of <note place="margin">Promisses to Virginitis.</note> our selues for the kingdome of heauen, volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie
<pb n="15" facs="15"/>
pouertie and the like: al (I say) he thru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth out, together with the scripture alleaged for the same. And finally, not to hold the reader any longer in the enumeratiō of thos thinges, which he shal finde almost in euery other leafe of the booke: Page 157. he thrusteth out not only S. Augustin talking of the price of heauē, and of the facilitie to gaine the same; but also striketh out in like maner the very wordes of <note place="margin">Christes vvordes thrust out by M. Buny. <hi>Mat. 11.</hi>
         </note> Christ him self, saying, <hi>the kingdome of heauen doth suffer violence, &amp; men doe lay handfast vpon it by force.</hi> And what may be said then (gentle reader) of thes mē, who spare neither Fathers, Doctours, Prophetes, Apostles, nor Christ him self, when they stand in the way against their foolis he herefies?</p>
      <p>
         <hi>AND THIS</hi> of thrusting out. But now if <note place="margin">OF man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling. OTHER mens say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</note> I would speake of mangling. I might say much more, but that this place beareth it not, and therfore thous halt be content (good reader) to accept of one example only among infinite that might be alleaged, and by this one, thou maist make vnto thy self some certaine conie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of the rest. Page 367. it is handled and proued by me against the impedimēt of delay, how that vvee by deferring our cōuersion, doe alwaies binde our selues to greater penance &amp; satisfaction afterwardes, &amp;c. In which discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se, M. Buny first in steed of the worde, Penāce, vseth alwaies the worde, repētance, (as though al were one) and so runneth on smoothly so long as it wil hold out. And as for the worde Satisfaction, for that he had no other word to put in for it, he thrusteth it cleane out. Then commeth he to S. Cyprian, who saith that, <hi>a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligint</hi>
         <note place="margin">Cyp. lib. de laps. &amp; l. 5. epist. 9. ad Corn.</note>
         <hi>and long medicine is to be vsed to a deepe sore;</hi> which wordes M. Buny admitteth and setteth
<pb facs="16"/>
downe as good and currant. But the other part of the sentēce immediatly following, was, <hi>that</hi>
         <note place="margin">The mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sare of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</note>
         <hi>our penance must be no lesse thē vvas our fault cōmitted,</hi> which part M. Buny striketh out of the text, as also al the rest ensuing, wherin S. Cyprian pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribeth, that this penance must be made with teares, watching, wearing of hear-cloth, &amp; the like, which seeme to be thinges nothing plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant to the bodie of a Minister.</p>
      <p>After S. Cyprian followeth S. Augustin in the very same page, affirming; <hi>That it is not sufficient for a sinner, to change his maners, &amp; to leaue of to sinne, except he make satisfaction also to God for his sinnes past by sororrful penance, geuing of almes &amp;c.</hi> With which wordes M. Buny would haue nothing to doe, for that they were incorrigible, &amp; therfore he' thrust thē quite out: yet out of S. Hierome, that in the third place insued, he was content to admit thes wordes, <hi>Our bodie that hath liued in many delightes must be chastised vvith affliction; our</hi>
         <note place="margin">Hier. ep. 27 ad Lustoch.</note>
         <hi>long laughing must be recōpenced vvith much vveping.</hi> But the wordes immediatly following in the same seutence, (<hi>our soft linning and fine silke apparel must be changed into sharpe hear-cloth</hi>) seemed to harde to this delicate doctour, and therfore he thrust them quite out.</p>
      <p>In the end of the ranke, came graue S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bros, affirming, <hi>That vnto a great vvound, a deepe</hi>
         <note place="margin">Intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dealing.</note>
         <hi>&amp; long medicine in needful;</hi> Which wordes M. Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ay very quietly and courteously let passe. But vpon th' other that immediatly followed, he gaue a deade blow, &amp; thrust them by head &amp; shoulders out of the booke, to wit, <hi>Grāde seelus, grādē necessariā habet satisfactionē.</hi> A great offence, requireth of necessitie a great satisfaction. <note place="margin">Ambros. ad virg. Laps. cap. 8.</note>
      </p>
      <p>Now thē (gentle reader) what shal we thinke or say of thes mē or of their maner of dealing?
<pb n="16" facs="16"/>
Haue they honest meaning trow you? Haue <note place="margin">A conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration vpon the premis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses.</note> they sidelitie? Haue they a conscience? Haue they respect of God or man, that deale in this order? Is it hard to found any new religiō, or to defend it, or to auouch what folie or falsaood soeuer, by this maner of proceeding? If thes mē had habilitie to doe what their consciences would permit thē in the world abrod, what an alteration, what a subuersiō, what a metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phosis would they make in al matters of anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie? If they had to them selues the setting forth of the holy fathers &amp; doctours workes, how would they loppe and circumcise the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me? how would they set them foorth in their Ierkins, yea, barehose and doubletes, cutting of al other garmentes and furniture that liked thē not, or were not sutable to the season of thes mens senses? If thes men (I say) had the keeping of al antiquities, of fathers, Councels, and scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, &amp; that to thē selues alone in their owne custodie, without the knowledge or cōtradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of any one Catholique, for the space of only fiue hundred yeares together, (as they graunt we held thē al in our handes for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand,) what maner of bookes (trow you) should we finde them? How currant and absolute for the protestant religiō? No doubt but we should heare thē speake euē as Iohn Caluin speaketh in al matters of controuersie, or rather as that good man for the time would haue them to speake, vnto whos handes the last edition of such workes should be committed.</p>
      <p>And thus much shal suffice for discouerie of M. Bunies editiō of my booke, now remaineth ther only a word or two to be saide of the treatise which he adioined, tēding (as he saith) to Pacification.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <pb facs="17"/>
      <head>Of M. Bunies Pacification.</head>
      <p>AND first of al, a man would thinke that M. Buny did take but a very strange way to pacification, in offering me the greate iniurie which before hath bene shewed, in his editiō. But for that he pretendeth his peace to be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the general, <hi>by labouring the aduersaries,</hi> as his phrase is: I shal be content to passe ouer my particuler, and to examine peaceably what he saieth, and how he laboreth vs to that effect.</p>
      <p>But here againe at the very first enterance, ther riseth a new stoppe against al vnion or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification with vs, for that he is so singulerly persuaded of the rare light and knowledge of truth which they haue alone among them sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, as he dareth to pronounce, <hi>That (to their knovvledge) God neuer yet bestovved the like on others.</hi>
         <note place="margin">Intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble pride of beretiques.</note> In which asseueratiō for that he excepteth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the fathers or doctours of the primatiue Church, nor yet th' Apostles them selues, whom we hoped to haue had at least wise for iudges and arbiters in making this peace: what proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie can ther be of vnion or composition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mōg vs, seing that at the very first word, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his cause better, not only then ours, but also then the case and condition of any other whatsoeuer, since Christes departure frō earth or before? But yet this I wil let passe also, as a vaunt proceeding of an humour peculier to mē of his stampe. For if you goe to al the petie se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes of thes our times, or of any other times that haue bene from the beginning: ech one wil sing the self same song, affirming euery other bodies candel to be out, but only theirs. And if they should not say so, they were not sectes or sectaries, for that they acknowledged
<pb n="17" facs="17"/>
not their true mother, which is pride, and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularitie.</p>
      <p>After this his proud enterāce, he beginneth, his seely discourse: and for methodes sake, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth many diuisions and subdiuisions, euery thing running therin by couples, wherin he is so fertile and abundant, as by methode he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundeth al memorie. But yet as I may, I wil here recite the cheef pointes therof.</p>
      <p>First then he saith, that ther is great reasō why we should ioine with them, and none at al why they should yeld to vs. The first he proueth, for that it becommeth the Church of God to be at <note place="margin">VVhy vve should ioine vvith pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testantes.</note> vnitie in it self. Which reason how far it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth his purpose, the reader can consider. The second he declareth, for that the gaine that they should receaue by comming to vs, in his opinion should be very smal, both touching <note place="margin">VVhy they vvil not ioine vvith vs.</note> matters of religion as also of state. For in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion he maketh his accompt, that they should haue nothing more thē now they haue, except only certaine Sacramentes, Images, and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies (which he calleth representations,) al which he esteemeth of smale auaile. In mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of state likewise, he supposeth the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities would be few and litle: as namely to be deliuered from the Popes curse, which he saieth, they finde now by experience, not to be so hurtful, as hertofore it was esteemed; which reason (as you know) may as wel serue against Godes curse also, for that it doth not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies shew forth presently his sensible effect.</p>
      <p>Next after this, he declareth how that by <note place="margin">Their hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to vs.</note> yelding to vs, they should not only not recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue gaine, but also great hurtes, &amp; that in double maner. First in religion, wherin among other things they should be bounde to coafession &amp;
<pb facs="18"/>
penance, which thinges (saith he) <hi>are burdensome and</hi>
         <note n="*" place="margin">So much the more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and of Gods special ordinance, for that othervvise men vvould neuer haue receaued thē.</note>
         <hi>abhorring from mans nature.</hi> Then in state, for that by this meane, they should come vnder the gouernement of the Byshope of Rome, which he estemeth intolerable: adding further, that this only reason of state holdeth many of their side, from comming to vs, who otherwise in conscience would-haue no scrupule at al; which is such a confessiō, as I meruail that euer my Lord Archebishope would let it passe in print. For howsoeuer this poore Minister to terrifie the common people, deuiseth bugges vpō the Ecclesiastical authoritie of the bishope <note place="margin">Note this.</note> of Rome, if it should be restored in England againe, yet euery man of reason can consider with him self, that the Emperour, the kinges of Spaine, France, Polonia and other Princes, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the-same authoritie, doe finde no such incōueniēces, as neither our Princes of Englād euer did, for so many ages together, when they were more potent and glorious then they haue bene since the suppression therof. Wherfore if this reason only doe stay so many from vs, as M. Buny affirmeth, it is very like we shal haue the greater part shortly, when God shal open their vnderstanding in a matter that in it self is so plaine and palpable.</p>
      <p>This being done, he commeth to shew the cōmodities that we should receaue by ioining with them, and thos also (after his maner) he <note place="margin">The cōmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to vs in ioining vvith thē.</note> maketh of two sortes. First in religion, and thē in our ciuil state. In religiō (saith he) we should first receaue, the free vse of holie seriptures, (as though amōg vs now ther were no vse therof,) and then also we should be deliuered from the burden of confession and penance, as also from <note place="margin">religion.</note> al vowes of chastitie, pouertie, and obedience.
<pb n="18" facs="18"/>
And finally we should so cleaue to Christ alone (saith he) <hi>as vve should abandon al other helpes both in heauen and earth, of Angels, Saintes, other men, as also our ovvne.</hi> Which (saith he) were a great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage. And then he maketh a solemne prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>station in thes wordes. <hi>If any people can be found</hi>
         <note place="margin">The Proto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation.</note>
         <hi>in the vvorld, that doe more abādone al other meanes in heauen &amp; earth, then vve doe, then vve must pronounce against our selues, that in this respect they are nerer to this aduantage then vve art.</hi> Vnto which protesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion notwithstanding, I doubt M. Buny (if he should be wel vrged) would be very much ashamed to stand and cleaue. For albeit I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, that he and his felowes doe very litle in deede wherby to helpe them selues by their workes, yet by this reason they should doe far better, ī doing nothing at al. For he that should neuer pray, nor desire other men to pray for him, he that should neuer fast or doe other good deede, but should rather defie the same, and lay al vpon Christes passiō, he should more abandone al other helpes and meanes both in heauen and earth besides Christ, then many of the best protestantes doe.</p>
      <p>Next in our ciuil state, he saith that we should greatly be bettered by ioyning with <note place="margin">Cōmodities by yelding, in our ciuil state.</note> them, being made partakers of the blessednes of England, which is greater (as he saith) at this time, <hi>then euer it vvas since the lande vvas first inhabited.</hi> Wherof he seemeth to alleage two reasons or causes. First, for that Protestantes in <note place="margin">Intellerable lying flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie.</note> thes temporal affaires are alwaies prosperous, for (saith he) how soeuer it goe with others that are not frindes to the ghospel, yet shal the fauorers therof alwaies <note n="*" place="margin">Hovv doe they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sper at this day in Frā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and Flā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders?</note> prosper: howsoeuer it be with the residue of the children of Israel, yet the tribe of Iuda shal alwaies florish. The
<pb facs="19"/>
other places the people are going vnder their burdens, but in England al is mirth and saftie. The second cause of this blessednes of England is, for that England (saith he) is gouerned by a Prince of their owne countrie, one that dealeth mildly with them, one that sendeth not ther pleas abrod to other cōsistories, one that drieth them not vp with exactions. And when conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient collections are made, the mony that is exacted of subiectes is not sent (saith he) <note n="*" place="margin">Note this blessednes.</note> out of the realme to the maintenance of forraine powers, but is imployed at home, to their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and defence. Wherin notwithstanding it seemeth that this good man, talketh rather by meditation or fiction, then by any great intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence he hath in such affaires.</p>
      <p>After al this, he goeth about to remoue certaine graue impedimentes, which he ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineth <note place="margin">The remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments.</note> doe let many Catholiques from coming vnto their side. For which cause he sheweth, first, that we Catholiques should not leese al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together our credites by making vs Protestan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, or at least wise we should not leeso the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me <note place="margin">Of discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</note> with them that be good and of their side: or if we did somewhat impare the same, yet patiēce were to be vsed, for the Ghospels sake. In like maner he sheweth that the holie sain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of heauen would not be angrie with vs (as we seeme to doubt) for leauīg their patronage. Also that keruers, kandlemakers, belcasters, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganistes, and other such like, who might feare <note place="margin">Of hurtes.</note> to want by following the Ghospel, albeit in truth they should leese no smale part of their gaine, yet might the matter be eased, and they comforted otherwise.</p>
      <p>Thus discourseth this wise man in very great sadues. And after al this, he hādleth diuers other
<pb n="19" facs="19"/>
pointes both of controuersies in religion, &amp; of the harde dealings of the Protestant magistra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te towardes Catholiques in Englād, wherwith he supposeth many are staied from comming vnto them, but al, with as great discretion and foundation as he hath done the former, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding of vs in very good earnest, why we should stand so much vpon Limbus Patrum, vpon Christes descending into hel, vpō real pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, freedome of wil, and merit of workes, vpon traditions, preestood, and sacrifice, vpon worshiping of Saintes and Images, mariage of preestes, inherent iustice, and the fiue Sacramē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that we numbre more then they doe? why (I saie) we should so relie and sticke vpon thes thinges, as for their sakes not to ioyne with thē and be Protestantes, wheras notwithstanding al thes thinges, the Protestātes saith (as he saith) <note place="margin">Atheisme.</note> and ours is al one in substance, and we al are members of one true Catholique and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolique Churche, albeit some of vs be some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what better members in that Church then others.</p>
      <p>And this last point of the Church (therby <note place="margin">Hovv by N. Buny vve are al of one Church.</note> to allure vs the more) he vrgeth very often and earnestly: to wit, that we are al members of one true Church, reprehending greatly his fellow Ministers and brethren, who, <hi>vpon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>discrete Zeale</hi> (as he saith) <hi>vrged first this separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and did vvrite in not so sensed a maner as they</hi>
         <note place="margin">Page 108.</note>
         <hi>ought to haue done,</hi> adding further; <hi>vve are to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifie that of departing from the Church, ther ought to be no question at al among vs.</hi> But what is the cause (thinke you) of this so greate and sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine curtesie which now at length M. Buny against al custome of his brethren doth offer vnto vs? you shal heare it vttered (if you plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se)
<pb facs="20"/>
in his owne wordes, <hi>for by cons<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
               <desc>•••</desc>
            </gap>ing so far vvith them</hi> (saieth he) <hi>as to graunt that vve are not both of one Church; vve bring our selues to needles trouble. For that it is greate probabilitie vvith them, that so vve make our selues aunsvverable for to finde out a seueral and distinct Church from them, from vvhich vve descende, vvhich hath continued from the Apostles age to this present, els that needes vve must acknovvledge that our Church is sprung vp of late, or at least, since thers:</hi> This is his confession; which <note place="margin">VVhy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testātes are novv so kinde as to make atto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement vvith vs.</note> we hauing heard, we neede not stande any longer in doubt, wherfore he is become so kinde, as at length to make vs al of one true Catholique and Apostolique Church with them, whom hitherto they haue detested as the Sinagogue of Antechrist. Why also M. Buny tooke in hande to write this treatise of pacification, to wit, for that in deede (as he confessed before) <hi>He novv perceaueth that men held vvith them, rather for respect of state and ciuil commodities, then of conscience and beleefe.</hi> Which <note place="margin">The only motiue to protestant religion in England.</note> regarde of temporal commoditie in very truth (Gentle reader) is the only reason or baite that they can lay before vs at this time, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to moue vs to come vnto their parte. Which respect and motiue notwithstanding, our Lord knoweth how bare and brickle a matter it is, and how longe or litle while it may endure. But this only thing set a side, in al other respectes, reasons, allurementes, moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, or considerations, which heauen or earth can yeld, wherby to stirre a Christian minde to embrace any religion, they are al for vs, and none for them; as perhaps hereafter may be declared more largelie, in some special trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisse, which by occasion of this may be taken in hand. In the meane space let this suffice for
<pb n="20" facs="20"/>
answere of so much as M. Buny hath writen in his pacification.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Of this present edition vvith certaine instructions to the Reader.</head>
      <p>THER remaineth now then (gentle rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) for the ending of this preface, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monish the only in a worde or two, what thou hast in this later edition more then in the former, and how thou maist reape the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie that is intended and wished to the therin. First, the whole booke hath bene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uewed, and both amplified and bettered in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers <note place="margin">1. The vvhole booke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uevved.</note> pointes throughout al the chapters that doe remaine as before. Secondly, the title ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is altered as may appeare in the beginning for that the other booke of Christian exercise, <note place="margin">2. The title altered.</note> since the first edition therof, hath bene set fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orth a parte by it self.</p>
      <p>Thirdly, diuers treatises and chapters haue bene wholy altered, especially in the first <note place="margin">3. Diuers treatisses altered.</note> part, wher, vpon a purpose of greate breuitie which in the beginning was conceaued, (but afterwardes could not be held) many things were shifted ouer, and diuers discourses knit vp with more imperfection then in the second part therof.</p>
      <p>Fourthly, sundrie new chapters and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises haue bene added in this edition. And thes <note place="margin">4. Nevv chapters added and vvhy.</note> partly of mine own liking, imagining that the matter might (perhappes) affect other men as much as it did me; among which I may accompt the chapter of examples of true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution, and some other: Partely also vpon aduertisement of good and reuerend Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique preestes that liue in England, who fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="21"/>
by their experience in dealing with mens soules, (as my self also did,) that this long time of schisme and sectes, wherein they heare nothing but weangling and contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in matters of courtouersies, (their life in the meane space running at al libertie without discipline, and loding their conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with infinite burden of sinne;) hath wroght in mens mindes a certaine contempt and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les insensibilitie in thes affaires, esteeming al things to stand vpon probabilitie only of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute to and fro, and so by litle and litle, doth <note place="margin">The gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of faith that come by he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie.</note> bring them also to thinke the same of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian religion it self, imagining that the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, Turkes, Saracens and other enimies ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, (being worldly wise men) may haue as greate reason perhaps to stande against the same, as thes later learned men of oar owae time haue, to staud in so many rankes and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uisions of sectes against the Catholique faith, and as the old Philosophers pretended to haue against the being of one God him self.</p>
      <p>Thes thinges (I saie) being so; (which is alwaies the effect of diuision and heresie,) thos vertuous and discrete men were of opinion <note place="margin">The reason of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler chapters added of nevv.</note> that it should not be amisse in this second edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to adioyne two chapters of the certaintie of one God, and of our Christian faith and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Besides this, I was admonished by the writinges of our aduersaries since the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishing of my first edition, how they misliked two principal pointes in that booke. First, that I speake so much of good workes and so litle of faith: secondly, that I talked so largely of Godes iustice and so breefly of his mercie. In both which pointes, albeit an indifferent man might haue bene satisfied before, and easilie
<pb n="21" facs="21"/>
perceaue that the aduersarie doth but picke quarels of calumniation: yet to giue more ful contentement in this matter, euen vnto our enemies: I haue besides that which is spoken els wher, (and namely in the 2. and 4. chapters touching faith,) adioyned also a special chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the two seueral partes of Christian profession, which are beleefe and life. And for the second, I haue framed a whole new cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter in the begiuning of the second part, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled; against dispaire of Godes mercie. Thos were the causes of my large and ample addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in this booke.</p>
      <p>And yet was ther besides al thes, one cause more, which also I conceaued by information <note place="margin">An other cause of the amplificatio of tins bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oke.</note> of others. An I this was, that diuers persons (as I was tolde) hauing desire in them selues to reade the former booke, but yet being weake and feartul to be touched so nere in conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, as they imagined this booke would doe; durst neuer intermedle therwith, being infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that ther was nothing in the same wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to intertaine them selues, but only such vehement matter of persuasiō, as would troble and afflict thom. For remedie of which incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniencie (if it were an inconueniencie,) I haue inserted diuers chapters and discourses of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters more plausiole, and of them selues more indifferent, whervvith the reader may solace his minde, at such times as he findeth the same not willing to feele the spurre of more earnest motion to perfection.</p>
      <p>And to the end he may the better be able to serue him self at al times and to al purposes, <note place="margin">The reason of the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioined in the ende.</note> of whatsoeuer is contayned within this booke; I haue thought good to set downe in the end of al, a short draught or methode for
<pb facs="22"/>
the particuler vse of euery part and parcel therof; how it may sorue either to prayer or meditation, or els to instruction, exhortation, consolation, or other effect according to the time and place, or to the neede, state, condition &amp; other qualetie, of the person that shal come to reade the booke.</p>
      <p>Now then (good reader and my deare Christian brother) hauing nothing els at this time to admonishe the of; I wil end this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face <note place="margin">The conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion vvith certaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions.</note> and remit the to the reading of the booke it self that followeth; exhorting the most ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly for thine owne soules sake in the tender bowels of our sweet Sauiour IESVS, that thou reade the same with attention, as matter that appertaineth nearest of al other vnto the, and with al to yeld most hartie and humble thākes to almightie God, that in his Catholique Church fayleth not from time to time to sende diuers strange and stronge meanes, whereby to stirre vp men to consideration of their estate, and to the gayne of their saluation in the life to come. This (I say) by almightie Gods diuine goodnes and prouidence, is ordinarie in his <note place="margin">True trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion only in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church.</note> spouse the Catholique Church, wher his spirit abideth vntil the worldes end: and it is so in her alone, as it is her proper and peculier posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and neuer trulie to be founde in them, who liue out of her, albeit for a time and in some pointes they maye haue a shewe or shadoe therof. This we see fulfilled in al he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques and sectaries both of old and of our daies, who albeit some times they wil seeme to writ bookes, of <hi>institutions to manners and good life;</hi> yet their doctrine therin being as wilde, as their faith is wandering; they neuer bring any thing to passe, but from worse to worse,
<pb n="22" facs="22"/>
wherof the whole world at this daye doth giue experience. The reason of this in general, <note place="margin">VVhy no heretique treateth sincerly of deuotion.</note> may be taken from the nature and spirit of heretiques, described vnto vs for our admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment in holie scripture, wherof one prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal point is, that they shalbe as S. Paul saith, <hi>Sine pace,</hi> without al rest or peace, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.</note>
         <hi>alvvaies learning and neuer attaining to the knowledge of truth.</hi> They shal bestow al their time in iangling and quarreling, and in the meane space, as S. Peter wel noteth, <hi>they shal vvalke according to their ovvne concupiscences,</hi> albeit <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.</note> they talke neuer so much of <hi>mortification</hi> and of their <hi>quickning spirite,</hi> for which cause he calleth them also, <hi>illusores,</hi> mockers and deceauers; that is, as S. Paul seemeth to interprete the same; <hi>fellovves that vvith seigned vvordes shal make their ovvne gaine, and vvhich hauing a shevv of pietie, shal (in life) deny the force or vertue thereof.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>And this why heretiques in general can neither teach true pietie and deuotion, not <note place="margin">VVhy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testantes of alother se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries can not teach true pietie.</note> yet giue example therof in their owne liues. But now if we looke into the particuler sectes that are of this our most vnhappie time; we shal finde a more peculier reason why they in special, much lesse may doc the same. For that in truth the very groundes of their opinions doc resist altreating of such affaires; neither can you vrge almost any one point of true pietie, but that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> must impugne some prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal article of their doctrine. As may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by that which hath bene declared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, concerning the places both of fathere and scriptures thrust out by M. Buny in my former booke, wherof also it were not hard to make diuers most cuident demonstrations in this place.</p>
      <p>
         <pb facs="23"/>
For, if (for example sake) you exhort men to labour for their owne saluation, as S. Paul <note place="margin">Examples bovv prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantes can not teach piesie of life vvithout imparing their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</note> did, Philip. 2. ver. 12. then you teach them to put confidence in their owne workes, which with protestantes is abhominable. If you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage men to suffer in respoct of rewarde, as Christ did, Matth. 5. ver. 12. then fal you flatly vpon the doctrine of merite. If you tel them that heauen is put in their owne han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to gaine, as our Sauiour did, Math. 11. ver. 12. then allow ye not only of morite, but also of free wil. If you wish men to liue in feare and trembling in respect of Gods secret iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and of the vncertaintie of our salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as S. Paul did, Phi. 2. ver. 12. Hob. 3. ver. 14. and S. Peter. 2. ep. 3. ver. 17. then impeach you the certaintie of protestantes predestination. If you counsail men to make amendes by good workes forth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>: euil life past, as S. Iohn Baptist did, Luke 3. ver. 8. then you reach sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction. If you terrifie them with the feare of hel, and with the declaration of the pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in the world to come, as Christ did, Math. 8. ver. 12. then with them you offer iniurie to Gods infinit mercie. If you exhort men to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting, praying, loue of virginitie, desire of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, chastesing their own bodies, restitutió, penance, and the like, as al the course of holie scripture doth: then runne you into plaine and open papistrie.</p>
      <p>And then (deare Christian brother) what treating can ther be of pietic in life, wher <note place="margin">No effect of verme sollovveth vpon the prating of protestants.</note> none of thes important matters may be once named? Truly (good brother) wel may a man vainlie talke in the aire of a <hi>quick ening spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite and mstrification,</hi> as they are wonte in pasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to doe; but nothing in sinceritie-wil euer be
<pb n="23" facs="23"/>
brought to passe, where thes weightie pointes be not soundly and seriously handled. For take away the mention of thes thinges forth of holie scripture it self, together with the large and frequent exhortations that therin are made vnto them; and very litle wil remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne about other affaires; the cheefe indeuour of Gods holie spirit being bent (as is manifest) to the setting forthe and inculcating of thes matters, aboue al other, vnto Christian peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
      <p>Which spirit of almightie God, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church his holie and deare spouse, <note place="margin">The spirit of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church.</note> taking vpon her to imitate; after the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of true faith once laide, calleth vpon her children both daily and hourly by infinit wayes and mianes, to remember and put in vre thes pointes of vertuous life, while her enimies in the meane space, doe lye wrangling and cauiling about contradictions in beleefe. And therfore in the Catholique Churche onlie (gentle reader) shalt thou finde the true spirite of teaching, and of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of thes pointes touching pietie: within the lappe and bosome wherof if thou alredy be, thou hast humbly and hartely to thanke God for the same, and with al sollicitous di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and care to make thy gaine of such helpes as she offereth the for attayning thy saluation. But if thou finde thy self in other estate (as alas many may at this daye in our poore afflicted countrie;) then I beseeche the tender marcie of our Soueraine Lord and Sauiour, that by readings of this present booke, thou maist the sooner be moued to make thy selfe partaker both of the one and of the other benefite; that is to saie;
<pb facs="24"/>
not onlie to enter into the vnion of his Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church, but also (which more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth) to leade a true Christian and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous life within the same. And so to our Lord IESVS I commit the. At S. Omer in Artoys this present xxix. of Iulie 1585. Being the daye of the holie virgin S. Martha.</p>
      <closer>
         <signed>Thy harty vvel vviller and seruant in <hi>IESVS</hi> Christ. R. P.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>