<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE</title>
           <author>M., F.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114265_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06901</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17332</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114265</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE</title>
                 <author>M., F.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Fiue decades of epistles of vvarre. By Francis Markham</title>
                 <author>Markham, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 200 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orkes of this Nature (in different Sir what euer you bee) as they are not without many difficulties, so they seldome or neuer passe without many diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Censures, and those alwayes led according to the Opinions of such as gouerne them; some be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing full of mercifull
<hi>Interpretation,</hi> some of scorne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Pittie,</hi> and some of
<hi>Seueritie,</hi> which it is no Iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice to call <hi>Tyranny.</hi> Any or all which since I haue made my selfe liable vnto them by this Publication, blame mee not if I seeke to reduce them to their noblest and best Countenances by my iust and vnfained excuses.</p>
   <p>It is true that I neuer had a daring to thinke there was an absolute perfection in any of my labours; for I knew mine owne Strength, and the many <hi>Precipices,</hi> which lay before mee, into some of which I must necessarily fall, though not through the rudenesse of
<hi>Ignorance,</hi> yet for some especiall ends to which I had tyed my selfe almost by a Legall condition: and therefore hauing no refuge but this PREFACE, let mee be held excusable, if I make it yeeld Reasons for such escapes, as those which are not familiar with my Bosome, may take for
<hi>Mistakings.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And of these the first which I thinke will bee called vnto memory, is some Misplacings or Errours in my Raunge, as namely, the omission of that Noble and Vertuous Lady, the Lady <hi>Dispenser,</hi> who although shee may truely challenge the first place in this Roll of Nobilitie, and that both her owne Goodnesse, and her Sonnes most noble parts, together with a strong Bond of Blood by which I am bound, ties mee rather to hunt and finde out any thing that might adde to their Greatnesse, then lose or let passe the least tittle belonging to their true Honour; yet in as much as the tendernesse of her sexe, and the vnfit proportions which are betwixt her and a Subiect of this harsh, rough, and vnpleasant nature, tels me how vnproper such applications haue euer beene held both in all times past, and in these which are now present amongst vs, I could not but imagine such an omission rather an ornament to Order, then an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batement of any due which is proper to vertue.</p>
   <p>Next this, the Raunging of the Earle of CASTLE-HAVEN, the
<pb facs="5"/>Viscounts of COLCHESTER and ROCHFORD, as also the two no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Heires of WORCESTER and SVFFOLKE, may draw on some curious exception, because I haue rankt them but as <hi>Barons,</hi> and as they sit in Parliament, whereas their places containe an higher estimation. To these exceptions I haue Appologiz'd in the Proems of their Epistles; but for a further satisfaction: true it is, that these Epistles (though but now published) yet were written long before, and at such time as the Range was proper (to most of them) without any serious exception. Besides, I must confesse I haue written another <hi>Semi Centurie</hi> of Epistles appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning onely to <hi>Honour,</hi> which I consecrate to the greater Nobilitie, and in them already haue ranged the Greatest; therefore to haue omitted these (being men of such noble worth and antiquitie) how euer mine errour now be pardonable, it had then beene past excuse. Hence it is, I haue ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made choice to bee too bold with some, then to neglect others, and howsoeuer in some places I may bee thought to skip or take too large strides, leaping ouer some, to attaine others, yet it is neither partialitie, nor singularity in affection; but rather a compeld Method which I must pursue out of the dutie I owe to the greatnesse of
<hi>Place</hi> and <hi>Vertue.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, hauing confined my selfe to the true proportion of <hi>Decads,</hi> &amp; those <hi>Decads</hi> iumping into a iust <hi>Semi-Centurie</hi> of Epistles, whose number is fiftie two and no more, I must either breake the whole frame of mine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Building, or else leaue some names to an after-remembrance, at which if any repine, saying mine owne libertie might haue bestowed on mee a limit of more largenesse: to that I must ingeniously confesse, that howsoeuer I might haue assumed more labour, yet I could haue hardly (in this subiect) found out more fit matter: for hauing made my Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as high as the <hi>Generall,</hi> it was not in me to seeke to ascend aboue it, least stepping but one haires breadth beyond my knowledge, I might so haue fallen backe with disgrace, and ruin'd my whole labour.</p>
   <p>Some peraduenture (yet but the ignorant) may condemne, or at least question why I elected this manner of writing in <hi>Epistles,</hi> rather then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Formes,</hi> which are now more frequent amongst vs, to which I answere, That I tooke this way for the most ancient, best, and noblest President: and hauing in my selfe a freedome of choyce, I held that <hi>Ambition,</hi> an honest and praise-worthy <hi>Desire,</hi> which conducted mee to follow those Steps which so many renowned and famous men haue not onely pursued, but also left vnto the world as a rule worthy our Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: for thus in Epistles write many of the excellentest Phyloso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, as <hi>Tullie, Seneca,</hi> and a world of others: Thus writ the best Poets, as <hi>Ouid, Horace, Martiall,</hi> and the like: thus haue Kings writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, as <hi>Dionysius:</hi> thus haue Emperours written, as
<hi>Aurelius:</hi> thus haue Popes written, thus haue Bishops; nay, thus haue the sacred Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Church written: and thus haue writ the most blessed <hi>Apostles.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Lastly, (for euery small Moate appeares a Beame to the eye of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riositie) some may except against some little litterall, and indeed no<pb facs="5"/>faults escaped in the Printing: to which I can but say, that if our Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage (which questionlesse is now as perfect, as significant, and as glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious as any other) stood vpon its owne ground-worke without the Bases of other <hi>Dialects,</hi> then there might bee one ready, certaine, and high way in which to walke and finde out true
<hi>Orthographie,</hi> but the <hi>French</hi> will challenge multiplicitie of Letters, the <hi>Italian</hi> gloriousnesse in sound, the
<hi>Dutch</hi> a filling of the mouth, the <hi>Latine</hi> his puritie, and the
<hi>Greeke</hi> his mysterie: so that indeed to satisfie all, is more then many mens labours; and I must begge, if any small escapes hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to encounter with your eye-sight, let a fauourable mercy cure it, and I shall not onely be thankfull, but praise a nature which is accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with so honest a patience.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>F. M.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>