<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>At Zoilus, Momus, and their mates, This doe I fling to breake their pates.</title>
           <author>F., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114628_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00551</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10688</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114628</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>At Zoilus, Momus, and their mates, This doe I fling to breake their pates.</title>
                 <author>F., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The complaint of Paules, to all Christian soules: or an humble supplication, to our good King and nation, for her newe reparation. Written by Henrie Farley. Amore, veritate, &amp; reuerentia</title>
                 <author>Farley, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legge (Legg), Cantrell</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb n="16" facs="11"/>
   <head>
      <hi>At</hi> Zoilus, Momus, <hi>and their mates, This doe I fling to breake their pates.</hi>
   </head>
   <lg>
      <l>CRitticks surcease, and doe not stirre too much,</l>
      <l>Least medling more then needs, I may you touch,</l>
      <l>And tell you to your teeth you are no friends</l>
      <l>To any good beginnings, or good ends.</l>
      <l>Though plaine I am, to <hi>Prince</hi> I am as true,</l>
      <l>And <hi>loyall</hi> too, as are the proud'st of you:</l>
      <l>Nor haue I wronged you or any other,</l>
      <l>More then a louing child would wrong his mother:</l>
      <l>Or written any thing so voide of reason,</l>
      <l>But that it may (to good men) come in season;</l>
      <l>Wherefore let <hi>Iustice</hi> rule you, and be quiet,</l>
      <l>And seeke not'gainst my right to make a riot:</l>
      <l>For if you doe, I must defend my cause,</l>
      <l>By helpe of God, or King, or Armes, or Lawes;</l>
      <l>Yet will I yeeld my life vnto my <hi>Betters,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>But not to you, if I should starue in fetters.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb n="17" facs="11"/>
      <l>Perhaps I'm borne to bee a <hi>Phinees</hi> bold,</l>
      <l>To begge and pray for poore, and weake and olde,</l>
      <l>And such as are both dumbe, and deafe, and blind,</l>
      <l>That in this flintie Age no helpe can find.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>What's that to you, or wherefore should you grutch,</l>
      <l>When nine times worse, you spend ten times as much?</l>
      <l>But that's to please your humour, that's well done,</l>
      <l>And in that vaine your course runnes headlong on,</l>
      <l>Vntill you make your selues so poore and bare,</l>
      <l>That twentie such haue not a <hi>doite</hi> to spare.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>If this my suite be rightly well regarded,</l>
      <l>I may haue thanks, and loue, and be rewarded:</l>
      <l>And more then that, (if lucke do not miscarrie)</l>
      <l>Paules friends will say, I was an honest <hi>Harry:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>So gaine a vertuous <hi>Fame</hi> when I am rotten,</l>
      <l>By future <hi>Ages</hi> not to be forgotten,</l>
      <l>While (if you please) you may goe shooe the goose,</l>
      <l>And (wanting garters) weare your stockings loose.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours, as you plainely see, till you are friends with mee. H. F.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>