<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the reasonable Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114229_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07370</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17754</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114229</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the reasonable Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The anatomie of Pope Ioane : Wherein her life, manners and death is liuely layed abroad and opened, and the forged cauils and allegations that our aduersaries vse further, thoroughly vnripped and confuted. Necessarie for all those that are not fully acquainted with the storie, and not vnfruitfull to all them that loue and embrace the true religion of Christ, and abhorre the sortish illusions of Romish antichrist. Written by I.M</title>
                 <author>Mayo, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the reasonable Reader.</head>
   <p>THou hast here mine Anatomie of Pope <hi>Ioane</hi> briefly comprised: if not cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as it ought, blame mine insufficiencie: if not as an expert Chirurgion, impute the fault to want of skill, and not of good will. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, <hi>errare fortassis possim, hareticus esse non possum.</hi> The matter hereof is so manifest, that <hi>corun copiae</hi> were needlesse to polish it, and the truth so euident, that the Pumi-stone of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite and superficiall eloquence would not haue bene requisite to flourish and smooth it. Reade therefore willingly, iudge indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, and correct friendly. Let reason rule thee, authoritie moue thee, and truth enforce thee. And let vs both pray together, that the truth may be maintained, all errors confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and Gods name glorified. Fare-well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>