<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>P., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114329_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09201</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19510</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114329</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>P., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A merry discourse of Meum, and Tuum, or, Mine and Thine : tvvo crosse brothers, that make strife and debate wheresoever they come; vvith their descent, parentage, and late progresse in divers parts of England. By H.P</title>
                 <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Clarke, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 38, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>REader whosoever. If many and great judgements have descended from their high imploiments, to please them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves at leasurable hours, with light exercises and mirthfull recreations as S<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Thomas <hi>Moore</hi> did, when he pend his <hi>Vtopia, Erasmus</hi> his praise of <hi>Follie, Fannius</hi> his Nettle. I trust thou wilt hold mee excused who at this time having no imployment at all, have made this relation of the late Progresse of <hi>Meum,</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> two Foot-posts, that dis-ease the whole Kingdome, set at strife Lords and their Tenants, Clergie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and their Parishes, Citizens and Country Chapmen, Inkeepers and their Guests, Carmen and Coachmen about the way, Pedlers for their standings at Faires, Gamsters in the Bowling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Alleyes,
<pb facs="3"/>
Water-bearers at the Conduite, in a word, men of all estates and condition, one with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I am informed they meane shortly to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sit all the Shires in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> and in those Shires every Market Towne, to follow all Assises, to get acquaintance among Proctors in all Spirituall Courts, and where they cannot be themselves, to send their Deputies; So that at their next returne to the City, I shall know their full intent; which (with what hath passed since their last being in the Country) I will from their own information hereafter (as neare as I can) relate. <hi>Vale.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>H. P.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>