<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORA∣BLE, AND TRVLY VERTVOVS, the LADIES CATHOLIQVE of great Britany.</title>
           <author>Higgons, Theophilus</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114948_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03332</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13452</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114948</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORA∣BLE, AND TRVLY VERTVOVS, the LADIES CATHOLIQVE of great Britany.</title>
                 <author>Higgons, Theophilus</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The apology of Theophilus Higgons lately minister, now Catholique : VVherein the letter of Sir Edvv. Hoby Knight, directed vnto the sayd T.H. in answere of his first motiue, is modestly examined, and clearely refuted</title>
                 <author>Higgons, Theophilus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Machuel, Jean</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 55, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE, AND TRVLY VERTVOVS, the LADIES CATHOLIQVE of great Britany.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST Illustrious, and Renovvned Ladies;</p>
   <p>It vvas the opinion of an ancient, and graue <note n="a" place="margin">Thucydi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storian, that <hi>men should speake nothing of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; neither good, nor euill.</hi> An opinion vnvvorthy of the Authour; vvhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch as <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>In his Treatise</hi> of the vertuous acts of vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note>
      <hi>Plutarch</hi> approoueth not in his censure, so nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sir <hi>Edward Hoby,</hi> nor my self, haue obserued in our practise; hovvbeit, in a different manner, and vpon vnlike respects: he speaking <hi>euill</hi> of you, to the disparadgement of your <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ites; I <hi>good,</hi> to the aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cement of your honours: he, out of his Zeale, and VVise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (vvhich, perhappes, did both set forth together, as <note n="c" place="margin">Currebāt simul, sed ille praecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currit. <hi>Io.</hi> 20.4.</note>
      <hi>Iohn,</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> but yet the first hath outrunne the second) he, I say, out of his zeale, and vvisedome, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame your Religion in your Persons; I, out of my duty, and obligation, to giue a just applause vnto your resplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent vertues. And thus I (vvith your <hi>Mary) haue chosen the BETTER part,</hi> to speake <hi>good</hi> of you, and not <hi>euill;</hi> as also, therein, <hi>I</hi> sustayn the TRV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ER part, because your selues are not <hi>euill,</hi> but <hi>good.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In vvhich assurance, and confidence, <hi>I</hi> may boldly
<pb facs="3"/> defend the lustre of such excellent LADIES, against the misprises of this KNIGHT, attempting to ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish their fame with his pen, which he should main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn with his sword. A work no lesse ignoble in him to vndertake, then impossible to performe. For, were it not a paradoxicall endeauour, in any man, to accuse <hi>Pallas</hi> of folly, or <hi>Venus</hi> of deformity, and likewise in the rest, where the perfection of the subject preuenteth the credibility of the discourse: Such also is the project of this Knight, and so improbable is his conceipt; since the generall esteeme, which you haue gayned by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of your liues, hath made you incapable of his wrongs. Neither so onely; but, wherein he would ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke you inglorious, therein your glory doth consist.</p>
   <p>VVherefore; <note n="d" place="margin">2. Cor. 7.4.</note>
      <hi>multa mihi fiducia est apud vos, multa gloriatio pro vobis;</hi> great is my trust in you, great is my rejoycing for you. Yea I am glad, that I may come vnto you, as my principall defendours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>against him, by whom you are equally offended; and that the tempest, raised against me by this Knight, hath driuen me vnto the secure harbour of your honourable fauours: whereof though I am vnworthy by my owne deseruings, yet you can make me worthy by your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious opinions. And <hi>I</hi> conceiue the greater hope thereof, because I am already intitled thereunto by the Knight, saying; <note n="e" place="margin">Pag. 12.</note>
      <hi>it is twenty to one, but some of YOVR Ladies will be pearing into this</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">To me, or against me rather.</note>
      <hi>Letter: therefore I will write no more, then I am able to justify.</hi> VVhereby your selues haue a peculiar in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest, from his owne hand, to require his <hi>justificatiō</hi> of all those things, which, in his <hi>Letter,</hi> he hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted vnto <hi>your</hi> obsequious, and faithfull seruant.</p>
   <p>In which regard, I appeale vnto you (religious, and
<pb facs="3"/> prudent <hi>LADIES</hi>) and assigne you (with your fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable leaue) to be my Iudges in this triall; since my <hi>CAVSE</hi> is honest, and your selues are just. She com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, before your presences, in hir natiue, and naked colours; not painted with eloquence, not adorned with inuention. Our vnhappy Father sought no <note n="f" place="margin">Genes. 3.7</note>
      <hi>sigge lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues,</hi> while he remayned without sinne, and (conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently) without shame. They, that are guiltlesse, seek no colourable defence; for <note n="g" place="margin">Stat. Caecilius.</note>
      <hi>Innocency is hir owne eloquence,</hi> being easily sustayned by hir inward, and proper strength: whereas an euill cause requireth much art; being like a statue (or <note n="*" place="margin">Deest ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid, quod intus esse oportet. <hi>Plut. in Laconic.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>dead carcasse</hi>) which hath the shape, and proportion of a man, but hath no soule within, to giue it life, and motion.</p>
   <p>Finally, therefore, whatsoeuer shall be found defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue in me, let your wisedome supply, or charity for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue, since he, that offereth vp this little Treatise vnto your acceptance, hath also dedicated himself vnto your seruice; remayning now, and euer,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours most humbly deuoted THEOPHILVS HIGGONS.</signed>
      <dateline>ROAN.
<date>
            <hi>12.</hi> Decemb. <hi>1609.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>