<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preachers friend to the READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114147_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04425</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1455</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114147</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preachers friend to the READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The sermon preached at Paules Crosse, the tenth day of Nouember : being the next Sunday after the discouerie of this late horrible treason. By the right reuerend father in God, William, by Gods permission, Lord Bishop of Rochester</title>
                 <author>Barlowe, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Law (Lawe), Matthew</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>38 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preachers friend to the READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle <hi>Reader,</hi> if thou thinkest the <hi>Preacher</hi> of this <hi>Sermon,</hi> was vppon purpose appointed to relate the discouery of this late <hi>Tragi-comical treason,</hi> (<hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical,</hi> in the dreadeful intention: <hi>Comicall</hi> in the happye and timely <hi>Detection</hi> thereof) thou art drceiued: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing three weekes before requested, to supply the roome amongst other <hi>Bishops</hi> for the <hi>Parliament,</hi> if it had continued: this <hi>occurrent</hi> happened in the <hi>interim</hi> some foure or fiue dayes before the <hi>Sabboth,</hi> wherein he was to <hi>Preach,</hi> whereby he thought it fit, (though he had purposed a <hi>Scripture</hi> of that day for his Text) to change a <hi>Gospel</hi> into a <hi>Psalme:</hi> which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, albeit out of the <hi>Psalmes,</hi> may well beare the name of <hi>Euangelium,</hi> not onely in respect of <hi>Dauid</hi> the <hi>Author</hi> (who writ more like an <hi>Euangelist</hi> then a <hi>Prophet,</hi> and therefore the <hi>Fathers</hi> conclude him to be▪ <hi>Homo in veteri, non de veteri Testamento,</hi> a man that liued in the <hi>Time,</hi> but not after the <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
of the olde <hi>Lawe,</hi> more like a <hi>Christian</hi> than a <hi>Iew</hi>) but also the <hi>Matter,</hi> which the <hi>Scripture</hi> (su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to this <hi>Accident</hi>) will affoord: which truly may be called <hi>Euangelium Regni,</hi> the <hi>Gospell</hi> or <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and could not but be <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable</hi> to the <hi>Hearer,</hi> if the <hi>Messenger</hi> thereof were <hi>accepted (for multum interest quid a quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que dicatur)</hi> and herin <hi>Reason &amp; Religion</hi> should be, because <hi>[Beautifull are those feet</hi> (<hi>saith</hi> Paul) which <hi>bring glad tidings of good things:]</hi> Now what <hi>Newes</hi> so good, as that in the Prophesie of <hi>Esay,</hi> to tell Sion, <hi>Regnauit Deus tuus,</hi> Thy God hath shewed himselfe a King; and what message more glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some, than with <hi>Nahum</hi> to tell <hi>Iudah,</hi> that the man of <hi>Belial</hi> is taken, and that the sonnes of <hi>wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi> shalbe <hi>vtterly cut off.</hi> How <hi>gratefull,</hi> or <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stastefull</hi> it was to the <hi>Auditorie,</hi> the present <hi>Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> can best report: but whether to tbe <hi>censorious rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der</hi> (who vseth to <hi>examine</hi> euery Periode &amp; sentence with a curious touch in an exact ballance) it will be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>currant</hi> or <hi>refuse,</hi> is a question, which none but he, which bringes the assay and scales can assoile, and yet if he will withal, remember the <hi>shortnes</hi> of the time for the gratulation, the <hi>dreadfulnes</hi> of the <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> the <hi>fresh escape</hi> whereof could not but leaue an impression of <hi>horror</hi> in the Preachers minde (able to haue confounded his <hi>Memorie,</hi>) who should haue bin one of the <hi>hoisted</hi> number, the late receiuing of the
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Instructions</hi> which in that short space could not bee many: hee will perhappes not bee so rigide in his Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, as either preiudice to the person, or opinion of his owne <hi>abilitie</hi> to haue performed it better, would cause him to be. And, as I heard, the <hi>Preacher</hi> himselfe frankely confesse, that vnlesse the <hi>Kings Maiestie</hi> his most excellent <hi>Speech,</hi> with the right honourable Lord <hi>Chancellour</hi> his graue <hi>Oration</hi> (both of them in the <hi>Parliament</hi> house the day before,) and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers circumstances sensibly conceiued and imparted to him ouer night, by the Earle of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties principall Secretary,</hi> had not succoured him, he had failed euen in that slender <hi>performance,</hi> which was then offered to the <hi>Eare,</hi> and here is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to thy <hi>View.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>Farewel</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>