<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Author his Preface, to his louing neigh∣bours and friends, within the towne of Shrewsburie in the Countie of Salop. R. G. wisheth all happines and felicitie in Christ Iesus.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114902_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01448</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11571</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114902</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Author his Preface, to his louing neigh∣bours and friends, within the towne of Shrewsburie in the Countie of Salop. R. G. wisheth all happines and felicitie in Christ Iesus.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Profitable insrvctions [sic] for the manuring, sowing, and planting of kitchin gardens : Very profitable for the common wealth and greatly for the helpe and comfort of poore people. Gathered by Richard Gardiner of Shrewsberie</title>
                 <author>Gardiner, Richard, of Shrewsbury</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Author his Preface, to his louing neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and friends, within the towne of Shrewsburie in the Countie of Salop. <hi>R. G.</hi> wisheth all happines and felicitie in Christ Iesus.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight welbeloued in Christ Iesus, neighbours and friends of this my natiue soile of <hi>Shrews<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie,</hi> I wish you all felicitie and happinesse in the true knowledge of our redemption in the merrits of our onely Sauiour Iesus Christ, to whom with the Father, &amp; the holy ghost, be all honor, praise and thankes for euermore. Beloued it is generallie knowne vnto all men in this towne, that I haue euer in good minde, desired the prosperity of the same, and in all good actions to my power and knowledge haue preferred the same, without desire of lucre or gaine thereby, and did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes desire to doe the vttermost of my skill, as well to the common causes, as also to priuate mens workes, and now in my olde age, or last daies, I would willingly take my last farewell with some good instructions to pleasure the general number: as for spiritual instructions and good aduertisments therein, I leaue you to the good admonitions of the godlye Clergie, and to your good proceedings in the same, which God graunt for his mercies sake, Amen. Amongst all the practises, knowledges and experiences which euer I receiued from Gods mercies in temporal blessings, I doe vndoubtedly perswade my selfe, that my practise and experience in Gardē stuffe, or the good benefits therein, dooth best benefit, helpe and pleasure the generall number of people, better then any other practise that euer I tooke in hand in temporall causes whatsoeuer. And therefore good neighbors and friends (of this my natiue soile) accept this my short and simple pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this my practise and experience in Gardening causes heerein mentioned. And if any other man, now or heereafter finde occasion to better in writing any thing which I haue omitted for want of full perfection by experience therein, I doe most hartily desire him, (that so shal finde cause to better
<pb facs="3"/>
any thing omitted by me or amend any thing by me penned) so to doe, that God may be glorified in his good gifts, the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall number the better comforted, and the poore the better releeued with Garden stuffe: whereas yet in this Countie of Salop, Gardening stuffe: is to small purpose, but I hope in God as time shall serue, my good beginning will be an occasion of good proceedings therein, and no doubt (b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>loued) if any man will hartily desire to doe good in these actions, then vaine, fruitlesse and superfluous things may bee taken out of good Gardens and sundry good commodities, to pleasure the poore planted therein: then no doubt the Almightie God will the better blesse your encrease, and blesse your walking in your Garden in that minde: and then no doubt but your good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science will delight you as well as the great blessings that God will blesse the Garden withall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Then shall you no doubt visibly beholde in your Garden, the blessed fauour and mercy of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> most mercifull God to your euerlasting comfort, not onely in the great increase there to beholde, but also other wayes to your great comfort, which I omit at this p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>esent. And when you make sale to the poore, consider you are the Lords Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards to sell with consciences<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and to lend and giue: also doe it willingly, for we haue the vnfallable promise of God for dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble recompence, if we so fauourablie will performe to all, and specially to the poore and needy: which God graunt for his mercies sake, wee may haue grace to doe, and also to haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> speciall care to satisfie, content or pay the tithes thereof to the ministers of the holy worde, and not to suffer a bad custome to corrupt the conscience therein, which God forbid. And also I desire thee good reader to beare with my grosse and simple penning in so good a cause, and willingly to accept my good will therein. And in so dooing I shall thinke my trauail here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to be well bestowed, and my good purpose the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter performed, which God graunt for his mercies sake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>