<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Dedication]</title>
           <author>Parr, Elnathan</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114077_Fr1_2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B15167</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19321</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114077</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Dedication]</title>
                 <author>Parr, Elnathan</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A plaine exposition vpon the whole thirteenth, fourteenth, fifteenth, and sixteenth chapters of the Epistle of Saint Paul to the Romanes : Wherein the text is diligently and methodically resolued, the sense giuen, and many doctrines thence gathered, are by liuely vses applied for the benefit of Gods children. Performed with much varietie, and conuenient breuitie, by Elnathan Parr Bachelor in Diuinity, and preacher of Gods word. To which is prefixed an alphabeticall table, containing the chiefe points and doctrines handled in the booke</title>
                 <author>Parr, Elnathan</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Samuel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 349, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <opener>
      <salute>MADAME;</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S is the</hi> boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie <hi>of the</hi> Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, <hi>so in</hi> Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice <hi>ought to bee the</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment <hi>of the</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. <hi>Your Ladiship was the</hi> first aduancer <hi>of my studies, and estate; and so you haue</hi> continued; <hi>which is not the least</hi> Ornament <hi>of</hi> Honour.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Of</hi> Due <hi>therefore what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer I can performe is your Ladyships; then</hi> whom <hi>I
<pb facs="3"/>know</hi> none <hi>more</hi> truely Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, <hi>for (which is the Crowne of Ladyes and of all the daughters of</hi> Eue) <hi>Chasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; for</hi> meekenesse of Spirit (<hi>an Ornament of price for all the Daughters of</hi> Sara) <hi>for</hi> Charity &amp;c.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>For neither will your</hi> excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent modesty suffer, <hi>nor this short Epistle</hi> suffice <hi>to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of your deserued praises.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>As we behold the</hi> maiesty <hi>of things</hi> sacred <hi>with</hi> venerable silence <hi>&amp;</hi> admiration; see <hi>I your</hi> incomparable <hi>vertues.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>I burne this Incense at</hi> their <hi>Altar: And I wish the</hi> world <hi>had more</hi> such Ladyes; <hi>the</hi> Church <hi>such</hi> ornaments; <hi>&amp;</hi> painefull <hi>and</hi> peaceable <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters</hi> such <hi>Patronesses, as</hi> your Ladiship <hi>hath beene to</hi> mee, <hi>who am</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours addicted, in all respectfull obseruance, ELNATHAN PARR.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>