<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO
THE RIGHT
WORSHIPFVLL
MASTER DOCTOR
WILKINSON Principall of Mag∣dalen
Hall: The Masters,
Batchelours, and other Stu∣dents
of that flourishing
Societie.</title>
           <author>Geree, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114368_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09274</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19589</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114368</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO
THE RIGHT
WORSHIPFVLL
MASTER DOCTOR
WILKINSON Principall of Mag∣dalen
Hall: The Masters,
Batchelours, and other Stu∣dents
of that flourishing
Societie.</title>
                 <author>Geree, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Vindiciae fidei, or A treatise of iustification by faith : wherein that point is fully cleared, and vindicated from the cauils of it's aduersaries. Deliuered in certaine lectures at Magdalen Hall in Oxford, by William Pemble, Master of Arts of the same house: and now published since his death for the publique benefit</title>
                 <author>Pemble, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Forrest, Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Lichfield, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Turner, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 16, 19-154, 171-239, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO
THE RIGHT
WORSHIPFVLL
MASTER DOCTOR
WILKINSON Principall of <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen</hi>
Hall: The Masters,
Batchelours, and other Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents
of that flourishing
Societie.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIRS</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Vstome hath made de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication
of bookes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most
as common, as
Printing of them: and
Wisdome directs there
to dedicate, where we
owe either respect, or
thankes: this worke
therefore is yours by right, the Author
<pb facs="3"/>
thereof (who is now with God) vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
it at your request, and performing it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
you for your good, so that now to
bestow it vpon you is not a gift, but retribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
and I hope, it will both stirre you vp to
be carefull to continue fit men to stand vp in
his place, and remaine to his successours as a
patterne of imitation, if it be too high for ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation.
To commend this Authour to
you, were to bring Owles to Athens, and for
me to commend the worke, would not adde
much worth to it: I know nothing can dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parage
it, vnlesse it be a naked Margent: but
you and all that will be pleased to take notice
of his yeares, and great abilities in all humane
learning, wil confesse he could not haue time
to reade many Fathers, and so that defect
may be easily pardoned. For he had fully
finished sixe lusters of yeares, yet had hee
throughly traced the circle of the Arts, and
attained to an eminency, not only in those
ordinary Sciences, wherein all Schollers haue
some smattering, but euen in those sublimer
speculations of which all are not capable,
<pb facs="3"/>
few search after: For hee was export in the
<hi>Mathematickes</hi> both mixt, and pure: his skill
in Histories was also praise-worthy: some<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>time
he spent (and not without successe) in
trauailing to learne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> and
much trauaile in the study of our home-taught
tongues, that he had worth to lai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e
beene Professour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>, or <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>brew:</hi>
all which indowments, as they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
haue enabled him to read with much
profit, so could they not chuse but preuent
younger yeares from reading at all the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
Fathers, so it was not want, but abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
of learning, that tooke vp his time, and
preuented his Margent, and therefore I hope
shall not disparage this worke. The first wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
young Fencers learne to vse is single
sword, when they are masters of that, they
inlarge their skill; our Author was but yong,
let it not preiudice him, that he first vses one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
the sword of the Spirit, the word of God;
especially sith that is so dextrously weelded,
that by it alone he hath deadly wounded the
Romish <hi>Leuiathan:</hi> Therefore (as in my
<pb facs="4"/>
knowledge▪ these Lectures were heard with
much applause, so doe I perswade my selfe,
they wil be read with great approbation, and
occasion the publishing of other Lectures,
and priuate labours, wherein hee tooke no
lesse paines, nor deserued lesse praise, then in
his publike indeauours. So hoping that you
will accept this small paines of mine, I take
my leaue, and rest</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From Tewkeisbury <date>this 9<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of
Iuly. 1625.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Yours: willing to doe you greater,
though not more acceptable
seruice,
IOHN GEREE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>