<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the right honourable and my verie good Lordes, the Lordes of her Maiesties realme of Irelande, and to all other in ge∣nerall of the saied lande, beyng louers of vertue, and imbracers of ciuilitie: grace bee mul∣tiplied, and peace euerlastyng.</title>
           <author>Derricke, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114109_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20313</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6734</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114109</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the right honourable and my verie good Lordes, the Lordes of her Maiesties realme of Irelande, and to all other in ge∣nerall of the saied lande, beyng louers of vertue, and imbracers of ciuilitie: grace bee mul∣tiplied, and peace euerlastyng.</title>
                 <author>Derricke, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The image of Irelande : with a discouerie of vvoodkarne, wherin is moste liuely expressed, the nature, and qualitie of the saied wilde Irishe woodkarne, their notable aptnesse, celeritie, and pronesse to rebellion, and by waie of argumente is manifested their originall, and ofspryng, their descent and pedigree: also their habite and apparell, is there plainly showne. The execrable life, and miserable death of Rorie Roge, that famous archtraitour to God and the croune (otherwise called Rorie Oge) is like wise discribed. Lastlie the commyng in of Thyrlaghe Leonaghe the greate Oneale of Irelande, with the effecte of his submission, to the right honourable Sir Henry Sidney (Lorde Deputie of the saied lande) is thereto adioyned. Made and deuised by Ihon Derricke, anno 1578. and now published and set forthe by the saied authour this present yere of our Lorde 1581. for pleasure and delight of the well disposed reader</title>
                 <author>Derricke, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Day, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>100 pages, 12 plates, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>¶To the right honourable and my verie good Lordes, the Lordes of her Maiesties realme of Irelande, and to all other in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of the saied lande, beyng louers of vertue, and imbracers of ciuilitie: grace bee mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied, and peace euerlastyng.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T maie be thought (right honourable) and likewise be imagined of some, who peraduenture) readyng this my little treatise, of the Image of Irelande, with a conscience corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to bee a thyng deuised and sette forthe, in reproche of all the Nobilitie, and others, borne within this Realme of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, as though the partie, ment nothyng els but a meere contempte of so many Noble, and worshipfull personages, and that this title of Woodkarne, should be but a couert, to shroude hym from suspition of the former allegation: Truth is my very good Lordes, if credite maie bee giuen to the artificer, simply as he meaneth, the substaunce is all one, (the matter I meane) to the verie Title, of that whiche is here called Woodkarne, who dissalowyng their Karnishe maners, affirme their dissolute life, and inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate liuyng, better to pertaine vnto Infidelles,
<pb facs="5"/>
and Heathen, then for those whiche in any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specte professe the name of Christe, (and what Christians thei bee, right honourable iudge ye) wherefore bee ye not then offended, O ye freen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of vertile▪ and imbracers of ciuilitie, that I should so fore lothe, or enuaigh their farre vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seemely maners, settyng out in liuely protrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, in contempnyng the same, bothe their shape, and execrable accions, for (in verie troth) my harte abhorreth their dealynges, and my soule dooeth detest their wilde shamrocke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, yea so muche the rather, because there is no societie, or fellowship betwene God, and the Deuill, little amitie betwene the Wolfe and the Lambe: like good will, betweene a Rebell, and a faithfull Subiect. Now for as muche then, as thinges with their cōtraries agree not, I moste humblie beseche your courtesies, not to deeme the reprehension of these wilde wantō Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>karne, to bee spoken of all menne in generall, whiche is here ment but of some, of those I saie, that are Rebelles to our (Queene) enemies to peace, and disturbers of the common wealthe, as for your (Honours) in good tyme bee it spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and voide of flatterie recited, who knoweth not, what festination by your Lordshipps hath been vsed, what godlie care taken, what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes practised, what pollicie shewed, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence bestowed at all tymes (as occasiō serued) to serue, accompanied either with the Lorde Deputie, or by your Lordshipps alone, against
<pb facs="5"/>
those whom I haue here tearmed by the name of Woodkarne bestowyng not onely your tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelles, adioyned with greate charges, but also ventred your liues in aduauncyng her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties honor, shewyng thereby, bothe a con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ant faithe, a perfecte fidelitie, to her royall Croune, conflictyng by force of maine batteil, many of these monsters, beeyng sworne enemies to her noble grace, the attempte whereof was lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the action meritorious, before GOD and man. This I truste maie suffice (right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable) your noble wisedomes, to withdraw all sinister suspicions from your suppliant, and his booke, giuyng full credite, my purposed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent is not, neither yet euer was, to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>emishe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mannes renowne, (beeyng approued serui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours to her moste noble and dreadfull scepter) whose continuaunce, I praie GOD, maie bee long and ioyfull, peaceable as the daies of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, copyng with the long yeres of Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>or, to gouerne vs her people, with an admirable regimente, and ouer her foes, triumphantly to raigne. <hi>Amen.</hi> God blesse your honours, with all maner of spirituall, and yearthly blessyng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s, the fauour, and loue of God and manne, muche honour in your countrie: and to conclude, life euerlastyng &amp;c.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your honours moste humble Ihon Derricke.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>