<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHOR TO THE Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114478_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09453</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19736</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114478</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHOR TO THE Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A reformed Catholike: or, A declaration shewing how neere we may come to the present Church of Rome in sundrie points of religion: and vvherein we must for euer depart from them : with an advertisment to all fauourers of the Romane religion, shewing that the said religion is against the Catholike principles and grounds of the catechisme</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 375, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE AVTHOR TO THE Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y a <hi>Reformed Catholike,</hi> I vnderstand any one that holds the same necessarie heades of religion vvith the Romane Church: yet so, as he pares off and reiects all errours in doctrine vvhereby the said religion is corrupted. Hovv this may be done, I haue begunne to make some little declaration in this small Treatise: the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent whereof is to shevve howe neere we may come to the present Church of Rome in sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie points of religion: and wherein we must for euer dissent.</p>
   <p>My purpose in penning this small dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course is threefold. The first is, to confute all such Politikes as holde and maintaine, that our religion and that of the Romane Church differ not in substance, and consequently that they may be reconciled: yet my meaning is not here to condemne any Pacification that tends to perswade the Romane church to our religion. The second is, that the papists which
<pb facs="4"/>
thinke so basely of our religion, may be wonne to a better liking of it: when they shall see how neare we come vnto them in sundrie points. The third, that the common protestant might in some part see and conceiue the point of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betvveene vs and the Church of Rome: an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> knovv in what manner and hovv far forth, vve condemne the opinions of the said Church.</p>
   <p>I craue pardon for the order vvhich I vse, in handling the seuerall points. For I haue set them downe one by one, as they came to minde, not respecting the laws of methode. If any Papist shall say, that I haue not allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged their opinions aright, I ansvver that their bookes be at hand, and I can iustifie what I haue said.</p>
   <p>Thus crauing thine acceptation of this my paines, and wishing vnto thee the increase of knowledge and loue of pure and sound religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I take my leaue and make an ende.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>