<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVL AND VVOR∣THIEST PATRONE OF ALL Learning and Excellencie, Sir EDMVND ASHFIELD Knight, one of his Ma∣iesties dputie Lieutenants o the Countie of BVC∣KINGHAM.</title>
           <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114350_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09198</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19508</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114350</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVL AND VVOR∣THIEST PATRONE OF ALL Learning and Excellencie, Sir EDMVND ASHFIELD Knight, one of his Ma∣iesties dputie Lieutenants o the Countie of BVC∣KINGHAM.</title>
                 <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The gentlemans exercise : Or an exquisite practise, as well for drawing all manner of beasts in their true portraittures: as also the making of all kinds of colours, to be vsed in lymming, painting, tricking, and blason of coates, and armes, with diuers others most delightfull and pleasurable obseruations, for all yong gentlemen and others. As also seruing for the necessarie vse and generall benefite of diuers trades-men and artificers, as namly painters, ioyners, free-masons, cutters and caruers, &amp;c. for the farther gracing, beautifying, and garnishing of all their absolute and worthie peeces, either for borders, architecks, or columnes, &amp;c. By Henrie Peacham Master of Artes</title>
                 <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Browne, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 115, 120-121, 1, 121-174, 2 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Art and architecture</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVL AND VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THIEST PATRONE OF ALL Learning and Excellencie, Sir EDMVND ASHFIELD Knight, one of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>putie Lieutenants o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the Countie of <hi>BVC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>KINGHAM.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, as to be excellent in anie skill is very rare, so the fauorers of excellencie are not euerie where to bee found, whom when by our good happe we find; I know not by what Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy we are drawne to admire and honour them aboue all other creatures, as the Saints and Soueraignes of our affections and deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: few they are I confesse, and so few, that if by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uents fore-past we may iudge of things to come, I feare me ere many yeares, euen the most necessary Artes to our posterity <hi>erun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> pos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>liminio reuocandae,</hi> so great a coldnesse hath benummed our times. I cannot much blame the Italian, though he accounts vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ull, and other nations, that haue the wit to worke vpon our idlenesse, which I can impute to none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cause, then the want of incouragement from the better sort. Our countrymen being as happy in their inuention as the best stranger of them all.
<pb facs="3"/>
For mine owne part, I hope I shall not be imagined to speake as <hi>Demetrius</hi> did for his siluer Images, as gaining ought heereby, since by profession I am a Scholler. Onely I am sory that our courtiers and great personages must seeke farre and neere for some Dutchman or Italian to draw their pictures, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent their deuises, our Englishmen being held for <hi>Vaunients.</hi> To which end as wel for their sakes who are as yet yong practitioners, as in regard of many yong Gentlemen in this Kingdome, who being naturally inclined hereunto, want fit directions to the attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this commendable skill, so many waies ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie, (fauoured in times past of the greatest Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narches, and of late daies practised euen by Princes, and the greatest personages themselues, as <hi>Francis</hi> the first, king of France, <hi>Charl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s Emanuel</hi> Duke of Sauoy, with many others who are reported to haue beene excellent with the pencill) I haue drawne and colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted together the most true and easie grounds of drawing, mingling and ordering all maner of water colours for limming, certaine obseruatiōs for perspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue and the light, the manner of annealing in glasse &amp;c. together with a short discourse of Armory, all which togither with my selfe (in regard as wel of that dutie I owed to your selfe for many fauours towards me at your <hi>Chesham,</hi> as that you are generally known to be a principall fauourer of all skil and scholership) I offer vp vnto your censure, of whom most humbly I take my leaue from <hi>Richmond.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Who is most affectionately deuoted vnto your Worship,</hi>
HENRY P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ACHAM.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>