<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114365_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B15223</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19587</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114365</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A summe of morall philosophy succinctly gathered, elegantly composed, and methodically handled, by that learned scholler and worthy diuine William Pemble Mr of Arts and late commoner of Mag. Hall</title>
                 <author>Pemble, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 <publisher>Forrest, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lichfield, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 56, 56-82, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ehold (vnpartiall and courteous) reader, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent vnto thee one whom I need not name the whole booke so fully speakes him, it being the character of him, whose name the Frontispice beares: here he yet liues although dead, for the booke breathes that which he once was &amp; when he was, he liued that which the book teacheth, for such was his admirable composure, that his very actions were a morall Lecture, hauing exacty learned that of <hi>Minutius, non loqui Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na sed viuere.</hi> I will not make any elogy of the Author, nor encomium on the booke, when as the one deserues rather the regestring in annales, then the light torch of a rūning pen; for the other vnlesse my guesse fayle me to a Iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous braine, and a well seasoned heart, it will commend it selfe, it having a mixture of learning &amp; delight, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it will both instruct and please the reader, and to say truth such was his dexterity, that by rhetoricke he could insinuate to a perswasiō, &amp; by solidity of argumēt evince thee to assent. But if perhaps the booke in all points an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere not the worth of the Man, or thy expectation, let it not detract from his deserts, or beget a preiudice in thy conceipt, since the worke is <hi>Posthumus,</hi> and (I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded) neuer by the author intended for the publique censure; neyther is the Printer much to be blamed, since he is so carefull to preserue any of thy blest reliques <hi>(Pemble)</hi> yet vnslaine, from the vnhappy fate of the vrne. Lastly since to offend is <hi>humanae sortis,</hi> whatsoever errors thou mayst find either in Author or Printer, the one thou mayest in thy Iudgement correct; the other in humanity condone. So mayest thou in some sort vindicate the Author, and gratifie the Printer. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>