<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface. To the Sodality of the most blessed Sacrament in A∣quicincts Colledge, in the Vniuersity of Doway. Of the best manner of Meditati∣on of the Passion of Christ.</title>
           <author>Costerus, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114528_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B12232</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5827</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114528</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface. To the Sodality of the most blessed Sacrament in A∣quicincts Colledge, in the Vniuersity of Doway. Of the best manner of Meditati∣on of the Passion of Christ.</title>
                 <author>Costerus, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Meditations of the whole historie of the Passion of Christ. Written by the Reuerend Father, F. Franciscus Costerus, Doctor of Diuinity, of the Society of Iesus. Translated out of Latine into English by R.W. Esquire</title>
                 <author>Coster, Franciscus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>—Recusant</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 629, 3 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Preface. <hi>To the Sodality of the most blessed Sacrament in</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quicincts Colledge, <hi>in the Vniuersity of</hi> Doway. Of the best manner of Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Passion of Christ.</head>
   <p>IT is manifest, that the end, for which Almighty God created Man, was, that beeing indowed not onely with that inferiour part, which is common to him with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Creatures; but also with the peculiar priuiledge and prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence of a Coelestiall minde;
<pb facs="4"/> hee should onely imploy his exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour sences in the mannaging of outward and transitory thinges, and with his minds surpassing all humane affaires should aspire wholy to God, and bee carryed to him, as to his first beginning. Wherefore it is wonderfull, and much to bee lamented, that some being vnmindefull of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and end, doe with such earnestnes follow these temporall Vanityes, as if they wanted this diuine vnderstanding; hauing not their mindes eleuated on high, but fixed on the earth, and creeping like Wormes vpon the ground, so as the very bru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e Beastes accuse them of ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, which by a certain instinct of Nature seeme to retaine a memory of the benefite they haue
<pb facs="4"/> receiued. Whom least you should seeme (deare brethren) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble, you are accustomed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the frequent partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the holy Sacraments, to giue your selues daily to the pious meditation of Heauenly thinges: That although in your bodyes you bee heere on Earth, yet your minde is transported in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Heauen, where you conuerse with the blessed Saints, and with Christ himselfe, labouring to v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite your minde to him, from whome at first it did proceed. This Godly endeauour both of you, and all pious persons, that I might in some sort promote and further, I haue gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diuors Meditations of the Passion of our blessed Sauiour, which may minister vnto you
<pb facs="5"/> occasion and matter of many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoute and profitable contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Which Meditations I haue thought good to commend vnto you for diuers reasons: First, because nothing is of such force to mooue mens mindes, and to inflame them with the fire of the loue of God, as the serious co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitation of benefites, especially such as are so great, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from so great a Lord and God. Some indeede, whose con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences are oppressed with the burthen of sinne, are oftentimes re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>laimed from their wickednes with the horror of Death, Iudgement, and the paines of Hell: b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t the vertuous sort, and such as serue Almighty God ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for loue than feare, are wholy set on fire with the loue of their
<pb facs="5"/> Redeemer through the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance and meditation of his Death and Passion. Secondly, because nothing doth so easily present it selfe vnto our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, as the meditation of the paines, torments, sorrowes, and tribulations, wherewith in our whole life we are enuironed, and beset on euery side. As for Heauen, Hell, and the last Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, because they are not sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to our sight, and seeme to be a farre off, we doe not sufficiently conceiue or apprehend the same: but for the afflictions of the body and the anguishes of the minde, we vnderstand oftentimes by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience more then wee would. Thirdly, because I know no me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation to be more acceptable to our blessed Sauiour, then that
<pb facs="6"/> which wee conceiue of the bitter passion, that hee suffered for vs. For as a Conqueror doth reioyce at the remembrance of his bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile, so we may well thinke, that Christ our Lord is delighted, when wee doe often remember his Passion; both because by so blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy a combat hee hath obtained a perpetuall and renowned victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry both for himselfe and vs; and also because herein hee seeth our thankefulnes which wee render vnto him for so great a benefite. Fourthly, because I perceiued that the meditation of no other thing could bee so necessary for Man-kinde, as of that, from which alone is deriued vnto vs the remission of our sinnes, our iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification, our workes of merite, and our whole saluation. Which
<pb facs="6"/> certainly is the principall cause, why the Catholike Church, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the institution of the Apostles, hath ordained that the memory of this Passion should by sundry wayes be so oftē iterated; as, by making the signe of the Crosse with our handes: by Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures and Images of the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ssi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which the Laye people are accustomed to vse in stead of Bookes; by fasting on Fridayes and Saterdayes; by the yearely celebritry of the Passion in the end of Lent; by Sermons, by Lessons, by sounding of Bells and such like, yea Christ himselfe hath instituted a most sacred and daily remembrance of his Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to wit the holy Sacrifice of the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sse, wherein his dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h, and shedding of his bloud is most
<pb facs="7"/> clearly represented vnto vs. Fiftly, because greater vtility redoundeth vnto vs by these Meditations, then by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of any other thing whatsoeuer. For as all good thinges are purchased for vs by the merites of our Sauiours Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siō, so in the same as in a wel fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished shop all precious wares of vertues and good examples are to bee found.</p>
   <p>But that you may more easily reape these fruites, I thinke it requisite to propose vnto you cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine aduertisements touching the best manner of Meditation. For many are deceiued, which thinke it is sufficient to repeat in their mindes the history of the Passion, or by consideration ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to feele an inward delight;
<pb facs="7"/> whereas notwithstanding, that auaileth little to their saluation, if withall, the affection and wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> bee not thereby mooued. For meate neuer satisfieth a man, if hee onely looke vpon it, and doe not put it into his mouth, chewe it with his teeth, and let it downe into his stomacke. The know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge indeed of the History is the ground of Meditation, and the discourses of the vnderstanding doe affoord the matter, but all the profite consisteth in this, that the will, which beareth the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test sway in man, bee moued with many affections: for she onely meriteth, she onely loueth, she onely directeth all our thoughtes, and actions towards God.</p>
   <p>Therefore to comprehend all in fewe wordes, those which haue
<pb facs="8"/> treated best of this matter of Meditation, haue designed and set downe vnto vs seauen affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions of the minde, which may bee moued with this consideration of the Passion: To wit; Compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, Compunction, Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, Thankesgiving, Admiration, Hope, and the Loue of God. Which I will explicate vnto you briefly and in fewe wordes, to the end you may vnderstand, after what manner you may bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed with profite in these ensu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Meditations. For by these seauen wayes, as by seauen teeth, the matter ministred by these Meditations may bee chewed, and with the affection tasted, and d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>gested.</p>
   <p>The first therefore is <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</note> that is, an affection of
<pb facs="8"/> the minde, by which we partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate of other mens griefes, and afflictions, feeling the same though not in body yet in minde: by which affection, the griefe of the Patient seemeth to bee diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and communicated with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and is thereby greatly mittigated and asswaged; as on the contrary side it is much aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and increased, if either we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eride him, or bee not moued with his afflictions. Chr st our Sauiour, to diminish our sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, would suffer for vs, and condole also wish vs, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle saith: <hi>Wee haue not a High Priest, that cannot haue compassiō on our infirmities, but tempted in all thinges by similitude, except sinne.</hi> And truly although we cannot lessen
<pb facs="9"/> by this our sorrowe the most grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and exessiue sorrowes that our Sauiour suffered for vs; yet this our compassion is most grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to him, whereby we make his dolours ours, and apply his suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frings vnto our selues. Wherefore the Apostle hath said very right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: <hi>We are coheires of Christ, yet if we suffer with him, that we may be also glorified with him.</hi> For hee that will not bee a partaker with Christ in his sufferings, cannot be a partaker with him in his kingdome. There are two thinges which are most availeable to prouoke this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miseration. First the condition of the person, that is to say, his nobility, his goodnesse, his piety towards men, and such other things, which doe aggrauate the
<pb facs="9"/> indignity of his inflicted miserie. Secondly, the cruelty and imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of his torments. If therefore we desire to fee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e in our hearts this cōmiseration, we must consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in euery article, First, who it is that suffereth: As first, that it is God, who with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty filleth Heauen and Earth; secondly, a most honorable man, descended of the house of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and conceiued by the holy Ghost in the wombe of the Virgine; thirdly, one most learned in his vnderstanding, and most holy in his will, who by no error or sinne, did euer offend either God or man; fourthly, most graue and sober in his conuersation, being neuer seene to laugh, but often to weepe, and that for our sinnes; fiftly, more beautifull in his body
<pb facs="10"/> then all the sonnes of men, and of a more tender and delicate complexion. Secondly wee must set before our eyes the greatnes of his torments, and with what particular payne euery member was afflicted. Considering first, that all the sences of his body, and all the powres of his soule sustay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their proper and peculiar tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Secondly, that his tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s were most grieuous, both by reason of the most tender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution of his body, and also be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he wanted all interior com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to indure the same. Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is the vndoubted opinion of all Diuines, that neuer any cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature indured such paynes and torments as our blessed Sauiour did. If we see a wicked man suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer such punishment, as he hath
<pb facs="10"/> most iustly deserued, we cannot but be moued to compassion and griefe: and if we see but a Dogge or an Asse cruelly whipped or beaten, we are presently touched with commiseration. Ought we not then to condole with the Son of God, suffering so vnspeakable tortures, and that for our sakes?</p>
   <p>The second affectiō is, <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Compun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> or sorrowe for our sinnes, when we are induced to an horror and detestation of our sinnes by the remembrance of our Sauiours passion: which may easily be done, if we ponder what the malice of sinne is, and what torments it hath drawne vpon Christ our Sauiour. As God is infinite, so the malice of sinne, which is committed against God, is also infinite: and this malice
<pb facs="11"/> in the iustice of God (which ought not to be violated) could not by any satisfaction be taken away, but by that, which was infinite. Wherfore either an infinite paine was to be endured, which no finite creature could endure; or for an infinite time, which the damned in hell endure; or by an infinite person, which is God himselfe. Hence let vs proceede, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, what it was that drewe God from Heauen to earth, and induced him to vndergoe his passion; which was nothing else but our sinnes. For if man had neuer sinned, God had neuer been incarnated, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uer suffered, neuer dyed. Wherefore, like as for the sinner, his sinnes prepare a place in hell; &amp; for the thiefe, his theft prepareth his punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
<pb facs="11"/> so for our blessed Sauiour our grieuous sins haue procured a necessity of suffering death. The malice therefore of sinne is aboue all things to bee detested, which caused euen our Lord God himselfe to bee crucified. But least thou shouldest imagine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happs, that the grieuousnesse of sinne is heereby extenuated, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause Christ did not suffer for thy sinnes alone, but for the sinnes of all the world; be thou assured of this, that the malice of sinne is not thereby diminished or impai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but the singular vertue of our Sauiours passion is declared, which hath washed away the sins not of this or that man, but of all the men in the world. For the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of his passion is infinite, and no malice whatsoeuer is able to
<pb facs="12"/> counteruaile it: which thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone doth sufficiently discouer the grieuousnes of sinne, because without the infinite merite of Christ it could not be forgiuen. As therefore if one only man see the Sunne, it will shine no more to him alone, then it would doe to him, and all other men together; and as a man doth no lesse kill another when alone he stabbeth him to the heart, then if he should take ten or twelue others to assist him in the same: so euen one mortall sinne (for redeeming whereof the death and passion of the Sonne of God was necessary) is no lesse the cause of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours death, then all the sinnes of the world ioyned together. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth the passion of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our bring vs lesse profite, being
<pb facs="12"/> vndertaken for the vniuersall saluation of the world, then if it had beene vndertaken for mee alone.</p>
   <p>The third affection is <hi>Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Imitation.</note> whereby wee desire to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe and imitate those rare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies, which we discouer in Christ, as the Apostle teacheth vs: <hi>Christ suffered for vs,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.</note>
      <hi>lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing you an example, that you may followe his steppes.</hi> And againe: <hi>Christ hauing suffered for vs in the flesh, be you also armed with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same cogitatiō.</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4</note> There are two thinges princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally to bee imitated in our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours Passion. The one is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to suffer for vs. The other is, a great heap of vertues, which appeared so plainly in this his Passion, that though our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb facs="13"/> spake nothing, yet by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample from the Pulpit as it were of the Crosse he taught all kinde of vertues; yea and taught them most perfectly, both for that hee was destitute of all interior com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, which doth ordinarily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company our vertuous acts; and also because there wanted not meanes, whereby hee might haue resisted his Passion. Wherefore in euery Meditation wee must search out, First, what vertue is chiefly cōmended vnto vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; Secondly, how our Sauiour exercised the same; And lastly wee must stirre vp a desire, and firme purpose to obtaine that vertue, deuising the meanes wherehy it may bee acquired, &amp; imploring the assistance of our Sauiour to accomplish our intēt.
<pb facs="13"/> Christ in his Passion gaue vs a patterne of all vertues, but es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially of those which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures doe so often commend vnto vs. Of which the first is <hi>Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> whereby being most bitterly scoffed at, cloathed in a white and purple garment, crowned with a crowne of thornes, lesse est<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eemed then the murtherer <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabas,</hi> crucified betwixt two Theeues, and suffering many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mockings and contempts, he alwaies humbly behaued him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe. The second is <hi>Meekenes,</hi> whereby he euer shewed himselfe milde and gentle to all men, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured torments most patiently, was silent in all reproches and iniuries; neuer vsed any excuses, neuer offended any body with his language or froward actions.
<pb facs="14"/> The third is <hi>Obedience,</hi> which then deserueth greatest commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, when hard thinges are commanded, &amp; by wicked men. Christ was not onely obedient to his Father euen vnto death,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.</note> yea the death of the Crosse; but also to wicked Iudges and torturers, whome he obeyed simply, cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and constantly, when hee put off his garments, put on the purple, receiued the Crowne of Thornes, caryed his owne Crosse, stretched out his hands and feete to be nayled, and did many other things that they cōmanded him. The fourth is <hi>Charity,</hi> which then onely seemeth to be perfect, when as for Gods sake wee loue, not onely our friends, but also our enemies, esteeming them not our enemies, but our friendes.
<pb facs="14"/> Which our Lord seemeth to haue performed most aboundantly, when speaking of his most perfect loue towards vs, hee said, <hi>No man hath greater charity then this, that a man giue his life for his friends.</hi> For albeit, it may seeme greater charity to yeild our life for our enemies; yet that charity is indeed most perfect which acknowledgeth no enemies, but reputeth those for our friends, which are our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and doth good no lesse to them then to our friends. Now Christ was so tenderly affected towards his enemies, that the more iniuries and wrongs he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued at their hands, the more his loue encreased towards them, and the greater benefites he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed vpon them; like vnto fire,
<pb facs="15"/> which the more it is blowed, the hotter it burneth. Therefore in the whole time of his passion he prayed vnto God his Father for his enemies: <hi>For this that they should loue me,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 108</note>
      <hi>they detract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from me, and I prayed in minde but not in voyce,</hi> But whē he was fastned to the Crosse, and the bloud ranne out of the foure fountaines of his hands &amp; feete, then with a loud voyce he prayed for them that crucified him: &amp; at the last when he yeil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vp his spirite, he moued with exceeding charity the heartes of the standers by to faith and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce. The first is <hi>Mercy,</hi> which is the daughter of charity. By this our Lord gaue vnto vs his garments, honour, fame, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimatiō, flourishing age, strēgth,
<pb facs="15"/> health, &amp; life. The sixt is <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the world,</hi> by which he refused all thinges which the world admireth, and accounteth good; and tooke vpon him those things which the world abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth; for riches choosing pouerty, for honours contempt, for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures paines, for comme dations mockings. The seauenth is <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seuerance,</hi> through which being neither ouercome by his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers sorrowes, nor moued by the heauines of his friends, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered by the derision of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, nor wearied with the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his body, he would not come down from the Crosse, which he had ascended for thy saluatiō.</p>
   <p>The fourth is <hi>Thanksgiuing,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Thankes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing.</note> by which, pondering the benefites bestowed vpon vs, wee breake
<pb facs="16"/> foorth into praises, not in wordes onely, which is the least praise, and action of thankes, but rather in heart and workes; that weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our mindes the great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite bestowed vpon vs, we should esteeme much thereof, and take heede of all offending our Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor, and omitt no occasion in all things to requite it. There are fiue thinges, which doe mooue much vnto this thankefulnesse. First, the euill, which we haue es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped. Secondly, the good, which we haue receiued by the benefite. Thirdly, the worthinesse of our Benefactor. Fourthly, the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the benefite bestowed. And fiftly, the condition of the person vpon whome the benefite is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed. Therefore that we may be moued to thankefulnesse, wee
<pb facs="16"/> must consider: first, the euills, which we haue escaped through this passion of Christ; as sinne the greatest of all euills; blindnes of minde; hardnes of heart; bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of the deuill; fowlenes of the soule; the present perill of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall fire, so grieuous, as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be conceiued; so long, as it hath no end; so certaine, as without Christ it cannot bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyded. Secondly, the goods, which we haue gayned; as grace, iustice, the adoption to bee the sonnes of God, Sacraments, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, vertues, the promise of euerlasting life, and to be briefe, all the goods both of body and minde. For there is no good thing in mans life, which the passion of Christ hath not either giuen or preserued. Thirdly, the dignity
<pb facs="17"/> of the person: for euen as we vse to allowe a greater stipend to a Nobleman, or Doctor, for a smell office, then to a plaine coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try man, for a great labour: so we ought to be more thankefull to the more worthy person. How thankefull then shall we bee to Christ, who is of infinite dignity? Fourthly, the manner of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite bestowed, to wit, gratis, and not without great labour. God made Heauen and Earth without any trouble by his onely word: but thee he redeemed with paynes, bloud, and his owne life: and for all these benefites he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth nothing of thee, but praise and thankefulnes. Fiftly, the condition of the person, vpon whome the benefite is bestowed; if base, if an enemy, if ingrateful.
<pb facs="17"/> What are we then? If (as the wise man sayeth) <hi>The whole world before God is as a drop of the morning deawe,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eccle. 11.</note>
      <hi>which falleth vpon the earth:</hi> What in comparison of God shall one silly man be, who being compared with the whole world, &amp; with all the multitude of men is nothing. Holy <hi>Iob</hi> hath expressed our basenesse: <hi>I said to rottennes, thou art my Father;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iob. 17.</note>
      <hi>and to the wormes, my Mother &amp; my Sister.</hi> Now, we are not only base, but we were also enemies, estran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, &amp; averted frō God, neither seeking, nor desiring his grace, but rather reiecting it, when it was offered. When therefore thou shalt consider, first, that thou art deliuered from the greatest, most certain, &amp; euerlasting miseries;
<pb facs="18"/> secondly, that thou art indued with most high and infinite goods: thirdly, by the most mighty God, of infinite maiestie; fourthly, with so great labours and paines, as neuer any mortall creature sustayned: thou canst not choose but thinke, whether it is fit that so abiect a creature should bee dissolued into praise &amp; thankes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing.</p>
   <p>The fift is conceiuing <hi>Hope.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hope.</note> By the consideration of three things our hope is much shaken and weakened. First of the puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which is required for eternall life,<note place="margin">Apoc. 21.</note> into which nothing defiled or vncleane shall enter. Secondly, of the strict examination of the Iudge, who will demaund an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of euery idle worde, and will reach euen vnto the diuision
<pb facs="18"/> of the soule and the spirit, and will search out the cogitations &amp; intentions of the heart. Thirdly, of our basenes, who both offend the iustice of God with our dayly sinnes &amp; liue full of concupisence &amp; imperfections, &amp; do not enter into the inward cogitations of our hearts.<note place="margin">Heb. 4.</note>
      <hi>And if I be simple</hi> (saith Iob) <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uen this my soule shall not knowe.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iob. 6.</note> To this diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence the Passion of Christ giueth help and remedy, and lifteth vp the hart of a sinner to confidence and hope. For first, as the glory of eternall life requireth great cleannes: so the Passion &amp; blood of Christ washeth away all our i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquities; it causeth our soules to be more bright then the Sunne; it maketh vs the sonnes of God, it giueth vs right vnto euerlasting
<pb facs="19"/> life, that now we goe not into a strange, but into our owne inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance. Secondly, the iudgement of Christ is very strict; but the merits of the Passion of Christ can wel beare the seuerity therof; because the satisfaction is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the debt; and our sinnes being in number infinite, his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are in value infinite; and to be briefe, he shall be our Iudge, which was our Aduocat, Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, and Redeemer, who, that he might giue vs heauen, payd the price thereof for vs, that is to say, his bloud, which he shed for our sinnes, being not ignorant of the value and dignity of that which he shed with so great paine and labour. Thirdly our basenes is very great, being able to doe nothing of our selues; but
<pb facs="19"/> his grace being communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto vs through the merite of his Passion, addeth an admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble splendor and brightnes to our soules, remitteth all our sinnes, giueth vs strength nnd power to worke, and addeth such dignity to our workes, as to bee able to merit euerlasting life. Therefore our hope will be much confirmed, if we consider, that all the wealth of Christ, all his merits, all his fastings, labours, paines, and, to be briefe, all that euer he did, or suffered, is ours, no lesse then the goods of the husband belong vnto the wife, which she may vse for the payment of her debtes, and her other necessities.</p>
   <p>The sixt is, the <hi>Loue of God.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Loue of God.</note> And first the nobility &amp; beauty of the thing beloued stirreth vp
<pb facs="20"/> the affection of Loue; euen as we are enflamed with the desire of vertues and sciences through their beauty and excellency. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>Loue,</hi> when we see our selues first beloued. And to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease this Loue, it auayleth much: First if wee see the loue of our Louer prooued, not onely by word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s, but also by great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites. Secondly, if hee procured these benefites for vs by his owne great labour and discommodity. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>irdly, if we often repelled him, and did him iniuries, and yet his loue was not diminished thereby. Fourthly, if by all his labours &amp; troubles he desireth nothing but to bee beloued againe. All these hath Christ done for vs in his Passion. First hee loued vs in deede and truth, and gaue vs all
<pb facs="20"/> good thinges. Secondly, hee to his great discōmodity became poore, that hee might inrich vs; and tooke vpon him selfe all euills, that hee might replenish vs with all goodnes. Thirdly, being so often repelled by vs, hee abated nothing of his Loue. Fourthly, hee requireth nothing of vs, but our Loue. Loue (saith hee) and it is enough. Moreouer, that thou mayest loue, thou must ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue the Lawes and conditions of a Louer, which Christ expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in this his Passion. The first is, that we alwayes thinke of that which we Loue; and this by the example of Christ himselfe, who, because hee would neuer forget vs, ingraued vs in his owne handes. Secondly, that we speake often of it: for <hi>Out of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance
<pb facs="21"/> of the heart the mouth speaketh:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 12.</note> and this also by the example of Christ, who on the very Crosse spake to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of vs, and prayed vnto him for vs. Thirdly, that we feare nothing more, then to offend him whome wee loue, as Christ hath taught vs, who referred his Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and all that hee had to this end, that hee might induce vs to loue him. Fourthly, that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow all our labours and indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours to helpe our freind: for Christ laboured not for himselfe, but for vs. Fiftly, that we should desire to bee alwayes with our friend: for <hi>The delight of Christ is, to bee with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sonnes of men,</hi> who hath sought vs, in Sea and Land, in the Ayer, &amp; in Hell; that hauing found vs hee
<pb facs="21"/> might ioyne vs with him in euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting blisse, and communicate his Diuinity vnto vs.</p>
   <p>The seauenth and last māner of meditating vpon the Passion proceedeth from Admiration.<note place="margin">Admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> This Admiration is commonly prouoked by some newe, strange, and incredible accident. Now, there are fower thinges, which shew the Passion of our Sauiour Christ to bee exceeding admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. First, because hee suffered, whose Maiesty cannot suffer, who is the glory and ioy of Saintes, whose dignity is infinite, whose life is eternall, &amp; whose Power is incomprehensible. Secondly, because hee suffered for them, by whom he was punished, base men enemyes, and vngratefull persons. Thirdly, because hee suffered so
<pb facs="22"/> many tormēts, as neuer any mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man indured, aswell if you consider the torments themselues as also his ignominyes, his irrisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, his pouerty, and other mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes of his life. Fourthly, because when hee redeemed Man-kinde by his Passion, he vsed admirable meanes for the fulfilling thereof. For first, with the great weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his body hee ioyned great power, wherewith hee beat downe and ouerthrewe the Deuill the Prince of this world. Secondly, hee ioyned perfect Iustice with perfect Mercy: for taking com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion vpon man, hee suffered the rigour of Gods Iustice vpon himselfe. Thirdly, his excellent Wisdome shined foorth in that, which to men seemed exceeding folly: <hi>For the Crosse of Christ
<pb facs="22"/> to the</hi> Iewes <hi>is a scandall,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.</note>
      <hi>and to the</hi> Gentiles <hi>folly.</hi> Great wisdome also it was; First, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome his most subtill enemy by Art and suffering, and to cast him downe with the same wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, by which he had ouercome. Secondly, to deliuer vs by such a kinde of punishment, in which he might lay vp for vs a medicine for all diseases, and set before our eyes an example of all vertues, and kindle the flames of Loue in vs. For nothing doth so much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite vs, either to the imitation of Christ, or to the loue of God, as this bitter Passion of our Lord. And thus much shall suffice to haue spoken of affections.</p>
   <p>Now that wee may vse these Meditations with fruit &amp; profit for the saluation of our soules,
<pb facs="23"/> these few thinges ought to bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued. First, that wee come not vnprepared to meditate, but (as the wise man aduiseth vs) <hi>Let vs prepare our soule before prayer.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eccl. 18.</note> Which preparation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth in this, that laying away all will to sinne, wee commit our selues wholy into the handes of God, and put out of our minde all externall cares and cogitations, and pray vnto Christ very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly for his grace, that we may obtaine wholsome fruite by this meditation. Secondly, that first of all wee read the Euangelicall text of that Meditation; &amp; then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> meditation it selfe either in whole or in part. Thirdly, that we lay aside the booke, and repeat in our memory, what wee haue read; and consider what affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="23"/> may bee stirred vp thereby, and labouring to excite, and moue them in our selues. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that we breake forth into some speach and prayer vnto God, through that affection, which is now stirred vp in vs; and that we either praise, or admire God, or pray for the forgiuenes of our sins, or for some other benefite: or (to bee briefe) that we speake those thinges, which our minde so mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued shall dictate vnto vs. It will profit vs also to begin first at the beginning of these Meditations; both because we shall better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand the History of the Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and also that by little and little we may proceed from the lesser to the greater.</p>
   <p>Also to the end that these Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations may bee more gratefull
<pb facs="24"/> and profitable, I haue incerted nothing, which is not sound and approued, because the vncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty shall not diminish the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor be a hindrance to deuotiō. For nothing is affirmed in this History, but what the Scriptures say, or the Fathers confirme, or traditiō vndoubtedly deliuereth. The documents thēselues, which are ioyned to these meditations, are for the most part taken out of the auncient Fathers, or out of the later Writers, which haue written best of the māner of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating vpon the Passion of our Lord. I haue drawen out some Meditations of purpose somwhat long, especially such, as are either of great force to mooue our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, or may bee vsed seuerally for Sermons; as namely, those of
<pb facs="24"/> the seauen words, which our Lord spake vpon the Crosse. For I was desirous in this Booke, not onely to set foorth the manner of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, but also to helpe the Preachers themselues, that they may teach the people profitably, and stirre vp their mindes with diuers Meditations.</p>
   <p>And I haue thought good to dedicate this my labour to you, my best beloued brethren &amp; fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, as to those, whose peculiar institute is to honour and receiue the blessed body of Christ our Lord in the most holy Eucharist, and to defend the honour thereof against the blasphemyes of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Heritikes: that comming to Christ his most Holy table, you may (according to the Cōman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of our Lord) repeate in
<pb facs="25"/> your memory his Passion, Death and Buriall; and make your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes sitt Sepulchers for the body of our Lord; &amp; with your mindes render vnto him praise, and thankesgiuings: and to be short, being inflamed with the loue of him, who gaue himselfe wholy for you, you may likewise imploy your selues wholy in his seruice, and the helpe of your neighbours. To conclude, I pray you that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of this my Labour, yee will vouchsafe to offer vp your prayers to our Blessed Sauiour for mee, that by his grace I may bee partaker of those benefites, which by his Death and Passion hee hath purchased for vs.</p>
   <p>Farwell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Seruant in Christ.</hi> Francis Costerus.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>