<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Prologue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114069_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B15165</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19309</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114069</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Prologue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The returne from Pernassus: or The scourge of simony : Publiquely acted by the students in Saint Iohns Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wright, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>68 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Prologue.</head>
   <stage>Boy, Stagekeeper, Momus, Defensor.</stage>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
      <p>SPectators we will act a Comedy <stage>(non plus.</stage>
      </p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Stageke.</speaker>
      <p>A poxon't this booke hath it not in it, you would be whipt, thou raskall: thou must be sitting vp all night at cards, when thou should be conning your part.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
      <p>It's all long on you, I could not get my part a night or two before that I might sleepe on it.</p>
   </sp>
   <stage>Stagekeeper carrieth the boy away vnder his arme.</stage>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
      <p>It's euen wel doone, hereis such a sturre about a scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie English show.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Defen.</speaker>
      <p>Scuruie in thy face, thou scuruie Iack, if this company were not, you paultry Crittick Gentleman, you that knowe what it is to play at primero, or passage. You that haue beene student at post and payre, saint and Locadam. You that haue spent all your quarters reuenewes in riding post one night in Chrismas, beare with the weake memory of a gamster.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
      <p>Gentlemen, you that can play at noddy, or rather play vpon Noddies: you that can set vp a ieast, at primero insteed of a rest, laugh at the prologue that was taken away in a voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Defen.</speaker>
      <p>What we present I must needs confesse is but slub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bered inuention: if your wisdome obscure the circumstance, your kindenesse will pardon the substance.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
      <p>What is presented here, is an old musty showe, that hath laine this twelfe-moneth in the bottome of a coale-house a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst broomes and old showes, an inuension that we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed of, and therfore we haue promised the Copies to the Chandlers to wrappe his candles in.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Defen.</speaker>
      <p>It's but a Christenmas toy, and may it please your cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisies to let it passe.</p>
   </sp>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
      <p>It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s a Christmas toy indeede, as good a conceite as slauging hotcockles, or blinde-man buffe.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Defen.</speaker>
      <p>Some humors you shall see aymed at, if not well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
      <p>Humors indeede: is it not a pretty humor to stand hā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering vpon two <hi>indiuidum vagum</hi> 2. schollers some whole yeare. These same <hi>Phil.</hi> and <hi>Studio:</hi> haue beene followed with a whip, and a verse like a Couple of Vagabonds through <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Italy.</hi> The Pilgrimage to <hi>Pernassus,</hi> and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne from <hi>Pernassus</hi> haue stoode the honest <hi>Stagekeepers</hi> in many a Crownes expence: for linckes and vizardes purchas'd a Sophister a knock: which a clubbe hindred the buttlers box, and emptied the colledge barrells, and now vnlesse you know the subiect well you may returne home as wise as you came, for this last is the least parte of the returne from <hi>Pernassus,</hi> that is both the first &amp; the last time that the Authors wit wil turne vpon the toe in this vaine, and at this time the scene is not at <hi>Pernassus,</hi> that is, lookes not good inuention in the face.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Defen.</speaker>
      <p>If the Catastrophe please you not, impute it to the vnpleasing fortunes of discontented schollers.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
      <p>For Catastrophe ther's neuer a tale in Sir <hi>Iohn Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuil,</hi> or <hi>Beuis</hi> of <hi>Southampton</hi> but hath a better turning.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Stagekeeper.</speaker>
      <p>What you ieering asse, begon with a pox.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
      <p>You may doe better to busy your selfe in proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding beere, for the shewe wil be pittifull drie, pittifull drie.</p>
      <stage>Exit.</stage>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <p>
         <hi>No more of this, I heard the spectators aske for a blanke verse.</hi>
      </p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <l>What we shew, is but a Christmas iest,</l>
      <l>Conceiue of this and guesse of all the rest:</l>
      <l>Full-like a schollers haplesse fortunes pen'd,</l>
      <l>Whose former griefes seldome haue happy end.</l>
      <l>Frame aswell, we might with easy straine,</l>
      <l>With far more prayse, and with as little paine.</l>
      <l>Storyes of loue, where forne the wondring bench,</l>
      <l>The lisping gallant might enioy his wench.</l>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <l>Or make some Sire acknowledge his lost sonne,</l>
      <l>Found when the weary act is almost done.</l>
      <l>Nor vnto this, nor vnto that our scene is bent,</l>
      <l>We onely shew a schollers discontent.</l>
      <l>In Scholers fortunes twise forlorne and dead</l>
      <l>Twise hath our weary pen earst laboured.</l>
      <l>Making them Pilgrims in <hi>Pernassus</hi> hill,</l>
      <l>Then penning their returne with ruder quill.</l>
      <l>Now we present vnto each pittying eye,</l>
      <l>The schollers progres<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e in their miserye.</l>
      <l>Refined wits your patience is our blisse,</l>
      <l>Too weake our scene: too great your iudgment is.</l>
      <l>To you we seeke to shew a schollers state,</l>
      <l>His scorned fortunes, his vnpittyed fate.</l>
      <l>To you: for if you did not schollers blesse,</l>
      <l>Their case (poore case) were too too pittilesse.</l>
      <l>You shade the muses vnder fostering,</l>
      <l>And make them leaue to sigh, and learne to sing.</l>
   </sp>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>