<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE ANSVVERE TO THE PREFACE TOVCHINGE DISCER∣NINGE of Spirites.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114152_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09100</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19401</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114152</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE ANSVVERE TO THE PREFACE TOVCHINGE DISCER∣NINGE of Spirites.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A defence of the censure, gyven vpon tvvo bookes of william Charke and Meredith Hanmer mynysters, whiche they wrote against M. Edmond Campian preest, of the Societie of Iesus, and against his offer of disputation : Taken in hand since the deathe of the sayd M. Campian, an broken of agayne before it could be ended, vpon the causes sett downe in an epistle to M. Charke in the begyninge</title>
                 <author>Parsons, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Fr. Parsons’ Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 173, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="response_to_letter">
   <pb n="10" facs="8"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb n="11" facs="8"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb n="12" facs="9"/>
   <head>THE ANSVVERE TO THE PREFACE TOVCHINGE DISCER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NINGE of Spirites.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Aister Charke besides the matter in question, maketh a praeface to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, touching the vtilitie, necessitie, and waye of tryeing spirites: alleginge the woordes of S. Iohn, whereby we are willed not to beleeue euerie spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 4.</note> but to trie the spirites whether they be of God. VVhich (he saythe) he and his felowes offer to doe: and we refuse. But that this is clearlie false, and a formall speche onelie, withoute trueth or substance: our dedes doe testifie: which are alwayes (with indifferent men) as good as woordes. Our bookes are extant, whereby we haue called to tryall all sectaries of our tyme, as they rose vpp, and shewed new spirites: as Luther, Corolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stad, Swinglius, Munster, Stankarus: and Caluin, whome our aduersaries folow as one of the last. And nowe in England, yf we had not bene willing or rather desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouse of this triall of spirites: we wolde neuer haue la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured so muche to obtayne the same of our aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, <note place="margin">
         <hi>VVhiche parte more desirethe triall of spirites.</hi>
      </note> in free printing, preaching, or disputatiō: &amp; much lesse wolde we haue aduentured our liues in comming and offering the same to thē at home, with so vnequall conditiōs on our syde, as we haue done, and doe dayly, for the triall of truthe. And yf all these our offers and endeuours, ioyned with so many petitions and suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations for triall, haue obtained vs nothing hitherto, but offence, accusations, extreme rackings, and cruell deathe: me thinke M. Charke had litle cause to make this preface of our refusing triall, and their offering the same: except it were onelye for lacke of other matter, and to kepe the custome of sayeing somewhat in the beginning.</p>
   <p>But perhappes M. Charke will saye, that althoughe we offer triall, yet not suche, nor by suche meanes, as in


<pb n="13" facs="9"/>
his opinion is lawfull, sure and conuenient. VVhen we come to the cōbate: then remayneth it to be examined, whiche parte doeth alleage best meanes: whiche shalbe the argument of this my answer to this preface. <note place="margin">
         <hi>VVho doe offer best meanes of tryall.</hi>
      </note> And I will endeuour to shew, that all the meanes of tryall whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch M. Chark &amp; his felowes will seme to allow in woord, (for they offer none in deede) are neyther sure, possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nor euident: but onelie meere shyftes to auoyde all triall: and that we (on the cōtrary parte,) doe not onelie allow, but allso offer, all the best and surest wayes of tryall that euer were vsed in Gods churche, for discer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning an hereticall spirit from a Catholique.</p>
   <p>The onelie meanes of tryall whiche M. Chark will seme to allow, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Onely scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</hi>
      </note> is the scripture: wherto onelie he wolde haue all triall referred: and that which can not be tryed therehence by hym, must stand vntryed. And then, as yf we refused all tryall of scripture, he vseth his pleasure in speche against vs. But this is a shyft common to all suche as M. Chark is. And the cause thereof I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare immediatlye. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Li.</hi> 2. <hi>de nu. &amp; concup. ca.</hi> 31. <hi>&amp; li.</hi> 3. <hi>cont. don. cap.</hi> 15.</note> S. Augustin dothe testifye it of the heretiques of his tyme. And all the sectaries of our dayes doe make it plaine by experience, referring thē selues in woordes eche one to the holie scripture one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, for maintenance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f there errours, and denyeing all other meanes of tryall, whereby the true meaning of scripture may be knowen.</p>
   <p>The causes of this shyft in all new teachers are principally three. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Three cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of appea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>linge onelie to scripture</hi>
      </note> The first, to gett credit with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by naming of scripture, and to seme to honour it more than their aduersaries doe, by referring the whole triall of matters vnto it. The second is by excluding councels, fathers, and auncitours of the churche, (who from tyme to time haue declared the true sense of scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture vnto vs,) to reserue vnto them selues libertie, and authoritie to make what meaning of Scripture they please, and thereby to gyue colour to euerye fansie they list to teache. The third cause is, that by chalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of onelie scripture, they may delyuer them selues from all ordinances or doctrines left vnto vs by the


<pb n="14" facs="10"/>
first pillers of Christe his Church, thoughe not expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selie sett downe in scripture: &amp; thereby assume autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of allowinge or not allowing, of comptrolling or permittinge, what soeuer liketh or serueth their turnes for the tyme. So, Martin Luther after he had denied all testimonie of man, besides hym selfe, he beginneth thus aboute the number of Sacramentes: <note place="margin">
         <hi>De captiui. Babilon. in initio.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Principio neganda mihi sunt septem sacramenta, &amp; tantùm tria pro tempore po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenda. First of all I must denye seuen sacraments, and appoint three for the tyme.</hi> Marie this tyme lasted not long: for in the same place he sayeth, that yf he wold speake accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the vse of onelie scripture, he hathe but one sacrament for vs: <note place="margin">
         <hi>Cap. de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cram.</hi>
      </note> that is, baptisme. But yet the confessiō of Auspurge, whiche pretendeth to folow Luther in all things, <note place="margin">
         <hi>In aeditio. vlt. loc. cō.</hi>
      </note> doeth allowe three, by onelye scripture. Mary Melancthon (whiche professeth onelye scripture more than the rest, and wolde seme to knowe Luthers mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning best of all men, for that he lyued with hym) hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth fower, <note place="margin">
         <hi>In institut.</hi>
      </note> by onelye scripture: and Iohn Caluin hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth two.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Com. in Amos.</hi>
      </note>Agayne, by onelie scripture Iohn Caluin fownd the title, <hi>of heade of the church,</hi> in king henry, to be Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiā, vvhich novve, our folovvers of Caluin in England doe finde by onelie scripture to be most christian. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Vide Ench. Eck. &amp; Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th. cont. la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom. de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiariis.</hi>
      </note> Mary yet the Magdeburgians by onelie scripture do condēne the same still. In like sorte, by onelie scripture the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testantes defended a greate while against Catholiques, that no heretiques might be burned, or put to deathe, whereof large bookes were written on bothe partes. But now our protestants in England, <note place="margin">
         <p>
            <hi>D. Fulk a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Bris. mot. pa.</hi> 98</p>
         <p>
            <hi>Artic.</hi> 28. <hi>cont. louā. tō.</hi> 2. <hi>vvit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tēb <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o.</hi> 503.</p>
         <p>
            <hi>Agaīst Br. mot. pa.</hi> 82.</p>
      </note> hauinge burned some them selues, haue fownd (as they write) that it is euident by scripture that they may be burned. Luther by onelie scripture, found that his folowers, and the Sacramentaries coulde not both be saued together: and therefore he condemned the one for arrant heretiques. Doctor fulke findeth by the same scripture, that bothe partes are good Catholiques, &amp; neyther of them here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques. Finallie, how many things doeth M. VVhittgift defend against T. Cartwright to be laufull by scripture<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="15" facs="10"/>
as byshops, deanes, archedeacons, officialls, holy dayes, <note place="margin">
         <hi>In his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of his ansvvere to the admoni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nition.</hi>
      </note> and a hundred more, whiche in Geneua are holden to be flatt contrarie to the same scripture? So that this appellation to onelie scripture bringeth good case in manie matt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rs. For by this a man maketh hym selfe Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, and Censurer, not onelie of all fathers, doctors, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, histories, examples, presidents, customes, vsages, prescriptions and the like: but also of the bookes of scripture, and sense it selfe, reseruing all interpretation vnto hym selfe. But Catholiques, albeit they gyue the soueraigntie to scripture in all things: yet bindinge thē selues to other things beside, for the better vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the meaning of scripture, (as to councels, aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient fathers, tradition of the Apostles, and primatiue churche, with the lyke) are restrained from this libertie of chopping and chaunging, affirming and denyeinge, allowinge and misliking at theyr pleasures. For albeit they hauing wittes as other men haue, might drawe so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me problable apparāce of scriptures to theyr owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uises, as euery heretique hitherto hathe done: yet, the auncient interpretation of holie fathers, and receiued consent of the churche not alloweing the same, it wold preuaile nothing. Mary the selfe-willed heretique, <note place="margin">
         <hi>The advā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage that heretiques haue by onely scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ure.</hi>
      </note> that reiecteth all things but scripture, and therein alloweth nothing but his owne exposition, may runne and range, and deuise opinions at his pleasure: for he is sure ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to be conuicted thereof, allowinge no man to be iudge of his interpretation, but onelye hym selfe, or so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of hys owne opinion. This we see fullfilled in all heretiques, and sectaries that now lyue: whome it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible so to conuince by onelye scriptures, but they will alwayes haue some probable shew, whereby to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them selues and theyr owne imaginatiōs. M. Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke therfore chanting so muche vpon this point of one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie scriptures, treadeth the pathe of his forefathers, and pleadeth for a pryuilege of ease: which whether we will allovve hym or no, he entreth vpon it, of his ovvne au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and dravveth scrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ure to euerye deuise of his owne braine, so violentlie, as a man may take cō<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ssion


<pb n="16" facs="11"/>
to see yt. I shall haue many examples hereafter in this ansvver: but yet one, vvhich is the chefe ground of this his preface, I can not omitt.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 4.</note>After he had proued ovvt of Saincte Iohn, that vve must trie spirites, and not beleeue euerye nevv spiritt: (whiche is true:) he will nedes alleage owte of the same Apostle a full and plaine rule (as he termeth it) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to discerne and trie his &amp; oure spirites. The rule is this: <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 4.</note>
      <hi>Euery spirit vvhiche acknovvlegeth Iesus Christe to haue come in fleshe is of God: and euerye spirit vvhiche dissolueth I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sus, is not of God, but of Antichriste.</hi> Here now may be se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne what difference there is in exposition of the scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures. For the aunciēt fathers interpreted this place, (as of it selfe it is most euident) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o be gyuen as a rule against the Iewes, which denied Christe to haue taken fleshe: <note place="margin">
         <hi>Diuersit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e of inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</hi>
      </note> Also against Ebion, and Cherinthus, heretiques, nowe gone into the worlde, as fore-runners of Antichriste, &amp; dissoluing Iesus: that is, denieing his godheade: and cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently denyeing the sonne of God to haue come in fleshe. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Tom.</hi> 7. <hi>vvittemb. Fol.</hi> 414.</note> Martin Luther interpreteth this place to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstoode of M. Charke and his felowes: sayeinge, <hi>That spirit is not of god but of Antichriste vvhich dissolueth Christs fleshe in the sacrament.</hi> But to vs Catholiques how can it be by anie deuise wrested, who neyther denye Christe to haue come in fleshe, nor yet do dissolue the name of Iesus, by anie doctrine of ours? But yet, Marke how M. Charke interpreteth this place: and cōfesse, that he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the a singular grace in abusing scripture.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>M. Charks grace ī in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretinge scriptures.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>VVhat soeuer spirit (sayeth he) shall confesse Christe to haue come in fleshe as a prophet, alone to teache (as papistes doe not, teaching traditions besides the vvritten vvoorde:) also, as a kinge alone to rule (as papistes doe not, defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the popes authoritie:) also, as a preest, alone to sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye (as papistes doe not, vpholding the Masse:) this spirit is of God, and the other of Antichriste.</hi> Is it maruaile yf these men build what they list vppon scripture, when they can fovvnde so many absurdities vppon one sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence thereof? I wolde here aske first, whether M. Chark thinketh that vve exclude Christe, vvhen vve allovve


<pb n="17" facs="11"/>
prophetes to teache vnder hym kinges to raigne vnder hym, preests to sanctifie vnder hym, or no? If he thinke we exclude Christe: he is to fond to reason against sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible men, knowing not what they holde. But yf he thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke we allowe prophets, kings, and preests vnder Christe onelie, and in hys name: how can he call this the spirit of Antichrist? doe not the scriptures allowe Prophets and teachers vnder Christe in the churche? Ephes. 4. Act. 5? Also kinges and rulers (thoughe puritanes wolde haue none) 1. Pet. 2. Act. 2? Also may not preestes sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie by the woord of God. 2. Timo. 4? How then are these things accompted Antichristian? doe not protestants teache the same? what deepe Mysteries of puritanisme are these, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Theyr my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries are the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throvv of all gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors: as M. VVhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>g. proueth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst M. Cartv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. Tovv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ng the masse.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Christe is a prophete alone, a kinge alone, a preest alone?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Againe, I aske what doe the traditions of Christe and his Apostles (for of those onelie we talke when we compare them with scripture) impeache the teaching of Christe and his Apostles? what doeth the spirituall authoritie of the pope vnder Christe, diminishe the kinglie power, and authoritie of Christe? how doeth the preesthode of mē as from Christe, or the sacrifice of the Aultar instituted by Christe, disgrace Christs presthoode, or his sufficiēt sacrifice ones for all offered on the crosse? There is noted in the Margent, the epistle to the Hebrewes, <note place="margin">Heb. 7. &amp; 9.</note> where it is saied: that, that sacrifice on the crosse was ones offered for euer for oure redēptiō. VVhiche we bothe graunt and teache in that manner as then it was done: but yet that impeacheth nothing this dayly sacrifice of ours, whiche must be in the churche vntill the end of the woorde, (as Daniel prophecyed, <note place="margin">Dan. 12.</note>) and that in euerie place amongest the Gentiles: (that is, in all the worlde) is Malachie fore-tolde, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Malac.</hi> 1. In declar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Anath. 11. Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 20. cō. faust. c. 21. Naz. ora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 1. in Iuliā. Hom. 17.</note> being called, by Sainct Cirill and other fathers, <hi>incruentum sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium: the vnbloodie sacrifice</hi>: which being one and the selfe same with that which was offered once vpon the crosse, is appointed by Christe to be offred dayly in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance and thanks geuing for that bloodie sacrifice, as Sainct Chrisostom doeth proue at large vpō the epistle


<pb n="18" facs="12"/>
to the hebrewes: whom, &amp; other his like yf M. Chark &amp; his felowes wolde not disdaine to reade &amp; beleeue: they wold be a shamed to cauill, and blaspheme gods myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries as they doe. But for a large and full answere of this common obiection of theirs, owte of the epistle to the hebrewes, towching Christe once bloodilie offered for all: I referre the reader, amōges many other, to certayne particular auncient and learned fathers, of the prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue churche; whoe doe handle this obiection, and answere it of purpose. <note place="margin">In ca 8 ep. ad Hebr.</note> The one is Theodoret byshop of Cyrus, whoe handleth this question: <hi>vvhie Christians doe novv vse to sacrifice in the nevv testament, seing the olde lavv vvith all sacrifices vvere abolished, by the one sacrifice of Christe</hi>? <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ep.</hi> 23. ad Bonif.</note> The other is S. Augustin, whoe proposeth this dowbt: <hi>hovv vve sacrifice Christe euery daye vpon the Aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, seing he is sayd to be sacrificed once for all vpon the crosse</hi>? And then he answereth it, bothe fullie and largelie, in that sense as I haue sayd before: So that this obiection was a cómon thing in the primatiue churche, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mōlie answered by euery writer, which M. Chark &amp; his felowes do make so much a doe abowt now, crieing owt that we denie the vertue of Christes passion, the effects of his offices, and the like. See the same answered also by Eusebius, li. 1. demonst. euang. cap. 6. and 10. And by Theophilact. in cap. 5. ad hebr.</p>
   <p>And so, hauing answered now the substance of all that which M. Chark hathe in his preface, <note place="margin">The aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sarie admit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth no triall.</note> I might here make an end, but that I haue promised to shew how we offer hym and his felows moste reasonnable meanes of triall, and that they in deede admitt none at all. For what is it to name scripture in woordes, when all thee controuersie is about the sense thereof, wherein they admit no Iudge but them selues? yf we bring scripture neuer so playne, yet will they shift it of, with some im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partinent interpretation: And what remedie or further triall haue we then? I will gyue an example or two for instruction of the reader in their procedings. The most of the auncient fathers wrote books in prayse of virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie aboue wedlocke, &amp; vsed to proue it by the sayeing


<pb n="19" facs="12"/>
of Christe: <note place="margin">Math. 19.</note>
      <hi>There be Eunuches vvhiche haue gelded them selues for the</hi> kingdome of heauen, he that can take it, let hym take it. Also by the woordes of S. Paul: <note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.</note>
      <hi>he that ioynethe his virgine in mariage dothe vvell, and hee that ioynethe her not, dothe better.</hi> VVhiche woordes being alleaged against Martyn Luther, <note place="margin">Lib. de vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Monast. in initio.</note> whoe preferred ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage (yea though it were of a vowed Nunne) before virgnitie: he answered it thus: that Christ by his woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des terrified men from virginitie and continence, and S. Paul by this speche dyd diswade them from the same. Now what could be replied in this case trow you?</p>
   <p>An other exāple may be towching S. Iohn Baptist: <note place="margin">
         <hi>Of S. Iohn Baptist.</hi> Lu. 1. &amp; 3. Math. 3. Marc. 1.</note> of whome the scripture sayth, first, concerning his pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of liuinge, that <hi>he vvas in the vvildernesse vntill the day of his appearing to Israel.</hi> Secōdlie, touching his apparell: <hi>Iohn vvas appareled vvith the heares of Camels.</hi> Thyrdlie, touching his diet: <hi>his meate vvas locustes and vvilde honie.</hi> Of whiche three things, the olde fathers of the prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church dyd gather a great and singular austeritie of S. Iohns lyfe, and doe affirme with all, that Eremits and Monkes, and other religious people did take their paterne of straite lyuing from hym. <note place="margin">Cent. 5 c. 6. pag. 711.</note> For whiche cause S. Chrisostome dothe often call S. Iohn Baptist <hi>Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chum, &amp; principem vitae monastice: a monke, and prince of Monasticall lyfe</hi>: whiche protestants being not able to abyde, doe rage maruailouslie against S. Chrisostome: condemning hym of rashenes and falsehode, for vsinge those termes, wherefore they fall to interpret the allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged woordes of scripture farre otherwise, sayeinge: that by the desert wherein he liued vntill he began to prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, is vnderstoode nothing els, <note n="a" place="margin">Sarcer. in ca. 1. Lu. &amp; mag. Cent. 1 li. 1. ca. 20.</note>, <hi>but his priuate lyfe at home in his fathers ovvne hovvse.</hi> And for his apparell (say they) of Camels heare, it was not straunge apparell, but vsual to Mountain men, <note n="(b)" place="margin">
         <p>Mario<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. in ca. 3. Math.</p>
         <p>Cytraeits in ca. 3. Math. <hi>COSMIOS. EVPORI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STOS.</hi>
         </p>
      </note> that <hi>is vndulata<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> sayeth another:) <hi>VVater chamblet, hansome, and decent, albeit som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvhat plentifull in that countrie.</hi> And lastlie, touchinge his dyet of locusts and wilde hony: it was no hard fare, (say they) for the locustes were creuises, <note n="c" place="margin">Ma. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>̄. 1. l. 1. c. 4. et 6</note> cast awaye by the fishers of Iordan, as vncleane by the lawe, but eaten of


<pb n="20" facs="13"/>
Iohn, by the libertie of the Gospell. And the wilde hony was no vnpleasant thing as the fathers doe imagin: <note place="margin">In cap. 1. Math.</note> but it was (say Cossius and Strigelius) that pleasant Manna whiche Apothecaires vse to kepe in their shoppes: <note place="margin">In cap. 1. Marc.</note> So that, accordinge to these men, all that austeritie of lyfe, whiche the scriptures so particularlie doe recounte, &amp; all antiquitie doeth wounder at, in S. Iohn Baptist, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth but to this: that he was brought vp priuatelie in his fathers house, cladde in chāblette, &amp; fedde with cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uisses &amp; swete Manna. VVhat great hardnesse was this?</p>
   <p>A thyrd example may be aboute the controuersie of reall presence in the sacrament: for whiche we bring plaine woordes of scripture, oute of fower diuerse pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the new testament, <note place="margin">Mat. 26. Marc. 14. Luc. 22. 1. Cor. 11.</note> where the same woordes are repeated withoute exposition or alteration: to witt, <hi>hoc est corpus meum: this is my bodie</hi>: VVhiche woordes dyd seme so playne and cleare for the reall presence of Christe in the sacrament, to all antiquitie: as no man might without great offence, doubt thereof, as the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ords of S. Ambro. <note n="a" place="margin">Lib. 4. de sacram. c. 5</note>, &amp; S. Ciril. <note n="b" place="margin">Catach. 4</note>, are. And (as the same Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril. <note n="c" place="margin">Li. 4. in Io. cap. 13. In Anco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rano.</note>, in an other place proueth at large) to aske onelye <hi>quomodo</hi> how it may be, is the parte of an vnbeleuinge Iewe: seinge God was able (as he sayeth) as well to doe this, as to turne the rodde of Moyses into a serpent. To whiche purpose allso holy Epiphanius sayeth, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the hoost seme to vs of a rounde forme &amp; insēsible: yet who soeuer beleeueth it not to be the verie true bodie of Christe, seing he hathe sayd it is: <hi>excidit a gratia &amp; salute.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ho. 83. in Math. &amp; 60. ad pop. Antioch.</note> Suche a one is fallen from grace, and saluation. And S. Chrisostom sayeth, we must not beleeue sense and reason in this matter. <hi>Sed quoniam ille dixit, hoc est corpus meum, credamus, etiamsi sensui absurdum esse videa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> But because Christ hathe sayed this is my bodye, we must bele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ue it, although it seme absurd to our sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se: <note place="margin">Hom. 24. in epist. ad Cor.</note>
      <hi>Hoc idem corpus cruentatum, lancea vulneratum, &amp; quod in caelum extulit. This is the very same bodie, vvhose bloode vvas shed, and vvhiche vvas vvounded vvith the speare, and vvhiche he caried vpp vvith hym to heauen.</hi> All whiche notwithstandinge, oure aduersaries haue founde out a


<pb n="21" facs="13"/>
new exposition of these woordes, <hi>thys is my bodye,</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, that it must be construed, this is onelie the signe of my bodie. For the whiche construction, as they haue neither scripture, nor auncient father for theyr warrāt or example: so agree they not amongest them selues of this exposition. For Luther in his tyme, numbreth vpp eight dyuerse and contrarie expositions of Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries vppon these woordes, <note place="margin">
         <p>
            <hi>In confess breui. tom.</hi> 2. <hi>germ. fol.</hi> 257.</p>
         <p>
            <hi>Claud de San. l.</hi> 1. <hi>rep.</hi> 1. <hi>de Euch.</hi>
         </p>
      </note> cōming from eight diuerse spirits of the deuyll, as he affirmeth. And a learned by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of our time hathe gathered 84. gyuen by diuerse sacramentaries vppon the same: So that, once goe oute of the highe waye, and there is no ende of erringe.</p>
   <p>And because I haue here made mention of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor Luther, a man by M. Charks opinion, illuminated singularlie by the holye ghost, and compared to Elias by the common phrase of all protestants: I will repeate here what he had reuealed to hym by hys holy spirit touchinge this interpretation of M. Charke and his fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</p>
   <p>First, he writteth thus to the protestants: <note place="margin">
         <hi>The letter beginneth thus: Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rissimis in Christo ami cis &amp; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianis Ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gentinae.</hi>
      </note> that is, to the true Christians, as he calleth them, of Argentina: <note place="margin">
         <p>
            <hi>This vvas an honest man in the meane spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, vvhiche laboured to peruert this sacrament, thereby to hurt the pope.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>Luthers la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin vvoords are, ex capi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e vertigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noso confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis.</hi>
         </p>
      </note>
      <hi>Hoc diffiteri nec possum, nec volo, si Corolostadius &amp;c. This can I not, nor vvill deny, but yf Corolostadius, or anie man els could for this fyue yeres, haue persuaded me, that there had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne nothinge in the sacrament but bread and vvine: he should haue bound me to hym by a great good turne. For I haue takē great care and anxietie in discussinge this matter, and haue endeuoured vvith all my povver, &amp; sinovves stretched ovvte, to rydde my selfe of the same. For I dyd vvell see, that by this thing I might hurt the pope more than in anie other matter. But I do see my selfe captiue, no vvay being left to escape. For the text of the gospel is too plaine and stronge, and suche as can not easelie be ouerthrovvne by any man, and muche lesse by vvoordes and gloses deuised by a phātasticall heade. For I my selfe (God forgyue me for it) am too prone to that par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e, so farre foorthe as I can perceyue the nature of my ovvne Adam.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Agayne, the same prophet in an other place, after many most detestable woords vttered against M. Chark


<pb n="22" facs="14"/>
and his parteners, sayeth thus: <note place="margin">
         <p>
            <hi>Epis. a.</hi> I0. <hi>har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>agium Tipogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phum. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentinensē: cuius etiam mentionem vide apud Biblioth.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>Gesneri fo.</hi> 501.</p>
      </note>
      <hi>his spiritibus credat doceri veritatem: si quem perire delectat &amp;c. Lett hym beleue that these spirites doe teache the trueth, vvho deliteth to damne him selfe, vvhereas in dede they began not theyr doctrine, but by manifest lyes, and novv doe defend the same onelye by lyes, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uulging the same by corrupting other mens bookes, not vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safing to heare the anguishes of our consciences, vuhich crie, &amp; saye, the vvoordes of Christ are cleare and manifest</hi>: <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 26.</note>
      <hi>eate, this is my bodye.</hi> And againe, in a certayne treatise intituled <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Tom.</hi> 7. <hi>vvittemb. page</hi> 380.</note>
      <hi>against the phanaticall Spirits of sacramētaries</hi>: He sayeth, talking of this interpretation of the woords: <hi>This is my bodye: Age ergo quando adeo sunt impudentes &amp;c. Goe to then, seing they are so impudent, therfore I vvill geue them a Lutheran exhortation: accursed</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">
         <p>
            <hi>A Luthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ran exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>O pleasant Martin.</hi>
         </p>
      </note>
      <hi>be their charitie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde for euer and euer.</hi> And after cōming to the expositiō of the sayde woordes he sayeth thus. <hi>Doctor Carolostad vvresteth miserablie this pronoune (this:) Svvinglius maketh leane this verbe (is:) Oecolampadius tormenteth this vvorde (bodye:) other doe boucher the vvhole text: and some doe cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie but the halfe thereof: so manifestlie doeth the deuyll holde vs by the</hi> noses. And agayne in the same worke: he hathe these wordes. <hi>To expound the vvordes of Christ as the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentaries doe, (this is the signe of my bodie:) is as absurd an exposition, as if a man shoulde interprete the scripture thus. In the beginning God made heauē &amp; earthe,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <p>Gen. 1.</p>
         <p>
            <hi>Currucam cū ossibus.</hi>
         </p>
      </note>
that is, <hi>the Cuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kovve dyd eate vp the Titling or hedge Sparrovv, together vvith her bones</hi> Again, <hi>in S. Iohn</hi>: <note place="margin">Iohn. 1.</note>
      <hi>And the vvoorde vvas ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de fleshe</hi> that is, <hi>a croked staffe vvas made a kyte.</hi> This was the opinion of holy Luther towching our aduersaries interpretatiō, or rather euasion, and shift: whiche I haue alleaged somewhat more at large against M. Chark, for that he esteemeth and defendeth the man, as a rare in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument of the holy ghoste. VVhich yf it be true: then woe to M Charke and his comparteners, whose spirit is so contrarye to this mans holy illumination.</p>
   <p>By this now it appeareth, that the controuersie is not betwene vs, whiche part prouoketh to scripture, &amp; which doeth not: but (as it hathe allwayes bene betwixt heretiques and Catholiques) which part alleageth true


<pb n="23" facs="14"/>
meaning of Scripture: whiche thing accordinge to the councell of wise Sisinius to Theodosius the Emperour, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Socrat. li.</hi> 5. <hi>hist. ca.</hi> 10.</note> we desire to be tried by the Iudgement of auncient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, indifferent in this matter, for that they lyued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our cōtrouersies came in question. But our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries will allow no exposition but theyr owne: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is easie to defeate what soeuer is brought against them ether scripture or doctour.</p>
   <p>For examples sake, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Examples of shifting scriptures and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours.</hi>
      </note> to proue that we may lawfullie make vowes, &amp; are boūd also to perform the same being made: we alleage the plaine woordes of the prophet: <hi>vouete &amp; reddite domino</hi>: vowe ye and rēder your vowes to god: how will the aduersarie auoyde this, think you? M. Fulke answereth: <note place="margin">Psal. 75. <hi>Against the rocke. pag.</hi> 153.</note>
      <hi>this text belongeth onelye to the olde testament.</hi> But what may not be wiped awaye from vs that lyue vnder the new testament by suche interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations? Again, to proue that there is some state of lyfe of more perfectiō in Christianitie than other, we allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the cleare saying of Christe: <note place="margin">Math. 19.</note>
      <hi>Si vis perfectus esse, vade, vende quae habes, &amp; da pauperibus, &amp; habebis thesaurum in caelo, &amp; veni, sequere me:</hi> Yf thow wilt be perfect, goe, sell all thow hast, and gyue to the poore, and thow shalt haue a treasure in heauen, and come, folowe me. VVhat answer haue they trow you to this? M. Fulke answereth: <note place="margin">
         <hi>Against the rock. pag.</hi> 154.</note>
      <hi>this vvas spoken onelie as a singular triall to that yong man alone, and not to others beside hym.</hi> VVhat a deuise is this? May not he as well say also, that the other woordes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatelie going before, were onlie spokē to this yong man: to witt, <hi>Si vis ad vitam ingredi serua mandata: yf</hi> thow wilt be saued, kepe the cōmaundements: and so deliuer all his gospellers from the burden thereof? what diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rēce is there in these two speches of Christe, seing they are bothe spoken to that yong man, and bothe in the singular number, as infinite other things of the Gospell are to other particular persones, as to the Cananaea, to the Adulteresse, to Nichodemus, to the Cēturio, to Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaeus, to the blynde, deafe and others, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing are common to all, in that they touche eyther lyfe or doctrine?</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="24" facs="15"/>The like absurd shiftes I might repeate in a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred other points. VVhat can be more plaine than the woordes of scripture: <note place="margin">Iacob. 2.</note>
      <hi>videtis quoniam ex operibus iustifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur homo, &amp; non ex fide tantum</hi>? Doe you see how that a man is iustified by woorks and not by fayth onelie? But yet it auayleth nothing. VVhy so? they auoyde it by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation. <hi>S. Iames</hi> (say they) <hi>vnderstandeth of Iustifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before men, and not before God.</hi>
      <note place="margin">D. Fulke <hi>loco citato.</hi>
      </note> O poore deuise: S. Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes hathe in the same place, (talking of fayth without woorkes:) <hi>Nunquid poterit fides saluare eum</hi>? Can faythe without woorks saue him? doeth S. Iames meane here of saluation before men, or before God? Again, whē S Paul sayeth, <note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note>
      <hi>factores legis iustificabuntur</hi>: the doers of the lawe shall be iustyfied: whiche is the verie same thing that S. Iames in other woordes sayeth, that mē shalbe iustified allso by woorks: Doeth S. Paul mean before men or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God? Yf you say, before mē: the text is against you, which hath expressely, <hi>apud deum,</hi> before God. The like euasiō they haue whē we alleage the woords of S. Paul: <note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.</note>
      <hi>qui matrimonio iungit virginem suam, benè facit: &amp; qui non iungit, melius facit</hi>: he that ioyneth his virgin in mariage doeth well: and he that ioyneth her not doethe better. VVhereof vve inferre, that virginitie is more accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, &amp; meritoriouse before God, than mariage, allthough mariage be holie. No (say our aduersaries) S. Paul mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth onelye, that he doeth better before men, and in respect of vvorldlie commodities, but not before God. But this is absurd: for they graunt the former parte of the sentence (he that ioyneth his virgin doeth vvel) to be vnderstoode before God: for that it is sayde also in other vvoordes, <hi>non peccat,</hi> he doeth not sinne: whiche must nedes be vnderstoode in respect of God. How thē can they denie the second clause, (<hi>and he that ioyneth her not, doeth better</hi>) not to be vnderstoode in respect of God also, and in respect of merit and rewarde in the lyfe to come, especiallie whereas Christ promiseth the same rewarde to virginitie in an other place, where he sayeth, <note place="margin">Math. 19.</note>
      <hi>there be Eunuches vvhich haue gelded them selues for the kingdome of heauen, he that can take it, lett hym take it?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb n="25" facs="15"/>You maye see now by this litle (and I might shew by many mo examples) howe bootelesse it is to bring scripture, when we agree not vpon the interpretation. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Hovv pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testantes deny all fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
      </note> VVhat then? shall we bring the auncient fathers and doctors of the primatiue church, for the vnderstanding of scripture? shall we interpret it as they doe? vnderstad it as they vnderstoode it? No, that our aduersaries will not agree vnto, but onelie in matters indifferent &amp; owte of controuersie. VVhere soeuer in matters of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersie betwene vs and them, the olde fathers doe make against them (as in all points they doe:) there will they denie their exposition. For example: The consent of auncient fathers (is alleaged against M. Fulke) attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting superioritie to Peter, vpon the woordes of Christ: <hi>Thovv art Peter, &amp; vpon this rocke vvill I buyld my Church</hi>: <note place="margin">Math: 16.</note> but he auoydeth it verie lightlie, thus: <hi>It can not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied but diuerse of the auncient fathers (othervvyse godlye and learned) vvere deceyued in opiniō of Peters prerogatiue.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Against the rocke. pag.</hi> 242.</note> S. Ambrose, Ierome, Chrisostom, Cyrill, and Theodoret are alleaged for expounding a pece of scripture against M. Fulk, Ioh. 5. abowt Antichrist. How doeth he shift it? thus: <note place="margin">
         <hi>Against the roke. pag.</hi> 291.</note>
      <hi>I ansvver, they haue no ground of this exposition.</hi> S. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome with all the ecclesiasticall writers are alleaged for interpreting of the woords of Daniel cap. 7. against the protestants: <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> M. Fulke, <hi>I ansvver, that neyther Ierome, nor anie ecclesiasticall vvriter vvhome he folovveth, hathe any direction out of the scripture for this interpretation.</hi> S. Austen is alleaged for interpreting Dauids woordes: <hi>he hathe placed his tabernacle in the Sunne</hi>: of the visibilitie of the churche: Fulke: <note place="margin">Psal. 14. <hi>Against the fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resse pa.</hi> 52. <hi>Against purg. pag.</hi> 262.</note>
      <hi>Austen doeth vvrongfullie interpret this place.</hi> S. Ambrose, Ephraim, and Bede are alleaged for interpretatiō of certaine scriptures. Fulke: <hi>Gods vvoorde is so pitifullie vvrested by them, as euery man may see the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ghoste neuer meant any suche thing.</hi> S. Chrisostome is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged for certaine interpretations of scripture: Fulke: <note place="margin">
         <hi>Against purg. pag.</hi> 237.</note>
      <hi>he alleageth in dede scripture, but he applieth it madlie: and yet he often applieth it to the same purpose<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> alas good man.</hi> The consent of fathers is alleaged for interpretatiō of certaine places of scripture, of the prefiguration of the


<pb n="26" facs="16"/>
crosse of Christ. Fulke: <note place="margin">
         <hi>Against the crosse, pag.</hi> 146.</note>
      <hi>The fathers do rather dallie in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feling allegories, than sovvndlie proue that the crosse vvas pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sigured in those places.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I might here make vp a greate volume, yf I wolde prosecute this argumēt, to shew how these new doctors doe contemne &amp; reiecte all authoritie, antiquitie, witt, learning, sanctitie of oure forefathers, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Hovv pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testantes re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iect the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretatiō of their ovv<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne vvriters</hi>
      </note> &amp; of all men (in effect) that euer liued beside them selues: yea, of their owne new doctors and maisters also, when they come to be cōtrarie to anie new deuise, or later fansie of theirs. This is euidēt in Luther reiected by his ofspring about the reall presence, number of sacraments, images, boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the Bible, order of seruice, and the like: <note place="margin">LVTHER CALVINE</note> Also in Caluine reiected about the head of the churche in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, and about all the gouernmēt thereof in Geneua. And I coulde alleage here diuerse examples where he and Beza bothe are reiected by name in diuerse points, bothe of puritanes and protestants in England, when they differ from them: but that this preface wold growe to be too long. VVherefore I maye perhaps (yf this booke come not otherwyse to be too greate) adde a short table or appendix in the end, to shew by examples the vnconstant dealings of our aduersaries herein, and that in verie dede, when all is done and sayd that may be, <note place="margin">
         <hi>The final conclusion of prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants for triall.</hi>
      </note> and all excuses made that can be deuised: the verye conclusion is that, onelye that must be taken for truthe whiche pleaseth them last of all to agree vppon: and theyr bare woordes must be the proofe thereof. For those bookes onelie be scripture in the bible whiche they appoint: &amp; in those bookes, that onelie is the true sense whiche they gyue out: the fathers erred in all things where they differ from them: the new doctors, (as Luther, Caluin, and the rest) sawe so much onelie, of the truthe, as they agree with them, and no further. This is the sayeing of our aduersaries: this is the saying of all the other sectaries of our time: this hathe bene the sayeinge of all heretiques from the beginninge: and this muste needes be the sayeinge of all heretiques for the time to come. For, except they take this waye: it is


<pb n="27" facs="16"/>
vnpossible to stand or encrease against the Church. And by this way a man may beginne what heresie he will to morow next, and defend it against all the learning, witt, and trueth of Christendome. Adioyne now to this, that our aduersaries (notwithstanding all request sute, offer, or humble petition that we ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> make) will come to no publique disputation, or other indifferent and lawfull iudgement: but doe persecute, imprison, torment, and slaughter them which offer the same: and then lett the reader iudge whether they desire &amp; offer iust triall or no, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> M. Charke affirmeth.</p>
   <p>Now for our partes (as I haue sayd) we offer vnto them, <note place="margin">
         <hi>The varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of triall. that Catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liques doe offer.</hi>
      </note> all the best, surest, and easiest means that possiblie can be deuised, or that euer were vsed in Gods Church for triall of trueth, or discouering of heresie. For, as for the bookes of scripture, seing we must receyue them vpō the credit and authoritie of the auncient Church: <note n="1" place="margin">
         <hi>Books of scripture.</hi>
      </note> we are cōtent to accept for canonicall, and allow those, &amp; none other, which antiquitie in Christendome hathe agreed vpon. Next, for the contents of scripture: <note n="2" place="margin">
         <hi>Expresse-vvoordes.</hi>
      </note> yf our aduersaries will stand vpon expresse and plaine woords hereof, we are content to agree therevnto, and we must needes be farre superiours therein. For what one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse plaine text haue they in any one point or article against vs, which we doe not acknowleige literallie as they doe, &amp; as the woordes doe lie? but we haue against them infinit, whiche they can not admit without gloses, and fond interpretations of their owne. For example sake, we haue it expreslie sayd to Pete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> (that signifieth a rocke) <hi>vpon this rocke vvill I buyld my churche</hi>: <note place="margin">
         <hi>Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</hi>
      </note> Math. 16. they haue no where the contrarie in plaine scripture. <note place="margin">HEGOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENOS.</note> VVe haue expresselie (touching the Apostles) <hi>he that is great among you let hym be made as the yonger.</hi> Luc. 22. they haue no where, there is none greater than other among you. VVe haue expresselie: <hi>this is my bodie</hi>: <note place="margin">
         <hi>Real pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence.</hi>
      </note> Math. 26. you haue no where, this is the signe of my bodie. VVe haue expresselie, <hi>the bread that I vvill gyue you is my fleshe Io.</hi> 6. they haue no where, it is but the sygne of my fleshe. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Iustifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
      </note> VVe haue expresselie, <hi>a man is iustified by vvoorkes and not


<pb n="28" facs="17"/>
hy faith onelie, Iacob.</hi> 2. they haue no where, a man is iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified by fayth alone: No, nor that he is iustified by faith without workes, talking of works that folow faith, vvhereof onelie our cōtrouersie is. VVe haue expresse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selye, <hi>vvhose sinnes ye forgyue are forgyuen: vvhose sinnes ye retayne, they are retayned, Ioh.</hi> 20. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Absolutiō.</hi>
      </note> They haue no where, that preestes can not forgyue or retayne sinnes in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the. VVe haue expresselie. <hi>The doers of the lavv shalbe iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified, Rom.</hi> 2. They haue no where, that the law required at Christiās hands is impossible, or, that the doing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of iustifieth not Christians. VVe haue expresselie, <hi>Vovv yee, and render your vovves, Psal.</hi> 75. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Vovves.</hi>
      </note> they haue no where, vow ye not: or, yf yow haue vowed, breake your vowes. VVe haue expresselie, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Traditions</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>kepe the traditions vvhiche ye haue learned, eyther by vvoorde or epistle,</hi> 1. <hi>thess.</hi> 2. They haue no where, the Apostles left no traditions to the church vnwrittē. VVe haue expresselie, <hi>yf thovv vvilt enter into lyfe, kepe the commaundements</hi>: <note place="margin">
         <hi>Commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes.</hi>
      </note> and (when he sayd he dyd that allredie) <hi>yf thovv vvilt be perfect, goe and sell all thovv haste, and gyue to the poore, and folovv me</hi>: They haue no where, that eyther the commaundementes can not be kept, or that we are not bound vnto them, or that there is no degree of lyfe, one perfecter than an other. VVe haue expresselye, <hi>vvoorke your ovvne saluation vvith fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re and trembling Philip.</hi> 2. <note place="margin">
         <hi>VVorkes</hi>
      </note> They haue no where, eyther that a man can woorke nothinge towards his owne sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, beinge holpen with the grace of God: or that a man should make it of his beleefe, that he shalbe saued without all doubt or feare. VVe haue expresselie, <hi>doe ye the vvoorthie fruits of penaunce. Luc.</hi> 3. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Penaunce.</hi>
      </note> They haue no where, that faithe onelie is sufficient with out all satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factiō, and all other woorkes of penaunce on our parts. VVe haue expresselie, <hi>that euerye man shalbe saued accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to his vvoorks, Apoc.</hi> 20. They haue no where that men shalbe Iudged onelie according to their faith. VVe haue expresselie, <hi>that there remaineth a retribution, stipend, and paye to euerie good vvoorke in heauen. Marc.</hi> 9. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>Apo.</hi> 22. <hi>Psal.</hi> 118. They haue no where that good woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes done in Christ, doe merit nothinge. VVe haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presselie,


<pb n="29" facs="17"/>
      <hi>it is a holie cogitatiō to praye for the deade.</hi> 2. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chab.</hi> 12. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Prayer for the deade.</hi>
      </note> They haue no where, it is superstition or vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to doe the same. VVe haue an expresse example <hi>of a holy man that offered sacrifice for the dead.</hi> 2. <hi>Machab.</hi> 12. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Sacrifice for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad.</hi>
      </note> They haue no example of any good man that euer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended it. VVe haue expresselie, that the affliction, whiche Daniel vsed vppon his bodie, was acceptable in the sight of God. <hi>Dan.</hi> 10. They haue no where, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Voluntarie corporall afflictions.</hi>
      </note> that su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che voluntarie corporall afflictions are in vaine. VVe haue expresselie, that an Angel dyd presēt Tobias good woorkes, and almes deedes before God. Tob. 12. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Almes.</hi>
      </note> They haue no were, that Angels can not, or doe not the same. VVe reade expresselie, that Ieremias the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>het after he was deade praied for the people of <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rael.</hi> 2. <hi>Mach.</hi> 15. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Prayer of sainctes.</hi>
      </note> they haue no where the contrarye to this. I leaue manie thinges more that I might repeate. But this is enoughe (for example sake) to proue, that albeit our aduersaries doe vaunt of scripture: yet when it cometh to expresse woordes: they haue no text against vs in lieu of so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie as I haue here repeated against them: nor can they shew, that we are driuen to denie anie one booke of the Bible, nor to glose vppon the plaine woordes of anye one plaine place of scripture, as they are enforced to doe.</p>
   <p>But now yf they will not stand onelie to plaine and expresse woordes of scripture, <note n="3" place="margin">
         <hi>Necessarie collections vpon scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</hi>
      </note> but also (as in dede they must) to necessarie collections made, and inferred of scripture: then muste we referre onr selues to the auncient primatiue church, for this meaning of Gods woord. For it is like they knew it best: for that they ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued nearer to the writers thereof (than we doe) whoe could well declare vnto them, what was the meaning of the same. And then our aduersaries well know, how the aunciēt fathers do ground purgatorie, prayer to saints, sacrifice of the Aultar, vse of the crosse, and other like points of our religion, (besides tradition) vpon the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of scriptures, also expounded accordinge to their meaning: albeit oure aduersaries denie the same to be well expounded.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="30" facs="18"/>If our aduersaries will yet goe further for the triall of our Spirits: we are well content, and we refuse none that euer antiquitie vsed for the triall of a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique and hereticall spirit. The olde heretiques Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mosatenus, Arrius, Macedonius, Nestorius &amp; Eutiches were tried and condēned by the councells of Antioche, Nice, Constantinople, and Chalcedon: <note n="4" place="margin">
         <hi>Councells</hi>
      </note> and other here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques by other councelles since. VVe are content to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre our selues to all the Christian councells that euer haue bene sence Christ dyed. And all men knowe that the last moste learned godlie and generall councell of Trent was gathered for that purpose, &amp; offered all safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conduct to our aduersaries to come thither to triall: but they refused it.</p>
   <p>
      <note n="5" place="margin">
         <p>
            <hi>Doctors of the olde Churche.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>Li.</hi> 1. <hi>contra Iulian. c.</hi> 2.</p>
      </note>Besides this, the auncient fathers haue vsed diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se times, diuerse other means of triall: As first, by refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the matter to the triall of olde doctors, which ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued before the cōtrouersies begāne. This meane vsed S. Austen against Iulian the pelagian, and produceth the consent of fathers, bothe of the east, and of the west Churche vntill his tyme: and there asketh hym, whoe he is that dareth to oppose hym selfe to the credit of these men: to call them blynde: to saye they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued: where as they were the verie lights of the citie of God? The like waye dyd Theodosius the Emperour take by the counsaile of Sisinius, and suggestion of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctarius, to bring the Arriās heresie to some ende, as So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates writeth. <note place="margin">
         <p>
            <hi>Socr. li.</hi> 5. <hi>hist. ca.</hi> 10.</p>
         <p>
            <hi>Li.</hi> 2. <hi>contra here.</hi>
         </p>
      </note> And Epiphanius I sayethe, this is enough to say against all heresies: <hi>Ecclesia Catholica haec non do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euit: Sancti pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>res haec minimè receperunt.</hi> The Catholique Churche hathe not taught this, the holie fathers haue not admitted this. Now, how our aduersaries doe flie this means of triall, they are not ashamed to confesse it openlie.</p>
   <p>
      <note n="6" place="margin">
         <hi>The Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi>
      </note>An other waie is to consider whiche is the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique or vniuersall Church, or great multitude of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, out of whiche the one part first departed. This way vsed S. Austen against diuerse heretiques, as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melie against the Manacheis, whē he sayeth: <hi>Multa sunt


<pb n="31" facs="18"/>
quae in Catholicae ecclesiae gremio me iustissimè teneant</hi>: <note place="margin">
         <hi>Cont. ep fundam. cap.</hi> 4.</note>
      <hi>tenet consensio populorum at{que} gentium, &amp; tenet ipsum Catholicae n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>men:</hi>
      <q>There are manie things which vpon good cause doe holde me in the lappe of the Catholique Churche: for the verie cōsent of people and nations doeth holde me: Also the verie name of Catholique church holdeth me.</q>
And Vincentius Lirinensis liuing about the same time writeth to the same effect against heresies. <note place="margin">
         <hi>In hys boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke against the profane innoua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>iōs of all here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies: in the beginninge</hi>
      </note>
      <q>In ipsa Catholica ecclesia magnoperè curandum est, vt id teneamus quod vbi{que}, quod semper, quod ab omnibus creditum: &amp;c. Sed hoc ita demū fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, sv sequamur vniuersitatē, antiquitatē, consen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sionem. Sequemur autem vniuersitatem hoc modo: si hanc vnā fidem veram esse fateamur, quam tota per orbem terrarum confi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>etur ec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lesia: Antiquitatem vero ita, si ab hiis nullate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus sensibus recedamus, quos, sanctos maiores ac patres nostros celebrasse manifestum est: Consensionem quoque itidem; si in ipsa ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ustate, omnium vel certè penè omnium sacerdotum &amp; magistrorum definitiones sententiasque sectemur.</q>
      <q>VVe must greatlie take heede, in the Catholique Churche, to hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> that whiche hathe bene beleued in euerie place, all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, &amp; of all Christiās &amp;c. And this we shall doe, yf in oure beleefe we folow vniuersalitie, antiquitie, and cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent. VVe shall folow vniuersalitie, <note place="margin">
            <hi>Vniuersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</hi>
         </note> yf we confesse that onelie faith to be true, whiche the Churche spred ouer all the worlde doeth cōfesse: we shall folowe antiquitie, <note place="margin">
            <hi>Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi>
         </note> yf we depart not from that meaning and sense of scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture which is euident that our forefathers and aunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stours haue held: we shall folow consent, <note place="margin">
            <hi>Consent.</hi>
         </note> yf we embrace the definitions and opinions eyther of all, or of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ste parte of preestes and teachers in antiquitie. The like way doeth S. Ierome take against the Luciferians:</q>
and other fathers against other heretiques. And howe quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quelie our aduersaries spirit were tried by this way of Antiquitie, vniuersalitie and consent, all men that haue vnderstanding may Iudge.</p>
   <p>An other way there is also, and muche vsed by the fathers against heretiques: and that is, <note n="7" place="margin">
         <hi>Succession of Popes.</hi>
      </note> to proue theyr religiō by the successiō of bishops in the See of Rome: wherein the successour alwayes, teaching the doctrine


<pb n="32" facs="19"/>
of his predecessour, it must nedes be a strong argument to proue the descent and continuance of one and the same faithe from the Apostles time. <note place="margin">
         <p>
            <hi>Contr. ep. fundam. cap.</hi> 4.</p>
         <p>Iohn. 21.</p>
      </note> This argumēt vseth S. Austen in the place before alleaged:
<q>
         <hi>Tenet ab ipsa sede Petri Apostoli, (cui pascendas oues post resurrectionem domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus commendauit) vsque ad praesentem episcopa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>um successio sacerdotum.</hi> The succession of preests in the Churche of Rome euē from the chair of Peter (vnto whome our lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de after his resurrection commended his sheepe to be fedde) vnto this byshoprik that now is, doeth holde me in the Catholique Churche.</q>
The same waye of triall he vseth, and muche more at large, in hys hundred three skore and fyueth epistle, where he reckoneth vpp all the byshopps of Rome from Peter vnto Anastasius (whiche was byshop in his tyme,) and thinketh this a good proofe against the donatists, that none of those held or fauoured theyr opinion. The lyke waye of triall vsed Optatus Mileuitanus against the same donatists before S. Austen, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Li.</hi> 2. <hi>cont. Donatist.</hi>
      </note> reckoning vp all the byshopps of Rome vntill SIRICIVS, that satte in his time. The same waye of triall vsed holy Irenaeus, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Li.</hi> 3. <hi>cont. haer. cap.</hi> 3.</note> before eyther of bothe these men, against the heretiques of his time, reckoninge vpp all the byshops of Rome, vntill Eleutherius that held the See in his time, <hi>addinge that by this succession, he dyd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fovvnd the pride of all heretiques that durst to teache other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvise than this See had held.</hi>
And after, concluding thus: <hi>est plenissima haec ostensio, vnam &amp; eandem viuificatricem fidem esse, quae in ecclesia ab Apostolis vsque nunc sit conseruata &amp; tradita in veritate.</hi>
      <q>This ys a moste full proofe, that one &amp; the selfe same quickninge faithe hathe bene deliuered in truthe, and commended from the Apostles vnto this day.</q>
But now this way of triall I know oure aduersaries will not admitt.</p>
   <p>
      <note n="8" place="margin">
         <hi>Infection<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> vvith olde heresies.</hi>
      </note>An other waye of triall is to examine what parte doeth holde anye olde cōdemned heresie. For as an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retique hauing once lost the habit of fayth gyuen hym in baptisme, is easily moued to cope with anye heresie new or olde that commeth in his waye, and serueth his turne: so moste certaine it is, that the true Catholique


<pb n="33" facs="19"/>
churche can neuer admitt or defend any heresie. <note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.</note> For otherwyse she coulde not be the pillar of trueth. And we beleeue with holie Athanasius in his creed: <hi>that he vvhich holdeth not the faythe vvholye in all points shall perish eternallie,</hi> howe soeuer our aduersaries doe salue the matter in theyr prophets Berengarius, Husse, VVikliffe, and Luther, whome they say to haue bene holie men, &amp; yet to haue erred in diuers points of faithe, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Marke this gentle rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi>
      </note> and to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue held theyr erreurs obstinatelie to the daye of theyr deathe. But wee beleue the contrarye, as I haue sayed. And therefore who soeuer could shew but one cōfessed heresie to be defended by our churche, there neded no more disputation about the matter.</p>
   <p>But now for the right vse of this way of triall, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Tvvo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</hi>
      </note> the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re be two conditions to be obserued of his part whiche will obiect an olde heresie to an other. The first is, that the partie doe in dede holde that thinge whiche he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecteth, and not a certaine likeliehoode of it. For that were to slaunder, and not to obiect. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Iniurious dealinge of our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries.</hi>
      </note> As when oure ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries doe obiect to vs the heresie of Pelagius abowt free will, it is a mere slaunder. For we holde that mans will beinge preuented and holpen with the grace of God may woorke well: but he helde that it could do the same by the power and force of nature, without the helpe of gods grace, as S Augustin proueth at large in his booke of free will. The like iniurie they doe vs, in many other things, which they obiect against vs: as the heresie of those whiche dyd sacrifice to our ladie, and the like, whiche we doe not. The second condition is that the heresie obiected be in dede suche as was accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted and condemned for an heresie, in the primatiue churche, and not onelie that an heretique held it. For heretiques doe holde diuerse truethes alwayes together withe falsehode: And for lack of this condition doe our aduersaries often abuse the simple people. As M. Fulke oftentimes sayeth: prayer for the deade is an heresie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Montanists (which were heretiques) helde it. But lett hym proue that euer this was accompted one of Mōtanus hys heresies, &amp; thē he proueth somewhat. But


<pb n="34" facs="20"/>
that he can neuer doe: for he graūteth, Austen, Ambrose, Chrisostom, Ierom, and others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o haue vsed prayers for the deade, whoe notwitstanding were great enemies to Montanus, and all his errors. VVherefore this is a verie malitiouse kynde of abusing people. And I heere saye again, that lett hym and all the protestants in the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de proue, that we doe holde in dede, but anie one thing, which was accōpted an heresie in the primatiue church, &amp; we will graunt that we are not the Catholique Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, but that in all other things we erre besides.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Protestan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes doe hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de olde he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resies.</hi>
      </note>But we in charging them vvithe heresies doe obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue allvvayes the foresayd tvvo conditions. As for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, vve charge them vvith the opinion of Aerius, vvhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che denied prayer for the dead: And that they holde this verie same opinion, they vvill not denie: And that it vvas accompted an heresie in the primatiue churche: <note place="margin">
         <p>
            <hi>Aug. li. de he. ad quod vult. haere.</hi> 53. <hi>Epipha. haer.</hi> 75.</p>
         <p>
            <hi>Against Brystoes mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiues pa.</hi> 15.</p>
      </note>
vve alleage for vvitnesses S. Augustin and Epiphanius. Hovv doe they auoyde this? No vvaye, but by sayeinge that Augustin and Epiphanius vvere deceyued, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording that for an heresie vvhiche vvas none: for that is M. Fulks answere: whiche is to condemne all that age: for that those holie fathers wrote downe heresies as they were taken in those dayes by the church. The lyke we doe about vigilantius: whose opinions were (among others) that Saints were not to be prayed to, nor their reliques to be honored: Now that the protestants hold this, no man dowteth: And that this was accompted he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie in the primatiue churche, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Li. cont. vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilantium.</hi>
      </note> we cite S. Ierome for a wittnesse which wrote against hym. VVhat shift is there here? None, but to deface S. Ierome and commend vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilantius, and to denie it to be an heresie: for so doeth, M. Fulke, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Against the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues. pa.</hi> 54.</note> sayeing further, that <hi>Ierome rather raileth than reasoneth, and that vigilantius vvas a good man, and his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion sovvnd.</hi> The like order we take in a nūber of other olde hereticall points, whiche we charge them withall: as may be sene in the tables and books sett owt of this matter. Now yf our aduersaries could bringe vs to anie suche confession of heresie, the matter were ended. But they can not: and therefore I know they will neuer ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt


<pb n="35" facs="20"/>
this way of triall.</p>
   <p>The last way of triall (whereof I will speake at this time) is to consider the maners of olde heretiques, <note n="9" place="margin">
         <hi>The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of olde heretiques.</hi>
      </note> &amp; to compare the same with oures. And here I wolde haue also the former two conditions obserued: To witt, that we consider suche qualities onelie as were accompted hereticall in them: that is, proper to heretiques: and to examine them trulie withoute partiall affection in our selues. For example: <note place="margin">
         <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cont. lit. Petil. cap.</hi> 51.</note> S. Augustin doeth note it as an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall propertie in the donatists to hate the See of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and to call it <hi>cathedram pestilentiae,</hi> the chair of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stilence. Doeth this agree to protestants, or to vs? As also the defaming of the said See, sor the euell pretended ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe of some particular men?<note place="margin">
         <p>
            <hi>De vnitare ecclesiae. cap.</hi> 12.</p>
         <p>
            <hi>Li.</hi> 3. <hi>contr. lit. peti. c.</hi> 4.</p>
         <p>
            <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 9. <hi>contr. epi. parm. &amp; ep.</hi> 169. <hi>ad Euseb.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>Li.</hi> 1. <hi>cont. maximinū.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cont. Donat.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>Victor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persecutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica.</hi>
         </p>
      </note> As likewise he noteth it as an hereticall tricke in them, to persuade the people that the visible churche had erred, and oppressed the true churche, banishinge her from the sight of the worlde. Doe not our aduersaries say the verie same? Also he no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the same heretiques <hi>for hatinge and condemninge the lyfe of monkes, as also for dravving Nonnes out of theyr cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, and ioyninge them selues vvith the same in pretended vvedlocke.</hi> Finallie he noteth it as hereticall in the Arriās, to appeale from traditions to onelie scripture. Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore S. Augustin, Optatus noted it as hereticall in the donatists <hi>to breake aultars vvherevpon the bodie and blood of Christ vvere kept,</hi> as the woordes of Optatus are. And about the same time Victor Vticensis wrote his storie against the vandall heretiques: where he setteth furthe moste liuelie the state of our time, by the maners and behauiours of those heretiques, in breakinge chalices: prophaning of holie Chrisme, spoylinge of churche ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimēts, throweing the blessed sacramēt of the aultar on the ground, with other moste horrible abuses to the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, not to be repeated: in prohibiting masse to be sayd by edicts and proclamation, and a hundred things moe: whiche are the verie exercises of our aduersaries now. The like things in many points doeth S. Basil obiect as sacrilegious against Iulian the Apostata and his folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers: <note place="margin">
         <hi>Orat.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>in Iulia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi>
      </note> wherfore I thinke our aduersaries will not admitt</p>
   <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
   </gap>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>