<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114342_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68614</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20476.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114342</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The unbishoping of Timothy and Titus. Or A briefe elaborate discourse, prooving Timothy to be no bishop (much lesse any sole, or diocæsan bishop) of Ephesus, nor Titus of Crete : and that the power of ordination, or imposition of hands, belongs jure divino to presbyters, as well as to bishops, and not to bishops onely. Wherein all objections and pretences to the contrary are fully answered; and the pretended superiority of bishops over other ministers and presbyters jure divino, (now much contended for) utterly subverted in a most perspicuous maner. By a wellwishe to Gods truth and people</title>
                 <author>Prynne, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stam, Jan Fredericksz</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>165, that is 173, 5 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, what that Oracle of wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome hath registred; <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb. 13. 10. Onely by pride cometh contention;</hi> was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more really verified in any one particular, then in the Prelates: whose ambitious windy tumor, and overswelling pride, as in al former ages, so in this, hath <note n="a" place="margin">See Theodoricus à Niem, Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barel, &amp; Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annis Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius De Schismate. Master Tyndals obedience of a Christian man; and practise of Popish Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates. Doctor Iohn White his Defence of the way, c. 6. the fifth part of the Homily against Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience &amp; willfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. Fox Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments throughout. Catalog. Testium Veritatis.</note>
      <hi>filled the whole Christian world with warres, with civill dissensions; and the Church it selfe, with endlesse schismes, controversies, contentions, which else would never had existence.</hi> The pretended pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy of the great Pontificall Bishop of Rome, what tumults, battles, warres, treasons, rebellions, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, martyrdomes, hath it ingendred on the one hand; what disputes, bookes of controversie, and paper-battles, on the other? What innumerable Schismes, Treatises (which the endoubted parity of Ministers and Bishops <hi>Iure Divino</hi> had prevented) have
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>
the Prelates pretended superiority by divine institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, over Presbyters and their fellow-Ministers, produced in all ages, Churches, especially in our owne, (which from the first glimmerings of the Gospell in Iohn Wiclifes dayes till now, hath beene more or lesse disquieted with this unhappy controversie?) which being raked up in the ashes for a space, by reason of our Bishops waiving of their divine right, (which not onely <hi>Archbishop</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Com. in Phil 1. 1. in Tit. 1. 5. 7. in 1. Tim 3. &amp; 4.</note>
      <hi>Anselme,</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">De Quest. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menorum. l. 11. c. 1. to 8.</note>
      <hi>Richardus Armachanus,</hi> and <note n="d" place="margin">Balaeus Cent. 8. c. 19.</note>
      <hi>Bishop Peacocke</hi> of old, but likewise <note n="e" place="margin">Fox Acts Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments p. 9▪ 2. 973.</note>
      <hi>Bishop Tonstall, Bishop Stokesly,</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">On the 8 Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</note>
      <hi>Bishop Hooper,</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">Defence of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie. part. 2. c. 3. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis. 1. 5. p. 85. 99. 100. 101. &amp;c. 9. Divis. 1 p. 196. 202.</note>
      <hi>Bishop Iewell,</hi>
      <note n="h" place="margin">Poore mans Library, part. 1. f. 95. 96.</note>
      <hi>Bishop Alley,</hi>
      <note n="i" place="margin">Exposit. on Aggius, vers. 1. &amp; 2.</note>
      <hi>Bishop Pilkington,</hi> yea <note n="k" place="margin">Against Cartwright. p. 389.</note>
      <hi>Archbishop Whitgift</hi> himselfe, and <note n="l" place="margin">Of the Princes Supremacy. p. 359.</note>
      <hi>Bishop Bridges,</hi> to omitt all others, have since them publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly disclaimed; <hi>confessing Bishops and Presbyters, lure Divino to be allone, equall, and the same;</hi> and the Statutes of 37. <hi>H. 8. c. 17. 1. Ed. 6. c. 2. 1. &amp; 2. Mariaec. 8. &amp; 1. Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>z ab. c. 1. for ever judicially in full Parliament resolved against;)</hi> yet our present ambitious Prelates studying to surmount their predecessors, not onely in worldly pompe and power, derived from their indulgent Soveraigne, but likewise in spirituall Iurisdiction, claimed from God himselfe, (though they have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time nor care to preach, pray, or doe him any Episcopall service, being wholly taken up with secular offices and affaires, and <note n="‡" place="margin">Maith. 6. 24. Lu. 16. 13. 1. Iohn. 2. 15. 16.</note>
      <hi>unable to serve God for ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="5" facs="3"/>
his incompacible enemies, Mamōn, and the world,)</hi> have lately blowne abroade the coales, and resuscita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the violent flames of this contention afresh, by a new ambitious claime of all their Episcopall Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignity and Iurisdiction, <hi>Iure Divino,</hi> even <hi>in the High Commission Court it selfe,</hi> in the late censure of <hi>Doctor Bastwicke,</hi> for a Booke written <hi>onely against the Pope and Italian Bishops,</hi> without any reflection upon them, as all men then conceived, and therefore wondred at, till their magnifying of the <hi>Church of</hi>
      <note n="m" place="margin">See Chownaeus Collect▪ Theolog. and Shel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford his 5. Treatises.</note>
      <hi>Rome as a true Church in that Censure of his, and some late licensed Pamphlets,</hi> their Antichristian and Papall proceedings against Gods truth, Ministers, Ordinances, and the late authorizing of <hi>Doctor Pocklingtons</hi>
      <note n="n" place="margin">Pag. 2. 43. 44.</note>
      <hi>Sunday no Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, by the Archbishop of Canterburies owne Chaplaine, Master Bray;</hi> which expressly avers, <hi>that our Arch-bishops and Bishops can and doe lineally derive their Pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree and Succession from Peter and the Popes of Rome; hath since in structed the ignorant people, that Popes Italian and English Bishops, are in truth</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">See Henry Stalbridge his Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatory Epistle. William Wraghton his Hunting of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish Fox. Rodericke Mors his Complaint. c. 23. Master Tyndals his obedience of a Christian man, and Practise of Popish Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates. Fox Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 414. 514. 516. 518. Master Whethenhall his Discourse of the Corruptions now in Question with others.</note>
      <hi>all members of the same body, whelpesof the same litter, branches of the same tree, and our present Prelates the Pope of Romes owne lineally dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended sonnes,</hi> so as they could not but be sensible of, and highly offended, if not actually lashed, wounded with their fathers scourge; <hi>Flagellum Pontificis &amp; Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coporum Latialium,</hi> being a whip for them, as well as for the Italian Prelates.</p>
   <p>Now because in that late Censure of theirs, they
<pb n="6" facs="4"/>
all founded the divine right of their Episcopall Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendency and Dominion over their Fellow-Pres by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, onely on the examples of Timothy and Titus, (whom they then new consecrated Diocaesan Bishops over Ephesus and Crete 1608. yearely after their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cease, though Christ and Paul himselfe had never done it in their life times:) and on a supposed divine Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopoly of conferring Orders and imposing hands, appropriated by God himselfe to Diocaesan Bishops, distinct in Iurisdiction, power and degree from Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters and Presbyters; I have therefore here for the future quie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>ing of this much agitated controversie, confined my discourse within the lists of such questions, (not formerly fully debated by any in the English tongue, that I have met with) by the discus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion whereof I have (I suppose) so shaken these rotten pillars, and undermined these <note n="o" place="margin">Matth. 7. 26. 27.</note>
      <hi>sandy foundations</hi> of their high-towring, over-swelling Hierarchy, as that I have left them no divine prop or groundworke to support it longer; so as it must now certainly (for any stay is left it in Scripture) come tumbling downe headlong to the very ground, (and me thinkes I heare the fall of it allready sounding in my eares) unlesse with speed they wholly quit these false foundations, and bottom their Prelacy and Iurisdiction onely on his Majesties Princely favour, (not Gods or Christs divine institution) which because they have so lately judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially disclaimed in open Court, and even at <hi>this present execute all Acts of Episcopall Iurisdiction by their owne inherent power, without any speciall Commission from his Majesty under his greate Seale, keeping their Courts,
<pb n="7" facs="4"/>
visitations, and making out all their citations, proces, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communications, probate of wils, Letters of administration &amp;c. in their owne names and under their owne Seales, as if they were absolute Popes and Monarches, contrary to the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of 25. H. 8. c. 19. 26. H. 8. c. 1. 37. H. 8. c. 17. 1. Ed. 6. c. 2. 1. Eliz. c. 1. 8. Eliz. c. 1. their Oath of Supremacy,</hi> and their <hi>High-Commission</hi> it selfe, which might teach them another lesson (as that it confines them to doe all things by his Majesties speciall Commission, in his name and under his Seale, when they are all there joyned together, much more therefore when they are divided in their severall Dioces;) and because they have <note n="*" place="margin">See Sir Iohn Dauis his Irish Reports. f. 97. 98▪ an excellent passage to this purpose. q Math. 7. 27.</note>
      <hi>blotted out Caesars Image and superscription, his Armes and royall Title out of their Courts, proces and all ecclesiasticall proceedings, and inserted onely their owne in leive thereof, that so they may appeare to all the world to be no longer his but theirs, and hee (if hee should chance to chalenge and resume them as his owne) might not henceforth owne or claime them to be his;</hi> they have litle reason now to attempt, and his Majesty farre lesse to suffer, and so having neither God nor the King, divine nor humaine Right to support them, they must (as the proverbe is, <hi>between two stooles the arse goes to the ground)</hi> now at last in the middest of their usurped greatnes, fall flat upon the ground, and this their <hi>fall, q proove very great,</hi> because they now of late, are growen so, <note n="*" place="margin">Doctor Barnes, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles. Artic. 8. p. 211. Master Tyndals Practise of Popish Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates p. 342 343. &amp;c. and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of a Christian man.</note>
      <hi>not being content with the office of a Bishop, but they must be also Kings, temporall Lords and cheife state officers, against Christs expresse commaund and Gods owne Law, to sway both Church and state at pleasure so they may ingrosse</hi>
      <note n="‡" place="margin">37. H. 8. c. 17.</note>
      <hi>into their sacred hands the sole rule
<pb n="8" facs="5"/>
and government of the world, having great possessions; and being great Lords also as they are Prelates, and yet doing nothing therefore at all in point of preaching, fecding, and instructing the people committed to their spirituall charge, but onely playing the part of a Bishop, as a Christmas game-player doth of a King and as a Poppet, which springeth up and downe, and cryeth Peepe, Peepe, and goeth his way,</hi> as <note n="*" place="margin">What the Keyes of the Church be. p. 266. u Prov. 16. 18.</note>
      <hi>Doctor Barnes writes</hi> wittily of <hi>the Bishops of his age.</hi> Which swelling greatnesse <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> ambition of theirs as it will make their downefall the greater, so the speedier, being a sure prognosticke of their approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ruine, as the greatnesse of any unnaturall swelling in the body is of its present ensuing rupture. <hi>u Pride ever going before destruction, and a lofty spirit before a fall,</hi> and they usually dogging them at the heeles; because <note n="*" place="margin">1. Pet. 5. 5.</note>
      <hi>God himselfe resisteth the proud,</hi> but then most of all when they are at the highest; according to that of the Psalmist, <note n="‡" place="margin">Psa. 119. 119.</note>
      <hi>Thou puttest away all the wicked of the earth like drosse,</hi> which assoone as ever it hath gotten up to the top of the pot, and elevated it selfe above the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> mettle, is then scummed off and cast away.</p>
   <p>Towards which their desired speedy downfall, if these my unworthy labours shall through Gods bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing on, and thy prayers for them, contribute any assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, for the ease, releife or comfort of Gods poore people, <note n="*" place="margin">See Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> on his supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Vol. 3. of his Workes in folio f. 21. to. 25. A most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage to this purpose sui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to our times.</note>
      <hi>who are every where most wrongfully, without, yea</hi>
      <note n="‡" place="margin">Magna Charta. c. 29. The Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of Right. 3. Caroli. and other Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes in Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctall Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation.</note>
      <hi>against all Law and reason oppressed, and cast out of their benefices, freeholds, possessions, imprisoned, fined, excommunicated, silenced, suspended, vilified, crushed, and troden under feet by their intolerable tyrannie, might and unbounded extravagant power,</hi> I shall neither repent me
<pb n="9" facs="5"/>
of the penning, nor thou thy selfe of the reading of it, wherefore here humbly prostrating it to thy impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Censure, and commending it to the blessing of that omnipotent God, who to shew the infinitenes of his wisedome and power, doth oft times <note n="z" place="margin">1. Cor. 1. 27. 28. 29.</note>
      <hi>choose the foolish things of the world to confound the wise, the weake things of the world to confound the things that are mighty, and base things of the world, and things that are despised, yea and things that are not, to bring to nought things that are, that no flesh should glory in his presence.</hi> I shall take my leave of thee till some further occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</p>
   <closer>Farewell, and pray for me.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>