<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the indifferent and friendly Reader.</title>
           <author>Perrot, James</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114574_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09490</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19773</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114574</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the indifferent and friendly Reader.</title>
                 <author>Perrot, James</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first part of the consideration of hvmane condition : vvherin is contained the morall consideration of a mans selfe: as what, who, and what manner of man he is. Written by I.P. Esquier</title>
                 <author>Perrott, James, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Barnes, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Barnes, Joseph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Broome (Brome), Joan</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the indifferent and friendly Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know that they, vvhich publish any thinge in writing vnto the worlde, doe submitte them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues vnto common censure. And I am not ignorāt, that as it is more easie to finde a fault in things done, thē to doe the same so substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially, as no faulte shall be founde therewith: so is it more easie to amend, then to make. If therefore I haue erred in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing (as I acknowledge no such excellency in mee, but that I may easily mistake) Let accustomed community of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring excuse me amōgst others. For, <hi>humanū est errare.</hi> And if he that pervseth this Tracte, do find any faultes therin, I shall desire the direction of his better iudgment to amend them; vvhich I vvillesteeme as a very greate favour. I commend this <hi>first parte of Consideration</hi> to thy honest and discreet construction. It containeth the <hi>Morall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration of a mans selfe.</hi> There are three other pointes of Consideration by mee intended to bee published: the next vvhereof is the <hi>Politicall Consideration of those thinges, that are vnder vs.</hi> The thirde is the <hi>Naturall Consideration of those thinges, that are about vs.</hi> The fourth and laste is the <hi>Metaphysicall Consideration of those thinges, that are aboue vs.</hi> This first, vvhich is here published, I haue offered as a taste of my labours, and a triall of thy good or ill allovvance; if it bee accepted with
<pb facs="4"/>as good meaning, as it vvas offered, and that the honorable Personage, to vvhome this is dedicated (and to vvhome all the rest of my labors are due doe not direct the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie; I vvill proceede as speedily, as conveniently I can, to publish the rest. But if this yeelde thee any distaste, or bee disliked; it is but so much labour lost in that, vvhich is al ready done, and so much labour saued, in that, vvhich should be hereafter done. So as thou wishest vvell, farevvell.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From my house at Haroldstone <date>the <hi>16.</hi> of November.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>The well willer of them, that wish well. IAMES PERROTT.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>