<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRI∣stian Reader; Increase of Faith, Hope, and Patience.</title>
           <author>H., A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114895_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02744</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12874</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114895</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRI∣stian Reader; Increase of Faith, Hope, and Patience.</title>
                 <author>H., A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A cordiall for the afflicted : Touching the necessitie and utilitie of afflictions. Proving unto us the happinesse of those that thankfully receive them: and the misery of all that want them, or profit not by them. By A. Harsnet, B.D. and Minister of Gods word at Cranham in Essex</title>
                 <author>Harsnett, Adam</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hodgkinson, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <distributor>Meredith, Christopher</distributor>
                            <distributor>Stephens, Philemon</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>42, 594 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader; Increase of Faith, Hope, and Patience.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ʋch is our blindnesse, and ignorance, that wee are too ready to judg amisse of our selves: as may appeare by two extreames, into which the most runne. The one is self-conceitednesse, or flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering our selves, in, and about our spirituall estate: perswading our selves that wee are in the estate of Grace, and that wee have the love and favor of God, when as it is neither so, nor
<pb facs="9"/>
so. For the redressing of which mischiefe, I have heretofore undertaken the discoverie of true and sound grace, from false &amp; counterfeit; that so we may no longer be deluded by an overweening of our selves, and too high an opinion of our goodnesse, as if we were that which wee are not, or were not that which wee are. The other extream is a diffidence, and distrust of Gods love, and our own happines, through the sense, and smart of some troubles and afflictions wherewith it pleaseth the Lord in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and wisdom to exercise and trie us. Whence it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to passe, that too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="9"/>
of Gods deere ones, are ready to cēsure themselves as out-casts (or at the best) as a people, but meanly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, or regarded of God, in that they are so sorely afflicted. For the healing of which error; that there may be no mistaking, that we neither charge the Lord with any want of love to us ward, or hard dealing with us in afflicting of us, nor surcharge our selves with unnecssary, &amp; needles feares, and cares; nor yet causelesly increase our griefe, by adding of more sorrow to our affliction, I have now undertaken this Treatise. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my desire, and ayme
<pb facs="10"/>
is to minister some comfort to such as are in affliction, that so they may not cast off their hope of hapines in Heaven, because they are exercised with judgments upon earth: but rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that the Lord it now refining and pollishing them, that so they may bee the fitter for that glory which is prepared for thē. I know it is a hard thing to obey in suffering: yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is that which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth for our good, we should with the more willingnes, and cheerfulnes, undergo whatsoever afflictiōs it shal please the Lord to exercise us with. If our afflictions brought God out of love
<pb facs="10"/>
with us, or us more in love with that which God hates and is hurtfull unto us: or if our afflictions were sent unto us as curses, wee had great cause to mourn in them: but seeing they make so much for our good (being sanctified unto us) and the word of truth telleth us, that wee are blessed in thē, have wee not great cause to bee thankfull to God for them? the Lord sees how ready we are to plunge our selves into perils, if we be but a while exempted from afflictions: therefore that wee may not be too bold with sin, the Lord wil have us to fall into affliction, least (being let alone) wee
<pb facs="11"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="11"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="12"/>
fall into condemnation. For where God is most si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in threatning, and most patient in sparing, there is he most inflamed with anger, and purpose of revenge. And seeing we are willing to receive (being sick or diseased) any medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine from the hand of him, that can truely say, <hi>proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum est,</hi> good experience hath been made of the worth, &amp; working of it; let my counsel <hi>(good reader)</hi> be acceptable unto thee, &amp; give me leave to tell thee, how much good thou maist gain by afflictiō, if through thine unbelief, and impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience thou doest not put it from thee. I assure thee (by
<pb facs="12"/>
good experience (that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever afflictiō be untooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some, and unpleasing to the flesh, it is most soveraign, and profitable unto the soul as in the Treatise follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I have made plaine unto thee. Now if the stile, and phrase dislike any, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is so plain, and homelike; let him know that I prepared this provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion for poore and hungry souls, unto whom course &amp; mean things are welcome, and bitter things are sweet; not for queasie, and full stomacks, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spise an hony-combe. He that is falne into a pit, wil refuse no hand that may help him out of it. He that
<pb facs="13"/>
hath a wound in his body, will be glad of any plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster that may heal or ease him. Accept then, of these my poore labors, which (I desire) may be as a hand to help thee out of affliction, or as balsume to heal those gashes which afflictiō hath, or may make in thee, or to give thee some ease &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in them. Read in faith, and receive in love, what is heer tendered unto thee. If any comfort, or content may hereby accrue unto thine afflicted soul, and grieved minde, let God have thy praises, and let me have thy praiers, who desireth to rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy servant in the Lords Worke. A. H.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>