<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114366_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10833</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21107a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114366</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A defence of the doctrine propounded by the synode at Dort : against Iohn Murton and his associates, in a treatise intuled [sic] ; A description what God, &amp;c. With the refutation of their answer to a writing touching baptism. By Iohn Robinson</title>
                 <author>Robinson, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles, Successors of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 203, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>record</hi> which the Apostle <hi>bare the Iews</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 2.</note> in his time; such as either reade these mens wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, or know their persons may bear them; which is, that <hi>they haue a zeal of God, but not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to knowledg,</hi> I add touching them, nor in modesty neither. Which if it held any place in their hearts, as were meet, would moderate and restrain both their causlesse presumption in themselvs, and gracelesse licentiousnesse which they fear not to use, both towards God, and other men.</p>
   <p>They would seem very zealous for the <hi>Scriptures</hi> purity and <hi>perfection:</hi> vvarning all to <hi>take heed they presume not aboue</hi>
      <note place="margin">Epistle to the Reader▪</note>
      <hi>what is written;</hi> nor to <hi>add to, or diminish from the perfect law of the Lord contained</hi> therin: And yet they themselvs presume so frequently, and notoriously in this their book, to corrupt the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry words of the Texts which they cite, by adding to, and taking away, and altering, for their advantage; as I suppose, the like hath not been seen before in any, of any sect whatsoever: and as if, in truth, they meant not to use a gift to interpret the holy Scriptures, but a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledg to correct them. A taste of this they giue us in their very <hi>Epistle,</hi> where answering an objection taken from the <hi>learning of the Synode at Dort,</hi> by Es. 29. 14, &amp; Math. 11. 25. 26, they, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of <hi>wise and prudent,</hi> which are Christs words, put <hi>learned,</hi> and that in small letters as part of the Text, both wronging therin that lawfull and helpfull learning in others, which themselvs want, and corrupting the Lords words, which they ought religiously to keep; and obtruding another meaning then ever came into his mind: which they doe usually in this Treatise, by neglecting the main scope of the place cited, and catching at a word or phrase in it▪ which is the highest way, that can be, to all heresie.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>And for men, how uncharitable are they towards them in their persons, judging them as perishing without remedie, if they receiv not their new Gospell of Anabatistry and Free-will? How injurious in relating their own mis-formed collections, for their opinions? And lastly, how contemptuous of their gifts and graces, how eminent so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever? As if <hi>the word of God came out from them, or to them</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 38.</note>
      <hi>alone.</hi> It is true, we ought not to pin our faith on the sleevs of any, nor to call any <hi>Master,</hi> as Christ speaks and means, but him alone: and no lesse true, that Christ hath <hi>given</hi> gifts <hi>to</hi> some <hi>men, for the edifying of others;</hi> and that we ought <hi>not to look on our</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 8. 11.</note>
      <hi>things alone,</hi> as if we alone had knowledg and conscience, and zeal, and soules to saue: <hi>but every man also of the things of others</hi> (though in some things differing from them) as having these<note place="margin">Phil. 4. 4.</note> things, as well as we: and therwith considering, that many eies see more then one, and that specially having, as so many spectacles, the advantages of knowledge of Tongues, and Arts, with daily tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail in the Scripture, which in us are wanting. And thus <hi>serving God, in all modesty of minde,</hi> and being <hi>sincere in the truth</hi>
      <note place="margin">Act. 20. 19 Eph. 4. 15.</note>
      <hi>in loue,</hi> we shall be much sitter, both to help others, and to be helped by them in the things agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thereunto.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>