<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Worshipfull and my Christian friend Maister Valentine Knightlie Esquire, one of her Maiesties Iusti∣ces of Peace in Northamp∣ton-shire.</title>
           <author>Perkins, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114483_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09466</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19752</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114483</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Worshipfull and my Christian friend Maister Valentine Knightlie Esquire, one of her Maiesties Iusti∣ces of Peace in Northamp∣ton-shire.</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise tending vnto a declaration whether a man be in the estate of damnation or in the estate of grace : and if he be in the first, how he may in time come out of it: if in the second, how he maie discerne it, and perseuere in the same to the end. The points that are handled are set downe in the page following</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Robinson, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 <distributor>Gubbin (Gubbins), Thomas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Porter, John</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 286, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right <hi>Worshipfull and my Christian</hi> friend Maister <hi>Valentine Knightlie</hi> Esquire, one of her Maiesties Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Peace in Northamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton-shire.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, I pray you consider with mee an especial point of Gods word carefullie to be waied: it is this.</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 25. 1 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. 11. 12. Luk. 13. 24. A caueat to all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants of what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state or cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer.</note> Manie professors of Christ, in the day of grace, perswade them selues that they are in the estate of grace; and
<pb facs="3"/>
so the true Church esteemeth of thē too: yet when the day of grace is past, they contrariwise shall find themselues to bee in the estate of damnation remedilesse. <hi>A dolefull case, yet a most resolute trueth, and the reason is playne. Men that liue in the Church are greatly annoyed with a fearefull securitie and deadnes of hart, by which it comes to passe that they thinke it inough to make a common pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testatiō of the faith; not once in al their life times, examining themselues whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be in the estate of grace before the eternall God or not.</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">2. Cor. 13. 5. Psa. 119. 59</note>
      <hi>And indeed it is a grace peculiar to the man Electe to trie himselfe whether he be in the estate of grace or not.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The further opening of the trueth of this point as also the danger of it, I haue enterprised in this treatise: which I am willing to bestowe on you; both for the
<pb facs="3"/>
profession of the faith, which you make as also for that Christian friendship, you haue shewed to me. Accept of it I pray you &amp; vse it for your edification.</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">Act. 20. 32.</note>
      <hi>Thus I commend you to God, and to the word of his grace, that is able to build you vp further and giue you an inheritance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them which are sanctified. From Cambridge this</hi> 24. <hi>of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uember.</hi> 1589.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships to command.
<hi>William Perkins.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>