<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
           <author>C., M.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114888_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14688</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24993</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114888</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>C., M.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of Antichrist : Conteyning the defence of Cardinall Bellarmines arguments, which inuincibly demonstrate, that the pope is not Antichrist. Against M. George Downam D. of Diuinity, who impugneth the same. By Michael Christopherson priest. The first part</title>
                 <author>Walpole, Michael</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 200, 221-420, 8 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O some I doubt not, this my labour, which I haue taken in discussing this question of Antichrist, will seeme superfluous, or at least not so well bestowed, as it might haue bene in many other subiects. And they will be much confirmed in this their opinion, if they consider, that among so many learned men, as haue written in our language, and euidently confuted the heresies of our tymes; none of them haue vouchsafed to yield so far to our Aduersaries, as to handle this question of set pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, which doubtles they omitted not without great considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and weighty reasons: the chiefest of which, if I be not deceaued, was for that they perswaded themselues, that few or none, especiallie of the prudent and moderate sort, did indeed, and in their hart hold this absurd paradox, though they were content to let it passe, because it serued for a motiue to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw the common people from the Catholike faith, which in their conceipt conteyned other errors.</p>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <p> And for this cause those worthy and zealous writers en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauored chiefly to take away this false perswasion of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches erring, partly by confirming and demonstrating the infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of her authority, and partly by descending to particuler controuersies, and most euidently conuincyng the Churches do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in euery one of them to be conformable to the diuine Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures and all antiquity. For they did easily discouer, that by this course they should not only confute this abhominable b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy; but also with one and the same labour confirme and establish the contrary truth: <hi>viz.</hi> that the Catholike Church, togeather with her supreme Pastour, is the piller of Truth and the building of Christ, against which no force of errors or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies either hath or euer shall be able to preuayle.</p>
   <p>Which course of theirs as most prudent in it selfe, so like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise most profitable to others, I am far from mysliking, but doe altogeather approue and admyre it. And yet notwithstanding, I hope, that this my labour may be in some sort profitable also. For all are not so quick wytted, as to make these necessary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, but rather many are with-held from yielding to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest truth in other pointes by a preiudicate opinion, which they haue conceaued in this; and the iust and discreet silence, which hath hitherto bene vsed, ministreth to them some cause of sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition, that the Protestants haue reason for that they say; espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially since they vrge this point so much both in their Writings and Sermons, and the matter is of so great importance and consequence, that whosoeuer hath the truth on his syde in this, ought iustly to be belieued in the rest, since that Antichrist can neither agree with Christ, nor so great a calumniation as this is of the Pope (if it be false) can agree or stand with the spirit of truth. Besides, the Protestants out of this their doctrine make most odious inferences against Catholikes, as to go no further, we may see in <hi>M. Downams</hi> last Chapter, where he deduceth out of it six conclusions.</p>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <p> First, <hi>that out of this all other controuersies may be decided;</hi> and that the doctrine of the Catholike Church is to be reiected, as <hi>the errors of Antichrist.</hi> Secondly, <hi>that their separation from vs, is warranted, yea commaunded by the word of God, and all returning forbidden.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>that all they which partake with vs, are reprobates, and to be damned.</hi> Fourthly, <hi>that the Recusant Papists, but especialy Iesuites and Seminary Priests ought not to be fauoured or spared in a Christian Common wealth.</hi> Fifthly, <hi>that there can be no reconciliation betwixt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants and the Church of Rome</hi> Sixtly, <hi>that Protestants ought to be thankefull to God, who hath not suffered them to be carried away with this Catholike Apostasy.</hi> By which last wordes we may also note, that if this their position of the Pope being Antichrist doth fall, they haue no colour left to accuse the Catholike Church of schisme or heresy, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently it remayneth euident, that she is the true Church of Christ. For no schisme or heresy can be Catholike or vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall, as the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is; only the persecution and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stasy of Antichrist may in some sort vsurpe this name; because, though it shall want the vniuersality of tyme, being to remayne but a very short tyme, yet it shalbe very vniuersall in respect of place, as is manifest by that, which is said in this Treatise.</p>
   <p>Thus much shall suffice of the importance and necessity of this my small labour. And now I will briefely say some thing of Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> whome I defend, and of <hi>M. Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam</hi> whome I confute. And concerning this renowned and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st learned Cardinall, I shall not need to vse many wordes, his fame being spred ouer the whole world by his large, and profound disputations against all sortes of hereticks which haue risen or are extant in these our dayes. Wherefore it shalbe sufficient to note, that which maketh to our purpose, that in this his Treatise of Antichrist he vseth not so many arguments as some others
<pb facs="9"/> haue don; only contenting himselfe with those which are proper and peculiar to this place; omitting others, which do rather proue, that the Pope is the chiefe Pastour of Christes Church then disprooue that he is not Antichrist, which in him procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from two causes: the one is, his exactnes in the method, and diuision of his disputations, which conteyne euery one seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall questions and arguments: the other, for that hauing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore sufficiently discussed the affirmatiue position that the Pope is, and ought to be acknowledged to be the chiefe Pastour of Gods Church, he would not make any needeles repetition of those demonstrations, but rather proceed to other which hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to he had not touched, and which directly concluded, that the Pope, not only by reason of his office, but also in respect of his person can in no sort be that Antichrist, which the Scriptures and Fathers affirme, that we are to expect towards the end of the world. I shall not need to adde any more in commendation of this his worke for that the whole Treatise following hath no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther subiect, &amp; I haue translated his whole Booke <hi>verbatim,</hi> so that the Reader may peruse it, and iudge of it himselfe. It were superfluous to giue any reason, why in my allegations of this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Cardinall, I only mention his name for the most part: for any man may easily perceaue, that I do it for breuities sake, and according to the vse of Schooles, and not for any want of res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to his place and person, whome I honour from my hart, and defend him in this Treatise, so far, as my poore ability will giue me leaue.</p>
   <p>Concerning <hi>M. Downam</hi> (for so I commonly call him, to giue him to understand, that I impugne not his person, but his detestable heresy) I shall haue something more to say: for first the Reader must not be ignorant that he hath peruerted the order of this disputation. For, whereas <hi>Cardinall Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> first demonstrateth, that the Pope is not Antichrist, and afterward answereth the obiections of his Aduersaryes, <hi>M.</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>
      <hi>Downam</hi> tooke it to be his best course, first to obiect whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer either former heretikes had inuented, or he himselfe could adde, omitting altogeather the answers, which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> gaue; that by this meanes, he might possesse his Readers mynd by inueighing against the Pope at his pleasure, without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction: and so haue him the more fauourable when he came to make shew of answering to <hi>Bellarmins</hi> arguments.</p>
   <p>This is the cause, why I am constrayned to confute <hi>M. Downams</hi> second booke in the first place; not producing the argumēts without his solutions, as he dealt with the Cardinall, but examining whatsoeuer he answereth distinctly; in so much, that, one Chapter excepted where his confusion would not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit <note place="margin">Cap. 4.</note> it, in all the rest, euery number of my confutation an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swereth to the same in him: so that if any man hath a desire to confer, what both he and I say, he may easily do it, by reading first one section or number in him, &amp; then the same in me; which I would require of all such as do any way doubt of my sincere dealing, because he findeth not <hi>M. Downams</hi> wordes <hi>verba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim</hi> alleaged; which could not be without great prolixity. But he that goeth thus far, should also do well to read so much in Cardinall <hi>Bellarmime,</hi> as is discussed in euery seuerall number, which, that the Reader may conueniently doe, I haue also prefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed numbers to the Cardinalls discourse, and noted in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, where that, which is handled in euery seuerall place, may be found in him without difficulty.</p>
   <p>And by this meanes I hope the Reader may peruse this my labour with clarity, and profit, and discouer <hi>M. Downams</hi> false dealing, aswell in this point specified, as in many other, which now it is no tyme to rehearse, they beeing very neere as many as there be leaues in this whole Booke, and they may easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be found, by either perusing the marginall notes, or seeking in the table at the word <hi>Downam.</hi> And yet perhaps it will not be amysse to note one or two of them in this place, which espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb facs="10"/> discouer the badnesse of <hi>M. Downams</hi> cause. For what can be more absurd or hatefull to Christian eares, then to heare the enemyes of Christ, and his Church, commended and imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and his true Seruants and Doctors insolently reiected and accused of errours? And yet this is <hi>M. Downams</hi> case, not once or twyce, but throughout the whole course of this disputation: for he doth not only agree in substance with the <hi>Samosatens,</hi> who are knowne heretikes, and condemned by his owne iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but also ioyneth himselfe <hi>ex professo</hi> with that vile A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postata and capitall enemy of Christ <hi>Porphiry,</hi> not only against <hi>S. Hierome,</hi> who most earnestly and learnedly confuteth him at large, but also against all other Ecclesiasticall writers, yea euen the very Iewes themselues, who in that point agree with the Christians; but in another, where they are opposite to vs, there <hi>M. Downam</hi> ioyneth with them: so that it seemeth, that <hi>M. Downam</hi> and his fellow Protestants seeke of purpose, how they may oppose themselues to Christ and his Church, yea that they esteeme more of Gentilles and Iewes, then they do of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian writers, though neuer so many, so worthy, or so ancient.</p>
   <p>And surely whosoeuer shall consider attentiuely, how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and how scornefully the ancient Fathers and pillars of Christs Church, be reiected by <hi>M. Downam,</hi> cannot choose but admire, yea <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hould vp his handes and blesse himselfe, to thinke, how it hath byn, and is still possible, that either they themselues, or others by them should be so bewitched. Neither can there any probable cause be giuen of so great blindnes, and so enormous a cryme, but only the want of Gods grace, which their sinnes haue with drawne, and deserued, that they should be in this sort as it were giuen ouer to a reprobate sense. What can be said in defence of this detestable excesse? Deny it they cannot, the thing being so euident, and so often reiterated. And dare they excuse it, by telling vs, That the Fathers are only forsaken, when they forsake the Scripture? Is not this
<pb facs="10"/> plainely to make Infidells and Heretikes better Interpreters of Scripture then the Church of Christ, and all Christians in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and the most learned Pastours thereof in particuler? If they answer, that it is not the authority of these Infidells, which they follow, but the inspiration of the Holy Ghost, which they experience in themselues; is this any thing els in effect, then to acknowledge that <hi>Porphiry,</hi> and the <hi>Iewes</hi> had the true spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Christ, and that the ancient Fathers, and the Church of Christ in their tyme had it not? For if the Protestants, haue the spirit of Christ now, it is manifest, that those others had it then, since their expositions be all one. But who is so foolish and sacrilegious, as to depriue Gods Church and Saintes of his spirit, and it tribute it to his professed enemyes, and consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly how shall we belieue the Protestants, when they tell vs that they are full of Gods Spirit, since we see their spirit to agree with that of the Diuells instruments, and to be quite opposite to that of Gods elect? Heere is no starting hole to be found, neither haue they any thing to reply, but only to stand vpon their bare affirmation; which <hi>M. Downam</hi> doth so often in his disputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, still desiring to haue that graunted which is chiefly in question. But I will omit this, and the rest of his absurdities, remitting the Reader to his owne experience, after that he hath with diligence perused the whole.</p>
   <p>Heere I would make an end of this Preface, hauing said asmuch, as I thinke necessary concerning the disputation, which followeth. But because I haue lately seene two Sermons not long since preached by this our Doctour, by which it seemeth, that he hath resolued to relinquish Puritanisme and turne Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant, I thought it good to admonish my Reader of this point also; because I rather inclined before to thinke, that he was a Puritan, and insinuated so much in a place or two. And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <note place="margin">Chap. 10. &amp; 13.</note> by this occasion, I must intreat my Reader to marke the great difference betwixt <hi>M. Downam</hi> in these his Sermons,
<pb facs="11"/> and the same man in his booke of Antichrist: for in this he euery where reiecteth all antiquity, as I haue said, but in his Sermons he singeth vs a new song, and can tell vs. <hi>that it neuer yet happened that the newest thinges did proue the truest,</hi> and argueth chiefely from authority, obiecting still to his Puritan Aduersaries, <hi>That they go against the whole streame of all Antiquity,</hi> yea he can alleadge <hi>S. Augustine lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de Bapt. con. Donat. cap.</hi> 24. <hi>&amp; ep.</hi> 118. to proue that the consent of the whole Church argueth either the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Councell, or an Apostolicali Tradition, though he cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptely translateth <hi>(Traditum, Ordayned)</hi> and likewise in the second place, where <hi>S. Aug.</hi> affirmeth that, <hi>Insolentissimae insaniae est,</hi> it is a most insolent madnes to dispute against that which <hi>(vniuersa Ecclesia)</hi> the whole Church obserueth; he addeth of his owne the word <hi>(Primitiue)</hi> that so he may haue some stareing hole against vs, when he is vrged with the same Authority of S. <hi>Augustine,</hi> which if he would follow himselfe, as he would now haue the Puritans do, he must of force retyre himselfe from the Protestants also, and betake himselfe to the Catholike Church, which all Antiquity most manifestly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth.</p>
   <p>And surely whosoeuer considereth the arguments, which <hi>Protestants</hi> make against <hi>Puritans,</hi> cannot but euidently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, that the very same principles do ouerthrow the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants</hi> themselues. And I meruaile much, how they can defend themselues from that terrible sentence of <hi>S. Paul, Inexcusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilises o homo omnis, qui iudicas: quo enim iudicas al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum, teipsum condemnas, eadem enim agis, quae iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas.</hi> And the very same iudgment falleth vpon the <hi>Puritans</hi> themselues, when they go about to impugne the <hi>Brownists, Familists, Anabaptists, Arians,</hi> or any other sect whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer. For this they cannot do, but by Antiquity, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding they are forced to reiect in all those pointes, in
<pb facs="11"/> which they differ, and dissent from the Cathelike Roman Church.</p>
   <p>I will not descend to any particulers, though I easily might; for what can be more euident, then that the autherity of S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> &amp; other Fathers, who vrge the neces<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ity of a Bishop, for the conseruation of vnity, is much more to be vnderstood of one chiefe Bishop in the whole Church, then of particuler Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops in particuler Diocesses, since there can be no question, that vnity is as necessary in the whole world, as in one Diocesse, and much more easily mayntained in this, then in that? Likewise <hi>M. Downam</hi> can tell vs not only of Bishops, but also of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitans</hi> and <hi>Patriarches,</hi> and alleadgeth for his purpose the Councell of <hi>Nice;</hi> but he will not acknowledge that in the same Councell, <hi>Rome</hi> hath the first place, and is preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all others, as likewise <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and <hi>Antiochia</hi> are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Ierusalem</hi> (which <hi>M. Downam</hi> would willingly haue the chiefe) of which there can be no other true reason giuen, but the excellency of <hi>S. Peter</hi> aboue the other Apostles, who foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded three Churches, and placed or fixed his Sea in <hi>Rome,</hi> where he ended his life with a most happy Martyrdome. Now if we a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ke <hi>M. Downam</hi> a reason why he seeth not this, aswell as that which fauoureth the Protestants against the Puritans, I cannot imagine, what he can answere vs, but only that by this meanes he should incurre the disgrace, and ouerthrow of his Ministry, which he esteemeth so highly. But I intreat both him, and all other, euen as they tender their owne saluation, to looke about them in tyme, and not to suffer themselues to be carried away with the sway of the tyme, and the desire of worldly pleasures and preferments, which <hi>M. Downam,</hi> and all others may easily conceaue not to be very great, if his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playntes of pouerty, and contempt, which he maketh in his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Sermon be true, as no doubt they are in great part, and these miseryes will daylie increase, as their credit doth decrease,
<pb facs="12"/> so that if now that pittifull (y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t ridiculou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>) complaint of <hi>M. Downam</hi> be true, <hi>That not only euery meane man almost</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ser. 1. pag. 67.</note>
      <hi>preferreth himselfe before the Minister, but also disday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to bestow either his Sonne on the Ministry, or his Daughter on a Minister,</hi> the tyme no doubt will come, and that shortly also, that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>halbe inforced to marry only within their owne Trib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>; for I can assure him, that neither the Kings, nor the Nobility of <hi>England</hi> will imitate those of <hi>Iuda</hi> in this; and it will be their only way to get a Law enacted, that their generation may succeed them in their Ministry; which <hi>M. Downam</hi> seemeth to wish, and to mislike that law not a little, which (in a parenthesis) he telleth vs hath otherwise prouided.</p>
   <p>These are the base and carnall cogitations of these new Ghospellers; and yet all will not serue: for they shall neuer find a remedy for this their griefe except they returne to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, whom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> they may thanke for the liuing they haue. But in it God hath prouided for this, &amp; all other inconueniences, that can any way arise: and in particuler for the deciding of all questions and controuersies. Wherefore if the Protestants and Puritans will haue an end of this of their Bishops and Presbite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, they must of necessity stand to the Catholike Churches iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in which they shall find Bishops established, and yet some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, by reason of persecution, Priestes only without Bishops, as now we see in our Country, where conformable to that which in their iudgmēt was practised in the Primitiue Church in many places, at least for a tyme, we haue hitherto only Priestes subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate to an Arch-Priest; but yet we are far from misliking Bishops, but do both wish, and expect them, when our lawfull Superiour, who succeedeth the chiefest of the Apostles, shall see it conuenient.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>M. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>