<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the godly and well affe∣cted Reader whosoeuer.</title>
           <author>P., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114413_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09364</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19668</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114413</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the godly and well affe∣cted Reader whosoeuer.</title>
                 <author>P., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first part of The cases of conscience : Wherein specially, three maine questions concerning man, simply considered in himselfe, are propounded and resolued, according to the word of God. Taught and deliuered, by M. William Perkins in his Holy-day lectures, by himselfe revised before his death, and now published for the benefit of the Church</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waterson, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 183, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>To the godly and well affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Reader whosoeuer.</head>
   <p>IT was not my purpose, (Christian Reader) at the first to haue sent abroad onely one part of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of Conscience, without the rest; but that I was mooued thereunto, partly vpon the importunitie of some of the Authors friends, and partly because I desired to satisfie thy expectation in a thing, which I perswade my selfe hath beene long expected. Upon which two motiues, I haue now commended vnto thee this first part, promising by the grace of God, ere it be long, to adde the second, and the third, so farre as the Author proceeded in this Treatise before his death. And although I could haue wished, this labour had beene vndertaken by others, better able to performe it then my selfe; yet beeing well acquainted with the copie, which is mine owne, and knowing it to haue bin perused by the Author himselfe, before his death, I was the more incouraged, to bestow my paines for thy good in that behalfe. If in reading thereof thou finde, either any thing amisse, or thy selfe not fully satisfied in the particulars; then remember that the Author himselfe is gone, who might haue brought the worke to perfection, if God had pleased to prolong his daies vpon the earth. And withall consider, that it were better for thee, to accept of these his labours, as they are now imparted to thee, then by the suppressing of them to be depriued of so great a benefit. And thus hoping of thy kinde acceptance of my paines for thy behoofe, I commend thee to God, and to the word of his grace. <hi>Iune 28. 1604.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>T. P.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>