<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NORABLE MY SPECIAL GOOD LLL: THOMAS BARON OF BVCKHVRST, Earle of Dorset, and Lord-Treasurer of England. Henrie Lord Howard of Marnehill, Earle of Northampton, &amp; Lord-Warden of the Cinq-Ports. And Robert Baron of Essen∣den, Vicount Cranbourne, Earle of Salisbury, and Principall Secre∣tarie of State to the KINGS Maiestie. All Knights of the most Noble Order of the GARTER, and Lords of his Highnesse most Honourable Preuy-Counsell.</title>
           <author>Milles, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114606_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07548</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17927</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114606</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NORABLE MY SPECIAL GOOD LLL: THOMAS BARON OF BVCKHVRST, Earle of Dorset, and Lord-Treasurer of England. Henrie Lord Howard of Marnehill, Earle of Northampton, &amp; Lord-Warden of the Cinq-Ports. And Robert Baron of Essen∣den, Vicount Cranbourne, Earle of Salisbury, and Principall Secre∣tarie of State to the KINGS Maiestie. All Knights of the most Noble Order of the GARTER, and Lords of his Highnesse most Honourable Preuy-Counsell.</title>
                 <author>Milles, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The custumers alphabet and primer : Conteining, their creede or beliefe in the true doctrine of Christian religion. Their ten commandementes, or rules of ciuill life and conuersation, daily grace, generall confession, speciall supplication and forme of prayers. Togither with a pertinent answere to all such, as eyther in iest or in earnest, seeming doubtfull themselues, would faine perswade others, that, the bringing home of traffique must needes decay our shipping. All tending to the true and assured aduancement of his Maiesties customes, without possibility of fraude or couyn. Alwaies prouided, in reading read all, or nothing at al</title>
                 <author>Milles, Tho (Thomas)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE MY SPECIAL GOOD LLL: <hi>THOMAS</hi> BARON OF <hi>BVCKHVRST,</hi> Earle of <hi>Dorset,</hi> and <hi>Lord-Treasurer</hi> of England. <hi>Henrie</hi> Lord <hi>Howard</hi> of <hi>Marnehill,</hi> Earle of <hi>Northampton,</hi> &amp; Lord-Warden of the <hi>Cinq-Ports.</hi> And <hi>Robert</hi> Baron of <hi>Essen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> Vicount <hi>Cranbourne,</hi> Earle of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and Principall Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie of State to the KINGS Maiestie. All Knights of the most Noble Order of the GARTER, and Lords of his Highnesse most Honourable <hi>Preuy-Counsell.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Dutie and Seruice to you honorable <hi>L.L.L.</hi> euery way humbly premised: I haue thought it good to present the same with the loyall Endeuours of a willing mind, though feeble wit, and weaker brayne; the Argument I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse being of a higher pitch and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter compasse, then I did imagine whē I tooke it in hand.</p>
   <p>Hazard at the first did much discourage me, &amp; in the mids, by Friendes I had been disswaded in regard of the paines, but for th' <hi>Enthousiasme</hi> still sounding in mine eares.</p>
   <q>Ton Ame ne doibt, ta flamme est si diuine, &amp;c.</q>
   <q>
      <l>Thy Soule is so beset by vowes that are deuine,</l>
      <l>Thou shalt not tread amisse, why should thy hart decline?</l>
   </q>
   <p>By whose perswasion whē I had but begun, my Conscience thrust me forward, and thus preuailed at last.</p>
   <q>Ie veulx qu'un bel oser, &amp;c.</q>
   <q>
      <l>Then dangers stand aside, tis <hi>GOODNES</hi> calls me to it,</l>
      <l>If ought doe put me by, t'is <hi>WISDOMS</hi> hand shall do it.</l>
   </q>
   <p>My stayes besides were these: That <hi>TRVTH</hi> was all my <hi>Ground,</hi> which as <hi>Time</hi> did suggest, <hi>Experience</hi> still sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyd. My Pen <hi>OPORTET</hi> made, and was euer apt to mend: But <hi>ORDER</hi> gaue the <hi>Forme,</hi> which I most of all suspected,
<pb facs="3"/>and saw some cause to doubt, till <hi>PRAYER</hi> in conclusion did vndertake to perfect or perswade the best. So that if the <hi>Forme</hi> for the plainenesse may passe without offence, the <hi>Matter</hi> for im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>portance may perhaps deserue a double and treble reading.</p>
   <p>The <hi>Matter</hi> indeed is <hi>TRAFFICK,</hi> I meane our freeborne <hi>Traffick,</hi> that Nurse of <hi>IVSTICE</hi> which feedes vs all, and (heere handled <hi>ab Effectis,</hi>) containes those very <hi>CVSTVMS</hi> for which the <hi>Schollers</hi> in all the <hi>Free-schooles,</hi> of our <hi>SOVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAIGNES</hi> daily <hi>Tributes,</hi> haue so long beene subiect to bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and beating: and for which my selfe, of late so graciously chidden, was forst (by speciall commaund,) to spell againe my Letters, and con this <hi>PRIMER.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now be it what it may be, as your <hi>WISDOMS</hi> shall esteeme, and as <hi>GOD</hi> shall giue successe, (to whom the Glorie of <hi>All</hi> in <hi>All</hi> is due,) three principall reasons haue moou'd me to present it to your LLL: view, in the names of All the rest. The <hi>FIRST,</hi> besides his <hi>knowledge</hi> and sufficiencie of skill, by emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie and Place hath speciall Experience to iudge of what I write. The <hi>SECOND,</hi> keepes the Keyes of all those verie <hi>Ports</hi> that lymits out my Charge, for whose sakes indeede reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proke Loue did instant me to write. And the <hi>THIRD</hi> was the meanes to make me first a <hi>Custumer,</hi> when I had giuen it ouer and little thought vppon it. For these regards (I say) and tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble respects, (mine Ends beeing no wayes priuat, myne Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons alwaies Loyall, disclayming no mans Person, but Sinne and Dishonestie,) I held it meetest and safest, to present my <hi>Selfe,</hi> and the Fruites of all my Vowes, to your LLL: mylde Censures and Protections. By whose speciall Fauours, as I am but what I am, so I desire but to be knowne</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your LLL: by seuerall Duties deuotedly bound</hi> Tho: Milles.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>