<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader whosoever. An admonitorie Postscript.</title>
           <author>B., S.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114807_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00951</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1106</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114807</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader whosoever. An admonitorie Postscript.</title>
                 <author>B., S.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Miles Christianus, or The campe royal : set forth in briefe meditations on the words of the Prophet Moses, Deut. 23, 9, 14. here under following, preached in the armie as Dungen-Leager, profitable for all sorts of men to reade; and published for the generall good of all that will read, By Samuel Bachiler, Preacher to the English at Gorinchem</title>
                 <author>Bachiler, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Plater, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>55, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="afterword_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader whosoever. An admonitorie Postscript.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>EADER,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>It may be, when thou seest the title in the <hi>frontispiece,</hi> and readest the text, thou wilt think, that as the profession whereunto thou art a stranger, (as suppose no Souldier) so the matter of this book concerns thee not, who perhaps art a <hi>Burger,</hi> or homedweller. But let not this hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der further inspection; and let me assure thee, that what is here spoken to them abroad, doth deeply concerne thee at home, though thou shouldst never be called, or once constreined to follow that course of life. For this being a Scripture-subject is profitable for all. And howsoever we haue too much cause to lament the vices, the outrages, the enormities of the Camp; yet know thou, and confesse, that all sin is not there alone. And take these words of <hi>Moses</hi> to be spoken to thee also, whose calling is dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stique and at home, in towne or countrey: <hi>When the host goeth forth to warre, then keepe thee</hi> (euen <hi>thee,</hi> who stayest at home for thy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie employments) <hi>from everie wicked thing.</hi> Keepe thou thy selfe I say, from the tap-house, the whorehouse, the play-house; and the execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble evils of those accursed places. Keepe thee from idlenes, and be diligent in thy calling, and in the holy exercises of prayer, hearing, and meditating <hi>Gods</hi> word, &amp;c. And let us feare, least not onely their sinnes abroad, but our sinnes at home also, doe help mightily to pull the wrath of <hi>God</hi> upon them, who for our sakes are employed abroad, and endure the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching heate, and the pinching cold, while we sit still under our own vines. Yea this concerneth you <hi>Magistrates,</hi> and <hi>Governours,</hi> publique or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, to looke to good order in your townes and families, and that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane libertie be not giuen to breake the <hi>Sabbaoths,</hi> to frequent and weare the thresholds of ryotous places, for heathenish <hi>May-games,</hi> and <hi>Whitson-ales</hi> (as they call their mad sports.) And suffer not youth to dis-order themselues as they doe, to the shame and scandall of those places where they are. Oh, what neede haue we in these troublous times, when the host is gone forth to warre upon our enimies, to be more carefull of our
<pb facs="4"/>selues and ours at home, if (as I hope we doe) we wish prosperitie to those who are gone out. We haue more neede to giue our selues to watch, and pray, and fast and mourne for their sinnes and our owne, and <hi>to cover the Altar of the Lord with teares,</hi> that so he may haue mercie upon us.</p>
   <p>You that are at home, and worthily complaine of the sinnes of the host, looke into your townes, and citties, and houses, and be ashamed of the stewes and brothel-houses among you, shamefully connived at under the nose of Authoritie, by those whom <hi>God</hi> will charge, for having so little heart, and zeale, and courage, and conscience to suppresse them. Looke and behold the breaches of the <hi>Sabaoth</hi> by carriage and re-carriage, looke into the beastly excesse of drunkennes, chambering and wantonnes among you. Is your host gone forth to warre, &amp; are you (o Citizens) free at home, to commit all uncleannesse, and that with greedines? Know, that for these things unreformed, and persisted in without repentance, <hi>God</hi> will search you out with lights, and visit those that sit frozen upon their dregs. Know, you are to guard against evill at home in your streets and houses, as they that are abroad, to withhold from evill in their Campes. For is it not all one, whether their sinnes abroad, or yours at home, doe undoe and marre all lawfull designes? <hi>2 Sam. 11, 11.</hi> The arke &amp; Israel and Iudah abide in tents, and the servants of my Lord Ioab encamp in the open fields, shall I then goe into mine house, and eate and drinke, and lye with my wife? &amp;c. As their Camps therefore should be holy Camps; so should your houses also be holy, that holynes dwelling in your streets and houses, <hi>God</hi> who walketh in the mids of their Camps, may see no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleannesse in you, and may walke in your streets and houses, and take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to dwell among you, and his soule may not abhorre you. Refuse not then to take up this, whosoever thou art, and make that use thereof which thou mayst doe. And <hi>God</hi> blesse the reading of it to thee. To <hi>God</hi> I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend thee, and the word of his grace. and bid thee farewell, and am</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine, if thou wilt make use of me. <hi>S. B.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>