<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL WILLIAM TOWSE Sergeant at Law, one of His MAIESTIES Iustice of Peace in Essex: As also to the Right Worship∣full, the Lady KATHERINE BARNARDISTON, his beloued Wife, both my much respected friends. The Author wisheth the blessings of this life and the next.</title>
           <author>Barnes, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114798_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04629</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1475</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114798</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL WILLIAM TOWSE Sergeant at Law, one of His MAIESTIES Iustice of Peace in Essex: As also to the Right Worship∣full, the Lady KATHERINE BARNARDISTON, his beloued Wife, both my much respected friends. The Author wisheth the blessings of this life and the next.</title>
                 <author>Barnes, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The court of conscience: or, Iosephs brethrens iudgement barre. By Thomas Barnes</title>
                 <author>Barnes, Thomas, minister of St. Margaret's, New Fish Street, London</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Newbery, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Redmer, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 88, folded plates, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL WILLIAM TOWSE Sergeant at Law, one of His MAIESTIES Iustice of Peace in <hi>Essex:</hi> As also to the Right Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, the Lady KATHERINE BARNARDISTON, his beloued Wife, both my much respected friends. The Author wisheth the blessings of this life and the next.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was a saying of one of the<note n="a" place="margin">Ambr. an Constan. Duo sunt tibi ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessaria, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scientia &amp; fama, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scientia prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter te, fama propter proximu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in an Epistle to one of his friends: <hi>Two things are needfull for thee,
<pb facs="3"/> conscience, and credite, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science for thy selfe, credite for thy neighbour.</hi> And not without reason spake he this; for the one is an inward witnesse, the other giues an outward testimony of our doings. The one serues to breed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward consolation, the other to bring outward commendation. But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the necessitie of both, yet the best of the two is least regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the Philosophers saying being most true:<note n="b" place="margin">Senec. de morib. Plerique fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scientiam autem pauci verentur.</note>
      <hi>Many feare their credite, but few their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science.</hi> So it fared (as it seemes) with those ten sonnes of holy <hi>Iacob,</hi> who did mis-use his beloued <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seph:</hi> So they might hide that wrong they did their brother, and saue their credite with their father,
<pb facs="3"/> little cared they (vntill distresse a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waked them) how matters stood in the Court within them. So also it fares with the <hi>Secret sinners,</hi> and <hi>Ciuill liuers</hi> of our dayes. To keepe their name good amongst men they are very curious, but to haue a cleere witnesse in their owne conscience, they are nothing studious. That this euill might be somewhat helped, this Treatise haue I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled; wherein my scope is to bring men to a care of their <hi>Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences</hi> as well as their names, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the one to be as needfull to cleere them from blame before the Barre of heauen, as the other to keepe them from shame amongst <hi>men.</hi> For (if <hi>Salomon</hi> saith true)
<pb facs="4"/> though <hi>a good name be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then a precious oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">Eccl. 7.1.</note> Yet, <hi>A good consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is a continuall ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">Prou. 15.15.</note>. If any one aske the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of this my drift: my reason is two-fold. First, because conscience is fearefull in accusing. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, because conscience is faithfull in recording: which two things (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst others, according to the tenour of the text) are principally and most largely handled in this Treatise. And good I desire all may doe in, and to the Israel of God.</p>
   <p>To your Worships I thought good to dedicate the same: though wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier papers were fitter for your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage. If I were not confident of
<pb facs="4"/> acceptation: I should not presume to present you with it. Albeit, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede it had beene fit that my first friends, should haue had my first fruits, yet I hope my second pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like labours in this kinde, will not be vnwelcome. Howsoeuer, I owe them, your Worships vndeserued fauours showne mee, challenge the same, and more at my hands. If you please to vouchsafe them the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. I doubt not but you shall finde something profitable, though plainly deliuered in an homely stile. If you please to afford them the protection, being so simple and small as they are, you shall get me into stronger bonds, continually to wish to both your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships, what <hi>Iohn</hi> did on the behalfe
<pb facs="5"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="6"/> of the <hi>Elect Ladie,</hi> and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Gaius,</hi> euen to your soules: <hi>Grace, peace and mercie</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">2. Ioh. 3.</note>: to your bodies <hi>health and pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">3. Ioh. 2.</note>: For which he promiseth to pray, who is</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships at command, in and for the Lord. THOMAS BARNES.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>