<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Author To the generous, and learned READER.</title>
           <author>Misselden, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114354_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16308</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3220</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114354</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Author To the generous, and learned READER.</title>
                 <author>Misselden, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The elements of armories</title>
                 <author>Bolton, Edmund</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 201, 15 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Heraldic works and genealogies</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>The Author To the generous, and learned READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N foure bookes it seem'd to mee, that the matter of Armo'ries (neuer as yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer'd in the better, and remoter parts thereof, but euen vntill this day (for ought that euer I could gather to the contrary) remaining altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toucht) was aptly (as in a <hi>PANDECT,</hi> or <hi>DIGEST</hi>) comprehensible. And those Foure (as I concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) might bee these:</p>
   <p>Their
<list>
         <item>
            <hi>1. ELEMENTS.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>2. FABRICK.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>3. MYSTERIES.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>4. VINDEX.</hi>
         </item>
      </list>
   </p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1.</hi> The <hi>ELEMENTS</hi> teaching the simple, abstract, pure, and remote materials, and causes of Armo'ries, of which (as words of letters) they consist.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2.</hi> The <hi>FABRICK</hi> teaching the putting-together of those Elements, and how they constitute Armorial bodies; with other speculations proper to the compositiue part.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3.</hi> The <hi>MYSTERIES</hi> teaching what those Armoriall bodies so constituted do purport, meane, or signifie; all clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with Rules, and Examples.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <hi>4.</hi> The <hi>VINDEX,</hi> Assertor, or Champion, teaching how this <hi>PHILOSOPHIE</hi> may bee freed from contempt, and who is truly Noble, and worthy to bee honored with Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories.</p>
   <p>But, generous, and learned Reader (for to such onely doth this part of humane letters appertaine) of those foure in proiect (through manifold Inter-turbations) there is only, and scarce performed vnto thee the first: <hi>The Elements of Armories;</hi> which here thou hast.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="8"/>My farther scope, and counsels thou shalt bee priuie vnto▪ if thou make the tenth Chapter of the Booke worthy thy thorough-view; whether I transmit thee. Onely I must not here forget, that (without respect to my priuate) I haue, vpon occasion in all the course of my present youth spent much time, and coyne, to view in person the chiefe places of <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> and <hi>IRELAND,</hi> to conuerse the better with our Antiquities in that kind, aswell to perfect thereby mine owne speculations, as that I might (whē opportunity would) deliuer vnto thee things certain &amp; pure, without abuse, or innouatiō.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Other things briefly to praemonish thee of are these.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1.</hi> That a competent Reader cannot lack so much lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage as may serue to interpret betweene him-selfe, and some few harder words, or places in the Booke.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2.</hi> That language onely, or common diligence can make no Armorist without <hi>Genius,</hi> and a Maister.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3.</hi> That the way to learne excellently, is to beleeue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently, for a meane conceit of a profession begets but a small proficience.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <hi>4.</hi> That in the deliuery of Elementarie matter I haue, for thy cause, rather vsed interlocution, then set, or continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous speech, as more apt to enter a Learner, for whose cause also at the end of the Booke are annexed sundry Tables.</p>
   <p n="5">
      <hi>5.</hi> That at the first reading to lay them downe, or away, either as too hard, or as now too stale, doth argue alike vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the one of too much abiection, the other of too little stedfastnesse.</p>
   <p n="6">
      <hi>6.</hi> That if thou wilt vse the pleasant obiects, and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall parts thereof to relish, and draw-on the rest the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, thou holdest the right Rule of profiting thy selfe.</p>
   <p n="7">
      <hi>7.</hi> That all is properly meant, and written herein to them that are <hi>filij Artis,</hi> and willing to coöperate with the fauour of the Armoriall Muse.</p>
   <p>How thou (my <hi>READER</hi>) doo'st in present thinke of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, and what minde thou bringest with thee, as I know not, so (howsoeuer) I may yet say a little in this place, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing that which is spoken throughout my whole Booke,
<pb facs="8"/>
to the same purpose, considering the generall state of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons touching them, that thou mai'st the rather be induced to thinke thy diligence in perusall of the whole, not ill-emploid; or I, in thy riper, and sounder iudgment stand the more iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, or at leastwise the lesse condemned for hauing taken so much paine to pleasure thee.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Armories</hi> therefore occurring euery-where, in seales, in frontes of buildings, in vtensils, in all things; Monarcks vsing them, mighty Peeres, and in briefe, all the noble <hi>tàm maio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, quàm minorum gentium,</hi> from <hi>Caesar</hi> to the simplest Gentleman, yet all of them (for the more part) most vnknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, very few (euen of the most studious) do sildome goe any farther then to fill vp a wide Wardrobe with particular Coates: whose zeale notwithstanding is worthy to know the▪ better things thereof: <hi>that other</hi> beeing no more <hi>the thing,</hi> then bookes not vnderstood are learning.</p>
   <p>For in them (I may without racking the value affirme) are all the <hi>Thems,</hi> and <hi>Theorems</hi> of generous knowledges, from whence doth breath so sweet an aër of humanity as thy man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners cannot but take, and mix thereby with true gentility, and noblesse.</p>
   <p>The outward parts of her palace are beautifide with infinit obiects full of all variety &amp; comlinesse: the walks▪ &amp; mazes which she vseth are those enwrapped circles of ingenuous sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences which the learned do entitle <hi>CYCLOPAEDIE</hi>: her Presence, and most inward retirements haue all the most <hi>CHRISTIAN,</hi> Haeroick, and Cardinall virtues, &amp; for Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maides excellent affections, without which the arguments, &amp; externall testimonies of noblesse are nothing worth.</p>
   <p>Hee that in the trust of any auditories ignorance, or base<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse shall say, <hi>All this is vaine,</hi> must be answered, that this is no otherwise <hi>vaine</hi> then as <hi>Omnia vanitas.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In any other good or honorable sense thou canst not (<hi>I</hi> thinke) but confesse <hi>that Armorie is a Maiesty worthy thy seruice:</hi> wherevnto if <hi>names of men,</hi> rather then <hi>things themselues</hi> can perswade, thou canst not bee vnknowing how many of our late, and presently both greatest, and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest haue heretofore, and now in present doe honor it.
<pb facs="9"/>
Neither doth She want her part also in our Cōmon-weal<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> and they, who sit chiefe in the <hi>primum mobile</hi> of state, be thinke themselues, how to enlighten <hi>BRITAIN</hi> with the beams of restored Honor.</p>
   <p>To praeöcupate more satisfaction till thy minde bee far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knowne, were meerely for me to diuine of obiections, but when thou expoundest thy selfe vnto Mee, thou shalt be most assured of my farthest diligence to keepe thee Mine.</p>
   <trailer>FARE-WELL.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>