<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣shipfull, the Major, and his Brethren, the Aldermen &amp;c. of the Citie of Coventrie.</title>
           <author>Holland, Philémon</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114268_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06878</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17311</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114268</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣shipfull, the Major, and his Brethren, the Aldermen &amp;c. of the Citie of Coventrie.</title>
                 <author>Holland, Philémon</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Roman historie : containing such acts and occurrents as passed under Constantius, Iulianus, Iovianus, Valentinianus, and Valens, emperours. Digested into 18. bookes, the remains of 31. and written first in Latine by Ammianus Marcellinus: now translated newly into English. Wherunto is annexed the chronologie, serving in stead of a briefe supplement of those former 13. bookes, which by the iniurie of time are lost: together with compendious annotations and coniectures upon such hard places as occurre in the said historie. Done by Philemon Holland of the citie of Coventrie, Doctor in Physicke</title>
                 <author>Ammianus Marcellinus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 432, 76 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull, the Major, and his Brethren, the Aldermen &amp;c. of the Citie of Coventrie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving entred heretofore into an English translation of the Romane Hystorie, compiled by <hi>T. Livius</hi> from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Rome-citie unto the <hi>Caesars</hi> dayes; and then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded forward in their lives, to the death of <hi>Domitian,</hi> according as they were penned by <hi>Suetonius Tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> J was of late earnestly moved by a noble Baron of this Kingdome, to travaile on still, and follow the traine of this argument, so farre forth as I found extant in <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus,</hi> who had written at large from the end of the said Emperour unto the beginning of <hi>Gratianus.</hi> And albeit this enterprise seemed unto mee more than difficult, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering the harsh stile of the Author, a Souldior, and who being a Grecian borne, delivered these Hystoricall reports in Latine; the strange tearmes occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioned by the late alteration of the State under <hi>Constantine;</hi> the greater part of the originall lost, which might have given light unto the rest; the prints so defective and faultie even of that which remained; and the want of others to tread out the way before me in other languages: yet could I not deny that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest request of so honourable a personage, whom I knew to be verie studious, passing well learned, and judicious, (right commendable parts adorning true Nobilitie) but set in hand with this peece of worke also, and finish the same in some sort, though I have not altogether therein pleased my selfe.</p>
   <p>And the better to give contentment unto the Readers (for now by this time I perceived it should come under the Presse) I tooke me to a new labour, and like as the losse of the later part of <hi>T. Livius</hi> I supplied with the breviaries of <hi>L. Florus,</hi> so the want in the beginning of this Writer I made up with a Chronolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie; to the end I might present unto my deere countreymen a continued narrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Romane affaires, from the first infancie, to the venerable old age and
<pb facs="3"/>
declining daies (that I may use <hi>Marcellinus</hi> his owne words) of that eternall Citie. To explane likewise those unusuall phrases and tearmes aforesaid, not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious in former Historiographers, as also to open some obscure places, which here and there offer themselves, I thought not much of my paines, to annex ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto certaine briefe Annotations and Conjectures of mine owne: which if they yeeld not full satisfaction unto the Reader, may yet minister occasion to some bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter learned than my selfe, for to travaile in that kind, unto whose censure and judgement I submit those my Supposals.</p>
   <p>These Endeavour of mine whatsoever I dedicate unto your Worships, the chiefe Magistrate and grave Senate of this Citie; and that for divers respects: First, your wise and moderat government of the place, wherein J have so many yeares conversed, hath affoorded unto me both quiet repose and meanes also to follow my studies: Secondly, the affectionate love that yee have alwaies borne to good literature, testified by courteous entertainment of learned men; by compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent salaries allowed from time to time to such professors, as have peaceably and with discreet carriage bestowed their talents among you; by exhibition given to poore schollers in the Vniversitie; by erecting also of late, and maintaining of a faire Librarie, not exampled (without offense to others be it spoken) in many Cities of the Realme: Lastly the experience I have already of your kind accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of my former Labours, though not exhibited unto you at the first hand, have emboldened or enforced me rather, immediatly to entitle you in this, and under your name to transmit the same unto all others: not doubting that you wil take this small gift in good worth, as a token of his unfaigned love and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who hath alwayes prayd for your welfare, and wisheth not to live longer than he may see the prosperous and flourishing estate of your citie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships in all dutifull respect, Philêmon Holland.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>