<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORTHY, THE RIGHT wel-deseruing of Church, and Common-wealth, Sir HENRY WILLIAMS, Knight.</title>
           <author>Scull, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114766_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11823</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22123</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114766</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORTHY, THE RIGHT wel-deseruing of Church, and Common-wealth, Sir HENRY WILLIAMS, Knight.</title>
                 <author>Scull, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tvvo sermons, upon that great embassie of our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ : recorded by his Euangelist, Saint Matthew, Chap. 10.V.16. Preached by Iohn Scull, an humble professor and minister of the word</title>
                 <author>Scull, John, minister of the word</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 50 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORTHY, THE RIGHT wel-deseruing of Church, and Common-wealth, Sir HENRY WILLIAMS, Knight.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Acile omnia tenenti, multa superfluè</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Bern. ep.</hi> 138. <hi>ad Hen. reg. Ang.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>ingeruntur.</hi> Many words to a man of vnderstanding, are more then enow. It was your desire to haue some thing said on this ensuing Text; your desire to know, intimates your will to obserue. <hi>Prius vtique est scire deum: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequens</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Lactant. de inst: lib</hi> 6 <hi>cap</hi> 5.</note>
      <hi>est colere.</hi> A man must know God, before he can serue him. It was your pleasure to assigne me the Speaker; your choice argued your opinion: Oh that it were as easie for me to make good, as (for him that sometimes saide) to say, <hi>Faciam vt ista de me tua duplicetur opinio.</hi> It is now <note place="margin">Cic. Epist.</note> your propper goods; It is your goodnesse to communicate it to the good of others. <hi>Bonum quo Communius, eo melius.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Arist.</note> The more common that a good thing is, the more good it will doe. <hi>Quibus parum, vel quibus nimium est, mihi ignoscant,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Aug. de Ciuit. Dei. li</hi> 22 <hi>c.</hi> 30.</note>
      <hi>quibus autem satis est, non mihi, sed domino mecum, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulantes, agant gratias.</hi> If ought be amisse, the fault is mine: If well, the praise is Gods.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>
And now, as <hi>Demosthenes</hi> spake to the <hi>Athenians,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Dem.</hi>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>:</note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: That as he respected them in all things, so they would him in this one: So also would I make bold, of you, to beg this fauour, that as I haue euer honoured your Vertues, and now ventured into the world to Obserue you: so you would vouchsafe to Patronize my Obedience, a more acceptable sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 22.</note> then the fat of Rammes, and to suffer it to passe vnder your name; <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, as an Argument of your <note place="margin">Isocr. ad Dem.</note> Fauour, and my Respect. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. Some body perhaps may be the better for it: you cannot be the worse; <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, Though not <note place="margin">Isocr. sup.</note> the richer, yet the more renowned. Pleaseth it you, that as you haue made your House, as <hi>Obediahs</hi> Caues, to hide the Prophets of the <note place="margin">1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 18. 13.</note> Lord, and to feed them: so you would make your Name also, as the house of the Lord, to preserue the Bookes of the Prophets, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect <note place="margin">2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 22. 8.</note> them. And so I leaue this Suckling at the breasts of your fostering, and you and yours to the fostering Father of the Church, and rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Totus in eo tuus cuius &amp; tu totus es. IOHN SCVLL.</signed>
      <note place="margin">
         <bibl>
            <hi>Aug. ad Paulin. ep.</hi> 32.</bibl>
      </note>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>