<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1568</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114792_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09832</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20097</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114792</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The hystories of the most famous and worthy cronographer Polybius : discoursing of the warres betwixt the Romanes [and] Carthaginenses, a riche and goodly worke, conteining holsome counsels [and] wonderfull deuises against the incombrances of fickle fortune. Englished by C.W. Wherevnto is annexed an abstract, compendiously coarcted out of the life &amp; worthy acts, perpetrate by oure puissaunt prince king Henry the fift</title>
                 <author>Polybius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Hacket, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1568</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 130, 1 leave, portraits (woodcut), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>WEre it as perillous to deale Cardes at play.</l>
      <l>As it is quarellous to deale Bokes this day</l>
      <l>One and fortie men amongst one and fiftie</l>
      <l>Would flee one and thirtie to flee one vnthriftie:</l>
      <l>And yet Cardes so dealt should haue in reuealing,</l>
      <l>Foredeale of Bokes in this hard time of dealing.</l>
      <l>Cardes be tooted on but on the one side,</l>
      <l>Bokes on both sides, in all places porde and pride,</l>
      <l>Not to content, but to contende vpon spiall,</l>
      <l>Of least tittle that can come in triall.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>Waying these things (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) I may be thought to haue attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a bold enterprise to take vpon me (being yet in my nonage) such a work as few or none haue done at like yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, also knowing the daunger there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which is the hasardyng of my good name: yet considering the causes that moued me to it, I truste there is none which will not beare with me.</p>
   <p>The principall and chiefe cause was, an Oration spoken extemporally by a noble and worthie péere of this realm before our victorious gouernor <hi>Henry</hi> the fift, as more at large appeareth in
<pb facs="5"/>
the Epistle to the Questioners. The seconde was a feruent zeale whiche I beare towardes my natiue countrey, and sundry exhortations written by graue and great lerned clearkes, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng vs to employ our whole laboure and studie, that we ouerslip not oure lyfe like sauage &amp; brute breasts, whom Nature hath formed prone and subiect to the filthy lustes of the belly. The thirde and last was, that they of riper yeares and exacter knowlege shoulde be pricked (as it wer with a spurre) by thys my doing, to the attemptyng of some worke to remain for an attesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that they liued not brutishely, but as men regarding their vocation. I cōfesse this my Translation to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polished, not exquisitely framed, or in a curious stile: for as our English E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pigramme sayth, <hi>The plain fashion is best, thats truely exprest,</hi> or, <hi>the plain fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion is best, thats plain without plaites.</hi> which epigrāme persuadeth me not to crepe into your fauour with any tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ambage or painted preāble, seing
<pb facs="6"/>
the mater is of importance inough to alliciate al men to the reading hereof.</p>
   <p>Thus I put forth this my freshmāly enterprise (yet not without reson) for

<q>
         <l>Time is tickle,</l>
         <l>Chaunce is fickle,</l>
         <l>Man is brickle,</l>
      </q>

to your grateful accepting, cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding thus.</p>
   <lg>
      <l>This work standing clere from all intent of yll</l>
      <l>In place or lack of good wit, accept good wyll:</l>
      <l>For if you carpe this, I tell you my minde plaine,</l>
      <l>Bold blinde bayard shal not lead me thus againe.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <salute>Fare you well.</salute>
      <dateline>From Gaudy Hall in Norfolke.</dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>