<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE Lorde Thomas Earle of Sussex, Vicount Fitzwalter, Lorde of Egremont, and of Burnell, one of the Queenes Maiesties Honorable priuie Counsayle, and Lorde high Chamberlayne of hir house, of the noble order of the Garter Knight, Iustice of Oyer of the Forrests, Parkes, VVarraynes, and Chases from Trent Southvvarde, and Captayne of the Gentlemen Pentioners: And to the right honorable Lady his wyfe, encrease of honour and true knowledge, in Christ Iesus.</title>
           <author>Tymme, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114256_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68449</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17406</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114256</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE Lorde Thomas Earle of Sussex, Vicount Fitzwalter, Lorde of Egremont, and of Burnell, one of the Queenes Maiesties Honorable priuie Counsayle, and Lorde high Chamberlayne of hir house, of the noble order of the Garter Knight, Iustice of Oyer of the Forrests, Parkes, VVarraynes, and Chases from Trent Southvvarde, and Captayne of the Gentlemen Pentioners: And to the right honorable Lady his wyfe, encrease of honour and true knowledge, in Christ Iesus.</title>
                 <author>Tymme, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A catholike and ecclesiasticall exposition of the holy Gospell after S. Iohn. Gathered out of all the singuler and approued deuines (which the Lorde hath giuen vnto his Church) by Augustine Marlorate. And translated out of Latin into Englishe by Thomas Timme minister. Seene and allovved according to the order appoynted</title>
                 <author>Marlorat, Augustin</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 <publisher>Harrison (Harison), John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 376, pages 376, 379-387, 389-418, 418-433, 433-497, 495-619 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶<hi>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE Lorde Thomas Earle of Sussex, Vicount Fitzwalter,</hi> Lorde of Egremont, and of Burnell, one of the Queenes Maiesties <hi>Honorable priuie Counsayle, and Lorde high Chamberlayne of hir house,</hi> of the noble order of the Garter Knight, Iustice of Oyer of the Forrests, <hi>Parkes, VVarraynes, and Chases from Trent Southvvarde, and Captayne of the Gentlemen Pentioners:</hi> And to the right honorable Lady his wyfe, encrease of honour and true knowledge, in Christ Iesus.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE GREAT</hi> PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite which the Christiā minde is to receyue by reading this Booke, was the cause why I tooke the paynes to Translate it out of Latin into the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish toung: and the Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending therof the more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently to haue it read, was the occasion which moued me to Dedicate my parte therein to your Honors. For what Englishe man is there which will not thinke it a Booke most worthy the reading, which he seeth warranted by your Names? The honorable and generall report whereof hartneth me to present it vnto you: wherein ye shall finde the deepe and deuine Euangelist <hi>Sainct John:</hi> the marrow of all Commentaries vppon him, vnder the name of <hi>Marlorates Collection:</hi> last, and least, my faythfull tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell to turne them bothe to the vse of my Countrey. The thing I know your Honors will like well, bicause, as I heare, you can skilfully iudge, so I doubt not but you haue made your choyce what to reade, which so muche bruteth the credite of your abilitie, founde out
<pb facs="3"/>
by effect. As for my labor, may it please your Honors to like it, as comming from one, which caught with the commendation of your Learning and Wisdome gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally noyzed, could not but offer my selfe to you, as the wondering Queene of <hi>Saba</hi> could not rest tyll she had seene <hi>Salomons</hi> person, of whose wisdome she had hard so muche. And withall I thought it good in offering my labor to your Honors, to ioyne you both togither, thinking with my selfe that it must needes follow, that suche skill and iudgement beeing in so Honorable a man, must needes by societie of matche worke like ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in so honorable a Mate. Wherefore not to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your Honors with longer speache, I take my leaue, Recommending my poore <hi>Paynes</hi> to your Honors protection, the recompence whereof you shall receiue in your reading of the booke, whose fruite will bring, by Gods grace, health to your soules, and continuance of your Honor.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors most humble, Thomas Timme.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>