<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ Iohan Bale to the Chri∣sten Readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1547</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114741_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A22106</idno>
           <idno type="STC">851</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114741</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ Iohan Bale to the Chri∣sten Readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first examinacio [n] of Anne Askewe : latelye martired in Smythfelde, by the Romyshe popes vpholders, wyth the elucydacyon of Iohan Bale</title>
                 <author>Askew, Anne</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1547</date>
                 <publisher>Hill (Hyll, van den Berghe, Montanus), Nicholas (Niko—laos).</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hill (Hyll, van den Berghe, Montanus), Nicholas (Niko—laos)</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>228 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="53"/>
   <head>¶ Iohan Bale to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the primatiue chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che, as the horible per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>secucyons increased, many dyligēt writers collected the godly an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>swers &amp; tryumphaūte sufferinges of the mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyrs, as necessarye ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Christen constancye to be fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of other. Of this nombre was Lucas, which wrote the Apostles actes So were after him Linus, Marcellus, Egesippus, Meliton Asianus, Abdias Babilonius,<note place="margin">Wryters.</note> Iosephus Antiochenus, Clemens Alexaūdrinus, Antherus, Phi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leas, Eusebius, Nicephorus, &amp; a greate sorte more, Fabianus, not a chayre Bys<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hopp, but a pulpet Byshop of Rome, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned in his tyme for that onely offyce vii. deacōs &amp; so many notayres, aboute the yeare of oure lorde. CC. XXXVI. that they shuld faithfully regestre theyr martyrdomes,<note place="margin">notaireye.</note> to holde thē in contynual remembraunce, as witnesseth Platina Polydorus, Masseus, &amp; soch other chro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyclers. No les necessary is that offyce now though fewe mē attempt it, nor no lesse profytable to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> christē cōmō welthe than it was in those terryble dayes. For
<pb facs="53"/>
now are persecucions all Christendome ouer, so wele as were than.<note place="margin">Martyrs.</note> Now are y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> true Christians vexed of the syttynge Byshoppes for their Christen beleue, so wele as thā. Now are they reuiled, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyshed, imprisoned &amp; haue all euyll spo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken against them for Christes verites sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke. Math. v. so wele as than.</p>
   <p>And what can be more confortable to the sufferers,<note place="margin">Sufferers</note> than to knowe the ernest constancye of their troubled company<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in that kingedome of pacience? Apo. i. or to marke in them the stronge wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of faythe, &amp; beholde the myghtye mageste of God in their agonies? what though they were afore, synners of the worlde. Saynt Barnard sayth in his ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>melyes vpon Salomons cantycles,<note place="margin">Bernar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</note> that the godlye sufferaunce of martyrs hath geuen as good erudycyon to the christen churche, as euer dyd the doctryne of the sayntes. Than is it mete that some be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sterynge, and not that all men in these dayes be ydell concernynge that godlye offyce. Manye haue suffered in thys re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme of late yeares,<note place="margin">Barnes &amp; other.</note> by the bolde calling on of Antichristes furyouse aduocates, whose lattre confessyons, causes, &amp; ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, are a great deale more notable &amp; godlye, if they be ryghtlye wayed, than euer were the confessyons, causes and
<pb facs="54"/>
answers of the olde canonysed martirs which in the popes Englysh churche ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue had so many solempnitees, seruices, and sensinges.<note place="margin">Recāters.</note> Manye haue also moste desperatly recanted through their most wicked persuacions and threttenynges in whose vaine recantaciōs are both to be seane, theyr blasphemyes agaynste God, and manyfest treasons agaynste their kinge.</p>
   <p>Now in conferrynge these martyrs, the olde with the newe, and the popes with Christes. I seclude first of all the Brytayne churche, or y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> primatiue chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of thys realme, which neuer had au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toryte of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Romishe pope.<note place="margin">Brytayne churche.</note> Her martirs in dede were agreable to that Chryste spake a fore in the Gospell concernyng his martyrs, wherby we shulde knowe thē, as we euydentlye finde in the liues of Emerita kinge Lucyes syster, Amphi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>balus, Albanus, Aaron, Iulius, Diono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus, &amp; soche other. I sende yow forthe (saith he) as sh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pe amonge wolues. Mē shall delyuer ye vp in their counsels &amp; sinagoges.<note place="margin">Christ.</note> Ye shall be brought before ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers and kinges, and be hated of all men in a maner for my names sake, Mathei x. Caste not afore in your mindes what answere to make. For I in that houre shal gyue ye both vtteraunce and wisdo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me,
<pb facs="54"/>
which al your aduersaries shall not be hable to withstande, Luce xxi. They shall excommunycate yow or condēpne yow for heretikes. Yea,<note place="margin">Byshop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes.</note> they shall bring yow in soch hate of the world, that who so euer killeth yow, will thynke he doth God great good seruyce. And thys shall they do bycause they knowe rightly nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther father nor yet me, Iohan. xvi.</p>
   <p>Manye other lyke sentences left y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de Iesus Christ in his holie Gospell, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we shulde alwayes by thē discerne hys true martyrs, frō the popes &amp; Mahomet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes coūterfet martyrs. In Englāde here sens the first plātacion of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> popes Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lysh churche,<note place="margin">Englysh churche.</note> by Augustine &amp; other Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish mōkes of Benettes supersticiō, ii. kindes of martyrs hath bene, One of mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nasterye buylders and chaunterye foun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders, whom the temporall princes &amp; se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular magystrates haue dyuerslie done to death, sumtyme for disobedience, and sumtyme for manifest treason, as we ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue of Wallenus of Crowland,<note place="margin">Martyrs.</note> Thomas of Lācastre, Rycharde Scrope, Becket &amp; soch other. The ymages of these haue bene set vp in their tēples, lyke the olde Gods of the paganes, &amp; haue had theyr vigyls, holy dayes, ringinges, sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sīges, cādels offerīges, feastīges, &amp; moch a do besides, as they had. The other
<pb facs="55"/>
sort were preachers of the Gospell,<note place="margin">Other martyrs.</note> or poore teachers therof ī corners, whā the persecuciō was soche, that it myght not be taught abroade. And these poore sow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les, or true seruauntes of God, were put to deathe by the holy spirituall fathers Byshoppes, prestes, monkes, chanons, &amp; fryers, for heresye &amp; lollerye, they saye. These Christen martyrs were neuer so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lēpnysed of them. No, they had not so moch as a peny dirge or a grote masse of Requiem,<note place="margin">No dyrge</note> no more thā had Iohan Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyst and Steuen amonge the Iewes. But they haue bene holden for condemp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned heretykes euer sens.</p>
   <p>Who euer hearde anye goodnesse yet reported of Dionothus with his M. &amp; CC. companyous,<note place="margin">Augustine</note> whom Augustyne can sed to be slayne at Westchestre in hys churches begynnynge, bycause they wol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de not preache as he dyd apoynt thē, nor baptyse after the Romysh maner, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet hallow the Eastre feast as they dyd. Many a blessed creature, both men &amp; womē, haue bene brēt sens Iohan Wy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cleues tyme &amp; a fore,<note place="margin">Wycleue.</note> for onlye disclosyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge the pharysees yokes &amp; teachynge the Gospels liberte. And thē haue that baw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye bloudie Synagoge of Sathā dyffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, blasphemed, condēpned, execrated &amp; cursed to hell as most detestable here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tykes
<pb facs="55"/>
and dogges. Wher as if they we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of Christ, they ought (in case they we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re their haters or enemies) to suffre thē,<note place="margin">Suffre.</note> to saye wele of them, to do them good, &amp; to praye for them. Math. v. Luce. vi. &amp; not thus to vse more tyrannie ouer them than euer dyd Saracene, Turke, Tiraūt or deuyll. A great dyfference is there of the martyrs whom they make, from the martyrs whom they canonyse. Of them whom they dampne,<note place="margin">Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs.</note> from them whom they worshypp, yea so great a difference or dyuersyte betwine them (if ye marke them wele) as is betwyxt golde and dyrt, or light and darkenesse.</p>
   <p>The martyrs,<note place="margin">Martyrs.</note> whose deathes they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue procured by all ages of theyr bloud-thursty church, harkned vnto Christ, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alde of ryghtousnesse, and sought their lorde God in sprete, Esa. li, but the mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyrs for the most part, whom they haue with so manye latyne wawlynges, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches &amp; candell burnynges, magnyfyed in their temples, harkened to the pope, healde of hys vnrightousnesse, &amp; sought out hys superstycyouse ydolatryes.<note place="margin">Compare.</note> In the conferrynge of their olde canonysed martyrs, with our newly condempned martyrs here. Anne Askewe and her other iii. companyons, with soche like, their difference will be moch more ease<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb facs="56"/>
perceiued. First lete vs beginne with Thomas Becket,<note place="margin">Becket.</note> which was so gloryou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>se a martyr and precyouse aduocate of theirs, that they made his bloude equal with Christes bloude and desyred to cli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me to heauen therby. Manie wonderful miracles coulde that mitred patrone of theirs do in those dayes,<note place="margin">Miracles</note> whan the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes had fryre Bakons bokes and knew the bestowynge of fryre Bōgaies mystes but now he can do none at al. Thys Bec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ket in all hys floryshynge doynges, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened to the pope, defended his pompou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>se kingedome, supported his churches ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cesse, &amp; wretchedlye dyed for the synne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full lybertees of the same. Anne Askew &amp; her sort,<note place="margin">Ryght matyrs.</note> gaue diligēt hede to their lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Iesus Christ, soughte the kingedome of heauen in daylye repentaunce, migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telye detested all ydolatrouse worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynges, &amp; in conclusyon suffered moste tryumphaunt deathe for the same.</p>
   <p>Cōcernynge other martyrs. As Wene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>frid, otherwyse called Boniface an Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lysh mōke &amp; archebyshopp of Magunce was slaine cōfirminge neophytes,<note place="margin">Bonifaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Angl{us}</note> or pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fessynge his newlie baptysed brode to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Romysh popes obediēce. There was foū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de aboute hym a casket full of rellickes or dead mēnis bones, whā he was put to death in the year of our lorde. vii. c. lv.
<pb facs="56"/>
Anne Askewe &amp; here felyshyp, had none other rellyckes aboute thē, whā they sto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de at the stake to be brent in Smythfel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de but a bundell of the sacred scriptures inclosed in their hartes, and redye to be vttered aganist Antichristes ydolatries. Saynt Clare of Orchestre contemninge lawfull marryage,<note place="margin">Clarus.</note> made hym selfe an ydel prest, &amp; was by headed in his owne gardene by procurimente of a womā. S. Clitāke of Southwales, was in like ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>se stabbed in with a dagger,<note place="margin">Clitancus</note> bycause a yonge maiden loued him. The only true honoure of God was it, &amp; no worldlye cause, that Anne Askewe &amp; her compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye dyed for. Saynt Edwyne being wel armed,<note place="margin">Edwin{us}</note> was slayne in battayle at Hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felde in the North, and S. Edwarde ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge a Huntinge in the forest of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham in the weast,<note place="margin">Edwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus.</note> was killed vpon hys horse in drinkinge a cuppe of wine. And all thys was done for the kyngedomes of thys worlde. The martyrdome of An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne Askewe and her Bretherne, was neyther in battelinge nor huntynge, ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge nor drynkynge, but in that ryght course which Christ prescribed vnto his dyscyples vnder the cruell Byshoppes, for his onlye glorye.</p>
   <p>Saynet Cadocke of Cowbridge a Bys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop,<note place="margin">Cadocus.</note> was pearced through with a spea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re,
<pb facs="57"/>
as he stode at his Masse at one of the clocke at after non, bicause he wolde be of the ordre of martyrs. Saynte El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phege archebishopp of Caunterburye was stoned to deathe of the Danes, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he wolde not pase them thre. M. Marke, in the yeare of our lorde. M. &amp; xii. Of soch martyrs, moch doubted Lā<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>francus,<note place="margin">Lanfran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</note> which suceeded him in that of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice about a iiii. score years after, and disputed therof with Anselmus. The cause of Anne Askewe and her compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, was neither madnesse nor mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neye, but the onlie sekinge of their lord God righte. As Sainte Indract with other deuoute pilgrimes of Rome laie in bed in their inne at Shapwyck by Blastenbury,<note place="margin">Indrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</note> their throtes were cut in the night for moneie, which was recke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be in their pylgrymes scryppes. Saynt Iuthware a virgine was behed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded also,<note place="margin">Iuthwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra.</note> for layenge fresh chese or crud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des whether ye will to her brestes. The cause of Anne Askewe and her other fel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowes, conferred with Christes scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res semeth a farre other matter. Hewal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de the blacke and Hewalde the whyght ii. Englysh mōkes,<note place="margin">Newaldy duo.</note> goynge frō place to place with cruettes, chalyce, and super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altare, to do their daylye sacrifices, we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re done to deathe in Frislande by the
<pb facs="57"/>
bowers of the contrey for teachynge a straunge relygyon, and are worshypped at Coleyne for martyrs. For bearynge about Christes testament, which is most heauenlye treasure,<note place="margin">Anne As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kewe.</note> and for spredynge y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wholsom doctrine therof, was Anne As<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kewe and her sort brēt by the prestes pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>curemēt, yet are they no honour for it.</p>
   <p>Osytha runnynge awaye frome her husbande,<note place="margin">Ositha.</note> by the intysement of. ii. mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes became a professed nonne, and was murthered of the Danes. Wenefryda by counsell of a prest,<note place="margin">Wenefri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da.</note> dysdaynouslye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusynge the marryage of a prynce chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stened, lost her head for it. Maxentia al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so played a parte not al vnlyke to thys.<note place="margin">Maxētia.</note> Soch pylde popysh martyrdomes, com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pared to the martyrdome of Anne Aske<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we and her faythful companye, is as is rustye yron compared to pure syluer.<note place="margin">Guilhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</note> S. William of Rochestre a Scotte, leauyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge both wife &amp; houshold, ydly to trudge on pylgrymage, was strycken in the heade wyth an axe, of his owne compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyon by the waye. Saynte Thomas of Douer a monke was suche a wone,<note place="margin">Thomas.</note> as was slayne of the frenche men for hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge the churches iewels, crosses, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyces &amp; copes. No such light corruptible vanytees were they, that Anne Askewe &amp; her constaunt bretherne dyed for, but
<pb facs="58"/>
for the precyouse veryte of God. Yonge S. Wyllyam of Norwych,<note place="margin">Yonge Sayntes</note> yonge S Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert of Burye, yonge S. Hugh of Lyncol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, yōge S. Melor of Cornewayle, yōg s. Kenelme of Glocestre, yonge S. Eldrede of Rāsaye &amp; his brother, wyth soch other lyke, were but verye babes (they saye) &amp; were martyred of the Iewes &amp; of other enemyes. Wherfore their martyrdomes shal be but babysh in cōparysō of these y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> verite hauing by thē so smal furtheraūce</p>
   <p>Foillanus &amp; his. iii. bretherne,<note place="margin">Foillan{us}.</note> goynge homeward in the nyghte, after they had well banketed wyth S. Gertrude &amp; her nonnes, were killed in a wod of one mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>therer, and their horses solde in the next market towne. Iustinanus. S. Dauyes ghostlye father in Wales,<note place="margin">Iustina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> was slayne in a gardene of hys iii. monkes, bycause he compelled them to do more laboure than he wolde do hys selfe. After Kilianus was come home frome Rome,<note place="margin">Kilianus</note> he was murthered in his selle wyth other holye pylgrymes by a woman, as they laye there a slepe in the nyght. Saynt Vrsula also and her she pylgrymes,<note place="margin">Vrsula.</note> with theyr chaplaynes, nurses, and suckyng babes were but homely handeled at Coleyne of the hunnes and pietes (if that legende be true) as they were commynge homewar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des from Rome. Compare me Anne As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kewe
<pb facs="58"/>
and her condempned companye, wyth these clowted, canonysed, solemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nysed, sensed, matrensed, and massed, martyrs,<note place="margin">Proue the ipretes.</note> and tell me by the Gosples tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, whyche of them seme moste Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke martyres. Yea, brynge saynte Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mound of Burye, saynt Fremūd of Dun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stable, saynt Ethelbert of Herforde, S. Oswalde of Glocestre, saynte Oswyne of Tynmoth, and Saynte Wynstane of Euesham (whych are the best of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyshe martyres) to the touche stone of Goddes worde,<note place="margin">Edmūd{us}. Fremūd{us} and other</note> and ye shall fynde theyr martyrdomes and causes full vnlyke to theyrs whome the Byshoppes murther now apace in Englande.</p>
   <p>In all these Englysh martyrs reherced here afore,<note place="margin">Tokens.</note> ye shall fynde verye fewe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loures or yet tokens, that Christ sayd his martyrs shuld be knowne by, on lesse ye take pylgrimages, pōpes rellyckes, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, battels, hūtynges, ydelnes, monke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryes, moneye, treasure, worldlye kingdo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes, contēpt of marryage, superstycyōs &amp; suche other vanitees for thē.<note place="margin">the autor.</note> And than wyll I saye, and not lye in it, that ye are moch better ouerseane thā lerned in the scriptures of God, as youre olde blynde bludderynge predecessours hath bene. Ye wyll axe me here, if I reckē Englāde thā all barrē of Christē martyrs: Naye mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="59"/>
do I not. For I knowe it hathe had good store sēs the popes faith came first into Englande to the Gospels obscura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyō, though their names be not knowne to al mē. Greate tyrānye was shewed by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> heythnysh emprours &amp; kynges at the fyrst preachynge of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Gospel in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyue churche of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> brytaynes,<note place="margin">Brytan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyshe,</note> by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cruel callynge on of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pagane prestes. But no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge lyke to y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hath bene shewed sēs in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Englysh church by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> spiritual tyraūt of Rome &amp; his mytred termagaūtes,<note place="margin">Englyshe.</note> at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prouocacyō of theyr oyled swylbolles &amp; blīd Baalamites. For they most cruel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye brēt those innocētes, whych dyd but only read y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> testamēt of God in their mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther runge, &amp; do not yet repente them of that myschefe but contynewe therin.</p>
   <p>Yf ye marke wel these. ii. examinaciōs of Anne Askewe, ye shal fynde in her &amp; in her other.<note place="margin">Tokens.</note> iii. cōmpaniōs, besydes other whō the Byshoppes in our tyme &amp; afore hath brēt, the expresse tokēs y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Christ sea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth his martyrs w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. Thei apered as she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe amonge wolues. They were throwne in strōg presō. They were brought forth into coūsels &amp; synagoges. Their answe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res were out of gods spret (as herin ape<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth) &amp; not out of their own.<note place="margin">Answers.</note> They were reuyled, mocked, stocked, racked, execra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, condempned, and murthered, as is
<pb facs="59"/>
sayde afore. By a spiritualte also, as he promised they shuld be. Mat. xxiii. and xxiiii. Yea, those spiritual tyrauntes be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sydes theyr mortal malyce vpō the inno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cent bodyes,<note place="margin">Tyraūtes</note> haue most blasphemouslye vttered in theyr spyghtful sermons and writynges, that their sowles are damp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned, as is to be seane in the bokes of win<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chestre and Peryn.<note place="margin">Winchost<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re Peryn.</note> But let them be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re lest they dampne not theyr own wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched soules. For ful sure we are by Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stes stronge promes. Luce. xii. That theyr sowles they can not harme wyth all theyr popes blacke curses. Ful swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telye rest they now in the peace of God, where theyr slaunderous and malyciou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>se iudgementes can not hurte them at al Sapi. iii. Lette those Epycures pygges dampne them with as manye blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouse lyes as they can ymagyne,<note place="margin">Epycures pygges.</note> for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther armour they haue not. And we shal on the other syde canonyse thē agayne wyth the myghty wordes and promises of Christ, which they shall neuer be ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to resist. The father of our lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, graunt the light of his word so to spred the world ouer that the dark mysces of Sathan maye clerely be expel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led,<note place="margin">Lyght.</note> to the specyall conforte of his rede<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med Churche, and glorye of his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall name. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>