<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Toothlesse Satire vpon him that made, or rather mard the for∣mer Booke.</title>
           <author>Taylor, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1146_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13440</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23748.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1146</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Toothlesse Satire vpon him that made, or rather mard the for∣mer Booke.</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Dolphins danger and deliuerance : being a ship of 220. tunne hauing in her but 36. men and 2. boyes, who were on the 12. of Ianuary 1616. set vpon by 6. men of warre of the Turkes hauing at the least 1500. men in them : who fought with them 5. houres and a halfe, yet t the glory of God and the honor of our English nation, both shippe and goods safely brought vp the Riuer of Thames and deliuered / truely set forth by the appoyntment of M. Edward Nichols, being Maister of the said ship ; with the names of all those that were slaine on the English part, the maner how, and how many were maymed, and what they are that suruiue</title>
                 <author>Nichols, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Gosson, Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>A Toothlesse Satire vpon him that made, or rather mard the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Booke.</head>
   <l>RIch cloath of gold vnto a Botcher brought,</l>
   <l>It shall be mard, not made, quite sham'd, not fram'd:</l>
   <l>When worser stuffe by a good Worke-man wrought,</l>
   <l>Becomes the owner, makes the maker fam'd.</l>
   <l>Rare Phisicke, as it is as abus'd, or vs'd,</l>
   <l>As is the Doctors ignorance, or skill:</l>
   <l>Such operation from it is infus'd,</l>
   <l>That it doth helpe, or hurt, or cure, or kill.</l>
   <l>Vnto the stuffe the fault we cannot put,</l>
   <l>Nor to the Phisicke, we the crime apply:</l>
   <l>The Bungling Taylor spoyld when he did cut,</l>
   <l>And want of skill did cause the patient dye.</l>
   <l>Then let a botching patcher botch and mend,</l>
   <l>Let Mountebankes giue Phisicke vnto dogs:</l>
   <l>Let Coopers on their hooples Tubs attend,</l>
   <l>And Millers deale no further then their Cogges.</l>
   <l>For, when a witles Rooke shall vndertake,</l>
   <l>Of such exployts as these to make a Booke:</l>
   <l>The ancient Prouethe true, he seeme to make</l>
   <l>God sends good meat, the Diuell sends a Cooke.</l>
   <l>Why, such a worke as this deserues to haue</l>
   <l>A <hi>Homers,</hi> or a <hi>Ʋirgils</hi> skill to grace in</l>
   <l>And not an ignorant intruding K----</l>
   <l>Whose blindnes did in euery place misplace it.</l>
   <l>Some lies some truthes together cram'd and thrust,</l>
   <l>Quite out of Time, like mustard after meat:</l>
   <l>That 'tis a wonder such a fellow durst</l>
   <l>VVith wit so little, write of things so great.</l>
   <l>VVhere thirty sixe men and two boyes in fight,</l>
   <l>Gainst fifteene hundred were sixe houres oppos'd:</l>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <l>Boorded with multitudes; with maine and might,</l>
   <l>Round with the foes, and fiery flames inclos'd</l>
   <l>Where death was scorn'd and vallour was belou'd,</l>
   <l>Where victory was that, at which they aym'd;</l>
   <l>Where noble Resolution was aproou'd</l>
   <l>Where Fame adornes, the sound, dead, hurt and maim'd,</l>
   <l>What subiect could a pen more Ample find</l>
   <l>(If all were written in perticular)</l>
   <l>From Thames, vnto the farthest shore of Inde,</l>
   <l>Or from the Artick toth' Antartick starre.</l>
   <l>Why should a fellow, beeing there in place,</l>
   <l>Remember not himselfe, or any other;</l>
   <l>But bury all their glory in disgrace,</l>
   <l>And each mans Acts in darke obliuion smother:</l>
   <l>O! tis a hell of hells, and shame of shames,</l>
   <l>Where men shall iustly dare to fight and dye:</l>
   <l>And writers will not regester their names.</l>
   <l>When noming makes them liue Immortally.</l>
   <l>To shew how valiant men doe spend their blood,</l>
   <l>It doth each worthy heart with courage strike,</l>
   <l>To Imitate the actions that are good,</l>
   <l>And by example to attemp the like.</l>
   <l>But when a man shall for a certaine know,</l>
   <l>That with his life, his memory must fall:</l>
   <l>And no Records his worthinesse shall show,</l>
   <l>These meanes will make starke Cowards of vs all.</l>
   <l>Then these poore lines shall make these men suruiue,</l>
   <l>Vnto the vtmost end of time or fate:</l>
   <l>They liu'd and dyed, and dead, are still aliue,</l>
   <l>In Name, in Pame, in Earthly, Heauenly state.</l>
   <l>And as for him that writ the Booke before,</l>
   <l>Let him write better, or else write no more.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Iohn Taylor.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>