<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE to the Christian Rea∣der, seruing as a preparative to the Treatise following.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114006_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15396</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25673</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114006</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE to the Christian Rea∣der, seruing as a preparative to the Treatise following.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A catholicon, that is, A generall preservative or remedie against the pseudocatholike religion : gathered out of the catholike epistle of S. Jude, briefly expounded, and aptly, according to the time, applied to more then halfe an hundreth of popish errours, and as many corruptions of manners. With a preface seruing as a preparatiue to the catholicon, and a dyet prescribed after</title>
                 <author>Willet, Andrew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waterson, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>44, 217, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE to the Christian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, seruing as a preparative to <hi>the Treatise following.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Kilfull Physitians, to worke safely and cure soundly, doe vse prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiues before they mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister to their patients, and prescribe a dyet to be obserued after: the same course will I take: that whereas I haue out of S. <hi>Iudes</hi> Catholike epistle, confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted a <hi>Catholicon,</hi> that is, a generall preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatiue against popish infection, I will first briefly prepare the minde of the discreete Reader, in shewing the danger of this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerspreading and contagious disease. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi>
      <note place="margin">Nihilmagis ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gris prodest quā curari ab eo, á quo volunt. lib, 4. declamat.</note> saith, that <hi>nothing doth more profit the sicke, then to be cured of him, whome they desire to be cured by.</hi> I trust then that this enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise of mine, shall not be fruitlesse to any, proceeding from him which wisheth well
<pb facs="6"/>
to the cause of religion, and to all those that vnfainedly loue the Lord Iesus, that they which stand, may continue, they which wauer may be setled, which doubt, may be confirmed. Such a physitian therefore, as is a friend, and such physicke as is whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some, is that, I trust, which euery man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sireth, that either would haue his sicknes cured, or his health preserued.</p>
   <p>Now to know how dangerous &amp; hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full the contagion of Poperie, and popish religion is, no better rule can be giuen, then that prescribed by our Sauiour, Math. 7. 16. <hi>Exfructibus eorum. &amp;c. By their fruits ye shall know them.</hi> And the wise man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribeth the harlot by these properties. Her crueltie: <hi>Her house tendeth to death,</hi> Prov. 2. 18. Her treacherie and vnfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: <hi>Shee forsaketh the guide of her youth,</hi> vers. 17. Her flatterie: vers. 16. <hi>Shee flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with her words.</hi> As a dishonest and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chast woman is thus discerned, so is a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt religion. And these are the very bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and ensignes of the whore of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, Crueltie, Treacherie, Flatterie. Where they get the sword, they shew all crueltie: where their power faileth, they worke by treacherie: where this speedeth not, they will deceiue by flatterie and hypocrisie.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="6"/>
Their rage and crueltie against the mē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers <note place="margin">Of Romanists.</note> of Christ, haue beene most brutish and vnnaturall; what tortures can be deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, which they haue not applied? what grieuous death which they haue not exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted vpon the poore members of Christ? Some they haue hanged, as a good mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster in Germanie in his owne house. <hi>Fox p.</hi> 880. Some drowned; as Peter Spengler at Ensishem. Some beheaded. Nicholas Paul at Gaunt. <hi>Fox p.</hi> 896. Some buried quicke, as two women at Lovaine. <hi>Ann.</hi> 1543. <hi>ex Francis Encen.</hi> Some pulled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sunder by peecemeale: Iohn Clarke at Melden. <hi>An.</hi> 1524. <hi>ex Crispino.</hi> Some had their eyes put out, as a priest in Germanie. <hi>Fox. p.</hi> 891. Some put into the pinchbacke, hanging by the hands and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>russed vp be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde, with a great waight at their feete. <hi>p.</hi> 882. Some poisoned, as a priest at E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ford. <hi>p.</hi> 896. Some burned with oyle. Steuen Browne at Poitiers. <hi>Ann.</hi> 1540▪ Some bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by peecemeale: Peter Gavart at Paris. <hi>Ann.</hi> 1558 Some burned beeing smeared with fat and brimstone, as Martius Alba, Petrus Scriba at Lyons. <hi>ex Pātaleon.</hi> Some burned with brimstone and gunpowder, as Iulianus Leville at Sanserre. <hi>Ann.</hi> 1554. <hi>ex Iohanne Crispino.</hi> Some burned with
<pb facs="7"/>
pitch and tarre dropping vpon them. <note place="margin">Of Romanists.</note> George Marsh. <hi>p.</hi> 1567. Some broyled. Iohn Whiteman at Ostend <hi>Fox. p.</hi> 2113. Some pressed with hot yron, hands and feete; Bertrande. <hi>Fox. p.</hi> 896. Some drawn <note place="margin">Here is the patience and faith of Saints. Rev. 13. 10.</note> and torne vpon the racke; Bennet Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane. <hi>Fox. p.</hi> 926. Some had their tongues cut out; Peter Roscan at Bloys. <hi>An.</hi> 1556. <hi>Crispin.</hi> And Peter Serre at Tholosse. <hi>An.</hi> 1553. William Hasson at Roane. <hi>Ann.</hi> 1544. <hi>ex Crispino.</hi> And it was generally decreed at Paris, that the Martyrs should haue their tongues cut out. <hi>Ann.</hi> 1546. <hi>Crispin.</hi> Some had their tongues boared through; Henrie Conboron. <hi>ex Crispin.</hi> Some had their throats cut, as 88. in Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bria. <hi>p.</hi> 942. Some women slain with child, and their infants tumbling out, troaden vnder feete, and trampled vpon: as the women of Merindoll. <hi>Fox. p.</hi> 952. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable are the torments which thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of Gods Saints haue endured and suffered vnder the tyrannie of Antichrist. 1500. were apprehended at once in Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bria. <hi>Fox. p.</hi> 942. Ten thousand were slaine in Paris in three daies, in the bloodie mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sacre. Within lesse then fiue yeares, three hundreth faithfull seruants of Christ, were burned to ashes in England. God be bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb facs="7"/>
for the happie change, and the Lord in <note place="margin">Of Romanists.</note> mercie deliuer his Church from such <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> times.</p>
   <p>Thus, as the Apostle spake of the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of Christ in former times, they were tried with mockings and scourgings: moreouer by bonds and imprisonment: they were stoned, hewen asunder, temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, they were slain with the sword: whom the world was not worthie of, Hebr. 11. 37. so haue the true worshippers of God beene handled in these latter times. And whereas they could not ouercome by sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie and sophistrie, they haue tried them by force and cruelty, as <hi>Hierome</hi> saith in the <note place="margin">Tallbu▪ institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus es discipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, vt cui respō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere non po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, caput aufe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras, &amp; linguam quae tacere non potest, seces? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polog. 3. ad Ruff.</note> like case; <hi>Are you sowell taught, that, whome you can not answer, you will take off his head, and cut out his tongue that will not hold his peace?</hi> So did Fulvia to Cicero, and Herod to Iohn. And thus did the Papists deale with the learned Martyrs: whome they could not conquer by Scripture, they thought to subdue by torture: they perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted them with fire and sword, whome they could not conquer by the word. Much like are these Romanists to their forefathers the olde bloodie Romanes, whose measure they fulfill.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Seneca</hi> reporteth, that L. Scylla com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb facs="8"/>
M. Marius legges to be broken, <note place="margin">Of Romanists.</note> his eyes to be pulled out, his hands to be cut off, and so tormented him by peece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meale, as some of the Martyrs were hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. <note place="margin">Lib. 3. de Ira.</note> Caius Caesar vsed this torment, to stop their mouthes with sponges, and pieces cut off from their garments, whome he cruelly put to death: euen as the popish Romanists boared through the tongues of the Martyrs, and thrust balls of y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>on in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their mouthes, and of some they cut out their tongues, that they should not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of their crueltie. Volesus the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>consull of Asia, vnder Augustus Caesar, hauing in one day beheaded 300. walked <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>en l. 2. de Ira.</note> among the dead bodies, vaunting himselfe with these words, <hi>Rem verè regiam, O kingly act!</hi> The like cruell part, if not worse, was shewed by the Romanists in Calabria <hi>Ann.</hi> 1560. when 88. Martyrs in one day had their throats cut. The manner where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <note place="margin">Fox. p. 942.</note> was this. They beeing all shut vp in one house togither as in a fold, the hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man tooke them out one by one, &amp; so di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spatched them: going from one to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the bloodie knife in his mouth, and a bloodie muffler in his hand, with his hands vp to the ellboes in goare blood. Did not this cruell wretch thinke also in
<pb facs="8"/>
his minde, that he had done a princely act? <note place="margin">Of Romanists.</note> Such haue beene, and yet is, the crueltie of the popish Romane Church, whereby we may certenly discerne that they are not guided by the spirit of God: for, the <hi>fruits of the spirit are meekenesse, gentlenesse, peace,</hi> Gal. 5. 22. These beastly cruell bloodsuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers shew themselues to be the right mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Antichrist, and the brood of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulus that laid the foundation of Rome in the blood of Remus his brother. Neither are we to looke for better entertainment, or other measure at their hands. For one of their own cuntrey men that best knew the bloodie disposition of the Romanists, <note place="margin">Hoc inter caete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra pessimum habet crudeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, perseveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum est: nec ad meliora patet regressus: scele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra sceleribus tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enda sunt. Sen. l. 1. de clem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n.</note> hath thus described their nature: <hi>This bad qualitie hath crueltie among the rest, they must hold out: and hardly returne they to a better minde: for wickednes must be defended with wickednes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>God graunt his faithfull seruants pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that suffer vnder their cruell hand, and to his Church in England continue this fauour, that as we haue shaken off their tyrannicall yoke, so we may neuer be brought vnder the same againe. Amen. So be it. Lord Iesus.</p>
   <p>But, because the Romanists doe falsly obiect against the Protestants, their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame
<pb facs="9"/>
crueltie executed vpon the Popes <note place="margin">Feverdentius re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>elled.</note> Catholikes, for stopping of their slaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous mouth, I will briefly set downe the truth herein.</p>
   <p>A certaine brawling fryer of Paris, namely <hi>Feverdentius,</hi> hath stepped forth of late, opening his lying mouth wide, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the proceeding of the Protestants in France especially and England. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning France he saith, that the whole na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did abound with blood, their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches made stables, or burned to ashes, their fields wasted, their riuers ran with blood: <hi>atque hi, novi evangelij, fructus:</hi> and these are <note place="margin">Dial. 1. p. 7.</note> the fruits, saith he, of the new gospel. And, of troubles in England mooued against Catholikes, he is not ashamed thus impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently to write: that they are drawne to come to heare sermons; if they refuse to come, they are imprisonned, whipped, hanged, racked, bowelled, their members quartered and boyled, and cast forth to be <note place="margin">Dial. 1. p. 15.</note> eaten of foules, beasts, and dogges, because they desire to obserue the religion recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from their fathers.</p>
   <p>Would any man thinke, that they were so shamelesse, as to publish such wicked slaunders and impudent lies, to the view of the world?</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="9"/>
This lying fryer hath most slaunderou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sly <note place="margin">Feverdentius refuted.</note> charged the protestants, with the ciuill warres and troubles of France, with defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the temples, shedding of blood, laying wast the countrie: whereas it is most notoriously knowne, that the Papists were the onely causes of all these mischeifes. Did not Miniers that cruell tyrant, when he had taken the towne of <hi>Cabrieis</hi> by tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie, <note place="margin">Fox p. 932 ex histor. Gallica.</note> enter into the Church, and cause men, women, and children, that were fled thither for succour, to be cruelly slaine? Did not the Duke of Guise at Vassiacum doe the like, causing his souldiers to enter <note place="margin">ex Insti. Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler.</note> the Church, and with a great slaughter put them all to the sword?</p>
   <p>Againe, is it not notoriously knowne, that in that treacherous massacre in Frāce, An. 1572. there were in Paris, Lyons, Orleance, Rhoane, and other cities, within one moneth, aboue thirtie thousand Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants slaine, in so much that the channels in the streetes ranne with blood? howe then are they not past all shame to obiect these things, and lay them to the charge of the Protestants? And what other cause is there of the treacherous practises of some french papists against their nowe most worthie king, both afore time, and now of
<pb facs="10"/>
late, (but that God in his mercie hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented <note place="margin">Feverdentius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>futed.</note> their mischeifes) but, for that his maiestie pitying the desolation and spoile of so famous a kingdome, hath in his wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome appeased the ciuill warres and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles there, to the great reioycing of all that loue their countrie. Who then were the first authors of those domesticall tumults, but they who secretly worke to haue them renewed, and the honourable edict of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification to be dissolued? Wherefore, I may say here, to this lying fryer, as <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi>
      <note place="margin">Non invenirē quo modo te refellerem, nisi vt, aut iocan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem riderem, aut insanientē dolerem: sed quia te iocari non credo, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des quid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stac. l. 2. c. 38.</note> said to Petilian the Donatist: <hi>If thou shouldest say vnto me, that I am Petilian, howe could I tell to refute thee, but either to deride thy scoffing, or bewaile thy madnesse? but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I thinke you iest not, you know what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</hi> See this shamelesse fryer in charging the protestants with the persecution in France, hath coyned as impudent a lie, as if he should face me downe that write this, to be lying Feuerdentius; which if he should doe, he might be truely iudged to be out of his wits: and so, I thinke he was possessed with a spirit of frenzie and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, when he set his mouth and penne to vtter this slaunder.</p>
   <p>Nowe concerning the affaires of the state in England, this franticke Franciscan
<pb facs="10"/>
hath couched many lies and vntrueths to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither. <note place="margin">Feverdentius refuted.</note> 1. that Catholikes are drawn and forced to come to Church. 2. that they <note place="margin">Protrahunt ad conciones.</note> are put to death, for refusing to come to Church; for simple recusancie is fined onely with a pecuniarie monethly mulct, they are not otherwise violently drawne to the exercises of religion, much lesse suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer death for it. 3. that the bodie of any are cast out to beasts and dogs, is a great vntrueth. But, it is most true that once a popish bishop in Hungarie, did cause a <note place="margin">Ex tomo 2. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vival. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>erm. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han. Gast.</note> godly minister, hanged round with hares, geese, hennes, to be torne in peeces, and woorried of dogs. 4. As vntrue it is that <hi>inaudira supplicia▪ &amp;c.</hi> that punishments ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer heard of are inflicted vpon Catholiks. For it hath beene the auncient and most deserued punishment for traitours, by the law of this land, to be hanged, drawne, and quartered. 5. That any pope-catholiks are put to death, for keeping the auncient religion of their Fathers, is a great blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of our state, as now shall be shewed for the satisfaction of all.</p>
   <p>The Romanists suffer not death for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but for rebellion, not for their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, but for their practising against the state, not for poperie but for treacherie, it
<pb facs="11"/>
may diuersly appeare. 1. Because there <note place="margin">Feuerdentius refuted.</note> are so many thousand knowne papists in the land, and yet fewe of them but such as are seditious and treacherous, are capitally punished. 2. Hereticks that doe swarue from the faith, are by the lawe adiudged to the fire: but, no papists haue yet felt that heate, as protestants did, who were consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the flames of fire, aboue 300. in lesse then fiue yeares space. 3. None of these traiterous papists that haue suffered for their demerits, were indited, arraigned, examined, or condemned for any article of faith, as it may appeare in the seuerall proceedings against them. 4. There is no law in England, to put any papist to death for his conscience: and without lawe our state punisheth none.</p>
   <p>It will be obiected, that the act which maketh the comming in of the Iesuits and Seminarie priests, treason, doth for their profession condemne them. I answere: that this is altogither vntrue: 1. because that this act was but lately made in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison of the whole time of Her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties raigne hitherto, about <hi>Anno regni</hi> 27. when it was found by experience, that the end of their comming ouer into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, was to peruert the obedience of the
<pb facs="11"/>
subiect, and to contriue most vnnaturall <note place="margin">For religion in England.</note> conspiracies against our most gratious Soueraigne. Then was it high time to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straine them by law. 2. If it be obiected that though some of them haue conspired against the prince, yet all of them doe not so: I answer, that they beeing birds all of a feather, and receiuing their direction from the Romish chaire of pestilence, are all to be feared, though perhaps not all alike im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied, yet they are all dangerous, beeing deuoted to execute the Popes will, who is a professed enemy to our state. 3. Their very purpose to alienate the subiects from due obedience, and to reconcile them to a forraine potentate, is, and hath alwaies bin adiudged by the lawes of this land, a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable act: as to be adhęrent or ayding to the kings enemies, such as the pope is, was made treason, <hi>An. Edwardi. 3. 25. c. 2.</hi> But, it cannot be denied that all Iesuits and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries are adhaerent and aiding to the Popes proceeding, who is the cheife ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersarie to our state. 4. All lawes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> ciuill and canon haue condemned all pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctises and conspiracies against the state. <hi>Arcadius</hi> made this lawe, that a conspiracy against the counsellers of the prince (much more against the prince himselfe) though
<pb facs="12"/>
it take not effect, is to be punished with <note place="margin">For religion in England.</note> the sword: which lawe is rehearsed in the <note n="b" place="margin">par. 2. c. 6. q. 1. can. 22.</note> decrees. <note n="c" place="margin">par. 2. c. 11. q. 1. can. 31.</note> Fabian decreed, that he which did lie in waite against the Bishop, should be committed to prison. By the councel of <note n="d" place="margin">Tolet. 12. c. 1.</note> Toletane, he is anathematized which did seeke any occasion to hurt the prince. He is by the <note n="e" place="margin">Constant. concil. sest. 15.</note> Canons adiudged an heretick that did seeke priuily to take away the life, though of a tyrant. This point then, I trust is sufficiently cleared, that not the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, but the papists are the cruell perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of these daies, and the spillers of the blood of the Saints, so that by their barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous crueltie, and vnsatiable blood thirsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, it is no hard matter to iudge of their religion, what it is, and of themselues, by what spirit they are ledde.</p>
   <p>Nowe I proceede to the second cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sance and Antichristian badge, which is treacherie: for, where by open violence, they cannot make a way, they doe attempt by wicked conspiracie to effect their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el desires: wherein they followe the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell and sentence of Lysander, whose say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this was, <hi>Ubi Leonina pellis non sufficit, assuenda Vulpina: That where a Lyons skinne</hi>
      <note place="margin">Plutar.</note>
      <hi>will not serue, a Foxes skinne must eeke it out.</hi> To passe ouer the olde treacherous pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctises
<pb facs="12"/>
of Popes and popelings against <note place="margin">The treacheri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>▪</note> kings and Emperours; <note n="q" place="margin">Caxton. l. 7.</note> as how king Iohn was poysoned by a monke of Swinstead; Gregorie the seauenth hired a russian to murther <note n="b" place="margin">Penno. card.</note> Henrie the fourth. Many trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons and practises attempted by Gregory the ninth against the Emperour Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke the second. Henrie the sixt Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour poysoned in receiuing the sacrament <note place="margin">Fox. p. 30<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> by one fryer Bernard procured by Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens <note place="margin">Avent in annal. lib. 7.</note> the fift. To let passe these and many other such wicked conspiracies contriued in times past, I will descend to the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable accidents of these daies.</p>
   <p>Was not the death of the prince of Auringe procured by the treacherie of papists? and the late king of France, Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the third, by a dominican fryer most treacherously murthered? But no country hath had greater experience of popish se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious practises, then this nation of ours, nor yet any people bound more to thank God, for the deliuerance of their prince from so many dangers, as we are. What shal I speake of <hi>Mortons</hi> conspiracie who was Pope Pius the fifths agent to raise the rebellion of the North? of Saunders at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts in Ireland, of Parry suborned by Gregorie the thirteenth, of Arden, Soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merfield,
<pb facs="13"/>
Lopeze, Babington, Yorke, Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liams, <note place="margin">Their treachery.</note> Stanly, Squire? all which, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, set a worke by that beast of Rome with his accomplices, haue conspired the death of our Soueraigne prince, as is extāt in our Chronicles. Yet God in his mercie hath preserued his annointed, and beene a wal of fire vnto her against al her enemies, &amp; I trust shall still be her protectiō, to be a comfort to his Church for his owne glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious name sake.</p>
   <p>Are these then the Catholiks of these daies, and is this that holy father of Rome, out of whose head such monstrous &amp; hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous practises are forged? and call ye this (ye papists) the holy Catholike Romane faith, that bringeth foorth such vngodly fruits? Euen old heathenish Rome would haue beene ashamed of such dealings. They might haue remembred, howe C. Fabricius, when Pyrrhus phisition sent him word by a letter, that he would, if he thought good, poysō the said Pyrrhus that noble captaine discouered the treason to Pyrrhus, who caused his phisitian to be hanged. This Fabricius had before refused great summes of gold sent him from Pyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhus, of whome Sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ca thus writeth, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iusdem animi fuit, auro non vinci, veneno non</hi>
      <note place="margin">Epist. 120.</note>
      <pb facs="13"/>
      <hi>vincere: He shewed the same minde, both not</hi>
      <note place="margin">Their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie.</note>
      <hi>to be ouercome with gold, nor yet to ouercome with poison.</hi> So vnlike our Romanists now, are to these ancient Romanes. Fabricius would not accept of the physitians offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red seruice to poison his master: the pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings corrupted Lopeze physitian to the Queenes houshold, with great summes to poyson her Maiestie. He reuealed a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracie against an enemie: the other doe not onely conceale, but contriue conspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies against the prince. And he did this to a violent &amp; professed aduersarie, that with all hostilitie had inuaded the confines of Rome, and made a great slaughter of the Romanes before; but, they haue offered this hard measure to a peaceable prince, that till shee was most iustly prouoked by their wrongs, offended none, but onely defended her selfe and her people. And, as this new generation of pretended Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes and Christian Romanists, hath dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated from the auncient Romes, yet bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing idolatrous heathen; so herein they doe farre exceede the barbarous Mahumetans the Turkes. For it is a rare thing amongst them to heare of insurrections, mutins, or rebellions, much lesse of any confederacie of cōiuration against the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> of the prince.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="14"/>
These that hold of Peter and Paul, who, <note place="margin">Their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie.</note> they say, were founders of the Romish Church, how vnlike are they vnto them in their profession and practise? Paul excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed himselfe, because he had vnwittingly called the high priest, <hi>painted wall,</hi> Act. 27. but Papists doe iustifie, not their reuilings onely, but rebellions against the highest powers on earth. Peter saith, <hi>Submit your selues to all manner of ordinance of man, for the Lords sake, as to Kings, to superiours, and vnto other gouernours,</hi> 1. Pet. 3. 13, 14. but these Petrians follow not Peters steppes, but in stead of submitting, seeke to subdue Princes. Much vnlike be they to Dauid, whose heart smote him, <hi>because he had cut off the lappe of Sauls garment:</hi> but their heart is not touched, for seeking to cut off the life of Princes. So that as Agis made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to an euill man, asking, <hi>Quis Sparta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum, optimus, Who was the best of the</hi>
      <note place="margin">Plutar. Apoth.</note>
      <hi>Spartans?</hi> answered, <hi>Qui tui dissimillimus: he that is vnlikest thee:</hi> euen so it may be answered concerning the Romanists, that he is the best Catholike that is most vnlike them.</p>
   <p>But now whereas the Popes champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons doe faile in these disloyall and trayte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous enterprises, there is a third engine
<pb facs="14"/>
which they put in vre, and that is Flatterie <note place="margin">The flatterie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> faire shewes of Romanists.</note> and hypocrisie, when vnder the pretence of friendship and profession of obedience, they worke mischiefe. Like as Ioab ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king shew of friendship to Abner, taking him aside, as if he would speake with him peaceably, smote him that he died. 2. Sam. 3. 27. And as Ismael serued Gedaliah, who eating bread with him as his friend, rose vp and slue him. Ier. 41. 1. As Iudas betrayed our Sauiour with a kisse; so, this is a new popish tricke, that where neither open violence and tyrannie preuaileth, nor secret practising and vnfaithfull trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie taketh place, there by deceitfull sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie they thinke to make a way. Thus was that great slaughter of Protestāts in Frāce, contriued <hi>Ann.</hi> 1572. vnder pretence of solemnizing the marriage betweene the king of Navarre, and the king of France his sister. Thus the Admiral with a great sort of most worthie men beside, whome they could not ouercome by force, were ouerthrowne by faire promises, &amp; a vaine hope and expectation of peace: that, like as Absalōs sheep shearing feast was made a snare, to intrappe his brother Amnon, 2. Sam. 13. 29. so this mariage feast and princely solemnitic, was but a stale to draw
<pb facs="15"/>
the Protestants into their nets. And as An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibal is reported to haue saide thus of the Romane captaines Fabius and Marcellus, whereof the one wrought by policie, the other by force: <hi>Magis se à non pugnante Fabio, quam à pugnante Marcello, sibi me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuere:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Plutar. apoth.</note> that he was more afraid of Fabius not fighting, then of Marcellus fighting: So the sequele of this enterprize shewed, that the Papists are more to be feared fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting then fighting in the field. The like deuice hath beene set afoote in England, when as, to the intent to make her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie and the Counsel secure in that behalfe, they set forth a booke, declaring it to be <note place="margin">Fulk. in epist. Iude, v. 8.</note> vnlawfull to conspire her Highnes death, which yet notwithstanding since the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming forth of that booke, hath beene often attempted, as all the world knoweth, but to their shame and confusion, thankes be giuen to God. And now of late there is broken forth a fire of dissention kindled betweene the Seminarie priests and Iesuits (or Iebusites, if you please, as our learned countriman calleth them, some other E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sauits, <note place="margin">D. Sutliff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> some Suits, all fitter names then that they would be called by: if you will Iuda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sites, for they imitate Iudas, and not Iesus) wherein the priest doth deepely charge
<pb facs="15"/>
the other sect, as principall or accessarie in the conspiracies attempted formerly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst her Maiestie, and doe cleare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues as good and faithfull subiects. The scope of which their inuention is this, that they may obtaine greater libertie, and so may corrupt and peruert the subiect more surely; in that they protest they are good subiects, and seeme to wish well to the State, and condemne the others as turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent practisers against it. We mislike not the words, but we feare their deeds, as Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine well saith, <hi>Non accuso verba, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam vasa preciosa, sed vinum quod illis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinatur ab ebriosis doctoribus. I accuse not the words, as pretious vessells, but the wine that in them is offered to vs, by these drunken tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.</hi> Now seeing I am fallen into menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this matter, I wil briefly lay open the deceit, that is like to maske and lie hidde vnder the vizzard of this dissention. True it is, that these popish sectaries, priests and Iebusites, the Pharisies and Sadduces of these daies, are bitterly fallen out among themselues; neither is it a formall or deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed contention, as some haue imagined, but a very materiall and reall diuision a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them: kindled secretly a long time afore it brake forth vnto these opē flames.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="16"/>
Which beeing espied by the vigilant eye of some worthie persons, was suffered to flame forth, as it doth, that other men see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the same might keepe it from their owne houses, though it burne a while where it began. And here, by the way, I can not passe ouer with silence some for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward affections, that take vpon them to censure the proceedings of the State here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: as though it were not safe that such dangerous stuffe as the Quodlibets and other bookes containe, should not be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished. Wherein (as to me it seemeth) they take a preposterous course. For the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate is not to giue a reason of his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings <note place="margin">The secrets of Magistrates not curiously to be search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> to euery one: neither should we rash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enter into their secrets. The wise man saith, <hi>The heauen in height, and the earth in deepenes, and the Kings heart, can no man search out.</hi> Prou. 25. 3. So that the counsell of the magistrate is as a great depth, that is not by euery one to be sounded. It is saide, that while Alexander was reading a letter of secrets, he suffered his friend Ephestion <note place="margin">Plutar. apoth.</note> to looke on, but when he had done, with his ring he sealed his lippes, by that cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie enioyning him silence And Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticus saith, <hi>If thou hast heard a word, let it die with thee, it will not burst thee.</hi> ch. 19.
<pb facs="16"/>
v. 10. So should we neither be inquisitiue to know, nor knowing, discouer the secrets of State: but, as the Apostle biddeth, we should pray for Kings and magistrats, that God would direct their counsells; not praie or talke our pleasure of them, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice their proceedings. Wherefore, till such time as it shall seeme good to the State, to haue those popish bookes more fully answered, I will set downe some ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertisments for the satisfaction of the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der concerning the foresaid dissentions.</p>
   <p n="1">1. Whereas the Priests doe lay all the blame vpon their fellow Iesuits as authors <note place="margin">Dissention be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene priests and Iesuits.</note> and contriuers of all the treacherous plots against her Maiestie and the state, they can not iustifie themselues. For it is certen that priests as well as Iesuits, haue had their hand in many of the saide conspiracies. Morton, Allin, Hall, Ballard, Gifford, were priests and not Iesuits. The first, the instrument of the commotion in the North: the second, a continuall practiser a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the State: the third, incited Arden and Somerfield: the fourth, Babington &amp; his fellowes: the last, yet aliue, prouoked Savadge, Williams, Yorke, to take in hand their wretched enterprise. It may be that all priests are not treacherously bent, but
<pb facs="17"/>
yet we see, they can not cleare euery one of their profession. They haue beene both very dangerous and are so to be held still. Me thinke then, their fellowes may very well say vnto them, as Ierome saide to Ruffinus, though the case be not alike, <hi>Quid vulneribus tuis prodest, si ego fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro vulneratus? an solacium percussi est a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tnicum socium videre morientem? What doth it helpe thy wounds, if I be wounded? Is it a comfort to him that is smitten to see his friend die with him?</hi> Secondly, they affirme and maintaine this position, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing they doe depend vpon the pope for their faith, yet they may be and are good subiects to the Queenes highnesse: which is a very false ground. 1. Because they gaue the pope preheminencie before the prince, and authoritie to excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate. 2. They allowe appeales to be made to Rome, which is contrarie to the lawes of this land. 3. They make the pope cheife in all spirituall causes; and so doe maime the office of a prince. 4. They count all these martyrs, which haue beene executed for treason, which is a great slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the state. 5. They commend Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall Allē, D. Gifford with others, which were known to be sworne enemies to the
<pb facs="17"/>
state. 6. They giue ayde and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to the Seminaries, and societie of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dasites, Iesuites I would say, which is no good subiects part to foster enemies to their countrie. Wherefore I conclude vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on these reasons, that a professed and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute papist, priest, Iesuite, pope catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, lay, regular or secular, can be no good subiect, though he may be no traytour. And if the Queene had no better subiects then such, her maiestie were ill bestead. And if the common wealth had no better sheild to defend it selfe, it might deceiue them, as Brasidas the Lacedemonian bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wounded through his sheild said, <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente me clypeo vulneratus: I was wounded,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note>
      <hi>my sheild betraying me.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thirdly, whereas a question is mooued by the popish priestes, which of them, or the other faction are likest to the puritans, and it is resolued, that the sect of the Iesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its commeth neerer vnto them, though not so absurd in doctrine, nor yet so mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious against either Church or common wealth: neither yet are they such grosse heads, but much finer witts then the puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans: for these are their owne words. Let it here be considered, that if by the name of puritans, they did vnderstand such buisie
<pb facs="18"/>
factious heads, as beeing malecontents, of a couetous and greedie minde, seeke the hauocke and spoile of the Church, not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, nor in trueth, touched with any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science of religion, such as Martin Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prelate might seeme to be, we would not greatly stand with them for this compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. For such a puritan may proue a good stocke to graffe a papist in, as that vile Hacket that iustly suffred for his villanies, and did leape, as it is reported, out of such a puritans skinne into a papists hide. But whereas vnder this scandalous name of puritans, they doe gall and wound the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit <note place="margin">Puritans better subiects then papists.</note> of many worthy ministers of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell as Caluin, Beza, and the preachers of Scotland, and diuers amongst vs, who o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise, setting aside their opinion of some externall vsages of the Church, are very profitable labourers, and most loyall subiects: betweene these and the best lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the papists, for true religion and sound diuinitie, and faithfull obedience, &amp; loue to their prince, there is no compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son at all. First, these whome they vpbraid with the name of puritans, do hold sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all points of religion, and articles of the protestants faith, throughout, excepting onely concerning externall matters of
<pb facs="18"/>
discipline and ceremonies, which belong rather to the pollicie of the Church, then to faith and doctrine. And therefore, they admitting of no absurd point of poperie, are by many degrees to be preferred, and I doubt not, but are better liked of the state, 2. Those preachers and ministers of the Gospell, neuer yet attempted any thing against the life of their prince, as priests and Iesuits haue done; neither (doe I trust) shall it euer be seene. They neuer conspired the death of Queene Marie, as these haue done of Queene Elizabeth. Wherefore it is a great slāder of thē to say, they seeke to pull downe kings &amp; princes. 3. These admitte of no forraine poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate to haue power in matters ecclesiastical as the popish priests doe, wherein they curbe the authoritie of princes. 4. They perswade to obedience to their prince, and thankefulnesse to God, for the puritie of religion professed among them. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creepe in corners to seduce and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert the subiects from the faith, and so cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently from due obedience to their prince. 5. They communicate with the assemblies of the Church, in the worde, praiers, and Sacraments: the Romanists re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse so to doe, and disswade whome they
<pb facs="19"/>
may from our Church assemblies. 6. They both in their publike and priuate praiers, doe lift vp their hands for the life of our Soueraigne, and the continuance of her state; of popish priests it is to be doubted. For, whome the pope their head curseth, how dare they blesse? &amp; whome he would haue cutte off, is it like they desire to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue? 7. They haue beene meanes to detect the conspiracie of the common ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersarie, and are readie with all their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to do it: popish priests vse not to reueale but to conceale them. 8. They are bound by oath to acknoweledge the princes su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame authoritie in all causes, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all forraine iurisdiction: popish priests will take no such oath. 9. They acknowledge a Church here in England, and themselues to be members of it; the popes priestes count vs no Church, but <note place="margin">Gifford praefa. 2, impudently &amp; traiterously saith, that in England, haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fis est regio di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ademat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> hold all protestants heretickes, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, her Maiestie (vnder whose autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, we professe the Gospell, which they call heresie) in that number, and out of the Church. 10. Those whome they call pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan ministers, haue both by preaching and writing, impugned the common ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersarie, as much as any, and therin haue done God good seruice in his Church.
<pb facs="19"/>
And this is the cause, if the trueth were knowne, why popish priests haue such a spite at them, because they stand so much in their waie, staying the spreading of their infection, by the contrarie exposition of sound doctrine. And as for <hi>grossum caput</hi> and his fellowe, let them seeke him among themselues. I doubt not, but they, whome they most scorne of the protestants, are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to set foorth from them those, which either by writing or conference shall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter the proudest priest or Iebusite. But in truth we disdaine this comparison, that the best popish priest should match with the worst protestant preacher, either for doctrine or obedience to his prince. Let them, the priestes and the Iebusites measure themselues with themselues, and compare themselues with themselues, as the Apostle saith of the false teachers of Corinth; <hi>2. Cor. 10. 12.</hi> We dare not make our selues of the number, nor compare our selues with them. But, as Ierome saith of the dialogue of Origen and Valentini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, so we of this contention betweene these <note place="margin">Apolog 2. ad. vers. Ruffin.</note> popelings, <hi>In quo duos Andabatas inter se digladiātes spectasse mihi videor: Me thought I see two blinde sword-plaiers play togither.</hi>
 The fourth &amp; last consideration is the
<pb facs="20"/>
scope &amp; end of these popish books, which is to insinuate themselues to the State, and to perswade a toleration of religion, which <note place="margin">A toleration of popery dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</note> I trust, they shall neuer obtaine, neither is it conuenient they should vpon these rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons.</p>
   <p n="1">1. It were not for her maiesties safetie; for if they haue practised so against her Highnesse person, in the time of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint, what will they doe hauing further libertie?</p>
   <p n="2">2. It were not for her Maiesties ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, that hauing held a constant course in religion these 44. yeares, should in her sacred old age, listen to any such motion.</p>
   <p n="3">3. It would be an offence to all other protestant princes, that the famous church and common wealth of England should giue such an example.</p>
   <p n="4">4. It would breed a confusion and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietnes in the land, and tend to the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe and abrogation of diuers profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble lawes alreadie made against popish practises and the masse.</p>
   <p n="5">5. It would be an offence to God, that a Christian prince should suffer idolaters, such as Romanists are, to exercise their i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous worship freely. Iaacob would not suffer it to be done in his house, but
<pb facs="20"/>
buried all the images vnder an oake, <hi>Gen. 35. 5.</hi> much lesse is it to be permitted in a kingdome. And Eliah well said, <hi>1. Kings, 18. 21. How long will ye hàlt betweene two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions? if the Lord be God follow him: but if Baal be, then goe after him.</hi> So to admit two contrarie religions, were to halt betweene two opinions.</p>
   <p n="6">6. The pope in none of his territories nor where he hath absolute iurisdiction, doeth graunt any libertie to protestants, but tolerateth rather Iewes and Turkes: neither is it reason that his popelings should receiue any such toleration.</p>
   <p n="7">7. It would be a meanes to obdurate and harden papists in their superstition, whereas I trust, there may be hope of thē, so many as God shall call to returne to the Gospell.</p>
   <p n="8">8. Her Maiestie hath the example of the good kings of Iudah, for her warrant: they are commended which did expell all contrarie worshipps; as Asa because he brake downe the altars and images of strange Gods, <hi>2. Chro. 14. 3.</hi> Iehosaphat for remoouing the high places and groues, <hi>2. Chro. 17. 6.</hi> Iosias for putting downe the Chemarims that were idolatrous priests, <hi>2. King. 23. 5.</hi> Whereas the scripture no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb facs="21"/>
such kings as did not take away the high places, as Iehoash, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 12. 3. and Azariah, 2. <hi>Kings.</hi> 15. 4.</p>
   <p n="9">9. Her Highnes hath a president from vertuous and blessed prince Edward 6. her Maiesties brother, who notwithstanding the request of Charles the Emperour, and the instance of Bishop Cranmer, and B. Ridley, would not consent to graunt to his sister the ladie Marie, to haue masse in her house. <hi>Fox. p.</hi> 1295. <hi>edition</hi> 1583.</p>
   <p n="10">10. Lastly, I will propound the most worthie example of the Emperour Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinian, that when the citie of Rome sent <note place="margin">Ambros. in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap> Valentin.</note> vnto him to restore the rytes of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the idolls, and all the consistorie being Christians perswaded therunto: the Emperour alone, being a yong man, gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said them, alleadging the example of his brother Gratian; <hi>Quod pius frater eripuit, quo modo à me putatis esse reddendum, cum in co relligio laedatur, &amp; frater: à quo se nol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let pietate superari? How can I restore that which my brother tooke away? for both reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion should receiue hurt, and my brother, of whome he would not be ouercome in religion. Postulet parens Roma alia quaecunque desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deret: Let my mother,</hi> saith he, <hi>aske any thing else that she please:</hi> but, in this request he
<pb facs="21"/>
would not yeelde. The like constancie and firme resolution, thankes be to God, hath well appeared in her Maiestie. And so I conclude with that saying of Ambrose to Valentinian, with whome certaine dealt to haue their altars restored: <hi>Sed hac siiam sublata non essent, auferenda tuo imperio com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probarem.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Epist. 30. ad Valentinian.</note>
      <hi>But, if they were not alreadie ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, I would prooue that they ought to be remooued by your authoritie: much lesse being now abolished, is it fit to haue them restored.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And to these Romanists, sacrificing priests, and others, I wish that either they would returne home againe to vs, and that God would giue them repentance, that they may know the truth, and that they come to amendment out of the snare of the deuil, of whom they are takē at his wil, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> S. Paul saith, 2. Tim. 2. 26. or, if they be setled and frozen in their dregs, that they would keepe them where they are, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the Pope from whēce they come, and trouble no more the peace of our Church. And as Flaminius said to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiui, which inuaded their neighbours, <hi>Ne</hi>
      <note place="margin">Plutar. Ròm. apotheg.</note>
      <hi>instar testudinum, prolato extra testam capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, se periculo exponerent: least like the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyse, they thrusting their head beyond the shell, should offer themselues to daunger.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>