<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PER∣oracion vnto the gentle reder, with a shorte rehersall of the Actes doon.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114184_Bo1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09164</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19476.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114184</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PER∣oracion vnto the gentle reder, with a shorte rehersall of the Actes doon.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The expedicion into Scotla [n] de of the most woorthely fortunate prince Edward, Duke of Soomerset : vncle vnto our most noble souereign lord ye ki [n] ges Maiestie Edvvard the. VI. goouernour of hys hyghnes persone, and protectour of hys graces realmes, dominions &amp; and subiectes: made in the first yere of his Maiesties most prosperous reign, and set out by way of diarie, by W. Patten Londoner</title>
                 <author>Patten, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Grafton, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>308 pages, 3 maps, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="150"/>
   <head>A PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oracion vnto the gentle reder, with a shorte rehersall of the Actes doon.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> Haue thus absol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued my boke, but neyther w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> suche spede, as perchaū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce it had bene the office of hym, that woold take vpō hym to wryte of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nor as the dignitie of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument required publicacion. For well it may be thought, a man with meane diligēce, that had ben forth in no parte of the viage might in this space haue learned and written, as muche by enquirie at home. And sith y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
      <pb facs="150"/>
pour of tyme is in eche case so great, as thinges indifferently good, by choyse of oportunitie are made muche comendable, &amp; agayn by cumming out of sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, maye muche be disgraced: Right small then maye I take my meryt to be, that cum nowe so intempestiuely to tell y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> tale, whearof al mens eares are ful of a four mooneths before. Yet for excuse of my slacknes (as who woolde not be blameles?) trustynge that my playne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession maye the rather mooue you too take thinges too the better: I haue thoughte it best, to render you the verye cause thearof: whiche is, that after I hadde sum what entred intoo thys busynes. And
<pb facs="151"/>
thearby compeld to consyder y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> precise obseruaunce of dedes, wordes, and in a maner of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stures: and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> diligēt markinge of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> situaciō of tounes, castels and churches, of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lieng of hils playns and feldes, of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> course of ryuers, of respect of wyndes and of infinite such other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that oughte fyrst too haue bene made thear, while they wear a doynge, &amp; whyle a man had bene at them (the which in dede I had not so perfitly writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten in my notes, and thearfore dryuen to stresse my memorie y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> more for callinge the same too mynd agayn) And here w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> regar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> greate hede that ought to be had in rehersall of circū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staunces, and placinge of thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, accordingly in writing as
<pb facs="151"/>
they wear done, seen or hard: I foūd the enterprise a great dele more weyghtie, then the slēder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of my wit was able quikly to pas with. Howbeit, whē vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon deper consideraūce I pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered with my self, what a thīg it was to make ony monument in this so prosperous a commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie, wherof the Gouernours are so absolutely wise, &amp; whear in an infinitie number of men soo fynely wytted and so pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly learned are besyde: I rather regarded the counsell of the wyse poet <hi>Horace,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Inde Art. Poet.</hi>
      </note> whoo wils a man to kepe his writin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in his handes nine yere, (meaning a good while for cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reccion) then hadde any hast of publicatiō, whearby at ones I shold lose my libertie of amēd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb facs="152"/>
Which libertie though after, I mought haue neuer so well, yet because it is nothinge so commēdable to mend a faut as to make no faut, I woolde gladly before haue had the ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to loke, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the thyng might haue past as faultes from me, as my diligēce could haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de it. And surely had it not ben more for aūswering the expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion of sum men of honour, whoo knew I was in hand w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the matter, and who els perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture might haue douted my diligence, then it was for myne own desyre, to haue my doings soon to cūme abrode, I woold haue taken a better breath ear they had cum out yet. But sins the chaūce is cast, &amp; the woord thus vttred cannot be called a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayn,
<pb facs="152"/>
whearby I haue ieoper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> your .iii. houres reding to make you cēsour of my three moneths wryting: Iudge ye I pray you (as ye maye) with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and conster my meanyng to the best. My nede, I knowe is much to pray, for I am not so foolysh too thinke my self so wise, that with a text al fautles I can driue foorthe so longe a proces. But as I, for the tyme haue endeuoured to say, rather as wel as I can, then aswell as can be, soo shall thear be for me libertie too all men too wryte, what els they can vtter, eyther foorther or better: which if thei do, I shal with all my hart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum then as benign a reder to thē, as I woold wish you now to be here to me.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="153"/>¶To the entent now, I woold quite from cumber of enquirie or question, suche as haply woold wyt, what a do I had in the armie, or how I hadde ony knowlege of that I haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: I haue thought it curtesie not to be daungerous to shew, that it pleased my very good lord, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> erle of Warwyke, Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaūt of the host (who thearby had pour to make officers) too make me one of the Iudges of the Marshalsey: as Master William Cycyl, now master of the Requestes, with my lorde Protectours grace was the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: whearby we both, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge bounde soo straightly in daies of trauel to ordre of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che: nor oother while, but when we sat in Courte, too any great
<pb facs="153"/>
affayres, had libertie to ride, to see things that wear doon, and leysure too note occurrences y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> came: The which thing (as it chaunced) we booth dyd, but so far from appoyntmēt betwene vs. As neyther was wyting of others doing, tyll sumwhat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our departure homeward. Mary, since my cūming home indede, his gētilnes being such as too communicate his notes with me (I haue I cōfes) bene thearby, bothe muche a certey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in many thinges I douted. And sumwhat remembred of y<seg rend="sup">t</seg>, which els I mought hap to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue forgotten</p>
   <p>¶But now, forasmuch as it hath pleased the moste benign goodnes of God, so fauorably to ayd vs in these our affaires,
<pb facs="154"/>
and so moch to tender the equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of our cause, as by hys my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister, and our hed in this iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney my lord Protectours gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, we haue tourned oure ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies entents for destruccion of vs, vnto theyr own confusion: And fyrst ouerturned of thear holdes, Dunglas, Thornton, Anderwyke, and Annā church, ouercummē then with the half of their number .xxxii.M: slain xv.M.iii.C: maymed .ii.M: ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken .xv.C: burned, lyeth &amp; kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>korne (as more of their tounes els we mought, if our Chieftaī had bene as willing, as our ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitayns wear redy) wun y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> best of their nauie, and burnt the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sidue: wun from thē, and kepe in the mids of their londe saint Coomes Ins, and Broughty
<pb facs="154"/>
crak, and thearby (but by oure leaue) kepe thē from their hole entercours of merchaūtes: wū also &amp; kepe the Castle of Mylk and Hume castle: wun of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naūce in their fortes, and at the feld aboue .lxxx. peces: Bylded Rokesborow castle, &amp; Aymouth and gayned vnto the kynges Maiesties obedience, al Tyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale and their Marches: All this in so short a time, as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in .xxv. dayes: with soo small a losse of oure syde in all the hole viage, as vnder the numbre of lx. persons: and that in this the fyrst yere of our kynges Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties dominion &amp; rule: whear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, according vnto his singuler towardenes, els euident, we may well conceyue an assured hope, hys hyghnes too shall
<pb facs="155"/>
haue a most happie reygn, and with a (Gods grace) a longe: I woold wyshe and exhort, that ye, whiche wear not theare (for thoughe ye wear far from ony daunger of the los, yet can ye not be but full parteners of the winnynge) shoolde effectually with vs (accordynge as we all haue cause) gyue &amp; wishe, firste glorie and prays vnto God, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bediēce and victorie to our so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraygn, honour and thankes vnto our Protectour and coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellours, woorship to our chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualrie, commendaciō vnto the rest that wear out, and a better mynd vnto our enemies. And I, trustyng vnto the benigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of your gentle acceptaunce, whoo of this woorke shall hap to
<pb facs="155"/>
be Reder, with such indifferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of request touching the same as <hi>Horace</hi> made to hys welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued frēd <hi>Numicius,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Epist. i.</hi>
      </note> shal thus take my leaue of you.</p>
   <q>
      <l>Viue Vale: si quid nouisti recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us istis,</l>
      <l>Candidus imperti: si non his vte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te mecum.</l>
   </q>
   <p>Out of the Parsonage of s. Mary hill in London, this xxviii. of Ianuary. 1548.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>