<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHOR TO THE DEVOVT READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114412_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11958</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4603</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114412</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHOR TO THE DEVOVT READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A manuall of spirituall exercises</title>
                 <author>Capilla, Andrés</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Boscard, Charles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Heigham, John (Roger)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>286, 12 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>THE AVTHOR TO THE DEVOVT READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F those thinges which are necessary vnto the perfection of a Christian life, the first and chiefest is, the continuall consideration and remembrance of God and his holy commandements. For this is a most stronge bridle to restraine our heartes that they follow not their inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate appetites, and a most effectuall remedy, to conserue the estate both of the inward and outward man. This is a most stronge buckler to receue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell
<pb n="7" facs="4"/> the dartes of all our enemies. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer this is an admirable meanes that God may alwaies worke in vs and heape vp his giftes and graces in our soules. For although God is as it were a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine springe or fountaine, incessantly flowinge, and as much as is of his parte most ready to deriue vnto vs the waters of his grace, wherunto he inuiteth all men: yet it is necessary, we repaire and approach vnto him, that we way re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceue them. And hereupon the Prophet Dauid saith. <hi>(Psal.</hi> 33.) Come vnto him and be illuminated, and your faces shall not be confounded. And in another place speakinge of the continuall remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce he had of God. My eyes, saith he, are alwaies vpon our Lord, because he will pull my feete out of the snare. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, he saith. I had God alwayes in my sight because he is at my right hand that I be not moued Where the Glosse of Cassiodorus saith: By declaring what he himselfe did, he geueth vs instruction
<pb n="8" facs="5"/> what wee ought to doe. For he that all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies beholdeth God with the eye of his minde, can in no sorte auerte his minde vnto sinne. And Saint Gregory Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zene saith: that the remembrance of God ought to be so continuall in vs, that we should not more often drawe our breath, then remember God: and this continuall remembrāce of God he saith, expelleth all sadnes from our soules, and that with meruailous much ioye and cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation. Which the princely Prophet Dauid confirmeth saying: my soule re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused to be comforted (that is to say, in the thinges of this present life) I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred God, and was comforted. S. Bernard saith. As there is no moment wherin a man doth not vse and enioye the goodnes and mercie of God, so ought there to be no momēt wherin we should not haue him present in our minde Saint Gregory the Pope exhorteth vs, that we continually haue him in our memory, by whō our memory was made. And in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
<pb n="9" facs="5"/> place declaring how profitable this cōtinuall memory of God is, he saith. No euill spirit can preuaile in that heart, which is continually occupied in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēbrance of God. Saint Ambrose admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisheth vs, that whether we eate or drinke or whatsoeuer we doe, we should alwaies expresse Christ, thinke of Christ, pray vnto Christ, speake with Christ inwardly in our hartes, and that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer depart out of our mouth. S. Ierome saith. As a souldier ought neuer to a lay away his armour in battaile: So euery Christian ought in euery place to arme himselfe with praier. When he goeth forth he should arme himself with prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, when he returneth home, prayer should be the first thinge he should doe.</p>
   <p>This continuall consideration and remembrance of God, may be done chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie two manner of wayes, either by tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge some certaine and set considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our owne, chosinge to meditate therof, or to take occasion by those thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="10" facs="6"/> which occurre to our sight, or those businesses we haue in hande, to lifte vpp our hearts vnto God. The former way is harder and requireth a man very well practised in the recollection of himselfe: it requireth also a minde quiet and free from all businesses, and therfore is more proper for Religious and solitarie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons.</p>
   <p>The other is easier, because, besides the varietie wherewith our nature is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted, and tediousnes taken awaie, those thinges wee see with our eyes, and those businesses wee haue in hande, doe easily stirre vp and incite our hearts vnto God, being a little inured there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. Which kinde of exercise, men may vse though neuer so much occupied and employed in externall affaires. And her-unto Saint Paule the Apostle exhorteth all faithfull people, in his Epistle to the Corinthians in these wordes. Speakinge to your selues in Psalmes, Hymnes and spirituall Canticles, singinge in your
<pb n="11" facs="6"/> hearts to our Lord, geuinge thankes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes for all thinges to our God and Father, in the name of our Lord Iesus Christ.</p>
   <p>I therfore, that I might promote this holy exercise as much as in mee lyeth, haue thought it a matter worth the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to write this Manuall, wherin I might set downe a methode, how out of all things wee doe or see, wee may take occasion to lifte vp our hearts to God, either by some shorte sentence of holie Scripture which directly concerneth the presēt matter, or by some Consideration or Thankesgiuing, or Confusion, or Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, or Oblation. Not that wee tye the readers to exercise them all at once: but that euery one in so great varietie of matter, may take that he shall thinke most conuenient for his condition and spirit. Or if besides these which are here sett downe (for wee cannot speake of all in particuler) any other shall offer it selfe to his minde, he may the better
<pb n="12" facs="7"/> know how to supplie it to his vse.</p>
   <p>This Manuall wee haue not written, ōly to be read &amp; perused, for that were a matter of small profit, but that the thinges therein contayned might be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercised and put in practise, which who so shall doe and continue therin a fewe dayes: I doubt not but he shal receiue in his soule such noble fruite, that he will thinke all his labour and paines taken therin, wonderfull well bestowed, and he shall performe that spiritually which was commaunded the priests in the olde law, namely that they should feede and nourish with wodd, the fire which was to burne continually before the Arke of the Couenāt, for by this meanes he shal conserue and keepe in himselfe, the fire of deuotion and loue of God, which ought continually to burne in our heart, which is the Altar whereon wee should offerr the spirituall sacrifices of holie thoughtes and desires. Almightie God graunt grace vnto all faithfull people of
<pb n="13" facs="7"/> Christ, that they minde him in all their workes, and in all thinges fulfill his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie will. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>