<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIP∣FVL AND MY CHISTIAN FRIEND MASTER Valentine Knightly, Esquire, one of her Maiesties Iusti∣ces of peace in Northampton shiere.</title>
           <author>Perkins, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114458_Fr4_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09339</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19646</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114458</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIP∣FVL AND MY CHISTIAN FRIEND MASTER Valentine Knightly, Esquire, one of her Maiesties Iusti∣ces of peace in Northampton shiere.</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A golden chaine: or The description of theologie : containing the order of the causes of saluation and damnation, according to Gods word. A view whereof is to be seene in the table annexed. Hereunto is adioyned the order which M. Theodore Beza vsed in comforting afflicted consciences</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Jackson (Jacson), Ralph 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Thomas 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Porter, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 184, 14, 185-524, 4, 525-570, 2, 571-684, 2, 685-711, 3, 713-771, 3, 773-830, 4, 831-906, 4, 907-1057, 1 page, 7 leavesof plates, tables, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="315"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FVL AND MY CHISTIAN FRIEND MASTER Valentine Knightly, Esquire, one of her Maiesties Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of peace in Northampton shiere.</head>
   <p>SIr, I pray you consider with me an especiall point of Gods word, carefully to be waied: it is this,<note n="a" place="margin">
         <p>
            <hi>Mat. 25. 1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11,12.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>Luk. 13. 24.</hi>
         </p>
      </note>
      <hi>Many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors of Christ, in the day of grace, perswade themselues that they are in the estate of grace; and so the true Church esteemeth of them too: yet when the day of grace is past, they contrariwise shall finde themselues to be in the estate of dā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation remedilesse.</hi>
      <note place="margin">A caueat to all protestants, of what estate or condition soe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</note> A dolefull case, yet a most resolute trueth, and the reason is plaine. Men that liue in the Church are greatly annoyed with a fearefull securite and deadnes of heart; by which it comes to passe that they thinke it enough to make a common protestation of the faith, not once in all their life times, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining themselues whether they be in the estate of grace before the eternall God or not.<note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>2. Cor. 13. 5. Psal. 119.59</hi>
      </note> And indeede it is a grace peculiar to the man Elect to trie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe whether he be in the estate of grace or not.</p>
   <p>The further opening of the trueth of this point, as also the daunger of it, I haue enterprised in this treatise; which I am willing to bestow on you, both for the profession of the faith, which you make, as also for that Christian friendship, you haue shewed to me. Accept of it I pray you and vse it for your edification.<note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>Act. 20. 32.</hi>
      </note> Thus I commend you to God, and to the word of his grace, that is able to builde you vp further and giue you an inheritance among them which are sanctified.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From Cambridge <date>this 24. of Nouember. 1589.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Worships to command, <hi>William Perkins.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>