<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE STATE OF THE QVESTION handled in this Booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114160_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09106</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19412</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114160</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE STATE OF THE QVESTION handled in this Booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A quiet and sober reckoning vvith M. Thomas Morton : somewhat set in choler by his aduersary P.R. concerning certaine imputations of wilfull falsities obiected to the said T.M. in a treatise of P.R. intituled Of mitigation, some part wherof he hath lately attempted to answere in a large preamble to a more ample reioynder promised by him. But heere in the meane space the said imputations are iustified, and confirmed, &amp; with much increase of new vntruthes on his part returned vpon him againe: so as finally the reckoning being made, the verdict of the Angell, interpreted by Daniel, is verified of him. There is also adioyned a peece of a reckoning with Syr Edward Cooke, now L. Chief Iustice of the Co [m] mon Pleas, about a nihil dicit, &amp; some other points vttered by him in two late preambles, to his sixt and seauenth partes of Reports</title>
                 <author>Parsons, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40, 688, 16 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE STATE OF THE QVESTION handled in this Booke.</head>
   <p>MAISTER <hi>Thomas Morton</hi> vpon the yeare 1606. tooke vpon him to write a malicious <hi>Dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>erie</hi> against Catholicks, and their doctrine about Rebellion presently vpon the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-treason: and the Pamphlet was soone after confuted and retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vpon himselfe by the <hi>Moderate Answerer:</hi> he replyed with a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course intituled, <hi>A full Satisfaction:</hi> adding therunto another Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise against <hi>Equiuocation.</hi> To this opposed himselfe P. R. Author of the Treatise tending to <hi>Mitigation:</hi> and handled in the same both the one and other subiect, charging him further with many foule faultes of witting falsehood; wherunto <hi>M. Morton</hi> hath exhibited now lastly a large new <hi>Preamble,</hi> with promise of another booke to follow in time, that is to say, he hath presented a great head with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a body; and this with no small signes of extraordinary impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</p>
   <p>For pacifying wherof P. R. hath takē the paines to reuiew o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>er againe the accompts, and findeth him farre more faultie then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. For that in lieu of clearing old debts, he contracteth new, and in excusing former falsities, he multiplieth many other. So as now,</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>The chiefe question commeth to be,</head>
      <p>Whether <hi>M. Mort.</hi> (in the cause he defendeth) can write true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or no: &amp; whether his falshood therin be volūtary or necessarie, or rather both: that is to say, voluntary in respect of himselfe, that might haue omitted them: and nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ssarie in regard of his cause, that could not be defended without them<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> and consequently in different respects, both voluntary and necessary. In which point <hi>M. Morton</hi> holdeth the negatiue, I the affirmatiue. The Reader shall see the proofes of both sides.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>