<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN
ADVERTISEMENT.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114269_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07267</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17662</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114269</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN
ADVERTISEMENT.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The history of Levvis the eleuenth : VVith the most memorable accidents which happened in Europe during the two and twenty yeares of his raigne. Enricht with many obseruations which serue as commentaries. Diuided into eleuen bookes. Written in French by P. Mathieu historiographer to the French King. And translated into English by Edvv: Grimeston Sergeant at Armes</title>
                 <author>Matthieu, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 232, that is 236, 212, 113-131, 13 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>AN
ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough that all Bookes which are presented vnto the
King, proceed not from those excellent pens which haue taken
life vnder his raigne, to aduance the French eloquence to the
height of glory, no more then all Statues which were dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
to <hi>Apollo,</hi> in Creet, Rhodes and Cypres, were not made by
the hands of <hi>Zeuxis</hi> or of <hi>Phidias,</hi> nor the wine which
was offered to <hi>Iupiter,</hi> in his sacrifice, did not alwaies come
out of the cup, nor grew in those Vines which he desired: yet
this History, being but in her Infancy, hath merited the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
of his iudgement, and of the greatest of his Court, who haue taken delight to
see, as in an Astro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ab, the rising and fall of those which are on earth as the Sunne is
in Heauen. This is the rampier wherein shee fortifies her selfe against so many af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts
wherewith she hath been threatned, for curious spirits are not pleased with all
kinds of writing, no more then the Planets feed vpon all sorts of vapours.</p>
   <p>The most difficult to please will obiect against her, and mee thinkes I vnderstand
these words proceeding out of their mouthes, or from their thoughts: why the History
of <hi>Lewis</hi> the eleuenth more then of any other? can they giue vs a better then that of
<hi>Philip de Commines?</hi> to all these exceptions she hath but one answere.</p>
   <q>
      <l>What though I giue not all humors content?</l>
      <l>A worke that's great cannot please eu'ry taster:</l>
      <l>But of so many tasts, so different,</l>
      <l>Let it suffice me that it likes my Master.</l>
   </q>
   <p>I haue not affected in this worke the glory of mine owne wit, I haue contented my
selfe with that of obedience. <hi>I</hi> haue made it such as you see it, his commandement car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
his reasons, and staies the curiositie of such as desires others. This great Prince,
who entertained himselfe and slept sometimes vpon the actions of this King, as <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi>
did vpon those of <hi>Achilles,</hi> and who made no lesse esteeme of <hi>Phil. de Com.</hi>
then the Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> the fift had done, would haue his History beautified and il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lustrated
in the same manner that I present it vnto you, to the end that being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
with his, Iudgement might make the difference, and that of two they might
frame a liuely Image of that which might serue for the conduct of a Prince. The
brightnes of truth appeares by the opposition of her contrary, and shadowes giue grace
to liuely coulours, examples are of more force then precepts. Cowards instruct the
Couragious, and lyars make Men speake the truth. He that turnes from vice en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters
<pb facs="4"/>
vertue. <hi>Ismenias</hi> mingled both good and bad Flute-players together, to
the end that the diuersitie of their musick might be a lesson to imitate the one and
leaue the other, and that comparison might make the difference. There is nothing so
difficult as to paralel Princes; if there be any conformitie in their fortunes, it is found
in their vertues, if they haue attained to one end, it hath not been by the same course,
and therefore they say there are a hundreth yeares required to breed a great Prince
or a great Captaine. <hi>Lewis</hi> hath carried, and <hi>Henry</hi> doth yet carry the glorious
Title of the most renowned and magnanimous Princes of their ages: but they haue
not purchased it by the selfe same meanes, the difference hath beene great in their
humours, and in their kinde of gouernement: Both had one kinde of beginning, the
one of the house of Valois, the other of that of Bourbon, two branches of S. <hi>Lewis.</hi>
There was some conformitie in their first fortunes; being both retired from Court,
and both instructed in patience in the schoole of necessitie: The beginning of their
reignes had some resemblance, for both had seene a great and mighty faction raised
against them, vnder two goodly pretexts, the one of the Common-weale, the other of
Religion: both haue been in paine to expell forraine enemies, to pacifie domestique, and
to diuide their humors; but what the one hath done by policie and force, the other
hath effected by the iustnes of his armes, and the mildnes of his clemencie. Both were
troubled to moderate those spirits, which had yet a feeling of ciuill diuisions: they
haue tried the infidelitie of their seruants, and haue made themselues to bee feared
and redoubted; but the one hath maintained the respect of his Maiestie by feare and
seueritie, and the other by wisedome and loue. The raigne of the one was a Sea of
sto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mes and tempest, the other a calme, milde, and cleare hauen. <hi>Lewis</hi> of much did
little, <hi>Henry</hi> of nothing did wonders; <hi>Lewis</hi> thrust himselfe into apparant dangers
to reap doubtfull fruits, <hi>Henry</hi> was neuer seene in any place but fortunate and vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious
<hi>Lewis</hi> medled with all things and would see and know all; <hi>Henry</hi> is a
Prince of all howers and for all affaires: <hi>Lewis</hi> feared the fat of his people, <hi>Henry</hi>
beleeues that the felicitie of the subiect is the glory of the Prince. <hi>Lewis</hi> the eleuenth
had royall vertues, but they were not all pure; his wisedome had a touch of oun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing,
his iustice of seueritie, his valour of rashnes, his clemencie of feare, his liberaliti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of
profusion, and his pietie of dissimulation: <hi>Henry</hi> takes delight to be what he appeares,
and to appeare what he is, wise and fore-seeing without deceit, iust without rigor, cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious
without feare or indiscretion, courteous, milde, magnanimous without pusil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanimitie,
liber all with iudgement, and religious without hypocrisie.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Lewis</hi> the eleuenth contemned the Sciences, and learning, <hi>Henry</hi> fauours them,
makes choise of the best wits to restore the exercises, peoples the Colledges, and labors
to make the famous Academies of France to flourish, and the Vniuersitie of Paris, the
eldest daughter of Kings, the Queene of the Academies of Christendome. <hi>Lewis</hi> was
blamed for the little care he had in the breeding, and institution of his son: <hi>Henry</hi>
considering how much it doth imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rt that the generous inclinations of my Lord the
Dauphin, should be seconded with good instruction, hath committed the care to a
Noble-man, which abounds in wisedome, generositie, experience and fidelitie for the
greatnes of that charge. Hee doth alwaies hold the minde of this Prince elleuated to
things worthy of his birth and courage. France is bound vnto the King, who could
make so good a choice; the election proues the dignitie of the person chosen, makes the
excellencie of the choosers iudgement to bee seene, and shewes that heauen hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spired
with him to make so happy an accord of two such different ages. <hi>Lewis</hi> would
not suffer his sonne to vnderstand aboue two words of Latin: <hi>Henry</hi> wils that his
<pb facs="4"/>
deare sonne should haue as much knowledge as a Prince ought to haue; he causeth his
yonger yeeres to be instructed in learning, by the diligence of a great and excellent
wit, who carefully and indiciously doth shew him vvhat he should know, and vvhat he
should be ignorant of: he giues him the whole vvorld for a lesson; for companions, the
study of Emperors and Kings; for a table, the image of glory; for Philosophy, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
of humors and manners, and entertaining him sweetly in the varietie of Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
vvhich is onely the Booke of Kings, frames his mind to a knowledge vvhich should
shew it selfe more by actions then by discourse: for as he himselfe saies,
<q>
         <l>For one that's not wedded to Arts, nor of them is vnknowing,</l>
         <l>Tis skill enough to render them such honor as is owing.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Lewis</hi> had more care then his predecessors to fortefie his frontiers, and forts. <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>
hath made great workes for the beautifying of his royall houses, and for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie
of his people he makes his forts vnexpugnable, and hath freed his affaires
from the outrages and violence of necessitie. <hi>Lewis</hi> was inconstant in his resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
and did sometime impaire them by change. <hi>Henry</hi> in his greatest affaires saies
nothing but vvhat he does, and doth nothing without premeditation, calling vppon
God in his thoughts. That vvhich is framed in his minde remaines firme. He hath
so much foresight as he preuents all impediments, and hath so great power as nothing
is impossible vnto him. <hi>Lewis</hi> loued a country ruined rather then lost, <hi>Henry,</hi> giuen
from heauen for the generall good of the earth, hath saued, enricht and preserued
the townes, which by the iustice of his armes he might haue spoiled and ruined. <hi>Lewis</hi>
neuer left offences vnpunished, <hi>Henry</hi> hath lost no part of his memory but iniuries.
<hi>Lewis</hi> tooke a delight to cut off the heads of poppy and eares of corne which doe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>top
the rest, the torrent of his iustice hath often carried away the innocent with the
guiltie. <hi>Henry</hi> hath so vsed his clemencie towards his greatest enemies, as if the
Iustice of God should demand of him the number, he would easily giue him an account.
<hi>Lewis</hi> left France so weake, so ruinous and so deiected, as it had nothing remaining
but the tongue to complaine: <hi>Henry</hi> hath chased ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>de, idlenes and pouerty out of
France, and from the necessitie of his affaires: and to conclude the paralel, there is
not any nation which doth not reuerence the name, admire the fortune, extoll the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,
enuie the triumphs, sing or vveepe for the victories, loue the gouernment, and
feare and redoubt the power of this great and incomparable Prince.</p>
   <p>This Historie doth truely show the diuersitie of the two portraits, and giues the
King an incredible content, to see that the raigne of a great, mighty, redouted; and
wise King, may not enter into comparion with his, by the difference which hee hath
set in the order of his treasure, in the number of his forces, in the force of his armes,
in the fortification of his frontiers, in the structures of his great buildings, and in the
restablishment of the publike safety and felicitie. As for the other obiection which I
haue made as done, it is true that <hi>Philip de Commines</hi> hath related the life of this
Prince so exactly and iudiciously, as if <hi>Statius,</hi> who hath written the life of <hi>Achilles</hi>
after <hi>Homer,</hi> did not maintaine my designe by his example, I should yeeld my selfe
vanquished of indiscretion and presumption.</p>
   <q>
      <l>Quamquam acta Viri multum inclita cantu</l>
      <l>Moeonio, sed plura vacant, nos ire per omnem</l>
      <l>Sic amor est, heroa velis, Sciroque latentem,</l>
      <l>Dulichia proferre tuba, nec in <hi>Hectore</hi> tracto</l>
      <l>Sistere, sed tota iuuenem deducere Troia.</l>
   </q>
   <q>
      <l>Though his great deeds by <hi>Homers</hi> lofty vaine</l>
      <l>Be highly sung, yet much is left vnsaied:</l>
      <l>Weele trace him all, and in Dulichian straine,</l>
      <l>Sound how this peere was close in Scyros laid;</l>
      <l>Nor in his dragging <hi>Hector</hi> stop our verse;</l>
      <l>But his yong Acts in all Troyes siege rehearse.</l>
   </q>
   <p>Iudgement must be the poulder of separation to reduce euery thing to his element,
and will show that he hath not so reapt his field, but he hath left some eares to gather:
In like manner I doe not thinke that I haue spoken all things so fully, and cleerely, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
him, but there will yet remaine something to exercise others after me. The hunts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
is commended that hunts and takes, but he is not blamed if hee hath not taken
all: We must yeeld something to the curiositie and diligence of others. He teacheth
not well that teacheth all. Another spirit will happily finde somethings wherewith
to please himselfe in this goodly ample field of the life of this Prince. I confesse I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e
drawne the principall pieces of this building from <hi>Philip de Commines,</hi> but the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
of the work, the Architecture, and the Ornaments are mine owne. He could not
speake, of his owne knowledge, of the affaires of <hi>Lewis</hi> the eleuenth but from the yeare,
1472. when as he left the D. of Bourgundy to serue him; but this History speaketh of
the infancy of this Prince, of his retreat into Flanders, and of all that had happened
memorable throughout the world, during the three and twenty yeeres of his raigne,
and, besides many manuscripts, I haue seene the forraine Histories of those times.</p>
   <p>The ten bookes are extended vpon that which concernes his life, and the eleuenth
vpon the obseruation of that which was done in those times, and of that which is done
now, to show that <hi>Lewis</hi> hath been as much inferiour to <hi>Henry,</hi> as he was held superior
to other Kings. If all things haue not bin exactly and curiously digested, if in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
there be found defects, it sufficeth to say that the worke hath been made following
the Court, and printed in my absence: To conclude, mens mindes should not be more
difficult to please then the Gods of the ancients; Hee that had no milke gaue them wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
and he that found no wine offered milke, salt for incense, leaues and flowers for
fruits, and fruits for beasts. He that giues what he hath, and doth what he can, is
bound to no more. They that content not themselues with that which seemes good,
trouble themselues to seeke for better. Whatsoeuer happen, all these disgraces shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
tire nor daunt me: Wee doe not leaue to till and sow the ground, although the sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
be bad and the haruest vnfruitfull. <hi>Hee</hi> that cannot content all the world must
endeuour to content himselfe.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>