<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVOR∣SHIPFVLL MAISTER EDVVARDE DODGE ESQVIRE, FABIAN WITHER WI∣SHETH LONG LIFE, VVITH PROSPEROVS SVC∣CESSE AND ENCREASE OF GODS GRACES. &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Wither, Fabian</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114070_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19849</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6275</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114070</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVOR∣SHIPFVLL MAISTER EDVVARDE DODGE ESQVIRE, FABIAN WITHER WI∣SHETH LONG LIFE, VVITH PROSPEROVS SVC∣CESSE AND ENCREASE OF GODS GRACES. &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Wither, Fabian</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A breefe and most easie introduction to the astrologicall iudgement of the starres : VVhereby euerye man maye with small labour giue aunswere to any question demaunded. Written by Claudius Dariot Phisition, and translated by Fabian Wither. Hereunto is annexed a most necessarye, ready, and breefe table, for the speedie finding out of the planetary and vnequall houres of euery daye thorow the yere, exactly calculated by the sayd Fabian Wither</title>
                 <author>Dariot, Claude</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>108 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL MAISTER EDVVARDE DODGE ESQVIRE, FABIAN WITHER WI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHETH LONG LIFE, VVITH PROSPEROVS SVC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CESSE AND ENCREASE OF GODS GRACES. &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen as I doe often times reuolue with my self (Right Worshipfull) the great laboures, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall paynes, and incessaunt diligence, whiche the forraign Nations vse for the aduancement of their countrey &amp; people, to bring them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the vnderstanding and knoweledge of all, and all maner Artes and sciences: in so much there is not anye Authour that hath written in any tongue or language, or of any Art or Science, which they haue not translated into their own proper and vulgar tongue, for the common commoditie of their countrey: as dayly experience without further proofe doth suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently approue &amp; testifie. I cannot a little maruell at the slack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, or rather contemptuous negligence of our countreymen in these our dayes, vpon whome, although God hath bestowed his giftes moste plenteously, so that I suppose them not to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour vnto anye Nation in learning and knowledge: yet as though they were borne only for themselues and to their owne vses, haue altogether neglected to publish or set forth any thing for the common commoditie of their countrey, or rather seeme to haue enuyed that anye man shoulde bee partaker of the fruites and benefites of their laboures and studies. The whiche their dealinges how farre off it is from Christianitie, they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues can easily iudge. But how farre different it is from a minde
<pb facs="3"/> endowed with wisedom, let this one sentence of Cicero in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> offices declare and shewe, he saith, <hi>Non nobis silum nati su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap> sed partem patris, partem parentibus partem amicis debemus.</hi> That is, we are not borne onely for our selues, but partly for our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie partely for our parents and partely for our friendes, where as he atiributeth the first and principall point and duetie of our being in this life to the vse and commoditie of oure countrie, the other partes as by destribution doth appeare the last and least parte vnto our selues. But now by a preposterous conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, as in all other humaine actions and affaires so likewise in knowledge and learning, euerie man seeketh to profite and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce himselfe that he may seeme to furmount and excell o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but none for the common commoditie of his countrie, which sheweth the greate abuse of God his good giftes and argueth the horrible ingratitude and contempt of naturall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which euen the heathen men whiche knewe not God did acknowledge to be requisite in a good man, but me thinketh I heare one obiect and say: Sir in no age or time hath there beene so many famous learned men which haue written of and vpon the sacred Scriptures both by way of controuersie as otherwise, as are in these our daies, but for your astrologie it is thought of many better vnknowne then knowne. Whereunto I aunswere thus, most true it is that the sacred scriptures are to be preferred before al other knowledge, learning arts, or sciences, whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and such as haue traueled in them for the commoditie of their countrie worthie to reape their due reward and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, but notwithstanding as God hath reuealed himself in his worde, so hath he also opened himselfe in his creatures, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it to be accounted the least or smallest poynt of Diuinitie to know God truely in his workes and creatures. The Psalmist saith. The heauēs declare the glory of god &amp; the firmamēt shew foorth his handie worke, now I suppose there is none so igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and wilfull that will affirme or say, the declaration of his glorie or the setting foorth of his handie worke to be wholie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded and conteined in the frame beautie or motion of the same, wherefore we must proceede further and with diligente
<pb facs="3"/> mindes enter into the contemplation of their natures seeking out their secrete and hidden quallities, for as it profiteth vs little to knowe that GOD hath adorned and decked the earth with all kinde of Corne and Cattell, with hearbes, fruites, Plantes, and trees, except he had also taughte vs to knowe the natural quallities and vse of thē, how some serue for foode and sustenance▪ some for the helpe and cure of sundrie disea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses greefes and maladies, some for other necessarte purpose, &amp;c. Whereby he doeth not all onely teache vs to knowe him to bee the Creator of these thinges, but also his fatherlie ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitie in the bountifull bestowing of these his giftes, and carefull prouidence in prouiding for vs all thinges necessarie for the maintenaunce and releefe of mans nature whereby wee mighte bee continually prouoked to acknowledge him to be our God and to prayse and glorifie his name for his greate benefites. So in like maner when wee duely consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the natures and influences of the caelestiall bodies behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and marking diligently thelr force and effectes in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior bodies, wee shall straightway bee brought to the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing and knowledge how that God hath planted and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in them a lawe of reigment, or rule, by whom as by his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments and second causes, he will rule and gouerne this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior Orbe making it subiect vnto diuers and sundrie mutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and chaunges at his will and decree. The which mutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and chaunges, notwithstanding hee hath not secretlie closed vp vnto himselfe but most plainelie set foorth as in a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in his celestiall creatures to beholde, and also to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warne vs to foresee and take heede, that when any euill is threatned, to flye vnto him, who alone can turne the same awaie, and likewise to stirre vs vp vnto thankefulnesse, when as hee sheweth his fauourable countenaunce and promiseth all goodnesse. The like that is spoken here in generall, may also bee saide and applyed vnto euerie particuler man in himselfe, whose nature with the disposition and inclination of the same eyther vnto good or euill with his sundrie mutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and changes prosperity and good successe, as also aduersity, sicknesse, or other mishappes is easily foreseene and soreshewed
<pb facs="4"/> by the course and disposition of the caelestiall bodyes, as by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueable examples set downe by sundrye learned men, is most euidently approoued that it needeth no further demonstration. If then the whole course of mans life be thus ordred &amp; guided, it is not to be doubted but all the actions of the same are in like sort ruled and gouerned, so that consequently the disposition of them is likewise to be foreseene, and therefore by wisedome most lightly borne if they be euill, or more thankfully receyued being good, the iudgemēts of both which parts are most playn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly set downe vppon seuerall questions for example sake in this small Treatise. Then let vs duly consider what Arte or Science is there that draweth nearer vnto diuinitie then this iuditial part of Astrologie discretely vsed (the abuse whiche happeneth as well in this as in all other Artes, I doe not excuse, neyther allow, but except) which teacheth vs not onlye to knowe GOD in his creatures, but also his absolute power and gouernaunce, his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly care and prouidence, his will and pleasure towarde vs, if we seeke to know it with reuerence, do altogether mooue vs to obedience, thansgiuing, and to the prayse of his holy name. Let no man therefore contemne or despise it causelesse, for as the prouerbe is, Learning hath no greater enimy then ignorance, &amp; it is the greatest mishap that may be, whē an vnskilfull man shal take in hand to iudge any Art. I therefore, Right Worshipfull, fearing the like censure vppon mee that hath happened vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, haue presumed to dedicate these my labours vnto you, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting that as you haue alwayes bene not only a fauourer, but a supporter and mayntainer of learning and learned men, so you will accept in good worth this rude, compendious, yet learned treatise, defending it as a Patrone, receauing with good will, as from a well willing Friend, Thus with encrease of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, prosperous health, and Gods graces, I commende you to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your worships to commaund <hi>Fabian Wither.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>