<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A DISCOVERIE OF INFINITE TREA∣sure hidden since the worlds begin∣ning, whereunto all men, of what de∣gree soever, are friendly invited to be sharers with the Discourser G. P.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114836_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68588</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19998</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114836</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A DISCOVERIE OF INFINITE TREA∣sure hidden since the worlds begin∣ning, whereunto all men, of what de∣gree soever, are friendly invited to be sharers with the Discourser G. P.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discovery of infinite treasvre, hidden since the vvorlds beginning : VVhereunto all men, of what degree soever, are friendly invited to be sharers with the discoverer, G.P</title>
                 <author>Plattes, Gabriel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Hutton, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>36, 92, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="text">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>A DISCOVERIE OF INFINITE TREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure hidden since the worlds begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, whereunto all men, of what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree soever, are friendly invited to be <hi>sharers with the Discourser</hi> G. P.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Must needs confesse that divers of these inventions and improvements contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this Booke, are not totally hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from the world at this day: yet in regard that some of them are onely known to my self, others not general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known, and all of them not practised generally; but the profit thereof which might accrue to the Common wealth, hath hitherto beene lost; I have been bold to intitle the Book, <hi>A Discovery of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Treasure, &amp;c.</hi> for that the intent of the publishing thereof is, that all in generall might receive benefit thereby, and that they might be satisfied so fully before hand, that they might joyn together with one consent to accomplish
<pb facs="9"/>the work more speedily for the generall good of all that are present and alive; and also for the generall good of their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steritie, whose happinesse all men are bound to indeavour themselves by their providence to further; though it should be some charges and labour extraordinarie: for by this meanes shall they shew themselves to be more like to the Creator of all things, who provideth forth all Ages, as well as for the present time. If any one shall carpe at any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in this Book; let him be pleased to call to minde the old saying, viz. That a given Horse is not to be looked in the mouth, especially when he hath cost so deare to the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. I must needs confesse that here is neither Stile nor Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posure answerable to the worth of the subject: for which I crave pardon, in regard that my time hath been spent in action and practise, and not in the Schooles. This Book is pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished for those which through their debonere disposition wil accept the Authors good meaning, though it were but paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a coale; and for such as will take a little paines to spell and put together the same themselves, and expound it to the best advantage for the generall good for which it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended: to please all is a thing impossible, for that very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son it self, which doth, or at least should rule their pleasures, differeth according to the constitution of the bodies, and also according to the Climates wherein reasonable creatures live; which because it may seeme strange, I will demonstrate by some few experiments amongst many. As for the Climate, the opposition in the determination of divers controversies, doth sufficiently testifie: as for the finall determinations of controversies in severall Climates differing one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it doth manifest the other: for the first, it is found that where a question ariseth, there every one disputeth according to his fancie, his constitution causing his will, and his will causing his braines to invent, and forge arguments to make good that which he desireth, be it good or evil: as for the second, the Climate differing causeth the Major part of the Assembly to agree upon a determination which sorteth with the constitutions of the bodies in that Climate: for more
<pb facs="9"/>plaine demonstration hereof, let us observe first severall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations, in severall Climates; of the same question; se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, let us observe severall determinations in one and the same Climate of the very same question: as for the first, the different determinations betwixt us and the Southerne Countries, about having many wives or but one, sheweth, that the Climates being hotter or colder, do sway the mindes of the disputants: as for the second, the late law for the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of onely one wife, doth demonstrate the coldnesse of the Climate, together with the difficultie of acquiring of mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; both which sway the mindes of the disputants here; and as for riches, the things most desired, are they not striven for according to the naturall desire of the parties affected to them? Is it not manifest that many wise and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent men have despised multitude of riches and honours; and other have affected the same most earnestly, and accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them with much danger and difficultie; and these have thought one another mad or foolish, for that they were of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall opinions, caused by their divers constitutions which swayed their reasons with such violence, that their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were hood-winked? And is it not manifest also, that many mischievous contentions have risen between parties in the same Climate, and betweene severall Countries in divers Climates, about frivolous questions, where neither partie hath had truth on their side, though they both thought they had it infallibly: like our hot <hi>Apocalyps</hi> men, and fierce ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounders of <hi>Daniel,</hi> who are sure, in their owne conceit, that they have such divine revelations, that they cannot possibly be deceived. Of this nature are the most part of the decepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the world at this time; which are to be pitied rather then punished, for that they differ from wicked intended de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions; even as betweene chance-medley and wilfull murder: he that could undeceive the deceived by laying o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to him his folly, might do more good in the world then all the lawes hitherto made: for men would not goe against reason rectified, unlesse it were some few miscreants. As for my part, my will is good; but I have neither much learning,
<pb facs="10"/>neither am made fit for it by nature: for the writing of these few lines hath prejudiced me in my health, more than many yeares spent in corporall practise: wherefore I desire all Schollers to endeavour to performe my wants, and by their learning to fulfill my want of learning, and to studie to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote my good intents: for I can but shew that I would say if I could speake; and for their so doing their reward is ready: for I have knowne the Tithes in one parish improved twenty pound <hi>per annum,</hi> in one Parsons age, through his good per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion to the people to be industrious in the planting and grafting of fruit-trees onely: and then the whole parish must needs gaine two hundred pound <hi>per annum:</hi> and there being in <hi>England</hi> about ten thousand parishes, it may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectured what benefit may accrue for the generall good of all the Land, viz. about ten thousand times two hundred pound <hi>per annum:</hi> and also what benefit may accrue, if all my inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and improvements shall be generally put in practise, this being one of the least of very many: also their honour, reputation and respect shall be doubled by furthering of this pious worke, whereby the working poore may be so well imployed, that the impotent poore will be easily mainteined; and for my requitall, I desire no more, but that they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member me and my posteritie in their prayers for the heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly benediction: as for other gratuitie, I am not so necessitated as to make begging letters, though I be not possessed of any great estate: for to deale plainly and truely with the world, I know no imperfection in my selfe, but that, if I were mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to acquire, governe, and conserve a great estate with that trouble that some of my friends doe undergoe, I could have it; but not making that my <hi>summum bonum,</hi> I am resolved, that unles it come with more ease, I had rather be without it: and herein I challenge no immunitie from being deceived like others; for my reason hath deceived me so many times, that I will trust it no more, unlesse it be confirmed and made manifest by experience; and if many more were of my mind, I suppose that the world would be lesse fooled by conceits and fancies, and would not be deluded so sottishly to strive and
<pb facs="10"/>undoe themselves in the breaking of the generall bond of peace. For particular fancies, it is a strange thing to see the different dispositions of men, yet all thinke they have good reason for what they doe: as may be seene by the laughing of <hi>Democritus,</hi> and the weeping of <hi>Heraclitus,</hi> at one and the same object; and perhaps another spectator would have beene angry at it; and a fourth being of a great minde and a large spheare, would have marvelled that rationall men should be moved at all in their passions for such triviall objects: and it is more strange to see men destroy one another by warres and injuries for triviall fancies, and about matters of so small moment: it argueth a meane love to God, when men will kill their own kinde, the wonderfull workmanship of Gods hands upon so slight grounds; it seemeth to me a very fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible worke to rid the world of those mischievous contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: for now that the Major part of the Princes are of good and peaceable dispositions; What were it to joyne together so strongly, that their power should be irresistable, and then the noise thereof would conquer the rest without Drummes or Cannons; and Hallelujahs would come in their place: but in this worke the Schollers must play their part, else all will be worse then it was before; for unles the world be unhoodwinked and shewed their follies every way, vices will abound by prosperitie, and love-sonnets and fables will come in the place of Hallelujahs after a small time: for I must needs confesse the truth, that at this time nature is so depraved, that prosperitie will cause destruction to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyers thereof, unlesse their judgements be so rectified, that they may doe the same things for love, that now they doe for feare and want: for want is now the best bridle to restraine vices, and therefore I have not indeavoured to my uttermost skill to bring plenty into the world upon a sudden; but that they may have some sowre sawce to their sweet meat, to keepe them from surfetting, yet is not the industry now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired any intolerable thing; for that many of these im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements consist of skill more then of bodily labour; so that no man hath cause to complaine, so long as his fare is
<pb facs="11"/>bettered: yet, howsoever, I could wish that this conclusion were put in practise, that experience might conclude the question. For though rationall discourses are subject to fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, yet they give good aime to hit the marke; which was the cause that I, having a strong love to knowledge, addicted my selfe so strongly to trie experiments, judging no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge perfect till it was thereby confirmed; yet I found that I prospered best in those practises, wherein I did first pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly dispute with my selfe <hi>pro &amp; contra,</hi> and was not partiall, but objected and accused the worke as strongly, as if my enemie had done it; and when I was remisse in this, I usua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lly fared just like a suitor in law, who telleth his Lawyer the fairest part of his cause, and concealeth the worst of it, till at length he is overthrowne in his owne suite; though his Lawyer were honest and learned. I have sometimes marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at my owne folly, in being carried with such a swinge to doe others good, that I have prejudiced my selfe much by it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> my foolish pity hath many times caused me to be wittingly and willingly soothed, and to part with my money, rather than to suffer another to be oppressed with extreme want and miserie; and this I did not meerely for very charitie; for it is a double vice to make my selfe more honest then I am: for the chiefe cause was my pronenesse to part with my money, being a thing I so little care for; finding a delectation rather in laughing at the parties mistaking, in thinking he had ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely Tantalized me with hope of some great advantage, when God knowes, I never expected either gaine or princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall againe. I know a man at this day of no meane capacitie, that having a good estate, but not yet very great, for whom I dare sweare, that he would not change estates with the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> whose dominions are so large, that the Sun never setteth in them; for before it goe downe in his Westerne do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, it riseth in some part of his Easterne dominions: these things I would have to be taken notice of, to the intent that mens conceits should be weakened, and that lesse bloud should be shed upon slight grounds, that hath beene hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. If any one say that warres and bloudshed are just, for
<pb facs="11"/>that it is for the maintenance of Religion and Lawes; I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, that the fancies of the people in many several climates, if not in all, bore so great a sway, not only in the making and composing of the Lawes and severall Religions, but also in the imbracing and receiving of such as sorted with their fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; that it seemeth not to be convenient, that the generall Law of Nature should be violated for particular Lawes; nor that the fundamentall points in Religion, which command generall love to God and man, should be neglected for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular differences. I am not sure how this enterprise, for the bringing of the world into a regularitie and uniformitie, will prosper; for it may prove to be a fancie as well as the rest: yet of all conclusions that are yet to be tried, I have the best fancie to it; for that the Major part of the world doe so much desire it, and for the furtherance thereof, if it come to a dead lift, I will try my cunning for some engines of Warre extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary, which will make foule worke with such miscre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants as shall oppose so worthy a worke, and will cause them to be trampled upon even as the mire in the streets: but to publish these were an execrable villanie, unlesse that a short warre might be sure to end all future quarrels. And what Prince soever shall first engage himself in this enterprise, his honour is sure to be perpetuall; for that all tongues, both pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent and future, will testifie his heroicall and noble nature; and all histories will record his fame to the worlds end; and this honour will be surely his, whether the designe hit or misse, for that he meaned well howsoever.</p>
   <p>But to speake according to my conscience purely, I thinke that in regard it is a worke of God and not of man, when the divine pleasure seeth it sit, it will be done by some weake meanes, whereby his glory shall be the more advanced; for men are so apt to be arrogant, that God Almightie will scarce trust them with such an honour. Now for that the old saying is true, That it is dangerous medling with edge tooles, I will cease this discourse, as seeming somewhat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove my Spheare, and addresse my selfe to my plough a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; wherein I shall be sure to doe good, or else no hurt;
<pb facs="12"/>unlesse it be to lose my labour in taking paines for unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full persons; or else to overshoot my selfe, in striving to bring in plentie and prosperitie into the world too suddenly, before they have learned to use it well, and to governe their fulnesse with moderation; wherein I have not bin altogether remisse in my care, that the mutation might not be too violent and expeditious. And as for Religion, doth not a strong conceited Papist, and a strange conceited Protestant, thinke one another to be mad, and deluded by their fancies? and doth not a Iew thinke the same by them both, and doth not a Turke thinke the like by all the three? and doth not a learned Pagan thinke the like by all the rest, being himselfe madder then any of them? Amongst all Religions which I have perused and looked into, which are not a few, I finde that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Religion doth manifest it selfe to come from God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, by the good discipline thereof, and also by the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable consolation which it giveth to men in adversitie and affliction, and at the very houre of death; thereby shewing it selfe to be the very salve of God who is all mercy and pitie: yet I could wish that Christians should not be so violent in mainteining it by bloudshed, as they are, but rather take ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way more powerfull, and lesse prejudiciall to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall good: also I could wish that the rest would looke into their follies, and not be so ready to break the generall bond of peace, and great Law of Nature, for their particular fancies. For if any Scholler should take upon him to mainteine by his Logicke that men might lawfully hate one another, if they should differ from them in opinion; me thinkes I durst undertake him, and would make no great doubt with my small learning to involve him into an unavoidable absurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; for if this might be done, it would be concluded, that there might be lesse love in the world then is at this present, which in my conceit is a thing that needs not: for the law of Nature doth complie with the generall profite, which this doctrine doth thwart extraordinarily; thereby shewing it selfe to be false and frivolous.</p>
   <p>And for a full demonstration of my meaning concerning
<pb facs="12"/>the great Law of Nature: I affirme it is that which forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth any man to doe that thing, which is prejudiciall to the generall good: which is more manifest in that every one that doth such things, doth hide the same, either by doing it privily, or by covering the same with pretences: thereby shewing that his conscience doth forbid him all the while he is in doing it, unlesse it be where the conscience is not rightly informed: for then the Conscience stingeth not at all, as it is manifest by the Pagans, who thought they did God good service in martyring of the Christians; and also by the people who thought the like in killing the Prophets, Apostles, and Christ himselfe.</p>
   <p>For the Conscience is guided by the science; if the science be a conceited fancie, then the Conscience is quiet; though it provoke men to doe execrable actions.</p>
   <p>But how men should be so blinded to doe things against the generall good, seemeth to me a strange thing; in regard that all Religions agree in this point, that we are not to doe that to another, which we would not have done to our selves: Now who would have himselfe killed, or injured, for his private opinion? therefore in my conceite, he ought not to doe the same to another, much lesse to destroy the wonderfull workmanship of God for that it pleaseth not his fancie.</p>
   <p>If any man should make a pot, or a glasse, or other whim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sey; he would take it ill if his inferiour should breake the same, for that it pleaseth not his fancie.</p>
   <p>Therefore why should he thinke that he can please God Almightie, in doing a thing of the verie like nature?</p>
   <p>I have made this tedious digression, not for any great skill in Divinitie that I pretend to have; but to shew to the world, that I am as others are, a little troubled with my phantasticall conceit; and wish, as others doe, that all the world were of my opinion: for then we would not for any particular opinion, whatsoever, forgoe the great prosperitie and happinesse, which peace would bring us; but would breake our swords, and instruments of Warre, into Plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shares,
<pb facs="13"/>and other instruments of Husbandrie; and would spend the charges of Gunpowder, Shot, &amp;c. in the building, repairing, and beautifying of Churches; and turne the noise of Drummes and Cannons, into Hallelujahs; and would according to my naturall pronenesse, try conclusion, whether Peace, or Warre, were better.</p>
   <p>Yet howsoever it cometh to passe in the generall, I would be glad that this particular Kingdome, would be a little ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by my fancie; which in this point is not different from the vulgar, to whom every contrarie opinion seemeth fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous, and ridiculous: as the opinion of those doth to me, who contend for trifles, and had rather forgoe their future happinesse, than lose an inch of ground in standing out for their strong conceited opinions: yea, verily they seeme to me as ridiculous, and childish, as for Boyes to fall together by the eares, and teare one anothers clothes, and give one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other bloudy noses about Cherry-stones, points, pinnes, and other trifles which they play for.</p>
   <p>Wherein, I am just like the Inhabitants in <hi>China,</hi> who suppose that they have two eyes, and all others have but one; therein manifesting their strong conceit of their owne wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; for that they thinke they know more than all the World besides.</p>
   <p>Yet I conceive my good meaning may beare me out in it; for that I conceiving my selfe to see the Kingdome post a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way apace into povertie and want, am willing to shew my good will for the prevention of such a mischiefe.</p>
   <p>And I am not wedded to my fancie so much, but that I wish every one to take better counsell when he may have it, and in the meane time, to accept of mine, rather than of worse.</p>
   <p>And where good counsell is wanting, let every one tell himselfe the old fable of <hi>Aesope,</hi> concerning the contention betwixt the members and the belly; and let him set before him the successe, of their discord; and also the happinesse that they had enjoyed by concord; and let it move them to joyne together for all their profits; and let them thinke as I
<pb facs="13"/>thinke, till they be better advised; that there is more wit in that fable, then is in an hundred of our new fabulous fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and strong conceited whimseyes.</p>
   <p>And whereas the old saying is true, That need is the whetstone of wit; let us be wiser than our Predecessours, and whet our wits with the thought of it; and studie to prevent neede before it cometh: for that the prevention of a disease is better than the cure afterwards.</p>
   <p>And let us not make so great a difference betweene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence and prudence as some doe; and if either be preferred, let providence goe before: so will prudence be lesse trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled when he cometh to doe his dutie; and lesse repentance will serve, when a vice hath beene stayed before it be actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly committed.</p>
   <p>And let me not totally destroy fancie, for that it is cause of much good sometimes: for Birds would not take so much care and paines to feede their young ones, but that every one thinketh his owne little one to be the fairest: and I would not have spent so much money, labour, and time; but to fulfill my fancie.</p>
   <p>For I have as small reason to doe it as any man in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> having received many wrongs and injuries, by divers persons whom I freely forgive; and desire God Almightie to doe the like: for it was not they that did it, but that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked root Covetousnesse, which got possession of their hearts: with whom I can never be reconciled; but have vowed the ruine thereof, and cannot be stayed with any perswasion whatsoever.</p>
   <p>And having tried divers waies to accomplish my enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise, can finde none, but to choake, suffocate, and make it to surfeit to death with the food that it most loveth.</p>
   <p>And it is a strange thing to see that I cannot rule my passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but to run headlong upon it; though I see plainly, that pride and luxurie are like to grow in the roome of it.</p>
   <p>And that I shall be just like to a Tinker that stoppeth one hole and maketh two greater; and were it not for feare
<pb facs="14"/>of this mischiefe; I would declare something that here shall be omitted.</p>
   <p>For I would be loath to be so bad a Physitian, as to have no more care in the Composition of my medicine, but that the hot ingredients thereof should cure an Ague, by putting the patient into a Feaver being a more dangerous disease.</p>
   <p>Amongst all my Observations in the workes of nature, I could never finde so exquisite a Modell or resemblance of a well ordered and flourishing Common-wealth, as is an hive of Bees; who in these two principall points doe so farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell men, that they may well goe to Schoole to them: for first they are all industrious, and suffer no drones to remaine amongst them, and by this meanes their well living is no whit diminished by growing numerous: Secondly, they are all bent to worke for the generall good, which is manifestly seene by this one remarkable point: for when any one hath fortune to finde out a pot or vessell of honey, he doth not like men eate it all up himselfe; but forthwith he goeth home and telleth his fellowes whom he guideth to the treasure which he hath found: and there they worke with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, till they have carried it to their owne hives if they be not letted by force: I being schooled by this commendable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, have published this Discovery, which must needs prove some huge Creature, for that it hath been threescore and foureteene yeares betweene the conception and the birth: this treasure consisteth of improvements in Husbandry; whereof the least is inestimable and infinite, for that thereby so many lives present and future are maintained; these part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by a Booke given me by one of my Auncestors, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the remarkable observations for fiftie yeares of the weather: the plentie and scarcitie: the cheapnesse and deare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: with all accidentall occurrences, and the naturall causes of the same; and partly by my owne observations and experiments for the space of 24 yeares, I have by the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of God found out, which if I should conceale, and not publish, I conceive that I did commit as execrable a villanie,
<pb facs="14"/>and as much defile my conscience, as if I should see a number of men in danger of drowning, and should not lend them my hand to helpe them: if any one shall calumniate these improvements with the name of innovations; let him be pleased to remember himselfe, that such innovations as these have beene accustomed in all ancient times, as the people grew more and more numerous, to be put in practise: for three severall times the people growing too numerous for their maintenance, God hath given understanding to men to improve the earth in such a wonderfull manner, that it was able to maintaine double the number, and so he that made mouthes, sent meat by teaching them understanding how to get it: for when there were but few, they were maintained by Fish, Fowle, Venison, and Fruits; freely provided by Nature: but when they grew too numerous for that food, they found out the Spade and used industry to augment their food by their indeavours: then they growing too numerous againe, were compelled to use the plough, the chiefest of all engines, and happily found out: whereby all Common-wealths have ever since beene maintained, and at length this invention would not serve the turne neither without new skill in the using of it: for at the first they used to till the Land till the fatnesse thereof was spent, and so to let it lye a long time to gather fatnesse againe of it selfe; and in the meane time to till fresh Land: but when they grew too nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous for the food gotten that way, they were compelled to finde out the fallowing and manuring of Land: by which invention the Land recovered more fatnesse in one yeare, then before in many yeares; and so a Countrey would maintaine double the number of people more then before: now the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are growne numerous againe, requiring new improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which are discovered in this little Booke, and shall be shewed by irrefragable demonstration, and infallible experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; also it shall be made manifest, that by the Common course of Husbandry used at this day, the barrennesse doth by little and little increase, and the fertilitie decrease every yeare more and more, which in regard that the people doe increase
<pb facs="15"/>wonderfully, must needs at length produce an horrible mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, and cause the Common-wealth to be oppressed with provertie and beggery.</p>
   <p>When as by these new inventions and improvements be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing industriously practised, their wealth shall not be dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, but contrary wayes wonderfully increased, though the people shall grow wonderfully numerous.</p>
   <p>And this businesse is not to be sleightly thought upon, for so much as Husbandry is the very nerve and sinew, which holdeth together all the joynts of a Monarchy.</p>
   <p>Neither is Invention to be lightly regarded: for all work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manship without invention, resolveth it selfe into the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans belly, as may be manifestly seene: for before the plough was invented, and before Horses, Oxen, and cattell were taught to doe the works which men did before, all their labour came to nothing, but onely to fill the belly; but since that time, by the benefit of these and other inventions, we see what Castles have beene built in time of Warres, and what Churches in time of Peace, what famous Townes, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Schooles, and other things conducible for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good: also, by this meanes men were spared from servile labours, that they might attaine to knowledge to be States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Clergie men, Lawyers, Physicians, Merchants, Trades<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, &amp;c. without which no Common-wealth can subsist.</p>
   <p>And for so much as the new world called America, doth for the present give aide and succour for the maintenance of the surplusage of people increased in those Countryes; yet in regard that the finding of new worlds, is not like to be a perpetuall trade; it seemeth to agree with providence, to beg in to improve the Lands formerly peopled, in such man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that by their industry there may be raised maintenance for double the number.</p>
   <p>Which to performe is no hard taske, in regard that all treasure and riches are nothing but congealed vapours: for what is corne, and fruits, the chiefest of all riches, but the fatnesse of the earth; <hi>Iacobs</hi> blessing elevated by the heate of the Sunne, and turned into vapour by the helpe of the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versall
<pb facs="15"/>spirit of the world, then drawne together by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damantine vertue of the Seeds, and Plants, and so congealed into the same forme? and what is Silke, Velvet, fine Clothes, &amp;c. but the vapours of Animalls congealed in the superfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of their bodies, where the Animall heate was able to ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate them no further? and if any man will hazard a wager upon it, I will undertake to shew by irrefragable demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration &amp; experience, the great Test and onely triall whereby truth is distinguished from imposture; That Gold that great Commander, is nothing else but the said fatnesse of the earth, elevated by the said universall spirit, and after depuration congealed into that splendorous Body.</p>
   <p>Yet I would be loath that this should animate men to spend their goods this way as many have done; Therefore I will them to understand, that though I affirme the Art of Gold making to be true, yet I doe not affirme it to be lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crous in these times.</p>
   <p>For the difference oft-times may make a gainfull art to be not gainefull: for when an Earledome, or Province was morgaged for a thousand Markes, as we finde in credible Histories they were; then gold making might be a profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Science, and yet nothing worth in these times, when as one Farme will buy a thousand Markes.</p>
   <p>By this meanes, the wise and godly men which have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of this Art, are cleared of aspersions, and impostures; for that they were no Prophets to foretell these mutations of times.</p>
   <p>Now seeing that all treasures are nothing but congealed vapours, there resteth nothing to be done for the performing of my undertaking, but to shew the Art of doing the worke, and then the treasure is discovered according to the Frontis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece of this booke: which worke is plainely made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest in these ensuing lines. And whereas all men are invited to be sharers, it concercerneth me to shew how they shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive benefit thereby; which thus I make good.</p>
   <p>Though the Husbandman carry away the greatest share, as they are most worthy; yet part cometh to the poore
<pb facs="16"/>workemen for their imployments; and part to the Clergie by the improvements of their Tithes; and part to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie by the improvement of their Lands and Rents; and the King hath no cause to doubt his part to come short: for if the subjects shall be rich, they will be ready, both with purse and person, to defend and offend upon all occasions: even as a man having good store of treasure, being assaulted by theeves, will fight more valiantly then he that hath nothing to lose: and then they will not pay their money with such grudging as now they doe; for that a little preserveth a great deale: and as for the Kings honour, it will be then as much more excellent then now, by reason of the heartie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the honourer; as a piece of true gold differeth from a counterfeit piece.</p>
   <p>Also the Tradesmen whom it least concerneth, shall be sharers too; for when there is such store of good imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Countrey; the Cities will not be so overcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with multitude of Tradesmen; and more then that, they will have greater dealings, and better imployment.</p>
   <p>Also the impotent poore; as old, lame, blind; also father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse, strangers, widowes, prisoners, and succourlesse people will have share: for then their number will be but very few, in comparison of what is now: also charitie will increase together with abilitie.</p>
   <p>I dare undertake to shew a way how the working poore may be imployed in these new improvements, in such man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that they may live twice aswell as they doe now; and yet notwithstanding, there may issue out of the benefit of their labours, sufficient maintenance for the impotent poore, and all others above mentioned.</p>
   <p>Which worke will be almost as charibable and good, as if I should build an Almes house in every Parish, and give per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall maintenance to the same.</p>
   <p>And of all sharers mine owne part will be the least, for I am like to be a loser by the bargaine in my wealth; onely I shall die with a more quiet conscience, which is better then wealth: for my knowledge how to get wealth, will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded
<pb facs="16"/>by this new alteration; for by my long and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent observations in these affaires, I am growne able to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne and foresee the scarcitie, and unavoidable dearenesse of many things before every vulgar person; by which meanes I could easily raise to my selfe, and to my posteritie, more wealth then can any way accrue to me by the publishing of these my Inventions and Improvements, which will cause such a mutation, that all my former observations will stand me in little stead for such a purpose; yet that all succeeding Ages shall know, that once a man did change so great wealth for a quiet conscience; I will proceed to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most of my skill, to make all my knowledge to be every mans, and to forgoe my owne gaine, for the benefit of many.</p>
   <p>And though here will be little found in this Booke, but what every understanding man knoweth to be true; yet I hope I shall performe sundry good offices: for to some I shall be but a remembrancer of what they knevv before, but forgot to practise it: to some I shall be as a Midwife, who though she neither conceiveth, nor beareth the child: yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth a good office in facilitating the birth of it: to some I shall help to bring to ripenesse certaine seeds of knowledge, planted in their hearts by the Finger of God in their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</p>
   <p>And as for my owne Inventions and experiments, I would be loath, that having pretended to give men so much wealth and treasure, I should bring any man into losse and damage of that which he had before. Therefore in regard that no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine rule can be given for so variable a worke; I wish that every man may trie the truth in a fevv Perches of Land; and when he hath found out his fit seed, his fit composition of manure, his fit depth of planting and setting, and hath dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered all inconveniences, and knoweth how to avoid them; then to goe to worke in greater quantities.</p>
   <p>For we see that though all riches are nothing but congea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vapours, yet the aire in <hi>Spaine</hi> and hot Countries, is apt to
<pb facs="17"/>be congealed into some manner of riches, and the aire in these Northern Countries is apt to be congealed into other manner of riches: also the vapours arising out of Clay ground are apt for some things, and the vapours of sandie ground are apt for other things, and all ground is fit for some use or other: for God and Nature made nothing in vaine, and therefore the saying being found true, <hi>non omnis fert omnia tellus,</hi> it is not so ridiculous a thing as the world doth repute it, for men sometimes to try conclusions: for if people did not increase; I confesse that then the old waies were best and surest: but in regard that new numbers grow daily, therefore it behoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth us to have new inventions and improvements, whereby they may live by their industry and not by shifts and unjust devices as now they are forced to use.</p>
   <p>For though the new Plantations were happily found, and have disburdened these Countries of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> extreame surplusage of people; yet we see by experience, that they are as it were squeesed out by force of povertie and want, and most of them try all their shifts before their departure, which causeth such store of shifts to be put in practise as are now used, wheras by honest industry they might helpe themselves, being set in a good way, with as much lesse trouble to their minds, as their industry would bring trouble to their bodies.</p>
   <p>And one of the principall Motives which mooved me to put out this Booke, was a griefe of minde to see some indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent well disposed persons, to lye and shift even as a thiefe that stealeth a Sheepe for very hunger: with whom I have conferred about it, and found that they could get no conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent imployment, at least answerable to their nature and edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
   <p>Wherefore my studie hath beene to finde out inventions of severall natures; whereof some of them consist of skill, as much as upon bodily labour; whereby men and women of good birth may without disgrace acquire their livings.</p>
   <p>Now, for so much as it is plaine that need causeth shifts, and also it is as plaine, that the saying is true in Philosophy,
<pb facs="17"/>
      <hi>sublata causa tollitur effectus:</hi> I will summe up my Booke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one grosse summe and conclude; that if I take away need, the shifts will be gone.</p>
   <p>Wherein I will put my selfe upon the great Test, viz. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, whereupon my drosse will be burned away, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Gold will remaine; for that Test suffereth no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posture.</p>
   <p>And I make no question, but there will be found some drosse, yet if the greater part prove to be Gold, my request is, that all Readers will play the Refiners; and if they finde more Gold then drosse, then I am Gold Oare at the least, which is Mine Royall, though not so pure Gold as I desire to be.</p>
   <p>And so I end my preamble, thinking the time as long as the Readers till I be at worke, and shew my skill in perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my undertaking in forme following.</p>
   <p>And my first worke shall be to divide my Booke into twelve Chapters, for the ease of the Readers mindes, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that their bodies are to be imployed in the enterprise more then their mindes, following the example of former in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventors, who discharged that part: for <hi>Solomon,</hi> and all other Wisemen never bore their disciples in hand with miracles, but evermore stirred them up to industry, shewing that it was accustomed that God Almightie did performe his providence usually by teaching men understanding to acquire their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings by industry, and seldome rained Manna, or fed them miraculously.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>