<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣shipfull and vertuous Lady, the Lady IOAN LEVENTHORP, temporall, and eternall happinesse.</title>
           <author>Granger, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114983_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02028</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12175</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114983</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣shipfull and vertuous Lady, the Lady IOAN LEVENTHORP, temporall, and eternall happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Granger, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The application of scripture. Or The maner how to vse the word to most edifying. By Thomas Granger preacher of the word at Botterwike in Holland, neere Boston, in Lincolnshire</title>
                 <author>Granger, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Pavier, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 27, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull and vertuous Lady, the Lady IOAN LEVENTHORP, temporall, and eternall happinesse.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MADAME:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He sincere conceit of your worthines, consisting part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in those heauenly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments, wherewith the Lord hath beautified and adorned you, as solid wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, pietie, humilitie, sinceritie in all things: herein shewing your selfe the expresse image of that worthy, and iudicious man <hi>Sir Iohn Brograue</hi> your Father; and chiefely in your Christian loue towards all that loue God, and liue a godly life: euen these sole considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="3"/>
haue moued mee to dedicate this small and worthlesse worke to your Ladiship, which if it shall please you to accept as the Widowes mite, into the treasury of your other Bookes, esteeming it rather by the minde of the giuer, then valuing it by the weight of it selfe, you shall fully satisfie my desire. The Lord conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue still his wonted goodnesse, and louing kindnesse towards you, who as he hath made you a ioyfull Mother of many faire children, and carefull of their vertuous education; so it would please his heauenly Maiesty to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill your ioy, in your latter daies, by beholding their vertuous courses and desired establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment here in the earth; that in the end both you and they may reioyce together for euer in the promised <hi>Canaan,</hi> when your Arabian pilgrimage is here finished. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From <hi>Botterwike</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> neere <hi>Boston</hi> in <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Ladiships<lb/>
in all dutie<lb/>
THOMAS GRANGER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>