<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL His much esteemd good Friend, Mr. RICHARD PELHAM, Esquire, S. P. Wisheth all happines and prosperity here and hereafter.</title>
           <author>Pick, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114710_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09626</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19897</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114710</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL His much esteemd good Friend, Mr. RICHARD PELHAM, Esquire, S. P. Wisheth all happines and prosperity here and hereafter.</title>
                 <author>Pick, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Festum voluptatis, or The banquet of pleasure : furnished with much variety of speculations, wittie, pleasant, and delightfull. Containing divers choyce love-posies, songs, sonnets, odes, madrigals, satyrs, epigrams, epitaphs and elegies. For varietie and pleasure the like never before published. By S.P. Gent</title>
                 <author>Pick, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, Elizabeth</publisher>
                    <distributor>Langford, Bernard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 54, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL His much esteemd good Friend, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. RICHARD PELHAM, Esquire, S. P. <hi>Wisheth all happines and prosperity</hi> here and hereafter.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>WORTHY SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may seeme something strange, that so meane a Muse as mine, upon so unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy a Subject as this, should so rudely dare to shelter it selfe under the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of your Name, or intrude upon the consure of so solid a judgement as resides in your brest; conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring how conversant you daily are with raptures both of a higher straine and better nature, daily proffered to your view and censure: But the perswasion of your courteous acceptation of such wild Olives as these are (as of Plants which inoculated and pruned, in time may produce more mature and delicious fruites unto her fosterers) hath emboldned me to it;</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>and shall therefore (I hope) be the better excused (though it want much of what I wish it had) because it flyes to you as a Refuge, under whose Hands it hath both security and warrant. Expect no quaint language nor fragrant Flowers of flowing Rhetorick, but such as use to proceed from springing youth, they are the wanton fruits of idle houres, and so happily cannot yeeld that rellish that may be expected from them But yet your ingenuity and generous dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on assures the acceptation being the first fruits of my Muses springing.) And that you cherish them, that they dye not in their Bud, but (by your promptitude) may be preferred from the blast of envy, and the rot of time and oblivion. The perswasion of your liberall acceptation vouchsafed me, not onely ympes my Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses wings for a higher flight in the future, but vowes me to acknowledge my selfe now and ever</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships most obsequiously to be commanded,
SAMUEL PICK.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>