<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epistle. To the ryghte honourable syr Thomas Audeleye knyght, lorde Audeley of Walden, and lorde Chauncelour of Englande, Peter Betham wisheth health and cō¦tinuaunce of ho∣nour</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1544</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114959_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09851</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20116</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114959</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epistle. To the ryghte honourable syr Thomas Audeleye knyght, lorde Audeley of Walden, and lorde Chauncelour of Englande, Peter Betham wisheth health and cō¦tinuaunce of ho∣nour</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The preceptes of warre, setforth [sic] by Iames the erle of Purlilia, and tra [n] slated into englysh by Peter Betham</title>
                 <author>Porcia, Jacopo di, conte</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1544</date>
                 <publisher>Telotson (Tylotson), William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Whitchurch (Whytchurch), Edward</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>204 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Epistle. To the ryghte honourable syr Thomas Audeleye knyght, lorde Audeley of Walden, and lorde Chauncelour of Englande, Peter Betham wisheth health and cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinuaunce of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome men peraduē<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture (right honourable lorde) wyll thynke me blame worthie, bycause I haue presented thys translation to the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of your lordshyppe rather then to some actyue and valyaūt capitayne, whose prowesse is wytnessed by his martiall affayres, and bolde en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprises, which also is thought in some mens opynyon by dutye to haue the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage of all those thynges that apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne to knyghthode and chiualry. Euen as Lawe wyghtes and Philosophers,
<pb facs="3"/>
which take to theyr selues y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> perfect kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wledge of thynges, are iudged amonge all other men (althoughe there be some men, whose iudgement is no lesse allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wable) mooste worthye, of whome in maters doubtfull, we ought to aske coū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sayle, and those men ben estemed vnwise whych debate suche causes with other, then wyth them, syth they haue profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed that knowledge: Yet to those whych weye thynges by the outewarde face, breuely I wyl make this answere. Lyke as there be many men whych although they haue not theyr beerdes longe, their lockes lyinge on theyr shoulders, ne be clothed with the robes of a philosopher yet for theyr hygh knowledge, they are not vnworthy that name. Euen so there be amonge noble men, that be worthye to haue the praysefull name of a capy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, not for theyr brode shoulders, out sette brestes, and knyghtlye feates: But for theyr wysedome, conueyaunce, and watchefull foreseinge of all suche thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, whych by any meanes maye anoie
<pb facs="3"/>
or ouerwhelme the state of the common wealth. For the strength of the bodye is not to be matched wyth wytfulnesse and fyne vnderstandynge. And that cytye is not best defenced whyche is inuyronned wyth stronge walles, and warded with fortresses of bulworkes, trenches, and suche other lyke, but that whyche wyth wyse counsaylours is proptvp and stren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gthed.</p>
   <p>Also ryght honourable lorde, lyke as Cicero whyche was chosen Consull in the ciuyle and inwarde ruffelyng, by the free consente of good men, was worthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called the father of theyr countrye, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendour of theyr cytye, and mayntayner of theyr liberties, not for his valyaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in warrely dedes, and that he was the graunde capytayne to leade the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne power agaynste Catilyne, and hys mooste wycked fellowes, but that throughe hys endeuoure and carefulle dylygence, he saued the cytye of Rome from fyre, the virgyns and wyues from rauyshyng, and the tēples frō spoyling,
<pb facs="4"/>
the Senatours from slaughter, and thoughtlesse for hys owne lyfe, vanquy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed the cursed conspiracye of Catiline, with the whole route of so many brain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syke hopelostes, whych were alied vnto hym. Thys was not done by hys stoute fyghtynge, but by hys dilygente carefulnesse &amp; swete orations: by whiche he brought to passe all hys attemptates and affayers. Euen so ryght honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble lorde, you beyng chosen to this hygh offyce, whyche by you is setteforth and honested, haue bothe in inwarde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, and outward warres, shewed your endeuour to defende this royalme, as well from the bloodsheddynge and slaughter of it selfe, as from the entryes of forayne enemyes, not that you dydde beare harnesse on youre backe, lodge in the campe, and leade an armye, but that by your aduyse and counsayle, such thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges haue ben decreed: suche enterpryses fynysshed, and weyghtye matters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that thys royalme hath flourys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, all thynges haue luckely chaunced and oure enemyes on euerye parte sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued.
<pb facs="4"/>
This your lordshyppes wysdome vnder oure moost gracyous, noble, and soueraygne prynce Kynge Henrye the tyght, by your swete and pleasaunte o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, haue opened and broughte to passe suche thynges amonge other the honourable senatours, auncient fathers and worthye counsaylours of this roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme, whyche haue auaunced the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon profyte, enlarged the marches of this lande, and brought vnder to thys daye all our enemyes. Wherfore the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and worthye name of a capytayne in suche one as you be, rather then in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other is prayseable, in whome so ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny vertues be linked: whyche you haue gotten by paynefulnesse, paynefulnesse hath purchased you great renoume, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noume hath auaunced you to honour, ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour hath made manye to folowe you, whych folowers with most prayse, do treade the, footesteppes of so auncient and wytfull a capytayne.</p>
   <p>Furthermore yf we cal to remembraūce the Grekes and Troians, and searche whych of them deserued greatest prayse
<pb facs="5"/>
in that longe battayle (amonge whome the feates of chiualrie were moost vsed) we shall sone se that wysdome had euer the hyghest prayse. For Vlisses bothe of Homere and other wryters, was moche more praysed then eyther was Achilles or Aiax, whyche both in strength passed all other. For howe many thinges were conueyed by Vlisses wysedome, whych the puissaunce of Achilles, the strength of Aiax, the fersenesse of Diomede could neuer brynge to passe, ne ones attouche Who was ambassadoure to Achilles? Vlisses. Who plucked the Grekes from flyght? Vlisses. Who caused the death of Rhesus? Vlisses. Who was the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of Troye? Vlisses: whyche all were doone by wysedome, and not by strength of the bodye. For strength stry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, wysdome refrayneth, strength fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth no perils, wisdome stayeth, strēgth is rasshe and foolehardye, wysedome is bolde and puissaunt, whyche alone doth shape and worke all thynges past mans iudgement, for which cause in the frame of mans body she is set in the hyest place
<pb facs="5"/>
Wysdome also is lykened to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> goddesse Pallas, whyche as well among the wil les of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> goddes as mens doynges doth decise all thynges. Thys ladye was of the grekes partye, whyche euer was at hande wyth Vlisses in all weyghty and dowbtefulle matters by whose helpe he waded thorough owte all ieoperdyes, whych mought haue ben noyouse to the whole armye of the grecians.</p>
   <p>Thys one ladye doth guyde al magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates as well in tyme of warre, as of peace. Thys lady in all common weales doeth lyfte vp one, to ben as a shynynge starre, &amp; a pure bright glasse, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> in one she maye shewe forth her hye gyftes, as ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peareth by one Annibal, whych by wys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome dydde almoste caste downe the ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne empyre, breke theyr force, &amp; dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the renoume of the noble Senators whych beyng lordes ouer all the worlde in strengthe coulde neuer be matched w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> anye forayne prince, but wyth thys one Anniball whome wysedome dyd guyde. Whyche also dyd welknowe that wyse<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome woulde mayster strength.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="6"/>
Nowe ryghte honorable lorde, none vpryght reader can blame me, that wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is so set alofte, &amp; enhaūced, which so moche surmounteth strengthe, whan greater renoume, is due to the polytike counsaylour, then to the stronge man of armes. Whyche thynge is daylye seen in our warres, &amp; in the noble capytayns of thys realme, whose straūge sleightes and feates of warre, yf any man wyl go abowte to brynge togyther, and make a booke therof: he shulde playnely shewe that the youthe of Englande doth so flo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rysshe in warlye knoweleage that they passe all other bothe Grekes &amp; Romans to thys daye. Thus whan the laude of chyualdrye, doeth so clerelye shyne in a wyse counsaylour: I shall desyre youre lordeshyppe to take in good worth thys my simple doynge, in whyche I haue done my diligence to content your lorde shyppe and satisfy the nobilitye and gē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye of Englande, as well in the termes as in the sentences, whome I do moste hartelye wysshe, that thys translation maye please, the whyche to reade theye
<pb facs="6"/>
shall be the rather drawen, whan that thynge shalbe taught here in lessons, the which is shewed to be done in dede, in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> booke of Iulius Frontinus, whyche is translated by the well learned Morison a man of swete and eloquent spekynge, so that the feates of war there done and tolde by hystories, doo proue these pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of chyualdrye, for the most parte in euerye place. That booke is worthye to be red of all thē that be chyualdrous, and couette to wynne renoume in war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, whych is wyth feate termes adour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned, to the euerlyuyng prayse of the trā<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>slatour. I se it tyme to make an end, lest my epistle waxe ouermoch, yet I wilbe bolde vnder your lordeshyppes licence, somethyng to wander from my fyrst mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyer, and to speake a lytle of the transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of thys age, whych after my pore iudgement do marre and misframe our englysshe tounge, through theyr termes vnnedefullye borowed of other langua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges. For lyke as the carpenter that goth abowte hys worke, doth occupye for the most parte hys owne instrumentes, and
<pb facs="7"/>
hath lytle nede to borowe of anye other craftesman: So I thynke that all tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slatours ought to vse the vsuall termes of our englysshe tounge, which of it selfe is ryche and plentyfull and not to breke wythout all iudgemente in to the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the latyn tounge, to steale termes of it, as yf our englyshe tounge had not in hymselfe suffysaunce of woordes, to set fourth all our speakynges. But suche men as do vnaduisedly desyre other tōg termes, woulde be taken (to my indge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) as authours of our woordes, ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by to enlarge our language (whyche ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they do make poore and barrayne) so that manye good mattyers be dusked and defaced, wyth theyr newe borowed ynkehorne termes, and the common peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of Englande, do not vnderstand the wrytynges ne yet the speache of thē, for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theyr trycke termes of theyr owne brayn shaped.</p>
   <p>These men thinke all theyr owne do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges woorthye greatest prayse whan that but some of them be well done.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>
Yet lette no man thyncke, that I doo damne all vsuall termes borowed of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tounges, whan I doo well knowe that one tounge is interlaced with an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But nowe to be shorte, I take them beste englyshe men, which folowe Chau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, and other olde wryters, in whyche studye the nobles and gentle men of En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glande, are worthye to be praysed, whā they endeuoure to brynge agayne to his owne clennes oure englysshe tounge, &amp; playnelye to speake wyth our owne ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, as our others dyd before vs, which men I coulde reherce by name, but that I shulde be thought to flatter. The dead I maye well prayse.</p>
   <p>Wyate was a worthye floure of our tounge, as appereth by the mornefulle ballet made of hys death in Englysshe, whyche is mooste wyttye fyne and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent.</p>
   <p>Nowe ones agayne ryght honorable lord, I must begge a little pardō to make an aunswere to some euylle speakers, whyche of nature enforced to dysprayse
<pb facs="8"/>
other mens doynges, wyll berke &amp; rage agaynste thys myne enterpryse, whyche am thus bolde to take marters of warre in hande, whan that I am no warriour But let them bluster &amp; spitte owte their poyson wordes: learned and witful mē do knowe, that phisitians and astrony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers do come to theyr knowleage, more by great studye and readynge of bookes wyth them selfe, than by the teachynge of other menne: so I ryghte honorable lorde, chyfelye holpe by moche readynge of bookes and markynge of the same, &amp; partlye by the helpe of them, that haue bene in warres, haue (as I truste) not gone farre amysse, as shall appere to the gentle reader, whom I desyre to report as he shall se. Thys sayde, I praye god shylde your lordshyppe frō al mischaūce and contynue your helth and honour to the comforte of poore suters, and prefer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of them that be honeste and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouse.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>In the moneth of Decembre, 1543.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>