<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114333_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09195</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19502</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114333</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The compleat gentleman : fashioning him absolute in the most necessary &amp; commendable qualities concerning minde or bodie that may be required in a noble gentlema [n] . By Henry Peacham. Mr. of Arts sometime of Trinity Coll: in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Constable, Francis</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 124, 129-162, 161-172, 1, 170-211, 1 page, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                    <term>Heraldic works and genealogies</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To my Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am not ignorant (Iudicious
Reader) how many peeces of
the most curious Masters haue
beene vttered to the world of
this Subiect, as <hi>Plutarch, Eras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,
Viues, Sadolet, Sturmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,
Osorius,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot,</hi>
M. <hi>Askham,</hi> with sundry
others; so that my small Taper among so many Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
were as good out, as seeming to giue no light at
all. I confesse it true. But as rare and curious stamps
vpon Coynes, for their varietie and strangenesse, are
daily enquired after, and bought vp, though the Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
be all one and common w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th ours: so fares it with
Bookes, which (as <hi>Meddailes</hi>) beare the Pictures
and deuices of our various Inuention, though the
matter be the same, yet for variety sake they shall
bee read, yea (and as the same dishes drest af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er a
new fashion) perhaps please the tastes of many bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.
But this regard neither mooued me. When I was
beyond the Seas, and in a part of <hi>France,</hi> adiorning
vpon <hi>Artoise,</hi> I was inu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ed oftentimes to the house
of a Noble personage, who was both a great Sould<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er
<pb facs="6"/>
and an excellent Scholler; and one day aboue the rest,
as we sate in an open and goodly Gallerie at dinner,
a young <hi>English</hi> Gentleman, who desirous to trauaile,
had beene in <hi>Italy,</hi> and many other places, fortuned
to come to his house; and (not so well furnished for
his returne home as was sitting) desired entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
into his seruice. My Lord, who could speake as
little <hi>English,</hi> as my Country-man <hi>French,</hi> bad him
welcome, and demaunded by me of him, what hee
could doe: For I keepe none (<hi>quoth he</hi>) but such as
are commended for some good qualitie or other, and
I giue them good allowance; some an hundred, some
sixtie, some fiftie Crownes by the yeare: and calling
some about him, (very Gentleman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> like, as well in
their behauiour, as apparell) This (<hi>saith he</hi>) rideth
and breaketh my great Horses, this is an excellent
Lutenist, this a good Painter and Surueyer of land,
this a passing Linguist and Scholler, who instructeth
my Sonnes, &amp;c. Sir (<hi>quoth this young man</hi>) I am
a Gentleman borne, and can onely attend you in your
Chamber, or waite vpon your Lordship abroad. See
(quoth <hi>Monsieur de Ligny,</hi> for so was his name)
how your Gentry of <hi>England</hi> are bred: that when
they are distressed, or want means in a strange Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,
they are brought vp neither to any qualitie to
preferre them, nor haue they so much as the Latine
tongue to helpe themselues withall. I knew it gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
to be true, but for the time, and vpon occasion
excused it as I could; yet he was receiued, and after
returned to his friends in good fashion. Hereby I
onely giue to know, that there is nothing more deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,
then the breeding in generall of our Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb facs="6"/>
none any more miserable then one of them, if
he fall into miserie in a strange Country. Which I can
impute to no other thing, then the remisnesse of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,
and negligence of Masters in their youth.
Wherefore at my comming ouer, considering the great
forwardnesse and proficience of children in other
Countries, the backwardnesse and rawnesse of
ours; the industry of Masters there, the ignorance
a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d idlenesse of most of ours; the exceeding care of
Parents in their childrens Education, the negligence
of ours: Being taken through change of ayre with
a Quartane Feuer, that leasure I had <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, as I
may truly say, by fits I employed vpon this Discourse
for the priuate vse of a Noble young Gentleman my
friend, not intending it should euer see light, as you
may perceiue by the plaine and shallow current of the
Discourse, fitted to a young and tender capacitie.
Howsoeuer I haue done it, and if thou shalt find here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
any thing that may content, at the least, not distaste
thee, I shall be glad and encouraged to a more serious
Peece: if neither, but out of a malignant humour,
disdaine what I haue done, I care not; I haue pleased
my selfe: and long since learned, <hi>Enuie,</hi> together with
her Sister <hi>Ignorance,</hi> to harbour onely in the basest
and most degenerate breast.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>