<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE, CONTEYNING THE OC∣CASION OF THIS TREATIS, with the subiect, purpose, and partes therof.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114150_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09097</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19398</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114150</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE, CONTEYNING THE OC∣CASION OF THIS TREATIS, with the subiect, purpose, and partes therof.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A conference about the next succession to the crowne of Ingland : diuided into tvvo partes. VVhere-of the first conteyneth the discourse of a ciuill lavvyer, hovv and in vvhat manner propinquity of blood is to be preferred. And the second the speech of a temporall lavvyer about the particuler titles of all such as do or may pretende vvithin Ingland or vvithout, to the next succession. VVhere vnto is also added a new &amp; perfect arbor or genealogie of the discents of all the kinges and princes of Ingland, from the conquest vnto this day, whereby each mans pretence is made more plaine. Directed to the right honorable the earle of Essex of her Maiesties priuy councell, &amp; of the noble order of the Garter. Published by R. Doleman</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Conincx, Arnout</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 220, 4, 267, 3 pages, folded table, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE, CONTEYNING THE OC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CASION OF THIS TREATIS, with the subiect, purpose, and partes therof.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>THER</hi> chaunced not long ago (I meane in the monethes of Aprill and May of this last yeare 93.) to mete in Amsterdam in Holland certayne Gentlemen of diuers nations, qualities and affections, as wel in religion as otherwise: (yet the most part Inglish and Irish) and they had bine in diuers countries, studied different ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and followed vnlike professions: some of souldiars, <note place="margin">Occasiōs of mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note> some of lawyers both temporal &amp; ciuil, others of meere trauelors to learne experience and pollicy: And for that the aduises which dayly came from Ingland at that tyme, (the parlament being then in hand) gaue occasion to discourse of Inglish affaires, they fell into diuers poyntes concerning the same: but yet none was treated so largly or so seriously, as was the matter of succession <note place="margin">The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession discussed.</note> and competitors to the crowne, for that it was presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a great while, that some thing would be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thereof in that parlament, though one or two of the wisest of that company, held euer the contrary opinion. But when at lenght newes was brought, that nothing
<pb facs="6"/>
at al had bin done therin, but rather that one or two (as was reported) had bin checked or committed for <note place="margin">M. Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely M. V Vēr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvorth.</note> speaking in the same: then came it in question among thes Gentlemen, what should be the causes of such proceding in a matter so waighty and so necessary for al Inglish men to know?</p>
   <p>But two Gentlemen Lawyers of the company, one <note place="margin">Tvvo la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvers.</note> of the common law, and the other a Ciuilian, alleaged so many reasons for iustifying the Queenes Maiesties doings in this behalfe, as al did seeme satisfied: for that it was made playne, that it could not stande with the safety eyther of her Maiesty, or of the realme, or of the party himselfe who should be preferred, that any declaration of heyre apparent should be made, during the life of her Maiesty that now is, how dangerons soeuer the delay therof may be estemed for the tyme to come.</p>
   <p>And so the end of this speach, brought in presently the begining of an other, to wit, what weare like to be thes dangers, and who might be likest of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendors to preuaile after her Maiestie, about which matter, ther was much discoursed by diuers parties, but the conclusion of al, was, that both thes poyntes remayned very doubtful, but much more the second, who should preuaile, of the competitors, which they said, did make the former poynt lesse doubtful of the multitude of dangers, that therby did hang ouer the common wealth of Ingland, though it wanted not doubt also in particuler, what and where they should fal, for (said they) whersoeuer many pretenders of the blood royall are knowne to be competitors to a crowne,
<pb facs="6"/>
ther cannot chuse but many perilles also must be immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to the realme.</p>
   <p>To this, one of the company said, that he did not see how ther could be eyther so many pretenders to the crowne as the day before had bin spoken of in that place (for the commō lawyer before named newly come <note place="margin">Many pre tendors to the crovvne of Inglād.</note> out of Ingland, had tould them that he had hard of so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me 9. or 10. or more plotts that were debated within the realme, for so many pretenders) or yf ther were any such great number descended of the blood royall, yet their titles could not be so doubtfull, seing it was an easy matter to discerne, who was next in discent of blood, and who not.</p>
   <p>Not so easy, quoth this Gentleman lawyer, for that although it cannot be denyed, but that ther is among al such as may pretend at this day: a certayne knowne order and degree of neernes in blood to some king or Queene that hath possessed the crowne before them: and in this discent it is knowne also commonly, who descendeth of the elder house, and who of the yonger, and other such like vulgar circumstances: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding for that ther be many other poyntes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable in this affaire, as the right of the first stock, <note place="margin">Successiō doubtful &amp; vvhy.</note> wherof ech part doth spring, the disabling of the same stock afterwards by attainders or otherwise: the bastardies or other particuler impedimēts that may haue fallen vppon ech discent or branch therof: al thes thinges (said he) may alter the course of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon supposed right, in him or her, that is taken to be next in blood, as prouing them not to be truly and lawfully the nerest, though they be the next in degree.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>As for example (said he) the whole multitude of <note place="margin">Three or fovver principal heades of praeten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors.</note> competitors or pretenders which I conceaue may come in consideration, or haue action or clayme to the crowne after her Maiesty that now is, may be reduced to three or fower first heads or principal stocks, to wit, to the house of Lancaster a part, as descendcd of Iohn of Gant Duke of Lancaster by his first wife <hi>Blanche,</hi> sole heyre of the Duchie of Lancaster. And of this branch or stock the most knowne of-spring in thes our dayes are <note place="margin">1. Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</note> thos Princes that are lineally discended of <hi>Don Iuan</hi> the first surnamed <hi>de boa memoria,</hi> tenth king of Portugal, who marryed with Philip the eldest daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the saide Iohn of Gant by his first wife <hi>Blanche:</hi> and thes Princes are king Phillip of Spayne now king also of Portugal, &amp; the Dukes of Parma and Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganza, who descended of the same race, as also the Duke of Sauoy one degree after them.</p>
   <p>The second stock is of the house of yorke a part, <note place="margin">2. Yorke.</note> descending of George the Duke of Clarence second brother to king Edward the fourth, who being put to death by the kings order in Cales left a daughter by whom are descended the Earle of Huntington with his brothers, which also haue children, and the ofspring of Geffrey Pole and Sir Thomas Barrington who mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed the other sister of her that was marryed to the Hastings.</p>
   <p>The third stock was in king Henry the seuenthe who being himselfe of the house of lancaster and <note place="margin">3. The tvvo houses ioyned.</note> warying the eldest daughter of Edward the fourth of the house of yorke, is presumed to haue ioyned thes two houses together, and from this man by his two
<pb facs="7"/>
daughters (for of his sonne who was king Henry the eight ther remayneth only the Queeue that now is) ther hath proceeded the house of Scotland deuided into the famylies of the king of Scots and Arbella, as also the progeny of the two Earles yet liuing of Hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford and Darby. Vnto thes three heads, which are commonlie knowen to al men, some of ourdayes do add also a fourth, which may seeme more ancient then ether of al thes three, to wit by the Dukes of Brytaine, who are discended dyuers wayes of the blood royal of Ingland as maye easely be declared, whose heire at this day by lineal discent is the Enfanta of Spaine named Dona Ysabella Clara Eugenia daughter to king Philipp. So that heerby wee come to discouer, no lesse then ten or eleuen famylies that may pretend, and haue al of them frends in Ingland, and els wher (as yesterday I told you) who do not fayle in secret to negotiat and lay plotts for them, for that ther are none of thes, so far of, but to their frends it seemeth (the tymes standing as they do) that reasons may be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for their preferment, and good hope conceaued of preualying.</p>
   <p>You do wel to adde (said a Captayne ther present) <note place="margin">Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of the tyme present.</note> the tymes standing as they do, or at least wise as they are like to stand, when this matter must come to trial, at what tyme, I beleue, not you lawyers, but we souldiars must determyne this title, and then (no doubt) if ther were not only thes tenn by you named, but twenty moore also of the blood royal, that would pretend, and had frends and money to stand by them, we should admit their causes to examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="8"/>
and perhapps giue sentence for him, that by your lawes would sonest be excluded, for whe matters come to snatching, it is hard to say who shal haue the bet ter part.</p>
   <p>I do not ad this circumstance of the tyme (said the lawyer) as though it were the only or principal poynt which maketh doubtful the matter of successiō, though I confesse that it helpeth ther-vnto greatly, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the great variety of mens affections, at this day in religion, which do incline them commonly to iudge for him, whom they best loue: but besids this I do say, that were the tymes neuer so quiet, and religion neuer so vniforme: yet are ther great doubtes in many mens heades, about the lawfulnes of diuers pretentions of the famylies before named: but if you adde vnto this, the said wonderfull diuersity in matters of religiō also, which this tyme yealdeth: you shal finde the euent much more doubtfull, and consequently it is no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile though many may remaine in hope to preuaile, seing that wher many are admitted to stand for a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, ther diuers may haue probality also of spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
   <p>An example you may take, (said the Ciuiliā lawyer) in the Roman Conclaue, at the popes election, wher, <note place="margin">The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claue.</note> among three or sower score Cardinales that enter in for electors, few ther are, that haue not hope also to be elected, not for that they see themselues, all as well qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, as others: but because oftentymes when diuers that are more forward by, likely hode cannot be agreed vppon: it falleth to the lott of hun that is fardest of, and so it may among your pretender's (quoth he) in Ingland.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="8"/>Your example (said the temporal lawyer confirmeth somewhat of that I meane though it be not al to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather in like matter, or maner for that the pope is made by electiō, &amp; here we talke of a king by succession.</p>
   <p>Your succession, said the Ciuilian, includeth also an election or approbation of the common wealth and so <note place="margin">Successiō includeth also some kinde of election.</note> doth the succession of al kings in Christendome besides, as wel appeareth by the manner of their new admis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion at their coronations, wher the people are demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded agayne, <hi>if they be content to accept such a man for their King:</hi> thoughe his title of neernes by <note place="margin">Of this more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervvards Cap 4. &amp; 5.</note> blood, be neuer so cleere. And therfore much more it is like to be in this case of Inglish pretenders now, wher their lawful neernes in blood is so doubtful as you haue signified, &amp; so I do come to confirme your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer proposition, of the doubtfulnes of the next successor in Ingland with an other reason besids that which you haue alleaged of the ambiguity of their true propoinqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in blood: for I say further, that albeit the neernes of each mans succession in blood, were euidently knowne, yet were it very vncertayne (as things now stand in Ingland and in the rest of Christendome rownd about) who should preuaile, for that it is not enough for a man to be next only in blood, therby to pretend a crowne, but that other circumstances also must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre, which if they want, the bare propinquity or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetrie of blood may iustly be reiected, and he that is se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, <note place="margin">Neernes only in blood not sufficient.</note> third, fourth, fifth or last, may lawfully be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before the first, and this by al law both diuine and humane and by al reason, conscience, and custome of al nations, christian.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="9"/>To this said the temporal lawyer, you go further (Sir) then I had meant to doe or did conceaue of the matter, for my meaning only was to shew howe many pretenders ther be to the Inglish crowne at this day, &amp; how doubtful the pretentions of diuers of the chiefe of them be, in respect of the many exclusions, stoppes and barres that their aduersaryes or fellow competitors do lay against them: and now you do adde further, that albeit thes stoppes were taken away, and their propinquity in blood were manifest, yet for other consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations the course of their next succession by birth may be iustly altered, vppon such considerations as you insinuate, that the Inglish may haue in the admis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of their next king or Queene, after her Maiesty that now is, which in deede (if it be true) maketh the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of succession much more doubtful, then I pretended, which I confesse I haue not so much studied or thought of, for that our common law goeth no further ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily, then to the next successor in blood, to consider whether he be lawfully descended or no, therby to giue him the crowne.</p>
   <p>I confesse (said the Ciuilian) that ordinarily nether your law, nor ours doth go any further, especially in thos realmes wher the gouerment goeth by succession <note place="margin">More to be consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendors.</note> of blood, which I thinke to be the best of al other wayes, but yet ther may happen out such extraordinary cases some tymes, agaynst this ordinary rule, as your common law must needs take also consideratiō of them except it wilbe contrary to al other law and reason both diuine and humane, as for example, if it should fal out, that the next in blood should be a natural fool
<pb facs="9"/>
or a madd man: if he should be taken by Turkes or Moores in his infancy &amp; brought vp in their religion aud would mayntayne the same in your countrey, with al his forces; and other like vrgent cases, wherin it is not probable, but that your common law must needs haue further consideration, then of the bare propinqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of blood only, for that otherwise it should be a very imperfect law, that hath not prouided for accidents so weighty and important, as thes are, for sauing and conseruing of your common wealth.</p>
   <p>At this speach, the residew of the company began to smile, to see the two lawyers grow into some heate and comparison of their professions. But yet for that both their asseuerations, did tendc to proue one thing, which was the first proposition set downe, to wit, <hi>that the next successor of Ingland must needs be very doubtful:</hi> they requested them both with very great instance, that ech one would be content to proue his <note place="margin">Tvvo prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipal poin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes hand<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led in this booke.</note> assertion a parte, to wit, the temporal lawyer to shewe that the titles and pretensions of al those ten or eleuen familyes of the Inglish blood royal, which remayne at this day, are ambiguous and doubtful, according to the common lawes of Ingland: aud the ciuilian to declare that albeit their titles by successiou were cleare, yet that as things stande now in that realme, and other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes neere adioyning, ther may be a great doubt which of them shal preuaile.</p>
   <p>This I say, was the request of the whole company, and the lawyers were cōtent to take it vppon them, and according to thes two poynts it was agreed that the whole speach or conference, should be deuided into two
<pb facs="10"/>
parts, and that the ciuil lawyer, should begin first, for <note place="margin">Tvvo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of this conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce.</note> that it seemed, that his assertion, being wel declared and proued, would giue much light to the other, and so he promised to do, and to be as brief, clere &amp; perspicuous as he mighte, and to reduce al that he would say to certayne principal heades and chapters therby the better to be vnderstood &amp; remembred, and so he began in manner and forme following.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>