<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all that can Iudge, of what Degree soeuer.</title>
           <author>Fennor, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114801_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00648</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10783</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114801</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all that can Iudge, of what Degree soeuer.</title>
                 <author>Fennor, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Fennors defence: or, I am your first man : VVherein the VVater-man, Iohn Taylor, is dasht, sowst, and finally fallen into the Thames: With his slanderous taxations, base imputations, scandalous accusations and foule abhominations, against his maiesties ryming poet: who hath answered him without vexatione, or [...] bling recantations. The reason of my not meeting at the Hope with Taylor, is truly demonstrated in the induction to the [...] udger. Thy hastie gallop my milde muse shall checke, that if thou sit not sure, will breake thy necke</title>
                 <author>Fennor, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Barnes, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To all that can Iudge, of what Degree soeuer.</head>
   <p>IVdiciall Reader, after a Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of Slanders, giue me leaue to bestow a Banquet of Defence; which, I hope, shall rellish with more delight in thy generous opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. I am sorrie that my Penne <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> pluckt backe from better Occasions, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>were an Opposite so ignoble. But seeing my Reputation is shot at by such a poysoned Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>toll, I thought it meete to scrue out the Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>t of his Infamie with my approued Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ie, before it grew ranke, or festered too farre <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n the Worlds Apprehension. But to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ose: Maister <hi>Taylor,</hi> the Gentleman-like <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>culler at the <hi>Hope</hi> on the Banke-side, at a
<pb facs="3"/>
friends house of mine, acquainted me with his Proiect; which was as followeth: That hee the said <hi>Taylor</hi> had studied such seuerall Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors in Prose, as neuer were the like before: (which indeede fell out true, to his shame) wherein hee would haue me ioyne; hee to play a Scene in Prose, and I to answere him in Verse: Whereto I condiscended, on these Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions; <hi>viz.</hi> That I might haue halfe the Commoditie thereof; Or Securitie for fiue pounds; Or else twentie shillings in hand, and the rest as the Day affoorded. Next, That I might heare his Booke read (which was fit) to know on what ground I might build my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention. And last, That I should see the Manner of his Challenge before it was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished, and set my Answere to it with my owne hand. To all which hee graunted, and deliuered mee fiue Shillings vpon the same: Whereupon I promised faithfully, That if all this were on his part performed, I would (God willing) meete him, and with my best endeauor striue to give the Audience content. Now, here I must entreat you, before you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne mee, note but the Occasions of my Breach of Promise: This <hi>Water-Taylor,</hi> with his Confederates, presuming he had bound
<pb facs="3"/>
me with his Earnest-money, printed his Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge-Bill, and my Answere annexed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, without my Hand, Knowledge, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent: Nay more; My Answere was by him set vp so meane and insufficient to so brauing a Challenge, that I altogether disliked there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (as I had reason) and thereupon sent my Man with the Money fiue dayes before the Play, to certifie them, That I was otherwise employed, and would not come, in regard of the Wrong done vnto mee, in setting vp my Answere without my Consent: My Man deliuered the Message, but lost the Money at Play, emboldening himselfe vpon the Wrongs I had receiued; which I haue since payed. And the same day I receiued a Letter out of Warwickeshire from my Father, That he was not well; wishing mee and my wife to repayre vnto him with all possible speede. Now, you that are Parents of Children, or Children to Parents, Iudge, whether I ought rather to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obay my Father, or displease <hi>Iohn Taylor</hi>; purchase my Fathers hate, or lose a Scullers loue; and I hope you will say I had sufficient cause to keepe me from the <hi>Hope.</hi> But fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring my homely Truth (though it be sufficient to plead my Honestie) is not answerable to your
<pb facs="4"/>
      <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>xpectation of my practice in Poesie; I will, as <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eare as I can, fit my Muse to your liking, which is my content: And euer rest honester by Land then <hi>Taylor</hi> by Water,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>WILL: FENNOR.</signed>
   </closer>
   <epigraph>
      <q>
         <l>Although I cannot Rogue it, as he can,</l>
         <l>Yet will I shew my selfe an honest man.</l>
      </q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>