<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Perkins, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114522_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09388</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19685</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114522</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A declaration of the true manner of knowing Christ crucified</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 39, 3 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the common sinne of men at this day, and that in the very places of learning, that <hi>Christ crucified</hi> is not known as he ought. The right know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of whome, is not to make often mention of his death and passion, and to call him our Saviour, or to handle the whole my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie of God incarnate soundly and learnedly, though that be a worthy gift of god: but first of all, by the consideration of the passion to be tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vvith an inward and a lively feeling of our sinnes, for which our Redeemer suffered the pangs of hell, and to grovv to a through dislike of our selves and our lives past for them and from the ground of the heart to purpose a reformation and a conformitie vvith Christ in all good du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that concerne man: secondly in the Passion, as in a myrrour, to behold and in beholding to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to comprehend the length, the breadth, the height, the depth of the love of the father that gave his ovvne deare sonne to death, and the
<pb facs="3"/>
goodnesse of the sonne that loved his enemies more then himselfe, that our heartes might be rooted and grounded in the same love, and be further inflamed to love God againe.</p>
   <p>To further this true manner of knovving <hi>Christ crucified,</hi> I have penned these feew lines, read them at thy leysure, and have care to put them in practise: othervvise, thou art but an enemie of the crosse of Christ, though thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse his name never so much.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>
            <hi>Ian.</hi> 5. 1596.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>William Perkins.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>