<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the vnlearned Papists.</title>
           <author>D., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114042_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19743</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6168</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114042</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the vnlearned Papists.</title>
                 <author>D., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A godlie and fruitfull treatise of faith and workes. Wherein is confuted a certaine opinion of merit by workes, which an aduersary to the gospell of Christ Iesu, held in the conference, had in the Tower of London</title>
                 <author>H. D.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Seton, Gregory</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>104 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_papists">
   <pb n="5" facs="3"/>
   <head>To the vnlearned Papists.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nto you I write yee vnlearned Papists, whom the Pope and his Prelates haue so blinded, and dulled your sences, that you haue eares and heare not, eyes and see not, a hart, and yet can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not vnderstand the trueth, nor finde the waie of your saluation. For blind igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, (who among you is called the mother of deuotion, though most vntruely) hath so lulled you a sleepe, in popish dreames, that you can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heare, see, nor vnderstand the word of life, but hath shut vp the same from you, so as you cannot learne Christ truly, nor obey your Prince faithfullie: but doth nussell you vp in old wiues fables, and legions of lies, as they thinke most meetest for your study: fearing that if they shuld suffer you to read the word of truth, the blinde way which they haue ledde you in all this while, would bee by you so espied, as their great hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crisie and false doctrine could no longer lie hid, but would be knowne to their great shame, and vtter condemnation. The Lord hath opened the eies of a number of his people, which haue bene led in the waie of your blindnesse: and the Lord in mercie may also open your eies, and wil if you will not too obstinatlie withstande his offered grace. The Lord calleth you, if you wil hear him. He bids you search the scriptures, for therin you shal find life and wisedome, which is Christ. But your Antichrist forbiddeth you to reade them,
<pb n="6" facs="4"/>
because he would haue you still blind, and know no other Christ, as a leader to heauen but him. Forsake not him that is life, to followe him that leadeth to death, whose doctrine draweth to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spaire, taking awaie al confidence, by the merites of Christ, and leaueth you in perpetuall blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and confidence of your workes. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore awake out of these Popish dreames, flie from that whore of Rome, who hath made you drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with the cuppe of hir fornication. Imbrace Christ Iesus the onlie Sauiour, and onelie rest vpon him for your saluation. Doe as much good as you can, and fulfill the lawe to the vttermost of your power, that God maie be glorified ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, but repose no trust of saluation, nor merite therein. Leaue that onelie to Christ, vnto whom it doth apperteine, for he onlie hath obteined it, by shedding his moste precious bloud without the helpe of our woorkes. For if those woorkes might saue vs, thē Christ died in vaine: for what need is there of his death, when our works maie saue vs. But forasmuch as this is most vntrue, and that there was nothing in the world whatsoeuer that was able to redeeme the soule of man, the commandement of God being once broken by Adam, but Christ. Therefore the most precious bodie of Christ, was made the alone and onelie sacrifice for to redeeme vs. Wherefore staie no longer, forsake all vaine helpes from the Pope, and flie to Christ onelie, and there rest yee.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>And so farewell. H. D.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>