<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORY TO THE VNIVERSITIES OF ENGLAND.</title>
           <author>R., P.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114160_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09106</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19412</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114160</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORY TO THE VNIVERSITIES OF ENGLAND.</title>
                 <author>R., P.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A quiet and sober reckoning vvith M. Thomas Morton : somewhat set in choler by his aduersary P.R. concerning certaine imputations of wilfull falsities obiected to the said T.M. in a treatise of P.R. intituled Of mitigation, some part wherof he hath lately attempted to answere in a large preamble to a more ample reioynder promised by him. But heere in the meane space the said imputations are iustified, and confirmed, &amp; with much increase of new vntruthes on his part returned vpon him againe: so as finally the reckoning being made, the verdict of the Angell, interpreted by Daniel, is verified of him. There is also adioyned a peece of a reckoning with Syr Edward Cooke, now L. Chief Iustice of the Co [m] mon Pleas, about a nihil dicit, &amp; some other points vttered by him in two late preambles, to his sixt and seauenth partes of Reports</title>
                 <author>Parsons, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40, 688, 16 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORY TO THE VNIVERSITIES OF ENGLAND.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>VCH more then one yeare is not yet past (learned Coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men) since I presēted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you a Treatise, intituled <hi>of Mitigation,</hi> in answere of an other most bitterly writtē by <hi>M. Thomas Morton</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>er, about <hi>Rebellion</hi> &amp; <hi>Equiuocation.</hi> In which Treatise of myne, besydes the two said poynts of principall argument handled at large (especially the later, as more capable of varietie in the Treatise therof) a great multitude of falsities were layd open, as vttered by <hi>M. Morton</hi>; and those so frequent, grosse, and palpable, as they must needes be thought to haue beene both
<pb facs="4"/>
willfull and witting: the censure wherof not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding, I was content to remitt vnto yow, as presuming more of the integrity of your iudgments in poynts of learning, and matter of fact, then distrusting the sequele of your vnequall, affections, by reason of our difference in religion.</p>
   <p n="2">2. This Treatise <hi>M. Morton</hi> perusing &amp; fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding himselfe, as it seemeth, not a litle strayned therein, was carried therby into so great &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant a streame of passion, as neyther he could stay himsel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e from answering somewhat out of hand (therby to preuēt the Readers pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice, as himselfe confesseth) nor yet daring to ioyne yssue vpon my booke and argument therof as it lay;<note place="margin">In his Epistle dedicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> did after a strange new fashion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> deuise to set forth a <hi>Preamble</hi> (for some present remedy) accompanied with a promise of a lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger booke, &amp; Reioynder to ensue afterwards. And I do call this <hi>a strange deuise,</hi> not only, for that I haue not seene the same often practized by any writer lightly, except <hi>Syr Edward Cooke</hi> (who perhaps by this mans imitation hath an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered of late with a Preface of lesse then foure leaues in <hi>quarto,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>La preface de la sixies<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>t des Reports.</hi>
      </note> his Aduersaries booke of more then two hundred against him:) but also for that in this <hi>Preamble,</hi> which inlargeth it selfe to aboue two hundred &amp; twentie pages, there is not the tenth part bestowed vpō the two chiefe Questions of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> &amp; <hi>Equiuocation,</hi> but rather vpon other matters &amp; subiects framed by
<pb facs="4"/>
himselfe of n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>w, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> most may ius<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly be de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>med wholy impertinent.</p>
   <p n="3">3. As for example, to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>termitt his two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, the one to my L. of <hi>Salis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>urie,</hi> the ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er to my selfe (wherof I may chance to haue oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to speake more in my next ensuing Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle to him) he d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uideth this whole <hi>Preamble</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to three seuerall parts,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Preamb. pag.</hi> 2.</note> which he termeth <hi>Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</hi> I do deuide (saith he) this <hi>Preāble</hi> into three Inquiries:<note place="margin">M. Mort. diuisiō of his worke</note>
      <q>The first is, what sufficiency &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency there is in P. R. to make so great an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sultatiō: the second, whether he may be thought a sufficient Proctor in this case or no: the third, whether he hath sufficiently performed his taske, eyther for the defence of his cause, or iustification of his cōscience; with a Challenge against him for them both.</q>
   </p>
   <p n="4">4. This is the diuisiō of his Worke, wherby I doubt not, but you will discouer also the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie, though I should say nothing therof. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hat he being pressed with a Worke of such <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eight, as the argument of my former booke did import, &amp; vrged therin, not only with an ouerthrow of his whole cause, but charged fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore with a monstrous number of playne wilfull vntruthes, not possible, as they seemed, to be answered, or excused; the iudicious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will easily consider, whether this were a tyme to tryfle as he doth, making himselfe an Inquisitour (without commission) &amp; to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rame his first Inqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y of the sufficiency &amp; excellency
<pb facs="5"/>
of his Aduersarie, and to spend eyght whole Paragraphes, as he doth, therin:<note place="margin">Imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding.</note> Inquiring first of his witt, then of his memorie, thirdly of his learning in Logicke, fourthly of his skill in Greeke &amp; Hebrue, fifthly of his kind of charitie, sixtly of his modestie, with other like poynts, spēding large discourses vpon eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of them. Is there any man (I say) so simple or sottish, as not to see the impertinency of this manner of proceeding?</p>
   <p n="5">5. His other two Inquiries are as wisely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied, and prosecuted as this. For that the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, <hi>Whether P. R. may be iudged a competent Aduocate or no,</hi> is but a silly discourse, contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning not full two leaues in all: and the argumēt therof is a ridiculous Dialogue feigned between the <hi>Mitigator,</hi> and the <hi>Moderate Answerer</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> The third cōprehēdeth the rest of the booke (which is, of foure partes, three) which may be not vnfittely deuided into the termes of <hi>offensiue</hi> and <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>fensiue warres.</hi> For that first to impresse some opinion of manhood in defending him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe from the imputations layd against him of wilfull falshoods, he taketh vpon him (quite from the argument of the controuersy in hand) to impugne others of like dealing, as namely <hi>Cardinall Bellarmine,</hi> my selfe, and others: and then hauing made this florish, he cōmeth lastly to his owne defence, in fourteene vntruthes layd against him, and culled by himselfe out of more then fourty obiected by his aduersary, and
<pb facs="5"/>
no one of them well dissolued by him, as after will appeare. And after all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>his, he imagining the feild to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mayne wholy to himselfe, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth all with a new vaunt and fresh Challēge in the ninteenth, and last Paragraph of this his booke, phantasying himselfe to haue had the victory in euery thing that he hath taken in hād to treat. And this being the sūme of <hi>M. Mort.</hi> new worke, I shall breifly lay forth to your iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the methode which I haue thought good to vse for his confutation.</p>
   <p n="6">6. First I haue bin content to follow him into those follyes of his first Inquiry,<note place="margin">The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode vsed for M. Mort. confutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> about my <hi>wit, memory, learning; skill in Logicke,</hi> and the like, confessing willingly the medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity therof in all things: but yet shewing by the substance of the po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nts handled, if I be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eyued,<note place="margin">First In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry.</note> that if <hi>M. Mortons</hi> wit had byn excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ent, or learning eminēt, he would neuer haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yn drawen to haue leapt ouer grauer matters, to handle such light toyes as these be. For what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mporteth me the disestimatiō, which <hi>M. Mort.</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rofesseth of my <hi>wit, memory,</hi> or <hi>learning</hi>; for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o much as the things themselues that are hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led (wherin wit and learning are to be shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) will be better witnesses,<note place="margin">Witlesse contentiō about wit.</note> and of more cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit with the prudent Reader, then eyther his or my bare wordes or vaunts? Wherfore to them I remit me.</p>
   <p n="7">7. In the second place,<note place="margin">Second Inquiry</note> I haue had pacience in like manner (for without pacience it could
<pb facs="6"/>
not be done) to peruse ouer his second Inquirie consisting of a meere idle fancy and fiction of a Dialogue (as hath bene said) deuised betweene me, &amp; his Aduersary the <hi>Moderate Answerer,</hi> as though he had fallen out about answering his booke: and me he bringeth in speaking very rudely and vnciuilly thus:<note place="margin">
         <hi>See his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble pag.</hi> 31.</note> Nay, <hi>I haue not beene arrogant, but thou hast beene rash and pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>cipitant. For is thou by thy former Answere mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>test haue beene thought sufficient for a reply, what needed such posting to me beyond the seas, for a supply of a more exact, and learn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d Reioynder?</hi> Thus goeth his fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and it is a very fiction indeed. For the truth is, that when I began my Treatise of <hi>Miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> against <hi>M. Mortons</hi> fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st exasperating <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery,</hi> I knew of no other that was in hand to answere the same: as more largely I haue she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed in the third Chapter of my sayd Treatise.</p>
   <p n="8">8. Moreouer he feigneth vs to reason togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther about itching and scratching, as though the <hi>Moderate Answerer</hi> had vsed these wordes:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Preamble pag.</hi> 32.</note>
      <hi>I thinke yow are troubled which the dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ase of s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>me of our Catholicke lawy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rs, of whome you haue said, they itch to be doing and answering M. Attorney: this was also my disease, but I after found a scratch, and so may you.</hi> Wherby he seemeth to insinuate as you see, a certayne threat of scratching his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersarie,<note place="margin">Threates of scrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</note> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>en other weapons of more force do faile him. But this I haue answered afterwards in due place, &amp; shewed, that aswell these scrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches (meant perhaps of those scolding skirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes
<pb facs="6"/>
before mentioned about <hi>witt, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>morie, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> and the like) as also deeper wounds of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiction of falshoods, and manifest impostures, are like to fall vpon himselfe: and that in so eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent a sort, as all the standers by may cleerly see it, and take compassion on him, and of his mā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of fight: wherof I am content to make your selues also, my learned Countrymē, both Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and vmpires.</p>
   <p n="9">9. Wherfore fynding so litle substance in these two former Inquiries (for what is added and brought in by me in the second, which are but two particuler cases only concerning our subiect and argument of <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Equiuocatiō,</hi> was borrowed frō the third to make vp some matter wherof to treate:) I do passe to the said third <hi>Inquirie,</hi> wherin one only exploit being requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed on <hi>M. Mortons</hi> behalfe, two are attempted, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ut with very euill successe in them both. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>xploit required was, that for so much as <hi>M. Morton</hi> in this his last <hi>Preamblatory reply</hi> by abā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oning the principall argument and subiect of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ur former controuersy,<note place="margin">What was prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of M. Mort. and what he perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth.</note> had changed the whole state of the Question by occasion of great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of witting vntruthes obiected against him, he should now haue gone roundly to the matter, and directly, plainly, &amp; substantially haue answered the said imputations: but I foūd him to take a farre other course, allowing to himselfe a more large feild to walke and florish in. And this was first, to seeke out, what like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood
<pb facs="7"/>
or appearance of falsities he could fynd in any Roman writer whatsoeuer: then of what Popes in particuler; then of Councels, &amp; their Interpreters: after this againe, against <hi>Cardinall Bellarmine,</hi> and that in diuers kindes, as namely for calumniating his aduersaries for false allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Fathers, for differing in his opinions frō sundry writers of his owne religion, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of notwithstanding no one can be proued as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you will see.</p>
   <p n="10">10. Fynally then after all this, he falleth vpon my selfe, pretending to shew that in fourteen se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall poynts at least he hath taken me tardy, which if he could proue, (as in no one he can) yet all this while, as you see, he walketh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the list of our controuersy cōcerning the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of his owne falshoods, which he driueth of as long as may be, according to the fashion of those that hauing many deepe woundes are loath to discouer them, or haue them handled. Wherfore this poynt of his owne defence or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse, which was first in his intention (for this was the cause that made him so hastily to shape out this Preamble) was the last in execution, as least gustfull vnto him: and so he dispatcheth it only in one Paragraph, of ninteene, that he hath in this Preamble, to wit the eyghtenth only: and by all liklyhood would haue pretermitted it wholy if handsomely he might.</p>
   <p n="11">11. But perhaps you will imagin, that he hath holpen somewhat his cause by seeking these di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerticles
<pb facs="7"/>
frō the purpose, in that he hauing wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kned first his aduersaries credit may find better passage to the defence of his owne. But indeed this reckoning falleth not out so, but rather the quite contrary,<note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ary suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e of M. Mort. expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> for that not being able when it commeth to the tryall to fas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>en any one vntruth vpon his aduersary, I meane in that nature that it may be thought witting and willing, which is our only question; he commeth by cōsequence to confirme, and authorize extraordinarily the credit of their integrity in their writings, who haue not giuen place to any least touch of iust reprehension in that behalfe: and by this meanes contrary to his meaning he becōmeth their <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comiast</hi> or Prayser, who endeauored to be their calumniatour, <hi>rectum ab errore,</hi> as oftentimes by Gods prouidence it falleth out.</p>
   <p>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>2. Wherfore I seeing <hi>M. Morton</hi> take this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ourse,<note place="margin">The sūm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> of all this my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere in 10. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note> after I had examined the first two In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uiries in two seuerall Chapters of mine, I was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>orced to bestow seauen or eight more vpon his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hird. Wherfore the first is to answere all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>articuler obiections, which he hath against o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Catholick writers, namely <hi>Card. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>llarmine</hi> and others. The second, for answering the like <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> obiections, and calumniations made by him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst my selfe in fourteene seuerall imputations layd against me. The third, how insufficiently <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
      <hi>M. Mort.</hi> defēdeth himself in other fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rteen char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges produced against him, which he thought good to choose out as defensible amongst a farre
<pb facs="8"/>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> greater nūber. The fourth how he pretermitteh more then other twice fourteene, farre more vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and eminent then the rest, without euer so <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> much as once mentioning them. The fifth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth sundry other important omissiōs or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termissiōs of his, aswell in slipping ouer matters belonging to himselfe, as to the defence of sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Clients of his, whome he ought to haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, especially <hi>Syr Edward Cooke</hi> now L. Chiefe iustice of the <hi>Cōmon Pleas</hi>: with whome <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> there is made a peece of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>euerall reckoning in like manner in a seuerall Chapter, aswell about some things of his set forth before, as also con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning two new Prefaces lately published and prefixed to the sixt and seauēth parts of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The seauenth, how in place of clearing himself from aboue fourty old imputatiōs of fals<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, he is cōuinced of more thē fifty new, su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peradded <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> to the former. And fynally, my eyght Chapter, (which is the tenth and last as they lye in order) doth handle new strange vauntes and challenges of <hi>M. Morton,</hi> after all this bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, as though nothing had byn sayd against him: wherin I can commend nothing, but his courage, remitting the rest to your better discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, when ye shall haue read both parts, this being the summe of our whole Concertation.</p>
   <p n="13">
      <note place="margin">The reasō of the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of this booke.</note>13. There remayneth to say a word or two, cōcerning the reason of the tytle of this my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere, which is, <hi>A quiet &amp; sober Reckoning</hi>: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I know that your Wisedomes will easily ghesse
<pb facs="8"/>
the cause, but much more will haue seene it, if ye haue perused ouer this <hi>Preāble</hi> of <hi>M. Morton</hi> which is so bitter and sharpe, and ouer eager in many places, as doth easily shew that the man was in great choler when he wrote it. And though I could alleage many exorbitāt speaches of his to this effect throughout the whole booke, yet the beginning and ending shall only serue for proofe therof: the beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nning, for that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoweth seauen or eyght whole Paragraphs of his first Inquiry (as already I haue sayd) to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine my <hi>wit, memory, skill in Logicke, ignorāce in Gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ke and H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>brue, modes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>y, charity,</hi> and the like, which hardly could p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oceed but from im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience. The last Paragraph also of his new challenges declareth the same more aboundātly where he auouching me first to be a man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all conscience, lame in hands, dumbe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>peach, dead in sense &amp; feeling of all cōtrition; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e passeth on to the most extrauagant, and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ulous termes of impatience, that euer I read in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y Author, that valued his owne credit, or you eyther perhaps.
<q>For he saith, that if he do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ot manifest me to be so malignant, as if the Capital letters P. R. did iustly betoken <hi>Princeps Rabularum</hi>: and so vayne, as if they signifyed <hi>Phormio Romanista:</hi> so dissolute in my cause, as if they might be interpreted <hi>Praeuaricator Rasus</hi>: so impudently vniust, as that they might import <hi>Persidiae Reus</hi>: then is he content that his Treati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses be purged with fyre, and himselfe challēged
<pb facs="9"/>
to a Recantation.</q>
And will ye not take pitty of this mans passion? Or can ye meruayle, why I tooke this tytle of <hi>A quiet and sober Reckoning</hi>?</p>
   <p n="14">14. Truly, if I should haue suffered my selfe to be c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rryed away with the same passion, &amp; with the like impatience haue returned him an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere in his owne veyne, &amp; character of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; you do easily see, wherunto this conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would haue growne: but I haue thought best to endeauour the pacification of <hi>M. Mortons</hi> choler, by a more moderate kynd of conferēce, if it may be, where heat of wordes layd asyde, the truth of matters may peaceably and more calmely be cōsidered. Wherin (as before I said) though I may haue iust cause to suspect your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: yet can I not distrust your iudgements in a matter of such apparent euidency, as this is, now committed vnto you. Wherin <hi>Christ Iesus</hi> direct you, to the discouery of that truth in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which only can saue vs all. And so to his protection I commit yow, this 19. of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember, 1608.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your louing Countreyman, wishing you all good, that is truly good. <hi>P. R.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>