<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER IN CHRIST MILES SMYTH BY THE DIVINE PRO∣VIDENCE L. BISHOP OF GLOVCESTER GRACE AND PEACE BE MVLTIPLIED.</title>
           <author>Benefield, Sebastian</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114173_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08364</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1869</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114173</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER IN CHRIST MILES SMYTH BY THE DIVINE PRO∣VIDENCE L. BISHOP OF GLOVCESTER GRACE AND PEACE BE MVLTIPLIED.</title>
                 <author>Benefield, Sebastian</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The haven of the afflicted : A sermon preached in the Cathedral Chvrch of Glocvester Aug. 10. 1613. By Sebastian Benefield Doctor of Divinity and fellow of C.C.C. in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Benefield, Sebastian</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barnes, Joseph</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 20 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER IN CHRIST <hi>MILES SMYTH</hi> BY THE DIVINE PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VIDENCE L. BISHOP OF <hi>GLOVCESTER</hi> GRACE AND PEACE BE MVLTIPLIED.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT REVEREND,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His <hi>little Sermon</hi> preached by your <hi>Lordships</hi> appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the chiefe <hi>Citie</hi> of that <hi>Shire,</hi> wherein I first drew breath, now seeth the light. The religious desires of some of my Countrymen there, wishing, that what I then vttered might not through obliuion perish in the aire, haue brought it forth. Now they, who <hi>heard it,</hi> may <hi>record it;</hi> they who <hi>heard it not,</hi> may <hi>read it;</hi> all, I hope, wil be <hi>satisfyed.</hi> My then endeavours were to arme my selfe, and that <hi>devout Auditorie</hi> with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence against the day of affliction; that day,
<pb facs="3"/> which we must looke for, if we be the sonnes of our Heauenly Father. S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
      <hi>Hierome</hi> in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle to <hi>Eustochium</hi> hath these words: <hi>Quis san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum sine certamine coronatus est? Quaere, &amp; inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies singulos adversa perpessos; solus Salomon in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litijs fuit, &amp; forsitan ideò corruit:</hi> Who of all the Saints was ever crowned without a combat? Seeke, and thou shalt finde, that every one of them suffered aduersities; onely <hi>Salomon</hi> was lulled in delights, and therefore <hi>perchance</hi> hee perished. It is but FORSITAN, <hi>perchance</hi> he perished. His booke called <hi>Ecclesiastes,</hi> or the <hi>Preacher,</hi> argueth his <hi>repentance,</hi> and perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth me of his <hi>remission</hi> and <hi>salvation</hi> with the LORD. And why might not <hi>Salomon</hi> in his time be, as many in our time are, inwardly <hi>in conscience</hi> for sinne <hi>afflicted?</hi> It's true; the <hi>stone</hi> hath no honourable place in <hi>a faire building</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lesse it be much <hi>hewed</hi> and <hi>hammered;</hi> neither can wee the liuely <hi>stones</hi> of <hi>Christs Church</hi> haue any place of credit <hi>in the Celestiall building</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse we, like the <hi>chiefe corner stone,</hi> Christ him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, bee <hi>hewed</hi> and <hi>hammered</hi> with adversitie. To the patient enduring whereof this little
<pb facs="3"/> Sermon hath a desire to perswade. Giue it <hi>(My good Lord)</hi> your fauourable countenance, that it may cheerefully goe abroad: and the Author of it shall heartely wish to your L. much encrease of grace and honour, with a daily influence of blessings from Heaven vpon your gouernment in the Church.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From my study in <hi>CORPVS CHRISTI COLLEGE in OXFORD,</hi>
         <date>August 27, 1613.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>YOVR LORDSHIPS <hi>in all Christian duty to be commanded</hi> SEBASTIAN BENEFIELD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>