<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Dedication]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114074_Fr1_2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09031</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19319</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114074</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Dedication]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A plaine exposition vpon the whole 8. 9. 10. 11. chapters of the Epistle of Saint Paul to the Romans : Wherein the text is diligently and methodically resolued, the sence giuen: and many doctrines thence gathered, are by liuely vses applyed, for the benefit of Gods children performed with much variety, and conuenient breuitie: being the substance of neere foure yeeres weekedayes sermons.: By Elnathan Parr, Bachelor in Diuinity, and preacher of Gods Word</title>
                 <author>Parr, Elnathan</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 <publisher>Man, Samuel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 305, 1, 138, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <opener>
      <salute>MADAM;</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Humbly intreat you with fauour to receiue this fruit of yo<seg rend="sup">r</seg> owne goodnes. If I haue performed any <hi>good</hi> by my poore labours; those which receiue it, owe the acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (next vnto God) to your Ladiship; who haue so watered my studies with your coūtenance and beneficence, that euen my Barrennes hath both by preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and writing yielded some <pb facs="3"/>fruit: which, as it may be profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to some, &amp; is cōfortable to my selfe to haue brought forth; so I hope it shal (somwhat) fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your Ladiships reckoning at the day of Christ.</p>
   <p>I know you take no pleasure to haue your goodnesse published, because you account Vertues fairest Theater to be a good Conscience: yet it becomes an ingenuous mind to professe, by whom he profiteth: And I wish that all the world vnderstood of your Honorable disposition, and Christian carriage, both in publique and priuate, that many more might be prouoked by your Noble example.</p>
   <p>For as in all natiue and infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Graces, you immeasurably exceed the painted Sepulchers of these dayes: so is your Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship in holy knowledge, discreet zeale, and compassionate chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, a liuely Image of those anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Heroines</hi> commended by <pb facs="3"/>Saint
<hi>Hierom,</hi> and other Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and also by vnerring Writers.</p>
   <p>As Ladies, delight not onely to see faire Iewels, and curious Needleworks, but to take them out and weare them; so I can truly testifie, that your Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships care is, not onely to knowe, but to expresse and weare the good things you know, in your conuersation. I earnestly pray for the increase of Gods fatherly blessing vpon your soule, and</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>