<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An Introduction hereunto, To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Cooper, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114304_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B12200</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5709</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114304</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An Introduction hereunto, To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Cooper, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvonderfull mysterie of spirituall growth : Describing the necessitie, nature, manner, measure, and markes thereof. As also, laying downe necessarie rules for the wise discerning of the same. And resoluing many speciall cases of conscience incident hereunto, tending t the comfort of distressed spirits, and so to the attaining of perfect holinesse. Diuided into two bookes</title>
                 <author>Cooper, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Bernard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 415, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>An Introduction hereunto, To the Christian <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is more then high time (Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in our Lord Iesus) that wee should in these euill daies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide against a storme, by <hi>casting vp our accounts,</hi> and <hi>cleering our euidences</hi> in the fauour of God: seeing we haue had such ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereof a long time, in so gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t <hi>Measure</hi> and varietie; and by the <hi>symptomes of the season: our generall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitablenesse therein,</hi> and <hi>refusall</hi> of the same; accompanied with many <hi>war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings,</hi> summoning vs thereto, and yet so desperatly reiected by our <hi>securitie</hi> and <hi>prophanenesse:</hi> we are not vnlikely
<pb facs="8"/> to be called shortly to <hi>account</hi> for the same. And therefore as <hi>one borne out of due time,</hi> and hauing spent the most part of my best daies in the wayes of death; seeing it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed God to respite me hitherto and <hi>renue my spirituall life,</hi> by offering yet more gratious oportunitie and meanes to improue the same: I haue thought it high wisedome now at length to endeuour the <hi>Redeeming thereof,</hi> by establishing my selfe and others in the <hi>worke of Grace,</hi> to the daily encrease, and building vp of the bodie of Christ; that so we may all grow vp to a perfect sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, euen to a perfect man in Christ Iesus.</p>
   <p>To this end, because <hi>words</hi> are but winde, and <hi>preaching</hi> without sealing and confirming thereof by <hi>Practice</hi> &amp; <hi>Experience,</hi> is of smal or no moment to build vp forward to perfection; I haue therefore endeuoured to ioyne with my <hi>publike Ministerie▪</hi> my <hi>priuate experiments</hi> in the worke of Grace: that so I might not be as <hi>sounding
<pb facs="8"/> Brasse,</hi> or as a <hi>tinckling Cymball;</hi> partly for the approuing and improuing of the worke of Grace in my selfe, and also for the triall and encrease thereof in others.</p>
   <p>And this hath beene the cause of my <hi>Publishing diuers Treatises</hi> in their places, as my <hi>experience</hi> and <hi>occasions</hi> haue ripened the same.</p>
   <p>As <hi>First,</hi> The Lord hauing renued our life and meanes by that <hi>wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deliuerance</hi> from the <hi>Gunpowder Treason,</hi> I haue therefore laboured to commend that great Mercy vnto Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steritie in <hi>diuers Treatises</hi> both <hi>Latine</hi> and <hi>English,</hi> vpon the 64. <hi>Psalme,</hi> and vpon the Historie of <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ster</hi> vnto the Church of God: That this being written for the Generations to come, the People so wonderfully new born and renued may praise the Lord, yea, Posteritie might magnifie God for the great things he hath done for vs.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Next,</hi> that we might be truly thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto our God, in offering vnto him our soules and Bodies as a reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable sacrifice all the daies of our life.</p>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <p>To this end I published the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians daily Sacrifice:</hi> as being a liuely Image of this <hi>Spirituall Sacrifice:</hi> and a gratious direction, how to offer the same daily vp vnto God in truth and righteousnesse.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thirdly,</hi> because <hi>contraries</hi> are best knowne by their <hi>contraries:</hi> in that our Profession and practice of since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is reproached and hindered by the faire shew of <hi>Hypocrisie,</hi> so neerely resembling, and so iustling out the same; therefore haue I laboured to discouer <hi>the differences betweene since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and hypocrisie,</hi> that so by the wise discerning of things that differ: wee may wisely decline the <hi>Counterfeit,</hi> and more carefully entertaine the <hi>true Paterne.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Because <hi>the outward pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie</hi> of the time, hath beene much abused to <hi>securitie</hi> and <hi>spirituall Pride:</hi> and so hath beene a meanes of much <hi>decay in zeale</hi> and <hi>courage for the truth;</hi> therefore I haue supplied hereto <hi>a Preseruatiue against Apostasi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> that so we might strengthen the things that
<pb facs="9"/> are ready to die, and remembring from whence we are fallen, might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and doe the first workes; least our <hi>Candlesticke</hi> be iustly taken from vs.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Fiftly,</hi> Because it hath pleased God to <hi>exercise</hi> me with many <hi>Buffetings of Satan,</hi> to preuent these Spirituall euils: and so thereby hath acquainted me in some measure with his <hi>sleights and methods;</hi> yea, hath <hi>called</hi> me by the <hi>Magistrate</hi> to communicate my <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience</hi> herein, vpon occasion of the practise of <hi>Witchcraft,</hi> questioned by some in these Atheistical daies: Could I do lesse then publish my <hi>Experience</hi> herein? haue I not giuen some light hereunto, in <hi>The discouery of the Miste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of Witchcraft?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Sixtly,</hi> Seeing the fulnesse of the Gentiles is well-neere come in, as a plaine euidence of <hi>some great alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> both by some <hi>grieuous Iudgement</hi> for our contempt of the Gospell, as also by some <hi>great Mercie,</hi> ensuing thereupon, <hi>in the calling of the Iewes</hi> for the perfecting of the Churches
<pb facs="10"/> Glorie in this life. Therefore haue I giuen warning also heretofore: <hi>In the blessing of Iaphet,</hi> wherein the <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Gentiles,</hi> and fulfilling thereof, is auouched as a <hi>Presage of some great storme</hi> hanging ouer our heads, euen by the Gentiles abusing and reiecting the Gospell, and also a comfort of some gratious calme after that heauie storme, <hi>by calling in of the Iew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s</hi> to make vp the breach, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire the old waste places to dwell in.</p>
   <p>And that we <hi>Gentiles</hi> that are with them to make vp one sheepfold vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Christ, our only sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pheard, may be better fitted to that glorious Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
   <p>To this ende haue I laboured to make <hi>sure the foundation,</hi> by disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering on the <hi>contrarie</hi> the <hi>hop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lesse</hi> &amp; <hi>fearefull estate of the worldling</hi> in his <hi>desperate aduenture,</hi> by losing his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious soule <hi>for the gaining of this transi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory world,</hi> that so we may not run with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he present streame: and also by lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe the maine euidence of our
<pb facs="10"/> sound building vpon the Rock, in that <hi>sacred mysterie of the Gouernment of the Thoughts;</hi> being the surest and most comfortable euidence of our <hi>true estate in Grace.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And now behold that we may yet <hi>minister a word in due season:</hi> when was there euer more neede of <hi>Grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Grace;</hi> when generally there is <hi>deceit</hi> thereof in the most, and <hi>decay</hi> therein euen of the <hi>Best?</hi> when euer more neede of <hi>fighting the good fight of Faith,</hi> and laying hold of eternall life, by labouring and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing hard after perfection; when we are summoned by <hi>Rumors of wars,</hi> nay by our owne vnprofitablenes, <hi>To giue account of our stewardship?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This is <hi>the end</hi> and <hi>vse of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Which I am bold to call <hi>a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Mysterie:</hi> not only by the warrant of the Holy Ghost, That <hi>great is the Mysterie of Godlinesse:</hi> but also in regard of the <hi>Meanes</hi> effecting the same; <hi>Christ Preached in a Mysterie:</hi> yea in regard of the <hi>entertainment
<pb facs="11"/> thereof in the world, esteeming</hi> it as a <hi>Mysterie,</hi> because it is sealed vp thereto, but specially in that, euen <hi>to vs,</hi> that are acquainted therewith: It is yet <hi>a wonderfull Mysterie,</hi> not being able to <hi>conceiue the measure thereof,</hi> not being able to expresse, what thereof we doe conceiue.</p>
   <p>And I call <hi>it a Mysterie of growing in grace:</hi> because it pleaseth the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to resemble it vnto vs by <hi>Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries:</hi> And the way to discerne the <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> thereof, and so to attaine the <hi>measure</hi> of the same, is still <hi>in</hi> and <hi>by</hi> a <hi>Mysterie: By the Mysterie of the Word Preached,</hi> as only effectuall thereto ordinarily: and in a <hi>Mysterie</hi> not <hi>discernable by sense,</hi> no not alwaies by <hi>Faith,</hi> that still we may liue by Faith in the iudging thereof, and by the <hi>power of Faith</hi> be led forward to perfection therein.</p>
   <p>And therefore if I speake of <hi>this great Mysterie</hi> vnto thee in a <hi>Mysterie:</hi> I aduise thee in the Feare of God, to get that <hi>spirituall Eie-salue</hi> by <hi>prayer</hi> and <hi>repentance</hi> with thy God, that so
<pb facs="11"/> thou maist so farre discerne the same, as that still finding somewhat herein, whereat <hi>carnall wisedome may stumble;</hi> thou dost further helpe me with thy prayers, to giue thee yet <hi>further light;</hi> (for still I professe my selfe to be growing, and shall not faile, God willing, to giue thee further testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie thereof, as occasion and grace shall be ministred) that so thou maist yet more cleerely discerne this <hi>won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull Mysterie.</hi> Meane time I desire thy patience, to beare with such fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings: as either for want of exactnesse, which neither my leasure will afford nor weake measure can compasse; or for <hi>fayling in circumstance,</hi> which I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse my selfe not curiously to stand vpon, may be offered vnto thee. Requiring thy <hi>wisedome to compare spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things together,</hi> and so still cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thy further <hi>Patience,</hi> till God of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer further leasure and measure of Grace, and thy <hi>renued Prayers,</hi> for both: I commend this to thy Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian view and charitable censure, and thee and thine holy endeuours in
<pb facs="12"/> this or in any thing whatsoeuer may further thy reckoning in Christ, to the gratious Protection and Blessing of our Wonderfull Councellor. In whom</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>I rest thine and the Churches seruant</hi> Th. Cooper.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>