<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE TRVLIE HO∣NORABLE, AS WELL FOR VERTVE, AS NOBILITIE, THE LADIE ANNE HERNE: Wife to that worthie and gene∣rous Gentleman, Syr EDVVARD HERNE, of the thrice Auncient and Noble ORDER of the BATHE, KNIGHT.</title>
           <author>Tofte, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114999_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07662</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18053</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114999</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE TRVLIE HO∣NORABLE, AS WELL FOR VERTVE, AS NOBILITIE, THE LADIE ANNE HERNE: Wife to that worthie and gene∣rous Gentleman, Syr EDVVARD HERNE, of the thrice Auncient and Noble ORDER of the BATHE, KNIGHT.</title>
                 <author>Tofte, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Honours academie. Or The famous pastorall, of the faire shepheardesse, Iulietta : A vvorke admirable, and rare, sententious and graue: and no lesse profitable, then pleasant to pervse. VVherein are many notable discourses, as well philosophicall, as diuine: most part of the seuen liberall sciences, being comprebended [sic] therein: with diuers comicall, and tragicall histories, in prose, and verse, of all sorts. Done into English, by R.T. Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Montreux, Nicolas de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Matthew</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 86, 2, 93, pages 92, pages 91, 88-162, 123-163, 158-166, 165-227, pages 622, 227-237, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE TRVLIE HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE, AS WELL FOR VERTVE, AS NOBILITIE, THE LADIE ANNE HERNE: Wife to that worthie and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <hi>rous Gentleman, Syr</hi> EDVVARD HERNE, of the thrice Auncient and Noble ORDER of the BATHE, KNIGHT.</head>
   <l>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ound by desert, not meriting the same,</l>
   <l>Words (still) to giue for deeds, doth make me shame.</l>
   <l>Yet (Beautious) pardon, since the pouer Man</l>
   <l>Giues, (thogh not what he should) yet what he can.</l>
   <l>Thanks yeeld I you, (the pay of younger Brother)</l>
   <l>Let Heyres be franke, and not their Riches smother.</l>
   <l>What you request, I wish you would commaund,</l>
   <l>For so my dutie to your Vertue's paund.</l>
   <l>Vouchsafe this modest Booke, fraught full of wit,</l>
   <l>A subiect chaste, a Ladie chaste doth fit.</l>
   <l>Then, honored ANNE, grace HONORS ACADEMIE,</l>
   <l>Since HONOR honoreth you, as much as anie.</l>
   <l>Your Eglets high Conceit, too well doth know,</l>
   <l>My Swallow MVSE, flies (for your pitch) too low.</l>
   <l>This stuffe is SHEPHARDS GRAY, spunne course and plaine,</l>
   <l>Vnlesse that you this worke, (to grace) shall daigne.</l>
   <l>But as your outward shape is louely faire,</l>
   <l>So inwardly, you'ar Curteous, Debonaire.</l>
   <l>Your disposition milde, all faults will couer,</l>
   <l>And (as vnseene) you gentlie them do smother.</l>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <l>My hope is then, that you will sweetly looke,</l>
   <l>With your all-pleasing Eye, vpon this Booke.</l>
   <l>Resolu'de whereon, your Votarie I rest,</l>
   <l>Liue happie, since manie through you are blest.</l>
   <l>The <hi>Phoenix</hi> faire, sprung from your Ashes sweete,</l>
   <l>As you, so her, in dutious sort I greete.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Euer deuoted vnto your matchlesse Vertues,</hi> Robert Tofte.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>