<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114001_Bo1_39</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06128</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16613</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114001</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Romane historie vvritten by T. Livius of Padua. Also, the Breviaries of L. Florus: with a chronologie to the whole historie: and the Topographie of Rome in old time. Translated out of Latine into English, by Philemon Holland, Doctor in Physicke</title>
                 <author>Livy</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 804, 809-1351, 1354-1403, 43 pages, portraits, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He historie of <hi>Titus Livius,</hi> as it was by him passing well penned otherwise, and none thereto in Latine comparable: so in the calculation &amp; date of times, which they call Chronologie (a singular light to give direction in a storie) hee is some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what defective and unlike himselfe, so as he cannot be praised without excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But if a man consider the huge volumes which he wrate, and namely in his declining age; the varietie and disagreement of former authours, whom he fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, who before him faulted also in this point, and where of he much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth; he is to be pitied and pardoned, if his memorie failed somewhat in this behalfe. For where shal we find a man that is <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>omnique exparte beatus?</hi> And in deed, if we weigh the thing aright, as it was a profession by it selfe &amp; required a whole man: so, many travailed therin alone, &amp; they that performed well but it only, deserved high thanks and commendation. And to let many others passe, how worthily is <hi>T. Pomponius Atticus</hi> praised by <hi>Cicero</hi> his friend, for digesting the head magistrates of seven hundred yeeres in one booke? As for <hi>Verrius Flaccus,</hi> who lived in the time of <hi>Augustus Caesar,</hi> he collected a catalogue and register of the chiefe rulers of Rome, how they were chosen successively, and how they governed from time to time: which as hee caused to be cut and engraven in a marble wall within the Capitoll for a perpetuall memorie to posteritie: so, thereby he deserved also to have his owne statue erected neere the temple of <hi>Vesta,</hi> for an everlasting memoriall of so great a benefit. But what is there so durable, that time wasteth not? what so conspicuous and evident, but trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some daies may overwhelme and hide in oblivion? Thus amid that havock which the Goths &amp; Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals made in Italie, there remained not one fourth part extant of <hi>Livies</hi> storie: thus in that generall confusion of Rome, these records of <hi>Verrius Flaccus</hi> were defaced, broken, and buried deepe under the ruines of the capitoll and other stately edifices. But the revolution of times, as it hath brought to light againe some reliques of <hi>Livie</hi>; so it hath discovered also those marbles of <hi>Verrius</hi>: for in the time of <hi>Paule</hi> the third, Pope of Rome, the fragments of the said stones were digged out of the ground betweene the Roman Forum and the broad street Via Sacra; brought forth also &amp; laid abroad in the capitol to the view of the world. To which, as the true touch-stone, certain learned men of late daies have laid to their owne labours in that kind, namely <hi>Bartholomew Marliau</hi> of Millaine, <hi>Onuphrius Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinius</hi> of Verona, <hi>Charles Sigonius</hi> of Modena, and <hi>Francis Robortellus,</hi> of <note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, or Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Vdine: &amp; comparing the same as also the annales gathered by <hi>Henry Glareanus</hi> before time, with the foresaid antiquities of <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> late found, have recovered much light to the his
torie of <hi>Livie,</hi> and supplied his wants in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe. I thought it not amisse therefore to gratifie my countriemen in some measure this way also, and deliver the same in English which I found annexed to the best editions in Latine, as followeth.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>