<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the gentle Reader.</title>
           <author>Booth, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114243_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00756</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10882</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114243</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the gentle Reader.</title>
                 <author>Booth, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discourse vpon chyrurgery: written by that famous doctour and knight, Signior Leonardo Phiorauanti, Bolognese. VVith a declaration of many wonderfull matters necessary to be knowne; with most notable secret found out by the said authour. Translated out of Italian by Iohn Hester, and now newly published and augmented, for the benefite of this country: by Richard Booth, Gent</title>
                 <author>Fioravanti, Leonardo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 117, that is 118, 6 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the gentle Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ealth, hath not vndeseruedly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the wisest mens opinions, the highest place amongst earthly blessings, without the which the most delightfull dainties are but vnsauery, the richest ornaments burthensome, &amp; the whole time of our life semeth tedious: For the preseruation and restauration of which vnualuable benefit, the Lord in his wisedome and mercy hath prouided diuersity of meanes and variety of reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: as also hath endowed man with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of those meanes, wherby his present strength might be maintained &amp; his ruind health repaired: in the laying open of which soueraign seueral me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines to the publique eye of the world, many learned famous men haue expended many houres and much study, in so much as it may seeme to some as friuolous and fruitlesse an enterprise, as to cast water into the Ocean; notwithstanding, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelling with the same desire of many of my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessours, and recollecting into my minde that antient and approued saying of <hi>Cicero,</hi> that <hi>We are not onely borne vnto our selues,</hi> I did study and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to find out somthing in which I might make a liuely expression of my intire loue &amp; sincere affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiō to this my natiue Country &amp; you my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie-men: &amp; in my earnest enquirie and diligent scrutiny, I could find nothing in my iudgement
<pb facs="3"/>more conducing to a publique benefit then publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing of this compendious and briefe treatise of Chyrurgerie, first compiled by a Knight of no small fame and a Doctor of Phisicke, by name Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior <hi>Leonardo Phiorauanti;</hi> which was translated out of the Italian by <hi>Iohn Hester</hi> of <hi>Lōdon</hi> an expert Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stillator, and by my care newly augmented: I haue taken the paines, doe thou accept of the profite, and let thy harnest succeede my seed-time, the which must of necessity be plentifull, if thou with care perusest this booke, and putrest the precepts contained in it into practise. For howsoeuer I might be iustly branded with the ignominy of a selfe conceite &amp; foolish Philautie, if I should com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my owne care or pains, yet thus much I date cōfidētly auerre that in this little book thou maist with much ease &amp; facility, discouer many precious preseruatiues against sicknes, as many restoratiues for health as euer hertofore thou hast vnderstood: here also be those secrets &amp; misteries in nature dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closed, which for a time haue laide raked vp in the ashes of ignorance, &amp; haue bin altogether obscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red &amp; hid from the eye of knowledge: neither are these rules of Phisick &amp; Chyrurgery bare likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods &amp; suppositions, but such as haue bin appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued &amp; confirmed by long experience: the way that leads to health is chalked out and made plaine by the Author, thy care onely remains to walke in it: which blessed period if thou attainest vnto, as thou hast the good, so let God haue the glory, neither be altogether vnmindful of the Authors painfull care.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine as his owne,</hi> RICHARD BOOTH.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>