<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the right worship∣full master Thomas Argall Thomas Paynel wisheth all prosperitye and health.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1562</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114192_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09181</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19492</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114192</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the right worship∣full master Thomas Argall Thomas Paynel wisheth all prosperitye and health.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A frutefull booke of the comon places of all S. Pauls Epistles : right necessarye for all sortes of people, but especially for those of the ministerye dyligentelye sette foorthe by Thomas Paniell. Anno. 1562</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Tisdale (Tysdale), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1562</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>384 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶To the right worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full master Thomas Argall Thomas Paynel wisheth all prosperitye and health.</head>
   <p>YOure gentlenesse ryghte worshipfull master Argall to me at all times and in al places most gently manifested and declared: And your sincere and vnfayned loue to the word of God most holy, and to those that trulye professe the same, wyth youre lyberall and dailye helpinge hande to the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce and encrease of the vnfained professoures and stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diantes there of hathe prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and inforced mee to wryte thys boke of Sayncte Paules Epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tles thus in common pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces digested vnto you a louer,
<pb facs="4"/>
a diligente reader and a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall ensuer and folower of the same. For in what other thing should a purely mynded Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiane solace him selfe, or delyte in, than in the precious worde of God, and in the cleare doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne of hys moste noble, and moste excellente Apostle Paul? Whose doctryne is frome hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen heauenly, replenished with all spyrytuall wysedome and ghostlye consolation, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thinges to you most gentle master Argall, and to all other of lyke conuersation and pure myn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, is no doubte most pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, mooste beautyfull, and mos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e amyable. Let this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine then bee grauen in youre harte moste stedfastlye. Take sure holde vppon thys Godlye learninge, that is vppon Iesus
<pb facs="4"/>
Christ. Let thys doctrine bee wrytten wych spirituall yncke throughe your Godlye admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ions, in the hearte (as I doubte not but it is) of youre most chaste and vert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ous wife, well nurtured and obedyen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e chyldren, and famelye mooste tractable and Godlye. For th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> is the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>arninge that shall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducte and bringe them too the kingedome of God, and hys eternall fruytio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. Thys is it, that shall learne them to feare, and to loue God, and to folow the fotesteppes of hys Godlye conuersation aboue all things. Thys is it, that shall instructe them to contemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e the world<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> wyth the caduke and frayle pleasures, honoures, ryches<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> pompe and pryde, therof. This
<pb facs="5"/>
is it that shall inflame them too be the true followeres of Christes gospell, and the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful champyons and protectors of the same. This is it, that shal instructe them too put theyr whole and onely trust and affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce in the merytes of Christ oure Sauyoure, and not in theyr onelye deedes withoute fayeth and merytes. Thys is it, that shall exalte and eleuate theyr earthly myndes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syres to be wyth Christe Iesu oure sauioure. Drawing their affections and gredye myndes frome this worldlye trumpery and slydynge bagage. Nowe then if thys be so (as in verye bede it is) receaue this my gift as a thinge moste precious and pleasaunte. And laye it vppe in
<pb facs="5"/>
the treasurye &amp; and store house of your hart, as a thing in time of nede, mooste excellente and coumfortable. For as vntoo a fayethfull and a true Christian there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>houlde be nothinge deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius and more acceptable, then the delicate and swete word of God: so there is nothinge to a Chrysten reader more sweete and sauerye, than the Epis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>les of Goddes electe vessell, and dearelye beloued Apostle saint Paule. Reade them therefore wyth all deuotion and syncere iudgement, and if ye intend (as I doubte not but that ye do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende) to be blessed, folowe the doctryne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and precepts of them most carefully, and as a prec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>us margarite and pearle. Whan ye haue perused and rede them moste tenderlye and dearly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue
<pb facs="6"/>
and kepe them. For it is not the onely he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rer or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eader of Pauls Epistles, and of scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that shall be iustified, but the reuerent and feruent prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er of the same. Thus oure Lorde to whom be all honour and glorye for euer, kepe you and your deuout and faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full yoke felow and most chaste wyfe nowe and euer.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>