<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Honourable Edward, Lord Russell Earle of Bedford: Grace and peace be multiplied.</title>
           <author>Perkins, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114458_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09339</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19646</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114458</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Honourable Edward, Lord Russell Earle of Bedford: Grace and peace be multiplied.</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A golden chaine: or The description of theologie : containing the order of the causes of saluation and damnation, according to Gods word. A view whereof is to be seene in the table annexed. Hereunto is adioyned the order which M. Theodore Beza vsed in comforting afflicted consciences</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Jackson (Jacson), Ralph 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Thomas 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Porter, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 184, 14, 185-524, 4, 525-570, 2, 571-684, 2, 685-711, 3, 713-771, 3, 773-830, 4, 831-906, 4, 907-1057, 1 page, 7 leavesof plates, tables, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="290"/>
   <head>To the right Honourable Edward, Lord Russell Earle of Bedford: Grace and peace be multiplied.</head>
   <p>RIght Honourable, if you consider what is one of the chiefest orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this Noble state, vnto which God hath aduanced you: it wil appeare, that there is none more excellent then <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Zach. 12.12.</hi>
      </note> the spirit of grace and prayer. For what doth your heart affect? would you speake the languages? Behold, by prayer you may speak the most heauenly tongue that euer was, <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Esa. 9.12 Rom. 15.6</hi>
      </note> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the language of Canaan. Would you haue the valor of knighthood? By prayer you may stand in place where Gods hande hath <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap> 23. psal. 59.16</hi>
      </note> made a breach, and doe as much as <note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>2. king. 2.</hi>
      </note> all the chariots and horsmen in a kingdom. Would you inioy Gods blessings which you wāt? By praier you may (as it were) put your hand in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the cofers of Gods treasures <note n="e" place="margin">
         <hi>Matth. 7.7.</hi>
      </note> &amp; inrich your selfe. Doe you desire the fauour of Monarks and Princes? By praier you may come in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence and haue speech with <hi>Iehova</hi> the king of heauen and earth. Lastly, would you know, whether now liuing you be dead, that beeing
<pb facs="290"/>
dead you may liue for euer? By prayer a man may knowe, whether hee bee dead to sinne, dead to the world, liue to God, liue to Christ and liue eternally.</p>
   <p>Prayer then, beeing so excellent a point of Religion: I am imboldened to commend this small treatise to your Honour: not so much for it selfe, as because it doth set out the matter and true manner of inuocation of Gods holy name. And I hope for your fauour in accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of it, the rather, because I doubt not but your desire is to be answerable to your most honourable, &amp; for religion most worthy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors, in the care of maintaining and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing any good thing that may any way serue for the furtherīg of the gospel of Christ.</p>
   <p>Nowe Iesus Christ our Lord, and God e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the Father which hath loued vs, &amp; giuen vs euerlasting consolation, and good hope through grace, stablish your Honour in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good word and worke to the end.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your H. to command, <hi>William Perkins.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>