<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114688_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00535</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10675</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114688</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe refutation of Iohn Traskes iudaical and nouel fancyes : Stiling himselfe Minister of Gods Word, imprisoned for the lawes eternall perfection, or God's lawes perfect eternity. By B. D. Catholike Deuine</title>
                 <author>Falconer, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>102, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Controuersies han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled in this short Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise are two: The first is of the Iewes Sabaoth, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolically translated into the euer memorable day of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours Resurection. The second, whether al forts of meates may be lawfully now eaten by Christiās: disputed against <hi>Iohn Traske,</hi> of a Puritan minister lately grown halfe a lew in his singular opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerning the old Sabaoth, and Moysaical difference of meates, held by him &amp; many other men and women, obstinately professing and practising the same doctrines, as morall Lawes
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>
vnreapealed by Christ, and necessari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly now to be obserued by Christians. His only learning is a litterall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Scriptures, and some little Hebrew and Greeke lately learned for the better vnderstanding of them: which alone he holdeth sufficient, not only to instruct vs in al points of faith, but to direct vs also in our particuler thoughtes, speaches, &amp; actions; so as no māner of speach is by Christians to be vsed, no meate to be eatē, no kind of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell to be worne &amp;c. not particularly expressed and warranted in Scripture. Humāe iudgment &amp; experience (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are originally taught to discerne the naturall goodnes and euil of al our actions, and to make a conscience of them) being so little regarded by him, as he ridiculously deemeth it not to be any rule at all to direct Christian men in common manners and morality of life; God himselfe hauing by a higher law contayned in the old &amp; new Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, particulerly instructed them in
<pb n="5" facs="3"/>
all holy and needfull knowledge.</p>
   <p>Out of which ground he deduceth, as I shall haue seuerall occasions to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare afterwards, strange Conclusions &amp; Distinctions not easy to be distintly knowne &amp; refuted by any learned man that hath not from his owne mouth hard them. This was my chiefe reasō to write these two Controuersies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him, wherby sōe of his disciples may peraduenture be reclaymed from his grosse doctrines; and other it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching eared people now inclinable to his Sect, may be moued vtterly to forsake him. And one soule so hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pely gayned to a neerer degree of truth, will make me thinke a few spare houres well bestowed from bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter studies. Learned men also will gladly, perchance, spare an idle houre or two to read a new Controuersy, breifly, as I could contriue it, and plainly expressed. Smaller errours, and of lesse consequence then these nouell fancies of <hi>Traske</hi> haue
<pb n="6" facs="4"/>
been by sundry holy Fathers answered in large volums, which may well serue to shew my labours not wholy needles.</p>
   <p>Little sparkes of fire not timely quenched, soone grow into flames, that deuoure houses and Citties. Small wounds waxe festered soares, when they are not speedily cured. Single seedes of tare and cockle sowne in fields amongst good Corne make great bundles in haruest, fit only for combustion. And the miserable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of these latter times aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with nouel &amp; heretical doctrines, witnesseth, that as plaguy people are for feare of infecting others carefully to be secluded; and small leakes in a ship are speedily to be stopped for the safety of such persons as sayle in it: so all morall and pious diligence is by Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours and Guiders of soules to be vsed for the timely preuention and suppressing of pernicious opinions, with which <hi>Traske</hi> is so stored, as he is in very few pointes of our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
<pb n="7" facs="4"/>
fayth rightly persuaded.</p>
   <p>He hath 8. arguments to proue that <hi>Melchisedech</hi> was the holy Ghost mentioned <hi>Genes. 14. Hebr.</hi> 7. He is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly assured, that he himselfe hath truly repented, and is made sure of his eternall election in Christ: and that he can in this life neither sinne, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent any more. Likewis, he is able to collect out of Scripture when <hi>Abraham, Isaac, Iacob</hi> and other Saints were truly. penitent and iustified in Gods sight: and will often presume to tell his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, whether at all, or when, they truly repented. Yea he is able, as I haue heard, by Phisiognomy, to make certaine ghesses whether parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular persons shal be damned or saued. His owne and his disciples prayers are commonly roaringes, and such loud out-cries as may be heard in distant roomes and houses, voluntarily fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and filled for the most part with frequent imprecations, that God would confound the aduersaries and
<pb n="8" facs="5"/>
persecutors of his little flocke, such as walke in the lust of their owne flesh, eating like the Idolatrous Gentiles all prohibited and vncleane meates; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaning his holy Sabaoth, and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging it into another day neuer coman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by him, but by themselues inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; Frequently rendring thankes to God for keeping them so holy as hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto he hath done, and desiring him according to their vprightnes to blesse and protect them.</p>
   <p>Pretended reuelations also are not wanting amongst them. He will tell you of straung abstinences from food and other great austerities vsed by himselfe, notwithstanding his chee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes seeme full, and his body still fatt and in good liking. He will with great glory vtter the singular approuement made of him in his Ministeriall ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when other Countrey Schollers were reiected, himselfe hauing neuer byn more thē a guest in any Vniuersity. His excellency aboue others was chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="9" facs="5"/>
occasioned by a perfect Summe of all Diuinity, only abstracted by his owne Confession out of <hi>Musculus</hi> his cōmon Places. When he was a school<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>master at a Gentlemans house in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mersetshire</hi> to a few Grammer scholers, he could write and speake pure latin, as he grauely tould one of his fellow prisoners, which in his riper and matu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer studies since of Diuinity, he hath quite forgotten, and altered his <hi>Cicero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> wonted stile into the humble and plaine phrase of Scripture; and indeed much more barbarous. When he was reprehended by an Aduersary for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the <hi>minor</hi> of an <hi>enthimeme,</hi> he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in excuse of his grosse ignorance <hi>Rhamus</hi> logique, only affirming an <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thimeme</hi> to be an imperfect sillogisme, and sayd, that <hi>Ramists</hi> and <hi>Aristotelians</hi> could not vnderstand each others termes and manner of disputing but after much practise togeather. He will bragge of many bookes written, and some of them dedicated by him to his
<pb n="10" facs="6"/>
Maiesty, who because he eateth not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly swines flesh, he supposeth by his Princely nature halfe framed and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to imbrace and professe his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, which he is confident to haue generally one day held in our English, and all other Protestant Churches.</p>
   <p>Hearing that <hi>Maister Howes</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuer &amp; Augmenter of <hi>Maister Stowes</hi> cronicle was desirous to see him, out of a vaine desire to haue al circumstances of his person and opinions historically blazed, he wrote a letter to <hi>Maister Howes</hi> fully to informe him of both, mentioning therein the day, order, &amp; continuance of his imprisonment, if he listed so to recount them. He wil tel you how many publique Lectures he made weekly with great applause du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his aboad with <hi>Maister Drake</hi> in Deuonshire, and how his chamber lay open besides to all comers, day and night for priuate instruction, shewing himselfe a Foole, if not a Pharisy, in affecting humane prayses so palpably,
<pb n="11" facs="6"/>
in all his speaches and actions.</p>
   <p>Two of disciples only vnderstand Latin aswell as himselfe: the one a poore seduced Gentleman, better skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Hebrew then himself, and equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conuersant in Scripture: the other a Comfit-maker, who lately vndertooke by <hi>Traskes</hi> directions, as is probably guessed, to publish his doctrinall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusions, &amp; to defend them against <hi>M. Crashaw</hi> who hath writē an idle &amp; loose refutation of them. For contrary to his common Pulpit-doctrine, and raylinges against Catholikes, for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting traditions and pointes of faith not contayned in Scripture, he suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth without further proofe, that Christ in conuersation with his Apostles af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Resurrection, taught our kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the Sunday in place of the Sabaoth, that being a meere Tradition no where mentioned in Scripture. Which sortes of aduantage are craftely obserued by <hi>Traske</hi> in all conferences of learned Protestantes with him,
<pb n="12" facs="7"/>
&amp; he will not sticke in answering their arguments deduced from the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and vniuersall practise of Christs Church in all ages before him, to tell them, that they fight against him with the Catholikes borrowed wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, and in their strokes at him, wound themselues more deeply, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing most opinions of their own faith, which are as strange and vnheard of, till within the last 100. yeares, as his doctrines, and equally repugnant to the ancient authority and knowne practise of all Christendome in times past. So that if his ground of admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting no doctrine not expressed in Scripture be shaken, their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will totter also. For the same authenticall testimonies of antiquity which serue to proue the Apostolicall obseruation of the Sunday, do likewise mentiō Liturgies &amp; Massing Sacrifices celebrated by Christians in their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique sinaxes and meetings on festi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall and dominicall dayes, testified by
<pb n="13" facs="7"/>
S. <hi>Augustine serm. 251. de tempore,</hi> by <hi>S. Cyprian de oper. &amp; eleemosyn.</hi> by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the <hi>Agathen Councell cap.</hi> 47. by the 6. <hi>Oecumenicall Councell cap.</hi> 8. and sundry other ancient authors.</p>
   <p>His <hi>Ipse dixit,</hi> and sole assertion is a sufficient rule of fayth to all his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, among whom if any chance to grow wiser (as many of them lately haue done) and to depart from his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, he will seeme to haue formerly feared &amp; foreknown that mans frailty and finall reprobation. Thus not long since he dealt with one of them, who notwithstanding then protested that <hi>Traske</hi> had heertofore vnder his owne hand warranted his true repentance, and eternall election in Christ Iesus, though passion at that time transpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him to make a contrary iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of him.</p>
   <p>There is nothing more trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some to him and his disciples, then to be tearmed ignorant or absurd in any of their assertions. And albeit himselfe
<pb n="14" facs="8"/>
seemeth modest and temperate in his speaches and carriage: yet anger and malice hidden in his hart, soone brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth out, vpon very small occasions, into rayling and ill tearmes, such as himselfe will condemne in others by many Texts of Scripture. Which his dangerous disposition tryed by one of his Protestant fellow-prisoners and other personall facts I purposely heere forbeare to relate, hauing more authenticall testimonies against him.</p>
   <p>His frequent Solecismes when now and then he boulteth out a word or line of Latin, as to say: <hi>Index expur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorium &amp;c</hi> are for quietnes sake to be accounted but <hi>lapsus linguae,</hi> vnfit to be tould him. His barbarismes in speaking or writing must passe currently as <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braismes</hi> and Scripture-phrases: and all his arguments are to be accounted no other then formall and conuincing demonstrations. Among which for proofe that S. <hi>Peter</hi> and the Apostles
<pb n="15" facs="8"/>
still obserued the legall difference of meates, this one for example is his <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chylles,</hi> written to my knowledg by him in three seuerall discourses sent to one of his fellow-prisoners.</p>
   <q>
      <p>Qui ambulat in praecepto veteri recepto à Patre, ambulat secundum legem discrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis inter animal quod comeditur, &amp; animal: quod non comeditur.</p>
      <p>Sed Petrus ambulauit in praecepto veteri recepto à Patre.</p>
      <p>Ergo ambulauit secundum legem discri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis inter animal quod comeditur, &amp; animal quod non comeditur.</p>
   </q>
   <p>
      <hi>Thus Englished.</hi>
   </p>
   <q>
      <p>He that walketh in the old Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment receaued from the Father, walketh according to the Law of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the liuing creature that is to be eaten, and the liuing creature that is not to be eaten.</p>
      <p>But <hi>Peter</hi> walked in the old Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment &amp;c.</p>
   </q>
   <p>If you tell him first that his syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gisme is tedious and composed in bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Latin, vnfit to come from the
<pb n="16" facs="9"/>
pen of an ancient schoolmaister and professed Grammarian: He wil falsely tell you that <hi>Praecepto veteri recepto à Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre &amp;c.</hi> is the expresse phrase of <hi>S. Iohn</hi> in his first Canonicall Epistle.</p>
   <p>If you further tell him, that his argument is ridiculous in sense and forme, as hauing no <hi>medium</hi> at all in the premises to proue the conclusion; <hi>to walke in the old Commaundement &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>to walke according to the law of difference &amp;c</hi> being in sense all one, in wordes only changed. He will more absurdly tel you, that <hi>by the old Commandment &amp;c.</hi> he meant Gods precept giuen to <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradise, which all learned men know to haue byn a personall precept of abstayning from the fruite of one tree, not cōcerning <hi>S. Peter</hi> afterwards or any Christian, more then to the generall knowne doctrine of Adams transgression therof fearefully puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed in his posterity. And to deterre his aduersary from laughing at this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, and other more ridiculous
<pb n="17" facs="9"/>
passages of his papers, he added this <hi>Caueat</hi> for a graue conclusion, or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable sentence of instruction.</p>
   <p>
      <q>Si fortè dum loquutus fuero, post<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum verò sermonem meum subsannato.</q> If when peraduenture I shall haue spoken; but afterwards laugh at my speach. Wherein any learned man may plainely see indeed his wonted Ciceronian style strangely altered.</p>
   <p>By reading in <hi>Eusebius</hi> history <hi>lib. 1. cap.</hi> 22. how Saint <hi>Policarpe</hi> and other holy Bishops of <hi>Asia</hi> obserued the Iewes time of keeping Easter, he and his disciples are lately therein resolued to imitate them. And that which he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer read of <hi>S. Policarpe</hi> or any Christian Doctor before him, he hath added to his Easter the festiuall obseruance of Azimes, as is probably guessed by all his fellow prisoners; seing him and his disciples after the fourtenth of March moone to eate contrary to their custo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me at other times, white vnleauened loaues, and seeming in his speaches to
<pb n="18" facs="10"/>
allow of the obseruance of that festi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity, albeit of the manner he be som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doubtfull, as peraduenture, whether it must be with a Phascall Lambe eaten &amp;c.</p>
   <p>He esteemeth it no arrogancy or pride of iudgment in him to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent in his doctrines from all known Christians, either liuing now, or in any age before him. Neither will he yield it to be a dangerous nouelty and notable giddines in him to change, and coyne at his pleasure weekly do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines; defending them with such peremptory pride of iudgment, as if he had receaued cleare and certaine reuelations therof.</p>
   <p>The order of my discourse is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sy to be discerned by the titles of my questions in both Controuersyes. My manner of writing is to declare and refute his assertions with as much bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity and plainesse as I could contriue ech question. I cite not many authors for any opinions, both because my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersary
<pb n="19" facs="10"/>
contemneth such proofes, as also for that I want the cōmodity of a Library to collect them. I haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentionally written this Preface to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer <hi>Traskes</hi> opinions, not to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace his person, further then I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued personall circumstances fitly vttered to expresse fully the grounds and occasions of his doctrines: hauing to authorize me therein sundry examples of great Saints, not sparing to relate grosser passages, then heere I haue done, of their Heresiarchicall Aduersaryes, who as Diuells in their fearefull apparitions by platter-eyes, clouen feete, or stinking smells are wont to be discerned: so they truly wolues in sheeps garments, are by le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity of Doctrine, pride of iudgment, and other personall demeanours easily discouered to want the innocent hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble nature of lambes, conterfaited by them. And as he that putteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe on a stage to play the Fooles part, must patiently expect laughter
<pb n="20" facs="11"/>
from his beholders: so <hi>Traske</hi> broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching his hereticall fancies, must pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently prepare himselfe to be more then smiled at by iudicious Readers.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>