<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Obseruations for Diet.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114964_Fr1_11</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20583</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6988</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114964</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Obseruations for Diet.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Rams little Dodeon [sic] : A briefe epitome of the new herbal, or history of plants. Wherein is contayned the disposition and true declaration of the phisike helpes of all sortes of herbes and plants, vnder their names and operations, not onely of those which are here in this our Countrey of England growing but of all others also of other realmes, countreyes and nations vsed in phisike: Collected out of the most exquisite newe herball, or history of plants, first set forth in the Dutch or Almayne tongue, by ... D. Reinbert Dodeon, ... and lately translated into English by Henry Lyte, ... and now collected and abbridged by William Ram, Gent. Pandit oliua suos Ramos</title>
                 <author>Dodoens, Rembert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <publisher>Stafford, Simon.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>43, 213 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="observations">
   <pb facs="22"/>
   <head>Obseruations for Diet.</head>
   <list>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Prime time. Chickens, &amp; Egs in mooneshew,</item>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Prime time. Kids with vergis, &amp; Roches,</item>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Prime time. Borage, &amp; Perches,</item>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Prime time. Beetes, &amp; Pikrelles,</item>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Prime time. Yolks of egges, &amp; All scale fish.</item>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Haruest time. Capons,</item>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Haruest time. Hennes,</item>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Haruest time. Pigeons,</item>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Haruest time. Good wines,</item>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Haruest time. Good drinks.</item>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Sūmer time. Light meates, &amp; Melons,</item>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Sūmer time. Chickens w<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vergis, &amp; Gourds,</item>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Sūmer time. Yong Hares, &amp; Cucumers,</item>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Sūmer time. Rabbets, &amp; Peares,</item>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Sūmer time. Lettice, &amp; Plume,</item>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Sūmer time. Purcelain, &amp; &amp; the fish afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said.</item>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Winter time. Béefe, and Partriches,</item>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Winter time. Porke, and Phesants,</item>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Winter time. Brawne, and Hares,</item>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Winter time. Harts, and Riuer fowles,</item>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Winter time. Hindes, and Wine,</item>
      <item>Diet for all the yeere. Winter time. Other venison. and Good spices.</item>
      <item>Good to comfort the braine. Smelto Muske, Quibibes, &amp; Camomill: drinke wine moderately: cate Sage not too much: couer thy head: wash oft thy handes and féet: walke measureably: fleep reason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably: delight to heare melodie &amp; singing: eat mustard and pepper: smel to red Roses: wash thy temples with red Rose water.</item>
      <item>
         <pb facs="23"/>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> braine All braines of beasts, and Too much watching,</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> braine Gluttony, and Too much walking,</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> braine Drunkennesse, and Milke,</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> braine Late Supper, and Chéese, and Nuts,</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> braine To sléep after meate, and To eate before hunger,</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> braine Corrupt Ayre, and Bathing after meate,</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> braine Anger, and Ouyons,</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> braine Heauines, and Garlick,</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> braine To vncouer y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> head, and Great noyse,</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> braine To eate softly, and To smel to a white Rose,</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> braine Too much heate, and Much stirring.</item>
      <item>Good for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> eies, Look oft on gold, and Pimpernell,</item>
      <item>Good for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> eies, Red Roses, and Oculus Christi,</item>
      <item>Good for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> eies, Veruin, and Plūge cléere water in y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> eyes.</item>
      <item>Good for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> eies, Rew, and Looke on gréene colour,</item>
      <item>Good for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> eies, Fenell, and Measureable sléepe,</item>
      <item>Good for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> eies, Eufrase, and Wash hands and séet often.</item>
      <item>Euil for the eyes, Garlick, and Lechery,</item>
      <item>Euil for the eyes, Onyons, and Sleepe after noone,</item>
      <item>Euil for the eyes, Hunger, and Much sleeping,</item>
      <item>Euil for the eyes, Leekes, and Much waking,</item>
      <item>Euil for the eyes, Waking, and Bloud letting,</item>
      <item>Euil for the eyes, Winde, and Looking against the fire.</item>
      <item>Euil for the eyes, Hot ayre, and Euill baked bread,</item>
      <item>Euil for the eyes, Cold ayre, and Dust,</item>
      <item>Euil for the eyes, Gluttony, and Wéeping,</item>
      <item>Euil for the eyes, Milke, and Looking against the sun or Moone,</item>
      <item>Euil for the eyes, Chéese. and</item>
      <item>Euil for the eyes, Much to behold, and Bright things,</item>
      <item>Euil for the eyes, Smoke, and Red colour,</item>
      <item>Euil for the eyes, Coleworts, and White colour.</item>
      <item>Good for the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, Red mynts, and Calamynt,</item>
      <item>Good for the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, Red Roses, and To vomit once a quarter,</item>
      <item>Good for the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, Comyn, and Great hunger,</item>
      <item>Good for the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, Sugar, and Euery day to stand after meate,</item>
      <item>Good for the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, Sage, and</item>
      <item>
         <pb facs="23"/>Good for the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, Wormewood, and Oft walking after meate,</item>
      <item>Good for the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, Galingale, and Euery cold thing,</item>
      <item>Good for the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, Nutmegs, and Vineger,</item>
      <item>Good for the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, Measureable sléep, and Pepper.</item>
      <item>Euil for the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, Nuts, and Too much casting,</item>
      <item>Euil for the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, Chéese old, and Too much bathing after meate,</item>
      <item>Euil for the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, Honey, and Too much trauell,</item>
      <item>Euil for the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, Marow not sod, and To eate raw flesh,</item>
      <item>Euil for the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, Heauines, and Bread not baked,</item>
      <item>Euil for the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, Dread, and To eate not hungrie,</item>
      <item>Euil for the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, Falling, and To eate many meates at a meale,</item>
      <item>Euil for the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, Fried meates, and</item>
      <item>Euil for the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, Milke, and To drinke not thirstie,</item>
      <item>Euil for the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, Stowping, and To eate stinking meate.</item>
      <item>Good for the throat, Liquoris, soft Egges, Isop, Sugar-Candie, Hony, Sugar, Butter with a little salt.</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> throat, Mustard, and Too much waking,</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> throat, Much lying on the breast, and Too much Rest,</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> throat, and Much drinke,</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> throat, Pepper, and Smoke of Incence,</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> throat, Anger, and Old chéese,</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> throat, All things rosted, and Much running,</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> throat, Lechery, and Sowre things.</item>
      <item>Good for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> heart, Saffron, and Nutmegs,</item>
      <item>Good for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> heart, Bourage, and Galingale,</item>
      <item>Good for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> heart, Laughing, and Red Roses,</item>
      <item>Good for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> heart, Ioy, and Violets,</item>
      <item>Good for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> heart, Muske, and Sugar,</item>
      <item>Good for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> heart, Cloues, and Maces before all things.</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> heart, Beanes, and Anger,</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> heart, Pease, and Dread,</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> heart, Léekes, and Too much heauinesse,</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> heart, Garlick, and Trauell,</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> heart, Onions, and To drinke cold water after labour.</item>
      <item>Euil for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> heart, Heauinesse, and</item>
   </list>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>