<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Hono∣rable, and Jllustrious LADIE, ANNA CAMBEL; LADIE MARQVES of HVNTLEY, COVN∣TESSE of AENZIE, BADINACH, LOCH∣ABRE, STRADOWN, AND STRABOGIE; LADIE GORDON
&amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114010_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10311</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20596</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114010</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Hono∣rable, and Jllustrious LADIE, ANNA CAMBEL; LADIE MARQVES of HVNTLEY, COVN∣TESSE of AENZIE, BADINACH, LOCH∣ABRE, STRADOWN, AND STRABOGIE; LADIE GORDON
&amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The glorie of man consisting in the excellencie and perfection of woman : Gathered out of Holie Scriptures, and most renowned wryters; as well ancient, as moderne; ecclesiaticall, as morall. Wherevnto is annexed The duetie of husbands</title>
                 <author>Raban, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Raban, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Aberdeen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 911, that is 119, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and Jllustrious LADIE, ANNA CAMBEL; LADIE MARQVES of HVNTLEY, COVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TESSE of AENZIE, BADINACH, LOCH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ABRE, STRADOWN, AND STRABOGIE; LADIE GORDON
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <opener>
      <salute>MADAME,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver my self, from the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Sarcastick, bitter, too loose, &amp; liberall speaches, agaynst the most Noble, Worthie, and Transcendant Sexe of WOMEN, (which some, kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing their own imperfect weaknesse, may apprehend to be
<hi>Calumnies,</hi> and detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue to the whole Sexe) I here make humble Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb facs="3"/> &amp;, with all Reverence, present vnto your Ladiships Honorable Hands, this litle TREATISE; as a part of my Studie, in my wearisome Journie, this halfe yeare by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>past, in forraygne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys.</p>
   <p>Which, indeed, MADAME, I aimed for Your La: the last New-years-day; if di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresse of weather, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie winds, had not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
   <p>But, through the mercie of GOD, your La: Servant being safelie arrived, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire no more, but that this <hi>Abortiue</hi> may shelter it self
<pb facs="3"/> vnder the shadow of Your La: Honourable Affection. Then may I think my selfe happie, and the payns well bestowed.</p>
   <p>Not doubting, but that it shall so plead for me, that by a just judgement of all Your La: most Glorious, Noble, and Gracious Sexe, I shall be pronounced guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse, quyte, and free, from all Aspersion, and Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vnjustlie here to fore layd to my charge.</p>
   <p>How-so-ever, Madame, if eyther this <hi>Subject</hi> maye anie wayes seeme pleasing vnto Your La: or my selfe
<pb facs="4"/> serviceable; all my cited <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors</hi> never thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues halfe so GRACED; as I will continuallie confesse MY FORTVNES HONOVRED.</p>
   <p>And, thus, MOST NOBLE, AND GRACIOVS LADIE,</p>
   <l>
      <hi>With humble Heart, true mynd, and tempred Brayne,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>NED <hi>vowes, Your Sexe poore</hi> PRINTER <hi>to remayne.</hi>
   </l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>