<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Chrysten reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1554</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114649_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09616</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19890</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114649</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Chrysten reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The trew report of the dysputacyon had [and] bego [n] ne in the conuocacyo [n] hows at london among the clargye there assembled the xviij. daye of October in the yeare of our lord M.D.LIIII</title>
                 <author>Philpot, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Emden</pubPlace>
                    <date>1554</date>
                 <publisher>Edmonds, Alexander, pseud.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Gheylliaert (Galliart), Jan.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mierdman (Mierdmans, Nuyts), Steven</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>74 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Chrysten reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not vnknowen to the world / Chrysten reader / what varietie and conten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciō hath bene abowt wey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghti matters of religion for a gret space / which were thought to haue bene so disiussed debated and examined of our clergie / that all men were in hope that such an vniformitie agreable to the word of god / to the doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trine of the patriarkis and apostles &amp; to the order of the primatiue church al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>so / had bene determined for our church of Ingland / that from hensforth one shuld haue liued wyth a nother in moch better vnitie and godli quietnes than in mani yeares before they had done: euery one imbracing one sincere maner of worshipping and inuocacion off god / wythowt any supersticion / ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latrie or hipocrisy that hath in processe of time crept in by the diuise and fanta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sie of mans braine. And the thing was brought to such a point that all men / in maner / were wōn to a wonderfull in
<pb facs="3"/>
differency / and begān to espie their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and errors wherewyth they haue bene heretofore blynded and sedu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced, But the awncient aduersari of mā kind / Satan / which neuer ceaseth to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke how he may destroye the workes of god in vs / enuieng that vnitie in trewe religion that all men of all agis statis and degreys as well high as lowe / had in maner atteyned and were well nigh comne vnto / hath now stirred vp the old cōtenciō agayne bringing the wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke vnlerned and simple sort thereby in to such a dowt and wauering that they can now lesser tell what they may bile<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue and which waye they may steye their faith and constiencys than euer thei could before. But as the great prophete (as Moyses nameth him) the son̄ of god doth prophecy and wytnes / that offēcys must nedis come / and that such offencys shuld come that euen the veri elect / (yff it were possible) shuld be seduced / now we see wyth our eyes and grope wyth our sensys that it is comne to passe and fullfilled euyn among vs. But let them take hede that haue bene
<pb facs="3"/>
the auctors thereoff ffor as it seruyth for the prouing and tryeng of gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect (to whom all thyngs worke to the best) euen so shall it serue to theyr woo and vtter damnacion / as he sayth that knoweth all thingis (ve homini illi per quem scandalum venit) woo vnto that man thorow whom offence doth come. And let the godly sort now reioyse in the crosse of christ / for they haue no lesse cause / for as moch as by this tēpta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyō they haue the same tokē that theyr professyō is the trewe religyō of god / which all the trewe byleuers euermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re frō tyme to time haue had / that is to saye / christys crosse the token that can not deceiue vs / and with owt the wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ich we can not be / yff we will be sure to liue godly in christ / as holy. s. Paul sayth. But now to my purpose as in other poītys moch varietye of opinyōs hatth bene / euyn so in the hygh miste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye of christys sup{per} (which was institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be a sacramēt of cōcord / loue and vnitie) the difference and diuersytie of opyniōs there abowt hath brought to passe that more dyscord / dissension and
<pb facs="4"/>
diuisyon hath growen among men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowt that than in any other one arty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of our chrysten religyon. And the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refor they whos subscripcyon was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyred in the conuocacyon holden at powlys at the last parlament / iudged not amysse / that thought it necessary to reason and dispute therein before they wold subscrybe to any conclusyon or determynate sentēce. And to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that all men may knowe and see what reasons and answers were made on both partys / I haue thought good to publyssh so moch thereoff as came vnto my handis / trusting that no man wyll be more offēded wyth the settyng furth thereoff / to the intēt that such as were not present may reade such thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gys as there were done and sayd / no more than they were that all that were presēt shuld heare them / and iudge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyfferently by the toch stone of gods word / on whych part the truth doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne. Whych / men may well goo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowt to suppresse / but whan they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue done all they cā agaynst it / yet will it owt and haue the ouer hand. God
<pb facs="4"/>
grant that all men may seke and study for the truth and not suffer thē seluys to be caryed abowt nor changed with euery blast of strāge doctrine / nor with euery fantastycall fable of Antychry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stys mynysters. Amen.</p>
   <p>And as by readyng and weyng the reasōs and answers of thys dysputaciō I dowt not but thow shalt be sussyciē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly confyrmed in the truth of the arty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles thereī reasoned and debated / euyn so in a lytle treatyse of the trewe sacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce of a christē mā which by gods gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce shall shortly also be set furth / thow shalt be instructed what to iudge off o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther artycles / as of the masse / of alta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rys / of the inuocatyon of sayntys / and such lyke. And now that we see how gods wrath is bent ouer our nacyon / that we may now well saye wyth da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd / O god / heathen peple are ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryd in to thyne inherytans. (For now Antychrystys generacyō thinck to sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish their kyngdō in Inglād for euer) let all faythfull hartis yoyne them sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis together in vnfayned and cōtynu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all prayer that god will haue mercy vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on vs
<pb facs="5"/>
and defend vs against them / that the light of his word which hath now nys shyned vp on vs o may both be preserued among vs / and also preserue vs agaynst all the practises and enterpry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of hys enemies Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>