<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most Gracious and Reuerend Father in Christ, IOHN by the proui∣dence of God Lord Archbishop of Canter∣burie, Primate of all England and Metro∣politane, and one of her Maiesties most Honorable priuie Councell.</title>
           <author>Pie, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114788_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09632</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19900</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114788</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most Gracious and Reuerend Father in Christ, IOHN by the proui∣dence of God Lord Archbishop of Canter∣burie, Primate of all England and Metro∣politane, and one of her Maiesties most Honorable priuie Councell.</title>
                 <author>Pie, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An houreglasse : contayning I a computation from the beginning of time to Christ by X. articles. II A confirmation of the same for the times controuersed before Christ: as also that there wanteth a yeare after Christ, in the vsuall computation. With other matters, offered to the iudgement of the learned, and vse of the studious in chronologie and historie. By Thomas Pie Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Pie, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Robinson, Robert</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 98, 8 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the most Gracious and Reuerend <hi>Father in Christ,</hi> IOHN <hi>by the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> of God Lord Archbishop of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie, <hi>Primate of all England and</hi> Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politane, and one of her Maiesties most <hi>Honorable priuie Councell.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>OW necessarie and requisite Chronologie is in the studie of all Historie, Diuine or Humane, it being the right eye thereof, as Geographie is the left: there is no man, vnlesse he be blinde of both eyes, but may easily discerne and will freely confesse. Without which we cannot but wander in the estate &amp; affaires of the world as <hi>Polyphemus</hi> in his caue, and be tossed in the vast Ocean of Historie, as a Pilot without the Northstarre, discerning nothing in the mayne course thereof, but an huge heape of diffused matter. For which cause <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus</hi> is so sharpe in reprehending both <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Xenophon,</hi> for misnoting the times of some stories; and <hi>Thucidides</hi> findeth the same fault with <hi>Hellanicus, Dionysius</hi> with <hi>Fabius Pictor, Plutarch</hi> with <hi>Thucidides,</hi> for misdating the Ostracisme of <hi>Themistocles,</hi> and the Raigne of <hi>Artaxerxes;</hi> and <hi>Tullie</hi> with certaine before him, which made <hi>Numa</hi> to be the schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> who was borne not a fewe yeares, but whole ages after <hi>Numa.</hi> And therefore it is the more straunge that
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Ouid</hi> after him should fall into the same errour.<note place="margin">Hieron. ad Nepot. de vica cleri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cali.</note>
      <hi>Hierome</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to <hi>Nepotian</hi> of vnlearned preachers in his time, alleageth this example out of an Oration of <hi>Tully</hi> for <hi>Quintus Gallus</hi> (which now is not extant:) <q>
         <hi>Quidam Poeta nominatus, homo</hi> perliteratus, cujus suntilla Colloquia Poetarum &amp; Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorum, cum facit Euripidem &amp; Menandrum intersese, &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio loco Socratem &amp; Epicurum disserentes, quorū aetates non annis, sed saeculis scimus esse disiunctas; quantos is plausus &amp; clamores mouet? multos enim condiscipulos habet in Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro, qui simul literas non didicerunt.</q> Doubtlesse, had <hi>Tullie</hi> himselfe beene there, or at the sermons of <hi>Hieroms</hi> vnlearned preachers, (I would God our age were voyde of the like,) he would haue exclamed,<note place="margin">Ad Atti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum. li. 6.</note> as he did of one <hi>Metellus,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pem! Oh foule ignorance of Historie!</hi> It is a wonder to see the Beauperes of the Lawe, <hi>Bartolus</hi> and <hi>Paulus Castrensis,</hi> rouing at Randon about the time and age of <hi>Papinian</hi> and <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cletian,</hi> and that when they handle the same of purpose for the reconciliation of certaine lawes: and a verie world to behold the great Antiquaries of the <hi>Saxons,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Specul. Saxon. li. 3. ca. 43. Alb. Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denfis ad annū 917. Epiph cont. haer. l. 7. tom. 3. Socrates li. 5. ca. 21. Lact. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin. instit. li. 4. ca. 5. Aug. de doctr. Ch. li. 2. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract li. 2. De ciuit. Dei li. 18.</note> auerring that their first aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors were <hi>Alexanders</hi> Macedonian companies, which assoone as <hi>Alexander</hi> was dead, arriued in <hi>Germanie,</hi> euen iump at that time, when <hi>Theodorik</hi> king of <hi>Frankes</hi> had warre with <hi>Ermifrid</hi> king of <hi>Thuringians;</hi> which was little lesse than a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand yeares after <hi>Alexander:</hi> and the great Historicians of the <hi>Danes, Iohannes Magnus</hi> Archbishop of <hi>Vpsala, Pantaleon</hi> and <hi>Heminges,</hi> making <hi>Dan</hi> the Archege and Grandsire of the <hi>Danes,</hi> to be equall in antiquitie to <hi>Gedeon,</hi> who was at the least a thousand yeares after <hi>Gedeon.</hi> And therefore the lesse maruell, that the great Fathers in Diuinitie are sometime out of their numbers too; as <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> mistaking the death of <hi>Iustin Martyr</hi> to be vnder <hi>Adrian: Socrates,</hi> misplacing the martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Polycarpus</hi> to be vnder <hi>Gordian: Lactantius</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that <hi>Moses</hi> was <hi>900</hi> yeare before the Troian warre: and <hi>Augustin</hi> himselfe likewise, auouching that <hi>Plato</hi> went into <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> in the time of <hi>Ieremie</hi> the prophet; and producing <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brose</hi> for a witnesse thereof, though afterward he both confesse
<pb facs="3"/>
the misciting of <hi>Ambrose,</hi> and also acknowledge that <hi>Plato</hi> was borne after <hi>Ezra</hi> his time.</p>
   <p>But it is not my purpose here to imitate <hi>Castor Rhodius;</hi> who as <hi>Suidas</hi> recordeth, hath written in large volumes <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>Errours of time and Ignorances of Historie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In ancient time, the <hi>Pagans</hi> so out faced and ouerbore the <hi>Christians</hi> with such mistaken Histories, antedated and forged authorities, worne and worme-eaten antiquities, that the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians</hi> were constrained to bestow more time and diligence in that studie: as among other <hi>Eusebius,</hi> and before him <hi>Clemens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrinus</hi> haue performed that part most painfully and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; whose tract other since haue diligentlie traced.</p>
   <p>And albeit many in our time haue laboured in this argument, with great paines and no lesse praise, whose candle my selfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> scarse worthy to hold; yet finding none of them all, fully to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent me in the mayne Computation of the yeares of the worlde, or thorowly to cleare that principall account, being the grounde of Chronologie, and as it were the maine bodie, whereout all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Computations as branches doe spring: no man, I hope, will blame my indeuours, eyther for wading further in the broken yce to finde out the trueth, or for diuulging my opinion and reasons in this naked shadow and short delineation: since it is done to this ende, that the iudgement of the learned may be had thereof, not that the coniectures of other should be preiudiced thereby, as I would not haue the conceites or authoritie of any to preiudice or forestall the trueth. It was truely said of <hi>Seneca</hi> to <hi>Lucilius,</hi> of all partes of learning generally, and it is verified of this specially,<note place="margin">Epist. l. 8. ep. 7.</note>
      <hi>Multum egerunt qui fuerunt ante nos, sed non peregerunt.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Besides this, great men imployed in great matters, busied with waightie affaires, and bestowing their studie in the greater partes of learning, haue not that libertie and quiet leasure, which these <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> and lesser studies doe require. Which since the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie hath vouchsafed me, as I take it for no small benefite of his goodnes, especially in these euill times, and very dogdaies of the Church and Religion, which now lie together in a desperate paroxisme and most dangerous fitte, ioyntly shaken and assaulted
<pb facs="4"/>
by Poperie and Atheisme, and daily weakned, yea hazarded by both, but that the zealous care of her sacred Maiestie, and the carefull foresight of her Honourable counsaile holdeth in life: so I thought it my duetie to imploy some part thereof in these smal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and lower argumentes, which greater matters will not suffer other men to stand about and thorowly to looke into. Which la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of mine (if the lownesse thereof in regard of your Highnes breede not too great a disparage) I hight as wholly due to your Grace, in respect not onely of the common right, in that you are the highest person and chiefest patron of my profession; or of that speciall interest, in that you are the Visitor and Ouerseer of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> Colledge my tender parent, but also euen of a certaine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie, which your Grace in regard of many benefites aboue other hath in me, now that I am bereft of that Reuerend Father D. <hi>Bickleie</hi> late L. Bishop of <hi>Chichester, Qui nobis haec otia fecit.</hi> Wherefore crauing pardon for my boldnesse heerein, I humblie submit this short treatise to your Graces censure and fauour, and with daily prayers commit your Grace to all the blessinges of the Almightie. <hi>September. 1597.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces most bounden: <hi>THOMAS PIE.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>