<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE TRVLY NO∣BLE
AND MOST HOPE∣FVLL
MR. WILLIAM HOVVARD,
third and youngest Sonne to the Right Ho∣norable
THOMAS Earle of Arundell
and Surrey, Earle Marshall of
England, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114333_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09195</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19502</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114333</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE TRVLY NO∣BLE
AND MOST HOPE∣FVLL
MR. WILLIAM HOVVARD,
third and youngest Sonne to the Right Ho∣norable
THOMAS Earle of Arundell
and Surrey, Earle Marshall of
England, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The compleat gentleman : fashioning him absolute in the most necessary &amp; commendable qualities concerning minde or bodie that may be required in a noble gentlema [n] . By Henry Peacham. Mr. of Arts sometime of Trinity Coll: in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Constable, Francis</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 124, 129-162, 161-172, 1, 170-211, 1 page, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                    <term>Heraldic works and genealogies</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE TRVLY NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE
AND MOST HOPE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FVLL
M<seg rend="sup">R</seg>. WILLIAM HOVVARD,
third and youngest Sonne to the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable
THOMAS Earle of Arundell
and Surrey, Earle Marshall of
England, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat Motiue (Noble Sir) may
induce others in their Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations,
I know not: sure I am
none other hath incited me,
then the regard of your owne
worth, and that natiue inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuitie
and goodnesse of Spirit,
I haue euer perceiued in you, since it was my
good hap to enioy your acquaintance, and to
spend some houres with you at your Booke in
<hi>Norwich;</hi> where at this present you haue your
education vnder the Reuerend, Religious, and
my Honorable good Lord, the now Lord Bishop
of <hi>Norwich.</hi> And indeed, to whom rather of
right should appertaine these my <hi>Instructions,</hi> in
regard of their subiect, which is the fashioning of
<pb facs="4"/>
Nobilitie after the best Presidents, then to your
selfe euery way so Nobly descended. Beside, it is
affirmed, that there are certaine sparkes and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
seeds of vertue innate in Princes, and the
Children of Noble personages; which (if che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished,
and carefully attended in the blossome)
will yeild the fruit of Industry and glorious Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
not onely aboue the strength of the vulgar,
but euen in the scient, and before the time Nature
hath appointed.<note place="margin">Pindar. in Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sis, Ode 3.</note> So <hi>Achilles,</hi> while hee was yet
very young, vndertooke to shoote the fiercest Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
and Boares, and was so nimble on foote, that
he was able to take a wilde Beast without either
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oyle or Dogge.<note place="margin">Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>es Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nach. in vita Alexandri.</note>
      <hi>Alexander</hi> also, when an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian</hi>
Priest saluted him, being very young, by
the names of Son and Child, replyed; But you
shall finde me a Man before the walls of <hi>Athens.</hi>
But to omit Heathenish examples,<note place="margin">Regum 1. cap. 3. ver. 9.</note>
      <hi>Salomon</hi> wee
reade, when he was but euen a child, begged wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
of God, and grace to gouerne well: and
<hi>Ignatius,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ignatius lib. Epist. cap. 3.</note> that holy Martyr writeth, <hi>Salomon</hi> was
scarce 12. years of age, when he decided that hard
controuersie betweene the two Harlots: so <hi>Iosias</hi>
was but eight years old, when he walked religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously
before God. And mee thinkes (Sir) as in
that <hi>Cornelian</hi> Stemme (whereof <hi>Scipio</hi> was said
to be the top, and <hi>In quo (vt plura genera in vnam
arborem) videtur infita multorum illuminata sapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cicero.</note>)
already you grow apace, reflecting as from
a faire Glasse, that Princely Moderation and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesty
of heart, of the good Duke your great
Grand-father, the Honourably disposed mind of
<pb facs="4"/>
my Lord, your Noble Father, together with his
loue and admiration, of whatsoeuer is honest or
excellent: so that verily you need no other pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne
to the absolute shaping of your selfe, then
the Images of your fore-fathers.<note place="margin">Arist. in E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis.</note> But as <hi>Aristotle</hi>
saith of the Vine, by how much it is laden with
Clusters, by so much it hath need of props: so
say I of Greatnesse and Nobilitie, euer fruitfull,
and apt to abundance, it hath hourely need of
support and helpe, by all timely aduice and instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
to guide and vphold it from lying along.</p>
   <p>Wherefore, since the Fountaine of all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell
and Instruction, next to the feare of God, is
the knowledge of good learning, whereby our
affections are perswaded, and our ill manners mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified,
I heere present you with the first and plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest
Directions (though but as so many keies to
leade you into far fairer roomes) and the readiest
Method I know for your studies in general, and to
the attaining of the most commendable qualities
that are requisite in euery Noble or Gentle-man.
Nothing doubting, but that after you haue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
seene the worth and excellence of Learning,
how much it addeth to <hi>Nobilitie;</hi> what errors are
hourely comitted through <hi>Ignorance;</hi> how sweet
a thing it is to conuerse with the wisest of all
Ages by Historie; to haue in-sight into the most
pleasing and admirable Sciences of the <hi>Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques,
Poetrie, Picture, Heraldrie,</hi> &amp;c. (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
I heere intreat, together with the most com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable
exercise of the body, with other gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
directions for Carriage, Trauaile, &amp;c.) you
<pb facs="5"/>
will entertaine this Discourse, as <hi>Vlysses</hi> did <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerua</hi>
at his elbow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> your guide to knowledge; the
ground, not onely of the sweetest, but the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piest
life. And though I am assured there are num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,
who (notwithstanding all the Bookes and
Rules in the world) had rather then behold the
face of heauen, burie themselues in earthly sloath,
and basest idlenesse; yet M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>William Howard</hi> at
the least, let vs recouer you from the tyrannie of
these ignorant times, and from the common Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation;
which is, to weare the best cloathes, eate,
sleepe, drinke much, and to know nothing. I take
leaue, from my house at <hi>Hogsd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n</hi> by <hi>London,</hi> May
30.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Who is, and shall be euer yours, <hi>HENRY PEACHAM.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>