<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE COVR∣teous Reader.</title>
           <author>C., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114465_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09383</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19680</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114465</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE COVR∣teous Reader.</title>
                 <author>C., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A commentarie or exposition, vpon the fiue first chapters of the Epistle to the Galatians: penned by the godly, learned, and iudiciall diuine, Mr. W. Perkins. Now published for the benefit of the Church, and continued with a supplement vpon the sixt chapter, by Rafe Cudwort Bachelour of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 475, that is 457, 7, 459-522, 525-662, 34 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>TO THE COVR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> Here offer to thy view (gentle Reader) a Comment, and a Supplement: the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment begunne by an excellent worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and drawne in excellent proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in all points suting to the analogie of faith, and the doctrine of the Orthodoxe Fathers of the Church, beeing the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of his three yeares Lectures vpon the Lords day. If his former workes ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Positiue Diuinitie in sundrie of his Treatises, or Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall Diuinitie in his <hi>Reformed Catholike,</hi> or Case-Diuinitie in his <hi>Cases of Conscience,</hi> haue ministred any comfort vnto thee, or giuen thee content: I doubt not but these Commentaries will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly satisfie thy expectation. For (to omit the varietie of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as also the breuitie and admirable perspicuitie, in regard of the manner, beeing the chiefest commendation of <hi>Oecumenius</hi> or any Interpreter) in them as in a mirrour thou maist more clearely see his knowledge in the mysterie of Christ; and his dexteritie in exempli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying <note place="margin">Eph. 3. 4.</note> that by practise which he had formerly taught by <note n="o" place="margin">In his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetica.</note> precept, thē in any of his writings besides: as hauing a double eminencie aboue the rest. First, in that they were penned the last of all his workes, beeing come to ripenes of iudgement: and that vpon mature deliberation after his Sermons (as his manner was.) Secondly, in that they were written with his owne hand, whereas all his other writings (except some short Treatises) were taken by some diligent auditors, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>used by himselfe. Herein resembling the Epistle it selfe, which was written with <hi>Pauls</hi> owne hand: all the rest (except that short one to <note place="margin">Gal. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Philemon) by his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ribes. And as they doe exceede his other Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, <note place="margin">Phil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m. v. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>8.</note>
      <pb facs="6"/>
so I might say (perhaps more truly then discreetly) that they surpasse in this kinde, all the moderne writers that haue gone before them: so that he which will vouchsafe to read them, shall not greatly neede nor desire any other Interpreter vpon this Scripture: the which I speake not as esteeming of Antiquitie no better worth then to be put vnder a bushell, that Noueltie might be set vpon the candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticke: but for that I see not, but that <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> the last of all <note place="margin">Ioh 5. 35.</note> the Prophets, was as goodly a burning and shining candle, as any of the rest: and that he pointed forth Christ more distinctly then the <note place="margin">Ioh. 2. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> rest. But I hope I shall not neede to vse many words in commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on either of the worke, or of the Author, beeing so well knowne and sufficiently commended by others, for soundnes of doctrine, and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie of life: which (whilst he was liuing) did parallel each other, his doctrine beeing a patterne of his life, and his life a counterpaine of his doctrine. And now beeing dead, his sauorie-writings which he hath left behind him, breathing forth (as it were) the sweete smell of a sanctified spirit (like a field which the Lord hath blessed) hath got him a name neuer to be forgotten: which giueth him after his death a second life.</p>
   <p>I am further to aduertise thee, (good Reader,) that there were some places in the originall copie to which the Author would (no doubt) haue giuen some reuiew and correction, if God had drawne out the line of his life but a little longer: which I haue filed and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed according to my poore skill, though very sparingly, in such pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces onely as were obscure, or had any phrase of doubtfull constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or otherwise seemed to be mistaken: pointing and interlining the rest to fit it for the Presse. It may be my vnskilfull handling of them, hath depriued them of their due lustre, yet sure I am it hath giuen them no tincture.</p>
   <p>Touching the Supplement: it was my purpose at the first to have made a supplie of that which was wanting, out of the Authors owne writings, as it hath beene done in <hi>Aquinas</hi> Summes and others: but afterwardes perceiuing that his workes alreadie extant, would not affoard me sufficient matter to furnish out that argument, I was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to take an other course, and to make a supplie with courser stuffe of mine owne, as I could. Which if it shall seeme not to sure the former in all points, I shall desire thee to consider that it is not so ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie a matter for <hi>As<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lepiodorus</hi> accustomed to draw with a cole or chaulke only, to finish a picture he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>nne by <hi>Apelles</hi> with so curious a pensill: and that it is an argument wherein (I confesse) I haue not
<pb facs="7"/>
beene so much conuersant as perhaps in some other: neither chosen out of purpose to make ostentation of witt, reading, or inuention: but left as a necessary task to be performed by some for the perfecting of the worke and the good of the Church: (if this poore mite may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre any thing to the Treasurie of the Lords temple.) And thus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that these respects may entreate for a friendly acceptance at thy hands, and that thou wilt afforde mee thy good word for my good will, and a fauorable construction for my paines: I commend it to the blessing of the Almightie, and thee to his gratious protection, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly wishing to thee as to my selfe, the mercie of God in Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus. <hi>August.</hi> 10.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord Iesus, R. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>