<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, EDWARD LORD DENNIE, BARON of Waltham, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Pickering, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114066_Bo1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09365</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19669</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114066</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, EDWARD LORD DENNIE, BARON of Waltham, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Pickering, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The whole treatise of the cases of conscience : distinguished into three bookes: the first whereof is revised and corrected in sundrie places, and the other two annexed. Taught and deliuered by M. W. Perkins in his holy-day lectures, carefully examined by his owne briefes and now published together for the common good, by T. Pickering Bachelour of Diuinitie. Whereunto is adioyned a twofold table: one of the heads and number of the questions propounded and resolued; another of the principall texts of Scripture vvhich are either explaned, or vindicated from corrupt interpretation</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waterson, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40, 199, 8, 436, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="121"/>
   <pb facs="121"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT <hi>HONOVRABLE, EDWARD</hi> LORD DENNIE, BARON <hi>of Waltham, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable. It vvas not vvithout speciall cause, that the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Apostle of the Gentiles, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into a serious meditation of the Calling and vv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ke of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisterie, and grovving at length to some issue of his thoughts, crieth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ut (as it vvere) in tearmes of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint; <hi>And who is sufficient for</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Cor. 2. 16.</note>
      <hi>these things?</hi> For if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nquirie be made into the reason of his demand, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Scripture shall ansvver for him; That Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters are <hi>the Angels of the Lord of Hosts;</hi> the <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mal. 2. 7. Iob 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 23. Math. 5. 13, 14.</note> of his vvill; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Salt of the earth;</hi> the <hi>Light of the World,</hi> And their Calling is, to <hi>carrie the Embassage</hi> of Reconciliation; to <hi>manifest</hi> vnto man the pleasure of the Highest; to <hi>season</hi> the corrupted heart <hi>instrumentally</hi> vvith grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>; to <hi>inlighten</hi> the darkened minde, by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spensation of sauing knovvledge, as the Sunne doth the Aire by the brightnesse of his beames.</p>
   <p>Novv these high Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>les and greatvvorkes, euidently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the vveight and vvorth of that Honourable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, are not either giuen or assigned, onely in respect of publike and ordinarie duties, vvherein by Diuine ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance they be made the <hi>mouth of God</hi> vnto Man by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, <note place="margin">Ierem. 15. 19. Nehem. 8. 7.</note> and againe <hi>of Man</hi> vnto God by prayer. For these are determined vpon certaine times and places, vvhen and vvhere they are to be put in execution, according to the laudable Constitutions and Canons of particular Churches:
<pb facs="122"/>
But in a further regard, as they haue receiued from God <hi>the Tongue of the Learned,</hi> and are indued vvith knovvledge and abilitie, to informe the Consciences of men touching euery action, vvhether <hi>personall</hi> appertaining to particular states, or <hi>relatiue</hi> emploied in the vvorshippe of God, and practise of Christian vertues, A gift, as no lesse necessarie, so of a farre larger extent then the other, and consequently performable vvithout limitation of time or place, in season, out of season, vvhensoeuer the minde requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth resolution in Case of doubt, or Comfort in distresse. The light of this candle is therefore erected vp on high, and set in open vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>vv, that it may communicate it selfe not to all in grosse, but to euery one in person. The Lords Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter in this sense, is to dispense his vvill in euery place &amp; <note place="margin">Matth. 5. 15.</note> time, to the poore vvidovv of Sarep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>a at her ovvne home; to the Noble <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>uch of Ethiopia in his trauell; to Dauid, <note place="margin">2. king. 17. 9. Act. 8. 30. 2. Sam. 12. Math. 26. 75.</note> that he may be dravvne to Confession of his sinne; to Peter, for his restoring after his fall; to the vveake, that they may be supported; to the strong, that they may stand; to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> VVauering minde for resolution; to the Troubled soule for comfort and releefe.</p>
   <p>Hence it is apparent, that this Messenger of God must be (as <hi>Paul</hi> saith) <hi>a</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>complete man,</hi> in euery respect, <hi>armed</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 17.</note> and <note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>well appointed</hi> vvith necessaries appertaining, for all purposes, to the honour of his Lord, and the credit of his Calling. He should be not onely a learned <hi>Text-man,</hi> mightie in the Scriptures; a <hi>positiue Diuine,</hi> established in the truth; a man prouided <hi>ad oppositum,</hi> to vvithstand and con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> the Aduersarie; but a skilfull <hi>Cas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ist,</hi> readie at all assaies vpon good grounds of knovvledge and obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, to giue a Rule, to yeelde a Reason, to speake a vvord <hi>in time</hi> to him that is vvearie.</p>
   <p>VVhich last propertie, to omit the rest, beeing so essential (as it is) to the Calling and condition of a Minister; yea of that importance (as heretofore I haue declared to your Lords<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>.) it seemeth strange, at least in my poore conceit, that among so many graue and learned discourses, published by vvay of Definition and Disputation in matter of Religion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>evv or none haue beene framed and con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>riued to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose; that in this florishing estate both of our Church and
<pb facs="122"/>
Commonvvealth, none haue emploied their indeauours in the vnfolding and displaying of this Subiect; yea, vvhereas they of the Popish Church haue beene so plentifull, or rather lauish in their <note n="a" place="margin">Ioannis de Thabia. Angell de Clavasio. Raymundi, &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>Summes,</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Martini Az<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilcust. Navar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>Manuels,</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">Emanuelis Sa. &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>Aphorismes,</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">Franci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let. &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>Instructions,</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">Iacobi de Graphii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> à Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pua, &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>Determinations, &amp;c.</hi> for direction of their Confessours in Case-points; that our Protestant Diuines for the most part, haue been so sparing and silent in speaking or vvriting of this Argument.</p>
   <p>Hovvbeit, the Lord in his most vvise prouidence, hath not vvholly denied this benefit vnto our Church. For not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvithstanding so great silence and forbearance in matter of Deuotion, as touching the rectifying of the Coscience, there hath beene of late yeares trained vp to this ende, a <note n="*" place="margin">M. R. Green. ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> speciall Instrument of his glorie, vvho beeing in time throughly grounded in the principles of one part of the Coses; by many graue Counsells, and comfortable directions, fetched from the vvord, and gathered by long obseruation, hath cured the vvounds of many a distressed soule. And those diuine Tracta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es of his, novv gathered together since his death, and communicated to the Church of God, are full of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly meditations to that purpose. And as himselfe desired to leaue vnto posteritie, some memorie of his knovvledge in that kind, so the talent he receiued vvas not buried in his graue, but againe reuiued in the person of that faithfull Minister of Christ, the Author of this Booke, a man both for learning and pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tie deseruedly reuerenced and renovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ed in the iudgements of all those that loue and embrace the Truth. VVho happily attempting the same course, and referring the vvhole bodie of his labours in preaching and vvriting thereunto principally; proceeded vvith much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage, added vnto the Cases of Distresse other Heads of Questions, and in his latter time reduced them into such a Frame and Order, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> might best serue for an Introduction of Case-diuinitie, for the helpe and incouragement of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
   <p>The first Part of vvhich Frame being formerly commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by me to your Hon. I haue againe emboldened my selfe to present you vvith the rest, that so the vvhole may haue the freer passage from you, to the common vse of others. VVherein I haue taken vp no nevv <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>shion, but kept my
<pb facs="123"/>
self<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to the commendable custome of vvriters in auncien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es, vvho haue betrusted the Church of God vvith the fruits of their indeavours, vnder the patronage of Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and vertuous Nobilitie. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> namely of that renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <note n="*" place="margin">Coloss 4. 14. Hieron. pro. log. in Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Catalog. Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. Ecclesiast. Nicep. l. 6. c. 16. Luc. 11. Act. 1. 1. 2. Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 1.</note>
      <hi>Phisitian</hi> of Antioche, and of S. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> vvho dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their sacred vvritings, the one to the Noble <hi>Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> the other to the <hi>elect Lady</hi> and her children.</p>
   <p>And that vvhich mooued these holy penmen of Scripture to this practise, hath also incouraged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> vpon the same respects, to offer this Treatise to your Honourable fauour: First, because your Lordship hath beene long <note n="*" place="margin">So was Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ph. with Lukes copies. Act. 1. 1.</note> acquainted vvith th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> person, life, and labours of this man, and vvell grounded in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> truth of Religion, the maine subiect of all his discourses. Secondly; the Lord hath inlarged your heart by his grace, to yeeld <note n="*" place="margin">So did Theop. Luc. 1. 1. 4. and the Lad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ers. 2. Ioh. v. 4.</note> entertainment to that truth vvhich he did teach and vvrite: and the manifestation of your vvilling minde to accept of any Treatise compiled by him, giueth sufficient proofe of this point, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uen i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> mine ovvne knovvledge. Thirdly, you haue not contented your selfe to be barely informed in the knovvledge of the truth, but haue further desired <note n="*" place="margin">This was also Theoph. his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire. Luk. 1. 4.</note> confirmation and assurance in the same. One instance hereof I must needes remember in this place: Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> sundrie yeares since, it pleased you to set him a speciall Taske, the interpretation of that golden Text touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Gaine of the greatest commoditie</hi> in the vvorld, <hi>(Phil. 3. 8.)</hi> for your further vnderstanding of the same, as himselfe reporteth to your great commendation: And great reason, you should tast both of <hi>his</hi> former and <note place="margin">Epist. dedicat. before the True Gaine.</note> Latter fruits, <hi>who</hi> by your motion vvas incouraged to take the paines, and no doubt revvarded for his labour by a plentifull measure of your loue.</p>
   <p>Vpon these motiues, I haue novv at length exhibited vnto your Lordship the remainder of this present Introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, my debt by bond of promise, and your due, by speciall right of patronage. If I be haply challenged of slacke pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof to this time, I desire to be holden excused. First, for that the totall Summe vvhich remained behinde vnpaied, vvas the greatest part, and therevpon required further respite, that it might be more easily collected, and more fully defraied. For though it be but one intir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> heape,
<pb facs="123"/>
yet it consisteth of sundry particulars, all vvhich vvere to be throughly examined, that vpon the Account, there might be a mutuall agreement of the vvhole and the parts. And further, it vvas my desire, that seeing the debt must needes be discharged, and that to an Honourable person, it might be tendred in pure and Currant Coyne, vvhich might beare the triall of the touch-stone: A thing necessarie in these times, vvherein so much corrupt stuffe in this kind, passeth abroad from hand to hand.</p>
   <p>And thus heartily vvishing that these holy Rules of Religion and vertue, may be perused at your Lordships best leysure, and entertained in practise for your daily comfort and direction: cra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing also your Honourable acceptation of my carefull indeauour in publishing them to the common veivve of the vvorld, I most humbly take my leaue: Besee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Almightie, vvho hath alreadie graced you vvith the true revvards of Uertue, Honour, and Nobilitie, to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stablish the same both in your person and issue in this vvorld, and after this life ended, to giue you that eternall inheritance of honour and happinesse, in the kingdome of glorie. From <hi>Eman.</hi> Coll. <hi>in Cambridge. Novemb.</hi> 20. 1606.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours in all Christian dutie to be commanded, Thomas Pickering.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>