<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE SVMME OF THE Eleuen first Chapters of the EPISTLE to the Romanes.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114074_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09031</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19319</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114074</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE SVMME OF THE Eleuen first Chapters of the EPISTLE to the Romanes.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A plaine exposition vpon the whole 8. 9. 10. 11. chapters of the Epistle of Saint Paul to the Romans : Wherein the text is diligently and methodically resolued, the sence giuen: and many doctrines thence gathered, are by liuely vses applyed, for the benefit of Gods children performed with much variety, and conuenient breuitie: being the substance of neere foure yeeres weekedayes sermons.: By Elnathan Parr, Bachelor in Diuinity, and preacher of Gods Word</title>
                 <author>Parr, Elnathan</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 <publisher>Man, Samuel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 305, 1, 138, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>THE SVMME OF THE Eleuen first Chapters of the EPISTLE to the Romanes.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint <hi>Paul</hi> in the eleuen first Chapters of this Epistle, intreateth of Iustification: his order is this: In the fiue first, hee proueth against all obiections of Iewes and Gentiles, that all men are iustified by the righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of Iesus Christ, apprehended by Faith. In the sixe next, hee ouerthrowes the engines whereby Satan went about to oppugne this heauenly Doctrine.</p>
   <p>These Engines were 4. First, that this Doctrine brings in liberty and licentious liuing. 2. That it makes God incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant, and not so good as his word to the Iewes. 3. That it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolisheth the righteousnesse of the Law. 4. That from thence it followes, that GOD hath quite cast away the people of the Iewes. The first of these <hi>Paul</hi> remoues, Chapter 6. 7. 8. the second; Chapter 9. the third; Chapter 10. the fourth; Chapter eleuen.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Chap. 6.</note> The Doctrine of Grace, teacheth men, not to liue loosely, but to deny all vngodlinesse, and to walke in newnesse of life. Therefore all beleeuers are to fight against sin, which they may doe, with so much the more comfort, in as much as they are not vnder the Law, but vnder Grace.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Chap. 7.</note> Indeed, before they were conuerted, they were subiect to the curse of the Law, and by it became more sinfull; but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing receiued Grace to beleeue, they are freed by Iesus Christ, <pb facs="8"/>notwithstanding, the lusting of the flesh against the Spirit, which is the condition of euery regenerate man in this life.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Chap. 8.</note> Therefore, though sinne remaine in them, and for it they bee chastised of God, yet it raignes not in them, nor can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them, neither can any tribulations separate them from the loue of God in Christ.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>