<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Translator to the indifferent Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114662_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09569</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19850</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114662</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Translator to the indifferent Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The key of historie. Or, A most methodicall abridgement of the foure chiefe monarchies, Babylon, Persia, Greece, and Rome : Being a generall and compendious chronicle from the Flood. Digested into three bookes. Whereunto is added a marginall chronologie of euery Roman emperors raigne, and of all the most memorable persons and accidents. Together with briefe illustrations vpon the more obscure names, places, and offices. With a directory table for the more profitable reading of history. Written by that excellent and most learned man Iohn Sleidan</title>
                 <author>Sleidanus, Johannes</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sheares, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sheares, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Swaine (Swayne), Robert 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>50, 377, 5 pages, 1 folded leaf of plates, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Translator to <hi>the indifferent Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE praise of History in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, or this Generall Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storie, being but tralatitious, especially both speaking their owne worth, may be my Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie for both; either to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse me from the vsuall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comions in the preface to most Histories, or dismisse mee with <hi>Salusts</hi> speech concerning <hi>Carthage,</hi> 'Tis
<pb facs="3"/>better to speake nothing, then not to speake home. For the first therefore, <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceroes</hi> fiue most significant, and seuerally volume-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>Epithetes,</hi> shall suffice: History is <hi>Times euidence, Antiquities Herald, Truths light, memories life,</hi> &amp; <hi>lifes Mistresse:</hi> And for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, (this Chronicall Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story following) besides the Authors own admired and approued knowledge in history: the large Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries, &amp; explication of the originall Authors, set forth by the accurate investigation of two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Diuines, and a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Poet, warrant it. His maine drift, as thou maist easily perceiue, was to bee
<pb facs="3"/>succinct &amp; close, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all perspicuous, by which he hath made himselfe the Prince of <hi>Epitomists:</hi> and, by this transcendent deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neation of the foure chiefe Monarchies chiefe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch of all Historians in this kind. For he hath at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd to such a height of perfection, that, as <hi>Polybius</hi> would haue it, a man may at the first view, behold the whole body of Historie, and euery mēber so pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traied to life, that scarce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man of eminencie, or act of excellency, either in Church or Common-wealth, is omitted: being withall so exactly and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodically coucht toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that thy eye may run
<pb facs="4"/>in a line, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the end. Hee hath made it a common <hi>key</hi> to euerie doore, and a little <hi>Perspicill</hi> to cary thy sight all the world ouer: the worke it selfe, being the very <hi>marrow</hi> and <hi>quintes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence</hi> (pardon the meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phors) of all historie. The consideration hereof inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me (one most vnfit) to aduenture the transplanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this pretious exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke root, into our owne soile. Wherein my care to the Authors meaning was religious, which (as I suppos'd) would bee the chiefest thing aim'd at, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially in an old mans last worke (for hee ended this booke &amp; his life both
<pb facs="4"/>in one yeere▪) where wee must not looke for a Pane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyricall stile, or lofty words (which I might haue perform'd and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps with more ease) but, as it is a plaine, facile, and methodicall narration best suiting with the tender ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of younger <hi>Incipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents,</hi> for whom the Author intended it, well knowing that oftentimes yong wits dote more vpon frothie words, then solid matter. Plainnesse is my ambition, else needed not these little marginall illustrations on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to satisfie a meere Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Reader. In some pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, (if thou considerest not my reasons) I maseeme to swerue from the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors
<pb facs="5"/>meaning.</p>
   <p>As in the word <hi>Caesar,</hi> with the Author vses for Emperor, almost through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the booke. But after <hi>Nero</hi> I call them all Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors (onely for more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse) because the line of the <hi>Caesars</hi> was extinct in him.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>France</hi> I call <hi>Gallia,</hi> till about <hi>Honorius</hi> his time, when (after the French <hi>Germans</hi> had seated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues there) it fell into their name. I haue taken the same course too, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching other Countries &amp; Cities, till they chang'd their names: except such, as still (with very little al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of the ancient idi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em) reteind their names,
<pb facs="5"/>as <hi>Vesontio</hi> now <hi>Besanson, Suessions</hi> now <hi>Soissons,</hi> &amp;c. Some may thinke, that <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Caesar</hi> would haue sounded better then <hi>Caius Caesar,</hi> (by which name the the Authour calls him in euery place) because that compellatiō is more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly knowne: but que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stionlesse the Authors meaning therein, was to auoid all doubts; for wee read of more of the <hi>Caesars</hi> beside him, that had the <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Iulius,</hi> as <hi>Lucius Iulius Caesar,</hi> &amp; <hi>Sext{us} Iulius Caesar,</hi> but neuer any other call'd <hi>Caius,</hi> that euer I heard of.</p>
   <p>For my well-meaning presumption, in adding the times of each more memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable accident, and of the
<pb facs="6"/>seuerall raignes of all the Emperors; I hope I shall find pardon, sith it may serue for a little Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie.</p>
   <p>Though I cannot be so ambitious to desire a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from euery open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth'd <hi>Ardelio,</hi> when the best deseruing men could neuer yet obtaine it; yet I both wish and entreat that euery indifferent eye would make a charitable construction of (if I may so call them) my good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauors, ballancing all ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall errours, with my young experience, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience of study, and to accept of the Diamond though not set in its deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued foile: the one may
<pb facs="6"/>encourage, the other can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not daunt mee, for I haue set vp my resolution, in old <hi>Mimnermus</hi> his Distich:
<q>
         <l>
            <hi>Oblectes animum, plebs est morosa legendo,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Ille benè de te dicet, &amp; ille malè.</hi>
         </l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>