<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE OF THE SECOND PARTE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114150_Bo1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09097</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19398</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114150</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE OF THE SECOND PARTE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A conference about the next succession to the crowne of Ingland : diuided into tvvo partes. VVhere-of the first conteyneth the discourse of a ciuill lavvyer, hovv and in vvhat manner propinquity of blood is to be preferred. And the second the speech of a temporall lavvyer about the particuler titles of all such as do or may pretende vvithin Ingland or vvithout, to the next succession. VVhere vnto is also added a new &amp; perfect arbor or genealogie of the discents of all the kinges and princes of Ingland, from the conquest vnto this day, whereby each mans pretence is made more plaine. Directed to the right honorable the earle of Essex of her Maiesties priuy councell, &amp; of the noble order of the Garter. Published by R. Doleman</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Conincx, Arnout</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 220, 4, 267, 3 pages, folded table, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="121"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE OF THE SECOND PARTE.</head>
   <p>THE Ciuilian had no sooner ended his discourse, but al the company being most desirous to here what the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral lawyer had prepared to say, about the seueral titles of the present pretendors to the crowne of Ingland, began with one accord to request him earnestly for the performance of his promised speach in that behalfe, who shewing himselfe nether vnwilling nor vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready for the same, told them, that he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to yeald to their desyers, but yet with one condition, which was, that he would take in hand this matter with the same asseueration and protestation, with the Ciuilian in some occasions had vsed before him, and it liked <note place="margin">A prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>station of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvyer.</note> him wel, to wit, that hauing to speak in this discourse of many princes, peeres, and nobles of the royal blood of Ingland (to al which by law of nature equity and reason he said that
<pb facs="122"/>
he bare reuerent honor and respect) and to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusse their seueral pretentions rightes, intere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes and titles to the crowne, he said, that his meaning was, to offēd, hunt, or preiudice none: nor to determyne any thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> or hinderance of any of their pretences or clay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, of what side, family, faction, religion, or other party soeuer he or she were, but rather playnly and indifferently without hatred or partial affection, to or against any, to lay downe sincerly what he had hard or reade, or of himselfe conceaued, that might iustly be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged in fauour or disfauour of euery tytler.</p>
   <p>And so much the rather he said that he would do this, for that in very truth the Ciuiltans speech had put him in a great indifferēcy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning matter of successiō, &amp; had takē out of his head many scrupulosites about nyse points of <note place="margin">VVhy the vvil not deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myne of any one title.</note> neernes in blood, by the many examples &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons that he had alleaged of the proceeding of Christian cōmon wealthes in this affayre, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring oftentymes him that was further of in blood, vppon other cōsideratiōs of more waight &amp; importance, which point seemed to him to haue bin so euidently proued, as no man can deny it, &amp; much lesse cōdēne the same, without the incōueniēces before alleaged &amp; mētioned,
<pb facs="122"/>
of calling al in doubt that now is established in the world, considering that not only foraine countries, but Inglād also it selfe so often hath vsed the same putting back the next in bloode.</p>
   <p>VVherfore he said, that for as much as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealthes, and the consent, wil, and desire of each realme was proued to haue high and soueraine authority in this affayre, and that as on the one side, nerenes of blood was to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected so on the other, ther wāted not sundry considerations &amp; circumstāces of as great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as this, or rather greater, for that often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes these considerations had bin preferred before neernes of blood, as hath byn declared, I do not know quoth he, who of the pretenders may next obteyne the garland, what soeuer his right by propinquity be, so he haue some (as I thinke al haue that do pretend) and therfore I meane not to stand vppon the iustification or impugning of any one title, but rather to leaue la to God and to them, that must one day try &amp; iudge the same in Inglād to whome I suppose this speech of myne, can not be but grateful &amp; commodious, for the better vnderstanding &amp; discerning of those matters, wherof of necessity er it be longe they must be iudges &amp; vmpires, when God shal appoint, and consequently
<pb facs="123"/>
for them to be ignorant or vnaquainted with the same (as men say that commonly most in Ingland at this day are) cannot be but very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenient and dangerous.</p>
   <p>In this manner he spake, and after this he began his discourse, setting downe first of al the sundry bookes and treatises which he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood had bin made or written hitherto of this affaire.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>