<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Honorable Knight, the most Iudicious and lear∣ned Sir FRANCES BACON, the Kings Attorney Generall.</title>
           <author>Bruch, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114246_Fr1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17053</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3927</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114246</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Honorable Knight, the most Iudicious and lear∣ned Sir FRANCES BACON, the Kings Attorney Generall.</title>
                 <author>Bruch, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The life of religion: or Short and sure directions : teaching how to 1 beleeue aright. 2 Liue aright, &amp; 3 pray aright. In the forme of exposition on 1 the Creed. 2 The ten Commandements. 3 The Lords Praier. Put into this kind of method, that it might the better 1. Informe the vnderstanding. 2. Affect the soule, and 3. Helpe the memory. Hereunto is added also a short treatise on the Lords Supper: with praiers to be vsed before, at, and after the communion. By R.B. minister of Gods Word</title>
                 <author>Bruch, Richard, minister of Gods word</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 287, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <head>To the Honorable Knight, the most Iudicious and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Sir FRANCES BACON, <hi>the Kings Attorney</hi> Generall.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was my chance (Right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Sir) that you were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sēt a hearer of my first made sermons:<note place="margin">At Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sington in Iuly 1607.</note> and if I might take their words that told me, you gaue good words of me then, and concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued good hopes of me for the time to come: on this inducement I resolued to present you with my first publisht writings, but I was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bashed in my selfe, and ready to fall off from my purpose, remembring a passage in your first booke of <hi>The Aduancement of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> where you seeme neerer to reprehensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then defence of those, that dedicate their books &amp; writings not to their owne equals, but to men of greater rancke. And had I not considered with my selfe, that where there were so many good parts of nature and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, there could not choose but be much hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity; the greatnes of your place, and your worth surmounting greater places, then that you hold, had deterd my meannesse and slen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernesse
<pb facs="2"/> from this attempt, neither had I dared to haue offerd that vnto you, which I haue now presumed. This I know, that for the Argument there can be an vnfitnesse in no booke to be presented vnto you, a man so generally read and learned: &amp; I am perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that he that is so industrious as your selfe, and abounding with so many vertues, will euen loue and cherish the least shew and resemblance of the same in others. Well <hi>iacta est alea,</hi> I am now come before you, and if you shall vouchsafe mee but a kinde and cheerefull aspect, it will much cheere me: but if I might vnderstand that I haue written any thing that may be to your tast, the approbation of your learned iudgement alone shall bee vnto me more then the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plause of a large Theater. Howsoeuer it shall be, let me intreate and obtaine this of your goodnes in the name of learning, though I be but the least and meanest in her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, that you would not vtterly dash and put me out of countenance, whose very wit and courage will euen stand and fall with your countenance.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>The man that highly loues and admires your vertues RICHARD BRVCH.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>