<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO
THE READERS OF
these Varieties.</title>
           <author>P., D.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114573_Fr1_13</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09500</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19781</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114573</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO
THE READERS OF
these Varieties.</title>
                 <author>P., D.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Varieties: or, A svrveigh of rare and excellent matters : necessary and delectable for all sorts of persons. Wherein the principall heads of diverse sciences are illustrated, rare secrets of naturall things unfoulded, &amp;c. Digested into five bookes, whose severall chapters with their contents are to be seene in the table after the epistle dedicatory. By David Person, of Loughlands in Scotland, Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Person, David</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Alchorn, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Badger, Richard 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Cotes, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>52, 47, 5, 49-93, 7, 97-123, 1, pages 126, 126-178, 4, 181-190, 4, 177-208, 217-256, 4, 105, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Military handbooks</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="23"/>
   <head>TO
THE READERS OF
these Varieties.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S best deserving Precedency I beginne
at you, whose short Character may be
this: One who is accomplished with
such endowments as make an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
man, the meanest whereof would
blow up some men with self-conceit,
selfe-love, selfe-praise, and an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall
disparaging of others abilities; He hath learned that
God distributeth not his gifts to all men, and makes good
use of it; for he derideth, despraiseth, nor condemneth
any man, nor his workes nor actions as being conscious
that God might have endued him with that mans spirits,
to have produced no more admirable thing: He reades
many bookes; though he may serve for a library himselfe,
yet his censure of these bookes he measureth by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors
abilitie, good intention, and the profits it may yeeld
to meaner Capacities than his, but so discreetly, that his
words favour more of Commendation than reproach: In
<pb facs="24"/>
a word, he is one that escapeth not the Venemous bites of
the ignorant Rable, but hath Antidotes against it, Yea hee
is one, who when he considers my Travells, studies, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences,
and painefull observations, and withall that my
tenne yeares travell abroad hath taught me almost to forget
my Native Language, and that the importunitie of friends
made me put this to the view of the world which I
thought ever to suppresse, as being for the most part com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed
in the Countrey, farre from the conversation of the
learned which is the cheefe helpe to the perfectioning of
such workes; he is one I say, that will then give such a
Candide censure of me and it, that the most rigide Critick
will be strucke dumbe from Calumnie; But before I leave
him, let him give me leave to tell him ingenuously, that to
him onely I present this worke, and promise that ere long
he shall be gratified with a present farre more worthy of
his excellently well qualified goodnesse. As opposite in all
the former expressions to the courteous, I addresse my selfe
to the carping Reader; He is not a naked but a ragged
pretender to all wit and learning and hath a smattering of
many some things: He is so conceited of himselfe that he
is not content to discommend some of the parts and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
of another mans creature, as not elegant enough
or uniformely composed, but will lay most vile and infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
asperations on the whole body of it whilst in his
owne conscience he findes his to be but prodigious mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters,
if ever he had a sparke of <hi>Promethean</hi> fire in him to
give a short life to any thing: When hee meetes with
any ignorant men, then the Peacockes taile of ostentation
spreads abroad and they silly creatures admire the Varietie
of its colours even to the disparagement of more perfit
and more sweetly singing Birds: but presently that falls,
and the most ignorant then perceive the harshnesse of his
note: He feedes all the world with large promises of some
rare worke to proceed from him ere long, and thereby hee
so long feedes and drinkes; till both he and it and his name
<pb facs="24"/>
doe all die: and none to sing his <hi>requiem;</hi> Now being
loath to resuscitate so peccant a humour, I leave him too
without an Epitaph in hope never to heare of his successi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
or his ghost wandring after this.</p>
   <p>For the ignorant Reader, hee hath such a qualitie, to
make himselfe appeare wittie, that he will commend eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
thing that he doth not understand and so I am sure of his
approbation; but <hi>Land<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>iab indocto vituperari est.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
I leave him to admire and wish for better proficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.
Lastly, to the view of all in generall; I expose this
booke into the world; upon this confidence that if the
most discreet and Iudicious give it but that auspicious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation,
that many worthy and learned gave it before it
sufferd the Presse; for the rest my care is taken; yet shall I
to all (but in a different manner) ever be</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>A Well-wisher.
D. P.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>