<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right worshipful Thomas Gaudy Esquier, Christopher Watson wysheth Argantos age, Poli∣crates prosperitie, Augustus ami∣tie, and after the consumma∣tion of this terrestriall Tra∣gedie, a seate amon∣gest the celestial Hie∣rarchie, &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1568</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114792_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09832</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20097</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114792</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right worshipful Thomas Gaudy Esquier, Christopher Watson wysheth Argantos age, Poli∣crates prosperitie, Augustus ami∣tie, and after the consumma∣tion of this terrestriall Tra∣gedie, a seate amon∣gest the celestial Hie∣rarchie, &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The hystories of the most famous and worthy cronographer Polybius : discoursing of the warres betwixt the Romanes [and] Carthaginenses, a riche and goodly worke, conteining holsome counsels [and] wonderfull deuises against the incombrances of fickle fortune. Englished by C.W. Wherevnto is annexed an abstract, compendiously coarcted out of the life &amp; worthy acts, perpetrate by oure puissaunt prince king Henry the fift</title>
                 <author>Polybius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Hacket, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1568</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 130, 1 leave, portraits (woodcut), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the right worshipful Thomas Gaudy Esquier, Christopher Watson <hi>wysheth</hi> Argantos <hi>age,</hi> Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates <hi>prosperitie,</hi> Augustus <hi>ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and after the consumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of this terrestriall Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedie, <hi>a seate amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest</hi> the celestial Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> guise in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient time, &amp; ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally is imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced at this instāt (ryght worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) that such as did or do yelde the fruites of their studie to bee patronized vnder the rampiers of any noble <hi>Philomos,</hi> or <hi>Mecoenas,</hi> as they vsed and vse (though vsur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedly to terme them) neuer stin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to trauaile with tooth &amp; naile to hunt for hauty stately and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb facs="4"/>
termes, wherwith they flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished forth such vertues as their patrons practised, so that vsual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for hope either of gaine or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor, a thousand times more laud thā they deserued, was attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto thē, whose tristing vain and Gnatonicall humour, I har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily abhorre, in so much y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> (least I might incurre the suspition of cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tain in that Getical kind of gab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing) I will speake no worde in your laude, and that not vnadui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sedly: for weying the insufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of my wit in performance but of the naked truth (if I shold at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to pen your panigrick) eke dreading least it should be obiect to me, which was to a certaine writer (not vnsēblable to my self in this matter) purposing to pen the praises of <hi>Hercules</hi> to desist frō such a foly, wherby rather disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor
<pb facs="4"/>
thā fame might be purchased to him, considering that there is no such simple sot whiche alredy reputeth hym not inthronised a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mōgst y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> heroicall estates. Way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the case then as it standeth, I count it a mere mockerie here, as the fashion was and is, to tell you of youre rare and vertuous qualities, of which youre very ennimies, if you (as I doubte) haue any, can saye nothyng but good. Thus then, al vain words set apart, I desire your worship benignely to accept this as a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the intier affection I bear towards you, which taken as I meane it, shal deserue to furnishe some voyde corner in the lowest parte of your Librarie.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From my chamber in your house at Gaudy Hall.</dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>