<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE The L. Cecill, Vicount Cranborne, Earle of Salisburie, principall Secretarie to his excellent Majestie, and Chancellour of the Vniversitie of Cambridge, and of his Majesties most honourable privie Councell: Grace, mercy, and peace, from the Lord Iesus.</title>
           <author>Willet, Andrew</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114193_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15408</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25685</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114193</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE The L. Cecill, Vicount Cranborne, Earle of Salisburie, principall Secretarie to his excellent Majestie, and Chancellour of the Vniversitie of Cambridge, and of his Majesties most honourable privie Councell: Grace, mercy, and peace, from the Lord Iesus.</title>
                 <author>Willet, Andrew</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Hexapla in Genesin &amp; Exodum: that is, a sixfold commentary upon the two first bookes of Moses, being Genesis and Exodus : Wherein these translations are compared together: 1. The Chalde. 2. The Septuagint. 3. The vulgar Latine. 4. Pagnine. 5. Montanus. 6. Iunius. 7. Vatablus. 8. The great English Bible. 9. The Geneva edition. And 10. The Hebrew originall. Together with a sixfold vse of every chapter, shewing 1. The method or argument: 2. The divers readings: 3. The explanation of difficult questions and doubtfull places: 4. The places of doctrine: 5. Places o confutation: 6. Morall observations. In which worke, about three thousand theologicall questions are discussed: above forty authors old and new abridged: and together comprised whatsoever worthy of note, either Mercerus out of the Rabbines, Pererius out of the fathers, or Marloran out of the new writers, have in their learned commentaries collected. By Andrew Willet, minister of the gospell of Iesus Christ</title>
                 <author>Willet, Andrew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Boler (Bowler), James 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 408, 12, 719, 23 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="166"/>
   <pb facs="166"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE The L. Cecill, Vicount Cranborne, Earle of <hi>Salisburie,</hi> principall Secretarie to his excellent Majestie, and Chancellour of the Vniversitie of Cambridge, and of his Majesties most honourable privie Councell: Grace, mercy, and peace, from the Lord Iesus.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, I present to your Honour, this last part of these my collections and Commentarie upon <hi>Genesis:</hi> wherein to set forth unto us the worthy history of honourable <hi>Ioseph,</hi> his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation first, and then his exaltation, together with his pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, chastity, clemency, equity, with the rest of his Princely vertues: A fit president for all noble persons to follow, and a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect patterne for men of honour and authority to looke upon.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Ioseph</hi> was famous and renowned for many noble vertues, but most especially for these foure: his <hi>chastity</hi> in himselfe, <hi>piety</hi> toward God; <hi>fidelity</hi> to his Prince; <hi>clemency</hi> toward his brethren.</p>
   <p>First <hi>Ioseph</hi> is a rare example of <hi>chastity,</hi> who in his youthfull yeares, being a poore stranger and a servant, enticed often and allured by promises, and that by no meane wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but by his Lady the Mistresse of the house, and not ignorant of the danger, which might befall him for his refusall, yet chose rather with his <hi>innocency</hi> to lie in chaines of yron, than yeelding to <hi>intemperancy</hi> to weare chaines of gold:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen. 39.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note> this was his godly reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, when hee was tempted, <hi>how can I doe this great wickednesse and so sinne against God?</hi> for he did very well know, that he which violateth wedlocke, doth sinne against God the author thereof: wherefore the Apostle saith,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Hebr. 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. Ambr. lib. de Ioseph. c. 5.</hi>
      </note> that the Lord will judge such himselfe: And <hi>Ambrose</hi> excellently concludeth this point concerning <hi>Ioseph, Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus vir</hi> Ioseph, <hi>qui adamatus, non adamavit; rogatus, non acquievit; comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, aufugit:</hi> Ioseph <hi>was a worthy man, who being loved, loved not againe: being entreated, consented not: being laid hold on, stayed not.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Secondly, Iosephs <hi>chastity</hi> is much more graced and commended by his <hi>piety</hi>: all his actions savour of godlinesse, and the feare of God as a sweet perfume doth give a pleasant scent to all his enterprises: before, when he was enticed, he had God in his mouth▪ when the two prisoners wanted an interpreter, he said unto them, <hi>are not interpretations of God? Gen. 40.8.</hi> when he stood before Pharaoh to interpret his dreame, he gave the glory to God, <hi>without me shall God make answer for the wealth of Pharaoh, Gen. 41.16.</hi>
      <pb facs="167"/>
when his children, <hi>Manasseh</hi> and <hi>Ephraim</hi> were borne, he remembred God: at the birth of the first he said, <hi>God hath made me to forget all my labour:</hi> and hee called the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and said, <hi>God hath made me fruitfull in the land of mine affliction, Genes. 41.50, 51.</hi> Afterward when <hi>Ioseph</hi> communed with his brethren, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> unknowne, he could not conceale his religion; <hi>This doe and live</hi> (saith he) <hi>for I feare God, Genes. 42.18.</hi> when he discovered himselfe to his brethren, he turneth himselfe unto God, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>God did send me before for your preservation, Genes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>5.5.</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Ioseph</hi> did shew himselfe twice noble indeed, by his unfained piety, and godly sincerity: Much like herein was devout <hi>Daniel,</hi> who being one of the three chiefe Governours of that great Monarchy of the Persians, did thrice every day upon his knees pray and praise his God, <hi>Dan. 6.10.</hi> Thus should all prudent Governours doe, to honour him, by whom they are honoured, and to crave wisdome of the Author and Fountaine of wisdome. <hi>Hierome</hi> giveth this counsell to a noble Matron: <hi>Cum claritate generis morum suavitate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendas, cum nobilitate corporis animi virtute nobilior proficias, magisque illa nobilitate glorieris, quae filios Dei, &amp; cohaered<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s Christi facit, &amp;c. non est quod si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi quis de nobilitate generis blandiatur, si ex meliore parte famulus sit:</hi> Hieron. ad Demetriad. <hi>With the greatnesse of thy stocke, strive by goodnesse of manners: to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with noblenesse of bloud, increase in the true nobility of mind: count that the best nobility, which maketh us the sonnes of God, and fellow heires with Christ: it availeth not to boast of highnesse of stocke, if thou be abased in thy bettter part.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thirdly, <hi>Ioseph</hi> is famous for his faithfull service toward his Prince, who when he had gathered up all the money, which was found in the land of Aegypt and Canaan, for the corne which they bought, did not store it up for himselfe, but laid it up in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sury, <hi>Gen. 47.14.</hi> wherein <hi>Iosua</hi> well imitated him, who in the division of the land of promise to the Tribes, reserved no part for himselfe: but when they had made an end of dividing, then the children of Israel with one consent cast him out a lot amongst them, <hi>Iosua 19.49. Ioseph</hi> then thought not to inrich himselfe by his office, as many officers now adayes, but he travelled more for the wealth of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> than his owne gaine: in whom was not wanting that property which <hi>Moses</hi> father in law requireth in a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, <hi>to be a man hating covetousnesse, Exod. 18.21.</hi> which point is touched well by Ambrose: <hi>Ne praeeminentem virum thesauri possideant sui, &amp; pecuniis ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viat,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ambr. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. c. 14.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>qui praeest liberis: That a great person should possesse, rather than bee possessed of his treasure, neither be commanded of money, who is a commander of men.</hi> Neither was <hi>Ioseph</hi> so devoted to his Princes profit, that he neglected the poore commons, but was a father also unto them: that whereas he had bought themselves and their land for <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> hee both releaseth them of their bondage, and taketh only the fift part of the increase of their land, whereas the whole belonged to <hi>Pharaoh:</hi> and by this means,<note place="margin">
         <p>
            <hi>De utilitate ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil perdiderāt, qui acquisie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant perpetui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elius fuit conferre aliquid de fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctibus, quàm to tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> de jure amittere, offic. 2.16.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>Non venditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem sui juris, sed redemptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem salutis pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ban<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ibid.</hi>
         </p>
      </note> as <hi>Ambrose</hi> saith, <hi>they lost nothing of their profit, that gained a perpetuity: for it was better to part with some of the fruits, than to forgoe the whole.</hi> Such a prudent moderation well beseemeth wise Governours, to be such honourable mediators betweene Prince and people (wherein this kingdome, God bee thanked, wanteth not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples) as that the royall dignity of the one may be <hi>preserved,</hi> the others poore estate pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied, that the people may say unto them, as the Egyptians did to <hi>Ioseph, Thou hast saved our liues</hi>: for as <hi>Amb.</hi> well saith, <hi>they thought it no sale of their right, but a safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their estate.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Lastly, <hi>Ioseph</hi> most wisely did temper severitie and clemencie, justice and mercy
<pb facs="167"/>
together: first he dealt roughly with his brethren, charged them to be spies, imprisoned them, caused <hi>Simeon</hi> to be bound, laid theft to their charge: but afterward he lovingly embraced them, wept over them, and was afoster father unto them:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Greg. hom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>▪ in Ezechiel.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>O tormenta mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricordiae! cruciat, &amp; amat: O the torments of pittie! hee vexeth, and yet loveth them:</hi> So mercie and judgement tempered together, make a sweet harmony,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal. 101.1.</hi>
      </note> as <hi>David</hi> saith, <hi>I will sing mercie and judgement:</hi> such a song did <hi>Ioseph</hi> sing;<note place="margin">
         <hi>Detersa est ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>, quae apparebat &amp; non erat, ostensa est mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sericordia, quae erat, &amp; non ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parebat. Greg. ibid.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>His wrath asswaged, which appeared, and was not: his mercie prevailed, which was, and appeared not.</hi> So Magistrates doe well sometime with <hi>Ioseph</hi> to use threats, and speake roughly, where is cause: but I well hope, that <hi>Iosephs</hi> irefull words, and <hi>pretended threatnings,</hi> will end toward his brethren, with mercifull deeds, and <hi>extended embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings.</hi> We praise God for your Honours mercifull government: let them first taste of your mercie, that teach you to shew mercie. The Egyptian priests under <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> by the hand of <hi>Ioseph,</hi> were maintained in the time of dearth: I doubt not but your Honour under our peerelesse <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> will doe your best, that the Ministers of the Gospell be sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with maintenance, where they have it not, much more bee suffred to enjoy that they have: <hi>Ioseph</hi> remitted his brethrens trespasse, that had taken away his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coloured coat: and although some of our brethren would have certaine ceremonies, which may seeme as the coat of this Church) removed, yet <hi>Iosephs</hi> brotherly connivence may heale up that breach. Toleration and forbearance toward friends and brethren in such matters, may well beseeme <hi>Ioseph:</hi> But your Honours constant resolution (therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring with his excellent Majestie) against all toleration of contrary religion, or giving countenance to such, is most honourable, and joyous to all faithfull hearts: If they differed from us only in some externall rites, and were beside peaceable and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table men, they might have some reason to desire and expect to be tolerated and borne with; according to that conclusion of the Toletane Councel:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Toletan. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> can. 5.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>In una fide nihil officit Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiae sanctae consuetudo diversa, &amp;c. In the Church the unity of faith is not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by the diversitie of rites.</hi> But seeing they dissent from us in substantial and funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall points of faith, and so are enemies to the Church, and depend upon a forreinē Prelate for their direction, and so are dangerous to the state, your Honours resolution is most Christian, to shew no <hi>connivence</hi> in this case, much lesse to give <hi>protection,</hi> but to use against such all <hi>providence</hi> and <hi>circumspection:</hi> for Christ and Belial, Dagon and the Arke, light and darknesse cannot dwell together. God give your Honour courage, strength, and zeale, notwithstanding the malice and envie of idolatrous Romanists, to hold on this happie course, that with Ioseph, <hi>though archers shoot at you, your bow may abide strong, and the hands of your armes be strengthened by the hand of the mightie God of</hi> Iacob.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen. 49.24.</hi>
      </note>
   </p>
   <p>Now lastly, I wish unto your Honour <hi>Iosephs</hi> portion, that according to his name,<note place="margin">Ioseph <hi>signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth added, of</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>asaph, <hi>to adde.</hi>
      </note> first <hi>Iosephs</hi> vertues, then <hi>Iosephs</hi> honours, may be added unto you in this life, and his ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting inheritance afterwards in the heavenly Canaan, through the great mercies of our gratious God, and infinite merits of our blessed Saviour Christ Iesus, to whom bee praise for ever.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honours ready to bee commanded in the Lord,</hi> Andrew Willet.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>