<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>
DOCTRINA PARIT VIRTVTEM.
</title>
           <author>Malynes, Gerard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114044_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06786</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17222</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114044</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>
DOCTRINA PARIT VIRTVTEM.
</title>
                 <author>Malynes, Gerard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Consuetudo, vel lex mercatoria, or The ancient law-merchant : Diuided into three parts: according to the essentiall parts of trafficke. Necessarie for all statesmen, iudges, magistrates, temporall and ciuile lawyers, mint-men, merchants, marriners, and all others negotiatin in all places of the world. By Gerard Malynes merchant</title>
                 <author>Malynes, Gerard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 501, 3 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head type="illustration">
      <figure>
         <head>DOCTRINA PARIT VIRTVTEM.</head>
      </figure>
   </head>
   <head>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTIE MONARCH <hi>IAMES,</hi> BY THE GRACE OF GOD, KING OF GREAT BRIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAINE, FRANCE, AND IRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND, DEFENDOR OF THE FAITH.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most Dread and Gratious Soueraigne,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He state of Monarchie must needes be the Supreamest thing vnder the cope of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, when Kings are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Gods Lieutenants vpon earth, and sit vpon his throne; but also are called Gods, by God himselfe, in regard of their <hi>Transcendent Preheminences</hi> and <hi>Prerogatiues,</hi> whereby they maintaine <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Iustice,</hi> whichare the onely true supporters and fundamentall stayes of all Kingdomes and Common-weales, so naturally vnited and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, that where both of them are not, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly there can be neither. These high <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes</hi> cause their Lawes to be sacred, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently religiously to be obserued; whereby <hi>Iustice</hi> is administred, which is <hi>Distributiue</hi> and <hi>Commutatiue.</hi> The <hi>Commutatiue</hi> part inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Traffick,</hi> which is the sole peaceable instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to inrich kingdomes and common-weales, by the meanes of <hi>Equalitie</hi> and <hi>Equitie,</hi> perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med especially by the <hi>Law-Merchant</hi> by reason of her stabilitie. For albeit that the gouernment of the said kingdomes and common-weales doth differ one from another: 1 In the making of lawes and ordinances for their owne gouernment; 2 In the making of War, Peace, or Truce with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine nations; 3 In the prouiding of money with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in themselues for their safegard and defence; 4 In the election of chiefe officers &amp; magistrates; and 5 In the manner of the administration of <hi>Iustice,</hi> wherein many mutations are incident: yet the <hi>Law-Merchant</hi> hath alwaies beene found <hi>semper eadem,</hi> that is, constant and permanent without abrogation, according to her most auncient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes, concurring with the law of nations in all countries. Great reuerence is due vnto Lawes at all times, and hath beene in all ages. <hi>Solon</hi> caused the Athenians to sweare to the obseruation of his Lawes during the time of one hundreth yeares: <hi>Licurgus</hi> did imbrace a voluntarie perpetuall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ile, to haue his lawes obserued by the Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians vntill his return, intending neuer to return: and the Romans did suffer their old law of twelue tables (though vniust in many points) to decay by little &amp; little, rather than to make a sudden altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, tending to the contempt of laws: grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reuerence then is due to the <hi>Law-Merchant</hi> which hath proued alwaies firme and inuiolable.
<pb facs="3"/>
VVise men haue obserued, that happie are those Common-weales which are gouerned by Philosophers; happier is that King who can wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gouerne them; but most happie is your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie in whom true Philosophie doth raigne and prosper, as vines do in eminent places, by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>estimable treasure of an obseruing, discerning, and applying Princely judgement, gouerning your kingdomes and dominions. The considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof (accompanied with my bounden duetie) hath emboldned me of late, to dedicate vnto your sacred Maiestie, a little treatise intitled <hi>The maintenance of free Trade,</hi> wherein menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is made of this <hi>Volume,</hi> which likewise is to be presented vnto your highnesse; for it befalleth vnto me, as it did to the Philosopher, who (by progression in wisedome, endeauoring to attaine to the perfection of knowledge) did perceiue that the neerer approaching thereunto, seemed to him to be furthest off: so my endeuours (stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to deserue some things at your royal hands) seeme vnto me to merit least of all: But being confident of your most gratious benignitie and superexceeding grace, I do offer vnto your most judiciall eyes this <hi>Law-Merchant,</hi> described ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the three essentiall parts of Trafficke with the means wherby the wealth of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties kingdomes and dominions may be increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and preserued, which being done by just and politike courses, may properly be called the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminent studie of Princes,</hi> grounded, by <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio
<pb facs="4"/>
negotiativ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> vpon the rule of <hi>Equalitie</hi> and <hi>Equitie</hi> as aforesaid, obserued by your High wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome vpon the Predominant part of Trade, which is the mysterie of <hi>Exchange for Moneys betweene vs and forreine Nations,</hi> wherein your Highnesse doth surpasse all the Treatises and Conferences had by your noble auncestors and predecessors Kings, with other Princes and States. If your most excellent Maiestie therefore shall be pleased (from the Zodiaque of your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious aspect) to cast some reflecting beames vpon the plaine superficies of this <hi>Law-Merchant,</hi> eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie little sparke therein will become a flame, and all Merchants and others shall bee enabled to draw (by the Diameter of it) Meridian lines of your royall fauour, without which this Booke may be compared to a Sunne dyall which is no longer seruiceable, than whilest the Sunne beames doe illuminate the same. In hope of which superaboundant fauour, I doe apostro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phate this Epistle, but doe multiplie my ardent praiers for your Maiesties most happie Raigne long to indure ouer vs, to Gods glorie and our comforts.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Maiesties most loyall and obedient subiect</hi>
GERARD MALINES.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>