<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE EDVVARD Lord Wot∣ton, Baron of Marleigh, L. Lieuetenant of the County of Kent, and one of his Ma∣iesties most Honourable Priuy Counsell, my singular good Lord; and to his most worthy associate my very good Lady and Mi∣stresse: health, wealth, and euerlasting happinesse.</title>
           <author>M., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114230_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07387</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17770</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114230</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE EDVVARD Lord Wot∣ton, Baron of Marleigh, L. Lieuetenant of the County of Kent, and one of his Ma∣iesties most Honourable Priuy Counsell, my singular good Lord; and to his most worthy associate my very good Lady and Mi∣stresse: health, wealth, and euerlasting happinesse.</title>
                 <author>M., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Misericors, mikrokosmos, or, Medeleys offices : containing an iniunction to all duties of mercy belonging to the whole man</title>
                 <author>Medeley, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 236 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE EDVVARD Lord <hi>Wot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> Baron of <hi>Marleigh,</hi> L. Lieuetenant of the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and one of his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties most Honourable Priuy Counsell, my singular good Lord; and to his most worthy associate my very good Lady and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresse: health, wealth, and euerlasting happinesse.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, there was a custom among the Iewes, that such dettors whose debts
<pb facs="3"/>amounted their abilities to satisfie, were to be sold themselues, their wiues and children to become slaues to content their Creditors. So calling to minde how farre I stand ingaged to your Honor, not onely for your great and daily bounty, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I haue continually ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted from time to time; but also in that you haue willingly furthered mee by your other many and sundry fauours, when oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion required: the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration of which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth me to confesse that I also should incurre the penaltie aboue said; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="3"/>no other meanes to cancell the obligation, wherein I rest bound to your Lordship; and now in your Honors absence, (aye me) I finde no other like minded towards me. Wherefore as one <hi>Sopho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> a poore schollar of <hi>Socrates</hi> did; so I hauing nothing else, doe dedicate not onely my selfe, but whatsoeuer is of mine, wholy to your Lordships seruice: continually pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the Lord would multiply his many and sundry blessings and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces vpon you, and yours in this life; and that hee would hereafter crowne
<pb facs="4"/>you with glory, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall happinesse for euer, with his Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually bounden, <hi>T. M.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>