<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHOVRS PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114966_Bo1_1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09859</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20124</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114966</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHOVRS PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The flowers of the liues of the most renowned saincts of the three kingdoms England Scotland, and Ireland : written and collected out of the best authours and manuscripts of our nation, and distributed according to their feasts in the calendar. By the R. Father, Hierome Porter priest and monke of the holy order of Sainct Benedict, of the congregation of England. The first tome</title>
                 <author>Porter, Jerome</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>36, 272, 277-611, that is 613, 7 pages, portraits (engravings), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_preface">
   <head>THE AVTHOVRS PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>EING to write the lise of the glorious King, and most beloued seruant of the king of kings S. EDWARD, we will take our beginning out of the words of S. PETER Prince of the Apostles, who admiring the wonderfull vocatiō of the <hi>Heathen Centurion</hi> to the Christian faith, crieth out: <hi>Jn verie deed I perceiue that God is not an accepter of persons; but in euerie natiō he that seareth</hi>
      <note place="margin">Act. 10. v. 34.</note>
      <hi>him, and worketh iustice is acceptable vnto him.</hi> For in euerie people, order, degree, and dignitie our Lord knoweth who are his seruants, &amp; according to his diuine will <hi>he taketh pittie on whom he thinketh good,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 9.</note>
      <hi>and sheweth mercie to whom he pleaseth</hi> Neyther can it be said, that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie of its owne nature doeth giue holines of life, nor that riches doe take it way: obscuritie, &amp; lownes of state maketh not a man per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, nor nobilitie of cōditiō a reprobate; neyther doth libertie shutt vp, nor seruitude lay open the gates of Paradise vnto vs. Our first Patriark <hi>Abraham</hi> whose wonderfull faith, &amp; vnparalel'd obediēce shined in the abundant poslession of wordly meanes, is highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended <note place="margin">Abraham rich and vertuous. loseph most chast</note> for a man excelling both in perfection of life, &amp; abounding in great store of wealth and riches. <hi>Ioseph</hi> being by King <hi>Pharao</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained lord &amp; master of all <hi>Egipt,</hi> shewed a perfect example of chaste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="2" facs="19"/>
to the whole world. What manner of man holy <hi>Job</hi> was in the <note place="margin">Iob a mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of patience.</note> prosperitie of his wealth, the losse of it giues sufficient testimonie, whom the teadious infirmitie of his bodie, the wicked temptation of his wife, and the shamefull reproaches of his owne friends endured with an vnmatchable patience haue rendred farr more excellent. No man was richer then king <hi>Dauid,</hi> &amp; noe man more Sainctly, noe man more exalted to the height of dignities, and noe man more depres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed <note place="margin">An vnion of royal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>e and saintetie.</note> to the rules of humilitie: he was buried in the midst of infinite treasure, and yet amongst the friends, and fauorites of all mightie God he was preferred before manie others, and held to be a man according to Gods owne heart. Let noe man therefore wonder if we g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ue vnto our glorious Edward the titles both of KING, and SAINT; who is knowne to haue bin rich in pouertie, and poore in riches, sober in his delights, &amp; delighting in sobrietie, makeing his purple robes the badge, of humilitie, and vnder the glorie of his royall crowne giuing a true example of the contempt of the world, as will plainly appeare by the historie of his life, which followeth.</p>
   <div type="biography">
      <p>
         <label>I.</label> WHEN KING ETHELRED by the Earle <hi>Thoretts</hi> daughter had <note place="margin">King E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelred his Father</note> receiued his sonne <hi>Edmond</hi> surnamed <hi>Jron-side,</hi> and <hi>Alfred</hi> by queene <hi>Ensnie</hi> his second wife, EDWARD yet inclosed in his mothers wombe was preferred before them both by the disposition of him that worketh all things according to the counsell of his diuine will, and by the prerogatiue of his supreme power gouerneth the kingdoms of men disposing them to whom he pleaseth. For a Councell of the Lords spirituall and temporall being assembled before the King to treate of the state of the Realme (which by horrible fore-warning signes was thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>atned with future destruction) some were of opinion that for the better establishing thereof, <hi>Edmond</hi> should be declared h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>re to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> crowne, be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ause of his inuincible valour, &amp; strength of bodie: others iudged it a safer way to preferre ALFRED, thereby to gaine the power of the <hi>Normans,</hi> in that <hi>Richard</hi> then Duke of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandie</hi> was h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> vncle But the high and mightie ruler of all things p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>t and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ture, foreseeing the short life of the one, and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mature death of the other, turned all their voices and consents to the ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ld<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nborne; and mooued them to elect for their king an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant <note place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
               <desc>•••</desc>
            </gap>vard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </note> as yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> in the weake cloisters of his mothers wombe: s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t the whom the land did not yet enioy was ordayned Lord &amp;
<pb n="3" facs="19"/>
Gorernor of the land; and the nobles, and Peeres with great ioy did sweare alleageance vnto him of whose birth they were ignorant and vncertaine. But this vncertaintie was shortly after taken away by the happie and wished birth of king EDWARD, soone after which the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>rie of the <hi>Danes</hi> cruelly inuaded the realme of <hi>England,</hi> spoyling and destroying a great part thereof with fier, and sword, which mooued king <hi>Ethelred</hi> to send the queene with her children into <hi>Normandie</hi> out of the reach of the <hi>Danish</hi> crueltie, where our princely EDWARD <note place="margin">S. Edward his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues being a boy.</note> liued in his vncles house a child among others his equalls, but all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies free from such vices as that age is wont to bee inclined vnto. He was chast of bodie, sparing of his speach, plaine in his actions, &amp; pure in his affections. He tooke great delight often to frequent Churches, more often to be busied in his prayers, to be present at the holy sacrifice of Masse, to visit Monasteries, &amp; religious houses, and to enter into a strict league of friendship particularly with such monkes whom true vertue, and Religion made worthie to be loued aboue others.</p>
      <p>
         <label>II.</label> IN THE meane time the enemies sword committed such ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trage <note place="margin">The Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians waste Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land.</note> within the realme of <hi>England,</hi> that all places were filled with slaughter, and destruction, nothing appeared that was not masked with the grimme vizard of sorrow, lamentations, clamours, and desolation. Churches were burnt, Monasteries pulled downe, and Priests chased out of their seates, compelled to lie in secret, and desert places to bewaile the cōmon miseries of their countrey. When among others the venerable man BRITHWOLD Bishop of <hi>Winchester</hi> as full of agonie as pittie, greif, and sorrow could make a pious heart, retired to the Monastery of <hi>Glassenburie</hi> putting his whole confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in prayers and psalmes to allmightie God. Where as in great abundance he powred out his deuotions washt in teares for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerie of the kingdom and people out of these calamities, at length he burst out into such like words saying: <hi>And thou, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> Lord, how long?</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>s. 12. 43. 87. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. 3.</note>
         <hi>how long doest thou turne away thy face? doest thou forgett our miseries &amp; affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions? They haue slaine thy Saincts, destroyed thy a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ltars, and there is none that can redeeme vs, nor bring health vnto vs.</hi> I know, ô Lord, I know that whatsoeuer thou hast done vnto vs, is by thy iust iudgement done. <hi>But what! wilt thou for euer cast vs off? and wilt thou not beginne to be</hi>
         <note place="margin">Psal. 76.</note>
         <hi>more pacified as yet?</hi> When when (ô my Lord God) shall there be an
<pb n="4" facs="20"/>
end of these calamities? Or will the sword of thy wrath for euer exercise his crueltie, and make a generall slaughter among vs? <note place="margin">A vision shewed to Bish. Brith wold.</note> At length amidst these prayers, and teares a sweet slumber seased on his sorrowfull sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>es, wherein, as it were, in a dreame he beheld the B. Apostle S. PETER seated in an eminent place, and king Edward clad in Royall ornaments standing before him, with an amiable countenance in most comly and decent manner, vnto whom the holy Apostle (hauing first with his owne hands consecrated, and anneiled him King) piously imparted some admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions and precepts tending to the health and saluation of his soule, &amp; aboue all things recommending vnto him a single life, he reuealed how manie yeares he should raigne and gouerne the Kingdom. The Bishop much amazed at this strange vision, humbly craued of the Apostle to make knowne the misterie thereof vnto him; desiring withall to vnderstand of the present state of the realme, and to know his sentence touching the end of their instant miseries. To whō the Apostle with a pleasing countenance: This kingdom (said he) is our lords who will raigne ouer the sonnes of men: he it is that transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <note place="margin">Dan. 2.</note> kingdoms and chaingeth Empires, and to punish the sinnes of the people giueth the gouernement to an hipocrite. By sinne the people haue offended our Lord, who hath deliuered them captiue into the hands of the <hi>Gentils;</hi> and their hatefull enemies, and strangers haue obtained soueraign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ie ouer them. <hi>But God will not forgett to be mercifull, neither in his ire will he containe his mercie from you.</hi> And it shall <note place="margin">Psalm. 76.</note> come to passe after thy death, that our Lord will visitt his people, &amp; and worke their redemption. For he hath selected a man according to his owne heart, who in all points shall fulfill his will, &amp; pleasure, and who hauing by my assistance obtained the kingdom of <hi>England</hi> shall sett a periode to the <hi>Danish</hi> furie. He will be acceptable vnto God, gratefull to men, dreadfull to his enemies, louing to his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, profitable to the whole Church, and at length shall conclude his worthy life with a most blessed and happie end. But as the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop <note place="margin">A Worthie commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of king Edw.</note> enquired further of Saint EDWARDS posteritie: The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>England</hi> (answeared the holy Apostle) belongeth vnto God himself, who after this will prouide a king according to the diuine ordinance of his owne will and pleasure.</p>
      <p>
         <label>III.</label> BVT as yet the furie of this <hi>Danish</hi> tempest continued, and the
<pb n="5" facs="20"/>
waues thereof were exalted to the height of an insulting and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious pride, in so much that the common miseries of the land were much encreased by a ciuill discord, &amp; inward iarring of mens minds amōgst them selues, noe man knowing whom to trust with the secrets of his heart. The whole Iland was full of traytours, noe true faith to be found, noe friendship but was scarred with suspition, no cōmon conference but was cloaked with deceitfull dissimulation. Till at <note place="margin">Canutus king of the Danes a Christiā of great piety cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen king of Englād ann 1016. the lawfull heires be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted for the vniust murder of S. Edw. the martir, halfbro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Ethelred.</note> length the treason of the countrey &amp; the craft of the enemie preuay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ed soe farre, that king <hi>Ethelred</hi> being dead, most part of the realme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>or saking the lawfull heyres of their late king, gaue vp obediēce vnto <hi>Canutus</hi> that wrōgfully had inuaded, &amp; cruelly spoyled the kingdom: and the mightie <hi>Edmond Jronside,</hi> when he had valiantly ouerthrowne the Danes in three seuerall battles, being at length by the treacherie of <hi>Eadrick</hi> Duke of the <hi>Mercians</hi> cruelly murdred, his little children were taken out of their cradles &amp; deliuered to the pittilesse furie of the <hi>Barbarians</hi> to be slaine. And ALFRED S. EDWARDS elder brother <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>omeing into <hi>England</hi> with a nauie of twentie fiue ships, hopeing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o bring some relief vnto these broyles, and calamities, was slaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>y the strainge and wicked treacherie of GODWIN Earle of <hi>Kent,</hi> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ll his armie murdred in most cruell manner, by the cōmaund of the sayd <hi>Godwin,</hi> and by the blouddie hands of his faythlesse friends, and countreymen. After whose death S. EDWARD wholly destitute of all humā assistance liued as a man miserably banished from his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, kingdom, and royaltie: he much feared to fall into the snares of wickednes, and doubted lest he should either be falsely betrayed by his owne seruants, or purchased for the butcherie by his enemies. Therefore putting his cheifest cōfidence in the almightie he humbly prostrated himself before the court of heauen, &amp; powred out his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout prayers, &amp; lamentations after this manner: Behould (o my Lord God) how in myself I am destitute of all helpe, &amp; comfort, my neerest friends and kindred haue forsaken me, my verie neighbours, and confederats are readie to stand against me, and now that my Father hath finished his manifold labours with death, the crueltie of my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and traiterous subiects hath deuoured my bretheren, and depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me of their companie, my nephews are cast into banishment, <note place="margin">Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>tus had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried his mother.</note> &amp; my owne mother carelesse of my safetie, is giuen in mariage to the only enuier and destroyer of my glorie. And thus desolate and lest
<pb n="6" facs="21"/>
alone without comfort they are not yet satisfied, but thirst allso for my bloud. But left to thee (o Lord) poore, and miserable I trust thou wilt be an ayde and succour to thy poore orphan. In times past thou didest wonderfully preserue King <hi>Edwin</hi> deliuering him out of the iawes of death, and establishing him in his kingdom. Thou didest re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store that bright ornament of <hi>England</hi> S. OSWALD from a miserable banishment to the royaltie of his crowne, &amp; giue him conquest ouer all his enemies by the vertue of the holy Crosse. If now in like manner thou will voutchafe to be my helper, and keeper and settle me in my Fathers kingdom, I vow euer to acknowledge thee for my God, and thy B. Apostle S. PETER for my Patrone, whose most sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Relique; at <hi>Rome</hi> I promise to visitt vnder thy good leaue, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection <note place="margin">S. Edward voweth a pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to Rome.</note> and gouernement. From this time euer after being made stronger in faith, and liuelier in hope, confidently expecting he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected the will of our Lord, referring himself wholly into the hands of his sacred prouidence and disposition.</p>
      <p>
         <label>IIII.</label> TILL AT length when death had robbed <hi>Canutus</hi> of thevse of the world, &amp; cutt of his sonnes before they were ripe, the <hi>English</hi> freed thereby from the hard yoake of the <hi>Danes</hi> elected EDWARD for their king, and caused him to be consecrated and annoynted in <note place="margin">He is crowned in the yeare 1043 by meanes of Count Godwin, as saith Baronius.</note> honorable manner at <hi>Winchester</hi> by the hands of <hi>Eadis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
               <desc>•••</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> Archbishop of <hi>Canturbury.</hi> Then the Clergie began againe to florish, and shine with wisedome and sainctetie, Abbeies, and Monasteries excelled with all kind of religious discipline, Churchmen performed their offices in peace, and the communaltie their duties in order. The verie earth it self seemed to reioyce hereat, and send forth fruit in more abundance, the ayre became more healthfull, and euen the waues of the sea more patient and temperate. And forreigne kings and Princes strucken with admiration at soe suddaine a chainge were glad with this soe great a king to enter into a firme league of peace and frienship, only <hi>Denmark</hi> desiring reuenge, and breathing <note place="margin">The royal vertues of S. Edward</note> nothing but slaughter still threatned the vtter ruine and destruction of the <hi>English</hi> nation. But amidst all these ioyes the blessed king was nothing puft vp with pride of humane glorie at his prosperitie, nor terrified with his threatned ruine, but alwaies measuring his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes by his goodnes, he proposed vnto him self a deuout manner of life, appearing equall to his domesticks, humble to Religious men
<pb n="7" facs="21"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nd Priests, gratefull to his people, compassionate to the distressed, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nd bountifull to the poore. He vsed noe exception of persons, for <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>he poorest and humblest mans cause as well as th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> richest he euer <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eighed in the ballance of true iustice, and pleaded for them both <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ith equitie, alwaies shewing him self a pittifull father vnto poore <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rphans, and a righteous iudge vnto widdowes. He graunted what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>oeuer was asked him, and what was giuen he receaued with silence. Noe man euer beheld him eyther puft vp with pride, or growne <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>erce with anger, or blemished with gluttonie. It is vnspeakable <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ow great a despiser he was of money, for he ueuer was found to be <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>yther sadder in the losse, or merrier in the possession thereof. He was of a comly and meane stature of bodie, nether verie grosse, nor <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ery slender, of a fayre sanguine complexion, his beard and hayre <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rowne.</p>
      <p>
         <label>
            <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</label> AS ONCE he tooke his rest in bed the chamberlaine came in, <note place="margin">See the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of money, &amp; the rare clemencie of soe great a king.</note>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>d opening the chest where the Kings treasure lay, putt therein such <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>oneies as he had brought, and departed forgetting to shutt it <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>gaine. Which one of the groomes espieing came to the box, and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>auing taken out as much money as he thought good, went away <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ith it, not knowing or suspecting the King to be soe neere; <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nd presently (hauing belike disburdened him self of that prey) <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e returned, and acted the like offence againe, hauing still the King him self for his spectatour. Which as the third time he attem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ted, the King (foreseeing by the spiritt of prophesie that the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>urer was at hand) beleeue me, good fellow (sayd he) thou art too <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mportune, and vnreasonable, take what thou hast gotten and be <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>one, for if <hi>Hugoline</hi> (that was the Chamberlaines name) come and <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ke thee, he will not leaue thee one pennie of thy gettings. The <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ellow suddenly fled, and was scarse out of the doores when the Chamberlaine came in, who finding some store of money taken <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>way, was much afflicted, and trembled with verie feare; his lowd <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ries and sighs bewrayeing the anguish, and furie of his mind: whereat the king rose vp, and seeming ignorant of what had happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned demaunded the cause of his great disquiet, which being decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ed, he sayd: Hould thy peace, and rest content, for it may be he <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hat tooke it hath more need of it then wee, let him, (on Gods <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ame) enioy it, that which remaines is sufficient for vs.</p>
      <p>
         <pb n="8" facs="22"/>
         <label>VI.</label> THE NOBLES and Peeres of the Realme fearing soe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie a stock should perish without fruit, were sollicitous to haue a <note place="margin">His care to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>ser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>tetie.</note> successour from this holy King, and to that end they verie earnestly dealt with him to perswade mariage. Whereto the King much ama<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>zed was verie loath to consent, fearing lest the beloued treasure of his chastetie conserued but in the weaknes of a fray e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>vessell might easily he dissolued with such a heate. But what should he doe? it he did obstinate y resist their desires, he feared to discouer, and betray the sweet secret of his holy purpose: on the other side, by consen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to their petitions he mistrusted the vtter ruine of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s vowed chastetie. At length iudging it the safer way to yeeld to their earnest importunities, he recommended his chastetie vnto God his only hope and refuge in distresse, saying; O good Lord, thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eretofore preserued the three children from harme in the midst of the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> fierie furnace. By thee holy <hi>Ioseph</hi> leauing his cloake in the hands of the adultrous woman, escaped with the iust <note place="margin">Dan. 3. Gen. 39. Dan. 13. Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ith. 12</note> title of chastetie. By thy vertue the incomparable constance of <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sanna</hi> triumphed ouer the wicked allurements of the dishonest <hi>Elders;</hi> and holy <hi>Judiths</hi> virginitie vnder the wings of thy safegard could receaue neither taint, nor blemish from the wicked minded <hi>Holos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>rnes.</hi> Behould (ô Lord) how I thy poore seruant, &amp; the sonne of thy handmayd, and after a fashion an honorer, and louer of thee, and thy Virgin-mother doe humbly beseech thy ayde and assistance that soe I may receiue this Sacrament of mariage, that I may not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e the hazard of my vowed chastetie. Therefore forcing himself <note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>ieth against <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>is will.</note> vnwillingly to consent to his nobilitie, he tooke to wife <hi>Edith</hi> the daughter of Count <hi>Godwin</hi> This <hi>Godwin</hi> was a man of great wealth, but of a notable subtletie, a traitour both to the King and countrey, who trained vp in the schoole of deceipt, was accustomed soe craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily to dissemble in all things, that he could winne the peoples con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to anie manner of seditious faction at his pleasure. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Edith his wife a ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of a wicked s<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ocke.</note> to his daughter was applied this verse as a prouerb: <hi>Sicut spina rosam genuit Godwinus Editham:</hi> which may be thus englished:
<q>
            <l>From rugged thorne as springs the sweetest rose,</l>
            <l>Soe <hi>EDITH</hi> fayre from wicked <hi>GODWIN</hi>growes</l>
         </q>
      </p>
      <p>For she was a holy Virgin whom (it seemes) Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>st our Sauiour had prepared for his beloued EDWARD, infusing into her, from the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="9" facs="22"/>
cradle, the loue of chastetie, hate of all vices, and a singular affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiō to vertue. By continuall reading and labour of her hands she <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uoyded idlenes, and secured her self from the staines of lasciuious thoughts, and the danger of youthfull conferences prouoking there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nto. Therefore this godly couple being mett together agreed both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n one holy purpose vowing alwaies to spend their liues in chaste<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>udging it expedient to admitt noe other witnes of this faithfull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, <note place="margin">He co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanteth vvith his vvife to liue cast.</note> then God him self. Soe that she became a wife in mind but not in bodie, he a husband in outward cōsent but not in act. A matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall loue remained betweene them without the act of matrimonie, &amp; an vnion of two chaste affections without anie preiudice to virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. He was loued but not corruptedly, she affected but left vn touched: and like vnto an other <hi>Abisag</hi> she warmed the king with loue, but did not prouoke him to lust; delighted him with obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience <note place="margin">3. Reg. 1.</note> but did not make him effeminate with vnchast desires.</p>
      <p>
         <label>VII.</label> BVT THE good name, and fame of queene <hi>Emme</hi> his mother <note place="margin">
            <hi>Thomas Rudburn. mon. win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton. in chron.</hi> Queene Emme his mother wrōgfully accused of incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinencie.</note> was branded with manie false reports by the instigation of <hi>Robert</hi> A chbishop of <hi>Canturbury</hi> and <hi>Godwin</hi> Earle of <hi>Kent</hi> who iointly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused her before the king of diuers crimes and especially that, vnder colour of priuate deuotions, she vsed the companie of <hi>Alwin</hi> Bishop of <hi>Winchester</hi> with more then honest familiaritie, to her owne great dishonor, and the kings disgrace. And they aggrauated the matter with manie vehement exclamations that such offences soe scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, ought not to be left vnpunished, for that it would be an instāce for others to committ the like. With these, and such like speeches the good king (whose pious simplicitie was not acquainted with the subtleties of their falsehood) was perswaded to giue vp the whole examination of the matter to <hi>Robert</hi> the Archbishop, who presently caused a Councell of other Bishops to be assembled at <hi>Winchester,</hi> and imprisoned Queene <hi>Emme</hi> in the Monasterie of <hi>Werwell,</hi> and <hi>Alwine at Winchester.</hi> In the meane time the miserable Queene (more greiued at the infamie raysed against <hi>Alwine</hi> then at her <note place="margin">She com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines to the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops.</note> owne) made her complaint before the Bishops that she was grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uously oppressed, and wronged by the malicious detractions of her aduersaries, earnestly craue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ng some helpe and redresse from them; and withall shewing a great readines on her part, to make knowne her innocencie by anie reasonable meanes and conditions as should
<pb n="10" facs="23"/>
be thought conuenient; when the Bishops with the king had easily composed all these troubles, if <hi>Robert</hi> of <hi>Canturbury</hi> had not soe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently withstood their good endeauours by aggrauating his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice against her, and heaping togeather manie fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e crimes to her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famie, in soe much that she was content for the satisfaction of the world, and cleering the imputation of her innocencie to purge her self with as sharpe a triall, as anie that is recorded; by vndergoeing the ouer hard law of <hi>Ordalium,</hi> which is to passe ouer hott burning irons barefooted; and for this end the king drawne therevnto by their importunitie, assigned her a day to be tried at <hi>Winchester</hi> in S. SWITHVNES Church, whither she came the night before, and imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">She clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>th her self mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culously</note> all that time in prayer at his tombe, she deuoutly recommended her self &amp; her cause vnto God, and his B. Sainct: And on the morrow in presence of the king her sonne, manie of his Nobles, and Peeres, and an infinite number of people of all sortes and sexes, being led betweene two Bishops, clad in a meane and simple garment, her eyes and hands lifted vp towards heauen, she passed ouer nine glowing red hott shares barefooted, without anie feeling of hurt, vseing this speech to her leaders, as not knowing she was past the danger: <hi>O Lord when shall J come to the place of my purgation?</hi> But vnderstanding she had alreadie walked vppon, and ouer those fierie instruments, she presently looked back, and then first beheld the burning shares, when straight falling vppon her knees with teares she gaue thankes to her deliuerer: whereby she recouered both the loue and her auncient estate of the king, who now seeing the manifest proofes of her integritie, cast him self downe at his mothers feete humbly desiring pardon for his oue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> much facilitie in permitting her spot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse innocencie to be soe hardly tried, and exposed to the perill of such an infamie: and the better to expiate this vnaduised fault▪ of his, he willingly submitted him self to receiue some few blowes with a rodd on the bare back giuen by the hands of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, and his weeping mother. But the nine plough-shares were <note place="margin">A rare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>tie in S. Edw.</note> in memorie hereof reserued in the <hi>Bene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ine</hi> Monasterie of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chester,</hi> and for the better recording of the same, the king gaue three mannours, the Queene nine (according to the number of shares) and Bishop ALWINE nine others to the sayd minster for euer, and enriched the same with manie fayre ornaments.</p>
      <p>
         <pb n="11" facs="23"/>
         <label>VIII.</label> AS ONCE on the feast of <hi>Pentecost</hi> the King was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent at the diuine misteries of Masse, in time of the eleuation of the sacred bodie of Christ, he beganne on a suddaine (allwaies obseruing his princely grauitie) to shew some more then vsuall alacritie and mirth in his lookes, and countenance, which he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed with a graue, and moderate smiling to him self: whereat all that were present beganne to admire, and not without cause, knowing that to haue befallen him contrarie to custome. And therefore Masse being ended some of his most familiar friends earnestly entreated him to declare the reason. He euer endowed with a sincere simplicity, plainly confessed the truth, saying: The <note place="margin">His visiot of the Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish kings destructiō</note>
         <hi>Danes</hi> mett and agreed togeather with their King to enter againe into the course of their auncient f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rie and malice, to disturbe, and ouerthrow that peace which the mercifull goodnes of God both bestowed vppon vs; and being ignorant of his diuine iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stice that hath scourged and chasticed our offences, they attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute it to them selues, extolling their owne strength, and saying: <hi>Our hands are mightie, and not our Lord hath wrought all</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.</note>
         <hi>these things.</hi> And because the Allmightie being angrie with our forefathers did deliuer vs to the mercilesse power of these <hi>Danes,</hi> they referring this to the vertue of their owne forces, iudge it an easie matter to bring vs to the like miseries againe, not vnderstanding that the same God that giues the wound, giues allsoe a salue to heale it, and the same <hi>that mortifieth, reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth,</hi>
         <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note>
         <hi>sendeth to hell, and reduceth from holl againe.</hi> For this verie▪ day, the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> hauing gathered a huge armie togeather, finding the winds to blow with his desires, commaunded a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie to be prepared. And now the ships were readie to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the sayles, and the sayles to the winds, when the wicked king whose hastie ambition not able to be contained within him self, as out of a little boate he entred into his ship, his feet slipt out, and he betweene both fell hedlong into the sea, in whose mercilesse depth, and swelling waues he was instantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uowred and swallowed vp. And thus by his sudaine death, the <hi>Danes</hi> and <hi>English</hi> were both sett free from sinne, and danger. And I hope in our Lord God, and his most sweet mother, that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring my time their blouddie endeauours against vs shall neuer take
<pb n="12" facs="24"/>
effect. This it is which by the reuelation of CHRIST I did both see, and know, and at which I seemed to reioyce and smile. Our Lord made me reioyce, and whosoeuer heareth this may reioyce <note place="margin">The truth of his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</note> with me. The time and hower being recorded, spies were sent into <hi>Denmark</hi> who found all to be most true, and to haue happened at the same instant, as it was reuealed vnto this B. King.</p>
      <p>
         <label>IX.</label> THESE things thus prosperously succeeding, the king not vnmindfull of his vow of pilgrimage, and calling to mind the great benefits he had receiued at the hands of all mightie God, who <note place="margin">His care to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme his vow.</note> had enriched his pouertie, exalted his humilitie, and ennobied his low estate with glorie, made diligent preparation for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of his promise, with money to desray the charge o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, &amp; rich gui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ts to bestow at <hi>Rome.</hi> And therefore hauing assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the Noble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> and Peeres of the Realme, he made a speech before them of the state of his kingdom, and of his pilgrimage to the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred shrines of the Apostles, in this manner. You cannot haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten <note place="margin">His speech to his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</note> how by the cruell inuasion of barbarous people into our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, we haue bin made a scorne to our neighbours, and a scof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing mockerie to those that are round about vs. For some being slaine, others oppressed with the hard yoake of an ignominious sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie, they left neyther honour nor glorie to our nation. At length my father being dead, my brethren murthered, my nephews cast into banishement, fortune soe highly fauoured our enemies in all things, that indeede it seemed to me that there was noe remnant of anie hope left, that promised anie redresse of our miseries. When contrarie to all expectation yeelding my self vp to the mercie of Allmightie God, and putting my whole confidence in him alone, I vowed my pilgrimage to the sacred tombes of the Apostles in <hi>Rome,</hi> and committed my self from thence forth to his diuine protection, and disposing. And he like a pittifull Father gaue such eare vnto my supplication, and was soe farre from disdayning my prayers, that he freed me from all blemish of scorne, and restored me from an exiled life to the quiet possession of my fathers kingdom. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer to the increase of my gloriè he added heapes of worldly riches, and ennobled all the rest with manie spirituall guifts, and graces from heauen. He it was, that without anie bloud-shed brought our rebells vnder subiection, made vs triumph ouer our enemies, and
<pb n="13" facs="24"/>
composed all our disioynted affaires, and inward broiles with a most amiable and desired peace. Now (God forbid) that we should prooue vngratefull for such, soe manie, and soe great benifits; but rather being deliuered out of the hands of our enemies, let vs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to obey and serue him in all truth and iustice, following the Royall Prophets counsell, that sayth: <hi>Make vowes, and render them vnto your Lord God.</hi> Therefore it behoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>es you togeather with <note place="margin">Psalm.</note> me to determine, and ordaine after what manner this realme may be gouerned dureing the time of my pilgrimage: by what law, what peace, what iustice, and what iudge things may be ordered, and by whose courage and prudence our castles, townes, citties, ports, and all our publicke and priuate affaires shall be ruled, My first hope is, that God him self will be the cheif and supreme gouernor of all in generall and he alone will be LORD-PROTECTOVR of the sweet peace he hath bestowed vpon vs, and he, I hope, will alwaies be with me, and guide me in my iourney; vnto whose sacred prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction I committ you all, humbly beseeching his heauenly maiestie to preserue, and keepe you, and soe to dispose of me, that once againe I may see you. Then all the whole companie with one voice cried mainly out vnto the King▪ alleadgeing manie reasons, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, that they ought not soe to be forsaken and exposed to the swords of their enemies, that the countrey was not to be left soe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and open to forreigne treacheries; nether was it fitt they should runne the hazard of soe manie dangers for one, and that but a see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming good deed. Whereat the King finding him self to be not a little vrged, and mooued with their woefull cries, lamentations and prayers, was verie wauering, and doubtfull in mind, not knowing for a long time what course to take: For on the one side, to omitt the performing of his vow he iudged most dangerous, and on the other, not to yeeld and giue way to the prayers, and teares of such and soe manie great Lords, he esteemed most discourteous and inhumane. At length he resolued to deferre his pilgrimage vntill he had consulted the Pope him self therewith, meaning to follow his <note place="margin">He c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Pope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </note> aduise and counsell; and to know, whether in this case his vow were to be fullfilled, or otherwise to be satisfied and redeemed.</p>
      <p>
         <label>X.</label> THE POPE hauing seriously considered and diligently discussed <note place="margin">Pope his<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap> to S.</note> the matter, wrote his answeare to the King in this manner. LEO Bishop seruant of the seruāts of God to his beloued sonne EDWARD
<pb n="14" facs="25"/>
King of <hi>England</hi> sendeth health and Apostolicall benediction. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we haue vnderstood of thy desire both laudable, and grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to God, we giue thanks to him by whom Kings doe raigne, and Princes decree iustice. But in euerie place our Lord is neere vnto <note place="margin">Dispēseth with his vow of pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.</note> them that truely call vppon him, and the holy Apostles vnited with their head are one spiritt, and equally giue eare to deuout prayers: and bicause it is manifest that the <hi>English</hi> nation will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domaged by thy absence, who with the raynes of iustice doest re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straine the seditious insurrections thereof, by the authoritie of God, and the holy Apostles we doe absolue thee from the bond of that vow, for which thou fearest to offend God, and from all thy sinnes, and offences by vertue of that power which our Lord in B. PETER graunted vnto vs saying: <hi>Whatsoeuer thou shalt loose on earth, shall be</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.</note>
         <hi>loosed alsoe in heauen.</hi> Furthermore, we commaund thee vnder title of holy obedience, and peanance to distribute the expenses prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for thy iourney, to the poore: and that eyther thou build a new one, or repayre an old Monasterie of Monks to the honour of S. PETER Prince of the Apostles, and prouide the brethren therein sufficient maintenance out of thy owne reuenewes; that their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall prayers sung there to allmightie God, may adde an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of glorie to his Saincts, and purchase more abundant par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don vnto thee. And whatsoeuer thou shalt giue or is allreadie giuen, or shall heereafter be giuen to that place, we commaund that it be ratified by Apostolicall authoritie, and that for euer there be an habitation for Monks, subiect to noe other lay person but the King himself: and we graunt and confirme by most strong au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie whatsoeuer priuiledges thou shalt there ordaine to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God; and lastly, we pronounce the heauie sentence of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall damnation against all that shall presume to infringe, or violate the same.</p>
      <p>
         <label>XI.</label> BVT FOR the greater confirmation of the Popes letters <note place="margin">The visiō of a holy man.</note> and answere to the King, an oracle was sent from heauen, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed to a holy man then liuing in <hi>England</hi> shutt vp in a hollow caue vnder ground, who now being well struck in yeares both of age, and sainctetie, dayly expected a release to the desired reward of his meritorious labours. To him the blessed Apostle S. PETER appeared one night in a vision with these words: King EDWARD
<pb n="15" facs="25"/>
sollicitous for the vow wherewith he obliged him self being in ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment, and carefull for the peace of his Realme, and the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessities and prayers of the poore, hath consulted the Pope, to be aduised of all things by the authoritie of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. Therefore let him know that by my authoritie he is absolued from this obligation, and that he hath receaued a commaund from the Pope, to erect a Monasterie in honour of my name. Let him then without delay giue creditt to the Apostolicall letters, be sure he obey the Popes precepts, and yeeld vnto his counsells, for whatsoeuer they containe cometh from me, whom in times past he chose to be his speciall Patrone, the companion of his iourney, and his obtainer of grace. But there is a place on the west side of the cittie of <hi>London,</hi> which long since I haue both chosen and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, <note place="margin">S. Peters loue to Vvestmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Abbey and the Monks thereof.</note> and which heeretofore I consecrated with mine owne hands, ennobled with my presence, and honoured with manie miracles. The name of the place is <hi>Thorney,</hi> which heeretofore for the sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the people was giuen vp to the enraged power of the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> and by them brought downe from wealth to pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, from maiestie to deiection, and from a place of respect and honour to an estate vile, and contemptible. By my commaund the King must vndertake worthily to repaire, and reedifie this Monasterie, and to amplifie, and enrich it with large possessions. There shall be nothing but the house of God, and the gate of heauen. There a ladder shall be erected by which the Angels as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending and descending shall present the prayers and petitions of men before allmightie God, and obtaine grace vnto them. I will lay open the gates of heauen to those that ascend from thence, and by vertue of the office which my Lord and Sauiour hath giuen me, I will absolue those that are tied in the bands of sinne, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue them, being absolued, and iustified, in at the gates of the heauenly courte, which sinne had barred vp against them. But doe thou write vnto the King whatsoeuer thou hast heard and s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ene, that by a redoubled benefitt of God, he may be se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curer of his absolution, deuouter in the execution of his precept, and become more feruently possessed with loue and dutie towards me. With these words he vanished in the glorious light that gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him: and the old man according to his commaund related
<pb n="14" facs="26"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb n="15" facs="26"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb n="16" facs="27"/>
what he had heard by letters directed to the King, which at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie instant that the Popes answer was opened, were allso receaued, and read. Whereat the good King, takeing great consolation, with <note place="margin">King Edw. obeyeth the Pope</note> a ioyfull cheerfullnes, &amp; a cheerfull ioy bestowed the money prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for his iourney amongst the poore, and reedified the Monasterie.</p>
      <p>
         <label>XII.</label> WHEN <hi>Ethelred</hi> king of <hi>Kent</hi> by the preaching of S. AVGVSTIN the <hi>Benedictin</hi> monk had receaued the Christiā faith, <hi>Sebert</hi> his nephew then king of the <hi>East-Angles</hi> by the same holymans endeauour was purged from <hi>Paganisme</hi> in the sacred font of Baptisme. This <hi>Sebert</hi> erected a famous Church in honour of S. PAVL within the walls of <hi>London</hi> (which was esteemed the cheif head of his kingdom) and placed <hi>Mellitus</hi> the Monk therein, honouring him with Episcopall <note place="margin">S. Melli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus made Bishop of London.</note> dignitie. But without the walls in the West part of the cittie he founded a goodly Monastery for Monks of S. BENEDICTS order, in honour of S. PETER the Apostle, enriching it with verie large reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news. When the night before the Dedication of the Church, s. PETER him self in an vnknowne habitt appeared to a fisherman on the other side of the riuer <hi>Thames</hi> running by the sayd Abbey, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siring him to passe him ouer, and he would reward his paines; which was performed: when goeing out of the boate in sight of the fisher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man he entred the new-built Church, where suddenly was seene a strainge light from heauen, that gaue such a wonderfull lustre to all therein, as if it would haue preuented the sunnes comeing by turning night into day. There was present with the Apostle in the Church a multitude of heauenly burgesses filling it with melodious musick, and most fragrant odours. Hauing finished all the solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and ceremonies due vnto the dedication of a Church, he whom our Lord made a famous <hi>FISHER</hi> of men, returned to the <hi>Fisher</hi> of fishes, whom he found wonderfully amazed, and carried allmost beyond him self with the flashes of the diuine splendour, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">S. Peter consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Church of westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</note> with a courteous consolation the Apostle restored him to him self againe, reduceing his distracted thoughts to the rules of reason; and the two fishers entring into the boate togeather. S. PETER de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded whether he had taken anie fish or noe? Being suddenly strucken (replied he) with the sight of that vnusuall brightnes, and detained with expectation of thy returne, I endeauoured not to fish, but securely a tended my promised reward from thee, wherevnto
<pb n="17" facs="27"/>
the Apostle answered; cast forth thy netts, and trie. He obeyed his commaund, and presently found his nett loaden with store of fish, all of one kind excepting one fish of a mightie greatnes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out comparison. Hauing drawne them on shore the Apostle bad him present that great one to Bishop MELLITVS in his name, and the rest (said he) take for thy reward. An aboundance of this kind thou shalt enioy all thy life time, and thy posteritie a long time <note place="margin">Fishing on Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden.</note> after thee; only hereafter dare not to fish on the Sundaies. I am the Apostle PETER who with my heauenly fellow-citizens haue all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie consecrated the Church built in my name, and by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of my owne dedication, I haue preuented the Bishops benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Tell him therefore what thou hast seene, and heard, and the markes imprinted in the walles shall giue sufficient testimonie to strengthen the truth of thy relation. Let him therefore forbeare from anie further dedication, and supplie only what we omitted, that is, to celebrate the most sacred misteries of our Lords bodie, and bloud, and with a sermon to instruct the people, giuing them to vnderstand that I will oftentimes visitt this place, and be present at the prayers and petitions of the faithfull, promising to lay open the gates of heauen to all those that spend their daies soberly, iustly, and piously in this world. The next morning the fisher with his great fish meets the Bishop MELLITVS as he was goeing to dedicate the Church, and makes knownes vnto him whatsoeuer was giuen him in charge by the Apostle. Whereat the Bishop much astonished entred into the Church, and finds the pauement signed with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Hebrew</hi> alphabet, the walls annoynted with holy oyle in twelue seuerall places, and the remnants of as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie wax cādles fastened to twelue crosses, all things being yet moist, with the late springling of holy oyle, and water. Wherevppon to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather with the people he gaue prayse, and thanks to allmightie God, for that great remonstrance of his goodnes vnto them. The whole posteritie of the fisherman confirmed the truth of this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, for as they receiued by tradition from their father they offered the tenth of all the commoditie gotten afterward by that art to S. PETER, and his seruants in that place. Till among the <note place="margin">The fish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers deceit punished.</note> rest there was one that attempted to beguile them of that dutie, but he receiued his punishment, for soe long he was depriued of
<pb n="18" facs="28"/>
the benefitt of his art, vntill hauing confessed his fault he had made condigne restitution of the wrong with, a faythfull promise of amendment.</p>
      <p>
         <label>XIII.</label> WHEN S. EDWARD had vnderstood all these things out of the relation and records of antiquitie, he was enflamed with an extreme desire to reedifie that Monasterie, and to restore it out of the ruines of deiection, and pouertie to the height of wealth, and dignitie: and to that end he dispatched messengers to <hi>Rome,</hi> as well to obtaine priuiledges for that place, as allsoe to treate some other affaires, with letters to the Pope, to this effect. TO NICOLAS <note place="margin">S. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Epistle to Pope Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colas 2.</note> the chief father of the vniuersall Church, EDWARD by the grace of God king of <hi>England</hi> sendeth due subiection and obedience. We glorifie our Lord for the care he hath of his elect Church, in orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thee an excellent successour in the place, and seate of thy good predecessour. Wherefore we thinke it fitt to leane vnto thee as vnto a firme rock, to sharpen and approoue all our good actions, and all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to admitt of thy knowledge, and fellowship in doeing good, especially desiring thou wouldest renew, &amp; encrease all those dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and priuiledges which we obtained from thy predecessour; to wit, that thou ratifie, and confirme the Monasterie of Monks, which I haue built in honour of the B. Apostle S. PETER, according as it was enioyned me by thy predecessour, vnder title of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and penance, for the dispensation of a vow I made to goe to <hi>Rome,</hi> and the remission of all my sinnes; as allsoe that thou ree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stablish, determine, and secure all the priuiledges belonging to the <note place="margin">He will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth duties to Rome.</note> possessions, peace, and dignitie of that place for euer. And I, for as much as lies in me, doe increase, and confirme the donations and customes of the moneies which S. PETER holdeth, and chalengeth in <hi>England:</hi> and now I send them accompanied with other free guifts from my self, humbly intreating thee to offer prayers and sacrifices to allmightie God for me, and the peace of my king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and that thou institute &amp; ordayne a continuall, and solemne memorie of all <hi>England</hi> in generall, before the sacred bodies of the Apostles.</p>
      <p>
         <label>XIV.</label> THE POPE answered him in this manner. NICOLAS <note place="margin">The Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to the king.</note> Bishop seruant of the seruants of God, to the most glorious, most pious, and most worthie of all honour our specially belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="19" facs="28"/>
EDWARD King of <hi>England,</hi> sendeth all manner of saluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, most sweet health, and Apostolicall benediction. We giue thankes vnto allmightie God who hath adorned, and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thy most prudent excellence in all respects to conserue deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion towards the blessed Apostle S. PETER, and all loue towards vs his vnworthie successour, in giuing obedience, and consent vnto Apostolicque counsels, and censures. Wee therefore send our letters to thy Royall nobilitie whereby we graunt vnto thee the holy Apostles societie, and ours, beseeching his mercie who is truly Lord of all, and only soueraigne aboue all, to make thee par taker of all our good workes, if anie we haue in the sight of God, and at all times to make vs more feruent brethren and fellows in his loue, wishing him to graunt noe lesse part or reward of our dutie and obedience in his heauenly kingdom vnto thee, then we desire to fall vnto our selues. Allsoe we will not cease heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after vnfaynedly to powre out our dayly prayers for thee, that God himself would bring thy foes and enemies which attempt to rebell against thee, into subiection, and confirme in thee the inheritance of thy fathers throne; beseeching the blessed Apostle S. PETER to be thy guardian and ayde in all tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, or aduersitie that may befall thee. Wee therefore doe restablish, confirme, and encrease all priuiledges giuen in thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, to witt, that thou be cleerly absolued from the vow which thou didest seeme to feare, and from all other thy sinnes, and iniquities by the authoritie of him, that hath ordayned my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthines chief pastour of his Church. Furthermore bicause it is credibly reported, that that place which vnder title of holy pennance thou hast vndertaken to build, and repayre, hath long since bin consecrated by the hands of S. PETER him self (whose vnworthie Vicar we are) as allsoe bicause it is, and hath bene the auncient seate of Kings, we by the authoritie of God, and of the holy Apostles, and by the power of this <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Sea, and ours, doe graunt, permitt, and most strongly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that henceforth for euer it be the place of the Kings Coronation, and the storehouse of his Royall enseignes, and a perpetuall habitation for Monks independent of anie other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, but only the king him self, and that they enioy absolute
<pb n="20" facs="29"/>
power to elect fitt, and worthie Abbots out of their owne bodie to succeede in the gouernmēt, according to the rule of S. BENEDICT, <note place="margin">Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictine Monks, &amp; exempted from Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops.</note> and that noe sorreigne or strainge person be brought in by violence but such as the conuent shall freely consent to elect. We doe alsoe exempt, absolue, and free that place from all Episcopall subiection and iurisdiction, that noe Bishop enter there eyther to order, or commaund anie thing, vnlesse it be done by the desire and consent of the Abbot and his Monks. And that the same place enioy a free precinct, that is a circuit, and Churchyard about it to burie the dead, without anie respect or exaction of the Bishop, or anie other person: and with a most readie and willing mind we giue, &amp; graunt to that place all priuiledges whatsoeuer by our authoritie may be graunted, which belong anie way to the honour of God, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease the dignitie of the place. We doe likewise by the authoritie of God, and ours, ratifie, confirme, and establish all the possessions, and hereditaments which auncient Kings, or anie other person, or thou thy self, or anie of thy Lords haue graunted vnto the same place: and all the charters, and writings made of the same dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions we decree to be and remaine still in force, and all such persons as shall attempt to infringe, inuade, diminish, disperse, or make sale of the same, we condemne and declare them to be guiltie of eternall malediction with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>raitour <hi>Iudas,</hi> and that they be not partakers of the blessed resurrection, but that they know them selues to be adiudged by S. PETER the Apostle when with his fellow-Apostles he shall sitt in iudgement ouer the twelue tribes of <hi>Jsrael.</hi> But vnto thee and thy successour-kings we committ to be the aduocats and defenders of the same place, and of all the Churches of <hi>England</hi> in our place and steed, that with the Councell of thy Bishops and Abbots thou constitute, and ordaine all things in all places according to iustice; and know that for such good doeing thou shalt receiue a worthie reward from him, whose king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and empire shall neuer cease, nor be diminished. This was the Popes answere. Now lets returne to S. EDWARD.</p>
      <p>
         <label>XV.</label> GOEING once with the Queene, and Earle <hi>Harold</hi> to see a <note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </note> great summe of money, which without his knowledge they had collected throughout the realme to supplie his wants, and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to cloathe his souldiers, &amp; seruants with new liueries against
<pb n="21" facs="29"/>
the feast of <hi>Christmas,</hi> entring with them into the <hi>Exchecquer</hi> he es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied the deuill sitting, and sporting him self vpon that heape of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; of whom the King hauing demaunded what busines he had there? I keepe my money (replied he) vniustly gotten out of the goods of the poore. Wherevppon the standers by were much ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, hearing their speeches but seeing nothing But the holy king, <note place="margin">S. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of money.</note> that contemned all temporall riches for loue of the eternall, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded all that money to be presently restored from whence it came, giuing herein a perfect example to all Princes and Rulers in the world, not to maintaine the glorie of their braueries with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney wrongfully raysed, and forced out of the meanes of their poore subiects the communaltie. The like clemencie mooued him out of his Royall bountie, to remitt and freely release his subiects <note place="margin">He remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne-gilt.</note> of that most grieuous tribute called <hi>Dane-gilt,</hi> which in his fathers time was payed to the <hi>Danish</hi> nauie, and afterwards brought into the kings <hi>Exchecquer.</hi> But he commaunding it should be noe more exacted, freed thereby the Realme of <hi>England</hi> for euer of that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>supportable burden.</p>
      <p>
         <label>XVI.</label> BEING on a time in his pallace neere to S. PETER'S Church, there came an Irishman noe lesse straing then miserable, lame of both his leggs; for the sinewes of his hammes being short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <note place="margin">His name was <hi>Giles Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel.</hi>
         </note> and contracted had forced, and drawne his leggs backward to the hinder parts of his bodie, not directly but sideward, soe that his ankles grew fast to his buttocks, and his toes being sunk into his haunches were growne ouer with flesh, that from the setting on of the chine-bone downwards, his bodie was quite out of order. He crept vppon his hands, and knees by the help of two little hand-stooles, and being most painfull and greiuous to him self, he haled, and drew him self, after him self. This wretched man see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the kings Chamberlaine, cried vnto him: O <hi>Hugoline</hi> (sayd he) wilt thou not look vppon me? nor take pittie on me? nor will not this my miserie and calamitie mooue thee to comfort my distresse? What (sayd he) wilt thou haue me doe? Six times (replied the poore criple) creeping in this woefull manner as thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eest, I haue visited the Churches of the Apostles, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d haue not yet obtained the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerie of my limmes. Notwitstanding the Prince of the Apostles hath not quite denied my petition, but hath deferred it only, desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="22" facs="30"/>
to haue king EDWARD his fellow-partner in this cure, whom he knoweth to be most deuout towards him in all things. For he himself hath cōmaunded me to goe to the king, and that on his sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred back he carrie my lame bodie to the Church adioyning to his pallace, and by that meanes I am promised to receaue the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect vse of my limmes. This being declared to the king, he gaue thanks vnto allmightie God, and causing the criple presently to <note place="margin">S. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cōparable humilitie.</note> be brought before him, like vnto that strong spirituall asse <hi>(Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesis 49.)</hi> bowing to his fortune, and chardge, layd downe h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s Royall shoulders to be the supporters of that miserable burden of calamitie. O most strainge miracle of humilitie! The poore wretch full of rusull, and nastie sores hangs on the back of this Royall Prince, clipping, and embracing his kingly neck with hands, and armes soe full of filth, and scabbs, that the verie sight bred a generall loathing in the beholders, and some it mooued to laughter, as it were, in scorne of his soe base, and sluttish humilitie: others iesting and scoffing as it, cried out that the begger had deluded the king: others againe rashly iudged his plaine simplicitie to be mere follie. But when this Royall Porter had marched some part of his way with this beggarly burden, the sinews of the criple began to grow lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, his bones to be strenghthened, the dead flesh to receaue the two companions of life, warmth, and feeling; his toes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore sunk into the flesh, issued out, and his feet loosed from his haunches were restored to their naturall function. When to <note place="margin">No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e a strainge miracle.</note> the great admiration of all, with the stretching forth of his thighs and leggs, by the pliant, and flexible <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ag litie of his hammes, there gushed out great store of filthie bloud, and corruption, which falling on the kings garments, serued for an ornament, rather then anie dishonour. Wherevppon the criple receaued the perfect vse of all the limmes of his bodie, whose one halfe hitherunto was rather a painfull burden, and grieuous trouble vnto him, then anie ease or commoditie. Which noe sooner was perceaued by the attendants, but they all cried out to the King to cast him downe now since he was healed, and free him self from the running vlcers of his loathsom burden. But he, mindfull of the chardge he had vndertaken,
<pb n="23" facs="30"/>
held on his pious iourney, not listning to their bewitching speeches, but entring into the Church, hauing resigned and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vp the sacrifice he had brought to allmightie God, and the Prince of the Apostles S. PETER, he dismissed him safe, and sound to walke forth him self by the help of his owne leggs, which neuer before had done him the like seruice. Therefore now hauing them by speciall miracle restored, to the end to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy the first fruicts of their labours in the honour of the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme authour, and worker of miracles, he receaued a sufficient viaticum of the King, and tooke his iourney towards <hi>Rome,</hi> there to giue thanks to allmightie God, and S. PETER for this soe great a benefitt.</p>
      <p>
         <label>XVII.</label> AS THIS B. King was once in S. PETERS Church pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent at the diuine sacrifice of Masse before the aultar of the B. TRINITIE, togeather with Count <hi>Leofricke;</hi> he, that in beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie <note place="margin">This <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frick</hi> is much cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for holy life, and founding Monaste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and namely that of Couen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie where he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>as buried.</note> farre excelleth the sonnes of men CHRIST IESVS, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red visibly on the aultar to them both, in the true forme and figure of his heauenly bodie, and stretching forth his sacred right hand gaue S. EDWARD his benediction, by makeing the signe of the Crosse in the ayre: at which the King humbly bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe his head, deuoutly adored the presence of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Maiestie: But the Earle ignorant of the Kings thoughts, and desiring to haue him partaker of soe great a vision, began to make towards him, when the king vnderstanding his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, willed him to be still, and keepe his place, assuring him that he saw that sacred vision as well as he. And Masse be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ended, the king spake to the Earle in this manner: By his Maiestie, and loue whom we haue seene (ô my <hi>Leofrick)</hi> I doe coniure thee, that this vision be not published in our life time, left for the fauour of the world-, we should be puft vp with pride to our owne ruine, or lest the enuie of the incredulous should endeauour to disable the truth of what we say.</p>
      <p>
         <label>XVIII.</label> A WOEMAN vnder whose iawes grew certaine kernels, which defiling her face with a deformed, and vglie swelling, blowne vp with corrupted humours, had chaīged the bloud into filthy mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, wherein were bred wormes which breathed out a most horrid,
<pb n="24" facs="31"/>
and loathsome smell; and long she had suffered the greif of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, till at length being admonished in her sleepe, she repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Court to hope for a remedie from the Kings owne <note place="margin">S. Edw. cureth the disease now cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Kings euill.</note> hands, by his eyther washing, touching, or blessing of the diseased place. And being come before the King, and hauing declared her case vnto him, he neyther regarded the filth of the sore, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued anie horrour at the stench that came from it, but handling, and washing the swelled places with his Royall hands, blessed them with the signe or the Crosse, whereat the skinge suddenly breaking open, the wormes togeather with the corruption gushed out, the swelling was asswaged, and all sense of payne ceasing, gaue place to a perfect recouerie of health.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>This wonderfull grace of cureing this disease called in latin</hi> struma, <hi>now the</hi> KINGS EVILL, <hi>(for noe other reason but because it hath bin vsually hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by Kings) was first deriued from S.</hi> EDWARD <hi>to all the Kings of England,</hi>
         <note place="margin">After him our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish kings doe the like.</note>
         <hi>and remaynes as a holy inheritance vnto them to this day, and hath been, and is dayly practised, and to good effect practised by our moderne Kings, allbeit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing a religion quite contrarie to that of</hi> S. EDWARD, <hi>yet by his meritts (as it may be piously thought) they worke this wonderfull cure. Yea Queene</hi> Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth <hi>but a woeman had the like power, and cured manie thereby as it is well knowne by men of creditt yet liuing. Therefore the Frenchmen are all deceaued, not against their wills, and particularly the</hi> French <hi>authour of the</hi> English <hi>history,</hi> ANDREW LE CHESNE <hi>did not speak candidly, and as he thought when he denies that the Kings of</hi> England <hi>euer enioyed this vertue, affirming it to be a grace peculiar to them of</hi> France <hi>deriued from</hi> S. LEWIS, <hi>but <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ur</hi> EDWARD <hi>florished aboue one hundred and fortie <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>eares before</hi> Lewis, <hi>and therefore it is likely that if anie such thing be among them, they must rather haue receiued it from our Kings, then that theirs haue it absolutly, and particularly to them selues. Furthermore</hi> William <hi>of</hi> Malmesbury <hi>(a</hi>
         <note place="margin">Lib. 2. <hi>de Reg. Ang.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>man farre better conuersant in our</hi> English <hi>histories, then anie</hi> Frenchman <hi>could be) hauing related the foresaid miracle, affirmed it to be the constant report of such as well knew the life of</hi> S. EDWARD, <hi>that he had cured manie of this same disease whilst he liued in</hi> Normandie. But let vs goe on. <note place="margin">A blind man cured with the w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ter in w<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
               <desc>••••</desc>
            </gap> the kin<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
            <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>hed.</note>
      </p>
      <p>
         <label>XIX.</label> A BLIND man vnderstood by reuelation that he should recouer his lost sight by the meritts of S. EDWARD, washing his face with the water wherein the King had washed his hands. The king vnderstanding this from his Chamberlaine, was much ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed,
<pb n="25" facs="31"/>
and made shew of some displeasure, and discontent, alleadging that the poore man was deluded with vaine imaginations, that noe such matter could be expected from the hands of a sinner as he was, but it belonged to the power, and vertue of the Apostles to worke such wonders, and for this cause he ought not to creditt those dreames. Notwithstanding he washed his hands, and went away into the Church, as not desiring to be present at the miracle, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to auoyd the occasion of being tempted with vaine glorie. But the Chamberlaine hauing reserued the water, brought it to the blind man, wherewith he had noe sooner washed his eyes, and face but presently to the great wonder of all, he recouered his sight, and with ioy beheld the light againe, whose losse he had long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailed. The like fauour was shewed to a citizen of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> who <note place="margin">An other cured in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</note> hauing lost his sight came to the kings pallace; and obtayned of this water, applied it to his vnprofitable eyes, and was immediatly cured, and his perpetuall night chainged to a most wellcome, and long desired day-light. An other blind man being admonished to goe to the king to haue his sight restored, desired the Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine, to make knowne his case vnto him; which done; Let him come (answeared the holy king) for why should I be greiued but rather reioyce if the diuine goodnes be soe pleased, as by my vnworthy hands, to bestow this promised benefitt vppon him. The man was brought in, and by the only touching, and bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing <note place="margin">Manie blind cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> of the king, betweene his royall hands a filthie bloud ranne aboundantly from his eyes, whereby they were cleered, and all the swelling of his eyelidds asswaged. Then he that before could not see, cried out; I see thee (my souueraigne Lord and King) and thy face shineth like vnto the face of an angel stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before me. Allsoe at an other time two blind, and one ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing but one eye, being sprinkled with the water in which the holy man had washed, were all three restored to perfect sight.</p>
      <p>
         <label>XX.</label> AS HE some time sate at table with Earle <hi>Godwin, Harold,</hi> and <hi>Tostins</hi> the Earles two sonnes as yet but children, according to <note place="margin">what the fight of Godwins children did por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend.</note> their age and condition played in the hall before them; but as one of them handled his brother more rudely then the sweetnes of their game required, their iest was turned into earnest, and
<pb n="26" facs="32"/>
their sport to a plaine fight. For <hi>Harold</hi> somewhat abler in strength of bodie, violently setting vppon his brother, fastned both his hands in his hayre, and hauing layd him along on the ground, had gone neere to thrattle him if by the standers by he had not bin pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented. The king behoulding this skirmish, turned to Earle <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wine,</hi> and sayd: Doest thou consider nothing in this contention of thy children but a childish sport or battle? Nothing else, my liege (replied he.) But by this boyish cōflict the blessed king vnderstood by reuelation what would afterwards befall to the children. For (sayd he) noe sooner shall they be out of their childhood in mans estate, but an inward malice towards one and other, will mutually possesse them: and at first (as it were in iest) they will seeme to goe about to ruine each other by priuate deceits, till at length the stronger hauing gott the vpper hand, will banish the weaker, and ouerthrow him, giuing him death for his rebellion. But his death will in a short time be recompenced with the ensueing calamitie of the authour. And all this fell out as <hi>England</hi> it self may be the <note place="margin">Their cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention &amp; ruine.</note> bleeding witnes of her owne miseries. For <hi>Tostius</hi> being by <hi>Harold</hi> put to flight, and he a while after had succeeded King <hi>Edward</hi> in the kingdom, <hi>Tostius</hi> togeather with the King of <hi>Norway</hi> (that came to his ayde) was vtterly ouerthrowne, and slaine and allmost all his armie destroyed. The same yeare <hi>William</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandie</hi> comeing into <hi>England</hi> to claime his right to the crowne in one blouddie battle vanquished <hi>Harold,</hi> who at once was depriued both of life, and kingdom: or (as some thinke) reserued in miserie to doe peanance for his former wickednes.</p>
      <p>
         <label>XXI.</label> AT AN other time <hi>Godwine</hi> sitting by the King at table, one of the seruingmen comeing towards them chaunced to stumble so much with on of his feet, that he had caught a fall, had he not recouered him self againe by the nimble bringing on of his other foote, by help whereof he was sett vp right againe. The beholders talking diuersly (as the manner is) of this accident, and reioyceing to see how opportunely one foote releeued the other, Earle <hi>Godwin,</hi> as it were in iest, put in these words. Soe a brother helpes his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and both relieue each other in necessitie. The King (calling to mind the death of his brother <hi>Alfred)</hi> In like manner (replied he) might myne haue bine a comfort vnto me, had <hi>Godwin</hi> permitted
<pb n="27" facs="32"/>
it. Hereat <hi>Godwin</hi> trembling, and makeing fayned signes of sorrow in his countenance: I know (my Liege) I know (sayd he) that your mind doeth yet accuse me as accessarie to your brothers death, and that you iudge them to be beleeued that wrongfully giue me the title of traitour both to him, and you. But let God the great eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witnes of all secrets be iudge betweene vs, and let him not permitt this morsell which I hould in my hand to passe downe my throate without causing my death, if I be eyther traitour to you, or guiltie of your brother's death. And the King makeing the signe of the Crosse vpon the morsell, the wretched Earle putt is into his mouth, <note place="margin">Gods pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishmeut against the trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win.</note> which being chewed, went into the midst of his throate, where it stuck soe fast, that, notwitstanding all his labour, and paines, he could gett it neyther vp, nor downe: But rather the more he stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, the more it seemed to fasten, soe that in a short time the sluses of his wind were stopped vp, his eyes turned round in his head, and without speaking one other word he vomitted out his traiterous soule to receiue her iudgement in the next world. The king that saw him make this lamentable end, perceiuing God's iust punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to haue befallen him; spake aloud to the standers by: Cast out this dogg, and burie him in the high way; which was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently performed. This <hi>Godwin</hi> abusing the king's pious simplicitie wrought manie villanies in the kingdom against both God and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice. By his wilie fleights, and craftie dealing he had chased out of the Realme allmost all the kings kinred, &amp; friends, which he had brought with him out of <hi>Normandie,</hi> imagening to haue all things goe according to his owne desires, when the king being depriued of his friends should onely make vse of his counsell, and follow his dictamen in all things. But the blessed man neuer tooke notice of his bad doeings, allwaies performing his owne dutie towards God, foretelling to manie that in the end allmightie God would punish his wickednes; yea and some times he stuck not to say as much to <hi>Godwine</hi> him self.</p>
      <p>
         <label>XXII.</label> THIS HOLY king next after the Prince of the Apostles, <note place="margin">S. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards loue to S. Iohn E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelist.</note> bore a singular affection and deuotion to S. IOHN <hi>Euangelist,</hi> in soe much that he would neuer denie anie thing demaunded in his name. For proofe whereof it happened that a certaine poore pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grim (his Chamberlaine being absent) importunately asked him
<pb n="28" facs="33"/>
an almes in the name of God, and S. IOHN: He hauing nothing else in a readines, gaue him a ring of great value of his finger. Not long after two <hi>Englishmen</hi> going in pilgrimage to visitt the holy sepulcher at <hi>Hierusalem</hi> lost their way, and wandered a long time throught strainge, and vncouth places, till the sunne goeing to sett, the darksom night approached, and encreased their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, soe that not knowing what to doe, nor which way to turne, there appeared a venerable graue old man that, brought them to a towne hard by, where they were receaued kindly, and entertayned very sufficiently with diet, and lodging. The next morning as they were departing, the same old man putt them in their right way, and in takeing leaue of them, Brethren (sayd he) be of good cheere, and doubt not but you shall returne to your countrey in safetie; for allmightie God will make your iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney prosperous, and I my self for your good kings sake will haue care to direct you in all your waies. For I am IOHN the Apostle who affect your King with all loue, for his pure vertue of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stetie <note place="margin">S. Iohn loueth him for his chaste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. j</note> which highly deserues it. Take therefore this ring which he gaue me for an almes, appearing in the habit of a pilgrim, and deliuer it vnto him againe, telling him withall that the time of his death drawes neere, for six moneths hence I will visitt him, and bring him where togeather with me he shall <hi>follow the lambe which way soeuer he goeth.</hi> At these words he vanished away, and <note place="margin">Apoc. 14. v. 4.</note> they hauing visitted the holy land returned safely into their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and related orderly to the King what they had seene, and heard. And in testimonie of all gaue him the ring, which was afterwards kept with great reuerence as a holy relique in the great Church of <hi>Westminster:</hi> and by vertue of it, manie were cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the falling sicknes, and of the contractions of their limmes.</p>
      <p>
         <label>XXIII.</label> NOT LONG after the blessed man fell into a grieuous sicknes, during which he was in such an extasie, that for the <note place="margin">S. Edw. in an extasie</note> space of allmost two daies he lay without anie signe of life. At length waking, as it were out of a deepe sleepe he opened his eyes and sitting vpp in his bed spake to the attendants in this manner. When in my youth I liued a banished man in <hi>Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die</hi> I euer held the friendship and companie of good and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous persons, as most deare and gratefull vnto me, and chiefly
<pb n="29" facs="33"/>
those Monks, and Religious men that excelled others in vertue and religion I obserued, and with them I conuersed most fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly; among whom two Monks <hi>Benedictines</hi> had obliged me in the bands of charitie verle particularly vnto them, by their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest <note place="margin">His loue to Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictine Monks.</note> conuersation, their holy life, their sweet behauiour, and their affable and courteous discourse. These I more frequently visitted, their discourses being to my soule, as sweet meates to my pallate. And these (being some yeares since translated out of this world to the ioyes of heauen) I beheld in this my sleepe standing before my face, rehearsing (according to the will of God) what shall befall this countrey after my decease. They say that the wickednes of the <hi>English</hi> nation is growne soe full, and to such a height, that it prouoketh Gods wrath, and hasteneth his <note place="margin">His pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesie of England.</note> reuenge. The Priests haue broken their. couenant with God, they handle the sacred misteries with polluted soules, and defiled hands. They are not true pastours but mercenaties, that doe noe protect their flock, but expose it to the deuouring iawes of wolues, seeking only their owne priuate commoditie of the milke, and the wooll neglecting the good of their sheepe, that at last eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death may iustly deuoure and swallow both sheepe, and sheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard in the bottomlesse pitt of hell. The Princes allsoe and gouernours of the land are vnfaythfull, companions of theeues, and wasters of the countrey, they neyther seare God, nor honour the lawes, men to whom truth is grieuous, and burdensom, right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eousnes contemptible, and crueltie delightfull: soe that neyther the Prelates heare anie respect to iustice, nor the subiects haue anie regard of good order and discipline. And therefore our Lord <note place="margin">And the comeing in of the Normans.</note> hath drawne his dreadfull sword, he hath bent and prepared his bow to shoote-forth the arrow of his iust wrath, and reuenge against this nation; into which he will send a mission of wicked spiritts, to whose power they shall be deliuered in one yeare and one day, to be punished with fier and sword. With that, sighing and grieuing at the newes of this calamitie threatned against my wretched countrey, (ô yee witnesses of the heauenly secrets) sayd I, what if this people beiog conuerted from their wickedenes shall doe worthie works of penance, will not God graunt thē pardon, &amp; leaue his blessing among them? Penance is of
<pb n="30" facs="34"/>
such force that it suspended the dreadfull sentence of death pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by Gods owne mouth against the <hi>Niniuites,</hi> and allso diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <note place="margin">
            <hi>Joan.</hi> 2. 3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 21.</note> the imminent reuenge due to wicked <hi>Achab.</hi> Therefore I will perswade my people to doe penance for their offences past, and carefully beware those to come, and perhaps our Lord will be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, and not powre out these great calamities vppon them; but with his wonted pietie will receiue them then returned vnto his seruice, whom peruerted from him by their wicked life, he was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to punish and destroy with this heauie iudgement. No no (replied they) it will not fall out soe happily; for the hearts of this miserable people are soe hardned, their eyes soe blinded, and their eares soe fast dammed vp against all goodnes, that they will neyther hearken to anie correction, nor vnderstand anie good counsell; they are neyther with threats terrified from euill, nor with benefits prouoked vnto good. At these their words my grief, and care en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creasing, What (sayd I) <hi>will our Lord shew his anger for euer? will he not at last beginne to be more pacified?</hi> When then shall ioyes succeed these soe manie miseries, what comfort, or consolation shall moderate <note place="margin">
            <hi>Psal.</hi> 76.</note> these great aduersities? What remedie is to be expected in these <note place="margin">An obscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> euills, that as on the one side we are terrified, and contristated at our future rebukes, soe we may be a little comforted with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise of the diuine mercie that followes them? Herevnto the Saincts proposed vnto me this Parable. When a greene tree cutt downe from the stock, &amp; remooued three furlongs distant from his owne roote, shall without the helpe of anie mās hand, or by anie externall ayde, returne againe to his owne roote, and placing it self thereon, shall resume iuice againe to florish, and bring forth fruit, then and not before some comfort may be hoped for, in this tribulation, and a remedie against the foretould aduersitie may be expected. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing sayd thus, they returned to heauen, and I to you, and my self againe.</p>
      <p>
         <label>XXIV.</label> WHILE the king related this vision, there were present the Queene, <hi>Robert</hi> keeper of the sacred pallace, Duke <hi>Harold,</hi> and wicked <hi>Stigand,</hi> who mounting on his fathers bed had defiled it, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piously inuading the Archiepiscopall Sea of <hi>Canturbury</hi> during the life time of <hi>Robert</hi> true Archkishop thereof: for which offence he was afterwards suspended by Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the second, and in a
<pb n="31" facs="34"/>
Councell held at <hi>Winchester</hi> by the same Popes Legats, and other Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, and Abbots of <hi>England,</hi> he was both deposed from all Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scopall dignitie, and cast into prison by the commaund of <hi>William Conquerour</hi> where he ended his wicked life with a most miserable, and well deserued death. This <hi>Stigand</hi> being there present at the kings narration, had all the powers of his soule soe barred vp against <note place="margin">Stigand a Clergie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished for inuading a Sea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictine Monks.</note> all goodnes, that he waxed more obdurate, at the dreadfull storie, neyther was he terrified with the threatning oracle, nor gaue anie creditt to the pious relatour: but murmuring within him self, that the king began to dote in his old age, he laughed where he had more cause to weepe. But the rest, whose minds were more ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuously giuen, lamented and wept abundantly, knowing verie well that the Prelates and Princes led their liues according as the blessed king had declared.</p>
      <p>
         <label>XXV.</label> SOME are of opinion, that the foresayd similitude is grounded vppon an impossibilitie; and these were chiefly such as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailed that the whole Nobilitie of the land was come to soe low anebbe, and soe farre spent, that there was neyther king, nor Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, nor Abbot, nor Prince of the same nation scarse to be seene <note place="margin">An inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the Kings vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</note> in <hi>England.</hi> But quite of an other opinion am I (saith <hi>Alured)</hi> espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that S. DVNSTAN did both foretell that this calamitie should befall vs, and yet afterwards promised a comfortable redresse. Thus then it may be expounded: This tree signified the kingdom of <hi>England</hi> in glorie beautifull, in delights and riches plentifull, and in the excellencie of the Royall dignitie most eminent. The roote from whence all this honour proceeded, was the Royall stemme, or race which from <hi>Alfred,</hi> (who was the first of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> Kings annoynted, and consecrated by the Pope) descended by a direct line of succession to S. EDWARD. The tree was cutt off from the stock, when the kingdom being deuided from this royall issue, was translated to an other linage: the distance of three fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs shewes that during the raigne of three Kings there should be noe mutuall participation betwixt the new and the auncient race of Kings: for <hi>Harold</hi> succeeded King EDWARD, next to him came in <hi>William Conquerour,</hi> and after him his sonne <hi>William Rufus.</hi> But this Royall tree tooke roote againe, when <hi>Henry</hi> the first vnto whom all Regall dignitie was transported, neyther by force compelled, nor
<pb n="32" facs="35"/>
vrged with hope of gaine, but meerly taken with an affection of loue, tooke to wife <hi>Mawde</hi> daughter to S. EDWARDS neece, ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and vniting togeather by this mariage the bloud royall of the <hi>Normans,</hi> and the <hi>English</hi> both in one. Then this tree did truely flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish, when of this vnited royaltie, <hi>Mawde</hi> the Empresse was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten: and then it brought forth fruit, when by her we had <hi>Henry</hi> the second who like vnto a corner stone vnited both nations togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And therefore by this we now see, that <hi>England</hi> hath an <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> King, as allsoe Bishops, Abbots, Princes, and knights of the same auncient race, deriued from this vnion of both nations. But if anie man be displeased with this exposition, let him eyther ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it better, or expect an other time vntill he find these parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularities fullfilled.</p>
      <p>
         <label>XXVI.</label> BVT LET vs returne to our B. King, whose sicknes still encreasing made him euidently feele and vnderstand by the secret <note place="margin">S. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards death.</note> Embassadours of neere approaching death, that his hower was come to passe out of this world; and therefore caused his death to be p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>blished abroade before hand, lest the knowledge thereof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing delayed, he should want the comfort of the prayers and sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of his Clergie, and people, which he earnestly desired. This done, the holy man loaden with manie dayes of ould age, and as manie good workes as howers in each day, he yeelded vp his pure soule into the most pure hands of his Redeemer. By whose death <hi>England's</hi> whole felicitie, libertie, and strength was vtterly lost, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>oken, and ouerthrowne. Noe sooner was the breath gone out of his holy bodie, but his face casting forth beames of wonderfull brightnes made death in him seeme beautifull, and louely to the behoulders. This glorious King, and worthie benefactour of S. BENEDICT's order died the fifth of Ianuary, one thousand sixtie six, <note place="margin">The beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</note> when he had raigned twentie three yeares six moneths and twentie seauen da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>es. He was honorably buried in S. PETERS Church which him self had built for the <hi>Benedictine</hi> Monks, and had now bin newly consecrated during the time of his last sicknes, on S. <hi>Innocents</hi> day before.</p>
      <p>
         <label>XXVII.</label> MANIE miracles by the merits of this B. Sainct were <note place="margin">A lame man cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at his tombe.</note> wrought afterwards at his sepulcher: among which, one <hi>Raphe</hi> a <hi>Norman,</hi> who for the space of manie yeares had bin by the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="33" facs="35"/>
of his sinewes soe lame of his leggs, that he could but creepe, (and that with great difficultie) on his hands, and hinder parts, came the eight day after S. EDWARDS buriall, to his tombe, and making his prayers to allmightie God, and this glorious Sainct, he was perfectly cured and healed of all his infirmities.</p>
      <p>
         <label>XXVIII.</label> ALLSOE about twentie daies after his buriall six blind men came following a man with one eye, hanging one to an other, <note place="margin">Six blind man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored to sight.</note> soe that one only eye leading the way, directed seauen persons to the B. Saincts sepulcher, where sorrowfully declaring their miserie vnto him, they humbly beseeched his assistance against the woefull teadiousnes of their perpetuall darknes; and immediatly by the merits of the holy King they had all their sights restored, and soe perfectly restored vnto them, that they were able to returne each one guiding his owne footsteps. Allsoe the bell ringer of <hi>Westminster</hi> Church being blind vsed to pray dayly at S. EDWARDS tombe, till one night he heard a voyce that calling him by his name, bad him rise, and goe to the Church, but as he went, he seemed to behould King EDWARD in great glorie goeing before him; and from that <note place="margin">Three cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of quartan agues.</note> time he had the perfect vse of his sight euer after. Allsoe a Monk of <hi>Westminster</hi> a verie learned man, one Sir <hi>Guerin</hi> a knight, and an other man of <hi>Barking,</hi> were all three cured of quartan agues, as they prayed at his holy tombe.</p>
      <p>
         <label>XXIX.</label> SIX AND thirtie yeares after the death of this glorious King, his sepulcher being opened, at the earnest request and sute of <note place="margin">His bodie found vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupted</note> the people, his holy bodie was found most entier without anie the lest signe of corruption, as cleere, &amp; white as the cristall, as if it had all readie putt on the diuine robes of glorie; casting forth of the tombe an exceeding sweet, and odoriferous sauour to the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ioy and comfort of all that were present. The linnen wherein he wrapped was as fresh, and pure, as when first it was imployed to that holy vse. Which moued <hi>Gundulph</hi> Bishop of <hi>Rochester</hi> to attempt to pluck a hayre of the Saincts head to reserue to him self for his deuotion. But his pious desire was frustrated, for the hayre stuck on soe fast that it could not be pulled off without breaking.</p>
      <p>
         <label>XXX.</label> A WOEMAN that contēptibly presumed to worke vpon S. ED<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WARDS <note place="margin">A miracle</note> day was grieuously punished with a suddaine palsie, till being
<pb n="34" facs="36"/>
brought to the B. Saincts sepulcher, and with teares demaunding pardon for her fault, she was restored to her health againe. Manie other miracles haue bin done by the meritts of this glorious Sainct, all which mooued Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the third, at the instant desire of King <hi>Henry</hi> the second, and the Clergie of <hi>England</hi> to putt him into the number of canonized Saincts, and to cause his feast to be cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated throughout the kingdom of <hi>England.</hi> But of this we will speake more at large on the feast of his translation the thirteenth day of <hi>October.</hi> This feast of his deposition hath bin allwaies verie magnificently, and religiously celebrated by his successour-kings on this day, as plainly appeares in the histories of <hi>England,</hi> and is particularly prooued out of that which <hi>Mathew Westminster</hi> rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth of king <hi>Henry</hi> the thirds deuotion towards S. EDWARD. In the yeare of grace 1249, (saith he) which was the thirtith yeare of our soueraigne king <hi>Henry</hi> the third, the King being then at <hi>London</hi> on the feast of the Natiuitie of our Lord, and hauing spent the <hi>Christ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> holidaies in sumptuous feasts and banquetting, as the custom is, togeather with a great multitude of his nobilitie, he assembled manie more Nobles and Peeres of the Realme to be present, and <note place="margin">Henry the thirds de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion to S. Edwar.</note> reioyce with him at the feast of S. EDWARD, whom more cordially he loued, and honoured, then others of the Saincts. And on the eue of that B. Kings deposition, our soueraigne Lord the King ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his pious custom fasted with bread, and water, spending the whole day in continuall watching, and praying, and giuing of almes. But on the feast itself he caused Masse with great magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence and solemnitie to be celebrated in the Church of <hi>Westminster,</hi> in vestments all of silke of an inestimable value, and adorned with a great multitude of wax tapers, and the resounding notes of the <note place="margin">A consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration on his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues.</note> Conuentuall and Monasticall quier, Ought not we likewise to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe this vertuous example, and giue prayse vnto allmightie God for the excellent guifts wherewith he honoured this B. King, in choosing, and calling him to soe great glorie euen before he was borne? And for that he reuealed vnto him the great fauours pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised to the kingdom of <hi>England</hi> for his sake, long before they happened? Who will not admire, and endeauour to imitate the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred vertue of chastetie, which soe great a King entirely conserued soe manie yeares, with his Queene in holy marriage? Who will not
<pb n="35" facs="36"/>
embrace his most profound humilitie, and contempt of the world, and him self, when he carried that wretched cripple on his royall shoulders to obtaine his health? Who will not striue to serue all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God with affection, seeing how highly he exalteth, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth his Saincts? How he exalts them with miracles, &amp; soe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously recompenseth their seruice, giuing peace, health, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speritie to kingdoms by their intercession, and in the end making them immortall kings, and euerlasting courtiers of the kingdom of heauen.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>This life is taken chiefly, and allmost wholly o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>t of that which</hi> B. ALVRED <hi>Abbot of</hi> Rhieuall <hi>hath written.</hi> Iohn Capgraue <hi>hath the verie same;</hi> William Malmesburie, Roger Houedon, Mathew Westminster, Nicholas Harpsfield, <hi>and allmost all writers of Saincts lines make verie honourable and worthie mention of him. And the</hi> Roman Martirologe <hi>on this day.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>