<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE GODLIE INDIFFERENT Reader, judgement to discerne, and zeale to imbrace the truth.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114383_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68566</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19603</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114383</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE GODLIE INDIFFERENT Reader, judgement to discerne, and zeale to imbrace the truth.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe discouery of the vntruthes and slanders (against the true gouernement of the Church of Christ) contained in a sermon, preached the 8 [sic] of Februarie 1588. by D. Bancroft : and since that time, set forth in print, with additions by the said authour. This short ansvver may serue for the clearing of the truth, vntill a larger confutation of the sermon be published</title>
                 <author>Penry, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 56 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE GODLIE INDIFFERENT Reader, judgement to discerne, and zeale to imbrace the truth.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hinke it no wonderful case beloued, to see the church of England so out of order at this day as our confusions are altogether more in number, then the ha res of our head. For those that will needes bee our Pastors and spirituall fathers, are become beastes as the Prophet Ierem▪ saith, and haue not sought the Lord. And therfore what mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell is it, though we the poore sheepe bee miserablie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spersed not knowing whether to turne vs for any succour. Our guides haue not onely misled vs, but they are become wolues in stead of shepheards. So that we dare not shew our selues, for feare of their teeth, to seke any pasture but the bare feeding which they haue laid before vs. And if we sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ld <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pen our mouths, to sue for the true shepheards and ouerseers indeed vnto whose direction, we ought to be committed: The rage of these wolues is such (thou seest) as this endeuor would almost be the price of our life. For if this request were once granted, they ful wel perceiue, that they should not haue so much as a place of a doore keeper within the sheepefold of the Lord. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, they euery way labour, to keepe vs in bondage. They hide the truth, &amp; will not suffer others to see the same. If the Lord in mercy, doe open the eies of any man, hee must not for his life, make it known that he hath seene the light, much lesse, walke in the same, and wish others to follow him.</p>
   <p>They seeme at this day, to haue greater liberty, to wound the church, then any they had since the beginning of her Majesties raign, and therfore ought the godly to enarme themselues against them, now more then before. They make vse of the time, and the oportunity which they haue gotten, to keepe the truth and the church in their bondage. VVonder not at it: for this is the very houre and power of darkenes, wherein they haue liberty to do no more yet, then the right hand of our God hath determined long before and when he hath accomplished his work, in mount Sion and Ierusalem, then let them, and whosoeuer fauour any of the ofspring of Romish Babell their mother, take heed vnto themselues. In the beginning of her Majesties raign, was the mouth of gods saints in England, filled with laughter, but a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>asse▪ these men labour to blot out all that ioy with the teares, if not with the bloud of the church. And in the meane time, her Majesty wee are assured, is ignorant of the right case of the murthering conclusions, set vp against vs by these Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants. Oh that it pleased the Lorde, that our course might bee examined by her highnes, and that she would not suffer both our judges and our accusers, to condemne vs for those thinges, whereof▪ they shall neuer bee able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince vs with any colour. If we must needs be persecuted, yea, and die (for I see that the Prelates, and their complices meane no otherwise to be satisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then with the blotting out of our names from among men) would to God yet, wee might die by her hand, that is, beeing conuicted by her godlie lawes, to deserue that which we are like to suffer For otherwise, I perswade my selfe, we should not be indamaged by her Majesty except we were found to bee gilty of punishment, by the voyce of her good lawes. The enemies haue long since endeuoured, to prooue vs to be dangerous subjects and yet
<pb facs="3"/>to this day, we are ready to defie them vnto their faces, and to maintaine our innocency both by the law of God, and the laws of this kingdome. Against which, Tertullus, the greatest Atheist, &amp; cunningest lawier of all their crew was neuer able to prooue, that we haue any waies offended How violently they wrest the lawes against vs, their soules (which I wish not) shall find it.</p>
   <p>The course which they haue taken to confute vs by writing, hath beene so gainles vnto them▪ that we neuer saw their third answer in the cause. They haue indeed, like men being driuen vnto a hole, sometimes made an irrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vpon vs, as they do daily in their Sermons, but when it coms to passe, that they must either stand vnto their cause, or suffer the ouerthrow, wee see not one of them, that wil abide the third encounter. And yet they cease not, dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to discouer themselues, although they bring no other furniture with them then that which hath bene battered and made vnseruiceable long since. M. Bancroft hath beene one of the last aduersaries that wee haue seene, and yet hath he furnished himselfe with no new artillery, but onely was content to borrow those, wherewith the Archbishop lost the field. For he hath nothing in a maner against vs in his whole Sermon, but such thinges as haue bin an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered long ago by M. Cartwright, yea, his slaunders, and all for the most part (though he bee skilfull that way himselfe) he hath borrowed either of D. VVhitgift, or of Doctor Cosins, in his answere to the Abstract, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue bene already confuted. In consideration whereof, I had thought him not worth the answering, were it not that I did see, the Lord to require at our handes, the justifiyng of his truth, as often as the same is called into question, or any waies vnworthily handled.</p>
   <p>There haue bene others I suppose, that haue taken more paines with this inuectiue Sermon of his, I haue therefore left place vnto them, whosoeuer they are, to publish that wherein they haue more fully and more largely dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, the euill and vnreasonable dealing of the Chaplaine. I haue exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned few or none of the testimonies of men brought in by him, the aduanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which that way might be had against him, I haue not taken, both because I saw it not very material, that he should be conuinced, to abuse the writings of men, who is not ashamed to offer iniurie vnto the holy scriptures of God, and also for as much, as it may be, others will indite him for that false dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his. If his cause be good, &amp; he able to defend it with truth &amp; vpright dealing, I haue shewed him the way to atchieue his purpose: And that is, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to father vpon vs such thinges as we neuer maintained, nor yet to bring the testimonies of men to oppugn our conclusions, whose grounds he is not able to shake: but to set downe that which we holde indeed, and with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons rather to answere our premisses, then with authorities to strike at our conclusions. The contrary dealing, may colour and white line the breaches of his cause for a time, but in the end, it will prooue to be the ruine thereof. Vnconscionable and sophistical dealing, can neuer be able to stand any long time. He and his Masters, would gladly beare the Magistrat in hand, that we deny the congregations in England, where the word is truly preached, and the sacraments rightly administred, to be the visible churches of God, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the truth is, that the Bishops and not we, doe maintaine this error. Let the reader judge, whether I truly accuse them by this which followeth.</p>
   <p>The visible church of God wheresoeuer it bee▪ hath the power of binding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd loosing annexed vnto it, as our sauiour Christ teacheth vs. Mathew 18.
<pb facs="3"/>which authority is so essentially tied vnto the visible church, that wheresoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer this power is to bee found, there the church of Christ is also visible,<note place="margin">Our Bb. are scismatickes and deny the assemblie of England to be visible church of God. booke of Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tins page 5. 6.</note> and wheresoeuer there is a visible church, there this authority cannot bee denied to be. The which point that reuerend father, M. Iohn Fox teacheth more at large. Now the reader cannot be ignorant that our Bishops wil neuer grant that the visible congregations in England, ought to haue this power of bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and loosing, for then should they manifest themselues to bee professed tyrants. The crime therefore of Scisme and Donatisme, which M. Bancroft and the Prelates would fasten vpon vs, doth justly cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aue vnto them selues. And if any of our poore brethren be caried away, to thinke otherwise of the congregations of England, which inioy the woorde truly preached, and the right vse of the Sacrament<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>: VVe cease not to pray that the Lord would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their iudgements. But woe bee vnto our Bishops, which are the cause of this their stumbling, and maintainers of their error. For the pore brethren doe holde nothing in this point, but that which the learned fathers, as M. Bancroft calleth them haue decreed. And you shall see in this Treatise, that he seeth no reason, why Popery being now abollished,<note place="margin">Sermon pag. 3,</note> wee should not reply vppon the determinations of these fathers, as other men in time past of a: great iudgement as we are, haue done. Let our Bishops then, and their vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders, whisper into the eare of the Magistrate what they will, it shall bee prooued in the end, that they are the scismatickes and not we. It shall appear that they are growing to make a body of their owne, wherewith the church of God in a while (if they hold on their course) can haue no mote to do, then in times past in had with the scismaticall Donatists.</p>
   <p>The deuill indeede hath within this twelmoneth, shewed himselfe to bee grieuously wounded in their persons, because he hath raged so mightily, as these 32. yeares his furie was neuer seene so great against the truth as at this present. That vile and scurrilous Palmphlet,<note place="margin">An almond a Patrot.</note> latey suffered to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad by their priuity (if not allowance) and in their defence doth euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly shew, that sathan feeleth the power and sway which he was wont to bear by vertue of the hierarchie, to be greatly weakned. And because he feareth that his time vnder their gouernment cannot be long therefore he meaneth now to infect the aire at once, with all his contagions. The strength which they get by such leud and filthie stuffe, &amp; the discredit which thereby they worke either vnto the cause, or the men and women whome they suffer to bee so vnworthilie traduced, is not other then it were to bee wished (that seeing they will needs be filthy) they would publish such another booke e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day: That then it might appeare indeede whose sonnes they are. And this is all the confutation that I thinke, so godles, &amp; leud a scrole to deserue.</p>
   <p>For thy selfe good reader, thou seest the time of triall to be now at hand, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen at the doore. If thou meanest to be partaker of Christes kingdome after this life: take heede, that neither the feare of men, nor the loue of the world draw thee to shrinke from any part of that truth, which the Lorde hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiled in his word. The Lord saith, that whosoeuer shall be ashamed of him or his worde, that is, any part of his truth before men,<note place="margin">Luk. 9.26.</note> of him shall the sonne of man be ashamed, when he commeth in his glory. VVell, I thinke it now no time to dally with the Lord and his word, but let vs craue strength at his hand, that we stand vnrebukeable, vnto the day of his appearance.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>