<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all my deare and loving Countrimen in service to the States of the Vnited-Provinces: the honourable Officers, and all honest Souldiers of the English nation residing in the Netherlands; and specially (as service bindeth me) to those of Gorcom in Holland: S. B. wisheth all happie successe, and further accesse of true noblenes and worth. And after an end of a wearisome warfare in this life pre∣sent, eternall welfare in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Bachiler, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114807_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00951</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1106</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114807</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all my deare and loving Countrimen in service to the States of the Vnited-Provinces: the honourable Officers, and all honest Souldiers of the English nation residing in the Netherlands; and specially (as service bindeth me) to those of Gorcom in Holland: S. B. wisheth all happie successe, and further accesse of true noblenes and worth. And after an end of a wearisome warfare in this life pre∣sent, eternall welfare in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Bachiler, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Miles Christianus, or The campe royal : set forth in briefe meditations on the words of the Prophet Moses, Deut. 23, 9, 14. here under following, preached in the armie as Dungen-Leager, profitable for all sorts of men to reade; and published for the generall good of all that will read, By Samuel Bachiler, Preacher to the English at Gorinchem</title>
                 <author>Bachiler, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Plater, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>55, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To all my deare and loving Countrimen in service to the States of the Vnited-Provinces: the honourable Officers, and all honest Souldiers of the English nation residing in the Netherlands; and specially (as service bindeth me) to those of Gorcom in Holland: <hi>S. B.</hi> wisheth all happie successe, and further accesse of true noblenes and worth. And after an end of a wearisome warfare in this life pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, eternall welfare in the life to come.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloved Countriemen:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>The cause we haue to maintaine <hi>(Ʋi &amp; armis)</hi> is the same in substance with that which the Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites had: they, the defense and propagation of Religion in spite of the <hi>Canaanites:</hi> we, the <hi>mysti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call warre</hi> of these <hi>Provinces</hi> for the same ends, against the <hi>Papacie.</hi> And the cause remaining, the effect continueth justly. What simple <hi>Sectarie</hi> might not see (if perverse opinion had not cast a mist before his eyes) the urgent cause of warrs (the worlds insurrection against the trueth) necessarie, and so conclude the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, in armes borne by us, to withstand hellish malice; of no lesse consequence, till that be wholly verified <hi>Ies. 2, 4. Mich. 4, 3. They shall beate their swords into plowshares, and their speares into pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hookes: Nation shall not lift up a sword against nation; neyther shall they learne warre any more.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>I will put enmitie between thee and the woman, and betweene thy seed, and her seede: it shall bruise thy head, and thou shalt bruise is heele. Gen. 3.15.</hi> is an old quarrell, a grudge inveterate, which will never out. The Church of <hi>God</hi> ever was maligned, ever will be. And <hi>Christ</hi> came not to send peace, but a sword; <hi>that is in a word:</hi> to rouse up the world by accident against himself, and his <hi>everlasting Gospell,</hi> which when the world will not receiue, the world will persequute and prosequute to the extirping of it, if it were possible. Yet God defendeth his little flock; but by meanes externall ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily, though not the most potent, strong, and likely in outward
<pb facs="3"/>shew, the which notwithstanding he is pleased to blesse for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of his.</p>
   <p>And is it not apparant (as though written with the beames of the Sunne) that <hi>God</hi> shall put into the hearts of the tenne Hornes (the Kings of the earth) to fulfill his will in the judgment of the Whore by warre against her?
<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rev.</hi> 17, 16, 17.18, 9.</note> And so by outward force overthrow her outward usurped power, and state politique at length; as by the breath of his mouth, he hath in great measure alreadie (and so doeth dayly, and will do more and more) and shall utterly abolish that Spirituall jurisdiction pretended by her <hi>Clyents</hi> to be giuen her.</p>
   <p>So then, your Cause (Beloved, wherein with others you are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teressed) is good and sure: onely looke to it, that misdemeanour in your warres doe not disadvantage you. Now, what was spoken to the <hi>Warriers</hi> of <hi>God</hi> heretofore; <hi>to doe no evill,</hi> and <hi>to be holy:</hi> may well be spoken to us now, and applied as needfully, peradventure more: for, as the world is older it groweth wickeder, and men of all conditions are more dissolute in this last and worst age, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the ends of the world are fallen. And, if there were one <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chan</hi> then lurking in the Campe,
<note place="margin">
         <hi>Num.</hi> 25, 6.</note> there will be tenne now more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious: and for an impudent paire of <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cozbie</hi> then, that will come in the sight of all, while Moses and the rest are weeping before the dore of the Tabernacle, many skores I feare me now durst doe as much: and for one <hi>Korah</hi> and his Complices of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiners then, what legions of rebels may we looke for now? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for if ever, it is needfull to presse divine law upon us. <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
      </label> But (will some say) to be so strict is a thing so difficult. I answer:</p>
   <p>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
      </label> First therefore it requireth your greater heedfulnes, and to be so much the more circumspect.</p>
   <p>Secondly, were it not hard to doe, it were lesse praise-worthie to doe, but being difficult, it will argue the more spirit in thee.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, it sufficeth that it is possible in some measure to doe Euangelically, if we be carefull: so that the difficultie is not so ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute to excuse us.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, some practise &amp; proofe of holy resolution will make it more tollerable, onely get a desire from God, to approue thy self unto him. But, he that refreineth himself from evill maketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe a prey. True, a prey to evill men, to whose disgrace and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie he cannot but expose and prostrate himselfe (for by and by,
<pb facs="3"/>he is a <hi>Puritan</hi> or <hi>Precisian,</hi> (
<note n="*" place="margin">Bottondise. of true happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</note> honourable nicknames of Christiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and grace) that will not giue freedome and libertie to himselfe, though it be to damne his owne soule) but while they giue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues the raines to all evill, they make themselues a prey to the Divell.</p>
   <p>Having by occasion thought upon the subject of my ensuing dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, to explaine and apply those words of <hi>Moses;</hi> and then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering how behoofefull it might be for these times, I haue thought to giue it further vent, especially upon the judgment and approbation of some godly-learned, deeming it might be usefull; hoping, that as the least haire hath it shadow, so the least endeavour of good might doe some good.</p>
   <p>Thus much would I craue of you, to whom I appropriate this, what ever it is. First to accept of an honest purpose and intent in him who wisheth he could be more serviceable to you, and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to <hi>Gods</hi> Church. And sure I am, the good and honest will not reject it, because they will see, and I trust say, he meant well, and had a minde to further us in pietie: As for the Prophane, while he scoffeth me, I will pittie and pray for him. Secondly, Vouchsafe to put it up in your pockets, and at your Vacancie read this litle ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall. This my minde doeth giue me, you will say doeth please you: He is not prolixe by extravagant digressions from the purpose of the words, or observations therein taken up; if any thing els doth savour with you, I hope it will the more profit you. The <hi>Ship</hi> that putteth out to sea hath his helme and Pilot to govern her.
<note place="margin">Iames 3.</note> The <hi>horse</hi> that is taken up for a journey, his bridle to rule him (for their mouths must be kept in with bit and bridle. <hi>Psal. 32, 9.</hi>) And when we goe out to war against our enimies, <hi>Gods</hi> law must order us, turn us about, and bridle our wayes. If this little unworthy thing proue better then I can presage it wil, I shal be the more willing to publish another
<note place="margin">" Essaies on Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shua, wherein the proprietie of the Hebrew &amp; what the Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum, &amp; Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins haue use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is set down: paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel places of the Scripture conferred; and matter of observation throughout that booke of the Lords wars; Whereof I may say: Venit silius us{que} ad matricem: sed non est virtus ad pariendum.</note> subject, at this time by me, for fitter oportunitie when it serveth. In the meane time I commend this to your practise, and you all to <hi>Gods</hi> grace, and remaine</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Servant in Chirst: <hi>Samuel Bachiler.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>