<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114765_Fr1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00675</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22105.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114765</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Vox Regis</title>
                 <author>Scott, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Herwijck, Abraham van</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Utrecht</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 74 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothing of more moment for the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse of a Kingdome then that the Prince and People should know each other. For where this is not, there can be no confidence, but iealousie takes place on both sides, and all actions are subiect to double, and so to doubtfull interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. That the Prince therefore should know the People, all men thinke it a thing fit; he cannot otherwise manage them aright, no more then a skilfull Horseman, before he find the mouth of his Courser, whether hard and headstrong or soft and gentle. But some iudge it not fit that the people should know their Prince, for feare of contempt (knowne things being contemned) or I wot not for what other danger; and these Machiuilians I suppose, vsing or abusing this compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison, would make the Prince beleeue (if they could) that his people were Horses in deed, and that there were the same odds betwixt him and them, as there is betwixt the Rider and his Hackney. Wise Princes know the difference, though they vse the comparison; and euen Horses will know the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by his feeding dressing, hand seate, and managing or let him know they vnderstand their owne strength to his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>Reason</hi> &amp; <hi>Religion</hi> are the raines of this Bridle which gouerne the Inferiour as long as they be kept in the hand of the Superiour; but being neglected by the one, they are straight reiected by the other, and the Rider exposed to the danger of an vncertaine course and a loose seate.</p>
   <p>Now the way for the Prince to know his people is by their words or actions: and the same way is left open for the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to know their Prince.</p>
   <p>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
      </label> But it is obiected, that <hi>Salomon</hi> saith or the seruants of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Pr. 25. 3.</hi>
      </note> from him, that <hi>The heart of Kings is vnsearchable.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>
      <label type="milestone">
         <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvv. </seg>
      </label> Yet God knowes the heart of <hi>Salomon</hi> himselfe, though neuer so deepe, and man may know it also by words &amp; works rightly obserued; for by these God himselfe reueales his owne heart.</p>
   <p>The Lord to all in generall, makes himselfe &amp; his power knowne by his workes of Creation, Prouidence, and Iustice; but to his Church (who are his peculiar flocke, his kingdome) he makes his mind knowne by his word and therein reueales his grace and mercie, and the entire affection of his heart to man, still making it good with his workes.</p>
   <p>But doe the words &amp; workes of God then differ or speake a strange language that each other vnderstand not, because he speakes to all by his workes, to his Elect by his word? God forbid. He speakes to all by his workes; That is, all see but all vnderstand not what they see: but he speakes to his Church by his word; that is, he expounds to his own the meaning of his workes. His workes are but the eccho of his word, <hi>He</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ps. 33. 9</note>
      <hi>spake and it was done; He commanded and it stood fast.</hi> But because oftentimes he suffers outward crosses to befall the rightreous for some inward euill, and outward comforts to be fall the wicked, for some shadow of good vnwise men who see not the hidden causes, imagine falsely that Gods workes doe contradict his word, and so iudge God not so iust in his promises to his owne▪ &amp; in his threatnings to his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as his word proclaimes him to be. For this cause the mouthes of the malignant are opened to blaspheme; but it is no matter for them, they do but begin to exercise &amp; practise here, what they shall act eternally hereafter, with the Diuell and his angels. Yet God hath a fatherly care to satisfie his owne Elect vessels of honour; to whom, lest they should mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stake, he communicates his Spirit, thereby to acquaint them, with the course of his secret counsels and entents so farre as concernes their particulars, or the elect in general, by which
<pb facs="3"/> they see how out of the worst, all <hi>things worke togither for</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 28.</note>
      <hi>the best, to those that are Gods, called according to his purpose.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Kings are like Gods, their hearts are deepe &amp; vnsearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, by reason of the variable waies they are forced to walke for the weale of their people; their eies being in euery corner of the State, where no single man can pursue them; and yet there are buckets to draw out their entents, though neuer so deepe, close and profound. Their actions speake to all the world, &amp; tell their power, to protect their owne within, and correct their enemies without. And if their words &amp; works seem to differ, it is to those who ought to be held in suspence. But to their own, their words &amp; works speake one language, and they striue to resemble him whose substitutes they are, <hi>Who spake &amp; it was done:</hi> So should they not only looke to haue all that they command obayd, but to do &amp; performe to the full, yea, to make good to the vttermost of their power, whatsoeuer they haue spoken or promised. Nor can they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to be otherwise iudged then by their words and workes, and the concordance of these in outward apparance; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are men hauing the Spirit but in <hi>measure,</hi> not in sufficient fulnesse to communicate it to others, thereby to acquaint them with inward entents when outward actions seeme repugnant; nor can they conferre Spirituall graces, for outward humiliations; nor inrich vs with Heauen, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing once depriued vs, of the riches of Earth; nor giue vs eternall life, in exchange of temporall; nor restore temporall life, if once they haue taken it away.</p>
   <p>Whereas therfore his most excellent Maiesty hath referd vs, his poore subiects, to the reading of his bookes for the sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of his heart in point of Religion; because some actions of his, either did (as he heard) or might (as he thought) giue occasion of suspicion and iealousie to some, who looked as it</p>
   <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
   </gap>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>