<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Author to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114120_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12087</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22391.8</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114120</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Author to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Vindiciæ senectutis, or, A plea for old-age : which is senis cujusdam Cygnea cantio. And the severall points on parts of it, are laid downe at the end of the follovving introduction. By T.S. D.D</title>
                 <author>Sheafe, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>25, 210, 11 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>The Author to the Reader.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Generous Reader,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doe willingly give thee an account both of my first thoughts and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, and also of my proceedings in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing discourse. Thus conceive of them. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, know thy selfe, is said to be a voice from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and ever hath it beene held for an high and necessary point of wisdome; as contrarie-wise, nothing comes neerer to a ben<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>mmed, sottish, and Nabal-like dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, then ignorance in this case. <hi>Know you not your owne selves,</hi> saith the <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13. 5.</note> Apostle.</p>
   <p>Many there are that with great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, no lesse expence, and extreame
<pb facs="12"/>
hazard of their lives, travell into the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e parts of the world, onely out of a desire to know them, and yet know little of their owne countrey: others, that search curiously into the pollicie of forraigne kingdomes, ignorant (the meane while) of the state of that in which they are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives. Some againe are busie priers into their neighbours houses and affaires, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver taking notice how it stands with their owne at home, all with shame enough, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> that they are lesse carefull of what more▪ neerely concernes them. A mans proper and neerest home of all, is himselfe.</p>
   <p>The consideration hereof caused me to▪ looke backe to the sundry passages of my life past, and to fixe mine eye on my present condition, being now farre gone in yeares: and in this Meditation, I fell upon a serious thought of my Old-Age: as, what the discomforts of it are, that so I might addresse my selfe to seeke after the true remedy: what good I may find in it for comfort to countervaile the evils it brings: and lastly, what oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities it may afford me, for my present and future happinesse. Having, as I
<pb facs="12"/>
thought, found something by this enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, I was willing my pen should helpe my memory: and so my paper was my storer for it. Thinke not I doe it out of that itching humour, <note n="a" place="margin">Pers▪ Sat. 1.</note>
      <hi>Scire tuum nihil est,</hi> &amp;c. No, being conscious to my selfe of my emptinesse, I have ever (in privatest places of my abode) said <note n="b" place="margin">Horat.</note> with the Poet, <hi>Hae latebrae dulces.</hi> Take this rather for the true cause of my suffering the discourse to come abroad. To impart to others what we have thought of and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured in for ourselves, is (especially when it passes not immediatly from the partiall hand of the Author, but hath approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from others more judicious) a thing usuall, not discommended, no not in these scripturient times, and in my opinion, it sorts well with society, for, <hi>Bonum est natura s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>a diffusivum, &amp; usu, quo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munius, eo melius,</hi> Every good thing is naturally communicative, and in use, the more common, the better, and more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
   <p>If any shall thinke the subject of which I have made choice to be but meane, and unworthy of my so many lines in writing,
<pb facs="13"/>
and his so much paines in reading; I would offer to his consideration these three things. First, touching the contempt of this age, how great and common a sin it is. Secondly, what need men in yeares may have, in respect of some bodily defects, of inward comforts, as of a staffe to support them, that so they may passe on to the end of their race with patience. And lastly, whether it will be lost labour, timely to minde young men of the evills, which not prevented, will dogg them to the age, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wads which they securely passe along; and which is to such (<note n="b" place="margin">Iuven. Sat. 9.</note> as one termes it) <hi>non intellecta senectus.</hi> Sure I am it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> now no lesse needfull, then it was in <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> time, to re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rove them for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyeing in their youth, &amp;c. and to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warne them of their account, as <hi>Eccles. 11.</hi> also to counsell them even in the daies of their youth to remember their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, <hi>Eccles. 12.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Let no man thinke that this Treatise is onely for <hi>OLD-MEN,</hi> chiefely it looks towards them: yet every age, once come to yeeres of discretion, may hap'ly by it be put in minde of some thing or other, that
<pb facs="13"/>
will concerne it for the present; and if GOD blesse them with long-life, the benefit of it may be the greater. We may say of it, as <note n="c" place="margin">Horat. Epist. lib. 1</note> the Poet doth in another case. <hi>Aequè neglectum pueris, seni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>busque nocebit.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And so, gentle Reader, thou hast my reasons (such as they are) for my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking this taske. If thou dislike them not, then reade on.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>