<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER. Concerning the weight, and importance of this our Con∣trouersie; wherby may be resolued whatsoeuer is in question between men of different Religions at this day in England.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114058_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09061</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19352</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114058</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER. Concerning the weight, and importance of this our Con∣trouersie; wherby may be resolued whatsoeuer is in question between men of different Religions at this day in England.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvvere to the fifth part of Reportes lately set forth by Syr Edvvard Cooke Knight, the Kinges Attorney generall : Concerning the ancient &amp; moderne municipall lawes of England, vvhich do apperteyne to spirituall power &amp; iurisdiction. By occasion vvherof, &amp; of the principall question set dovvne in the sequent page, there is laid forth an euident, plaine, &amp; perspicuous demonstration of the continuance of Catholicke religion in England, from our first Kings christened, vnto these dayes. By a Catholicke deuyne</title>
                 <author>Parsons, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bellet, Francois</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72, 351, 353-386, 15 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="29"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER. Concerning the weight, and importance of this our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie; wherby may be resolued whatsoeuer is in question between men of different Religions at this day in England.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>ALBEIT</hi> the moment, and vtility of that we haue in hand (discreet Reader) will best be seene by perusall of the Treatise it self, and by thy iudicious consideration therof: yet for thy better encouragement to this labour, and to stirr thee vp to more attention herin; I haue thought good, to touch some points in generall, at this first en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, remitting the larger, and more particular decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration therof, vnto that which is to ensue throughout the whole discussion of the Controuersie.</p>
   <p n="2">2. First then, to pretermit the whole view of our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Christian antiquities, which heer by fit, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie occasion is searched &amp; laid open, togeather with the liues, and laws, gouerment, and Religion of all our Christian Kings, both before and after the <hi>Conquest</hi>; <note place="margin">
         <hi>The im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant weight of this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersy.</hi>
      </note> This one point seemeth to me to be of most moment for the present; that wheras vnder the raigne of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> (about whome principallie is our question) three sortes of Religion did stand vp, &amp; striue togeather (and doe vnto this day) the <hi>Protestant,</hi> the <hi>Puritane,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd the Catholicke: their whole contention seemeth to


<pb facs="30"/>
mee to ly within the limits of this Controuersie, moued by <hi>M. Attorney</hi> about <hi>Q. Elizabeths</hi> spirituall iurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and that out of the same, the whole may easily be determined, as presentlie you shall see.</p>
   <p n="3">3. For wheras there are two principall partes of any Religion whatsoeuer; the one, doctrine or precepts, for instruction; the other, power and authoritie, for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and gouerment; <note place="margin">
         <hi>Two partes of Religiō.</hi>
      </note> albeit the first be the ground, and foundation wheron to buyld, and worke; yet is the second that which giueth life, and motion to the former; and must try and iudge the same: for that in euery reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion or societie of men, professing one, and the self same faith, those that are the cheife mēbers therof, &amp; presumed to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aue principal power and spiritual iurisdiction therin, are they that must authorize, discerne and iustifie the doctrine therof to their followers. For as <hi>S. Augustine</hi> said in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>is daies to the <hi>Manichies</hi> that pressed him to beleeue certaine thinges out of the scripture in their sense: <hi>That he vvould not beleeue the ghospell it self to be the ghospel, except the authority of the Chuch did moue him thervnto</hi>: <note place="margin">August. contra epist. Fū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>menti. cap. 5.</note> that is to say, the cheife go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours of the Church, and such as had cheife spirituall authoritie therin from time to time: of whome Christ meant when he said: <note place="margin">Math. 18</note>
      <hi>Dic Ecclesiae,</hi> denounce it to the Church; and againe. <hi>If he heare not the Church, let him be to thee, as a heathen, or publican:</hi> so in like manner must we say in these daies, nor haue we any


<pb facs="30"/>
other reasonable answere, why we beleeue any one booke of the new, or old Testament to be scripture (that is to saie to containe doctrine of the holie ghost, and not of man) but for that the gouernours of our Church, which haue spirituall power among vs, doe tell vs so.</p>
   <p n="4">4. Yea, all Sectaries likewise, of what sorte or sect soeuer, are forced to follow the same rule; for that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer they admit to be scripture, they admit the same either vpon the credit of our Church, and gouernours therof, or of their owne, or of both; but especially indeed of their owne, which is seen by their doubting or reiecting of any parcels of scripture, doubted of, or reiected by their owne leaders, though admitted by ours. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, the booke of <hi>vvisedome,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>See</hi> Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debar. Gen. 2. li. 2. cap. 3. col. 41. 42. &amp; deinceps. Magde. ibid. Col. 53. 54. &amp; deinceps.</note> of <hi>Toby, Iudith, Ecclesiasticus,</hi> the first and second of <hi>Machabees,</hi> and other parcels of the old Testament, reiected by <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and <hi>Lutherans</hi>; as also the Epistle of <hi>S. Iames,</hi> the second and third of <hi>S. Peter,</hi> the <hi>Apocalips,</hi> and other peeces of the new testament, which our Church admitteth simply. But <hi>Caluin,</hi> and <hi>Caluinists,</hi> though expreslie they reiect them not with the <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans,</hi> as appeareth by our English Church, where they are left to stand in the Bible: <note place="margin">
         <hi>See</hi> Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin l. 1. instit. cap. 11. &amp; lib. 3. cap. 5.</note> yet is their admission so could, and conditionall, as it may rather seeme a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous dimission, then any way a faithfull, or confident acceptation.</p>
   <p n="5">
      <pb facs="31"/>5. And the same may be said of any other particular point or points of doctrine of any Religion, or sect what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer; the leaders, or gouernours that are presumed to haue cheife authoritie, must iudge and discerne, distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish, expound, and determine, what is to be beleued or not; what is to be held and taught, or reiected; and final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, what is to be done and practised; what Sacraments, what Ceremonies, what Customes are to be vsed, hovv, where, and when; And last of all this second part of power and authoritie, rule, order, gouerment, and iurisdiction is that, which giueth light, direction, and life to euerie religion. And for so much as there can be but one true, that can bring vs to saluation; <note place="margin">
         <hi>True power and spi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rituall iurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction the only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>uide to saluatiō.</hi>
      </note> it followeth, that whersoeuer this true spirituall power, and iurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is found, there is the onlie true religion also, which a man may securelie follow: yea, that vnder paine of eternall damnation, he is bound to follow, for that this authoritie will lead him to life euerlasting, Christ hauing giuen the keies of heauen thervnto, that is to say, <note place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. &amp; 18.</note> full po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to shut and open heauen by binding or loosing sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vpon earth; and that in such sort (saith S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sostome</hi> and all other ancient Fathers with him) <hi>that the Courte or Tribunall of heauen standeth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting, vvhat is done vpon earth to confirme the same there</hi>: <note place="margin">Chrysost. lib. 3. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>acer. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> 4. &amp; 5. de verb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> for so much, as euer since this admirable, vniuersall, and dreadfull authoritie was giuen (say they) by Christ vpon earth, <note place="margin">D Hier. epist. ad</note> vnto the Gouernours of his


<pb facs="31"/>
Church, nothing is done in that Court of heauen, but by presidence, and predetermination of that which is done, <note place="margin">Heliodor. de vita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> solitaria. Hilar. Can. 16 in Mat. &amp; alij a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libi.</note> or sentenced in the Tribunall of the militant Church on earth; that is to say, he that is here absolued, is absolued there, &amp; he that is here condemned, is condemned there, without remission. VVherof also the said Fathers do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre, that to find out this authoritie, and to follow the same, and the direction therof, is the only sure way to saluation. And that the erring herin, either wilfully or of ignorance, is the most certaine path to damnation; for that by no other ordinary means (since this Commission giuen, and authoritie instituted among Christians) is any grace, fauour, pardon, light, direction, or other spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall benefit to be receiued from God, but by way of this subordination of spirituall authoritie appointed in his Church.</p>
   <p n="6">6. VVherfore al hope of life depēding, as you see, of this soueraigne point so as whosoeuer erreth in this, erreth in al; ech man wil easilie cōsider how much it importeth him to looke well thervnto, and to stand attentiue and vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant in the discussion therof; to see whence, and how, and by what means, and from what sourge and fountaine, this authoritie and spirituall Iurisdiction is deriued: <note place="margin">
         <hi>Three grounds of spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie supposed by three different religiōs.</hi>
      </note> In which point the three professors of different religions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, doe principally differ, and distinguish themselues. The <hi>Protestāt</hi> deducing this spiritual power from the temporall Prince (or rather Princesse vnder


<pb facs="32"/>
      <hi>Q. Elizabeth.</hi>) The <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>See Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright, Iunius, &amp; other of then allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in</hi> the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey of preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline. Cap. 16. Rom. 13. Math. 24</note>
      <hi>Puritane</hi> from the people. The <hi>Catholicke</hi> from the succession of Bishops from Christs time downe wards, and especially from the highest, which they hold to be <hi>S. Peter,</hi> and his successours. And which part soeuer of these three hitteth right, goeth happely &amp; securelie, &amp; the other two doe run to euerlasting perditiō.</p>
   <p n="7">7. The Protestant for his ground, hath those sayings of scripture: <hi>That all orderly authoritie is from God.</hi> That <hi>vve must giue to Cesar, that vvhich is Cesars</hi>: That <hi>Princes are to be honoured, and obeyed for God;</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. pet. 2.</note>
      <hi>and Kings, as highest in dignitie,</hi> and that <hi>he vvhich resisteth lavvfull authoritie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth Gods ordination: and therby incurreth damnation &amp;c.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>The foū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants assertiō.</hi>
      </note> All which the other two parties gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, doe affirme to haue byn vnderstood of tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall authoritie only, for gouerning the Commonwealth; and not of spirituall for gouerning of soules, which they proue: for that all Kings, and Princes were then infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, and especially the Roman Emperours of whom this was principally meant, who by these places of scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, cannot be said to haue receiued Commission, to gouerne the Christian Church, which was in their times, and vnder their dominions; but onlie in temporall matters, and Ciuill affaires. And that the spirituall power and iurisdiction wherof we talke, was at that time in another sorte of men, to wit in the Apostles and their successours, which were Bishops, according to the


<pb facs="32"/>
testimonie of <hi>S. Paul</hi> in the Acts of the <hi>Apostles,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Acts 20.</note> spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vnto them, and saying: <hi>The holie Ghost hath placed you Bishops to gouerne his Church vvhich he hath purchased vvith his ovvne bloud.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="8">8. The <hi>Puritanes,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Puritane groūdes.</hi> Acts <hi>1.23.</hi>
      </note> or rigid <hi>Caluinists</hi> haue for their ground, certaine elections made by the people, and recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as well in the Acts of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> as in other hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stories of the Primitiue Church: as for example when they chose two in the place of <hi>Iudas,</hi> to wit, <hi>Ioseph,</hi> and <hi>Matthias,</hi> to bee determined by lot which of them should be. And when afterward they chose S. <hi>Stephen,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Acts 6.5.</note> &amp; six others to supply the place of <hi>Deacons,</hi> &amp; many ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes afterward in the primitiue Church we read, that the people did choose or name their Bishops. But to this, the other two parties doe answere, that in the first two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, out of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> it is euident by the Text, that those elections, or nominations were permitted to the people, by the <hi>Apostles</hi> themselues, for their comforte and encouragement; but that the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties so chosen, had, &amp; receiued their authority &amp; spiritual iurisdiction from the <hi>Apostles</hi> themselues. And the like is answered for the times ensuing, wherin the Bishops did oftentimes permit the said electios to the people, for their greater cōtentment, &amp; consolation in those daies of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutiō, to choose &amp; nominate for their Bishop &amp; Pastor the man whom they best liked, who afterward was inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted &amp; cōsecrated by the said Bishops notwithstāding: &amp;


<pb facs="33"/>
tooke his iurisdiction, and spirituall power from them, to whom properly that power and authoritie belonged, to ordaine, both Bishops, and Priests, as we see the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles themselues did euerie where, and gaue the like autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to others ordained by them. As we read, that <hi>S. Paul</hi> hauing made <hi>Titus</hi> Bishop of <hi>Creta,</hi> gaue him or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der also to ordaine: <hi>vt cōstituas per ciuitates presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teros, sicut &amp; ego disposui tibi.</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Tit. 5.</note> That thou ordaine Priests for Citties, as I haue appointed thee.</p>
   <p n="9">9. The <hi>Catholickes</hi> for their groūd haue this: That Bishops only, &amp; Priests were made spirituall gouernous of Christs Church by Christ himself, and so continued vader Infidel Emperours for three hundered yeares to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Groūdes of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks for spiritual iurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
      </note> vntill the time of <hi>Constantine</hi> the great, that was first conuerted, as afterward more largely will be shewed in due place; and that this authoritie is to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in lawfull succession of Bishops, by ordination, and imposition of hands, vntill the worlds end. And that neither temporall Prince can haue this, except he be also Priest, and receiued it by the same ordinary way of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination and succession (whereof <hi>Q. Elizabeth</hi> was not capable) and much lesse the common people, except only by permission, to elect and nominate, as hath byn said: wherof ensueth that if they haue not this spirituall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in themselues; much lesse can they giue it to others. And thus according to the Catholickes iudgment, doe faile the grounds, both of the <hi>Protestant,</hi> and <hi>Puritan</hi> in


<pb facs="33"/>
this great affaire: and failing in this, doe faile in all the rest; for that of this, dependeth all, as before hath byn said.</p>
   <p n="10">10. For if in their Religions, there be no true autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie spirituall, or iurisdiction, deriued by ordinarie me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and succession from Christ; <note place="margin">
         <hi>Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi>
      </note> then are they awry in all, nor haue they any true authority, to preach, admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister Sacraments, absolue, or bind from sinnes, iudge of doctrine, determine or decree of any spirituall action whatsoeuer; nor are they within the compasse of Christs Church, or state of saluation, as by necessarie conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence doth ensue; and the like of the <hi>Catholickes,</hi> if they in this point be amisse</p>
   <p n="11">11. And herby we may see the importance now of this controuersie, between <hi>M. Attorney</hi> and me, as also their shallow vnderstāding (if they speake as they thinke) or rather malicious folly (if they doe not) who affirme euery where in their bookes against <hi>Catholickes,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Sir Frācis Hastings against the</hi> vvard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvord <hi>&amp; M. Sut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliffe in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</hi>
      </note> that <hi>Protestants</hi> and <hi>Puritanes</hi> are but onlie iarring-bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and reconcilable between themselues, and that their differences are not in principall points of Religion, but in certaine lesser things, and ceremonies. For that this being indeed, not onlie so substantiall a point of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as before you haue heard; but containing also the whole second part of Religion before mentioned (to wit, all that belongeth to power, authoritie, gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and iurisdiction) by which Religion hath her life, vertue, force, and efficacy: It is easily seen, how vaine,


<pb facs="34"/>
and false, or rather ridiculous and pernicious the other assertion is, and if we well enter into the examination of particulars, we shall easilie see the same.</p>
   <p n="12">12. For suppose (for examples sake) that the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants</hi> ground be true, that all spirituall iurisdiction, force, and efficacie therof came vnto their Church in <hi>Queene Elizabeths</hi> time, by her, and from her, out of the Right of her Crowne; &amp; that the <hi>Puritanes</hi> ground be false, who pretend the same from the people, I meane from their owne Congregations, Classes, &amp; Presbyteries (for no other gaue it them) what followeth of all this? No doubt, it must needs follow, by manifest consequence of truth, that the <hi>Puritanes</hi> haue no authoritie, or spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall iurisdiction in the Church of God at all, nor are lawfull Pastors, but vsurpers, and intruders; <note place="margin">
         <hi>Puritan and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants grounds vncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible.</hi>
      </note> and that they entred not by the doore, as Christ saith, but by other means: that is to saie, not by the ordinarie doore of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vocation, ordination, and succession of Priesthood. Of which doore the Apostle <hi>S. Paul</hi> made such high ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, as hauing set downe that vninersal proposition to the Hebrews: <note place="margin">Heb. 5. 2. para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip. 10.</note>
      <hi>Nec quisquam sumit sibi honorem, sed qui vocatur a Deo, tanquam Aâron.</hi> That no man taketh vnto him the honour of being a Bishop, or Priest, but he that is called by God therevnto, as Aâron was in the old law. <note place="margin">Psal. 2.</note> After this (I saie) he passeth on to proue, that Christ himself the sonne of God, tooke not this honour of high Priesthood vpon him, but by the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike testimonie of his said Fathers vocation, set downe


<pb facs="34"/>
by the Prophet Dauid, manie hundred years before he was borne. <hi>Tu es sacerdos in aeternum secūdum or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem Melchisedech.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 1</note> Thou art a Priest for euer, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the order of <hi>Melchisedech,</hi> and not of Aâron. And according to this high order of <hi>Melchisedech,</hi> that was both King and Priest, and whose sacrifice was not of beasts and birds, as those of Aâron, but of bread, and wyne onlie, to prefigurate the most pure, and holie sacrifice, that Christian Priests were to offer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward to the worldes end, of the body and bloud of Christ, in like formes of bread and wyne, as all an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <note n="*" place="margin">Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. l. 2. ep. 3. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust. l. 16. de Ciuit. Des. cap. 22. &amp; l. 1. contra aduers. leg. &amp; Proph. cap. 2. &amp; lib. 2. cont. lit. Petil. c. 37. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sost. hom. 35. in Gen. Clem.</note> Fathers doe expound it: Of this order (I say) Christ being high Priest, made all his Apostles Priests, and they others after them, and they others againe, by the ordinarie way of ordination, imposition of hands, and succession, which hath endured from their time to ours, and shall from ours, vntill the day of iudgement.</p>
   <p n="13">13. And this ordinarie doore (so called by Christ our Sauiour) of entring into spirituall authoritie, and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction ouer his flocke, is of such high esteeme and importance, that as the first generall doore, <note place="margin">Alexād. lib. 4. strom.</note> wherby a man must enter to be a sheep in the said flocke, to wit Baptisme, is a Sacrament, not reiterable, <note place="margin">Ambros. l. 4. de Sacram. c. 3. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom. in cap. 1. ad <hi>Titum.</hi> &amp; alij. Ioan. 10.</note> and so abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutelie necessarie, as no man can enter by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way: so likwise this other particuler doore of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into Prelacie, or Pastor-shipp ouer Christs flocke, was ordayned a Sacrament by our Sauiour, no


<pb facs="35"/>
lesse necessarie for distinguishing theeues, robbers, and intruders, from true and lawfull Pastors (to vse our Sauiours similitude) then the other of Baptisme, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish sheep from wolues, and Christs flocke, from In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidells and others of the Synagoge of Satan.</p>
   <p n="14">14. And now in all this which we haue spoken by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of the <hi>Puritanes</hi> pretence, to enter into spirituall gouerment ouer Christs flocke, by voice and choise of their owne people, we doe not much differ from their Maister and Doctor <hi>Iohn Caluin,</hi> who confesseth that this doore or entrance to the Clergie by lawfull voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ordination, is so necessarie, as if it be not obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, all would grow to confusion, and no man could know, who hath spirituall iurisdiction ouer soules, and who hath not. <note place="margin">Caluin. lib. 4. instit. cap. 19. §. 31. &amp; 14. §. 31.</note> And further he confesseth that albeit be appoint but two generall Sacraments for all sortes of people, <hi>Baptisme</hi> (to witt) and the <hi>Lords supper</hi>: yet he graunteth this Ordination of Church-ministers, to be a true Sacrament also, and to haue promise of grace an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed vnto it, as other Sacraments haue, but that it strecheth not so far, as the other two doe; but is particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar for ministers and Clergie-men onlie.</p>
   <p n="15">15. But then if we presse him, how he, and his came in by this doore; he and they haue no other shift, but to say, that their first maisters and teachers entred in by this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie vocation and ordination of our Bishops (for others there were none at that time to call; or ordayne them) from whom afterward they disioyned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues


<pb facs="35"/>
in doctrine, to ioyne with the Apostles. And this is the leap they make from our age to the Apostles time.</p>
   <p n="16">16. But suppose they could say this of their first tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, that they had their ordination, and consequentlie also their vocation and spirituall iurisdiction from our Bishops; yet afterward when they fell to different do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and for that cause were cut of by excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from them, and especiallie now when the said first teachers are dead and gone; they can haue no other assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their vocation of ministerie, then from the people of their owne sect, in their Presbyteries, as before hath byn said: which how much it is, or whether it may be any thing at all, shall <note n="*" place="margin">Infra cap. 2.</note> afterward be discussed.</p>
   <p n="17">17. Now it shall be sufficient onlie, for the argument of this Preface, concerning the weight, and importance of this Controuersie we haue with <hi>M. Attorney</hi> about spirituall iurisdiction, that we consider, and beare in mind the different origen, from which ech partie of the foresaid three professors of Religion, doe pretend to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riue their right and interest to the said spirituall iuris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, which they exercise. And what side soeuer erreth therin, erreth also in the maine marke of their saluation, and doth draw both themselues, and their followers to euerlasting perdition. And furthermore that the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence &amp; contrariety in this point, is much more between <hi>Puritanes</hi> and <hi>Protestants,</hi> then between them both and <hi>Catholickes</hi>: For that they both doe graunt and cannot denie, but that the deduction of spirituall iuris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction


<pb facs="36"/>
in our Catholike Prelates, <note place="margin">
         <hi>The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan yelde more in deed, to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke then to ech o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
      </note> hath come downe line-allie, and successiuelie by ordination, and imposition of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ands, the one of the other, from the Apostles time, though declined (as they saie) in doctrine. But we, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary side, doe inferre the suretie of our doctrine, by the certaintie of this succession of Priestlie power, and spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall iurisdiction. For that whersoeuer this is trulie to be found, which cannot be but in the true Church; there also hath Christ assured vs, that by his omnipotent power and presence, the puritie, and certaintie of doctrine shall euer in like manner be infallibly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued.</p>
   <p n="18">18. But to the <hi>Protestant,</hi> the <hi>Puritane</hi> doth not yeeld thus much by manie degrees, and much lesse the <hi>Protestant</hi> to the <hi>Puritane.</hi> For they doe not graunt the one, to the other, that they haue true ordination of Priests and ministers among them, as to vs they doe: in s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>gne wherof, if anie Priest of ours doe fall to their side<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> they giue him no new orders, but thinke him sufficientlie ordayned by vs, to minister in their Church, which the <hi>Protestant</hi> doth not admit in <hi>Puritane</hi> ministers, <note place="margin">
         <hi>The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters not ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted the one by the other.</hi>
      </note> but that they must be ordered againe by their Bishops, as hauing no Orders before; nor yet the <hi>Puritanes</hi> with the <hi>Protestant</hi>-ministers when they turne vnto them, but doe appoint, that he renounce his former Orders in their Congregation, or Presbyterie; and by new imposition of hands of the said Presbiterie he be ordayned a new minister in that profession: so as by opinion and estima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion


<pb facs="36"/>
of the Protestant-religion, the <hi>Puritane-ministers</hi> are meere laie-men, taking vpon them spirituall iurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ouer soules without any lawfull authoritie, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission at al; and consequentlie haue no power to preach or teach, or administer Sacraments, and much lesse haue they that high, and excellent iudiciall authoritie to binde, or loose sinnes. <note place="margin">
         <hi>What the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan is to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant by this grounde of spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall power.</hi>
      </note> And that which followeth also of this, that they haue no Sacraments at all, no Clergie, no mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisterie, no sacred or diuine thinge; but are onlie a lay companie of men and women, ioyned togeather in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine worldlie secular society, as <hi>Fish-mongers, Iron-mongers, Drapes,</hi> and other like companies in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi> And the same opinion haue they of the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants,</hi> and of their Church.</p>
   <p n="19">19. And by this you may see, how farre they differ in substance of religion (though somtimes for fashion-sake they call themselues <hi>Brethren</hi>) more indeed then both of them from vs, as before hath byn said; which procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from this mayne ground &amp; Principle, to wit, from whence ech part draweth their Ecclesiastical Power, &amp; Spiritual Iurisdictiō ouer soules: for that this being once found out, all the rest is easie and cleere, for so much as this true spirituall authoritie, can be but in one partie, and in one Church onlie, which is the true: and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer it is found, there is assurance also of all truth, Christ hauing promised vs, that this Church, and the true Pastors thereof shall not deceiue vs, <note place="margin">Mar. vlt. Luc. 10. 1. Tim. 3.</note> nor be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. And therefore that we may boldlie, and confiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie


<pb facs="37"/>
heare their voice, and doe that which they bid vs, though otherwise in life, and manners, they should be as bad as <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pharises.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 23.</note>
   </p>
   <p n="20">20. And on the other side where this true authoritie, and lawfull iurisdiction is not, there we must not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, though they speake neuer so faire, for that we are fore-told and fore-taught, <note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> that they are but wolues in sheeps apparrel, false prophets to deceiue, theeues and murderers to kill and destroie, <note place="margin">Iohn. 10.</note> &amp; other such fore-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings left vnto vs by Christ and his Apostles. All which ought to make vs vigilant, attent, diligent, &amp; curious to vnderstand really the truth about Spirituall Iuris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, which in the ensuing <hi>Treatise</hi> is handled, so far forth, as <hi>M. Attorney</hi> hath giuen occasion, though no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing so largely, as the thing it selfe might be discussed; but yet sufficientlie for euerie discreet man to see the grounds, and with that modestie also (I hope) as may iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stlie offend no man. And so I shall now passe on, to ioyne with <hi>M. Attorney</hi> more neerly in the maine battaile, if first by the way (as it were of skirmish) we shall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere somewhat in like manner to his <hi>Preface,</hi> wherin diuers points are not vnworthy of consideration.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>