<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most Reuerend Father in GOD, the Lord
Archbishop of Canterbury his GRACE, PRIMATE and ME∣TROPOLITAN
of all England, and one of his MAIESTIES
most Honourable Priuie Councell. And to the Right Honourable SIR EDVVARD
COKE, Lord Cheefe Iustice of England, and one of his Maiesties most Ho∣norable
Priuie Councell: THOMAS MASON wisheth all Happinesse
in this Life, and eternall Felicitie in the world
to come.</title>
           <author>Queen Elizabeth</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114403_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07225</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17622</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114403</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most Reuerend Father in GOD, the Lord
Archbishop of Canterbury his GRACE, PRIMATE and ME∣TROPOLITAN
of all England, and one of his MAIESTIES
most Honourable Priuie Councell. And to the Right Honourable SIR EDVVARD
COKE, Lord Cheefe Iustice of England, and one of his Maiesties most Ho∣norable
Priuie Councell: THOMAS MASON wisheth all Happinesse
in this Life, and eternall Felicitie in the world
to come.</title>
                 <author>Queen Elizabeth</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Christs victorie ouer Sathans tyrannie : Wherin is contained a catalogue of all Christs faithfull souldiers that the Diuell either by his grand captaines the emperours, or by his most deerly beloued sonnes and heyres the popes, haue most cruelly martyred for the truth. With all the poysoned doctrins wherewith that great redde dragon hath made drunken the kings and inhabitants of the earth; with the confutations of them together with all his trayterous practises and designes, against all Christian princes to this day, especially against our late Queen Elizabeth of famous memorie, and our most religious Soueraigne Lord King Iames. Faithfully abstracted out of the Book of martyrs, and diuers other books. By Thomas Mason preacher of Gods Word</title>
                 <author>Foxe, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Blower (Blore), Ralph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 418, 14 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the most Reuerend Father in GOD, the Lord
Archbishop of Canterbury his GRACE, PRIMATE and ME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TROPOLITAN
of all England, and one of his MAIESTIES
most Honourable Priuie Councell. And to the Right Honourable SIR EDVVARD
COKE, Lord Cheefe Iustice of England, and one of his Maiesties most Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable
Priuie Councell: THOMAS MASON wisheth all Happinesse
in this Life, and eternall Felicitie in the world
to come.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST Reuerend and Right Honorable zealous Lords,
your daily and faithfull Orator, being a professed Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
vnder Christs Banner, in the behalfe of his spouse a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
Antichrist: I could busie my selfe in no office so pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable
for the Church, and hurtfull vnto Antichrist, as
to gather together the bullets which haue been shot at him by Christs Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours
in times past, that now his children may shoote them at him againe,
with great facilitie. And whereas venerable M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>Fox,</hi> of worthy memory,
hath gathered into one Booke the Acts and Monuments of the Church vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
his time; one of the most profitablest Bookes that is for Gods Children,
except the Bible; a Club able to beate downe the Popish Tower of Babell:
Yet what with the labour of reading so large a volume, together
with the deareness of the price thereof, few that haue the Booke reade
it ouer, and the most part of men are not able to buy it, whereby very
little profit ariseth thereof vnto the Church. I haue, according to my po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer,
pared off the barke of this Club, and made it tractable for all sorts
of people; they may buy it with little charge, and peruse it with small
paines; and I dare promise them that they shall reape as much profit by
reading this abridgement, as by reading of the Booke at large. I haue
willingly omitted no matter of substance: Here the Reader may see the
cruelty of the Emperors vnto the Primitiue Church, and whom they put
<pb facs="3"/>
to death, and the manner of their deathes during the first ten Persecutions;
and how, and when Christianitie began in this Realme: And what successe
it hath had at all times; and when, by what occasion, and by whom most of
the Monasteries, and Cathedrall Churches of this Realme were builded, and
how, when, and by whom, all points of Popery came into the Church; and
how the Pope hath exalted himself against Emperors &amp; Kings; what iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
he hath done to them: With the Treasons, &amp; Conspiracies that Papists
haue practised, against those that the Lord hath annointed, vnto this day:
The Reader may also heere see the innumerable multitude of the Saints of
God, that the Papists haue from time to time murdered in all Countries▪ for
the testimonie of the Truth: With all the points of Religion that the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs
did defend vnto death; and all the reasons that the Papists vsed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
their Arguments, and how cruelly they handled them; with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
most profitable things. After I had done this Booke, I was discoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
from putting of it to Print, by reason I found another had abridged the
Booke of Martyrs before me; but when I perceiued it was done but super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially,
for all the points of Religion that the Martyrs defended, or Papists
obiected were omitted; (which disputations I chiefly labour to set forth)
therevpon I was resolued to goe forward. When I had begun to quote all the
Authors, from whence <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Fox</hi> had his proofes for them that the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors
put to death, the Quotations were almost as large as the Story, and
made it very vnpleasant: wherefore in most places, for breuitie, I haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
them, leauing them that would see the proofes to the Book at large.
I haue herein abridged many bookes, but especially the Booke of Martyrs;
as the Papists cannot abide the booke of Martyrs of all bookes: so much
more will they hate my booke, which hath so truely and briefely discouered
all their shame, not onely out of that booke, but out of diuers other bookes.
Wherefore most Reuerend, and Right Honorable Lords, your manifest
dislike that you beare against the wickednes and falshood of Antichrist;
hath imboldned me to be an humble sutor vnto your Lordships, to bee the
Patrons of this my Booke, and that you would vouchsafe to defend and
further it, by your Spirituall and Temporall Powers, to the honour of
Christ, the great dishonour of Antichrist, and the vnspeakeable benefit of
Gods Children. So with my hartie prayers, I commit both your Honors,
your soules, bodies, and all that you haue, vnto the safe preseruation of
Christ Iesus and his holy Angels.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships daily Oratour, THOMAS MASON, Preacher of
Gods word in Odiham, in the County of Southampton: whose
Father was Heire vnto S<seg rend="sup">r</seg> IOHN MASON, sometime a
Priuy Councelor vnto Queene ELIZABETH.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>