<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114357_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09202</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19511</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114357</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Minerua Britanna or A garden of heroical deuises : furnished, and adorned with emblemes and impresa's of sundry natures, newly devised, moralized, and published, by Henry Peacham, Mr. of Artes</title>
                 <author>Peacham, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dight, Walter</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>15, 100, 4, 101-212, 1 page, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> haue heere (kind Reader) sent abroad vnto thy view, this volume of <hi>Emblemes,</hi> whether for greatnes of the chardge, or that the Invention is not ordinarie: a Subiect very rare. For except the collections of Master <hi>Whitney,</hi> and the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of some one or two else beside, I know not an <hi>Englishman</hi> in our age, that hath publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any worke of this kind: they being (I doubt not) as ingenious, and happy in their invention, as the best French or Italian of them all. Hence perhaps they terme vs <hi>Tramontani Sempii,</hi> Simple and of dull conceipt, when the fault is neither in the Climate, nor as they would haue it, in the constitution of our bodies, but truely in the cold &amp; frozen respect of Learning, and artes, generally amongst vs: comming far shorte of them in the iust valewing of well deseruing qualities. To begin at the foote of their <hi>Alpes,</hi> and so discend by <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie</hi> (which <hi>Bodine</hi> truly termeth <hi>officinam hominum,</hi> a shoppe of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute men for all Artes) how she hath excelled in this, as in all other rare Invention, witnesse the many volumes she hath sent vs over of this Subiect. With what excellent Bodies, and <hi>Motto's,</hi> haue the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landes</hi> especially <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Zealand,</hi> vpon sundry occasions (as the recoverie of their Libertie, the overthrow in <hi>eighty eight,</hi> and the like) commended their Invention to the world? as we finde in <hi>Meteranus,</hi> and others. I should seeme partiall, if I should lay to your view, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and almost vnimitable <hi>Impresa's</hi> of our owne Countrie: as those of <hi>Edward</hi> the black Prince, <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, <hi>Henry</hi> the seuenth, <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the eight, Sir <hi>Thomas Moore,</hi> the Lord <hi>Cromwell,</hi> &amp; of later times, those done by Sir <hi>Phillip Sydney,</hi> and others. Nor were it needefull since their Memory is fresh, and many of their sheildes yet scarce drie in the world. Who hath ever seene more wittie, proper, &amp; significant devises, then those of <hi>Scotland</hi>? (to omit more auntient times) as that of <hi>King Iames</hi> the third, devising for himselfe (to expresse the care he had of his country and People) a <hi>Hen</hi> sitting over her <hi>Chickens,</hi> with the word <hi>Non dormit qui custodit</hi>: as also of <hi>Iames</hi> the fowrth, taking to himselfe a bifront, or double face, plac't vpon the top of a Columne: the heades crowned with <hi>Laurell,</hi> the word <hi>Vtrumque</hi>: meaning (as
<pb facs="4"/>
it is thought) he would constantly, and advisedly like <hi>Ianus,</hi> obserue the proceedings aswell of the <hi>French</hi> as the <hi>English,</hi> holding them both at that time in Ielousie. Many and very excellent haue I seene of his <hi>Maiesties</hi> owne Invention, who hath taken herein in his yonger years great delight, and pleasure, by which thou maiest see, that we are not so dull as they would imagine vs, nor our Soile so barren as that we neede to borrow from their Sunne-burnt braines, our best Invention. Whereas I haue heere dedicated many <hi>Emblemes</hi> to sundry and great Personages, (yea some to Forraigne Princes,) I haue heerein but imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated the best approued Authours in this kind: as <hi>Alciat, Sambucus, Iunius, Reusnerus,</hi> and others: they being such, as either in regard of their transcendent dignitie, and vertues, deserue of all to be honoured: or others whome for their excellent parts and qualities, I haue ever lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and esteemed: or lastly some of my private friendes, to whome I haue in particular beene most beholden some way or other. Wherein I trust thou wilt not condemne me, since I haue no other meane then by word to shew a thankfull minde towards them.</p>
   <p>It is not my intent here (which I might well doe) to diseourse at large of the Nature and Libertie of <hi>Embleme,</hi> wherein it differeth from the <hi>Impresa</hi>; because heerein I haue beene alreadie prevented by <note place="margin">Paulns Iovius. Sambucus. Mr. Sam. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niell.</note> others. The true vse heereof from time to time onely hath beene, <hi>Vtile dulci miscere,</hi> to feede at once both the minde, and eie, by expressing misti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally and doubtfully, our disposition, either to <hi>Loue, Hatred, Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, Iustice, Pietie,</hi> our <hi>Victories, Misfortunes, Griefes,</hi> and the like<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> which perhaps could not haue beene openly, but to our praeiudice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed. And in truth the bearer heerein doth but as the Travailer, that changeth his Silver into Gold, carry about his affection in a narrow roome, and more safely; the valew rather bettered then abated.</p>
   <p>Accept I pray thee in good worth, what I haue heere done, not for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hope of reward, or gaine, but onely for thy pleasure, and recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Imagining thou art delighted (as I haue ever beene my selfe) with these ever esteemed, honest, and most commendable Devises.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine assuredly, <hi>HENRY PEACHAM.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>