<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Tombes, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114334_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09262</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19576a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114334</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Tombes, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Fiue godly, and profitable sermons : concerning 1 The slaverie of sinne. 2 The mischiefe of ignorance. 3 The roote of apostasie. 4 The benefit of Gods service. 5 The Christians loue. Preached in his life time in sundry places. By that late faithfull minister of Christ Mr William Pemble of Magdalen Hall in the Vniversity of Oxford</title>
                 <author>Pemble, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 <publisher>Forrest, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lichfield, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 24, 72, 31-39, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HRISTIAN Reader: These ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons were by the godly, and learned Author of them fitted for the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations to which he was to speake, &amp; no doubt intended onely for the benefit of hearers, not of readers. Neverthelesse it was the desire of many that they might bee published vpon hope of good that might be done to the Church of God by them. There is neede of plaine instructions to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite men to holynes of life, as well as accurate trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises to discerne trueth from error. For which end I dare promise these Sermons will make much, where they finde an honest, and humble reader. It was the Authors greatest care <hi>to handle the word of God by manifestation of the truth commending himselfe to every mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science in the sight of God;</hi> as once S. Paul pleaded for himselfe.<note place="margin">Gell. noct. Attic. lib. 1. cap. 15.</note> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 2. And if that be the property (which they say) of an eloquent, and
<pb facs="3"/> good speaker <hi>non ex ore, sed ex pectore,</hi> to speak frō his hart rather thā his tongue, then sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this Author was an excellent orator, one that spake out of sound vnderstanding with true affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō. Many excellencies there were in him for which his memory remaines: but this aboue all was his crowne that he vnfainedly sought Gods glory, and the good of mens soules. It remaines, that these sermons be read by thee with a care to profit, and thanksgiving to God for the benefit thou hast by them, sith they are such talents, as in the vse of which hee requires, and expects to bee glorified: Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord Iesus IOHN TOMBES.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>