<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Printer to the READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114813_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16990</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3870</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114813</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Printer to the READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A letter to a friende, touching Mardochai his age : which helpeth much to holde the trueth, for that chiefe prophecie of our saluation in Gabriels seuenties: which shew, that most exactly 490. yeeres after the angels speach, Christ the most holy should be killed, to giue life. Dan 9.23</title>
                 <author>Broughton, Hugh</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>White, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Printer to the READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT the Letter following might better be vnderstood, I requested the Authour, that one speciall Text might be set before it, as hee had translated it. <hi>Daniel,</hi> 9.24. I heard him affirme, that none, for skill in Hebrew, would blame that Translation: and though many differ, it was not for ignoraunce of the tongue; but by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite touching the matter, drawing the words as they iudged of the whole cause. Thus he transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that poynt, which was <hi>Gabriels</hi> speach; who came to
<hi>Daniel,</hi> praying at the time of the Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning offering, or three of the clocke, or ninth houre by Scripture phrase: (<note n="§" place="margin">For so he wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the letter.</note> at which houre 490. yeares after most exactly, our Lord gaue vp the Ghost, and told, that at the beginning of his<note n="*" place="margin">So the author taught. that euen the faythles Iew Aben Ezra vpon Dan. 9. begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the time from the word that came forth at Daniels pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and endeth it when Christ is sealed. And that the Iew though he could not cast the times particularly, nor knew Christ to be the most Holy, yet durst not depart from the proprietie of plaine wordes, to peruert the speach of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God; &amp; be wished others that circumspec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Such as begin &amp; end to that effect, may not make here a certaine num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, for an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine.</note> Prayer, came foorth the word (or answere from God) which he came to shew, and sayth
<pb facs="3"/>thus. <hi>Seauentie seauens (of yeares) are cut out, for thy people, and for thy holy Citie; to consume wickednesse, and to abolish sinnes, and to make reconciliation for iniquitie, and to bring righteousnesse euerlasting, and to seale Vision and Prophet, and to shew</hi> Christ, <hi>the</hi> Holy <hi>of</hi> Holy. <hi>Know and marke; from the out-going of the Word, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne and to build</hi> Ierusalem,
<hi>vnto</hi> Christ <hi>the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, shalbe seauen seauens (of yeares,) and sixtie and two seauens:</hi> (in th'other) <hi>it shall be restored and built, Street and Wall; and troublous shall these times be. In that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the sixtie and two seauens,</hi> Christ <hi>shall be killed; and not for him selfe: thereupon the Citie and Holy place shall he destroy, the</hi> Gouernours <hi>owne people to come, &amp; their end shalbe with a Flood: and at the end of Warre, it shall haue a finall iudgement to desolation. But hee shall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the Testament for many the last Seauen; when in</hi> Halfe that Seauen, <hi>hee shall end the Sacrifice and Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Afterwardes, by an Armie abominable, hee shall make a desolation, euen till vtter destruction, and finall iudgement flow vpon the desolate.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And thus much for the Readers preparation, to vnderstand the Epistle following.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>