<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, Sir FRANCIS BACON, Knight, Lord Keeper of the Great Seale, my very singu∣lar good Lord; All in∣crease of true Honour, with the glorious comforts of Grace.</title>
           <author>Worship, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114443_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15711</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25985</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114443</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, Sir FRANCIS BACON, Knight, Lord Keeper of the Great Seale, my very singu∣lar good Lord; All in∣crease of true Honour, with the glorious comforts of Grace.</title>
                 <author>Worship, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christians iewell. Or, The treasure of a good conscience. By William Worship, Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Worship, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 <publisher>Fetherstone (Featherstone), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Parker, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Parker, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 243, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, <hi>Sir</hi> FRANCIS BACON, Knight, <hi>Lord Keeper of the Great Seale,</hi> my very singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar good <hi>Lord;</hi> All in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of true Honour, with the glorious comforts of <hi>Grace.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Gospell</hi> (Right <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable</hi>) is like the <hi>Booke</hi> of <hi>Canticles;</hi> which begins with a <hi>Kisse,</hi> and ends in <hi>Spices.</hi> The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie sound of it imports <hi>Glad
<pb facs="3"/> Tidings of</hi> PEACE; without<note place="margin">Rom. 10. 15.</note> which, this Inch of time al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted, is but <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>a Dead kinde of Life,</hi> as <hi>Plato</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. De Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub.</note> speaks of a <hi>Guilty Conscience.</hi> Forwere a man <hi>The Darling of the World,</hi> with <hi>Titus Ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pasian;</hi> were he so repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed with all earthly good things, as that no mortall creature <hi>durst</hi> wish the like,<note place="margin">De Ciuit. Dei, l. 5. c. 25.</note> as S. <hi>Augustine</hi> speakes of <hi>Constantine the Great:</hi> yet if in this matchlesse prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, hee want the fauour of GOD, and <hi>Tranquillitie</hi> of minde; he is no better than<note place="margin">AElian. l. 1.</note>
      <hi>Xerxes Plane-Tree,</hi> which tooke no delight in it selfe, though it was richly hung with <hi>Bracelets, Tablets, Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles, Chaines of Gold.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>This <hi>Peace</hi> of GOD, so<note place="margin">Phil. 4 7. Gal. 6. 16. Col. 3. 15.</note> much magnified in <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> is better known by <hi>fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> than <hi>Discourse;</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fayrest <hi>Iewell</hi> vnder Heauen, is peculiarly giuen to the <hi>Elect,</hi> who cherish the sparke therof, with workes of <hi>Pietie</hi> to GOD, and <hi>Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> to their Neighbour.</p>
   <p>Thus, in briefe, hath your <hi>Lordship</hi> the drift, and scope of this present <hi>Indeuour.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now that I, a <hi>Grasse-hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> (in respect of many lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) dare thus boldly, and hoarcely sing in the eyes and hearing of <hi>Him,</hi> who is <hi>Magnus</hi> in <hi>Magnis, Prim{us}</hi> in<note place="margin">Hieron. Ad Pammach:</note>
      <hi>Primis, <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Herôum,</hi> is, (I confesse) <hi>Piaculum:</hi> whereunto notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="4"/> the <hi>Noblenesse</hi> of your <hi>Honours</hi> disposition (which is wont with <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> to<note place="margin">AElian. l. 1.</note> take in worth <hi>Synaetas</hi> hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of water) the <hi>Correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> of the <hi>Treatise</hi> with that High place of <hi>Iustice</hi> whereto God hath aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced you; together with the zeale of declaring my thankefulnes, and duty for so many <hi>Incouragements</hi> vouchsafed from your <hi>Lordship,</hi> haue, in a manner, instigated me.</p>
   <p>Goe on (most Noble <hi>Lord</hi>) to be a <hi>Sanctuarie</hi> to <hi>Conscience;</hi> a <hi>Place</hi> of <hi>Refuge</hi> to the <hi>Innocent,</hi> &amp; <hi>Oppressed;</hi> and remember to serue that GOD with a faithfull heart, who so graciously hath set
<pb facs="4"/> you in the seate of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <hi>Father;</hi> and go not onely beyond <hi>Him,</hi> but <hi>Your Selfe</hi> too. And as hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto your <hi>Lordship</hi> hath esteemed of <hi>Siluer,</hi> as of <hi>Tinne;</hi> and contemned the <hi>Wedge</hi> of <hi>Gold,</hi> which so many great Idolaters doe crouch to: so still, in this <hi>Exuberance</hi> of all things, continue con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tant: <hi>Et nudum Christum, nudus sequere. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hieron.</note>
      <hi>Grande, Difficile; sed Magna sunt praemia.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your <hi>Lordships</hi> most bounden, and duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Chaplaine,</hi> William Worship.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>