<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A preface or introduction to the Booke, containing a rea∣son of the Title.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114246_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17053</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3927</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114246</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A preface or introduction to the Booke, containing a rea∣son of the Title.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The life of religion: or Short and sure directions : teaching how to 1 beleeue aright. 2 Liue aright, &amp; 3 pray aright. In the forme of exposition on 1 the Creed. 2 The ten Commandements. 3 The Lords Praier. Put into this kind of method, that it might the better 1. Informe the vnderstanding. 2. Affect the soule, and 3. Helpe the memory. Hereunto is added also a short treatise on the Lords Supper: with praiers to be vsed before, at, and after the communion. By R.B. minister of Gods Word</title>
                 <author>Bruch, Richard, minister of Gods word</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 287, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>A preface or introduction to the Booke, containing a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the Title.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Feare me it may be iustly said of many a one, that now a daies makes profession of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as it is said to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of the Church of <hi>Sardis, Reuel. 3.1. Thou hast a name that thou liuest, and art dead:</hi> For how great soeuer the shew be that they make to the world, yet if they were examined of their faith, it would be so farre, that they should be bespoken with the <hi>Canaanitish woman, Great is your faith. Mat. 15.28.</hi> That we should ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bespeake them as our Sauiour his Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. <hi>Mat. 16. O ye of little faith,</hi> or, <hi>O ye of no faith</hi> rather. If their workes were well seene and considered, we would not commend them for their fruites, but speake to them in the words of the <hi>Baptist, As trees that did not bring forth good fruit. Mat. 3.10.</hi> yea if they would seriously consider with themselues of their key cold praiers, how heauy, leaden, dull, and dead they were in their deuotions, they would euen testifie against themselues, that they had little or no feeling at all in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, that they had little or no life at all of grace in them.</p>
   <p>Of their holy and sound faith, of their god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="3"/> conuersation, of their deuout praiers, are men rightly termed religious, the outward shewes of words, of lookes, of gestures make men no more such, then doth his weed the Frier: He that hath true faith is religious. <hi>The iust by his faith shall liue. Abac. 2.4.</hi> Here then is life. He that walkes in the way of the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in the way of good workes, which God hath ordained that we should walke in them, is religious: These are the waies of life, wherein if we keepe vs, we shall be safe <hi>a ruine mortis,</hi> from the ruine of death: here is also life. <hi>Aliue from the dead saith the Apostle. Rom. 6.13.</hi> and <hi>dead indeed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o sinne, but aliue vnto God through Iesus Christ our Lord,</hi> v. <hi>11.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If the spirit and life of God be in a man, he shall quickely find it in his praiers, he shall thereby quickely find, if he haue any sparke of grace or religion, if he be earnest and feruent in them, if they be full of zeale: It is a sure signe that a mans soule and heart are religious, when hee can powre them out in praier before God. There is the presenting of our bodies <hi>a liuing sacrifice, holy and acceptable vnto God. Rom. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.1.</hi> And there is the presenting of our praiers also a liuing sacrifice, for our soules are in them. Here then also is life.</p>
   <p>True faith, an holy conuersation, and pure deuotion doe constitute a man and absolue him for religious: in each of these there is life, in
<pb facs="4"/> them altogether is the life of religion.</p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1.</hi> The rule of things that are to be beleeued, <hi>Regula credendor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>n,</hi> is the Creed; in this short exposition <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>y perchance be found some. what that may informe a mans vnderstanding in the knovvledge of the mystery of godlines, and to teach him also to make application of his knovvledge to himselfe. This is for faith.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2.</hi> The rule of a mans life are the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demens, of vvhich vve may say in the vvords of the Prophet: <hi>This is the way walke in it.</hi> This small treatise vvill affoord a man some light in the way, and giue him some entrance, to the vnderstanding of the precept, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise of the duties that are required. This is for conuersation.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3.</hi> The rule of a mans praiers, is that praier which the Lord himselfe hath taught vs, som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what for a mans learning to teach him to pray according to this praier, may hee find in this small Booke. This is for deuotion.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3.</hi> The Lord of life giue vnto vs to liue in this World the life of grace, that in the other vve may liue the life of glory: here to liue religiou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sly, that there vve may liue blessedly, through his Sonne our Lord and Sauiour Christ Iesus. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>