<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Reduction of the Lawe and Gospell, Letter and spi∣rit, Shadow and substance vnto Leuiticus, 1. Chapter.</title>
           <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114490_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18923</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5344</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114490</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Reduction of the Lawe and Gospell, Letter and spi∣rit, Shadow and substance vnto Leuiticus, 1. Chapter.</title>
                 <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A manuell of the Bibles doctrine, for law and Gospell, letter and spirit, signe and thing signified : reduced to the first chapter of Leuiticus: Wherewith (occasionally) be plainely considered, and briefelie concluded, the most mayne questions wherewith the christian churches be combred. By H.C</title>
                 <author>Clapham, Henoch</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bradock, Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 259, 5 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb n="1" facs="13"/>
   <head>
      <hi>A</hi> Reduction of the Lawe and Gospell, Letter and spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Shadow and substance vnto Leuiticus, 1. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
   </head>
   <epigraph>
      <q>Heauenly father, which openest to them that knocke, and reuealest my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries of thy kingdome vnto Babes, vouchsafe to remoue all clowds of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance from my min: that so the shine of thy countenaunce comming more clearely vpon me, I may discouer faithfully, the sauing sence of thy word: and this for the sake of Iesus Christ our Sauiour, Amen.</q>
   </epigraph>
   <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND the <note n="a" place="margin">Iehouah.</note>
      <hi>Lorde</hi> cried vnto <hi>Moses</hi> &amp; <note place="margin">Iebrue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ions.</note> spake vnto him, out of the Tabernacle of the Congregation, saying:</p>
   <p n="2">2. Speake to the sons of Is raell, and thou shalt saye vnto them: If any <note n="b" place="margin">Adam.</note>
      <hi>Man</hi> of you shall
<pb n="2" facs="14"/>
offer an <note n="a" place="margin">Korban.</note>
      <hi>oblation</hi> to the <note n="b" place="margin">Iehouah.</note> lord you shall offer your <note n="c" place="margin">Korban.</note>
      <hi>oblation</hi> of cattle <hi>[as]</hi> of the hearde and the flock.</p>
   <p n="3">3. If the <note n="d" place="margin">Gnólah.</note>
      <hi>Burnt offring</hi> be his oblation of the heard, hee shall offer a male thats <note n="e" place="margin">Tamim.</note>
      <hi>perfect,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting it at the dore of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of Conuention; <hi>(euen)</hi> of his owne will shall he offer it, before the face of Iehouah.</p>
   <p n="4">4. And he shall put his hand vpon the head of the Burnt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and it shall be accepted for his attonement.</p>
   <p n="5">5. And he shall kill the <note n="f" place="margin">
         <hi>Hebr.</hi> The son of the Beef.</note> bullock before the face of Iehouah, and the Sons of <hi>Aaron</hi> (the priestes) shall offer the blood, and shall sprinkle the blood vpō the Altar round about, that is by the dore of the Tabernacle of conuētion.</p>
   <p n="6">6. And he shall flay the burnt offring, and shall cut it into his peeces.</p>
   <p n="7">7. And the Sons of <hi>Aaron</hi> the priest, shall put fire on the altar, &amp; lay the wood in order vpō the
<pb n="3" facs="14"/>
fire on the altar.</p>
   <p n="9">9. But the inwards thereof and he legs therof, he shall wash in water, &amp; the priest shall burn all vpon the altar, it being a <note n="a" place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ólah sheh.</note>
      <hi>burnt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ffring,</hi> a <note n="b" place="margin">Reia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>h <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>icoach.</note>
      <hi>sauour of rest</hi> vnto Iehouah.</p>
   <p n="10">10. But if his oblation for the burnt offring bee of the flocke [as of sheepe or of Goates) hee hall offer a male that is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
   <p n="11">11. And he shall kill it at the <note n="c" place="margin">Ièrèk.</note>
      <hi>thigh</hi> of the Altar vpō the north, before the face of Iehouah: and the sons of <hi>Aron</hi> (the priests) shal sprinkle the blood thereof, vpon the altar round about.</p>
   <p n="12">12. And he shall cut it into his peeces: the head and the far, thē the Priest shall lay in order, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wood, that is vpon the fire on the Altar.</p>
   <p n="13">13 As for the inwards &amp; the legs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e shall wash the in water, &amp; the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>iest shall offer the whole, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rne it on the altar, it being an <note n="d" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>nólah ish<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>h.</note> offring made by fire, an odor of rest vnto Iehouah.</p>
   <p n="14">
      <pb n="4" facs="15"/>
14. But if his oblation bee an offring to Iehouah of the fowls, then he shall offer of Turtles or of <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Helr.</hi> The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> of the pigeon.</note>
      <hi>young pigeons.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="15">15. And the priest shall offer it at the Altar, and wring the neck of it asunder, and burne it on the Alter; and the blood thereof shall be squeased vppon the <note n="b" place="margin">Kir.</note>
      <hi>wall</hi> of the altar.</p>
   <p n="16">16. And hee shall plucke out his mawe with <note n="c" place="margin">The fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers about the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>.</note> his feathers, and shall cast it besides the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, on the cast part in the place of the ashes.</p>
   <p n="17">17. And he shall cleaue it with his wings, but not diuide it asun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and the priest shall burne it on the altar, vpon the wood that is on the fire, it beeing a fierie oblation, an odour of Rest vnto Iehouah.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>