<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the godly and well∣affected Reader whosoeuer.</title>
           <author>P., Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114066_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09365</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19669</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114066</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the godly and well∣affected Reader whosoeuer.</title>
                 <author>P., Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The whole treatise of the cases of conscience : distinguished into three bookes: the first whereof is revised and corrected in sundrie places, and the other two annexed. Taught and deliuered by M. W. Perkins in his holy-day lectures, carefully examined by his owne briefes and now published together for the common good, by T. Pickering Bachelour of Diuinitie. Whereunto is adioyned a twofold table: one of the heads and number of the questions propounded and resolued; another of the principall texts of Scripture vvhich are either explaned, or vindicated from corrupt interpretation</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waterson, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40, 199, 8, 436, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>To the godly and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected Reader whosoeuer.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> Doe now at the length offer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy view (Christian Reader) the whole Treatise of Case-divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, so farre as the Author pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in the deliuerie thereof before his death. If thou hast bin longer held in expectation thereof, then either thy selfe desiredst, or was meete, I must intreat thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable interpretation of my forbearance, partly in regard of many priuate distractions, and sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie occurrents wherewith I was detained from this dutie, and partly also in respect of my desire to publish it in such sort to thy contentment, that it might afterward require no further filing or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishing by secondarie Corrections. Wherein, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding mine endeauour to the contrarie, my hope hath beene in part preiudiced, by reason of some faults escaped in the Printing, through want of carefull attendance on the Presse in my necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie absence. The principall I haue noted in a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before the first Booke, and the other of lesser moment, I commend to thy priuate pardon.</p>
   <p>Touching the Treatise it selfe, I haue dealt as faithfully as I could, keeping close to the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers owne wordes, without any materiall addition, detraction, or amplification. His Methode re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines the same in the bodie of the discourse, not admitting the least alteration. Onely it was
<pb facs="9"/>
thought conuenient to distinguish it into Bookes according to the severall distinct parts, the Bookes into Chapters, the Chapters that were most capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of diuision into Sections; and my meaning therein was, to helpe the memorie of the Reader, and to avoid tediousnes the daughter of longsome discourses.</p>
   <p>Now if in the perusing, thou either find a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing amisse, or thy selfe haply not fully satisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in particular; then remember what is the Lot of learned mens workes which are <hi>Scripta post<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huma</hi> (wherof these latter times haue yeelded ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny examples) to be left after a sort, naked and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, when the Authors themselues are gone, who might haue brought them to perfection. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider againe, that in regard of the weight of this worthy Argument, it were much better kindely &amp; thankfully to accept and inioy these labours, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer imparted, then by their suppressing to be wholly depriued of such a benefite. And withall rest with me in hope, that as himselfe hath first <note place="margin">In the Treat. Page. 4.</note> traced the way, and walked by the bankes of this maine Sea, so others vpon this occasion, will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to attempt the like course, or at least to enlarge this worke by addition of more particulars. Meane while, not doubting of thy Christian ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of my paines for thy good, I commend them to thy loue, thy selfe vnto God and the word of his grace. <hi>Eman.</hi> Coll. <hi>Novemb.</hi> 20. 1606.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ Iesus, Tho. P.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>