<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A BREIFE RELATION OF THE LIFE AND DEATH OF THE BLESSED FATHER FR. PETER DE ALCANTARA, FRANCISCAN FRYAR. VVritten by G. VV. of the same Order &amp; obseruance.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114589_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09514</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19794</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114589</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A BREIFE RELATION OF THE LIFE AND DEATH OF THE BLESSED FATHER FR. PETER DE ALCANTARA, FRANCISCAN FRYAR. VVritten by G. VV. of the same Order &amp; obseruance.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A golden treatise of mentall praier : with diuerse spirituall rules and directions, no lesse profitable then necessarie for all sortes of people. First composed by the venerable and blessed father, Fr. Peter de Alcantara, of the Seraphicall Order of S. Francis. Beatified the 18. of Aprill. 1622. Translated into English by G.VV. To vvhich is prefixed a breife relation of the life, and death of the same father vvritten by G.VV. of the same order and obseruance</title>
                 <author>Peter, of Alcantara, Saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Antoine—Velpius, Hubert 1, widow of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Brussels</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>76, 176, 4 pages, plates, portraits, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>A BREIFE RELATION OF THE LIFE AND DEATH OF THE BLESSED FATHER FR. PETER DE ALCANTARA, FRANCISCAN FRYAR. <hi>VVritten by G. VV. of the same Order &amp; obseruance.</hi>
   </head>
   <head type="sub">THE PROLOGVE.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Isericordias Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini in aeternum cantabo.</hi>
      <note n="(a)" place="margin">
         <hi>Psalm.</hi> 88.</note> I will singe the mercies of our Lord for euer, saith that Kingly Prophet <hi>DAVID:</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>And not without cause: for so great and vnspeakable, are the mercie-workes of the almightie, which out of the bowells of his infinite goodnes, he hath shewed to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde from the first instant of his creation, that the toungues of men and Angells are neuer able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse them.</p>
   <p>How wonderfull was this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit; that creatinge man after his owne<note n="(b)" place="margin">
         <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26.</note> image and likenes,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Magister sent. lib. <hi>2.</hi> dist. <hi>20.</hi>
      </note> he would haue made him partaker of eternall felicitie, and vested with his originall iustice, vvithout<note n="(d)" place="margin">Gabriel. lib. <hi>2.</hi> dist. <hi>19.</hi> quaest. vnica, art. <hi>2.</hi>
      </note> death or any passage by misery would haue associated him with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of Angells, if he had not, by his ovvne default, violated the lawes of his creatour? notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standinge this act of malice, the
<pb facs="6"/>diuine clemencie would not suffer the worke of his powerfull handes, so to perish: but he accordinge to the diuersitie of times,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Scotus lib. <hi>4.</hi> dist. <hi>1.</hi> qu. <hi>7.</hi> n <hi>2.</hi>
      </note> alwaies ordeined opportune remedies, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce wanderinge man to the right way of his owne saluation. Nowe manifestinge his diuine pleasure by the meanes of Angels: nowe sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge the Patriarchs replenished with his heauenly grace, who by their good example, might stirr them vp to pietie: then sendinge the Prophets illuminated with his holy spirit, not only to preach the present benefits exhibited to mankinde, but also to foretell the future incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sonne of God, with the mysterie of his death and passion, by meanes of which man should be loosed from the power of Sathan,
<pb facs="7"/>and eased of the heauy loade of his transgressions.</p>
   <p>Thus farr hath that impene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trable abysse of the diuine clemencie, sweetly disposed all thinges, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site for the sauinge of the soule of man. But if we will extend our thoughtes a little further, and call to mind the great benefits, still heaped vpon man, after the ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of our blessed Sauiour, we shall finde them innumerable. VVho is not astonished at the vocation of mankinde, that the Apostolicall trumpet of a fewe men, soundinge to humane eares, the Euangelicall truth, through the wholl world, should rouze vp<note n="(f)" place="margin">(Religiosi) Ecclesiae pars selectior, &amp; sapientior; si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quidem ij sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientiores ha lē li sunt, qùā reliquū mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talium vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus, qui seip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sos à mundi cōsortio segre garunt, vt v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tā suam Deo consecràrunt Nazianz ora in laudē Basi lij</note> soules makinge thē<note n="*" place="margin">Beati illi certè, ac ter beati, vt qui Dei amore fia gràrunt, at{que} ob eius amorē omnia pro ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilo duxerūt, siquidē lacr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas profudè<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt die{que} ac nocte in luctu versati sunt, vt aeternam consolationem adip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>scerētur: carues su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> fame &amp; siti, &amp; vigilijs confe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>erūt, vt illic paradisi diliciae, &amp; gaudia ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s ex iperent. Damascen. in hist. B. Iosa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t.</note> happy &amp; thrice happy to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake all worldly vanities? to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take themselues to a state of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection;
<pb facs="7"/>to sell all they haue and giue to the poore: to liue in perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall chastitie, and simple obedience: to spend their dayes in rigorous pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, watchinge, fastinge and prayer, and finally to renounce all the seeminge pleasures (for<note n="(g)" place="margin">Consolati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> mūdi vilis, &amp; ad nibilū vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, &amp; quod magis metuē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum est, verae &amp; salubris consolationis impedimentū. D Ber. in ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vir. Natiu sic se habēt vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersa sub so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, vt nihil sic in eis verè iucundū, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis siquidem laboris reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium, alterius laboris initi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>̄ est. Idem in se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m de pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mordijs &amp; medijs nouiss. Vide plura apud Hieron. Platū de bono staet. relig. l. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
      </note> true there are none) which the flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe world could afford vnto thē.</p>
   <p>These thinges are dayly putt in practice by many, who professe the gospell of <hi>Christ.</hi> For where Catholique Religion flourisheth, we see diuerse Monasteries of men and women, filled with reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious soules, who consecrate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues a perpetuall sacrifice to the almightie.</p>
   <p>How many religious doe vve see honoured vvith Preistly fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, (an office requiringe more
<pb facs="8"/>then humane<note n="(h)" place="margin">Quo non oportet esse p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>riorem tali fruentē sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio? quo sola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri radio non splendidiorem manū carnem hanc diuiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem? os quod igni spiritali repletur, lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guā quae tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendo nimis sanguine ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bescit. Sic D▪ Chrys. hom. <hi>83.</hi> in Mat. <hi>And Pope Gelasius vvritinge to Elpidius Bishop, doth excellently set dovvne the great purity required to Preistly function sayinge:</hi> Sacrosancta Religio quae Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam continet disciplinam, tantam sibi reuerentiam vendicat, vt ad eam quilibet nisi pura conscientia, non aude at peruenire: nam quomodo ad diuini mysterij consecrationem caelestis spiritus inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catus adueniat, si sacerdos &amp; qui eam adesse de precetur crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nosis plenus actionibus reprobetur? <hi>1.</hi> q. <hi>1</hi> c. SACROSANCTA. <hi>Although a vvicked Preist doth consecrate and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster the Sacramentes truely, yet he sinneth greiuiously in cōsecratinge, &amp; administratinge vnvvorthily,</hi> Sacrificia im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piorum eis ipsi soberunt qui offerunt impiè. <hi>1.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> c. PER ISAIAM. necesse est, vt esse munda studeaet manus, quae diluere sordes c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat: ne tacta quaeque deteriùs inquinet, si sordida ipsa stercoris lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum tenet. Greg. inregefto. l. <hi>1.</hi> Epist. <hi>24.</hi> &amp; ponitur <hi>1.</hi> qu <hi>1</hi> cap. NECESSE EST.</note> puritie and a burthen scarcely to be supported by Angels shoulders) executinge their charge vvith great integretie of minde, carefull of their ovvne, and zealous of the sauinge of their neighbours soules, vvho by their holy doctrine and exemplare liues, preach to the Christian vvorld a reformation: vvho spare noe paines or tedious trauells, to propagate the
<pb facs="8"/>faith of <hi>IESVS CHRIST,</hi> to heathens and infidells; vvho coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giously labour in God almighties vineyard, exposinge their liues for the name of <hi>IESVS. Indies</hi> both east and vvest are vvitnesses of their zealous and heroick spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, there they sealed the truth of the gospell vvith the effusion of their sacred blood. Yea vvhat actes memorable in the church of God are there, vvherin<note n="(i)" place="margin">Hieron. Platus de be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no status re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>30.</hi>
      </note> these men haue not had a very greate stroke. And finally they so well employ, and multiply those talentes, vvhich the great commaunder of heauen and earth, hath bestovved vpon them here, that assuredly they may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect an eternall revvard in the Kingedome of heauen hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="9"/>
But that which is more admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, to see a multitude of the weaker sexe, to abandon all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleasures: they who in the world might haue swoome in brauery, and haue bad all thinges at their owne commaund; to inclose themselues in a retired Cloister, there to spend their dayes in penance, and to consecrate the very flower of their springinge youth, a sweet smellinge sacrifice to their celestiall spouse <hi>CHRIST IESVS.</hi> These truly are those that<note n="(k)" place="margin">Nuptiae replēt terr a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> virginitas parad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sum. D. Hieron.</note> fill and beautifie the garden of paradise with lillies of puritie: these are the<note n="(l)" place="margin">Flos est il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le Ecclesiastici germinis, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus atque or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namentū gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae spiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, laeta, indo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, laudis &amp; honoris, opus integrum at{que} incorruptum Dei imago re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spondens, ad sanctimoniam Dn̄i, illustrior portio gregis Christi, gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det per ipsas, atque in illis largiter floret S. Matris Ec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clesiae gloriosa faecunditas, quanto{que} plus gloriosa Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginitas nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero suo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, tanto plus gaudium ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris augescit. Cypr de babit. virg. l <hi>4</hi> c. <hi>24</hi>
      </note> flowers of our holy mother the Catholique Church, which make her glorious and fruitfull. These are they, that make that happie chaunge, amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments fadinge pleasure, for an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall
<pb facs="9"/>crowne of glorie.</p>
   <p>Thus we see perpetuall riuers streaminge from the fountaine of God almighties mercie. But let vs descend a little further into his aboundant charitie, and take notice of his fatherly prouidence, that in process of declininge times, when the blood of our redeemer, hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes begun to wax cold in the hearts of men, he would not suffer it altogether to be extinguished, but accordinge to varietie of times, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ceased to repaire his church by the ministery of some elected seruāts, whom he sent into this world as se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Apostles, who by their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and doctrine might drawe men out of the mire of their sinnes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newe the feruour of our blessed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours passion, and reduce collapsed
<pb facs="10"/>discipline to her former rigour. Many hath he sent for this end, and amongst many this blessed Saint, <hi>S. PETER DE ALCAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TARA,</hi> a man from his very cradle consecrated to Euangelicall perfection; he was a faithfull labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer in our Lords vineyard, with great fidelitie performinge his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded taske, as it will plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by that which followeth in his life.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>