<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ Here after foloweth the prologue of the foure last thynges.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1496</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114682_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19336</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5759</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114682</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ Here after foloweth the prologue of the foure last thynges.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Here after foloweth the prologue of the foure last thynges</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Worde, Wynkyn de</publisher>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1496</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>3, lxxxviii, 1 leave, 4⁸</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb n="i" facs="4"/>
   <head>¶ Here after foloweth the prologue of the foure last thynges.</head>
   <p>MEmora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re nouis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sima et meternū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>non pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabis Ec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clesiastici septimo capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulo. Ecclesiasticus sayth in his seuenth Capitre these wordes folowynge Bere well in thy mynde the last thynges / &amp; thou shalt neuer falle in syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. Also Saynte Austyn sayth in his book of me dytacyons. That man ought rather haue in fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re and eschewe the abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynacōn &amp; fylthe of syn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne / than ony other cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees of the Infernall tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. Loo thenne how y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> knowlege of these four last thynges and frequen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng the memorye &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraūce of them cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vs from synne / and draweth vs to vertue / &amp; conformeth vs to all go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de werkes. Wherfore by the helpe of the dyuyne Inspyracyon I haue pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>posed to reherse and saye a lytyll of these four tyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges. As whiche they be / and what they be / and also to declare somwhat of euery of them syngu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerly by them selfe / precy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ously &amp; dygnely by sayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges &amp; auctorytees of sayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes / and generally by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples and saynges of auctorysed clerkes. It is to be noted that after the sayeng of saynces men sayt comynly. ther be fou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re the last thynges. And whiche they be it appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth clerely by the wordes of Saynt Bernard in a sermon where he sayth
<pb facs="5"/>
in all thy werkes haue re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membraunce of thy laste thynges / whiche be four. That is to wyte fyrste. Bodely dethe. Seconde. The daye of Iugement▪ Thyrde. The paynes of helle. Fourth. The glorie of heuen. O what thyng is more horrible than de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the. What thyng is more dredefull &amp; terryble than y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> day of Iugement. what thyng is more Importa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be suffred than the gehēne &amp; paynes of helle And what is a more Ioye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full blysse than celestyall glorye. Saynt Bernard sayd in the same sermon These ben the four whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les of the chare / wherof the Remembraunce bryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth mānes soule to the euerlastyng glorye of pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>radyse. These ben also iiii. moeuynges y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> awake the spiryte of man to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de that he disprayse alle worldly thynges &amp; retor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vnto his creatour &amp; maker. Lo it is then both cōuenyent &amp; proufytable y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they be had contynuelly in remembraūce. &amp; therfo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re sayth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wyse man in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> xxviii. chapitre of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastic{us}. Bere in thy myn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> last &amp; fynall thyng is &amp; loke alway perfyghtly vpon them to thentent y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they may be surely fixed &amp; printed in thy memorie Now syn all this processe princypally &amp; soueraynly enforseth hymselfe tendu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce euery crature to haue an assured mynde &amp; an ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le remembraūce of these iiii. last thynges / &amp; y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they may cordyally be enpryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted with in your hertes. Therfor it is consonant &amp; accordyng yf it so may please. y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> this present trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyse may be entytled and
<pb n="ii" facs="5"/>
bere the name of the Cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyall.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>