<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶A prayer for all Kings, Princes, Countreyes and people, which doe professe the Gospel: And especially for our soueraigne Lady Queene Elizabeth, vsed in her Maie∣sties Chappell, and meete to bee vsed of all persons within her Maiesties Dominions.</title>
           <author>Cotton, Roger</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114046_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09049</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19342</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114046</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶A prayer for all Kings, Princes, Countreyes and people, which doe professe the Gospel: And especially for our soueraigne Lady Queene Elizabeth, vsed in her Maie∣sties Chappell, and meete to bee vsed of all persons within her Maiesties Dominions.</title>
                 <author>Cotton, Roger</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A trve and plaine declaration of the horrible treasons, practised by William Parry the traitor, against the Queenes Maiestie. The maner of his arraignment, conuiction and execution, together with the copies of sundry letters of his and others, tending to diuers purposes, for the proofes of his treasons. Also an addition not impertinent thereunto, containing a short collection of his birth, education and course of life. Moreouer, a fewe obseruations gathered of his owne wordes and wrytings, for the farther manifestation of his most disloyal, deuilish and desperate purpose.</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 <publisher>Barker, Christopher.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>[2], 53, [1], 7, [1] p. ;  4⁰</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prayers</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>No match</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prayer">
   <pb facs="29"/>
   <pb n="1" facs="29"/>
   <head>¶A prayer for all Kings, Princes, Countreyes and people, which doe professe the Gospel: And especially for our soueraigne Lady Queene Elizabeth, vsed in her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Chappell, and meete to bee vsed of all persons within her Maiesties Dominions.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God of hostes, most louing and mercifull fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whose power no cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature is able to resist, who of thy great goodnesse hast promised to graunt the petitions of such as aske in thy sonnes name: we most humbly beseech thee to saue and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend all Princes, Magistrates, kingdomes, countreyes &amp; people, which haue receiued and doe professe thy holy word and Gospel, and namely this Realme of Englande, and thy seruant Elizabeth our Queene, whome thou hast hitherto wonderfully preserued from manifolde perils and sundry dangers, and of late reuealed and frustrated the trayterous
<pb n="2" facs="30"/>
practises and conspiracies of diuers against her: for the which, and all other thy great goodnesse towardes vs, wee giue thee most humble and heartie thankes, beseeching thee in the name of thy deare sonne Iesus Christ, and for his sake, still to preserue and continue her vnto vs, and to giue her long life &amp; many yeeres to rule ouer this lande. O heauenly father, the practises of our enemies, and the enemies of thy worde and trueth, against her and vs, are manifest and knowen vnto thee. Turne them, O Lord, if it be thy blessed will, or ouerthrowe and confounde them for thy names sake: suffer them not to preuaile: take them, O Lord, in their craftie wilinesse that they haue inuented, and let them fall into the pit which they haue digged for others. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte them not vngodly to triumph ouer vs: discomfort them, discomfort them, O Lorde, which trust in their owne multitude, and please themselues in their subtill deuices, and wicked conspiracies. O louing Father, wee haue not deserued the least of these thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies which we craue: for we haue sinned and grieuously offended thee, we are not worthy to bee called thy sonnes: we haue not bene so thankefull vnto thee as we shoulde, for thy vnspeakeable benefits powred vpon vs: we haue abused this long time of peace and pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie: we haue not obeyed thy worde: we haue had it in mouth, but not in heart: in
<pb n="3" facs="30"/>
outward appearance, but not in deede: wee haue liued carelessely: Wee haue not knowen the time of our visitation: we haue deserued vtter destruction. But thou, O Lorde, art mercifull, and ready to forgiue. Therefore wee come to thy throne of grace, confessing and acknowledging thee to be our onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge in all times of perill and daunger: and by the meanes of thy Sonne wee most hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily pray thee to forgiue vs our vnthankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, disobedience, hypocrisie &amp; all other our sinnes, to turne from vs thy heauie wrath and displeasure, which wee haue iustly deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and to turne our hearts truely vnto thee, that dayly we may encrease in all goodnesse, and continually more and more feare thy holy name: so shall we glorifie thy name, and sing vnto thee in Psalmes and Hymnes, and spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall songs: and thy enemies and ours, shall knowe themselues to be but men, and not able by any meanes to withstande thee, nor to hurt those whome thou hast receiued into thy protection and defence. Graunt these thinges, O Lorde of power, and Father of mercy, for thy Christes sake, to whome with thee and thy holy spirite, bee all honour and glory for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>