<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           <author>D., N.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114221_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09112</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19418</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114221</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 <author>D., N.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvarn-vvord to Sir Francis Hastinges wast-word : conteyning the issue of three former treateses, the Watch-word, the Ward-word and the Wast-word (intituled by Sir Francis, an Apologie or defence of his Watch-word) togeather with certaine admonitions &amp; warnings to thesaid [sic] knight and his followers. Wherunto is adioyned a breif reiection of an insolent, and vaunting minister masked with the letters O.E. who hath taken vpon him to wryte of thesame [sic] argument in supply of the knight. There go also foure seueral tables, one of the chapters, another of the controuersies, the third of the cheif shiftes, and deceits, the fourth of the parricular [sic] matters conteyned in the whole book. By N.D. author of the Ward-word</title>
                 <author>Parsons, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Conincx, Arnout</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 131, that is 133, 138, 11 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> HOLD</hi> not for needful (good Christian Reader) to make any, large presace for thy instruction in that which is to ensue in this book the controuersy beeing suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently knowen by that which hitherto hath byn written and printed therof. The summe of all is this.</p>
   <p>There happened some <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ew yeares past (as often also before) a certayne false all-arme of a Spanish inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,<note place="margin">
         <hi>An. 1598.</hi>
      </note> then said to be vpon the Seas towards England, vpon the rumour wherof, one knight more hasty then the rest (for that he was of the <hi>Hastings</hi>) stept forth,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Syr F. Has<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings.</hi>
      </note> and offered not only a <hi>swift foot to the field</hi> (for so are his words) but a much swifter tongue to accuse, and bring in question all Catholike men within the realme, himself being knowne to be of the Puritan crew.</p>
   <p>And to performe this with more probability of iust occasion he made himself (without commission) a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral VVatch-man ouer all the land, and wrote a most bitter and bloudy pamphlet against thesaid Catholiks,
<pb facs="3"/>
vnder the title of a <hi>Watch-word</hi> replenished with all kynd of slaunders and most odious calumniations,<note place="margin">
         <hi>The VVatch-vvord.</hi>
      </note> which being ioyned with the iealousy of the tyme, &amp; the disgrace wherin the said Catholiks were before for confession of their religion, was very likely to haue brought them to some general ruine, and consequently this knight also to some desired diuident of their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings.</p>
   <p>VVherfore this intemperate inuectiue comming to the hands of a certaine Catholike man that took com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion of their oppression, and some disdayne at the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious deuise of this watch-man, he thought good to write a temperate <hi>Ward-word</hi> to this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>urbulent watch-word,<note place="margin">
         <hi>The VVard-vvord.</hi>
      </note> drawing all that the other had vttered in many wyld &amp; wast words into 8. seueral Encounters, intituling his book a <hi>Ward-word</hi>; which being published it seemed to touch the matter so to the quick as the first newes after the publication therof was in most mennes mouthes, that the knight disauowed the watch-word, attributing thesame rather to certayne ministers of his communion, that eyther wrote the same or induced him therunto, then to himself, &amp; most men commended the discretion and modesty of the knight in so doing.</p>
   <p>But as men are not alwayes constant in the best; so Sir <hi>F.</hi> making a new consultation with his presbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery at <hi>Cadbury,</hi> took another resolution to reply againe vnder the name of <hi>An Apologie,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>The nevv re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of Sir F.</hi>
      </note> &amp; heerby the matter hath growne to a larger discussion then was expected, for that the book (after long expectation of more then two yeares) comming to my hands, I was drawne to enlarge my self much more in this my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynder,
<pb facs="3"/>
then at the beginning I purposed: in so much as hauing ended the whole answere, with in few mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethes af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er the receit of the book, it grew to such a bulk, as conueniently it could not be set forth in one volume; and this was one cause of some delay &amp; longer deliberation.</p>
   <p>But another more principal was, an aduise written vnto me,<note place="margin">
         <hi>O. E. his book.</hi>
      </note> that one O. E. a minister had published ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther volume of thesame argument in supply of the knights defence, much more intemperate &amp; malignāt, then the other; which being vnderstood, it seemed ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to expect thesame before the publishing of the former, which hath caused much longer delay then was wished or meant, especially some other impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments also cōcurring therewith, wherof most men can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ignorant.</p>
   <p>Now then these being the causes of the enlargemēt both of tyme and matter, it seemeth I should tel yow also of the reasons, why these two first Encounters are set forth a part from the rest; but this is sufficiently declared by a certaine addition in the end of this book set downe by the publisher therof, wherunto I remit the reader, only I am to aduertise him to consider how easily words do beget words, and how a few lauish speeches spoken at rādome by the knight in his watch-word haue giuen an occasion to the handling of aboue fifty controuersies in these first two Encounters only; and then may yow imagine how much more the rest may amount vnto.</p>
   <p>And one principal reason of this encrease &amp; growth is,<note place="margin">
         <hi>The causes of enlarging this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tese.</hi>
      </note> for that our aduersaries do handle matters of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion so confusedly, and with so litle order, sincerety or
<pb facs="4"/>
truthe, that we must eyther shuffle ouer things as they do, scarce vnderstood eyther by themsel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es or others, or els we must be forced for drawing them into s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>me method and perspicuity to spend much tyme &amp; labour, to explicate, and distinguish thesame, and to yeild to eache thing his true ground, reason and probation; which point, for that I had rather the reader should learne by proof and experience of the things themsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues here to be handled, then by my spech, I wil proceed no further; but remit my self to the insuing treateses, beseeching almighty God that all this may redound to his glory and to their good for whose spiritual benefit I haue most willingly taken this smalle playnes.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your harty freend that wisheth your greatest good. <hi>N. D.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>