<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>BY THE KING.</title>
           <author>Denison, Stephen</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114429_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15350</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25634</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114429</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>BY THE KING.</title>
                 <author>Denison, Stephen</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A second memento for magistrates : Directing how to reduce all offenders, and beeing reduced, how to preserue them in vnitie and loue both in Church and common wealth. By W.W. Doctor of Diuinity, and one of his Maiesties chaplains in ordinary</title>
                 <author>Wilkes, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jackson, Roger</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 73, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="royal_notice">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>BY THE KING.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He care which we haue had, and paines which we haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to settle the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of this church of England in an vniformitie as wel of doctrine, as of gouernment, both of thē agreeable to the word of God, the doctrine of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue church, and the lawes heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore established for those matters in this realme may sufficiently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by our former actions, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>In the meane time, both they may resolue either to conforme themselues to the church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and obey the same; or else to dispose of themselues and their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies some other waies, as to them
<pb facs="5"/> shall seeme meet. And the Bishops and others whom it concerneth, prouide meete parsons to be sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutes in the place of those who shall wilfullie abandon their char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges vpon so light causes. Assuring them that after that day, we shall not faile to do that which Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prouidence requireth at our hands. That is to put in execution all wayes and meanes, that may take from among our people all grounds and occasions of Sects, deuisions, and vnquietnesse, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as we wish there may neuer be occasion giuen vs to make proofe, but that this our admonition may haue equall force in all mens hearts to worke an vniuersall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie. So we doe require all Arch-bishopps, Byshopps, and
<pb facs="5"/> other Ecclesiasticall parsons, to do their vttermost endeauours by conferences, arguments, perswati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and by all other wayes of loue and gentlenesse, to reclaime all that be in the Ministrie, to the obedience of our Church lawes.</p>
   <p>For which purpose onely, we haue enlarged the time former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prefixed for their remoue, or reformation, to the end, that if it bee possible, that vniformitie which we desire, may be wrought by clemencie, and by weight of reason, and not by rigour of lawe.</p>
   <p>And the like aduertizement we doe giue to all ciuill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates, Gentlemen, and others of vnderstanding, as well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in the counties as in Citties
<pb facs="6"/> and Townes, requiring them also not in any sort to support, fauour, or countenance any such factious Ministers in their obstinacy. Of whose indeauours we doubt not but so good successe may follow as this our Admonition with their indeauours may preuent the vse of any other meanes to retaine our people in their due <hi>obedience</hi> to vs, and in <hi>vnitie</hi> of minde to the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of Almightie God.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Giuen at our Mannor of Ottlands</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>the</hi> 16. <hi>day of Iuly</hi> 1604. <hi>in the second yeare of our raigne of England, France and Ireland, And of Scotland the xxxvii.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <hi>God saue the King.</hi>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>