<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the indifferent and intelligent Reader.</title>
           <author>Cl, He.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114490_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18923</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5344</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114490</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the indifferent and intelligent Reader.</title>
                 <author>Cl, He.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A manuell of the Bibles doctrine, for law and Gospell, letter and spirit, signe and thing signified : reduced to the first chapter of Leuiticus: Wherewith (occasionally) be plainely considered, and briefelie concluded, the most mayne questions wherewith the christian churches be combred. By H.C</title>
                 <author>Clapham, Henoch</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bradock, Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 259, 5 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the indifferent and intelligent Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot knowing (and that not-knowing a greuous tētatiō) whether God shall giue me to cōtinue, or necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risy to <hi>Conuert</hi> my studies another waie (for vnder this or that colour, wee are not as Drones to eate not laboring, as the manner of some howse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creepers is) &amp; setting before mine eies, what may for the present he best fitted to the churchesgood: without al res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of persons I hādled th'in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing argument <hi>Of sacrifices</hi> and finally concluded, <hi>for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moouing</hi> som scandalous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour <note place="margin">A reason of this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle.</note> towards me (for these
<pb facs="3"/>
nine years at least) to preface my saide booke, with an Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of such nature, as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. <hi>Et sic ab origine pandā.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Aboute some 9. y. since, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siding then at Amsterdam in Nether-land, in an Epistle, prefixed to my Treatise of the <hi>Sin against the Ho. Ghost.</hi> I (for the effect) concluded as followeth,</p>
   <p n="1">1. First that certaine heere <note place="margin">This cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. were more then now would be knowne: for som are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for meer aduantage: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> in co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ners, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ey be mar tins disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, still.</note> at home, labouring for Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in an ouercariage of wordes (as <hi>such and such per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sōs, ordinations &amp; adminis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trations &amp;c were Antichris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, badges of the beast, &amp;c)</hi> they thereby ministred occasiō of <hi>Separatiō</hi> from our Church: as <hi>Brown</hi> is said at first to do, &amp; many soules since least otherwise (as they say) <hi>they shoulde drinke of
<pb facs="4"/>
the pure wine of Gods wrath.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="2">2. Secondly I there auer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that such Separists mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred occasiō of further inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. As, if the Church, mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>strie and sacraments, left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind in the English church be Antichristian, then how is it possble that <hi>Them-selues</hi> so separated should either be pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed of true <hi>faith,</hi> or true <hi>baptisme:</hi> seeing Antichrist teacheth, leadeth and sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth to himselfe and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill his parent, &amp; not to christ For say they, <hi>out of a bitter fountaine can issue no sweet water: &amp; as the root is, such be the branches.</hi> Whereupon insued that some such sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rists did forthwith <hi>willingly</hi> and <hi>freely</hi> root vp their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer faith touching Christ, as
<pb facs="4"/>
also, puffe of the former Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme: one first baptising him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, and then hee baptising o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (as <hi>Abraham</hi> first cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcised himselfe and then others) so sinning I feare the fearefull sin against the Holy Ghost. Only, one thing may be a lette to their committing of that sin, if so happily, the spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall <hi>sight</hi> and <hi>sense</hi> supposed to haue been in them, were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer indeed, so deepely setled in them.</p>
   <p>That Epistle comming ouer to London, ô vvhat a storme the Diuell there raised for smiting the corners of silly <hi>Iobs</hi> house? And my selfe comming ouer about a yeare after, how did a sort of supposed refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists flie vpon my credit cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in my Bookes and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, as the Shabeans and
<pb facs="5"/>
Chaldeans ceazed on Iobes substance, charging diuers their disciples, to fly all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sultation with Clapham or his writings, euē as they shold flie poison. The case so stan ding, I sent them word by some of their hearers, that if they would denie, they had defined of Antichristianity as I had charged them afore; or that granting they had so taughte, they would yet denie that se paration frō our Church cold necessarily be inferred there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from; that then I would be rea die to cleare the one and the other, either by word or wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge, as they shoulde thinke beste. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>d surdis auribus,</hi> what they had done, they had done: &amp; I was not a man to bee talked withall. And so
<pb facs="5"/>
forwards they went in theire euill, &amp; by coloured craftines drew many simple harted peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple after them, in a blind kind of schisme. And this not only within the Citty, but also a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad they practised, to the abusing of many. Had they had the power of our Bishops, doubtlesse they would haue im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisoned me, and had they had the power of our Prince, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all question, they would, haue slaine mee. They can speake against the power they haue not, but had they that they would, it would be greater then that which others with vs haue, euen a power for trampeling Kinges, crownes and scepters vnder theire feet, little or nothing differing
<pb facs="6"/>
from Papall supremacy. Hee that knowes not that, is very sillily acquainted with the too true stories of our times, and the positiue doctrines of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall leaders in that kind. But to proceed.</p>
   <p>VVhile thus they labored to make men hate mee and my labors, I toiled in my ministry, wheresoeuer the dore of vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance was opened vnto me, and God mercifully gaue vnto me the holy likengs of many. Yea, some of these, that had beene charged not to heare me, did (God beeing mercifull vnto them) repaire to my Sermons, concluding vvith themselues to vvalke by the Apostles rule, namely, to <hi>try all things, and then keepe that is good.</hi> In fine, they perceaued how they had beene <hi>hood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winked,</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
and bursting out of <note place="margin">Som yet in the ministry as Fa'coners do lead the people hood winked they know not whither: looking for their day, as the Papistes for theyr day: hauing one speeche in publique &amp; another <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> priuate.</note> the snare vvherewith they had been tangled, they came vnto mee readily, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed theyr faulte hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.</p>
   <p>The worke so proceedinge on both sides, let me by the way tell the gentle reader, how a welwiller of mine, dealte with a foe of mine, for causing him against the purpose of his heart, to iustify mee and my labours. And thus it was. My <hi>Tables of houshold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> Gouernement,</hi> beeing here newly come foorth, a <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>urgian</hi>
      <note place="margin">A prety iest, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>o the shame of partiall spi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ts.</note> (my friend) getteth them, and vppon my name, hee procureth the name of a certaine Preacher to be clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye pasted, to whome many glued themselues, as if <hi>the faith should bee held in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect
<pb facs="7"/>
of persons.</hi> These Tables, my friend brought to a certaine Sectarie, desiring his iudgemente vppon these Tables. The Sectary espying the Preachers name belowe, doth take them (for had hee seene my name, hee woulde not haue looked vpon them) and then he falls on reading Anon, he burstes out into such patheticall speeches: <hi>Ey marry sir, this is indeede to the purpose: O hee is a rare man &amp;c:</hi> My friend ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing gotte what he expected, did thereuppon pull the pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted name off, and pointed him to the Authour thereof, <hi>Henoch Clapham.</hi> The Sec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie seeing that, O how blank hee was, hee stoode as one looking on <hi>Medusaes</hi> head,
<pb facs="7"/>
and so my friende left him. Apiteous thing, that hearers shall affect <hi>men</hi> rather then <hi>matter,</hi> praising and dispray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing they know not what. But had they beene taught bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then would they (happilie) haue learned better.</p>
   <p>For an ordinarye thing it is, with that people and the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paristes to proclayme all Dunses, No-scholers, &amp;c: that differ from them; but beeing one with them, then they bee verye learned, and what not? But againe to my fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>mer discourse.</p>
   <p>Some few scholers aboute the Cittie, hauing so proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med mee an aduersarye to theyr laicail discipline (not onelye to the banding of Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens against mee, but also
<pb facs="8"/>
of others in the Country) haue they not since been opposite to themselues? Then mark: They being of the nōber that petitio nated to the King for Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation (not to speake of some then reconciled to the Bishops, at least outwardly) I beseech you, what doe they speak of their <hi>Lay-Elders</hi> (for wee all grant Elders) what speake they of their <hi>Lay-deacōs</hi> for wee all graunt Deacons) what say they of their <hi>Lay disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline</hi> (for we all graunt disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline) what say they to the King of these matters, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they had intoxicate the heads and harts of their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers? They speak not a word, not so much as <hi>God saue it.</hi> They onely couet some other <hi>by-things,</hi> and then all is well inough, the former Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christianitie
<pb facs="8"/>
shall be all true (or at least, tollerable) chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity.</p>
   <p>But methinks I heare some say, that howbeit they desired not of the King an intertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the former discipline: yet they neuer the lessewer of the same opinion still, but propounded it not, for that the King seemed aduerse vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it. I answere, it is vntrue, for many of them had chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged their opinion. In somuch as amongst them the case so stood: some few did faintly hold <note place="margin">Three son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Sects vnder one Gener<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ll head of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</note> that the gouerning Elders (as afore) were but lay-people, in owe in office and anone out, as bee church-wardens and Syde-men. <hi>Some</hi> other again did rather belieue, that all church-elders and presbiters oughte to bee <hi>apte to teache
<pb facs="9"/>
and so to continue assistante<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> to the pastor. A thirde sorte with</hi> Maister. I. B. held and still holde, <hi>that the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of the Churche by Bishoppes (as with vs in England) or by ruling Elders (as in other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of God) that neither of them was prescribed by the Apostles of Christe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them repugn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>nte to the worde of God; but maye well and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablie be vsed, if more fault be not in their persons, then in the callinges them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Being so diuided into three heade of opinion, touching the very <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi> that shoulde exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise discipline, they coulde
<pb facs="9"/>
not in one petitiō beg al three nor coulde the king graunte moe then one, and therefore no one sort propounded. But if the diuision be so manifold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the very persons that should gouerne the Churche, I beseech you, what aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of difference would bee found amongst them touching the matter of d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>scipline it self, in such and such cases for pro ceeding? these that haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersed with the Separistes and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e proceedinges, can beste declare that theire head-lesse petition beeinge gaine saide, and so theire affections stirred vp, <hi>One</hi> saith, hee sees not, But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>he Brownist did well so to separate, as I spoke before.
<pb facs="10"/>
some others againe say, they do not see, that it is good to separate so, that is, to departe as from a false church: but to separate as from a Churche neere wounded to death and very infectious, they thinke it good and hye-time so to do, as some before them did, whome I willinglie leaue namelesse. <hi>A thirde sorte</hi> acknowledge, that they see not either of the saide Separations to be good, and therefore will await he Lordes pleasure, mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the very middest of Zion. There bee so three heades, one sounding a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate,</hi> the other <hi>Tara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> tara</hi> to the battaile: and of these two to the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile, the one side proclaiming an absolute defiance, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst a false Church, wherein
<pb facs="10"/>
not any one is a true visible Christian; the other houlding that proclamation to be false: saying, howsoeuer it is not good to come nere vnto <hi>Iob,</hi> being so vlcer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>us, yet a liuing soule he is, and may be so restored, as in time we may draw neerer vnto him, meaning the church. So, amongst them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues they bee diuided. And <hi>if the trumpet</hi> (saith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle) <hi>do giue an vncertaine sounde, who shall prepare himselfe vnto the battaile?</hi> No body. Martin. mar must first better direct his people: For moste absurde it were, to march after a Champion eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse &amp; handlesse. If the blind leade the blinde, both must <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>umble into the ditche: that is, into the state of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="11"/>
Gentle Reader, consider of it soberly, and the Lorde giue thee vnderstanding in al things. Looke how I taxed them at first, they haue made it good at the last. But how many of them haue the grace to laie downe their enmitie towards me, to confesse their euill, and accordingly to make satisfaction? well, if I haue spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken euill, beare witnesse of the euill, but if it bee but trueth, why still doe they smite mee? The trueth is greate and will conquer, and better for them to be subdued <hi>vnto</hi> it, then subdued <hi>of</hi> it. As for their followers, let them beware they followe them not in euill, howsoeuer it be their duety to reuerence their good. Be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of all, as they be follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Christ, but not fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="11"/>
That many thinges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst vs neede amendment, who knowes not, and what honest hearte lamentes not? And that it is the duetye of euery soule, so farre as cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and meanes extende, to labour such amendemente, euerye discreet person graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.</p>
   <p>But if the lawes of our Land bee truely considered, euills bee rather <hi>Personall,</hi> then <hi>Legall,</hi> and the abuse in persons, must not condemne the lawfull vse of things.</p>
   <p>Let vs striue in mutuall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations daielie, while it is called to day, but (as the Apostle commaundeth) <hi>Let all our thinges bee done in loue:</hi> for without <hi>loue,</hi> all
<pb facs="12"/>
our talke of faith, hope, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, will bee but as the noise of a tinckling Cimball, a <hi>noyse,</hi> no <hi>voice:</hi> and that will neuer (or seldome) bringe any edification to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers.</p>
   <p>And thus gentle reader, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that by other mens harms God will giue thee to beware as also the heart of entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning good counsaile, how base, poore, or otherwise soeuer the counsellor bee, I leaue thee to the sequell of <hi>diuine Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> which the Lorde make blessed vnto thee. In receiuing good by it, giue to GOD the praise, and for mee to god thy praiers, speciallie, that it woulde please <hi>GOD,</hi> to giue som timely issue out of my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent tentation.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="12"/>
And so heartilie farewell, this seauenteenth of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uember,</hi> the <hi>memoriall daye</hi> of our late blessed Soueraign, good Queene <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> whose name be euer honoured in the Catalogue of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Princes.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord,
<hi>He. Cl.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>