<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Readers.</title>
           <author>Fletcher, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114474_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A22871</idno>
           <idno type="STC">936</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114474</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Readers.</title>
                 <author>Fletcher, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An introduction to the looue of God. Accoumpted among the workes of S. Augustine, and translated into English, by the right reuerend father in God, Edmund, Bishop of Norvvitch, that nowe is, and by him dedicated to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie, to the glorie of God, and comfort of his chosen. And newlie turned into Englishe meter : by Robert Fletcher. 1581</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>110 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Christian <hi>Readers.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hatsoeuer hath been writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi> before time, was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for our learning, that we through patience &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the scriptures, might haue hope. Among which (right courteous Readers) I may insert this present Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, béeing trāslated by my Lord Bishop of <hi>Norwitch,</hi> to the benefite of our corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall bodyes, and comfort of our soules, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coumpted amongst the workes of S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine,</hi> and no lesse commended by that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and learned Father of godly memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, <hi>Erasmus</hi> of <hi>Rotardam,</hi> to taste of good learning: which to peruse, I referre you to the Preface in the Prose, written to the Reader, by that honourable and godly Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, who translated the same, naming it, <hi>An Introduction to the looue of God.</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring thereby the looue he beareth vnto his Prince &amp; Soueraigne Lady, to whom he Dedicated the same: as also the good wil to comfort in the looue and mercie of God, his loouing neighbours, and countreymen, following y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> example of a true Shéepheard
<pb facs="5"/>
and faithfull Pastours, in penning this so profitable a Discourse, which distingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth vnto you by equal portions, the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious benefites of our creation, preserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, sanctification, iustification, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, by God the Father, through the merites and frée grace of Christe Iesus our Lorde. Which great mercies you maye beholde in this lyttle Booke, euen as if in a glasse you were disposed to take viewe of your countenaunce shape, and bodilie proportion, but much more to your profite, for that the one is presentlie for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, the other remayneth permanent for euer, if it be sought in singlenesse of eye, and simplicitie of harte.</p>
   <p>Which woorthy worke, according to my skillesse capacitie, I haue turned into Englishe Meter, not thereby to derogate the Prose, or to arogate the prayse thereof in any part to my selfe, for so might I iust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie be condempned of presumption, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogant follie: but he which knoweth the secret of all hearts, knoweth also how far I am from séeking vainglorie thereby: on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie this mooued me therevnto, the profite that I sawe contained in the Prose, which I hope will be no lesse pleasant in the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb facs="5"/>
béeing plaine, and not much alienated from the former sence. I hauing so good a theame, thought good to meditate therein, following the example of these godly min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, with whome I will make no compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison, but onelie for endeuour, which haue turned many Bookes of the olde Testamēt into Englishe meter, as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Psalmes of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> the life of <hi>Dauid,</hi> containing the secōd booke of <hi>Kings,</hi> the fiue bookes of <hi>Moses,</hi> the Prouerbes of <hi>Salomon,</hi> and diuers other, as well Canonicall, as Historicall: accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that saying of the Apostle <hi>Iames, If any be afflicted, let him pray, if merrie let him sing Psalmes.</hi> So he that is dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to profit in the prose, it is an excellent meditatiō, if to pleasure, in the meter, it is present for him that feareth God. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, I know y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> meter is more acceptable to some then prose, &amp; may with lesse capacitie be cōprehended, as of children, yoūg men &amp; maides, &amp;c. which mooued me also to take this paines therein, and the rather to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse that huge heape, &amp; superfluous rable of balde Ballads, Rimes &amp; Ridles, Songs &amp; Sonnets, yea, and whole volumes of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, which tend to the nourishing of vice, and corrupting of Youth, which be not
<pb facs="6"/>
written for our learning, but for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion of those that delight therin, to teach vnlawfull lust, and outragious ribauldry, and to trayne vp in the toyes of vanitie, the vaine, fickle, and fantasticall youth, yea, and some aged, whose modestie ought to be ashamed of such immoderate follie. It is not long since I happened to speake with a good fréend of mine, concerning the Printing of this Booke in meter: truely (sayth he) it is woorthy the publishing in Print, but Bookes of vanitie be better sold twentie to one, which is lamentable, that vanitie should be preferred, and Vertue supplanted, or at the least, verie much sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed. Is that the fruites of our professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (sayde I) that haue enioyed the cleare light of the Gospell, now full thrée &amp; twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yéeres? No (sayth he) God be thanked, many haue, &amp; doo receyue the glad tydinges of the Gospell, with reuerence and feare: but there commeth vp so many fine heads, newlie pullished for the purpose, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse Poetrie, and commit paltries, for he that can eyther Prose or Rime wyll be in print, if his Pen can but blotte foorth a Bable, it shall be a Ballad, with <hi>Finis,</hi> &amp;c. at the ende. They be all <hi>Chaucers</hi> and
<pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>Gowers, Lidgates,</hi> and <hi>Bocases,</hi> and he is a foole that is not fiue <hi>Skeltons</hi> for cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: these write woonders, newes neuer séene before, no, nor neuer heard of, but at Billings gate, or in Grauesende Earge. I would to God, these wittie writers would take paines in penning profitable Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, eyther godlie Meditations, or good Prayers, whether in Prose or in Verse, that the practise of Poperie, which was wunt to be published in Fables, to delude the simple ignorant and vnlearned, might be abolished, with their maister the <hi>Pope,</hi> and newe matters, professing Faith and Religion, published in place thereof. I speake not of any the commendable works of many woorthy wittes, set foorth of late by diuers Worshipfull Gentlemen, good Schollers, and well experimented Poets, which containe bothe pleasure and profite: but of those which in déede, their workes smell not so much as of an honest minde, but will make a mans eares ake to heare them, and his face blushe to reade them: and because they abounde, I am bolde to bewraie my minde of them, wishing you that shall reade this my simple endeuour,
<pb facs="7"/>
in so woorthy a worke, to estéeme the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as it is, and the meter as it shall please you, and bothe so, as God may be glorified, and you certified of his intire looue, if so you looue him, as héerein is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed. To whose looue, grace, and mercie, I committe you for euer.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours, euer in Christ, Robert Fletcher.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>