<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114436_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15420</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25694</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114436</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A retection, or discouerie of a false detection : containing a true defence of two bookes, intituled, Synopsis papismi, and Tetrastylon papisticum, together with the author of them, against diuers pretended vntruths, contradictions, falsification of authors, corruptions o Scripture, obiected against the said bookes in a certaine libell lately published. Wherein the vniust accusations of the libeller, his sophisticall cauils, and vncharitable slaunders are displayed</title>
                 <author>Willet, Andrew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>46, 247, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>SAint</hi> Paul <hi>both as a Prophet fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeing the state of Christs Church, and as an Apostle teaching how we should behaue our selues, saith,</hi> There must bee heresies, that they, which are approued among you, may be knowne, 1. Cor. 11. 19. <hi>For though it be pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>to finde</hi> a countrie without wilde beasts, <hi>as they doe write of Creete: yet a commonwealth without enemies, a religion without gain sayers, a Church without heresies, is not to be found: Euen</hi> Creta, <hi>which was freed from wilde beasts, was pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stered</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>with brutish beastly men,</hi> liers, euil beasts, slow bellies, Tit. 1. 12. <hi>The Church of England likewise wanteth not priuie whisperers and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers at religion, maligners of the present state, and professed enemies to all that loue the truth: which as heretofore hath diuersly appeared to be most true; so the flames of this fire of malice pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilie kindled, haue of late burs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>orth in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine slaunderous Libell or inuectiue, especially directed and intended against two particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>one of excellent learning and singular indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strie, Master</hi> D. Sutcliffe: <hi>the other, though not worthie to be ioyned with him in that quarrell, a well willer likewise of religion, and to his vtmost power a defender of the same. These two need not take it to be a disgrace, that they are singled out, and made markes to shoote at: but rather as</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damidas <hi>said concerning the Thebanes, whom</hi> Alexander <hi>onely excepted, proclaiming libertie to depart to the rest of the Grecians:</hi> This de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree though it seeme hard, yet is glorious to<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> you, because Alexander onely feareth you: <hi>which though it cannot be said alike of both these defenders, yet as it appeareth, the one is feared of them; so the other hath no cause to feare them.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The Libeller hauing first discharged vpon that learned writer before named, doth renew his second battaile against the other, laying siege to two of his fortresses, I meane his two bookes,</hi> Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopsis Papismi, <hi>and</hi> Tetrastylon: <hi>in which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprise he promiseth himselfe a notable victorie, not remembring that saying:</hi> Let not him that girdeth his harnesse, boast himselfe, as he that putteth it off, 1. King. 20. 11. Augustine <hi>saith,</hi> Facile est, vt quisque Augustinum vincat, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deris vtrum veritate, an clamore: <hi>It is an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie matter to ouercome</hi> Augustine, <hi>but see it be not rather with crying and outfacing, then in truth,</hi> epist. 174. <hi>So may we say to this boasting and bragging</hi> Thraso: <hi>I doubt not but his ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined victorie will fall out to be such, as</hi> Pyrrhus
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>was against the Romanes:</hi> If we ouercome but<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> once more (<hi>saith he</hi>) wee are vndone. <hi>It had been much better, in mine opinion, if the Libeller had harkened to S.</hi> Paul, to haue auoyded op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions of science falsely so called, 1. Tim. 6. vers. 20. <hi>that is, not to haue opposed himselfe and his small skill and false knowledge against the truth. But this their opposition redoundeth much to the benefit of the Church of Christ: first, by this meanes they discouer the nakednes of their cause, that cannot be maintained but by railing, and slaunders: as</hi> Hierome <hi>saith:</hi> Istae machinae haereticorum, vt conuicti de perfidia ad ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledicta<note place="margin">Apol. 3. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers. Ruffin.</note> se conferant: <hi>These are the engines of heretikes, that being conuicted of their faithlesse doctrine, turne themselues to railing. So that one</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>reading their mad writings and furious stile, may say of them as</hi> Diogenes <hi>to a phrantike and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse yong man:</hi> Thy father was drunke when he begat thee. <hi>But, as the saying is,</hi> Like lippes,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> like lettice, <hi>like religion, such writing, like au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, like bookes: Like to</hi> Demonides <hi>slippers,</hi> which were euil fauoured, yet fit for his lame feete.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Secondly, by these barking fits and hollow ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choes, I trust others will be awakened from their sleepe, and bend themselues to defend the truth by them defaced, and maintaine religion by them diminished, and hereby be put</hi> in remembrance<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1. 6.</note> to stirre vp the gift of God, which is in them. For (<hi>as the Apostle saith</hi>) God hath not giuen
<pb facs="4"/>
vs the spirit of feare, but of power &amp; of loue, and of a sound minde; <hi>that they may say with</hi> Hierome: Breuiter respondeo, nunquam me<note place="margin">Dialog. 1. aduers. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagian.</note> haereticis pepercisse, sed omni egisse studio, vt hostes ecclesiae mei quoque hostes fierent: <hi>I answere briefly, that I neuer spared heretikes, but did wholy studie, that the enemies of the Church should also become mine enemies.</hi> Ono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mademus <hi>gaue counsell, in a certaine sedition and commotion in</hi> Chius, <hi>that all the enemies</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>should not be expelled,</hi> least we should then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to fall out with our friends, <hi>saith he.</hi> Nasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, <hi>when Carthage was destroyed, vsed to say, that the Romane state was daungerous, because now they had none left, whom they needed to feare. And</hi> Antigonus, <hi>when he heard that</hi> Zeno <hi>the</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>Philosopher was dead, said,</hi> That the theater of his exploits was taken away. <hi>In like manner, if Religion had no forren enemies, we should haue cause more to feare domesticall contention: and if superstition found no patrones to fauour it, the truth would haue fewer friends to vphold it: the opposition therefore of gainsayers doth make the defence of the truth more glorious: and the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of the aduersarie to offend, should make vs more readie to defend the truth: and as the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle answered the Cirrheans,</hi> to fight night and<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> day <hi>in the maintenance of the truth. Like as, when a fire is kindled in a citie, it is not fit that the standers by should looke on and doe nothing, but euery one in that case ought to set to his hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>hand to quench the flames: so should wee seeke to put out those sparks of superstition, which begin to be blowne from the coales of Popery and false religion. And in this respect, that law of</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon <hi>is not much to be misliked:</hi> who decreed<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> him to be infamous, that in the commotion of the citie, would ioyne to neither part. <hi>So neither is he to be commended, that in this dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of religion, standeth as indifferent and a</hi> Neuter.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thirdly, a peculiar benefit may arise to the partie impugned and traduced, to profit by the admonition of his aduersarie: for as it were no shame for him, wherein he hath slipped, to confesse an error, if he found himselfe guiltie: as</hi> Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine <hi>disdained not to retract diuers things in his workes: and</hi> Hierome <hi>saith,</hi> Imitati estis erran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, imitamini correctum: <hi>Ye haue imitated me, while I erred, imitate me also now being cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected,</hi> Hieron. Ocean. Hippocrates <hi>that lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Physition did acknowledge his error about the sutures or seames of the head, and committed the same to writing, least others might by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample be deceiued: So this further vse one may</hi>
      <note place="margin">Plutarch. lib. de▪ pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. virtut. sent.</note>
      <hi>make of an enemies reprehension, thereby to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more cautelous, and to walke more circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectly: as the Prophet</hi> Dauid <hi>saith,</hi> I will keepe my mouth bridled, while y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wicked is in my sight, Psal. 39. 1. Ambrose <hi>saith,</hi> Laqueus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersarij<note place="margin">In Psal. 91.</note> sermo noster; loquimur plerumque, quod excipiat inimicus, &amp; quasi nostro gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio
<pb facs="5"/>
nos vulnerat: <hi>Our speech is the aduersaries snare; we often vtter that, which the enemie cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth at, and so woundeth vs with our owne wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon.</hi> Antisthenes <hi>vsed this saying, that he which</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>desired to be sound,</hi> had need to haue either lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing friends, or angrie enemies: for the one would instruct, the other correct him. <hi>For though one be not guiltie of that, which the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie reproueth, yet he may be more warie not to commit that, which offendeth. As</hi> Chrysippus <hi>answered one that told him that he was euill spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of by some:</hi> But I wil so leade my life, that no man shall giue credite-vnto them. <hi>In like manner</hi> Philip <hi>was wont to say,</hi> that he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to his backbiters, for they made him better. <hi>And so this carping of the aduersarie</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>will minister occasion of greater circumspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>But now to come a little neerer, to take a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall view of this Libellers proceedings: I doe note foure grosse ouersights by him committed: I finde his affection to be</hi> malicious; <hi>his matter</hi> friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous; <hi>his manner of handling</hi> scandalous; <hi>his obiections to himself</hi> contumelious, <hi>being guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the same crimes, wherewith he vpbraideth others.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>First, if he had espied any such faults in his brother, charitie would that he should haue been first by priuate writing or conference admonished to amend them, not at the first by publike libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to seeke to defame him. This is our Sauiours</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>rule, Matth.</hi> 18. 15. If thy brother trespasse a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thee, go and tell him his fault between him and thee alone, &amp;c. <hi>Vpon which words</hi> Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen <hi>saith:</hi> Non vult continuò te euolare in publicum, &amp;c. <hi>Hee will not haue thee straight to flie out into publike censure, &amp;c.</hi> Ruffinus <hi>saith well to</hi> Hierome: Si ebrietas mihialiqua obrepens sicut patriarchae nudau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rat turpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem, lcui palliolo rescripti tui cōtexisses opprobrium, &amp; velasset epistola vigilantis, quem stilus nudauerat dormitantis: <hi>If some ouersight, as of the Patriarke, had vncouered my nakednes, you should haue hidden my shame with the cloake of your priuate writing, that your wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king epistle might haue couered that, which the sleepic penne had vnfoulded. And</hi> Plato <hi>had good</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>;</note>
      <hi>reason thus to say to</hi> Socrates, <hi>reprouing sharply one of his friends in a publike feast:</hi> Had it not been better to haue spoken these things pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately? <hi>And</hi> Socrates <hi>againe to</hi> Plato: Might you not also much better haue told me of this priuately?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Secondly, the whole discourse of this Libeller is</hi> superfluous <hi>and impertinent: for what is this to the truth of religion, or what preiudice to the common cause, if some few places should by some ouersight be mistaken? For as</hi> Augustine <hi>saith:</hi> Sine his dici potest, quod volumus: <hi>Take them away, and yet we are able to confirme, what we say,</hi> cont. Petilian. 3. 20. <hi>But it falleth out vnto them, as the Apostle saith:</hi> They would
<pb facs="6"/>
be Doctors of the law, not knowing what they speake, nor whereof they affirme, 1. Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth. 1. 7. <hi>So this challenger taketh vpon him to be a great Rabbin in popish learning, and yet lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the discussing of matters of religion in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion, brauleth about words and syllables.</hi> Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome <hi>saith,</hi> Quis omissa causa in criminum obiectione versatus est: <hi>Who leauing the cause would spend the time in obiecting of crimes?</hi> aut quid refert si causa cadas, &amp; crimine superes: <hi>Or what great matter is it, if you faile in the cause, and preuaile in crimes?</hi> Apolog. 3. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers. Ruffin. <hi>And what if this cauiller had his will vpon the defender (which he is neuer like to haue) the cause of religion neither standeth nor falleth with him? I say vnto him, as</hi> Augustine <hi>did to his aduersarie:</hi> Noli attendere quomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do vincatur Augustinus qualiscunque vnus homo, sed attende potius vtrum vinei poss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Homou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</note> veritas: <hi>Doe not marke how</hi> Augustine, <hi>how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer but one man may be ouercome, but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the truth may be ouercome. And as</hi> Calli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratides <hi>said to the Southsayer, that foretold victorie to the armie, but death to the Captaine:</hi> That the Spartane affaires depended not vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> one man. <hi>Neither doth the defence of the truth relie vpon any one mans credit. But as</hi> Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seph <hi>said to</hi> Pharaoh, <hi>so may I in this case,</hi> Without me God shall answere, Gen. 41. 16.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Now in the third place let vs see the manner of his stile: which is powdred (I warrant you)</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>with such sawcie termes and popish Rhetorike, euery page of the Libell so garnished with railing, slaundering giuing the lie, that he cannot be dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to haue a religious heart, that so prophanely and vncharitably handleth his tongue. S.</hi> Peter <hi>saith,</hi> If any man speake, let him speake as the words of God, 1. Pet. 4. 11. <hi>Now whether the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beller do speake the words of God, it shall euen now appeare in the rehearsing of some of his phrases: wherin as</hi> Hierome <hi>cōplained of his aduersaries:</hi> It a nomen meum frequenter assumitur, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitur,<note place="margin">Ad Theoph. aduers. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solym.</note> ac si de libro viuentium deletus essem: <hi>My poore name is so often abused and carped at, as though I were rased out of the booke of life.</hi> Phocion <hi>did compare</hi> Leosthenes <hi>oration to the Cypres tree,</hi> that was faire and tall, but bare no fruite: <hi>so his speech was eloquent and</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>pleasing, yet not profitable. But this Romane Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, neither bringeth good speech nor good mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: yet were his sharpnes somewhat to be borne withall, if he had any colour or iust cause so to do: as</hi> Hyperides <hi>the Rhetorician desired the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians to consider</hi> not onely if he were bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> but if hee were bitter vniustlie without cause.</p>
   <list>
      <head>Now I will gather out some of his sweete flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers.</head>
      <item>Fuller of lies then leaues. pag. 118.</item>
      <item>A lie also it is. pag. 123.</item>
      <item>He hath here belied vs. pag. 124</item>
      <item>Whether he be a lier or no, &amp;c. pag. 126</item>
      <item>
         <pb facs="7"/>Put in print an abominable lie. 127</item>
      <item>Palpable lying. 129</item>
      <item>Shamelesse lie. 131</item>
      <item>He belieth him. 148</item>
      <item>By lying and corruption. 150</item>
      <item>He belieth him. 153</item>
      <item>A notable lier. 159</item>
      <item>A lie it is. 169</item>
      <item>A notorious lie. 133</item>
      <item>He maliciously belieth vs. 140</item>
      <item>Notable lies. 141</item>
      <item>Summe vp his lies. 142</item>
      <item>A lier and a falsarie. 144</item>
      <item>Shamelesse lying and falsification. 147</item>
      <item>Notorius lie. 155</item>
      <item>A lie and a knocker. 156</item>
      <item>Lies and mad trickes. 161</item>
      <item>Hunt all his lies. 170</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>As the Libell is pestered with <hi>lies, belying, lier,</hi> so hath it great store of other like stuffe of bitter reuiling and railing.</head>
      <item>Mere malice. 124</item>
      <item>A proper tale as to set the diuell to sale. 132</item>
      <item>Filthie Doctor, shamelesse mate. 133</item>
      <item>Runnagate Roger. 138</item>
   </list>
   <list>
      <head>So he blasphemeth Roger Holland Martyr.</head>
      <item>Shamelesse vntruth. 159</item>
      <item>Spruse Minister. 171</item>
      <item>A giueth the same answere that Baal did to his suppliant seruants. 187</item>
      <item>As Balaam deceiued Balaak. 187</item>
      <item>
         <pb facs="7"/>Perfidiously peruerted. 213</item>
      <item>Maliciously abused. 215</item>
      <item>Malicious dealing. 220</item>
      <item>Maliciously suppressed. 220</item>
      <item>Cunningly and maliciously. 223</item>
      <item>Maliciously abuseth. 231</item>
      <item>Vnmaske malicious dealing. 234</item>
      <item>Weare <hi>Proclus</hi> hereticall liuerie. 238</item>
      <item>If he had not cast off all care of conscience, and shaken hands with death, hee would neuer so maliciously haue corrupted <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine.</hi> 239</item>
      <item>Maiming them most disgraciously wickedly peruerted. 240</item>
      <item>Detest and forsake so malicious a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster. 245</item>
      <item>Without al cōscience by shameful shifts. 253</item>
      <item>Malice and wilfull falsification. 258</item>
      <item>If any should denie him the honor of a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table falsarie. 246</item>
      <item>Shamefully corrupted <hi>S. Augustine.</hi> 247</item>
      <item>A cunnicatching trick and in plaine English a lie. 251</item>
      <item>Most absurdlie and maliciouslie corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, &amp;c. 256</item>
      <item>Maliciously added. 278</item>
   </list>
   <p>
      <hi>Will not any man now thinke, that this fellow hath well profited in</hi> Zoilus <hi>Rhetorike? but such is the manner of popish writers: railing and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing is one of their common weapons. They shew themselues not to fight of</hi> Michaels <hi>side, that</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>durst not giue railing sentence against the diuell,</hi> Iud. 9. <hi>nor yet to be of</hi> Pauls <hi>spirit, that when he called</hi> Ananias <hi>painted wall, excused it by his ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance,</hi> Act. 23. 5. <hi>But this hath alwaies been the guise of heretikes and other aduersaries to the trueth, with euill and slaunderous words to assaile the professors thereof. Thus did the Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians call</hi> Augustine, Cultorem daemonum, <hi>A worshipper of diuels,</hi> cont. Iulian. 3. 18▪ Petilian <hi>the Donatist obiected against him sinne against the holy Ghost,</hi> libr. 3. cap. 62. <hi>He said further, that he had</hi> damnabile ingenium Carneadis, <hi>the damnable wit of</hi> Carneades, lib. 3. 20. <hi>Thus</hi> Celsus <hi>behaued himselfe against</hi> Origen: <hi>whose words we may well vse in this case against our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries:</hi> Si grauiter &amp; modestius haec tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaret plus forsitan suasionis sunt habitura, &amp;c. <hi>If he handled these things grauely and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destly, he might perswade more: but seeing now he scoffingly and scurrilously vttereth many things,</hi> dicturi sumus eum elegantium verborum inopia, vt quae nec nactus esset, nec <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="4 letters">
         <desc>••••</desc>
      </gap>et in tantā incidisse garrulitatem: <hi>we may say, that for want of good words, which hee was vnskilfull of, he hath fallen into such a vaine of brabling.</hi> Origen. cont. Cels. lib. 6. <hi>It is said that the Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ians</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>went to warre with</hi> great noyse and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries, the Grecians in silence: <hi>But how sped they? the stilnes of the Grecians preuailed against the Troians outcries. Neither must these brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging fellowes thinke to carrie all away with great</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>words. They are like to the pratling Pie, that chattereth vpon euery occasion: or rather to the Vultures and Kites, that</hi> follow the smell of<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> stinking carrions, but haue no sense and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in holesome flesh. <hi>So is this Libeller rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to take the least occasion to speake euill, and seemeth to sport himselfe with great delight in filthie and vncleane words: That like as</hi> Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thius <hi>said of</hi> Diogenes <hi>tragedie,</hi> that he could not see it, because the strange words did hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the sight thereof: <hi>So his vncouth termes, and vnseemely speeches, as a stinking mist and gloomie clowde doe couer and hide his slender stuffe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Augustine <hi>would not giue the lie to</hi> Pascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius <hi>the Arrian, though he were worthily dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted thereof, but thus saith vnto him:</hi> If you say those things, which are reported, not to bee so done, either your memorie faileth you; <hi>Non audeo enim dicere te mentiri; aut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>go &amp; fallor &amp; mentior:</hi> For I dare not say you lie, or els I am both deceiued &amp; do lie, <hi>epist.</hi> 174. <hi>But nothing is more common in the Libellers mouth, then</hi> you lie, you belie him, a notable lier, a shamelesse lie: <hi>who herein representeth vnto vs another Stoical</hi> Antipater, <hi>who writing and railing against</hi> Carneades, <hi>was called</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, one that rored or raued with his pen: <hi>or like vnto</hi> Salmoneus, <hi>that counterfeited</hi> Iup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piters <hi>thunder: as</hi> Hierome <hi>saith,</hi> Tu alter no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis Salmoneus omnia per quae incedis illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stras,
<pb facs="9"/>
tu flammeus, immo fulmineus, qui in<note place="margin">Apolog. 3. aduers. Ruffin.</note> loquendo fulminas, &amp;c. <hi>You are another</hi> Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moneus, <hi>which fire all the way where you goe, flashing out lightning, and spitting foorth fire in your speech. But like as men vse to alay the heate of wine, with coole water; and so, as</hi> Plato <hi>saith,</hi> Deum insanum alio sobrio castigare, <hi>To cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect a furious spirit with a tame and sober spirit:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>So I trust to qualifie this railers furious heate, with a true and modest defence: and not as</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raclitus <hi>diseased with the dropsie, desired the Physition</hi> to turne the abundance of showers into drought; <hi>but to alay his intemperate heate and drought with the pleasant dew of the truth.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>I am not purposed to answere him in his owne vaine: for the Scripture teacheth vs,</hi> that wee should recompence no man euill for euill, Rom. 12. 17. Augustine <hi>saith to</hi> Petilian <hi>the Donatist:</hi> Si ego tibi vellem maledicta pro maledictis rependere, quid aliud, quam duo maledici essemus, vt ij, qui nos legerent, alij detestatos abijcerent sana grauitate, alij sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiter haurirent maleuola voluntate: <hi>If I would render euillwords for euill, what els should we be, but two railers, that they which reade vs, should either of a graue iudgement reiect vs, or els of a corrupt fancie affect vs? It is a sufficient defence against a false accuser not to be guiltie.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>The heathen Philosopher could say,</hi> To be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fault is not the least comfort: Crantor. <hi>That saying also of</hi> Diogenes <hi>is much celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>
      <hi>who being asked how he might be reuenged</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>of his enemie:</hi> If thou thy selfe (<hi>saith he</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a good and an honest man.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Fourthly, it remaineth to be shewed how the Libeller iustly incurreth the same offence, which vntruly he obiecteth to others: as first he is guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of many vntruths: as that none of them reade</hi> obtulit, <hi>he offered, for</hi> protulit, <hi>he brought foorth, Genes.</hi> 14. <hi>pag.</hi> 123. <hi>that no author can be cited, that saith the fathers of the Inquisition</hi>
      <note place="margin">Diuers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Libeller.</note>
      <hi>cannot erre, pag.</hi> 117. <hi>that women are allowed by the Communion booke to be ministers of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, Libel. p.</hi> 129. <hi>which is vntrue: for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the baptizing by women collected out of the booke, neither yet is it practised, that I know, in our Church: as a most reuerend Prelate hath auouched in these words:</hi> For common prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise I can say little, but for mine owne expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience this I dare affirme, that I haue not knowne one childe so baptized in places, where I haue had to doe, no not since the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of her Maiesties raigne, &amp;c. <hi>And in the same place:</hi> I thinke if the circumstances of the booke be well considered, it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare that the meaning is, that priuate bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme is rather to be ministred by some Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister (which in time of necessitie may soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest be come by) then by any woman: De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the answere to the admon. pag. 794. <hi>This graue testimonie, omitted in the answere, I thought good here to insert, which is sufficient to</hi>
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <hi>deliuer us from the vntruth obiected, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound it vpon the accusers head. See the answere more at large to the</hi> 7. <hi>Slaunder.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Besides, a great vntruth it is, which he vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, pag.</hi> 164. <hi>contradict.</hi> 5. <hi>that</hi> Luther <hi>confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth,</hi> he was stirred vp by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> diuell against the Masse: <hi>for in the places which he quoteth in the margin,</hi> libr. de Miss. angular. tom. 6. fol. 28. tom. 7. Wittemberg. fol. 443. <hi>no such thing is to be found, in the edition printed at Wittemberg</hi> anno 1558. <hi>neither hath</hi> Luther <hi>any such title,</hi> de Miss. angular. <hi>in the</hi> 6. <hi>tome.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The matter which the Libeller aimeth at, by other mens reading (as it seemeth) rather then his owne, is in</hi> Luthers <hi>booke,</hi> de Miss. priuat.<note place="margin">A slaunder of Luther, that hee should con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse hee was stirred vp of the diuell, to write a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Masse.</note> tom. 7. <hi>where</hi> Luther <hi>indeede reporteth, in the beginning of that treatise, how the diuell tempted him in the night, and set before him his hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, in the celebrating of priuate Masses, contrary to the institution of Christ, and that therein he committed most grosse idolatrie, in worshipping bread and wine in steed of the bodie and bloud of Christ. And whereas it might be said vnto him, that the diuell is a lier, he answereth:</hi> Ipse sic adoritur: The diuell so setteth vpon a man, that first he apprehendeth some solide truth, that cannot bee denied, &amp; so doth turne and tosse it, and doth cast such goodly shew vpon a lie, that hee may deceiue the most circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect: <hi>as that thought, that stroke</hi> Iudas heart, was true, I haue betrayed innocent bloud:
<pb facs="10"/>
      <hi>But this was a lie: Ergo,</hi> you must despayre of the mercie of God.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>So</hi> Luther <hi>saith,</hi> The diuell lieth not, when he vrgeth a mans sinne: Confessus quidem sum, &amp;c. <hi>I confessed being ouercome by the law of God, before the diuell, that I had sinned, and was damned as</hi> Iudas: sed verto me ad Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stum cum Petro: <hi>but I turne my selfe vnto Christ with</hi> Peter.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>This is the summe of the whole narration, there set downe by</hi> Luther <hi>of this temptation.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Any man may now see the cauilling spirits of Papists:</hi> Luther <hi>onely reporteth how Sathan dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>played his hypocrisie and idolatrie, while he was a Masse priest, not to stirre him vp against the Masse, but to bring him into despayre; but that God deliuered him with</hi> Peter.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>They may say as well that when Sathan sifted</hi> Peter, <hi>and set before him his sinne, which drew such bitter teares from</hi> Peter, <hi>that Sathan mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him to repentance: or that when</hi> Paul <hi>felt the pricke of his flesh, the messenger of Sathan sent to buffet him, whereupon he betooke him to prayer, that Sathan also stirred the Apostle to prayer. So then</hi> Luthers <hi>conuersion and opposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion against the Masse was a sequell, but no effect of Sathans temptation: the diuell intended his confusion, God thereby wrought his conuersion.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The like cauill against</hi> Luther <hi>is vttered by</hi> Bellarmine, <hi>and vented againe by the Libeller, pag.</hi> 167. that Luther thinketh that if the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell
<pb facs="11"/>
himself should minister the Sacraments, that they might bee fruitfull and effectuall: <hi>whereas</hi> Luther <hi>saith not if the diuell himselfe, that is in his owne person, as the diuell: but these are his words,</hi> ego pono, <hi>but I set downe this,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Demiss. priuat. tom. 7. p. fol. 243 p. 2.</note>
      <hi>that if</hi> I should afterward know, the diuell irrepsisse, to haue crept into the office of a pastor of the church, &amp; in the shape of a man to be called to preach and baptize, &amp;c. that the Sacraments therefore are not without ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacie. <hi>Thus they curtall and mangle his words, and alter his meaning at their pleasure.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Vntrue also it is, that the Apocalypse hath no more ancient authoritie, then the Councell of Carthage, p.</hi> 130. <hi>That</hi> Leo <hi>confirmed not, that the bloud issuing out of a certaine Crucifixe, was the bloud of Christ, pag.</hi> 131. <hi>That</hi> Gregorie 7. <hi>was not a sorcerer and adulterer. pag.</hi> 159. <hi>That it is a fabulous tale of the taking vp of diuers thousands heads of children in</hi> Gregories <hi>mote, pag.</hi> 160. <hi>That father</hi> Fox <hi>is belied, whereas he is truly alleaged contradict. 5. pag.</hi> 166. <hi>That it is a lie, that</hi> Nectarius <hi>abrogated priuate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, contradict.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 169. <hi>That the ancient fathers are called heretikes, contradict.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 177. <hi>That we should hold, that adulterie, murther, ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, in the regenerate are no sinnes, contrad.</hi> 11. <hi>pag.</hi> 202. <hi>These apparant vntruths the Libeller vttereth, as more at large may be seene in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall answers: and therefore he is worthie of</hi> Esops <hi>reward, who being asked what liers gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned:</hi>
      <pb facs="11"/>
That they, when they speake the truth,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>(saith he)</hi> be not beleeued.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Secondly, this Libeller is not free from contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions: he affirmeth, that</hi> Saul <hi>was elected, and yet damned, pag.</hi> 191. <hi>contrarie to the opinion of</hi>
      <note place="margin">Contradic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note>
      <hi>the most learned of his side, who though they hold that a man cannot be certaine of his election, yet dare not, neither doe affirme, that election before God may be lost: nay</hi> Bellarmine <hi>writeth the contrarie, that the elect,</hi> per infallibilia media, <hi>by infallible meanes, are directed to eternall▪ life:</hi> lib. 2. de grat. cap. 9.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Likewise he seemeth to affirme, that Martyrs are not to be inuocated in the sacrifice of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Christ, falsific.</hi> 10. <hi>pag.</hi> 251. <hi>contrarie to the common practise of the Popish Church, which in the canon of the Masse prayeth to be defended by the merits and prayers of the Saints: see the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thirdly, the Libeller himselfe is full of falsifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Falsificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note>
      <hi>as pag.</hi> 209. <hi>contradict.</hi> 13. <hi>lin.</hi> 24. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his doctrine of originall and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall sanctification: <hi>where not the</hi> eternall <hi>sanctification, but</hi> externall <hi>rather and eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall of the faithfuls children is spoken of. pag.</hi> 244. <hi>falsific.</hi> 9. <hi>he himself leaueth out diuers materiall words in</hi> Augustine, <hi>as is noted in the answere. He doth the like, pag.</hi> 247. <hi>falsific.</hi> 10. <hi>as is declared also in the defence, pag.</hi> 226. <hi>falsific.</hi> 5. <hi>in alleaging a canon of the Councell of Colen, in these words,</hi> to heare Masse, <hi>he addeth</hi> Masse, <hi>of</hi>
      <pb facs="12"/>
      <hi>his owne. Pag.</hi> 268. <hi>corrup.</hi> 7. <hi>he misreporteth the words inferring thus:</hi> He maketh S. <hi>Paul</hi> to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme absolutely that faith worketh by loue. <hi>See the correction of that corruption.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Fourthly, he is found to be a corrupter of scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: as pag.</hi> 123. <hi>vntruth</hi> 1. the scripture saith it was Samuel, <hi>whereas the scripture saith only,</hi> Saul knew it was Samuel. <hi>Pag.</hi> 141. <hi>vntruth</hi> 11. <hi>he readeth,</hi> Saul an elect and good man, 1. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> 9. 2. <hi>for,</hi> Saul was a goodly young man and faire.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thus it is euident how the Libellers eyes were blinded, and hoodwinked with selfeloue toward himselfe, and hatred toward others, that while he prieth to finde faults abroad, he forgetteth his owne at home. He should haue remembred our Sauiours words to the Iewes, Ioh.</hi> 8. Si quis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strum peccatum non habet mittat primum lapidem: <hi>He that of you is without fault, cast the first stone at her. He should haue taken the beame out of his owne eye, before he had as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saied to pull a moate out of his brothers. It fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth out now to him, as</hi> Ruffinus <hi>saith:</hi> Quasi siquis furti alium incusans, id ipsum vnde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium arguit in sinu suo contegat furtum: <hi>As if a man should accuse another of theft, and hide a stollen thing in his owne bosome:</hi> Inuectiu. in Hieron. Plato, <hi>when he saw any vncomely thing to be done by others, would thus say to himselfe apart,</hi> Whether I my selfe were not such an<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> one. <hi>Thus this carper of others, should first haue</hi>
      <pb facs="12"/>
      <hi>examined himselfe: whereas now the reproch, which he would fasten vpon others, of</hi> vntruths, contradiction, falsification, corruption, <hi>is cast vpon himselfe. Like as</hi> Melanthius <hi>said to</hi> Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gias <hi>the Orator, perswading concord to the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians:</hi> This man (saith he) counselleth vs to<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> peace, being not able to perswade himselfe, his wife, and maide three priuate persons to haue peace at home. <hi>And so this detector of others, is detected himselfe, of vntruths, falsifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, corruptions, and that not once or twice, but often: whereas in</hi> writing, <hi>as in</hi> warring, <hi>as</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machus<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>said to a souldier crauing pardon of his offence,</hi> It is not lawfull in warre to offend twice.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>