<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Introduction.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114010_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10311</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20596</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114010</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Introduction.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The glorie of man consisting in the excellencie and perfection of woman : Gathered out of Holie Scriptures, and most renowned wryters; as well ancient, as moderne; ecclesiaticall, as morall. Wherevnto is annexed The duetie of husbands</title>
                 <author>Raban, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Raban, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Aberdeen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 911, that is 119, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb n="93" facs="58"/>
   <head>The Introduction.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Atient <hi>IOB</hi> saying, that the whole lyfe of Man was nothing else, but a tyme of Temptations, spake most fearfullie, and yet most truelie: for wee are tempted in our olde Age; and in our Cradle wee are not free. If anie evill bee set before vs, wee are easilie provoked vnto it. If wee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound with <hi>Adam,</hi> in Paradise, there may bee <hi>Death</hi> in that: And, if wee want, with our Saviour, in the Wildernesse, there are Temptations in that also: So sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile is Satan, and so envyous is our Enemie, to serue himselfe, even vpon all occasions.</p>
   <p>In the former age of the World, hee wrought, and prevayled with Men, by bringing in Errours of Mynde, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Devils, to seduce the Church: But now the cleare light of the Gospell bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come in, and Knowledge abounding, hee
<pb n="94" facs="59"/> laboureth to bring in Errour of lyfe, and depravitie of Conversation; for that, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding men know their Masters will, yet they performe it not, that all meanes possible ought to bee vsed, for the Reformation of these so notorious and knowne Evills: yea, everie man to put a hand to this worke: amongst the number of which, I haue brought foorth this my poore Talent, to the fartherance thereof: that wee married Men may stryue yet with our Arch-enemie; and, through the assistance of GOD'S Spirit, giue him the foyle; even by showing our vpright duetie towardes our Wyues, and our wyues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs, in the true loue and feare of GOD.</p>
   <p>As for these contentious objectours, and barkers agaynst the Moone, I weygh not. Shepheardes, Cow-heardes, and Clownes, haue writen good thinges, yea, Divyne matters; Why, then, may not I show my good will? desiring no other Reward, nor Thankes for my paynes, but onlie good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance: And so I goe forwardes to thE WoRke.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>