<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114001_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06128</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16613</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114001</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Romane historie vvritten by T. Livius of Padua. Also, the Breviaries of L. Florus: with a chronologie to the whole historie: and the Topographie of Rome in old time. Translated out of Latine into English, by Philemon Holland, Doctor in Physicke</title>
                 <author>Livy</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 804, 809-1351, 1354-1403, 43 pages, portraits, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Rue is that Axiome received from Philosopie, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. i. <hi>The corruption of one thing is the generation of another.</hi> Thus out of the ashas and ruines of Troie sprung the cittie of Rome: and by the wofull fall of that one state, arose not only the most glorious empire of the Romans, but also the best writer of their historie, <hi>Titus Livius.</hi> For wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as after the fatall destruction of Troy, two principall men of name remained alive, <hi>Aeneas</hi> and <hi>Antenor</hi>: the one with his fleet arriving in that coast of Italie where Tybre runneth, built Lavinium, and became the first father of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, according to <hi>Virgil</hi> in the first <hi>Aeneid</hi>:
<q>
         <l>—genus unde Latinum,</l>
         <l>Albanique patres, atque altae moenia Roma.</l>
      </q>
      <q>
         <l>—from vvhence are Latines come,</l>
         <l>The noble Albanes eke, and vvalles of stately Rome.</l>
      </q>
      <hi>Antenor</hi> entered the Venice gulfe, and founded the citie of Padua, the native place of <hi>Livie</hi> their historiographer; as the same Poet writeth a little after:
<q>
         <l>Hic tamen ille urbem Patavi sedésque locavit</l>
         <l>Teuerorum, &amp;c.—</l>
      </q>
      <q>
         <l>Yet here the citie Padua built he: therein to plant</l>
         <l>His Trojanes, left when Troy vvas lost, vvho resting seat did vvant.</l>
      </q> And I wot not wel, whither they were more beholden to that fortune of theirs, (wherof so much they boasted) for <hi>Aeneas</hi> the author of their beginning &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable greatnes: than for this writer <hi>Livie,</hi> who cōmended their deeds to ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting same. For from their very first rising [even vvith <hi>Aeneas</hi>] unto their sensible declining and decay, were not twelve hundred yeeres compleat: but since <hi>Livie</hi> enchronicled their acts, sixteene hundred are come and gone: yet continue they as fresh this day as at the first, and spred still farre and neere into all parts of the vvorld, So much more durable and permanent are the memorials recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by learned Historians, than either any monarchie bee it never so great, or all those vvonderfull Pyramides and Obeliskes, reared by most magnificent Kings, and mightie emperors, to immortalize their name and memorie. This <hi>T. Livius</hi> then, vvas borne at Padua, in the yeere 694 after the foundation of Rome, vvhen <hi>L. Afranius</hi> and <hi>Q. Caecilius Metellus Celer</hi> vvere Consuls. He flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished
<pb facs="4"/>
all the time of <hi>Augustus Caesar,</hi> and died in the fourth yeere of <hi>Tiberius</hi>: By vvhich account, hee lived full LXXVI, yeeres: as appeareth by an aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Epitaph upon his tombe at Padua, (where it is thought hee died) with the pourtraict of his visage: whereof the one is represented here, and the other immediatly before the beginning of the Historie.
<figure>
         <head>T·LIVIVS PATAVINVS·</head>
      </figure>
   </p>
   <q>TITVS LIVIVS PATAVINVS, Cujus invicto calamo, invicta Romanorum facta scripta sunt.</q>
   <q>
      <l>TITE LIVIE OF PADUA, Who wrote long since with peere-lesse pen,</l>
      <l>The acts of Romanes, match-lesse men.</l>
   </q>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>Other evidences there be concerning the same, which needlesse it were to call to witnesse: for no Epitaph nor inscription either enchased in stone or cut in brasse, is there left, better than the monuments of his owne writings (if they had come entire to our hands) and the testimonie of good and approoved authors. For during the time of <hi>Augustus,</hi> he wrote the worthie deeds of the Romanes, and continued the narration thereof, from the verie foundation of the cittie of Rome unto the one and twentieth yeere of his Empire. A storie of 750 yeeres, and a peece of worke for the artificiall frame and elegant setting out, compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the best in that kind. My purpose is not here, to enter into a large field and rhetoricall discourse of his praises in regard of any gifts of fortune where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he was plentifully enriched: namely, the place of his nativitie, a citie more auncient by 400 yeeres than Rome; flourishing in martiall puissance, able to set out and maintaine 100000 fighting men for the warres; in stately port at home, having a nobilitie of 400 in numbers; in gorgeous and costly buildings; in traffique and frequent affluence of Merchants thither; as also, that Venice was a Colonie deducted and drawne from thence; and, which is not the least, how at this day the famous Vniversitie there, affourdeth excellent professors in all kind of learning: nor his happinesse and felicitie to live and die with the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and beautie of Rome, and not to behold with his eyes those daies of her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining state and deformitie, which in great wisdome he foresaw in his spirit, and denounced accordingly: ne yet the speciall favour wherein hee stood with his prince <hi>Augustus,</hi> and <hi>Livia</hi> the Empresse: much lesse then meane I to set forth the singular qualities and perfections of his mind, and namely his rare and pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing eloquence; which my pen is no more able now to describe and amplifie to the worthinesse thereof, than it was to imitate and expresse the same in transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of his storie. Moreover, if I should set into his commendation, besides that I must needs come farre short of his merit, the thing it selfe would but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new the iust griefe, that all learned men have taken for the piteous maime and defect of that norable peece of worke and uniforme composition which hee left unto posteritie. For having digested the whole historie into an hundred and two and fortie bookes, as <hi>Petrarch</hi> was of opinion, and as <hi>Sigonius</hi> therein well collecteth: like as also it is evident by the Breviaties of <hi>L. Florus</hi> the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomist, whereof vve have 140, vvith an evident flavv and default of twaine, to vvit, the 136 and 137: see the partiall iniurie of the time, the crooked &amp; maligne destinie of the man! Bookes of farre lesse moment and importance, yea and those of greater antiquitie, have been spared and remaine safe: but of that vvork of his, one fourth part hath not escaped the envie of fortune: and that vvhich novv is extant, hath been delivered unto us either by fragments of old copies unperfect, or by the over-curious medling of some busie <hi>Aristarches</hi> of late daies depraved, who vvith their correcting have corrupted; &amp; in stead of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vvords, have deformed the naturall sense and primitive construction. Where, by the vvay, I must advertise the Reader of that vvhich <hi>Petrus Crinitus</hi> hath observed, even against the common opinion approoved by those vvho othervvise are vvell learned, namely that our Author dispensed not this historie into Decades: that is to say, luted and sorted them not into severall Tomes and Sections of ten bookes a peece. For <hi>Priscian</hi> and other old Grammarians,
<pb facs="5"/>
vvhen they cite any testimonie out of <hi>Livie,</hi> quote the book, and make no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at all of any Decade: and with him the abovenamed <hi>Petrarch, Florus, &amp; Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litian</hi> doe agree. Now in these 35 bookes, so few as they be, preserved as another Palladium out of a generall skarefire, vve may conceive the rare and vvonderfull eloquence of our vvriter in the whole: for the farther he proceedeth into a world as it vvere, of matter, the more copious still he sloweth; and vvith such varietie, as that he never iterateth one thing twice; but at every change of nevv affaires, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth alvvaies fresh and gay, furnished vvith nevv devises, inventions, and phrases: much like a second <hi>Antaeus,</hi> gathering greater strength &amp; moreforces stil at eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry turn: or after the maner of a little rill, vvhich issuing from a small source, is main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained vvith fresh springs and nevv riverets; &amp; hasting toward the vast ocean, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth a deeper channell &amp; broader streame. For the forme of his style, I referre the readers to the sound &amp; staied iudgement rather of <hi>Quintilian,</hi> who cōpareth him vvith <hi>Herodotus, Thucydides,</hi> &amp; the best Greeks; than to the fantastical conceits of some Criticks of our time, vvho seeking <hi>nodum inscirpo,</hi> have dreamed of I vvot not vvhat Paravinitie in him. What should I speake of that Patheticall spirit of his in moving affections? But, that which most of all commende than historie, which being <hi>lux veritatis,</hi> ought especially to deliver with synceritie the whole truth &amp; nothing but the truth, without respect of face or person: to keep only to the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance &amp; train of the subiect argumēt; the due &amp; orderly regard of the important circumstances there to belonging, vvithout inserting extravagant &amp; impertinent by-matters, much lesse then, fabulous tales: therein he hath the pricke and price above all others. For, neither for beareth he to reprove (as occasion is offered) the Romans, in whose favour he might be thought to have vvritten, nor doubteth to praise the good parts &amp; the valiant exploits of their mortall enemies. The Gauls he may seem to gallmore bitterly upon a sinister affection, glauncing at them, as he doth, in many places for their greedie desire of gold &amp; idle slouth, as not able to endure any long travell, and heat least of all: yet so, as the French novv li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, seeme not much offended therewith: for above other nations they have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him most friendly intertainment, and twise enfranchised him among them. I am not unwilling to touch by the way this principal point and vertue of an Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storiographer, I meane the deliverie of a simple trueth in his narrations: for that I have observed in him throughout, that he hath been most modest in reporting from others by heare say any thing that soundeth to an untruth: so little deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth he to be noted with the infamous brand of lier. The vvarie circumsecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his in that behalfe vvhich I dare be bold to recommend unto the reader, I proposed unto my selfe in making him english; endevoring by conference es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially of the select copies in Latin, yet not reiecting other translations (such as I had some little skil in) to come as neere as possibly I could, to the true meaning of the Author: making this account, that if I could approve my diligence that way to men of reason and understanding, all other my wants and defects might sooner be passed by and pardoned. A desire I had to performe in some sort, that which is profitable to the most, namely, and english Historie of that C.W. which of all others (if I have any iudgement) affourdeth most plenteous examples of devout zeale in their kind, of vvisedome, pollicie, iustice, valour, and all vertues vvhatsoever. According to this purpose &amp; intent of mine I framed my pen, not to
<pb facs="5"/>
any affected phrase, but to a meane and popular stile. Wherein, if I have called againe into use some old words, let it be attributed to the love of my countrey language: if the sentence be not so concise, couched and knit togither, as the originall, loth I was to be obscure and darke: have I not englished everie word aptly? ech Nation hath severall maners yea and tearmes appropriate, by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves: have I varied in some places from the French or Italian? censured I looke to be, and haply reprooved: but like as <hi>Alcibiades</hi> said to one, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>i. Strike hardly (Euribiades) so you heare me speake</hi>: even so say I, Find fault and spare not; but withal, read the original better before ye give sentence. And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever I have faulted otherwise by oversight, set against it my affection &amp; desire to do some good whiles I live to my sweet native country: adde therto the long travell that I have taken to testifie the same: and if that will not bring down the ballance, let the profit and delight both, which you shall find in the argument and discourse of the historie, countrepoise and over-weigh my wants, more or lesse. And thus I recommend unto my countrymen, <hi>Livie</hi> in English habit: <hi>Livie</hi> (I say) who whether he were more honored whiles he lived, than beloved at this day of forrein nations, I cannot easily determine. For like as then, (by the testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> and <hi>Plinte</hi> in his Epistles) there repaired many great and noble personages from the farthest parts of Spaine and Fraunce, only to see his face, for the admiration they conceived of him by the fame of his incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eloquence: even so of late time, his spirit (which yet liveth in his writings) hath made a voyage by Florence into the same Fraunce and Spaine: and hath passed as far as into Arabia one way, &amp; Almaine another. In which dissite and remote parts he hath found such kind entertainment, not only in courts of em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours and kings, in pallaces of princes and great potentates; but also with the people in generall: that they seeme to strive no lesse (who may endow him with most ample franchises and free burgeoisie) than those seven citties in old time who every one chalenged to themselves, the birth of the poet <hi>Homer.</hi> Since then, he hath thus long been desirous to crosse the feas into this noble <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>and, not as a travailer to soiourne for a time, in the Court onely or the Vniversities; but to remaine here still both in citie and countrey, and thereto hath learned our lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage indifferently; let it now appeare that this nation of ours (like to reap as great fruit and benefit by his acquaintance as any other) is readie also to receive and embrace him as friendly as the rest.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>