<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ A shorte Poeme, seruing for an introduc∣tion to the Text.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114490_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18923</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5344</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114490</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ A shorte Poeme, seruing for an introduc∣tion to the Text.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A manuell of the Bibles doctrine, for law and Gospell, letter and spirit, signe and thing signified : reduced to the first chapter of Leuiticus: Wherewith (occasionally) be plainely considered, and briefelie concluded, the most mayne questions wherewith the christian churches be combred. By H.C</title>
                 <author>Clapham, Henoch</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bradock, Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 259, 5 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb n="5" facs="15"/>
   <head>¶ A shorte Poeme, seruing for an introduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Text.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Lorde hauing set the Angelicall spirites out of his hand,</hi> Tobh, <hi>good, fayre, ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, behold a certaine num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">Iude 6.</note> forsooke their place, <hi>and so becomming ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue se to God, they waited o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of vexing GOD in his creature, coueting that the heauenly places they had lost, might neuer of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ers be supplied. Mankind no sooner created and beautifuly seated
<pb n="6" facs="16"/>
but loe, Satan that sleeps not, aggressed woman, first peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting her at the time of eating, &amp; thē hauing</hi> virtual possessiō <hi>of her (as before of the beast) he moues her to solicite mā as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he moued the beast to soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit womā: he by womā, so came to sinne, as shee by the serpent, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>hereupon soon after God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulsed them Paradise, the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament all signe of heauens<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blisse aboue. But as the Lord first cloathed them in Beastes skins, so doubtlesse he informe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> them forthwith (vpon the bles</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 15. &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>sed seede promised) of laws for sacrificing the flesh of beasts &amp; birds, so well as of a meate of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring to concur threwithall; by which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>remonies they might more familiarly be lēd (as by the hand) vnto the promised seed, Christ Iesus.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb n="7" facs="16"/>
Adam <hi>liuing in this faith, hee cōmēded the same to his sons; for no sooner we hear of them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ut we hear they did sacrifice;</hi> Abel <hi>of his flock,</hi> Caine <hi>of his ground fruits.</hi> Abel <hi>slaine, the verity of sacrifice was renued in</hi> Sheth, <hi>whom god put in the place of</hi> Abel. Seth <hi>begot AE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nosh, and he begot</hi> Kenan. Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nan <hi>beg at</hi> Mahalaleel, <hi>&amp; hee</hi> lared. Iared <hi>begat</hi> Henoc <hi>(the 7 frō</hi> Adam) <hi>he begot</hi> Mathu selah, Mathusela Lamech, <hi>&amp; he</hi> Noah. <hi>By these to the flud, and by</hi> Noah <hi>the sacrifice of faith was maintaind.</hi> Noah <hi>at the. y. end, cōming out of the ark (world aged 1657) sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth a sweet sauor to the lord▪ his son</hi> Shem <hi>doth specially de riue the care of continuing</hi>
      <note place="margin">Shem liued 600 years.</note>
      <hi>the holy ceremony, dying but about 25 years before</hi> Abram
<pb n="8" facs="17"/>
      <hi>To this</hi> Abram, <hi>the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued the</hi> promise, <hi>telling him more particularlye, that that Seede (not seedes as speaking of many) shold be deriued from his lyne. This holy father con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued the ceremony of faith; as also, vpon a peculiar com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, offereth Beastes, and birds vndiuided, in</hi> Gen. 15. <hi>whereupon he is told, that his seed should be a stranger and afflicted, 400. yeares, and that in land not theirs, that is, as the auncient</hi> Rabanus Maurus <hi>(from</hi> Eusebius) <hi>wel noteth, not onely in AEgypte, but also in the first vnpurged</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Eab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>s</hi> in his 2. b. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Exodus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ache Neoph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>t. to no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ber the times better.</note> Canaan. <hi>The first open perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of his seede, begonn in the halfe Egiptian Ismael, flowting at the promise in</hi> Isa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ac, <hi>what time</hi> Isaac <hi>was way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi>
      <pb n="9" facs="17"/>
Abraham <hi>begat</hi> Isaac, Isaac Iacob; Iacob <hi>the twelue patriarches, whereof came the twelue tribes termed Israel, which went down into AEgipt for 215. yeares, not for 430, as the former ancient wil teache Neophyts, from the fathers age, thus: Abraham at his hundred yeare, had Isaac, (then the affliction begon by one of</hi> Chams <hi>kytes) Isaac li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued 180 yeares, and then was gathered to his fathers. Ten years after, Iaacob went down into AEgypt with his 70 souls <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e being then aged 130. Put Isaacs 180 vnto the ten years after before the descensiō into AEgipt and the sum will proue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ust 190. Adde vnto this 190, he sum of years before Isacs birth vnto the promise giuen
<pb n="10" facs="18"/>
to his father</hi> Abraham <hi>(which was in his 75. yeare) &amp; their wil be 25 years: for the addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (namely, from Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams 75 vnto his 100 yeere) and so the particulars from Abrahams peregrination vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> Israels <hi>descension, wil be 25 years and 190 years, the whole sum 215 years. In Egipte so they were but 215 moe: the whole 430. according to that in</hi> Exod. 12. 40. <hi>where from the first peregrination made by their grandfather out of</hi> Vr <hi>of</hi> Chaldie <hi>vnto that going out of his seede from AEgypt with</hi> Moses, <hi>be nombred 430 years. The same nomber, from the Gospel preached to Abram vnto the giuing of the two ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled lawe at mounte</hi> Sinai <hi>in the wildernesse, is pressed of
<pb n="11" facs="18"/>
the apostle, when to the Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians he saith thus;</hi> The law which was 430 yeeres after <hi>the Gospell was preached to Abram, cannot disanull that couenant, that was confirmed before of GOD in respecte of Christ, that it shoulde make the promise of none effect.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thus from the worlds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning (Adam hauing sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) vnto the guift of the Law (morall, iudiciall, ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all) at</hi> Sinai <hi>or</hi> Horeb <hi>(euen, som 2513 years) was the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised seed set out vnder cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall shadows, &amp; not now first giuen at the mount to the sons of Leui.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>