<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114005_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15103</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25401</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114005</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvveare vnto certaine crabbed questions : pretending a reall presence of Christ in the Sacramente: latelie propounded by some secret papist, to the great troubling of the consciences of the simple, together with a discouerie of the Jesuiticall opinion of justification, guilefully vttered by Sherwyne at the time of his execution. Gathered and set foorth by Peter Whyte, very necessary &amp; profitable for this dangerous time</title>
                 <author>White, Peter, vicar of Eaton Socon</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 <publisher>Kirkham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>5, 44, 8, 41 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="48"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE To the Reader.</head>
   <p>THe old serpent, The red Dragon,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. <hi>Iob.</hi> 1. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 9.12.13 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2.3. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. <hi>Esay</hi> 28.</note> Sathan the deceiuer of the whole worlde, the continuall selaūderer and accuser of Gods childrē hath no way (gentle reader) more molested Gods people, and preuailed against his Church to the great hinderance of his true worship and glorie of his blessed name, then by renting the vnitie of his Church into the sectes and fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men, couering neuerthelesse these manifolde sectes and factions vnder the Cloake and shadow of the Catholike Church when in deede there most times emong these factions either remaineth no part of Gods worship and true religion at all, or els verie little, and that so corrupted, as therein the true glorie of God may no way appeare, when the true glorie of God his worship and religion is truly founded in Christe,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen.</hi> 3 17. <hi>Deut.</hi> 18, <hi>Esay</hi> 8.9.10.13. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3 10.28. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.3.4.5.10. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.6. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4. <hi>Collos.</hi> 2. <hi>Epist. Iohn cap</hi> 1.2.</note> by whom the knoweledge of God the father, wisedome, righteousnes, sanctification and redemption is denied vnto vs through ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his holy spirit and ministerie of his worde, and wee againe by the same meanes as it were by iointes and cooples inseparable conioyned vnto Christ in whom dwelleth the fulnes of the Godhead substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, and is the only head of his Church &amp; Sauiour of his bodie, that in him and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe him we may both see and enioy the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb facs="49"/>presence of God essectually. This craftie workeman Sathan so cunning li transsigureth himselfe as though he were an Angell of light,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>Ebru</hi> 1.2.3.4.8.9.10.13. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1.4.6.7.10.11.14. <hi>Cal.</hi> 1.2.3.4. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.2.3.</note> that hee often renteth the parts and mēbers of this bodie from Christ and God: conioyning them vnto himselfe through the inuentions, titles, and holines of men, treading downe the true doctrine of Christ, his precious blood, death and merits by the doctrine of mens deuises, merits, and other such like abhominations. Thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan Sathan in Paradise to worke at the very beginning: Thus so soone as the lawe was giuen vnder Moyses, wrought hee by Corah, Dathan, and Abyran, and hath so continued vntill this day,<note place="margin">Num. <hi>16.</hi>
      </note> and will doe vnto the worldes end. Vnder the titles, names, &amp; traditions of Saduceis, Esseans, and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riseis he aduanced so farre his owne king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that hee vtterly defaced the kingdome of God, blinded both Priest and people, that not onely the name of a true Israelite in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of a Saducie, Esseā, or Pharisy was of no regard or estimation, hee thereby so much blinded them that they knewe not Christ the true Messias whē he was come among thē: but vtterly refused him and to their great condemnation reiected him whom they dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had in their mouthes and bragged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to be his people, his Church, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Abraham,<note place="margin">Iohn <hi>1.</hi>
      </note> vnto whom as vnto his peculiar inheritance he was especially sent. The sonne of God found none more obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate &amp; malicious against him, his doctrine, and kingdome, then these men that continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb facs="49"/>vaunted and bragged of his name, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises law, Church, and kingdome. After Christes giorious Ascention, by false Apost<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Sathan set forward againe his aunciēt practice, which although the great paine and diligence of the Apostles &amp; Apostolicall Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors in their time mightily suppressed: But when the Apostles and the Apostolical Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors were taken out of this life to rest with the Lorde, and that the faithfull workemen and diligent Pastors wared shant and thin in the Lordes vineyard, then did Sathan go forward very busily with this practice:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 2. <hi>Thes</hi> 1 <hi>Apoc.</hi> 13 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 9.</note> and by such as came sorth of the very bosom of the Church, speaking great thinges to the drawing of Disciples and followers after thē, vntil he had set his chiefe Preudēt, anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ &amp; vicar general in his sente, wherin hee in these sectaries stil pretendeth religion and godlinesse: but alwaies denyeth and detest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the substance thereof, this well appeareth in the sectaries of all ages: but especially af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the first seuen hundreth yeered, when the Monkish Locustes began to rise &amp; swarme out of the bothomles pit, &amp; to spreade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues into the worlde, as the Benedictes, Augustines, Donstinians, Cistrians, with an infinite number beades, some blacke, some white: and when the admiration of these be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to decay, then giueth the Deuill a fresh onset againe by a newe supplie of fryers, Chanons, Nunnes, Ancorettes, and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, a new band of other sectaries, which termed thēselues schoolemen &amp; Canonists, some Sententionaries, Some Thomistes,
<pb facs="50"/>some Scotistes, some Canonistes, some Summistes, some Penitenciaries, Angelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Doctors, some Cyraphicall, and some Sorbonistes: and euery of these for the most parte both of sundry orders and fraternites and of diuers opinions, and yet euery of these orders, fraternities, sentences, decrees, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces, holines, yea and their houses and garments, whether they were old or newe of more honour, estimation and credit, then their Christ, his death, his passiō, his merits, his in tercestions, his Gospell, or any thing vnto him any way belonging. And nowe last of all as the onely fray of his kingdome the Deuill hath transformed the former sec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries this ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e founde Hidra or sect of the Iesuites the very dragges of his bothomles pit, whose beginning, falshed and abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hipocryste diuers learned and godly men of our time as Chimnisius, Boquin and our owne countriemen Master Charke, Master Hammer and Master Filde haue both true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and effectually described.<note place="margin">Apoc. <hi>12.</hi> Apoc. <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> Apoc. <hi>18.</hi>
      </note> These (good reader) are guided by the three vncleane spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites that come out of the beastes mouth. These be sent into the vniuersall worlde as the last power and strength of Sathan to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre and bolde vp against Christ and his gospel the kingdome of Antichrist now euen falling downe. These the Pope sendeth into al Countries, but especially where the gospel is preached, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>reily to seduce the people to drawe younglings into their Seminaries, to moue &amp; frie rebellions, to practize the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of Godly Princes and zealous magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates
<pb facs="50"/>that their kingdome might againe become a pray vnto the Romish Antichrist, and so to be made doublely the children of hel fire, as they themselues be. These recapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulate into thē selues the whole substance of Popery, &amp; take vpon them the defence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of more impudently then any yet heretofore newe or olde. These in hipocry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e and al ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of dissēbling goe far beyond the Mōkes, Fryers, Nunnes, Chanons, or whatsoeuer dissembling broode hath beene heretofore. It may seeme that the Deuill in these mē hath shewed his whole skil of dissembling and the very depth of his crafte: for where in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer sectes he rent the Church by the names of men and with grosse rearmes and homely wordes, opposed mans inuentions againste Christ and his gospell, in these men he labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to plucke Christes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aheritaunce from him by the title of his owne name peculyar onely vnto himselfe, &amp; by furnishing againe the corruption of the scheolemē leauing their knowen and lothsome rearmes by a new shewe of wordes and termes of their own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention, that vnder them without suspicion they may deliuer againe the vile and filthie puddle of frinking Popery.</p>
   <p>These newe Messengers of his there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee Garnisheth with the N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne and title of Iesuites, pretending them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to be the true reformers of Christs church sent from God in these laster dayes. But (gentle reader) This <hi>Latet Anguis in Herba: <hi>This name or Title of theirs is ful of deceite &amp;</hi>
      </hi> perill:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Esay</hi> 8.9.</note> First in this title (Iesuite) they blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemously
<pb facs="51"/>rob Christ of his special &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuilar title and name, of his office, that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may nor can without great blasphemy,<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>1.</hi>
      </note> be geuen to none other, by reason of the sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of the same. And thou (sayth the Angell) shalt call his Name Iesus,<note place="margin">Phil. <hi>3.</hi>
      </note> because hee shall deliues his people from their sinnes, &amp; this name is aboue all names and geuen onely to the sonne of God, this is euer actiuely taken &amp; neuer pastiuely, it sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mfieth to saue and not to be saued by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. These blasphemous Iesuites there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as they can by no meane saue and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer men from sinne: so shall they neuer (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they repent from this blasphemy) be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from the bottomles pit of hell: but there with the Deuill and his Angels for their wie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked presumption shall they be euerlastingly damned.</p>
   <p>Secondly vnder the shewe of this name and title they most crastely and wickedly dissolue the vuity of Christs Church &amp; misti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call body, defacing the name and title of a christian, wherewith the holy ghost hath gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished and beautified the members of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as a name most conuenient for their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. This name and title (I say) as a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane thing and to base for their holynes and professiō: thus in the spring of the gospel did Sathan labour among the Corinthians to dissolue the vnitie from Christe, vnder the name of Paule, Apollo, and Cephas, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes as I saide throughly &amp; wickedly performed it vnder the names of Benedict, Frauncis, &amp;c. Their owne Gratian long
<pb facs="51"/>agoe thus said of the like. <hi>Negat Christian, qui se negat Christianum: <hi>He denieth Christ,</hi>
         <note place="margin">Causa 11. Quaesu. 5.</note>
         <hi>that denieth the name of a Christian.</hi>
      </hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thirdly, with the great hurt &amp; extreeme perill of all Christian Realmes, they dayly awayte to destroye by trayterous practizes, Godly Princes, and zealous Magistrats, by sturring vp sedition and rebellions emonge their subiectes, and oftentimes procure despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat persōs to attempt horrible murders vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Noble personages, and as King Iohn was poysoned by a besperat Monke, sundry Emperors by such their religious pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>izes: so in these daies sūdry great personages are put in great dāger by these holy persōs. The leagues of Gods Children, with the wicked, wherby the mightie helping hande of God hath continually beene turned euen from his owne deare children is no more daungerous vnto the Godly and Christian princes,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 18.19. 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 18.19.20.21.22.32. <hi>c</hi> 35. 1. <hi>Macha.</hi> 8.9.12.14.16. Examples the of are manie both newe an lamentable. <hi>Baruch. Timo.</hi> 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. Tertul. ad Scapulam.</note> then the accesse of this religious fraternitie or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly league and brotherhood vnto the presence of Kinges, Princes, or other noble mē is dā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous vnto our state and time. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of God led by his holy spirit taught vs to pray for Tyrauntes, yea for such as op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed and persecuted the Church of God, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming that in their peace and safetie the Church of God yet vnder the Crosse shoulde prosper. But these led by the vncleane spirit, prepare and suborne desperate persons to kill and murder Godly Princes and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates that be nurses and vnder God the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders of the Churche. Godly Princes therefore for the better safetie of themselues,
<pb facs="52"/>and subiectes may not deale herein as Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenna did, who when hee vnderstood, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers desperate persōs had s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>orne his death, fled, and left the siege to auoyde that daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: But they must followe the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God in the auoyding of their flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring promises and friendship, and depende vpon the inuicible power and arme of the Lorde that neuer faileth such as do trust one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto his helpe and defence, and vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy the dissembling kingedome of Popery seruing the members thereof,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 11.</note> as God gaue commaundement of Agag and the Amate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kites, of the Cananites: as Moses serued the false prophet Balaam with the Madianits:<note place="margin">Reg. <hi>18.</hi> Reg. <hi>9.</hi>
      </note> as Dauid serued the children of Ammō: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyas &amp; Iehu the false prophets and priestes of Baall,<note place="margin">ester.</note> and all the posteritie of Achab: as Mardocheus serued Ammon and his poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Finally as the Lord commaundeth the strumpet of Babilon to be serued:<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>poc. <hi>18.</hi>
      </note> So shall they with peace and safetie raigne to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God and comfort of his Church, which they can neuer possibly doe so long as these Antichristian members doe abuse their cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memcie and mercy as hetherto they to their great imboldening haue done. Therefore of them,
<q>
         <l>Olim quod Vulpes oegroto cauto Leoni.</l>
         <l>Respondet, referam, qua me vestigia terrent</l>
         <l>omnia te aduorsum spectantia nulla retrorsum.</l>
      </q>
      <hi>As the wilie Fox aunswered the sicke Lion. Well I say the steps of all men that trusteth thē, maketh me afraid, we see many noble persona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges destroyed by thē, from their holy Caue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth
<pb facs="52"/>none, in their felowship is nought but bloud and destruction.</hi> We still therefore crie with the holy Ghost, <hi>Tollite Vulpeculas, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliuntur enim vineam Domini: <hi>Out with the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Cubbs, for they destroy the Lordes vineyard.</hi>
      </hi>
   </p>
   <p>Fourthly (as it were an other Hyrostratus by burning Diana her Temple, or an other Curtius for a yeres pleasure with great pride and oftentation to leape desperatly into the Gulfe to win a vaine reporte or same emong the foolish people, or as it were an other des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate Monke newe returned from hell, shre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and houseled to poyson King Iohn (a most Noble and valiant Prince) to the end he might through so vile and wicked a fact be accoūted amōg the popes Canonized saints) doe these wicked and desperate Hipocrites attempt with losse both of body and soule to murther christiā princes &amp; godly magistrats to be Regestred in the Popes Martyrologe to haue Graines, Beades, Medalles, bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed &amp; plenary pardons giuen in their names. These Hypocrites herein follow the steps of the desperate Iewes that wickedly and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully cast away themselues to saue the tēple which God would destroy.<note place="margin">Iosephus de bello Iudeico</note> We may not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be deceiued with this desperate hipocrisie of theirs: For hereof we haue infinite exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples, as of the Circumcilians in S. Augus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines time, of Thomas Becket, Thomas More, Iohn Fisher, Fekton and such like,<note place="margin">Tertul. August.</note> whose desperate deathes may not commend them vnto vs for Martyres. For not the death but the cause maketh a Martyre.</p>
   <p>Last of all as these Iesuits the last brood
<pb facs="53"/>of Antichrist doe with like hipocrisie seeme to forme their speeches vnto the Phrases of the Scripture, and to vse the sentences of the holy scriptures to couer &amp; hide from the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the vgly and Monstrous face of fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy popery, that thereby they might with lesse suspition cure againe in the heartes of the people the deadly wounde of the beast, which otherwise to doe, the Diuell well seeth is vtterly impossible. Thus Alberius Pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hius, Eruius, Andradius, the late Courcell of Trident, and thus the late executed Iesuites attempted to perfourme: But among the residue Raph Sherwin, one of the foure exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted at Tiburne for treason on Friday the first of December playeth this pageant most guilefully to the deceauing of a greate num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber then and there present,<note place="margin">1581.</note> and purchased by his deepe &amp; desperate Hipocrisse a commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation aboue the rest, as though there had bin wrought in him before his death, some fast of Christ and true religion. But all was sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie &amp; an hipocriticall hipocrisse, to leade the people from the detestation of his popery to a liking or a more tollerable iudgement there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: If Raph Sherwin (good reader) had meat according to the good fourme of words by him then vttered, then woulde hee vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue cōdemned mans merites, inuocation of Saintes, with the residue of his popety to that point belonging, &amp; contrary to the persō of Christe and free iustificatiō by his death: This hee did not. But contrariwise (saieth he) I die a good Catholique, that is, to wit an arrogant and an obstinate papist. These last
<pb facs="53"/>wordes of his (gentle reader) namely I die a Catholique, doe well declare his meaning no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to agree with his good forme of words, by him first vttered. Therefore one Master Edward Fleetewood a godly learned Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, and I, thought good by conference with Some of his fellowes yet remaining in the Tower, to learne out by them his meaning in the good forme of wordes by him at his death vttred, therby either to sift out the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of their Iesuitical practize, or to giue oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation vnto his fellows by his worses to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and embrace the trueth, and hauing cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferēce with Iames Bosgraue, Iohn Hart, &amp; Henrie Orton, wee found their meaning in these good wordes vttered by Sherwin, to be nothing lesse then to attribate our whole iustification wholly and onely vnto Christ, as the good forme of his wordes did pretēd: but partly vnto Christe &amp; partly vnto them: selues, as in the discouery more plainely will appeare, which thing all papistes haue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore done. Sherwin therefore meant not, and the rest of the Iesuites intend not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract any thing from the grossenes of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, but guilefully and subrilly to vpholde the whole. The Lorde of his great mercy spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily treade downe Sathan vnder our feete for the better ouerthrowe of this wicked king dome, the full restoring of the beautie of Christes Church, and comfort of his deare Children, So be it.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>