<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND MOST NOBLE, ROBERT, EARLE OF CARNARVON, LORD DORMIR, BARON OF Wing, &amp;c. M. of the Hawke to his Maiesty.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114510_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68036</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10530</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114510</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND MOST NOBLE, ROBERT, EARLE OF CARNARVON, LORD DORMIR, BARON OF Wing, &amp;c. M. of the Hawke to his Maiesty.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Anti-duello. The anatomie of duells, with the symptomes thereof : A treatise wherein is learnedly handled, whether a Christian magistrate may lawfully grant a duell, for to end a difference which consisteth in fact. Also, the maner and forme of combats granted, with the seuerall orders obserued in the proceeding thereof, with the list of such duels, as haue beene performed before the Kings of England. Truly and compendiously collected and set forth by Mr. Iohn Despagne, for the good of soueraigne and subiect. Published by his Maiesties command</title>
                 <author>Espagne, Jean d'</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Fisher, Benjamin</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 63, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND MOST NOBLE,</hi> ROBERT, <hi>EARLE OF CARNARVON, LORD DORMIR, BARON OF Wing, &amp;c. M. of the Hawke to his Maiesty.</hi>
   </head>
   <head type="sub">
      <hi>As also, TO THE TRVELY, Worthy, Vertuous and Learned Gentlemen, M. Andrew Pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carne, Master Falconer to the King; M. Patrick Maulle, and Master James Leuiston, Esquires; Groomes of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties Bed-Chamber.</hi>
   </head>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Noble and truely Worthy,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>NDER whose protections could I more meritoriously commit this Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then to you, whose Noble hearts are so deeply stampt with the true marke of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted honor, that your faire Names in the front of this Booke, will bee to it a strong Buckler, as well as a singular Ornament; For it is not the eminency of your great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; that induceth me to this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication, but your admired good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and sweet affability, most rare, in this Iron age, but still in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent
<pb facs="3"/>
and abiding in your Illustri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blood. Vouchsafe then now, out of your noble disposition, and vsuall, fauour, to learning and good endeauours, to honor with a kind acceptance this poore oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; consecrated to your VVorth: For such courtesies from you, will make you liue againe and flourish in your graues, Laurell springing from your ashes; while the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainers of the Muses (which doe abound in this degenerated Age, and like VVormes in Libraries, seeme onely to liue to destroy, root out, and banish Learning) will lie witherd, neglected &amp; forgotten; Therefore as the Poet hath,
<q>
         <l>Let not our Worthy thinke, it is in vaine,</l>
         <l>They by this meanes eternall Names doe gaine,</l>
         <l>The Muses doe such Honour to them giue,</l>
         <l>That when they dye, their vertues most doe line:</l>
         <l>
            <pb facs="4"/>
But the enemies of learning, when they die,</l>
         <l>As in obliuion shut forgottenlie.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>VVere it not for the Muses, our Names and Liues should at one time depart; and when faire Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues worthy louers dye, then doe their memories suruiue eternally;
<q>
         <l>Our guilded Monuments doe soone decaye,</l>
         <l>But Fame thus sounded shall endure for aye,</l>
         <l>Muses embalme our names with sweet perfume,</l>
         <l>Times Odor, which no time can e're consume.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Accept then (most Noble and Worthy) of this small scantling of the Muses seruices, by this Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, as courteously, as officiou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sly it is humbly Dedicated and Consecrated vpon the Altar of your Diuine Vertues.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>