<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHORS PROHEME.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114608_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68585</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19815</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114608</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHORS PROHEME.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A dialogue of dying wel. First written in the Italian tongue, by the reuerend father Don Peeter of Luca, a chanon regular, a Doctor of Diuinitie and famous preacher. VVherin is also contayned sundry profitable resolutions, vpon some doubtful questions in diuinitie. Translated first into French, and novv into English</title>
                 <author>Pietro da Lucca</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Conincx, Arnout</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 50, 1 leave, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="proem">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE AVTHORS PROHEME.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>CCORDING</hi> to the iudgemēt of Aristotle, man of all mortal creatures is moste prudent, for that hee alone foreseeith thinges to come, and therefore differeth from the brute beast, which regardeth only thinges that bee present.</p>
   <p>Man therefore seeing hee must dy, is by his natural wisdome enclyned to foresee his death, the cogitation wherof is vnto him a thing more terrible, then any other thing els what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer, and it much more doth importe him.</p>
   <p>He therefore that desyreth to walk wisely in this miserable lyfe, must in such sorte pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare and dispose himself for dreadful death, that when it approcheth neere vnto him, hee be not taken vnprouyded, and that for want of
<pb facs="5"/>
due consideration he lose not the chief felicitie, and besydes that be assigned for euer vnto the paines of hel. VVherefore beeing desirous to begin this discourse of the arte or science to dy wel: for an introduction thereunto I presuppose suche an imagined nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration as heer ensueth.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>