<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>B., John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114789_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04261</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1438</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114789</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>B., John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Hierons last fare-vvell : A sermon preached at Modbury in Devon, at the funerall of that reuerend and faithfull seruant of Iesus Christ, Master Samuel Hieron, sometimes Preacher there. By I. B</title>
                 <author>Barlow, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butler, William 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 33, iv, 39-79 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>EADER,</hi> This report hath beene published: that the abundance of Sermons (by some, and of some) preached, and printed, haue brought both the Word of God, and his Ordinance to be contemned; either, through the insuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency of the Authors, or, the corruption of Readers, and Auditors. For when the Word is not diuided aright, men of the best apprehension will not, cannot, giue approbation. And on the other hand, such as cannot discerne betwixt good and euill, sit at home, with a printed paper, dreaming that will suffice to get faith for saluation: and so absent themselues from the more powerfull meanes in the publike Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Dost thou expect my reply? Shall I take in hand to giue thee satisfaction? No: for if I can but cleere my selfe from being the iust cause of the one (the which (likely) will be hard) Let him that list, and can better iudge, resolue the other. Now if it be demanded of thee, that knew vs both; why by me, for him, (whose shoo-latchet, I was not worthy to vnloose) this Sermon was first preached; then printed: take one answere for all: which is, that a kinde of necessity was the cause, both of the one, and the other. If thou iudge this darke: Consider, that God doth not alwayes render (and why may not man then sometimes conceale?) a reason of his proceedings. For the worke it selfe, what shall I say? but as <hi>Naomi</hi> to her Daughters at their departure: It grieueth me much for your sakes, that I could conceiue no better: yet
<pb facs="5"/>
as <hi>Peter</hi> said to the Cripple, such as I haue, such haue I gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. I deny not but thou maist finde words, phrase, matter, and method, that may not content thee: what then? why, try all and keepe that which is good, for he that offends not in tongue, is a perfect man: but where is he?</p>
   <p>In my opinion I haue seene this euill vnder the Sunne: Men in hearing, and reading, if they dislike any thing ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in speech, or person, like little children, that haue many things in their hands they like well, yet if their Parents doe but either adde or detract one, contrary to their minds, throw all away in displeasure. Wherefore let me learne thee this lesson, Get a sound mind, that thou maist be able to iudge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the person, and his speech, doctrine, and doctrine. For it is the perfection of a man in his calling, to know the worth of a commodity, though set to sale by the poorest per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son; and the basenesse of that which is bad, though proffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and proclaimed for good, by the hands of Princes: so is it for a Christian to discerne the true Word, from the false, whether it come from him that weareth the coursest rags, or Kinglyest rayment. This is to iudge righteous Iudgement. Furthermore, for doctrine, some may be Corne, other Chaffe; therefore thou art to separate the precious from the vile, by the fan of thy vnderstanding, and hauing winnowed it well, treasure it vp as good graine in the Garner of thy Memory. This is to haue a mans wit rightly exercised, when in the multiplicity of opinions, Truth is elected, error reiected. And thus wishing thee no worse, then willingly I would receiue from thee my selfe, I cease and rest:</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>The same thou takest me for toward God, and thy selfe: in truth (I hope) though not in measure. Io. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>