<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Prologue, or Authors Epistle, to his Ladie, a louer of vertue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S114638_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09553</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19832</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S114638</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Prologue, or Authors Epistle, to his Ladie, a louer of vertue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The philosopher of the court, written by Philbert of Vienne in Champaigne, and Englished by George North, gentlema [n]</title>
                 <author>Philibert, de Vienne</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harrison, Luke (Lucas).</publisher>
                            <publisher>Woodcock, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 114, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Book industry, catalogues and inventories</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Prologue, or Authors Epistle, to his Ladie, a louer of vertue.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall now see moste noble La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, whither the doubtfull opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that you haue long tyme had of mee: which I haue ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beene hythertoo able by reasons or excuse to remooue, may by the troth it selfe make you of a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry iudgement. For it is not once, twice, or thrice that you haue reproued mee, to bee a promiser, a deceyuer, and such a one as ye perceyued (as you tolde mee your selfe) to bee worthy of lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no credit at all: Notwithstanding that in all my promises, or any other wayes withoute promise, wherein my humble seruice might be most agreable and best liked of you, I haue not fayled, either in desire, or execution. But this is none other than the naturall disposition of you Gentlewomen, still to pick suche quarels: when (according to your good custome) you desyre any thing, bee it neuer so wayghtie, weake, or daungerouse: your longing for the same is so greate, that without consideration, of the opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitye, the easinesse, or the possibilitie, you
<pb facs="5"/>
thinke on nothing else, but on the necessitie to haue it done. And if the ende succeede not as you wishe, you lay the faulte vpon your ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes, whome afterwardes you call lyars and promisers. Yet whatsoeuer I say, though it bee reported to bee a common faulte in women, I will not mainteyne the same to bee in you: For knowing your noble minde aboue others, set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in so loftie a seate, as seeing and vewing a farre off the small faultes, errours, and abuses, wherin their Ignorance may bee wrapped: your wisedome I nothing doubt, is able well ynough to auoyde it: beeing exempted from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon sorte, and contrarie too suche waywarde conditions. I will then perswade my felfe, that suche reproche (if it may so bee called) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from a good minde, and of good will, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng sure that you knowe mee otherwise to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes you. And therefore by the waye haue sayd it, rather to aduertise me, thā that I should seeme suche to you, or you account so of mee, but rather bycause I should become such a one, euen as it often fareth with those, that being in feare, commonly complayne before they feele any greefe. Yet can I not content my selfe with this perswasion, seeing that my affection see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes not to bee so entier lie knowen vnto you, while ye make so little accompt of it. Therfore
<pb facs="5"/>
to gyue you better testimonie of that you are so doubtfull to beleeue, and to the end that by this argument, you maye hope for better assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance hereafter, of that whiche (it may be) yee suspect. For (I desire rather to satisfie you, than my selfe, thoughe I haue iuster cause too sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect you, than you mee) after my departure from <hi>Paris,</hi> expelling and chasing from mee sundrie fantasies, by the absent remembrance of your so good a will, whiche ordinarie presence woulde not suffer: I enterprised this trauell, to write this little treatise vnto you, packing vp in this so small a volume, the delightfull instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Philosophie,</hi> and manner how to lyue: in the which we passed this melancholike tyme of winter, where, and in what cōpanie you knowe: mingling our other cōmon pastimes, with this Noble discourse. I am not ignorāt of the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uētnesse of your desire, to vnderstand the troth in all things: for when as somtimes beeing with you, betweene our selues, I would assaye to be come a good Orator: you by importunate meane, haue cōstrained me to become a Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sopher.<note place="margin">Yong yeares meetest for the studie of Philosophie.</note> And I pray you who are meeter to <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophie:</hi> that is to searche the knowledge of God, &amp; of man, to know who we are, where we are, wherefore wee are, and howe wee shoulde gouerne and guyde oure lyues one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="6"/>
than oure yonger people? VVho by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of greene yeares and small experience, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing not yet their iudgementes certaine or set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, but wild and rash, and till the scum &amp; filth of youthfull heate bee boyled oute of them, are but little profitable to the cōmon wealthe. O what a laudable custome were it, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious to any coūtrie, if the administration of common wealth, were not committed and put on suche as are yong, rude, and of no experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: and that such in no wise shoulde gouerne or giue counsell, till they were throughly tried and approued. Then the people should not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure so muche daunger, and they in applying some payne to discretion, should in the ende, be most profitable to themselues: For it would be a great contentment to their life (after experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence had) and specially, their olde age would not be so melancholy, angrie, impacient, and waywarde, in digesting all things euill. For<note place="margin">Experience n akes age <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>asie.</note> what made <hi>Cato</hi> the elder, as <hi>Cicero</hi> in his booke <hi>de Senectute,</hi> sayth, to beare his yeares so paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, too bee so pleasant. and well disposed an olde man, and (which is more marueylous) to bee ioyfull and merie in yong and youthfull companie, but the great knowledge, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience he had in all things? I feele my selfe to stray from my first intent, and by little and little
<pb facs="6"/>
to fall from my purpose: It is then requisite for youth, to vse and acquaint themselues to a soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie and contemplate life, not as Hermites in the wildernesse, or lyke Monkes in the Cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters: but suche a sure and diligent meane, as they may bee capable, to informe, and instruct themselues in time to all good things: So that when the spirite is thus framed and taught, and the furious flame of youth put out: they may the sooner and better exercise the life actiue, and then take vpon them, to trauell for the common wealth of their Countrey. If my head and bearde were somewhat gray in siluer shewe answerable to this cause, I woulde make an inuectiue, and declame agaynst this foolishe, brutish, and vnbridled youth, which delightes not but in vnprofitable matters, and voyde of reason, neuer regarding nor following other guyde than Carelesnesse, accounting it shame, and reproch to be seene or thought to doe any thing for good purpose. And (if you will noble Ladie, pardon me priuately to reproue you) I cannot wonder ynough to see, that among you worthie Damsels, being (as you are) the iudges,<note place="margin">Ladies are the patrons and preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of the priuiledges of youth.</note> patrones and preseruers of the priuiledges of youth: howe you can commonly approue and allow those vnprofitable actions, in doltes and beasts of no courage, somtime proceeding of an
<pb facs="7"/>
euill nature: and yet they haue such place with you, that being in your Court men lawded and glorious flatterers, you reioyce with them, and equally fauour them, as pleasant and worthie seruaunts. It woulde very well become (as it seemeth vnto me) yong men, to employ this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, and pleasant time of youthfull yeares, in the knowledge of vertue, and in other commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable exercises of the bodie, as wrestling, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is shewed both valure &amp; vertue: To the end that being so experimented, feeling their owne strength, and comming too mans state, they neede not any longer to learne how they ought to liue. For so soone as a man commes either to serue the common wealth, or to haue care of his housholde: he should no more be a scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, but rather an instructer. VVho if he will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter breake his braynes about <hi>Philosophie,</hi> neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting his charge, and regarding not his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, <hi>Plato</hi> willes, he shoulde bee turned to play with nuttes among boyes, and whipped wyth roddes among children. And for this purpose, I desire you noble Damsell, to reade one peece in <hi>Plato</hi> of <hi>Gorgias,</hi> beginning with this sentēce (for there he teacheth, why, howe, where, and when <hi>Philosophie</hi> is to be vsed,) <hi>Philosophie</hi> sayth he, is an excellent thing and very seemely, so that it be vsed moderately, soberly, and in due
<pb facs="7"/>
time of yeares: wherein if any plunge themsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues too deepe, it destroyeth them vtterly. It may seeme by this, that <hi>Plato</hi> reproues indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, the perfit knowledge of <hi>Philosophie:</hi> yet truly he neither despiseth nor disprayseth it, but so far as it is vnprofitable and hindreth vs from our other needfull affayres. For since that all sciences were inuented for the helpe of man, and as much for the conseruation of the Soule, the bodie and goodes, as consequently to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne a societie, companie, and felowship a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men: To what purpose then, doe anye breake their braynes in their studies, if it be not for profite to themselues, or benefite to some others? Considering therefore that you haue your witte at libertie, rouing at will, and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding your pleasant steppes at randon, where best liketh your youthful yeres to carrie you (though it somewhat yeldeth to naturall affection) fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low I pray you your first intent, and there shall want no good will in me, seeing I prepare my self to matters of greater importance than this, and other matters also, but that your desire shall be satisfied. Yet I knowe that this worde <hi>Philosophie</hi> doeth sounde so hatefull in the eares of manye, thoughe some false and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll opinion they haue of <hi>Philosophie</hi> too them vnknowne: that they will thinke it
<pb facs="8"/>
straunge and absurde to peruert or mar (for so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hey terme it) so excellent a perfection of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ure, as is in you, with so melancholike opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ns. Therefore this I will say: seeing they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>her know nor hate Philosophie, but onely for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he name, let vs leaue the worde, and speake no more of it: but let vs say, that you do learne howe to lyue in the worlde: which all persons do couet too knowe, and yet too liue in the worlde is no other thing than the same which we call or tearme Philosophie, as we wil proue hereafter, wherein, it would greeue mee, (fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing my purpose) if you and I, shoulde so much vse our iudgements, and with such hote affection, that wee forget to knowe our selues, and so make vs mockeries and laughingstockes to the worlde. I thinke it not good to haue my house of a tunne as <hi>Diogenes</hi> had: nor to scratch out my eyes as <hi>Democritus</hi> did: or die for hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger as hee that had his <hi>Malissa,</hi> the better too know and vnderstand Philosophie. But I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and prayse him, who making good ohere, louing good wine, and seeking good felowship, can by the waye contemplate and marke the maner and liuing of euery one: and consider of those that do both good and euill, the vantage of either. In thus vsing the mother of all Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,<note place="margin">Philosophie the mother of Sciences.</note> she will neuer make any heauie nor an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie
<pb facs="8"/>
or as (some report) by inordinate study ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholie: but she may drawe them from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and sundry follies, that smell more brutishe than manlie. And if any will say that withoute this, euery man may liue: I dare affirme, that he is so farre from reason, as his opinion deserues no answere. As for the pleasure, desire, and cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment that comes of it, thus muche may be sayde: that if in the morning, when you attire your selfe amōg your maidens, the cleere chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stall, and good looking glasse, delightes you, in shewing the perfit Image of your outward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion: how much more shoulde you reioyce to beholde and see your selfe in this Science, to knowe what is your life, what it ought too bee, what you are, and what is the substance of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie thing? Heereby you shall learne, howe the wyfe ought too gouerne and behaue hir selfe, with hir husbande: it sheweth howe you shall well instruct and guyde your householde: your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ittle priuate common wealth shall be so neate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd polished, as nothing better: you shall know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>owe to vse your selfe towarde straungers: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ou may bee assured by this, without reproofe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o do any thing freelie, for infamie and slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er shall no way torment you. VVhat woulde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ou wishe or desire more? On the contrarie, withoute this knowledge, you remaine in su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spence
<pb facs="9"/>
and doubt, like too a traueler beeing in the open fielde and pressed on his iourney, not knowing his way: you haue no other guide, than that blinde beast of common and popular iudgement, who (as ignorant and vnexpert in all things) sayeth and doth one while one thing and an other while an other. For what is more inconstant than Ignorance? Thus being bound to this foolishe, variable, and common opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and hauing no other reason or councell, but to followe others: you shall soone vnderstand in what miseries and care you liue. Knowing therfore your so good affection, and to the end to deliuer you out of his prison and miserable darkenesse of Ignorance, I haue written to you this little treatise, altogither rude and impoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, as a w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nderer through the countrie: In the which you shall breefely see the summe of that I euer thought in Philosophy: wherin the auncient &amp; Sages past reposed their soueraine bountie: Then howe it is in these dayes disgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and masked, grounded onely on mans opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and not on Nature: And last, you shall amply finde (yet not so much as I gladly would) what I thinke of this newe <hi>Philosophie,</hi> which is the order and manner of liuing in these dayes▪ In writing whereof I haue played <hi>Democrates,</hi> &amp; applyed the whole too a pleasant conclusion.
<pb facs="9"/>
Therefore when you vnderstande the one and the other, you will vse it (I know) so discretely, that it shall not let you frō your necessarie cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, of more importance. And if in the discourse of the booke, I speak more vnciuilly and boldly than is meete or conuenient to your excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: It may please you payse those woordes and sentences, in the balance apte and conuenient to the matter heere treated, whiche hath ofte &amp; in many places made me forget the sweete and gentle style that ye might desire. To conclude, I humbly request you to receyue this my little labour, as the frute of your owne possession &amp; inheritance: wherby I shall seeme to haue gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned great profit, if it please you to preserue it &amp; close it in the coffer of your gracious fauour: wherewith I haue nothing too wishe or desire, but the immortalitie of the same.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>