<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>VNTO THEM WHICH WOVLD know the trueth.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115012_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B13519</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10715</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115012</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>VNTO THEM WHICH WOVLD know the trueth.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second report of Doctor Iohn Faustus, containing his appearances, and the deedes of Wagner. VVritten by an English gentleman student in VVittenberg an Vniuersity of Germany in Saxony. Published for the delight of all those which desire nouelties by a frend of the same gentleman</title>
                 <author>English gentleman student</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jeffes, Abel</publisher>
                    <distributor>Burby, Cuthbert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>76 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>VNTO THEM WHICH WOVLD know the trueth.</head>
   <div n="1" type="part">
      <head>I</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is plaine that many thinges in the first book are meere lies, for proofe marke this: it is saide that it is translated, so it is, and where it is word for word: But I haue talked with the man that first wrote them, hauing them from <hi>Wagners</hi> very friend, wherein he saith manie thinges are corrupted, some added <hi>de nouo,</hi> some canceld and taken awaie, and many were augmented. As for addition to the Coppy is there where <hi>Mephostophiles</hi> disputeth of the numbers of Hels, and some other disputations: And let a man marke them duely, they shall finde them I will not saie childish, but certainly superficiall, not like the talk of Diuels, where with foldings of words they doe vse to dilate at large, and more subtell by farre. But as for his Obligation and the most part, it is certaine they are most credible and out of all question.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="2" type="part">
      <head>II</head>
      <p>For to take away a doubt, whether there were such a man, which is generally a thing not beleeued, <hi>I</hi> assure them this, that there was, and it is prooued thus, nor is <hi>Germany</hi> so vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen but that the trueth of these thinges following may be founde if any suspect.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="3" type="part">
      <head>III</head>
      <p>First there is yet remaining the ruins of his house, not farre from <hi>Melanchtons</hi> house as they call at the townes end of <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenberg,</hi> right opposite to the Schooles.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="4" type="part">
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <head>IIII</head>
      <p>Secondly there is yet to be seene his tree, a great hollowe Truncke, wherein he vsed to reade <hi>Nigromancy</hi> to his schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, not farre from the towne in a very remote place, which I thinke is sufficient testimony to any reasonable eare. And enquire of them which haue beene there, see if they will not affirme it. Notwithstanding I doe not goe by these meanes I, to entreate men to beleeue, for <hi>I</hi> care not whether they do or no, but onely to certifie you of the trueth as I my selfe would bee.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="5" type="part">
      <head>V</head>
      <p>Next, his tombe is at <hi>Mars</hi> Temple, a three miles beyond the Citty, vppon which is written on a Marble stone by his owne hand, this Epitaph, which is somewhat old by reason of his small skill in grauing.</p>
      <q>
         <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
            <body>
               <div type="epitaph">
                  <p>Hic iaceo Iohannes Faustus, Doctor diuini iuris in dignissimus, qui pro amore magiae Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolicae scientiae vanissimè cecidi ab amore Dei: O Lector pro me miserrimo damnato homine ne preceris, nam preces non iuuant quem De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us condemnauit: O pie Christiane memento mei, &amp; saltem vnam pro infiducia mealachry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulam exprime, &amp; cui non potes mederi, eius miserere, et ipse caue.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </floatingText>
      </q>
      <p>The Stone was found in his study, and his wil was fulfilled, and he lieth betwixt a heap of three and thirty fir trees in the fort of the Hill in a great hole where this is erected.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="6" type="part">
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <head>VI</head>
      <p>If these will not serue, then shall you heare the testimonie of a learned man <hi>Iohn Wierus, cap.</hi> 4. <hi>libro</hi> 1. <hi>de magis infamibus.</hi> Which I haue translated.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>Iohn Faustus</hi> borne at <hi>Kundling</hi> a little village, learning Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke at <hi>Graconia,</hi> where he was openly taught, and exercised it.</p>
      <p>In sundry places of <hi>Germany,</hi> with the admiration of many and with manifold lies, fraud, and illusions, with vaine vaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and promises but could doe nothing: one example I wil shew to the Reader, vppon this condition, that he will passe his faith first to me that he will not imitate him: Then reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth he one of his knaueries, how he tooke vpon him to make no haire grow vppon a mans face, and tooke away with a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which <hi>I</hi> will not name, both the beard that he had and all the skinne, causing such inflāmations in his face that it burned all ouer cruelly. This he committed being taken at <hi>Batoburg</hi> vppon the banke of the riuer <hi>Mosa</hi> hard vppon the boundes of <hi>Gelderland:</hi> Another (saith this learned Phisition) not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen to me, hauing a blacke bearde, the rest of his face somewhat darke and swarte, witnessing melancholy (for hee was splenaticke) when he came to <hi>Faustus,</hi> who redily saide: Truely I thought you had beene my Familiar, straight waie marking your feete, whether long and crooked nailes stook out of them: So likening this man to the Diuell, which hee thought had come vnto him, which Diuell he was wont to cal <hi>Sorarius.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="7" type="part">
      <head>VI</head>
      <p>For his death in the same place, thus saith he: At length hee was found in a Village of the <hi>Dutchy</hi> of <hi>Wittenberg</hi> by his bed side starke dead, and his face turnde backewards, and the midnight before, the house was shaken as it is reported. Thus farre he, an Authour not to bee doubted of, and approoued through Christendome of singular and exact iudgement, as appeareth by his writings of the like argument confutation.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="8" type="part">
      <head>VII</head>
      <p>More in the same place he saith: That a schoolemaister a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
<pb facs="4"/> the <hi>Goslaryens,</hi> instructed of <hi>Faustus</hi> the Magitian, or rather <hi>Infaustus</hi> his euill doctrine, learned a way how the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell might be bound by spell on a glasse, who as you may ther reade was so affrighted, that lying one whole yeare speeches, at thend he spake of his feare and diuels appearance, and then hauing receiued his christian rites died.</p>
      <p>As for the Author this Doctor <hi>Wier,</hi> doubt you not of his credite, for he is alledged of the very singularest schollers, as the best that euer wrote in that argument. We haue a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of our owne countrey, maister <hi>Reignold Scot</hi> Esquier, that doth vniuersally quote him as his chiefe and especiall helpe in his discouery of Witchcraft, yea and hee testifieth of him not without good desart, saying: I. Bode in his lawyerly Phisicke reasoneth contrarily, as though Melancholye were farthest of from these old women whom we call Witches. And the most famous and noble Phisician <hi>Iohn Wier</hi> for his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in that behalfe: Loe where he calleth him the most famous Phisitian as he was then certainly, in the discouery of Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, lib. 3. Cap. 7.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="9" type="part">
      <head>IX</head>
      <p>Thus farre I haue sette downe that you may knowe and perswade your selues so farre as you see iust cause by the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons.</p>
      <closer>
         <salute>Vale.</salute>
      </closer>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>