<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PROPOSITION OF the whole Worke.</title>
           <author>Bedford, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115474_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10260</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20544</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115474</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PROPOSITION OF the whole Worke.</title>
                 <author>Bedford, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A feast for vvormes : Set forth in a poeme of the history of Ionah. By Fra. Quarles</title>
                 <author>Quarles, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Moore (More), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>108 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="proposition">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE PROPOSITION OF the whole Worke.</head>
   <l>'TIs not the Record of Great <hi>HECTORS</hi> Glory,</l>
   <l>Whose matchlesse <hi>Valour</hi> makes the <hi>World</hi> a Story;</l>
   <l>Nor yet the swelling of that <hi>Romans</hi> Name,</l>
   <l>That onely <hi>Came,</hi> and <hi>Look'd,</hi> and <hi>Ouercame</hi>;</l>
   <l>Nor <hi>One,</hi> nor <hi>All</hi> of those braue <hi>Worthies</hi> Nine,</l>
   <l>(Whose Might was Great, and Acts almost Diuine,</l>
   <l>That liu'd like <hi>Gods,</hi> but di' de like <hi>Men,</hi> and gone)</l>
   <l>Shall giue my <hi>Pen</hi> a Taske to treat vpon:</l>
   <l>I sing the praises of the <hi>KING</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Out of whose <hi>mouth,</hi> a <hi>two-edg'd Smiter</hi> springs,</l>
   <l>Whose <hi>Words</hi> are <hi>Mystery,</hi> whose <hi>Works</hi> are <hi>Wonder,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Whose <hi>Eyes</hi> are <hi>Lightning,</hi> and whose <hi>Voyce</hi> is <hi>Thunder,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Who like a <hi>Curtaine</hi> spreads the <hi>Heauens</hi> out,</l>
   <l>Spangl'd with <hi>Starres,</hi> in Glory round about:</l>
   <l>'Tis <hi>HEE</hi> that cleft the furious waues in twaine,</l>
   <l>Making a <hi>High-way passage</hi> through the <hi>Maine</hi>:</l>
   <l>'Tis <hi>He</hi> that turn'd the waters into <hi>Blood,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>And smote the <hi>Rocky stone,</hi> and caus'd a <hi>Flood:</hi>
   </l>
   <l>'Tis <hi>HEE,</hi> that's iustly Armed in his <hi>Ire,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Behind with <hi>Plagues,</hi> before with <hi>flaming Fire</hi>:</l>
   <l>More bright then mid-day <hi>Phoebus,</hi> are his <hi>Eyes,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>And whosoeuer sees his <hi>Visage, Dyes.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>I sing the Praises of <hi>Great Iudah's Lion,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>The fragrant <hi>Flowre</hi> of <hi>Iesse,</hi> the <hi>Lambe</hi> of <hi>Sion,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Whose <hi>Head</hi> is whiter then the driuen <hi>Snow,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Whose <hi>Visage</hi> doth like flames of <hi>Fire</hi> Glow:</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="5"/>His <hi>Loynes</hi> begirt with Golden <hi>Belt,</hi> His <hi>Eyne</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Like <hi>Titan,</hi> riding in his Southerne <hi>Shine,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>His <hi>Feet</hi> like burning <hi>Brasse,</hi> and as the noyse</l>
   <l>Of surgie <hi>Neptunes</hi> roaring, is his <hi>Voyce.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>This is that <hi>Paschall Lambe,</hi> whose dearest <hi>Blood</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Is soueraigne <hi>Drinke,</hi> whose <hi>Flesh</hi> is sauing <hi>Food</hi>:</l>
   <l>His precious <hi>Blood,</hi> the Worthies of the <hi>Earth</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Did drinke, which (though but borne of <hi>Mortall</hi> birth)</l>
   <l>Returnd them <hi>Deities</hi>: For who drinkes <hi>THIS,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Shall be receiu'd into <hi>Eternall Blisse</hi>:</l>
   <l>Himselfe the <hi>GIFT,</hi> which <hi>HE</hi> himselfe did giue,</l>
   <l>His <hi>Stripes</hi> heale vs, and by <hi>HIS Death</hi> we liue:</l>
   <l>
      <hi>HEE</hi> acting <hi>GOD</hi> and <hi>MAN</hi> in double Nature,</l>
   <l>Did reconcile <hi>Mankind,</hi> and <hi>Mans Creator.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>I, heer's a <hi>TASKE</hi> indeed; if <hi>Mortals</hi> could</l>
   <l>Not make a Verse, yet <hi>Rocks</hi> and <hi>Mountaines</hi> would:</l>
   <l>The <hi>Hils</hi> shall daunce, the <hi>Sunne</hi> shall stop his Course,</l>
   <l>Hearing the <hi>subiect</hi> of this <hi>high</hi> Discourse:</l>
   <l>The <hi>Horse,</hi> and <hi>Gryphin</hi> shall together <hi>sleepe,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>The <hi>Woolfe</hi> shall fawne vpon the silly <hi>Sheepe,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>The Crafty <hi>Serpent,</hi> and the Fearfull <hi>Hart</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Shall ioyne in <hi>Consort,</hi> and each beare a <hi>part,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>And leape for <hi>Ioy,</hi> when my <hi>VRANIA</hi> sings,</l>
   <l>
      <hi>She</hi> sings the praises of the <hi>KING</hi> of <hi>Kings.</hi>
   </l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>