<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115329_Fr1_9</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68615</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20490</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115329</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The mirrour which flatters not : Dedicated to their Maiesties of Great Britaine, by Le Sieur de la Serre, historiographer of France. Enriched with faire figures. Transcrib'd English from the French, by T.C. And devoted to the well-disposed readers</title>
                 <author>Puget de La Serre, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, Elizabeth</publisher>
                    <distributor>Thrale, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 48, 45-59, 1, 71-228, 18 pages, illustrations (metal cuts), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <head>To the READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may, perhaps, seeme <hi>strange,</hi> that I treat so often in my <hi>Works</hi> of the same <hi>matter,</hi> as of the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> and <hi>meditations</hi> of <hi>Death:</hi> But if the importance of the <hi>sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> be considered, and the <hi>profit</hi> to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived thence, a <hi>Man</hi> will never be <hi>wearie</hi> of seeing such <hi>faire truths</hi> under <hi>different presentations.</hi> Besides, the <hi>conceptions</hi> of <hi>spirit</hi> upon the same <hi>matter,</hi> are like the <hi>productions</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> in the <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies's</hi> of <hi>Tulips:</hi> Every <hi>yeere</hi> shee gives a <hi>Change,</hi> both to their <hi>Colour,</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray.</hi> And though they be still <hi>Tulips,</hi> shee <hi>renders</hi> them so <hi>different</hi> from their
<pb facs="13"/>first <hi>resemblance,</hi> that they can <hi>hardly</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise be <hi>knowne,</hi> but by <hi>name.</hi> The <hi>Mind</hi> doe's the same, upon the same <hi>sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject;</hi> its <hi>Fancies,</hi> which are its <hi>ornature,</hi> and <hi>embellishment,</hi> render it by their <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versitie</hi> so <hi>different</hi> from it <hi>selfe,</hi> that 'tis hardly <hi>knowne,</hi> but by the <hi>Titles,</hi> which it <hi>beares,</hi> to particularize each <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit.</hi> So that if <hi>once againe</hi> I <hi>represent</hi> unto thee the <hi>pourtrait</hi> of <hi>Vanitie,</hi> and the <hi>Image</hi> of <hi>Death;</hi> my <hi>spirit,</hi> which hath <hi>steaded</hi> me for <hi>Pencill,</hi> and <hi>colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> in this <hi>Worke,</hi> hath rendred it so <hi>rare</hi> in its <hi>Noveltie,</hi> and so <hi>excellent</hi> in <hi>difference</hi> from those which have <hi>prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> that thou shalt finde nothing in <hi>it</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune with <hi>them,</hi> but my <hi>name.</hi> Thou mavest <hi>consider</hi> moreover, that I dedicate <hi>Bookes</hi> to <hi>KINGS</hi> and <hi>QUEENES</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ot every <hi>day,</hi> and that these <hi>objects</hi> of such <hi>eminent magnificence</hi> doe so <hi>nobly</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the <hi>faculties</hi> of my <hi>Soule,</hi> that I
<pb facs="13"/>could not have <hi>pettie thoughts</hi> for such <hi>high Personages.</hi> 'Tis that, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>ostentation,</hi> makes me <hi>beleeve,</hi> that if thou <hi>buy</hi> once againe this <hi>Booke,</hi> and tak'st the paines to <hi>reade</hi> it, thou wilt <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greet</hi> neither the <hi>Time,</hi> nor <hi>Money,</hi> which thou shalt <hi>employ</hi> therein. <hi>ADIEU.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If thou bee'st of so good an humour, to pardon the Faults, excuse those of the Impres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>