<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To Mr. Robert Norton, and his Practise of Artillery.</title>
           <author>Butler, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115254_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08347</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18673</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115254</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To Mr. Robert Norton, and his Practise of Artillery.</title>
                 <author>Butler, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The gunner : shevving the vvhole practise of artillerie: vvith all the appurtenances therevnto belonging. Together with the making of extra-ordinary artificiall fireworkes, as well for pleasure and triumphes, as for warre and seruice. VVritten by Robert Norton, one of his Maiesties gunners and enginiers</title>
                 <author>Norton, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Robinson, Humphrey</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 100, 99-158, 4 pages, 27, 2 leaves of plates (25 folded), illustrations (woodcuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                    <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To Mr.</hi> Robert Norton, <hi>and his</hi> Practise of Artillery.</head>
   <l>VVHen first I knew the difference of Time, and seuerall <hi>Climates</hi> of the Worlds round Globe,</l>
   <l>I then thought <hi>Artists</hi> fittest Men to clime to Honor, and to weare the Golden Roabe;</l>
   <l>But now these Times doe differ from that Time,</l>
   <l>Strangers respected are By Courtiers crime.</l>
   <l>Then when I knew the Seas, my whole delight was how to trimme a Shippe prepar'd for Warre;</l>
   <l>But all was vaine, till <hi>Gunners</hi> Skill and Might, with practiz'd Forces all excells so farre;</l>
   <l>Let <hi>Sea-men, Land-men,</hi> all <hi>Men</hi> truly know</l>
   <l>That <hi>Gunners</hi> Art's of Substance, not of Show.</l>
   <l>The <hi>Land-man,</hi> he most boldly makes Approach with Horse and Foote, with Sword, and Shield, and Speare,</l>
   <l>But all were vayne, he neuer could encroach, if <hi>Gunnes</hi> and <hi>Gunners</hi> should be wanting there;</l>
   <l>Therefore such Artists sure t'were best to cherish,</l>
   <l>And expert <hi>Gunnered Engeneers</hi> to nourish.</l>
   <l>For proofe whereof, let euery Artist view, why such Men should not to preferment mount,</l>
   <l>Peruse this Booke, its Lynes, and Fgures true, so may he finde the difference of Account</l>
   <l>Twixt th'<hi>English,</hi> and the <hi>Dutch, Norton,</hi> and <hi>Borre,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Then giue our owne their due without demor.<note place="margin">Moratur in lege.</note>
   </l>
   <l>But <hi>Norton,</hi> I haue been something to bold to Paraphrase vpon thy Worth and Quality,</l>
   <l>Because I want sufficient, to vnfold them, and th'Ingenious Workes reality;</l>
   <l>Let this suffice, thy praise will shew it selfe,</l>
   <l>It's worth the <hi>Golden-Fleece,</hi> the <hi>Indian</hi> Pelfe.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Captaine <hi>Iohn Butler.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>