<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, MY VERY GOOD Lord, TOBY, by the prouidence of God, Lord Arch-bishop of Yorke, Primate, and Metropolitan of England.</title>
           <author>Jackson, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115461_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20679</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7077</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115461</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, MY VERY GOOD Lord, TOBY, by the prouidence of God, Lord Arch-bishop of Yorke, Primate, and Metropolitan of England.</title>
                 <author>Jackson, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An aduertisement to the English seminaries, amd [sic] Iesuites : shewing their loose kind of writing, and negligent handling the cause of religion, in the whole course of their workes. By Iohn Doue Doctor in Diuinity</title>
                 <author>Dove, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Waterson, Simon</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 78, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, MY VERY GOOD Lord, TOBY, by the prouidence of God, Lord Arch-bishop of Yorke, Primate, and Metropolitan of England.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST Reuerend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in God, my especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all good Lord. Albeit <hi>there is no end in</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ecclesi. 12. 12.</note>
      <hi>writing many books, and much reading is a wearinesse to the flesh</hi> (as the wise man speaketh:) yet doth the condition of this present age require a multitude of bookes: neither ought we to be weary, so long as the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour onely is ours, the cause Gods, and
<pb facs="3"/>
not our owne. Our Aduersaries are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer weary of withstanding the truth, they neuer cease to prouoke vs by bookes, our names are daily traduced in their papers, that vnlesse the Spirit of God waxe cold, and the zeale of his house be quenched in vs, we cannot be silent. And as your Grace hath laboured these fourty yeares without intermission, like a silfull Maister-builder of Gods house, a painefull husbandman in the Ʋineyard, a vigilant Pastour ouer the flocke, and were neuer yet weary of wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing: so my trust is this small volume shall not seeme tedious, which heere I offer vnto your reading, and humbly present vnto your Grace. Since your Grace hath bene called to the office of a Bishop, (as with S, <hi>Paule, it is a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Tim. 3. 1.</note> worke) so it hath bene with you,
<pb facs="3"/>
all your time hitherto, a worke rather then a promotion, neither haue you fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnder so great a burthen. My pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is for you, that God wich hath begun this good worke in you, will also per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it vntill the day of Jesus Christ. That as you haue deserued that good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port which the godly Emperour <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dosius</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Sixtus Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nensis, Bib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lioth. sanctae lib. 4.</note> in the Church of <hi>Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> gaue of S. <hi>Ambrose</hi> then Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of <hi>Milanie:</hi> so you may contiuue still another Saint <hi>Ambrose</hi> in our Church, to the glory and honour of God, to whose goodnesse and mercy I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend your Grace, and your godly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the Lord. IOHN DOVE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>