<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Vpon Mr. Randolph's Poems, collected and published after his Death.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115618_Fr1_2_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10411</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20694</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115618</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Vpon Mr. Randolph's Poems, collected and published after his Death.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Poems : with the Muses looking-glasse: and Amyntas· By Thomas Randolph Master of Arts, and late fellow of Trinity Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Randolph, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Bowman, Francis.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lichfield, Leonard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 128, 2, 93, 7, 114 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>Vpon M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Randolph's Poems, collected and published after his Death.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>AS when a swelling Cloud melted to showres,</l>
      <l>Sweetly diffuses fresh and active powers</l>
      <l>Into the shrunke and thirstie veines of earth;</l>
      <l>Blessing her barren wombe with a new birth</l>
      <l>Of graine and fruit: and so redeemes a land</l>
      <l>Of desperate people from th' destroying hand</l>
      <l>Of merc'lesse Plague, Famine, or Dearth; and then</l>
      <l>Collects it's streames unto the Ocean:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>So thy diffusive soule, and fluent parts,</l>
      <l>(Great miracle of naturall wit and Arts,)</l>
      <l>Rapt up some Regions 'bove our Spheare, did flow</l>
      <l>And showre their blessings downe on us below:</l>
      <l>Whilst we, dull earth, in extasies did sit,</l>
      <l>Almost o'rewhelmed with thy Flouds of Wit.</l>
      <l>What bloud of verse is pump't from our dry Braines,</l>
      <l>Sprung like a rushing Torrent from thy Veines.</l>
      <l>When a long Drought presag'd some fatall Dearth,</l>
      <l>Thy unexhausted Founts gave us new byrth</l>
      <l>Of Wit and verse: when <hi>Cham,</hi> or <hi>Isis</hi> fell,</l>
      <l>Thy open'd Floudgates made their Riv'lets swell</l>
      <l>'Bove their proud Banks: Where planted by thy hand</l>
      <l>Th' <hi>Hesperian</hi> Orchards, <hi>Paphian</hi> Myrtles stand,</l>
      <l>And those sweet Shades, where Lovers tell their blisses</l>
      <l>To th' whisp'ring leaves, and summe'em up in kisses.</l>
      <l>There in full Quire the Muses us'd to sing</l>
      <l>Melodious Odes, bathing in <hi>Cham,</hi> their Spring:</l>
      <l>And all the Graces, TOM, dwelt with thee too,</l>
      <l>Crowning thy Front for old <hi>Citherons</hi> Brow.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Nor were we rich alone; Climes farre from hence</l>
      <l>Acknowledge yet thy soveraigne influence:</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Sicilians</hi> owe to thee their fruitfull <hi>Vale,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>And <hi>Cotswold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> thy Dewes created <hi>Dale.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="7"/>All Lands and Soyles from hence were fruitfull growne,</l>
      <l>And multipli'd the measures thou hadst sowne.</l>
      <l>Green-sword-untilled milk-maids wish no blisses</l>
      <l>Beyond a stammel Petticoat, and kisses,</l>
      <l>And thy sweet <hi>Dowry!</hi> This alone, they cry,</l>
      <l>Will make our Beasts and Milk to multiply.</l>
      <l>And the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ll Fallow Clownes, who never thought</l>
      <l>Of God or Heaven but in a floud or drought,</l>
      <l>Doe gape and pray for Crops of Wit, and vow</l>
      <l>To make their Lads and Wenches Poets now.</l>
      <l>For they can make their fields to laugh and sing</l>
      <l>To th' Muses Pipe, and Winter rhime to spring.</l>
      <l>They pray for the first curse; like Schollers now,</l>
      <l>To earne their livings by their sweaty Brow.</l>
      <l>Then the fine Gardens of the Court, are set</l>
      <l>With Flowers sprung from thy Muses Coronet.</l>
      <l>Those pretty Imps in Plush, that on trust goe</l>
      <l>For their fine clothes, and their fine Iudgments too,</l>
      <l>The Frontispice or Titlepage of Playes,</l>
      <l>Whose whole discourse is—<hi>As the Poet sayes.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>That Tavernes draine, (for Ivy is the signe</l>
      <l>Of all such sack-shop wits, as well as wine.)</l>
      <l>And make their verses dance on either hand</l>
      <l>With numerous feet, whilst they want feet to stand.</l>
      <l>That score up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ests for every glasse or cup,</l>
      <l>And th' totall summe behind the Doore cast up;</l>
      <l>These had beene all dry'd up, and many more,</l>
      <l>That quafse up <hi>Helicon</hi> upon thy score.</l>
      <l>The sneaking Tribe, that drinke and write by fits,</l>
      <l>As they can steale or borrow coine or wits,</l>
      <l>That Pandars fee for Plots, and then belie</l>
      <l>The paper with—<hi>An excellent Comedie,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Acted</hi> (more was the pitty,) <hi>by th' Red Bull</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>With great applause,</hi> of some vaine City Gull;</l>
      <l>That damne Philosophy, and prove the curse</l>
      <l>Of emptinesse, both in the Braine and Purse;</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="8"/>These that scrape legges and trenchers to my Lord,</l>
      <l>Had starv'd but for some scraps pickt from thy Bord.</l>
      <l>They'had try'd the Balladiers or Fidlers trade,</l>
      <l>Or a <hi>New Comedie</hi> at Tiburne made.</l>
      <l>Thus, TOM thy pregnant Phancy crown'd us all</l>
      <l>With wealthy showers, or Mines Poeticall.</l>
      <l>Nor did thy dews distill in a cold raine,</l>
      <l>But with a flash of Lightning op't thy braine,</l>
      <l>Which thaw'd our stupid spirits with lively heat,</l>
      <l>And from our frosts for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>'d a Poëticke sweat.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And now, Wit's Common-wealth by thee repriv'd,</l>
      <l>(For its consumption shewes it not long liv'd,)</l>
      <l>Thy farre dispersed Streames divert their course,</l>
      <l>(Though some are damned up) to th' Muses Sourse,</l>
      <l>This Ocean:—He that will fadome it,</l>
      <l>By's Lines shall sound an <hi>Ocean</hi> of wit;</l>
      <l>Not shallow, low, and troubled, but profound,</l>
      <l>And vast, though in these narrow limits Bound.</l>
      <l>The tribute of our eyes or pens, all we can pay,</l>
      <l>Are some poore drops to thy <hi>Pactolus</hi> Sea,</l>
      <l>And first stolne thence, though now so muddy growne</l>
      <l>With our fowle channels, they scarce seeme thy owne.</l>
      <l>Thus have I seene a peice of Coine, which bore</l>
      <l>The Image of my King or Prince before,</l>
      <l>New cast into some Peasant, loose its grace;</l>
      <l>Yet's the same body with a fowler face.</l>
      <l>If our owne store must pay; that Gold which was</l>
      <l>Lent us in sterling we must turne in brasse.</l>
      <l>Hadst thou writ lesse or worse, then we might lay</l>
      <l>Something upon thy Vrne thou didst not say:</l>
      <l>But thou hadst Phansies vast Monopolie,</l>
      <l>Our stocke will scarce amount t'an Elegie!</l>
      <l>Yet all the Legacies thy Fatall day</l>
      <l>Bequeath'd, thy sad Executour will pay.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>To late Divines (by Will and Testament)</l>
      <l>
         <hi>A Paraphrase on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>ach Commandement,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="8"/>In Morall <hi>Precepts;</hi> with a <hi>Disputation</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Ending the Quarrells 'bout <hi>Predestination.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>To those that study how to spend the Day,</l>
      <l>And yet grow wise—<hi>The Ethicks in a Play.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>To Poets, 'cause there is no greater curse,</l>
      <l>Thou bequeathdst—Nothing, <hi>in thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>mpty Purse.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>To City-Madams, that bespeak new faces</l>
      <l>For every Play or Feast, <hi>Thy Looking-glasses.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>And to their chamber-maids, who only can</l>
      <l>Adorne their Ladies head, and dreame on man,</l>
      <l>Th'ast left a <hi>Dowry;</hi> They till now, by stealth</l>
      <l>Writ only members of the Common-wealth.</l>
      <l>To Heaven thy <hi>Ravish't Soule,</hi> (though who shall look</l>
      <l>Will say it lives in each line of thy Book.)</l>
      <l>Thy <hi>Dust,</hi> unnaturall Reliques that could die,</l>
      <l>To Earth; Thy <hi>Fame</hi> unto Eternitie.</l>
      <l>A <hi>Husband</hi> to thy Widdow'd Poetrie,</l>
      <l>Not from the Court but Vniversitie.</l>
      <l>To thy sad Aunt, and now despairing mother,</l>
      <l>Thy litle Orphans, and thy younger Brother;</l>
      <l>From all of which this free Confessions fit,</l>
      <l>The younger sister had the elder Wit.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>