<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Rightly Honourable, and truely worthy Ladies, the Countesse of Pembrooke, and the Countesse of Mountgomerie.</title>
           <author>F., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115119_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B13592</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11160</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115119</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Rightly Honourable, and truely worthy Ladies, the Countesse of Pembrooke, and the Countesse of Mountgomerie.</title>
                 <author>F., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Honor triumphant. Or The peeres challenge, by armes defensible, at Tilt, Turney, and Barriers : In honor of all faire ladies, and in defence of these foure positions following. 1. Knights in ladies seruice haue no free will. 2. Beauty is the mainteiner of valour. 3. Faire lady was neuer false. 4. Perfect louers are onely wise. Mainteined by arguments. Also The monarches meeting: or The King of Denmarkes welcome into England</title>
                 <author>Ford, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Burton, Francis</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Rightly Honourable, and truely worthy Ladies, the Countesse of <hi>Pembrooke,</hi> and the Countesse of <hi>Mountgomerie.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST EXCELLENT LADIES.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>Where perfect honour is ennobled with ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complisht perfection, Beauty is not scant: which euermore is the glorious shrine of honourable fauour: else had I misconceited mine owne hopes, and beene grauelled in mine own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts: but my strong confidence, is my confident war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant: neither can ye distast that, which explanes, but what is done for you, what is done by yours. If the pleasure ye shall take in the Defenders, who are yours, by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, which is for you, be great: then the acceptance cannot be lesse, in reading the reasons for that defence: especially being to you deuoted: and onely to you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoted. What defects and weakely mainteyning argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in the arguments there are, your protection shal wipe off, and the trueth it selfe (which needes no lustre) chiefly priuiledge. I affect no singularity, I boast no affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation: yet can I not freeze in the one, when I am tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately heated with the other. To whom (noble Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesses)
<pb facs="3"/>should I dedicate the ornaments of loue, and beauty? but to the beautifullest ornaments, worthy to be beloued. Neither doubt I, but as these endeauours were willingly intended, so will they as gratefully bee accepted. Otherwise (as I hope, as I feare not) I will be an alien to mine owne issue: as vnworthy to be christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for mine, since dis-esteemed in being mine. Others, who oppose themselues, if not by <hi>Mercury</hi> perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, I referre to be by <hi>Mars</hi> enforced. So ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenturing at once all my deserts, in your like or dislike: I rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Deuoted to your <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable virtues,</hi> I. F.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>