<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣nourable the Lord Charles Haward Baron of Effingham, and Knight of the most noble order of the Garter: Edward Hellowes wisheth long life, with the fulnesse of all perfecte feli∣citie.</title>
           <author>Hellowes, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115663_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02293</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12425</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115663</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣nourable the Lord Charles Haward Baron of Effingham, and Knight of the most noble order of the Garter: Edward Hellowes wisheth long life, with the fulnesse of all perfecte feli∣citie.</title>
                 <author>Hellowes, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A booke of the inuention of the art of nauigation : and of the greate trauelles whiche they passe that saile in Gallies: compiled by the famous Sir Anthonie of Gueuara, bishop of Mondonnedo, preacher, chronicler, and counseller vnto the Emperour Charles the fift. Dedicate by the said authour, vnto the famous Sir Frances de la Cobos, great comptroller of Leon, and counseller vnto the said Emperour Charles the fift. Wherein are touched most excellent antiquities, and notable aduertisements for such as saile in Gallies</title>
                 <author>Guevara, Antonio de, bp</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Middleton, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>58 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable the Lord Charles Haward <hi>Baron of Effingham, and Knight</hi> of the most noble order of the Garter: Edward Hellowes wisheth long life, with the fulnesse of all perfecte feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Noble, I not</hi> onely directed by the glorious Gueuara in this example and treatise which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated vnto a noble man of Spaine, &amp; in singular fauor with the Emperour Charles the fifte, but also constreyned with the oppression and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of your bountie, wanting all other mean either of abilitie or facultie, to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer my dutiful affection, with the more boldnes, not without regard of the mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of your humanitie, with an humble
<pb facs="3"/>
feare to be noted of mine owne parte, of some presumption, or want of due consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of any imperfection of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, do present, respecting your age &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour annexed vnto the rare vertues of fortitude and temperance, with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the sea and sea matters, with shippes and shipping, wherein approued trial, no lesse worthie credite, hath made knowne vnto all persons not insensible: your readines &amp; aptnes in all weathers, to manure not only the meanest matters, as all maner of cordage and tackle with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in boord, namely sheat, halliard, bowline, tacke and helme, with such other, as also the vse and practise of the Astrolobe, Balistilio, Carde and Compasse: but also the diligent searche in knowledge, of all capes, forelands, shores, portes, creekes, hauens, races, tides, bankes, and rockes. All which things although not vsuall to
<pb facs="3"/>
Noble men, &amp; yet most necessarie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all manner persons that haunteth the seas: expresseth kinde to be an assured guide, to yeld vnto your honour more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertnes then is common or easily obtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to be heyre and successour of Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes charge and gouernement. This small treatise, (as a subiecte in nature) were it of worthines sufficient, most due vnto your honour: but barren prouision impayring my good meaning, forceth me to present vnto your honour, the handfull of water, (as it were) which was presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto the mightie Artaxerxes, who with such mildnes did accepte the same, that he said no lesse noblenesse did consist in receyuing small thinges, then to giue great and mightie giftes. Right humbly beseeching, that it may please your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, not onely to receiue this simple pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent in good part, but my sincere meaning
<pb facs="4"/>
into your good fauour: and I shall not cease with fortified minde to craue the omnipotent GOD to giue your Honour large and vertuous increase to the noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of your minde, as also the concluding and most absolute felicitie, which yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth happines in all worlds.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to commaund: <hi>Edward Hellowes.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>