<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Luthers report of his Confe∣rence vvith the Deuil.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1567</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115168_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02635</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12761</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115168</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Luthers report of his Confe∣rence vvith the Deuil.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A reioindre to M. Iewels replie : against the sacrifice of the Masse. In which the doctrine of the answere to the .xvij. article of his Chalenge is defended, and further proued, and al that his replie conteineth against the sacrifice, is clearely confuted, and disproued. B Thomas Harding Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Harding, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Fowler (Fouler), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Louvain</pubPlace>
                    <date>1567</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 10, 9-35, 46-50, 262, 6 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="account">
   <head>Luthers report of his Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence vvith the Deuil.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>COntigit me semel, &amp;c.</hi> It befel me on a time, that after midnight suddainly I awooke. Then Satan began disputation with me after this manner. <hi>Audi, inquit, Luthere Doctor perdocte.</hi> Listen, {quod} he, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> right lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned M. Doctor Luther.</p>
   <p n="2">2 Thou knowest thou hast celebrated priuate Masses these fiften yeres almost e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day.</p>
   <p n="3">3 What if suche priuate Masses were horrible Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie?</p>
   <p n="4">
      <pb facs="48"/>
      <note place="margin">Denial of Adoratiō of Christs body, the Deuils Doctrine.</note>4 What if it were so, that the body and bloud of Christe were not present, but that thou didst adoure bread and wine onely, and shewedst the same to be adoured of others?</p>
   <p>To whom I answered. I am an annointed Priest, I haue recei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed vnction and consecration of a Bishop, and al these thinges haue I done 5 by cōmaundement of my Superiours. Why should I not haue cōsecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, sith that I pronounced the wordes of Christe seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously, and celebrated Mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses in great earnest?<note place="margin">The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil cōfes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard Priesthod M. Ievvel deneeth.</note> This muche thou knowest.</p>
   <p n="6">6 Al this ({quod} Satan) is true.</p>
   <p n="7">7 But the Turkes and the Gentiles also doo al thinges in their temples vpon obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diēce, and make their sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices in ernest. The Priestes of Ieroboā also did al thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges with a certaine zeale, and desire contrary to the true Priestes that were in Ierusalem.</p>
   <p n="8">
      <pb n="46" facs="48"/>8 And what if thy taking of Orders, and consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were also false, as the Turkes, and Samaritanes Priestes, are false Priestes, and their worship is false and wicked worship?</p>
   <p>First thou knowest, {quod} he, 9 At that time thou hadst no knowledge of Christe, nor true faith, and as touching faith, thou wast no better then any Turke. For the Turke, yea al the Deuils also doo beleue the storie of Christe, that he was borne, that he was orucified, that he died &amp;c. But the Turke and we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected sprites doo not truste in his mercie, neither haue we him for a mediatour and Sauiour, but feare him as a cruel Iudge.</p>
   <p>This manner of faith, and none other thou hadst, when thou tokest vnctiō of a Bishop, and 10 al others, bothe the annointers, and the ānointed, so thought of Christ, and none otherwise.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="49"/>For that cause ye fled 11 from Christ, as from a cruel Iudge, to S. Marie, and the Saintes.</p>
   <p>They were your medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atours, betwene you and Christe: 12 so the glorie was taken from Christe.</p>
   <p n="13">13 This neither thou, nor any other Papist can denie.<note place="margin">The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil calleth vs Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ste<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Therefore ye are annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, consecrated and sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and haue sacrificed in the Masse, as Gentiles, and Heathens, and not as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians.</p>
   <p n="14">
      <pb n="34" facs="49"/>14 How then could ye consecrate in the Masse, and celebrate a true Masse, sith that (which thing after your owne doctrine mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth altogether) there wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a person hauing pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to consecrate? &amp;c.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>