<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the most noble Captaines and renowmed Souldiours of Eng∣land, health to their persons, and happi∣nes to all their honourable attemptes.</title>
           <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1587</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115957_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10716</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20995</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115957</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the most noble Captaines and renowmed Souldiours of Eng∣land, health to their persons, and happi∣nes to all their honourable attemptes.</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A path-vvay to military practise : Containinge offices, lawes, disciplines and orders to be obserued in an army, with sundry stratagems very beneficiall for young gentlemen, or any other that is desirous to haue knowledge in martiall exercises. Whereunto is annexed a kalender of the imbattelinge of men: newlie written by Barnabe Rich souldiour, seruaunt to the right honorable Sir Christopher Hatton Knight. Perused and allowed</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1587</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Walley (Waley), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>❧ To the most noble Captaines <hi>and renowmed Souldiours of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, health to their persons, and <hi>happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to all their honourable</hi> attemptes.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough I haue</hi> vndertaken (honorable gentlemen) to set down directions for younge Souldiours not yet ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perfected in <hi>Militarie Practise,</hi> yet for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter experienced (of whō my selfe would gladly be instructed) as I haue not presumed to offer them prescriptions, so I hope they haue no cause to mislike of this mine enterprise. It is now 24. yeres agoe, sith I first vndertooke Armes &amp; serued at <hi>New hauen,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that most honorable Earle of <hi>VVarwicke</hi> (a father to Souldiours at this day) sithe which time, what I haue either practised by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, seene by example, or gathered by Historie concerning Martiality, I haue here set them downe, to the benefit of my countrie men, that are not yet practiled in so honourable and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise, what faultes I shall commit through ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunce. I hope you will pardon of curtelie, when they shall proceede rather of the zeale I haue to please, then of any desire I haue to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend: thus submiting altogether to your dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creete corrections, I ende.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours as his owne, Barnabe Rich.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>