<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>S.E.K. concerning the Philosophers Stone, written to his especiall good friend, G.S. Gent.</title>
           <author>K., Sr. E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115988_Fr1_8</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10786</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21057</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115988</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>S.E.K. concerning the Philosophers Stone, written to his especiall good friend, G.S. Gent.</title>
                 <author>K., Sr. E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The compound of alchymy. Or The ancient hidden art of archemie : conteining the right &amp; perfectest meanes to make the philosophers stone, aurum potabile, with other excellent experiments. Diuided into twelue gates. First written by the learned and rare philosopher of our nation George Ripley, sometime Chanon of Bridlington in Yorkeshyre: &amp; dedicated to K. Edvvard the 4. Whereunto is adioyned his epistle to the King, his vision, his wheele, &amp; other his workes, neuer before published: with certaine briefe additions of other notable writers concerning the same. Set foorth by Raph Rabbards Gentleman, studious and expert in archemicall artes</title>
                 <author>Ripley, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>104 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <head>S.E.K. concerning the <hi>Philosophers Stone,</hi> written to his especiall good friend, <hi>G.S.</hi> Gent.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>THe heauenlie Cope hath in him natures fower,</l>
      <l>Two hidden, but the rest to sight appeare:</l>
      <l>Wherein the Spermes of all the bodies lower</l>
      <l>Most secret are, yet spring forth once a yeare:</l>
      <l>And as the earth with water Authors are,</l>
      <l>So of his part is drines end of care.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>No flood so great, as that which floweth still:</l>
      <l>No thing more fixt, than Earth digested thrise:</l>
      <l>No winde so fresh, as when it serueth will:</l>
      <l>No profit more, then keepe in, and be wise:</l>
      <l>No better hap, than drie vp aïre to dust,</l>
      <l>For then thou maist leaue of, and sleepe thy lust.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Yet will I warne thee, least thou chaunce to faile,</l>
      <l>Sublime thine earth with stinking water erst:</l>
      <l>Then in a place where <hi>Phoebus</hi> onely tayle,</l>
      <l>Is seene at midday, see thou mingle best:</l>
      <l>For nothing shineth that doth want his light,</l>
      <l>Nor doubleth beames, vnlesse it first be bright.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="8"/>
      <l>Let no man lead, vnlesse he knowe the way,</l>
      <l>That wise men teach, or <hi>Adro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> leadeth in,</l>
      <l>Whereof the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>st is large, and easiest pray,</l>
      <l>The other hard, and meane but to begin,</l>
      <l>For surely these, and no one more is found,</l>
      <l>Wherein <hi>Apollo</hi> will his harp strings sound.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Example learne of GOD, that plaste the Skies,</l>
      <l>Reflecting vertues from and t'euerie poynt,</l>
      <l>In which the moouer wherein all things lies,</l>
      <l>Doth hold the vertues all of euerie ioynt:</l>
      <l>And therefore <hi>Essence</hi> fift may well be said,</l>
      <l>Conteining all, and yet himselfe a maid.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Remember also how the Gods began,</l>
      <l>And by discent who was to each the Syre:</l>
      <l>Then learne their liues and kingdomes if thou can,</l>
      <l>Their manners eke, with all their whole attire?</l>
      <l>Which if thou doe, and knowe to what effect,</l>
      <l>The learned <hi>Sophies</hi> will thee not reiect.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>If this my Doctrine bend not with thy braine,</l>
      <l>Then say I nothing, though I sayd too much:</l>
      <l>Of truth tis good, will mooued me, not gaine,</l>
      <l>To write these lines: yet write I not to such</l>
      <l>As catch at crabs, when better frutes appeare,</l>
      <l>And want to chuse at fittest time of yeare.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Thou maist (my friend) say, What is this for lore?</l>
      <l>I aunswere, Such as auncient Phisicke taught:</l>
      <l>And though thou red a thousand bookes before,</l>
      <l>Yet in respect of this, they teach thee naught:</l>
      <l>Thou maist likewise be blinde, and call me foole,</l>
      <l>Yet shall these Rules for euer praise their Schoole.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Sr. E.K.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>