<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A CATALOGVE OF SVCH QVAERES as are submitted by the Author in all due respect to the Iudgment of the wisest sonnes of his mother the Church.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115852_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00200</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1025</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115852</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A CATALOGVE OF SVCH QVAERES as are submitted by the Author in all due respect to the Iudgment of the wisest sonnes of his mother the Church.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The curse of sacriledge : Preached in a priuate parish church, the Sunday before Michaelmas last. To which are annexed some certaine quære's, which are pertinent to the vnmasking of our homebred church-robbers. D.E.B</title>
                 <author>Brouncker, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lichfield, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 38, 6 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="questions">
   <pb facs="24"/>
   <pb facs="24"/>
   <head>A CATALOGVE OF SVCH QVAERES <hi>as are submitted by the Author in all due respect to the Iudgment of the wisest sonnes of his mother the Church.</hi>
   </head>
   <p n="1">1 VVHether Sacriledge may not bee called the worshipping of Mammon?</p>
   <p n="2">2. Whether the Sacriledgïst his loue to tithes bee not worse Idolatrie, then a Papist his praying ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Sainct or Angell?</p>
   <p n="3">3. Whether our forefathers, who liued before <hi>Hen.</hi> the 8. dayes, might not haue been more assured of their saluation, though dying Papists, then any Puritan Church-robber now can bee if so dying?</p>
   <p n="4">4. Whether those who labour for a pensionary Clergy are not therein secret vnderminers of <hi>Caesars</hi> throne? Or thus, whether the touching of Gods Priests by inforced beggery, lead not directly to the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the King by a minoration of his iust Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue?</p>
   <p n="5">5. Whether the scapes and errors of whatsoeuer faulty ones there bee in the Clergy, may not in part bee iustly laied to the charge of Church-robbers, and not only to the tinder-like corruption of <hi>humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> or the sudaine blasts of Satans cunning tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions?</p>
   <p n="6">6. Whether a Patron hath the least couler of
<pb facs="25"/> reason to expect that his Clerke should consionably performe the office of a Pastor after he hath enforced him to add periury to Simony, and that in a breath?</p>
   <p n="7">7. Whether it stands not with the rule of equall proportion, the Patron should take an oath hee nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath or will take any thing, directly or indirectly for his Praesentation, as well as the Clerke, hee neither hath or will giue any thing? Herein only the supreme Maiesty being excepted, because such a transcendent as cannot (being once crowned,) bee put to an oath, without great derogation?</p>
   <p n="8">8. Whether hee may not bee accompted hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critically partiall who hauing seuerall towne ships and mannors, holds it lawfull to discharge his duty in those places by his Bailiffs and Rent gatherers, &amp; yet will by noe meanes allow that Diuine to teach a Flock, by the substitution of an able Curate whom the pinching tyranny of Sacriledge hath enforced to accept of a second Benifice.</p>
   <p n="9">9. Whether it bee not apparent by that of the second to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> the 11. and the 8. That S. <hi>Paule</hi> tooke Maintenance from on place whilst hee was resident in another?</p>
   <p n="10">10. Whether it may not truly bee said the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puritan makes vp a religion of his owne, whilst hee is not content to allow his teacher more then the poore pittance of Fifty pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> though cloggd with a long heauy chaine of domestick expences, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sids the want of bookes, when as not only all sound <hi>Protestants</hi> and <hi>Papists,</hi> but likewise M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>Cartwright,</hi> with all the iuditious of that stamp doe clayme a libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb facs="25"/> &amp; plentiful entertainment, such a one as where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may bee able to answere the Apostles Iniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of being <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> louers of Hospitality?</p>
   <p n="11">11. Whether in probability the Knoledge of <hi>Christ</hi> which is the foundation may not sooner bee lost through their meanes, who runne the next way to the bannishing of all solid learning, then by them who labour by learning to vphold their errors.</p>
   <p n="12">12. Whats the reason why they who are most sacrilegious in withholding tithes from the Priest, doe most cry-out against vniuersality of grace, and mans freedome to goodnesse?</p>
   <p n="13">13. May it not bee imagined, they intend here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> there prophanation of holy thinges to the charge of God, because hee giues them not wills to a bandon so sweet a Darling <hi>Ganymeded</hi> sinne.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   <pb facs="26"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>