<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian reader</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115514_Bo1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10320</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20605</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115514</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian reader</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvvere to a sermon preached the 17 of April anno D. 1608, by George Downame Doctour of Divinitie and intituled, A sermon defendinge the honorable function of bishops : wherein; all his reasons, brought to prove the honorable function of our L. Bishops, to be of divin institution; are answered and refuted</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Hondius, Jodocus 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Thorp, Giles</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>58, 2, 166 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian reader</head>
   <p>CHRISTIAN reader, when I had perused this sermon made by M. Downame, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the honorable function of Bbs, as he saith, &amp; sawe that it tended directly to prove, that the Caling of our L. Bbs. (as they now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise it in the Church of England) is not onely <hi>lavvfull &amp; good;</hi> but also to be holden, <hi>jure diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no;</hi> not as an humane ordinance, their ancient &amp; wonted tenure, but by devine right, as the verie &amp; ymediate ordinance of Christ: I deemed it as needfull to be answered, as any book our Opposites have at any time sett forth. For how ever M. D. affirmeth the doctrine therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined, <hi>to be not onely true, but a profitable &amp; necessa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie truth,</hi> and that in the judgment of all men, which are <hi>not partiall &amp; full of preiudice:</hi> it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that it is a doctrine vtterlie false, verie hurtfull &amp; obnoxius, necessarie in deed, to be confuted, at no hand to be beleeued: doctrine, repugnant to the truth, the word of the truth, scripture of truth, contrarie to the judgment and practyce, of the prime Churches next after
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>Christ &amp; his Apostles; &amp; of all reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, since the restablishinge of the gospell by the worthyes in these later
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff, Husse, Luther, Zuin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glius, &amp;c.</note> times: Against the doctrine of our ymediate forefathers, (some of whom were worthy Martyrs,)
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Latimer, Cramner &amp;c</note> who in their submission to K. H. the 8. at the aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing of the Popes authoritie out of England, acknowledge with subscription,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">See the whole story in the acts &amp; monuments &amp; in the book called the Bbs. kook,</note> that the disparitie of Ministers and Lordly premacie of Bbs, was but a politik device of the Fathers, not any ordinance of Christ Iesus:
<note place="margin">&amp; Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat legum Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticarum, tit. de divi nis officijs. ca. 10. 11.</note> and that the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Churche by the Minister and certeine Seniours or Eldes in everie parishe, was the ancient discipline: a doctrine, I saie, cleane contrary to the professed judgment of all our worthy writers,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Whita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, Fulk, &amp;c.</note> who in their answeres to the papists, that plead for their hierarchie, with the same reasons that M. D. doth for his, doe determine, that the government our Bbs. exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise ouer other Ministers, is <hi>iure humano,</hi> by the positiue lawe of man onely: the which, if M. D. saith true, is false: and soe the Papists are lefte
<pb n="5" facs="3"/>vnanswered: yea a doctrine contrariant to the lawes of our land,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">S Edw. Cooke de ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Regis ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastico. fol. 8.</note> which make it one parte of the Kinges jurisdiction, to graunt to our Bbs. that ecclesiasticall povver they novv exercise o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer us: &amp; also to tak it from them at his pleasu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re: the which his Highnes taketh to himself, &amp; giueth to all Kinges, where he professeth,
<note n="(f)" place="margin">in his premonitiō before one of his last bookes.</note> that God hath lefte it to the libertie, &amp; freewill of princes, to alter the Church-gouerment at their pleasure. Lastly, it is a doctrine contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the doctrine of the Church of England, professed even by the Bbs. themselues
<note n="(g)" place="margin">Bb, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well in his Apolog. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Arch. Bb. white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gifte ag: M. Cart.</note> till of late daies: when as men wearie to holde any longer <hi>in Capite</hi> &amp; of the Kinge: they began to change their tenure into <hi>soccage,</hi> and desyred to be free even from <hi>Knights service.</hi> The newnes and strangnes of which doctrine notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge, (to use the words of Socrates
<note n="(h)" place="margin">Plato in Apolog. Socratis.</note> against his accusers) M. D. hath told his tale soe hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somely, &amp; carried the matter so smothely, like<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly &amp; confidently; that every word he speaketh, hath an appearance &amp; promis of truth, though
<pb n="6" facs="4"/>in truth, he hath scarce uttered one word of truth. By reason whereof, I sawe much hurt was lik to come to the Church of God. The pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists would be much advantaged, seing that Antichristian doctrine (even after the renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and revivinge of their ceremonies amongst us) soe freely preached and published, tending to the upholding of their hyerarchie, from the Pope to the Apparitor, aswell as ours: his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons being in deed the verie same with theirs, as in the answere to them, it shall appeare. Others would be much scandalized; those that were in love with their owne ease, would easily crouch downe lik Isachars Asse, and seeing that reste is good, would readily &amp; without exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, imbrace his doctrine soe pleasing to the fleshe: as for others, it would <hi>remoras obijcere ardentioribus,</hi> cast blocks in their waie whose hearts were upright with God, and ran well, &amp; soe mak themst and at the gaze like the Corpses of Asael &amp; Amasa: or <hi>retardare zelum,</hi> make thē slack their pace: at leste <hi>sanctorum spiritus in quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare</hi>
      <pb n="7" facs="4"/>disquiet the mindes of al the saincts, to see a sermon of that consequence, preached and published, by a man of that nam &amp; note in the Church. These things considered, my hearts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syre and praier to God was, that he would raise up some man, like Moses to stand in the gapp, &amp; by some short &amp; sound answere, to make up the breach he had made, and waytinge for the performance of it, the newes was: that work was vndertaken and in hand; but answere, and presse, &amp; printer, and concealer of the author, were taken and imprissonned, as dealers against the state. Thus was my soule caste downe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me, to see a truth, soe profitable &amp; necessarie a truth suppressed. I thought with my self, but shall the cause lie there? hath no man that cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage for the truth, as to sett upon that worke a freshe? I sawe by experience, that nothing but bands &amp; afflictions abode, him especially, who after this forewarninge should tak up the gant lett M. D. had throwne downe: but knowing of none that was resolued of it: I cast my counts
<pb n="8" facs="5"/>and summed up my reckonings, &amp; found that my life was not deare to me in this case: &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing dismaied, I sett downe my rest, not to be bound onely, but to die also for the name of the Lord, &amp; the giving testimoney to this parte of the word of his grace. With this resolution I sett upon this answere, &amp; through the blessing of God (who will mainteine his ovvne cause a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all opposition of man vvhatsoeuer) have here brought it to thy vievve: in much weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; with many wants I confesse: (my self be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the leaste able of thousands in this land to manage this busynes) yet with evidence suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, to make it manifest, I doubt not, that M. D. doctrine in this sermon is nothing lesse, then <hi>true, profitable &amp; necessarie,</hi> as he affirmeth. That his praeface is full of witty caluminations to make our cause odious, &amp; our selues hatefull to the wourld: &amp; that (notwithstandinge his great boa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stinge) his sermon hath in it no one sound syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable of argumēt to prove his cause &amp; disprove ours. I have made no large discourses to teach
<pb n="9" facs="5"/>over a nevve the discipline of Christ: besides that it belongeth not to me to doe it at this tyme, professing to ansvvere so farre onely as he opposeth: it hath bin already layd dovvne sufficiently &amp; at large vvith proofes pregnant and demonstratiue those fevve of them vvhich M. D. in his sermon indeavoureth to infringe, I have defended &amp; upheild in this ansvvere o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely, except that sometimes I giue him and the reader to vvitt, &amp; as it vvere a taste, vvhat might further be sayd therein. According to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syre &amp; my abintie I have distinctly applyed my ansvveres to his arguments in order. Weigh them both vvell, good reader, compare the one vvith the other, beleve nether, further then evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence trulie produced, leadeth the: euery such Pythagoras as vvould be beleved upon his ovvne vvord vvithout authoritie &amp; good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, vvas longe since condemned
<note n="(i)" place="margin">
         <hi>Ierom epist.</hi> 152.</note>
      <hi>famae nemo credit nisiinconsideratus, quia sapiens non credit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certo,</hi>
      <note n="(k)" place="margin">
         <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tull in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polog.</hi> c. 7.</note> he is not vvise but inconsiderate that beleeveth flying and vncerteine speaches, look
<pb n="10" facs="6"/>well therefore to thy evidence, before thou giue thy verdict. Yf thou fyndest no sufficiency in his reasons to inforce thee to acknowledg his doctrine for true, justly think with thy self, it is not else where to be had, all men know him to be a scholler; he professeth he hath read the cheef treatisses on bothsydes, thou hast here the pith &amp; substance of all that all of them can saie for themselues and against us. The Lord open our eyes to see his truth &amp; sanctifye our hearts vnto the love of it. And the same God, the Lord himself of peace, graunt us his peace, alwaise, by all meanes. To him be praise for ever Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>