<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE VNTO the Theoremes.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1551</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115664_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10541</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20812</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115664</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE VNTO the Theoremes.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pathvvay to knowledg : containing the first principles of geometrie, as they may moste aptly be applied vnto practise, bothe for vse of instrumentes geometricall, and astronomicall and also for proiection of plattes in euerye kinde, and therfore much necessary for all sortes of men</title>
                 <author>Record, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe, Reyner (Reginald)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1551</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>184 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="48"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE VNTO the Theoremes.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doubt not gentle reader, but as my argument is straunge and vnacquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the vulgare tougue, so shall I of many men be straungly tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of, and as straunglye iudged. Some men will saye peraduenture, I mighte haue better imployed my tyme in some pleasaunte historye, comprisinge matter of chiuasrye. Some other wolde more haue preised my trauaile, if I hadde spente the like time in some morall matter, other in decising some controuersy of religion. And yet some men (as I iudg) will not mislike this kind of mater, but then will they wishe that I had vsed a more certaine order in placinge bothe the Propositions and Theoremes, and also a more exacter proofe of eche of theim bothe, by demonstrations mathematicall. Some also will mislike my shortenes and simple plainesse, as other of other affections diuersely shall espye somwhat that they shall thinke blame worthy, and shal misse somewhat, that thei wold wish to haue bene here vsed, so that euerie manne shall giue his verdicte of me according to his phantasie, vnto whome ioinctly, I make this my firste answere: that as they ar many and in opinions verie diuers, so were it scarse possi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble to please them all with anie one argumente, of what kinde so euer it were. And for my seconde aunswere, I saye thus. That if annye one argumente mighte please them all, then shoulde thei be thankfull vnto me for this kind of matter. For nother is there anie matter more straunge in the englishe tungue, then this whereof neuer booke was written before now, in that tungue, and therefore oughte to delite all them, that desire to vnderstand straunge matters, as most men commonlie doo. And againe the practise is so pleasaunt in v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>singe, and so profitable in appliynge, that who so euer do the
<pb facs="49"/>delite in anie of bothe, ought not of right to mislike this arte. And if any manne shall like the arte welle for it selfe, but shall mislyke the fourme that I haue vsed in teachyng of it, to hym I shall saie, Firste, that I dooe wishe with hym that some other man, whiche coulde better haue doone it, hadde shewed his good will, and vsed his diligence in suche sorte, that I myght haue bene therby occasioned iustely to haue left of my laboure, or after my trauaile to haue suppressed my bookes. But sithe no manne hath yet attempted the like, as far as I canne learne, I truste all suche as bee not exercised in the studie of Geometrye, shall finde greate ease and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theraunce by this simple, plaine, and easie forme of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge. And shall perceaue the exacte woorkes of Theon, and others that write on Euclide, a greate deale the som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, by this blunte delineacion afore hande to them taughte, For I dare presuppose of them, that thing which I haue sette in my selfe, and haue marked in others, that is to saye, that it is not easie for a man that shall trauaile in a straunge arte, to vnderstand at the beginninge bothe the thing that is taught and also the iuste reason whie it is so. And by experience of teachinge I haue tried it to bee true, for whenne I haue taughte the proposition, as it imported in meaninge, and annexed the demonstration with all, I didde perceaue that it was a greate trouble and a painefull vexacion of mynde to the learner, to comprehend bothe those thinges at ones. And therfore did I proue firste to make them to vnderstande the sence of the propositions, and then afterward did they conceaue the demonstrations muche soner, when they hadde the sentence of the propositions first ingrafted in their min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. This thinge caused me in bothe these bookes to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte the demonstrations, and to vse onlye a plaine forme of declaration, which might best serue for the firste intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction. Whiche example hat beene vsed by other learned menne before nowe, for not only Georgius Ioachimus Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus, but also Boetius that wittye clarke did set forth some whole books of Euclide, without any demonstration or any
<pb facs="49"/>other declaratiō at al. But &amp; if I shal hereafter perceaue that it maie be a thankefull trauaile to sette foorth the propositions of geometrie with demonstrations, I will not refuse to dooe it, and that with sundry varietees of demonstrations, bothe pleasaunt and profitable also. And then will I in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner prepare to sette foorth the other bookes, whiche now are lefte vnprinted, by occasion not so muche of the charges in cuttyng of the figures, as for other iuste hynderances, whiche I truste hereafter shall bee remedied. In the meane season if any man muse why I haue sette the Conclusions beefore the Teoremes, seynge many of the Theoremes seeme to include the cause of some of the conclusions, and therfore oughte to haue gone before them, as the cause goeth before the effecte. Herevnto I saie, that although the cause doo go beefore the effect in order of nature, yet in order of teachyng the effect must be fyrst declared, and than the cause therof shewed, for so shal men best vnderstād things First to lerne that such thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ar to be wrought, and secondarily what thei ar, and what thei do import, and thā thirdly what is the cause thereof. An other cause why y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the theoremes be put after the cōclusions is this, whā I wrote these first cūclusions (which was .iiiij. yeres passed) I thought not then to haue added any theoremes, but next vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cōclusiōs to haue taught the order how to haue applied thē to work, for drawing of plottes, &amp; such like vses. But afterward cōsidering the great cōmoditie y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thei serue for, and the light that thei do geue to all sortes of practise geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metricall, besyde other more notable benefites, whiche shall be declared more specially in a place conuenient, I thoughte beste to geue you some taste of theym, and the pleasaunt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of suche geometrical propositions, which might serue diuerselye in other bookes for the demonstrations and proofes of all Geometricall woorkes. And in theim, as well as in the propositions, I haue drawen in the Linearie examples many tymes more lynes, than be spoken of in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of them, whiche is doone to this intent, that yf any manne lyst to learne the demonstrations by harte, as somme
<pb facs="50"/>learned men haue iudged beste to doo) those same men should finde the Linearye exaumples to serue for this purpose, and to wante no thyng needefull to the iuste proofe, whereby this booke maye bee wel approued to be more complete then many men wolde suppose it.</p>
   <p>And thus for this tyme I wyll make an ende without any larger declaration of the commoditees of this arte, or any far<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther answeryng to that may bee obiected agaynst my hande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng of it, wyllyng them that myslike it, not to medle with it: and vnto those that will not disdaine the studie of it, I promise all suche aide as I shall be able to shewe for their far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther procedyng bothe in the same, and in all other commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees that thereof maie ensue. And for their incouragement I haue here annexed the names and brefe argumentes of suche bookes, as I intende (God willyng) shortly to sette forth, if I shall perceaue that my paynes maie profyte other, as my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syre is.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>