<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO PHILIP SVRVS OF MIL∣TENBVRGH A SHARP-WITTED MAN, MASTER OF Art, and a most cunning Musitian, Chappel-Master to the Count Palatine the Duke of Bauaria: Andraeas Ornithoparchus of Meyning, sends greeting.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115197_Bo1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08534</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18853</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115197</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO PHILIP SVRVS OF MIL∣TENBVRGH A SHARP-WITTED MAN, MASTER OF Art, and a most cunning Musitian, Chappel-Master to the Count Palatine the Duke of Bauaria: Andraeas Ornithoparchus of Meyning, sends greeting.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Andreas Ornithoparcvs his Micrologvs, or Introduction: containing the art of singing : Digested into foure bookes. Not onely profitable, bvt also necessary for all that are studious of musicke. Also the dimension and perfect vse of the monochord, according to Guido Aretinus By Iohn Dovland lvtenist, lute-player, and Bachelor of Musicke in both the Vniuersities. 1609</title>
                 <author>Ornithoparchus, Andreas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Adams, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 80, that is 90, 2 pages, music, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb n="67" facs="38"/>
   <head>TO <hi>PHILIP SVRVS</hi> OF <hi>MIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TENBVRGH</hi> A SHARP-WITTED MAN, MASTER OF Art, and a most cunning <hi>Musitian,</hi> Chappel-Master to the Count <hi>Palatine</hi> the Duke of <hi>Bauaria: Andraeas Ornithoparchus</hi> of <hi>Meyning,</hi> sends greeting.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost deere</hi> Philip, <hi>in that a man is the most worthy of all Creatures, a creature made like to God, by nature milde, of stature vpright, prouident, wise; of memory, witty; by reason, susceptible of Lawes and learning; by his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours great gift, farre preferred before all vnreasonable Creatures in al things, but specially in two, to wit, Speech and Reason; it followes that Ignorance in him is so much the fowler fault, by how much hee is more worthy than other Creatures. Now this as it is a fowle shame for all men, so for Schollers it is the fowlest disgrace: the course of whose life is ordayned for this, that by liuing well they may shew others an example of good fashions, learning and honesty, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creasing feruent Faith in the people, and (which is their chiefest Office, by praising God in Hymnes and songs, stirring vp deuotion in the hearts of the faithfull.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>By obseruation whereof (most kinde friend) I was stirred vp to helpe learners in that kinde also, and after the handling of</hi> Concent, <hi>which in the former bookes we haue deliuered, to deliuer the Ecclesiasticall Accent. A matter surely hard, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it requires both a Grammarian and a Musitian, and also because it is to be had rather by vse than by writing: and further because either none or very few men haue handled this point: by this difficulty the worke was a while hindred from seeing the light; now being set out and perfected, I commit it to your tui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and subiect it to your censure, beseeching you both to mend the errours you find in it, and to defend it from the inuasion of enuious men: because thou art able, learned, godly, and besides other gifts of nature, hast an elegant stile, a sweet vain, and in singing a graceful cunningnesse, wherin thou doest exceed thy fellow-Musitians, in entertaining strangers (as I to your cost found) a liberall humour. Whence it is come to passe, that all the Masters of the</hi> Budorine <hi>vniuersity, which they call</hi> Heydelberg, <hi>do singularly loue, honour, and respect you. Farewell, (wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Sir) and defend thy</hi> Andreas <hi>from the enuious backebiter.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>