<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Anonymus to his Friend.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115830_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10594</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20869</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115830</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Anonymus to his Friend.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Remedies against discontentme [n] t : drawen into seuerall discourses, from the writinges of auncient philosophers. By Anonymus</title>
                 <author>Anonymus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Blower (Blore), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>114 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>
      <hi>Anonymus</hi> to his Friend.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou earnestlie entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted mee to sende you those small discourses you tooke view of in my studie, not longe since. You haue so great authoritie ouer me that I can not (without breaking the league of friendshippe) make that iust excuse vnto you, which I might vnto others. They were onely framed for mine owne priuate vse; and that is the reason I tooke no great paine, to set them foorth anye better, thinking they should neuer see
<pb facs="4"/>the light. Imagine not to find in them, those subtill questions, and profound discourses which so waightie a matter requireth. It was not my purpose to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter so farre, both in regarde of the weakenes of mine owne forces, as that I did likewise knowe well, that the auncient Philosophers haue lefte vnto vs many volumes of the same sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, whose perfection I am in no wise able to imitate. But as they all with one accord doe acknowledge thus much, that wee do naturallye desire to bee happie, and that there is no
<pb facs="4"/>meanes in this world to attaine thereunto, but to bridell our affections, and to bring them vnto a sounde temper, which is the onelye waye to set our mynde at rest: So did they iudge it requisite, that wee should referre all our labour, watching, and meditation to this end. And in deede it is the course which the best witts of those times, haue taken: yea not onely they who haue been guided by the obscure lighte of nature, but euen those whoe thorowe faith haue been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened, by the cleare shining
<pb facs="5"/>of the Sonne beames. From these faire flowers, whiche their labours haue afforded mee, I haue as I passed by, gathered this small heape, and as my time and leasure serued me, distilled them, and kept them as preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Deeming that the lesser quantitye they did containe, so much greater shoulde their vertue and power be. For I was long since thus perswaded, that the receiptes which wee seeke, to calme, and appease our mind with all, ought to bee gathered into the fewest words, &amp; shor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test precepts that may be, that wee may alwayes haue them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb facs="5"/>vs. Forasmuch as disquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which stoppeth the passage offelicitie, and with the which we are alwaies to combate, doth for the most part take vs vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, and keepe vs at that bay, that if wee haue not still some short, and easie weapons about vs, which we may well handle, we should not be able to defend our selues. I doubt not but your age, and experience, hath long since prouided you those that are of better mettle, better for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and tempered. But sith that you haue a good opinion of mine, and desire to vse hem (as you make me beleeue) I do an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable
<pb facs="6"/>to your desire send the you. If they please you, it shalbe according to my wish: If they displease, yet is it according to your commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Fare you well.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours <hi>Anonimus.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>