<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the King.</title>
           <author>Henry, </author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115687_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02966</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13106</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115687</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the King.</title>
                 <author>Henry, </author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The declaration of the King of Nauarre : touching the slaunders published against him in the protestations of those of the League that are rysen up in armes in this realme of Fraunce. With priuiledge. Truely translated into English according to the French copie</title>
                 <author>Henry, IV, King of France</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>79, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="petition">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the King.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y soueraigne Lord, your</hi> Maiestie shall well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, howe they that lately, rose vp in this Realme, haue bent themselues against me in their protestations. And in the same haue gone about by all manner of slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to bring me in suspition with your Maiesty, into hatred with all orders and estates, and into the great misliking of all Princes and nations of Christendome.</p>
   <p>Therefore, my good Lord, I thought it good to sende vnto your Maiestie, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, written and signed with mine owne hande, which shall be presented vnto you by <hi>Mounsier Cleruaut,</hi> and <hi>De Cas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sincourt.</hi> The which I most humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech your <hi>Ma.</hi> vouchsafe the reading from point to poynt, and there to set be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your eyes myne actions and deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noures
<pb facs="5"/>passed, wherin I hold my selfe assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that the vpright and indifferent eye of your Maiestie, shall perceiue nothing but faithfulnes and integrity. The which (my soueraigne Lorde) hath not beene either in causes or effects, more deepely or cleere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier seene by any other, then onely your Maiestie. And therefore, although my principall desyre aboue all thinge, bee to yeeld satisfaction to your Maiesties iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which I doubt not but shalbe a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie easie matter for me to performe: yet neuertheles (my Lord) for that the poyson of these slaunders is spred throughout all the vaines of this Realme, and of all Christendome (as much as in them lyeth) wherin my honor and reputation do suffer incredible domage: I am most humbly to beseech your Maiestie to shew me so much fauo ur, as to thinke well of my sending this present declaration, to all your Courtes of Parliament, and other the notable incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porat townes of this Realme, with whome most cheefely my aduersaries seeke to stayne and diffame me. And also that it
<pb facs="5"/>wold please your maiestie to vouchsafe mee this honour, to commaund your Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors to exhibite it to all Christian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces your freends and allies, with those let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which (with your Maiesties licence) I purpose to write vnto them. And I am certainly perswaded, your Maiestie cannot but thinke it a thing most straunge (being so neere allied vnto you as I am, and with the mynd that I beare) that I passe in si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence the great blames and slaunderous reproofes wherewith they charge mine ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor: which I dare say cannot be spotted without some domage to your Maiestie.</p>
   <p>VVherfore in all humblenes and dutifull affection. I beseech your Maiestie to graunt these my requestes: And so referring the rest of my minde to the discharge of the sayde <hi>Mounsier de Cleruaut,</hi> and <hi>de Cassincourt,</hi> I most humbly beseech your Maiestie to giue credite vnto them.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your most humble and most obedient subiect and seruaunt.</hi> Henry.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>