<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1556</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115662_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10520</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20796</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115662</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The castle of knowledge</title>
                 <author>Record, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1556</date>
                 <publisher>Norton, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe, Reyner (Reginald)</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 286, 2 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), tables, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>If reasons reache transcende the Skye,</l>
      <l>Why shoulde it then to earthe be bounde?</l>
      <l>The witte is wronged and leadde awrye,</l>
      <l>If mynde be maried to the grounde.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>
      <hi>THEREFORE,</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN SCIPIO BEHELDE OVTE of the high heauens the smallenes of the earth with the kingdomes in it, he coulde no lesse but esteeme the trauaile of men moste vaine, which sustaine so muche grief with infinite daungers to get so small a corner of that lyttle balle. so that it yrked him (as he then declared) to considre the smalnes of that their kingdom, whiche men so muche did magnifie. Who soe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer therefore (by Scipions good admonishment) doth minde to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide the name of vanitie, and wishe to attayne the name of a man, lette him contemne those trifelinge triumphes, and little e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steeme that little lumpe of claye: but rather looke vpwarde to the heauens, as nature hath taught him, and not like a beaste go po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe on the grounde, and lyke a scathen swine runne rootinge in the earthe. Yea let him think (as Plato with diuers other philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers dyd trulye affirme) that for this intent were eies geuen vnto men, that they might with them beholde the heauens: whiche is the theatre of Goddes mightye power, and the chiefe spectakle of al his diuine workes. There are those visible creatures of God, by which many wise philosophers attained to the knowledg of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uisible power. There are those straunge constellations, by whiche Job doth prooue the mightye Maiestie and omnipotency of God. There are those pure creatures, whiche waxe not werye with la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure, nother growe olde by continuance, but are as freshe nowe in beutye and shape, as the firste daye of their creation. and as apte nowe to perfourme their course, as they were the firste hower that
<pb facs="5"/> they began. And thoughe time wholly depend of it, yet time can not vtter anye force in it▪ yea thoughe all other thinges in the worlde by tyme be consumed, and euen the moste harde metals freted into drosse, yet the liquide heauens not only gouerne time it selfe, but vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly stande cleere from all corruption of time. Oh woorthy temple of Goddes magnificence: Oh throne of glorye and seate of the lorde: thy substaunce most pure what tonge can describe? thy beu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with starres so garnished and glytteringe: thy motions so mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailous, thine influence strange, thy tokens so terrible, to stonishe mennes hartes. thy signes are so wonderous, surmountinge mannes witte, the effects of thy motions so diuers in kinde: so harde for to searche, and worse for to fynde. Thy greatnes so huge, thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe so large, thy rollyng so swifte, and yet seemeth slowe: thy staye so vnknowen, thy place without name: thy spheres are mere wondres, and so is thy frame. Thy lyghtes are so lykinge to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte mennes myndes, no beaste is so brutishe, but that hee styll fyndes, thy warmenes to woorke him greate solace and ease: thy coloure to comforte his sight and his braine. Thy starres in suche ordre, thy circles so fine: thy platte forme is painted with manye a signe. Oh meruailous maker, oh God of good gouernaunce: thy woorkes are all wonderous, thy cunning vnknowen: yet seedes of all knowledge in that booke are sowen. The signes of the tymes who can them comprise? the tokens of troubles what man could de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uise? And yet in that boke who rightly can reade, to all secrete knowledge it will him straighte leade. The starre in the easte dyd gouerne the Wisemen, and taughte them the very region where Christe should be borne. And farther by it they vnderstode, that he was the true kynge of Jewes, and sauiour of Jsraell. And thoughe manye sawe the starre as well as they, yet fewe or none knewe the signification but they yet dyd God at the beginning or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine the starres to be as signes and tokens of times alteration: and namely of suche straunge effectes as seldome come in vre, and therefore are knowen but to fewe men. These woorkes the more
<pb facs="5"/> strange they be, the more oughte men to esteeme the frute of them: to magnifie the knowledge of them, and to studye to vnderstande the mean to attaine them, but most of all to honour, praise and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie the author of them. who willeth nothinge to happen so so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly on the moste wicked, but by som signes and tokens hee giueth warnyng of them. of which thing who so euer standeth in doubt, let him pervse the state of tymes, and hee shall see wonderouse thinges. Before the floude of Noe althoughe God did by speciall reuelation vtter his mynde to his seruaunte Noe, yet dyd hee also by wondrefull signes and straunge coniunctions, expresse the same to the whole world. for all the Planetes were in coniunction in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terye Signes. so that no nation might excuse them selues, for that they were so farre distaunte from Noe, that they could not heare his preachinge. sith all nations myght see the heauens and the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens in it, althoughe but fewe in euery nation coulde skyll of them. And thoughe Noe coulde not in person go into all partes of the worlde, yet was that office supplied by the heauens, of whose re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolutions it is written by Dauid the prophet: They haue no speach nor language, so that their voice can not bee hearde. yet did their course extende into all the earthe, and their woordes into the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame boundes of the worlde. So was there neuer anye greate chaunge in the worlde, nother translations of Imperies, nother scarse anye falle of famous princes, no dearthe and penurye, no death and mortalitie, but GOD by the signes of heauen did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monishe men therof, to repent and beware betyme, if they had any grace. The examples ar infinite, and all histories so full of them, that J thinke it needeles to make any rehersall of them now: espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially seeyng thei appertain to the Iudicial part of Astronomy, rather then to this parte of the motions, yet shall it not bee preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall anye waies, to repeate an example or twoe. As namelye before the buildinge of Rome, there was a verye notable eclipse of the Sonne, declaringe that the libertye of the worlde beganne then to decay, whē Rome began to rise: which shuld subdue all the
<pb facs="6"/> world neare hand: as in effect afterwarde it dyd succeede, increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>singe styll by lytle and little, and continuynge for a longe tyme, tyll the Gothes in the time of Arcadius and Honorius, did spoile that citye, and subdue their power. At which time also straunge signes dyd appeare in the ayer, and in the skye: whiche seemed not onlye to signifie the deuastation of the Imperye of Rome, but also the subduyng of all the weste prouinces, by straunge inuasion of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous nations. Many other straunge eclipses both of Sonne and Moone, beside the appearing of sondrye Sonnes, and straunge shapes of the Moone, and the starres diuerselye disordered, with Rainbowes of meruailous formes, Cometes of diuers kindes, and other wonderfull signes, whiche euer were messangers of as won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull effectes, of newe innouations, straunge transmutations, and sometime vtter subuersions, not onlye of small prouinces, but also of greate kingdomes, yea and of many regions at ones. And therefore sayth M. Manilius.</p>
   <q>Nunquam futilibus excanduit ignibus aether.</q>
   <q>
      <l>The earthe doth euer feele griefe and teene,</l>
      <l>When those straunge syghtes in heauen be seene.</l>
   </q>
   <p>But who that can skyll of their natures, and coniecture rightlye the effect of them and their menacynges, shall be able not only to auoide many inconueniences, but also to atchiue many vnlikelye at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptes: and in conclusion be a gouernoure and rulare of the stars accordynge to that vulgare sentence gathered of Ptolemye:</p>
   <q>Sapiens dominabitur astris.</q>
   <q>
      <l>The wise by prudence, and good skyll,</l>
      <l>Maye rule the starres to serue his will.</l>
   </q>
   <p>J mynde not to discourse in declaringe the profite and commodity of Astronomye, but only to admonishe briefly the reader, that hee maye thinke the study woorthye his trauaile, and to knowe it to be the moste necessary studye that can be, for anye man that desireth perfection of wisedome. What benefite doth come by it to the true knowledge of husbandrye and nauigation, J am assured the verye simplest in those artes do partlye perceaue: and the cunningest
<pb facs="6"/> in the same do so fullye vnderstande, that they iudge them selues naked and bare without it, and vtterlye destitute of all excellency in their arte. Jn physicke the vse of it is so large in iudginge due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of complexions, in prescribinge righte ordre of diete and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersation, in gouernaunce of healthe, for iuste ministration of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines in time of sickenes, and in righte iudgement of the Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call daies, that without it physicke is to be accompted vtterlye im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfecte. For proofe wherof althoughe there be infinite places in Hippocrates and Galene, and diuers other good writers, yet hee that hathe readde in Hippocrates but that one booke of Ayer, water, and Regions, and Galen his third boke of Criticall daies, can not be ignoraunte howe necessarye an instrument Astronomy is vnto Physicke, as bothe those bookes do testifie at large. But omittinge the testimonies of famous wryters (whiche would make a wonderfull volume of them selues, if they were written only to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether) J wyll vse a simple plaine proofe manifest to all men, and therefore moste apte for to perswade all men. Firste to begin with sowinge of graine, with graffynge and plantinge, who is so rude, but knoweth that without these be dulye doone, and in their seasonable time, men can not conueniently lyue on the earthe? And bowe are their times knowen, but by the risinge and setting of cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine notable starres? Peraduenture some man will answere, that by the monethes of the yeare all men do know their times without farther Astronomy whiche answere is suche, as if a carpentar or mason shoulde saye, that he can woorke with his compasse, ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, squire, plumbe rule, and suche like instrumentes, without any knowledg in Geometrye. but how ridiculous an answer this were, all men can iudge. Likewaies, if a master of a shippe would say, that he can saile and gouerne his course by his compasse and his carde, with his quadrante and his other instrumentes, without any knowledge in Cosmographye or Astronomye, would not all men that heare him, deryde him, or thinke him madde, for speaking so vndiscreatly, especially such as know (as few ar ignorant therin)
<pb facs="7"/> that all those instrumentes are made by those artes, and appertain to them? So if the distinction of times do depende of Astrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my all togither, and the monethes woulde soone runne out of their courses, if the ayde that it hathe by that arte were neglected, so that Michelmas day wold happen in the Spring time, and the An nunciation of our Ladye would fall after haruest (as the truthe is, it would do, if Astronomicall accompte were not) who can shew him selfe so madde as to denye the necessarye vse of Astronomye, in due keping the times of the yeares? The ecclesiasticall historye dothe declare at large, and other writers in greate numbre do te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifie, that greate controuersye hath beene in the churche, for the righte obseruation of Easter, whiche controuersye could neuer be decided but by the knowledge of Astronomye. And of late yeares in diuers councelles redresse hath beene sought for the iuste obseruation of it: consideringe that if errour be in it, all other mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueable feastes, are wrongly kepte by that occasion, and Lente dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placed so, that some tyme it hath beene kepte sooner then it ought, and at other times later then it oughte. whiche faulte can neuer bee redressed but by astronomy. Whereby it appeareth also manifestly, that in ecclesiasticall maters Astronomy hath a great vse. but that is so well knowen, that euerye man almoste doth confesse it. And generally who so euer dothe take benefite by the dewe distinction of the yeare, he can not chose but acknowledge that the same com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moditie doth come by Astronomy. Jf J should specially and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticularlye discourse in euerye kinde of science and artes, and shewe how they are ayded by astronomye, J should make my preface ouer longe, and repeate thinges that all men doth knowe. Jn lawe for contractes and bargaines the time is moste necessarye to be obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: but especiallye if they depende of moueable feastes, wherein astronomy must discusse the doubte. Jn Grammar, Logike and Rhetorike howe needefull it is, and in histories also, J neede say nothinge, but remitte all men to the readinge of those bokes, which are vsed in those artes, whereby it shall appeare, that without the
<pb facs="7"/> principles of Astronomye those bookes can not bee vnderstande. Then for vulgare artes how the knowledge of ebbes and studdes doth profite, manye men, but speciallye mariners can testifie: and namely suche as vnderstande, what errour commeth by the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the true accompte therein and the vulgare accompte. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine for loppinge of trees and wodde fall, and diuers other ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruations in husbandry, the consideration of the sonne and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlye of the moone doth greatly healpe. Wherfore J maye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that in all artes and sciences, in lawe, physicke and diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in mariners arte and husbandrye, the profite of Astronomye is exceding necessarye. But aboue all other thinges the testimonye of Christe in the scripture doth most approue it, when he doothe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that signes of his comming, and of other straunge effectes shall be seene in the Sonne, Moone and Starres. Also for alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of wether he testified that many did marke the face of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and pronounced truly of the wether, and therefore blameth them that thei coulde not marke and iudge the signes of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Sonne of man. But here possiblye some men will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte the saynge of the prophete: Feare not the signes of heauen-wherevnto J maye duelye answere: that those woordes of Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remye do forbidde honouringe of them as goddes, as the texte is plaine. for oftentimes in the scriptures fear of God is taken for honoure of God, and so is it here, els other wayes might J answer that the true seruantes of God whiche haue reposed the loue and feare of God in their heartes, are neuer aferde of any tokens that God sendeth, but reioyce to see them, and glorifie God for them. But bicause in this case there be manye diuines that can better de clare those thinges then J, whiche am a man of an other professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, J will remitte that matter to them. only admonishing all men, that the Sonne, the Moone and the Starres, were ordained of God to serue all nations that be vnder the heauens, as Moses dooth testifie. Then seynge God hath made them for mannes com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moditie, and to be distincters of times, and for signes and tokens,
<pb facs="8"/> for aide of mennes knowledge, let not men be vnkinde to God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, but lyfte vp their eies to heauen and beholde the good guiftes of God: Note diligently their meruailous motions, and studiouslye considre their wondrefull alterations, with perpetualle constancye and inuiolable ordre: so shall men neuer bee doubtfull of Goddes prouidence towarde them, of his daylye prouision for them, when they see that he hath made suche an vnexplicable frame to serue onlye for mannes vse, for whose sake all other creatures also were made. Jn token therfore of thankfulnes, let vs singe an Hymne vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to that God, praisinge his name, and magnifiynge him foreuer and euer.</p>
   <lg>
      <l>The worlde is wroughte righte wonderouslye,</l>
      <l>whose partes exceede mennes phantasies:</l>
      <l>His maker yet moste meruailouslye</l>
      <l>Surmounteth more all mennes deuise.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>No eye hath seene, no eare hath hearde</l>
      <l>The leaste sparkes of his Maiestie:</l>
      <l>All thoughtes of heartes are fullye barde</l>
      <l>To comprehende his Deitye.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Oh Lorde who maye thy power knowe?</l>
      <l>What mynde can reache the to beholde?</l>
      <l>Jn heauen aboue, in earthe belowe.</l>
      <l>His presence is, for so hee woulde.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>His goodnes greate, so is his power,</l>
      <l>His wysedome equalle with them bothe:</l>
      <l>No wante of will sith euerye hower</l>
      <l>His grace to shewe he is not lothe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Beholde his power in the skye,</l>
      <l>His wisedome echewhere dooth appeare:</l>
      <l>His goodnes dooth grace multiplye,</l>
      <l>Jn heauen, in earthe, bothe farre and neare.</l>
   </lg>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>