<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PRINTER TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115932_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10745</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21022</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115932</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PRINTER TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Holy pictures of the mysticall figures of the most holy sacrifice and sacrament of the Eucharist: set forth in French by Lewis Richome, prouinciall of the Societie of Iesus; and translated into English for the benefit of those of that nation, aswell protestants as Catholikes. By C.A</title>
                 <author>Richeome, Louis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Birchley Hall Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Lancashire</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 300, 12 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE PRINTER TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader: Whereas the Descriptions whereupon the seuerall parts of this work are framed, doe suppose as thou wilt finde so many painted Tables of the matters themselues described in them, to bee set, as it were, before thine eyes, which the Author himselfe, in his French booke, thought good to supply with so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny printed Pictures prefixed before them: I haue beene induced, by the aduice of others, to omit those Pictures altogether, for the reasons heere mentioned.</p>
   <p>First, because hauing receiued order to procure them from the French Presse. I found the stamps so ouer-worne by meanes of a second Edition, which came foorth at the same time, that I thought the Pictures not worth the buying.</p>
   <p>Secondly, because when they were first printed, though no doubt they were done with great arte: yet were they so defectiue, not onely for want of colour, but also in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the worke it selfe, that the Printer was faine to excuse them in a Note to the Reader, remitting him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, for the better vnderstanding of those stories presented in them, to the Authors Descriptions of those Painted Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, which he faineth to haue before the eyes of his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. Whereby it appeareth, that the printed Pictures came farre short of the Authors Descriptions: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore serued to little purpose, not being able to expresse ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry many of those things, which the Author describeth, as contained in them.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, because the descriptions themselues, are so glorious, so liuely, and so compleate, as there is no need
<pb facs="6"/>of the Pictures; which therefore, though easily perceiued to be missing, can no way be thought wanting by any iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Reader: especially considering, that such descrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are made to supply the want of those Painted Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles which they describe; as Pictures againe were inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to supply the office of Descriptions. The Painted Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble being nothing else but a visible report, or a certaine kind of speech to the eye of the beholder: as the Descrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof againe is fitly tearmed by our Author in his Prologue, a certaine Picture deuised for the eare of the Reader. The Orator or Poet, no lesse then the Painter, endeauouring to beget with pleasure and delight, a liuely conceit of those things in vs, which their Descriptions and Pictures doe set before vs. Wherefore, if eyther of them be excellent, there is no need of the other: and to ioyne a Picture to the Description of a Picture, is in a sort to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace them both, and to shew in effect, that they are both defectine. And I doubt not, that <hi>Philostrat as</hi> himselfe, whom our Author was content to imitate, would haue taken it very ill at his hands, who for the better concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of his Descriptions, should haue thought it necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to haue had those Pictures added, which he describeth as present before the eyes of his Reader.</p>
   <p>For these reasons therefore, if it were not the best, I hope thou wilt not iudge it to be much amisse, that I haue altogether omitted those Printed Tables, being in truth no lesse defectiue then superfluous, in respect of their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Descriptions, which of the two are farre the better Pictures.</p>
   <p>That which doth more conceme me, is to excuse some faults of mine owne, which haue escaped mee heere and there, in the Printing of this notable Worke, the Copie which was sent mee being very soule; and hauing no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by mee that could correct mee. All that I can doe at this present in satisfaction thereof, is onely to make a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular confession, or recantation of them; which you
<pb facs="6"/>shall finde in the latter end of this Booke, set downe in such manner, as thou mayest easily reforme them in thy reading: for the number of the page and line where the error is being noted there, will easily shew thee how to mend it. And so desiring Almighty God to pardon also those secret faults of thine, with the rest of mine, which I feare are farre the greater. I bid thee hartily fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>