<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An admonition to the reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115561_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10322</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20607</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115561</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An admonition to the reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A defence of the iudgment of the Reformed churches. That a man may lawfullie not onelie put awaie his wife for her adulterie, but also marrie another. Wherin both Robert Bellarmin the Iesuites Latin treatise, and an English pamphlet of a namelesse author mainteyning the contrarie are co [n] futed by Iohn Raynolds. A taste of Bellarmins dealing in controversies of religion: how he depraveth Scriptures, misalleagthe [sic] fathers, and abuseth reasons to the perverting of the truth of God, and poisoning of his Churche with errour</title>
                 <author>Rainolds, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waters (Walters), Joris (George)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Dordrecht</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 80, 80-94, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>An admonition to the reader.</head>
   <p>ALthough the Printer hath beene carefull, &amp; supplied someti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes
the defects of his coppie, yet hath he somtimes fayled, not
only in mispoyntinge, or not poynting, or transposing, omitting,
or adding, sometimes a letter (which the readers iudgment, &amp; dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
must helpe) but in omission, or alteration of woords, obscur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing,
or perverting the sence; which the reader shal doe wel to corect,
before he reade the booke, as they stand herevnder.</p>
   <p>It is like enough there may bee more faults, especially in the quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations
chiefly in the greeke woords written in a lattin letter, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
which I onely desire that the author whose skill, and dilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
were admirable, might take no damage by other mēs faults.</p>
   <p>The faults are omissive, or coruptions of words. The woordes
omitted are in the corrections following writtē in another letter,</p>
   <div type="errata">
      <head>Faults escaped in the Printinge.</head>
      <p>Pag. 12. l. 1. reade some <hi>other</hi> cause. Pag. 19. l. 29, reade <hi>but</hi> incidēt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
touched. Pag. 21. l. 28. reade <hi>owne</hi> argumēt, 39. Marg. 1. Cor
17. 10. 34. Marg. in the end. Iudg: 5. 31. Pag. 59. l. 11. read yet
hath he <hi>not</hi> the generall cōsent, Pag. 74. l. 32. read, submitteth him
selfe <hi>expresly,</hi> Pag. 80. l. 6. reade <hi>If</hi> notwithstanding.</p>
      <p>The corruptions of woords, correct thus,</p>
      <p>Pag. 2. l. 18. reade, Canonists. for <hi>Canoists</hi> Pag. 7. l. 24. reade, excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
for <hi>excepsitions,</hi> 16. Marg. in the quotation, out of Ioh' 9.
reade, verse 41. for 21. Pag. 31. l. 8. reade, Coumpts, in stead of
<hi>Counsells</hi> of money. <hi>Pag.</hi> 53. l. 10. reade, the, for <hi>that</hi> papistes.</p>
      <p>Pag. 57. l. 10. read, Calumniously, for Calmuniously.</p>
      <p>59. Marg. at the letter C. reade not <hi>extra</hi> but tittulo, &amp;
so at the letter D. for those places are not in the extravagants, but
in the 4. booke of the decretals vnder those titles. pag. 60. l. 27.
reade yea, for <hi>yet</hi> setteth downe, Pag. 60. l. 28. reade specifie them,
for <hi>then.</hi> Pag. 61. l. 8. reade through error thought, <hi>for though,</hi> &amp;
mende there the poynting. Pag. 73. l. 22. read of all, for <hi>by</hi> all the
rest, Pag. 75. l. 2. reade any Bishop ror <hi>my</hi> Bishop, Pag. 77. l. 19. reade
one of theirs, for, <hi>out,</hi> of theirs, Pag. 78. l. 28. reade, convicted, in
stead of <hi>corrupted</hi> by the texte, Pag. 90. l. 13. reade, the weaknes, for
<hi>of</hi> weaknes</p>
      <p>The woords corrupted are written in another letter.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>