<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Directions for the vnderstanding the vse of this Dictionarie, contriued in diuers points differing from other Dictionaries heretofore set foorth, for the speedier furtherance of the learner in this toong.</title>
           <author>Minsheu, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115747_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09309</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19620</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115747</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Directions for the vnderstanding the vse of this Dictionarie, contriued in diuers points differing from other Dictionaries heretofore set foorth, for the speedier furtherance of the learner in this toong.</title>
                 <author>Minsheu, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A dictionarie in Spanish and English, first published into the English tongue by Ric. Perciuale Gent. Now enlarged and amplified with many thousand words, as by this marke * to each of them prefixed may appeere; together with the accenting of euery worde throughout the whole dictionarie, for the true pronunciation of the language, as also for the diuers signification of one and the selfesame word: and for the learners ease and furtherance, the declining of all hard and irregular verbs; and for the same cause the former order of the alphabet is altered, diuers hard and vncouth phrases and speeches out of sundry of the best authors explaned, with diuers necessarie notes and especiall directions for all such as shall be desirous to attaine the perfection of the Spanish tongue. All done by Iohn Minsheu professor of languages in London. Hereunto ... is annexed an ample English dictionarie ... by the same Iohn Minsheu</title>
                 <author>Perceval, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bollifant, alias Carpenter, Edmund</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 391, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>
      <hi>Directions for the vnderstanding the vse of this</hi> Dictionarie, contriued in diuers points differing from other Dictionaries heretofore set foorth, for the speedier furtherance <hi>of the learner in this toong.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>FIrst I haue declined all the Irregular and hardest Verbes thorow this whole Booke as they <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> fall in their Alphabeticall order, in the singular number in two moodes, the Indicatiue and Subiunctiue, and three Tenses (by which the other are formed) and in the Indicatiue moode in three persons, and the Subiunctiue in two, <hi>viz.</hi> the Present tense, the first Preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect tense, and the Future tense of the Indicatiue moode. The Present tense, the Preterim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect tense, &amp; the Future tense of the Subiunctiue moode, to make the learner &amp; desirous of the toong exact &amp; readie with little or no labour in any of them. The maner of setting downe thus. Praes. for Present tense, 1. Praet. for first Preterperfect tense, Fut. for Future tense. Sub. for Subiunctiue moode. Imperfect. for Preterimperfect tense, &amp;c. as for example this Verbe, <hi>Traèr,</hi> to fetch or bring, Indicat. Praes. <hi>Tráygo, tráes, tráe.</hi> 1. Praet. <hi>Trúxe, truxíste, trúxo,</hi> or <hi>Tráxe, traxíste, tráxo.</hi> Fut. <hi>Traeré, traerás, traerá.</hi> Sub. Praes. <hi>Tráyga.</hi> Imperfect. <hi>Truxéra, Traería</hi> or <hi>Truxésse,</hi> or <hi>Traxéra, Traería</hi> or <hi>Traxésse.</hi> Fut. <hi>Truxiére.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Also for the more ease of the learner, and to make vse of this Declining hard and Irregular <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> verbes, I set downe the Tenses of such verbes in their owne Alphabet, as <hi>Trúxe, Trúxo, Truxéra, Truxésse,</hi> and say, <hi>vide Traér,</hi> and there hee shall see him declined at large, lest hee might mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stake and thinke <hi>Trúxe, Trúxo, Truxéra, Truxésse,</hi> might come of <hi>Truxér,</hi> or the like, and not of <hi>Traér.</hi> In like manner I say <hi>Cúpe, Cúpo, Cupiéra, Cupiésse, vide Cabér.</hi> also <hi>Quíse, Quisiéra, Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siésse, vide Querér. Díxe, Díxo, Dixésse, Dixéra, vide Dezír,</hi> and so of all the rest: so that by this meanes he shall not onely finde euerie one of these and their like in their right Alphabet as they shall looke, but also know the true signification and declining them to make him most perfect in any or all of them.</p>
   <p>Likewise I accent euery word in the whole Dictionarie to cause the learner to pronounce <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> it right, otherwise when he speaketh he shall not be vnderstoode of the naturall Spaniard: as <hi>Bacía,</hi> a bowle, a basen, a trey, not <hi>Bácia:</hi> as <hi>Bárrio,</hi> a warde, not <hi>Barrío:</hi> as <hi>Difícil,</hi> hard, difficult, not <hi>Díficil,</hi> nor <hi>Dificíl:</hi> as <hi>Amór,</hi> loue, not <hi>àmor: Pastór,</hi> a shepheard, not <hi>Pástor:</hi> as <hi>Religión,</hi> not <hi>Relígion: Caridád,</hi> dearnes, charitie, not <hi>Cáridad:</hi> as <hi>Davíd,</hi> not <hi>Dávid:</hi> as <hi>Tenér,</hi> to holde, not <hi>Téner,</hi> and so of an infinit company of the rest.</p>
   <p>This accenting serueth also and maketh one and the selfe same word of diuers significati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> (wherefore I thought it needfull for the learners behalfe) as <hi>ámo,</hi> a maister, or I loue, <hi>amó,</hi> he hath loued. <hi>Cèrco,</hi> a siege, <hi>Cercó,</hi> he hath besieged. <hi>Házia</hi> towardes, <hi>Hazía,</hi> I or he did make. <hi>Báxa,</hi> a daunce so called. <hi>Baxá,</hi> a Bassa or commaunder among the Turkes. <hi>ésta,</hi> shee or this thing. <hi>Está,</hi> it standeth. <hi>éste, hee. Esté,</hi> let it stand. <hi>De,</hi> of or from. <hi>Dé,</hi> let him giue. <hi>Péro,</hi> a peare tree; <hi>Peró,</hi> but, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>The two letters for two genders m. for masculine, and f. for feminine. The neuter is of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> small vse in the Spanish toong, when it is the common of two, or doubtfull, I referre it to euery Latinist to consider how easily he may discerne them, to others, this profiteth nothing.</p>
   <p>Further to shew wherehence the compounds do arise, to know their Radix and originall, I <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> make the composition in a smaller letter, and the simple in a greater, thus: <hi>abs Tenér,</hi> to abstaine, of <hi>Tenér,</hi> to hold, and <hi>abs,</hi> from and so <hi>abs Tenér,</hi> to hold from or abstaine: so <hi>ab Suelto,</hi> loosed from or absolued. <hi>des Atár,</hi> to vntie: <hi>des Armár,</hi> to vnarme: <hi>des Dícha,</hi> mishap: <hi>des Ventúra,</hi> misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. <hi>re Tenér,</hi> to retaine: <hi>re Hécho,</hi> made againe.</p>
   <p>Besides, I would haue those that haue not read much in this toong to be aduertised, that in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> diuers good Authors one word is written sometime with one letter or character, and sometime with another, and yet the selfe same worde and the selfesame signification, whereby they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found and vse one letter for another, as B for V consonant, and V consonant for B; as <hi>Ballésta</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
or <hi>Vallésta,</hi> a crossebow. <hi>Vandéra,</hi> or <hi>Bandéra,</hi> an ensigne, a banner, a flag of a ship. <hi>Bisárma,</hi> or <hi>Visárma,</hi> a weapon with two pikes. <hi>Visabuélo,</hi> or <hi>Bisabuélo,</hi> a great grandfather. <hi>Bogár,</hi> or <hi>Vogàr,</hi> to row. <hi>Volúmen,</hi> or <hi>Bolúmen,</hi> a volumne of a booke: so in the middle of a word, as <hi>Cábo,</hi> or <hi>Cávo,</hi> an end. Wherefore I aduise the Reader if he finde not the word in B turne to V: if not in V looke to B. In like sort these following, as ç cerilla for z, and z for ç cerilla, as <hi>Haçér,</hi> for <hi>Hazér,</hi> to make or to do; as <hi>Rezélo,</hi> for wary feare, or suspition, for <hi>Reçélo;</hi> as <hi>Corçilla,</hi> or <hi>Corzilla,</hi> a little row bucke: so e for i, and i for e, as <hi>Desfavór, Disfavór, Disfamár, Desfamár:</hi> also o and u, as <hi>Mochácho, Muchácho,</hi> a boy, a lad: so f and ph, as <hi>Filósofo, Philósopho,</hi> a Philosopher: g for j, and j for g, as <hi>Magestád,</hi> or <hi>Majestád:</hi> j for x, <hi>Desár</hi> for <hi>Dexár,</hi> to leaue: and x for j, as <hi>Tixéras</hi> for <hi>Tijéras,</hi> or <hi>Tigéras,</hi> sheares or scissers: also x for ch, as <hi>Cartúxo</hi> for <hi>Cartúcho, Patáche, Patáge,</hi> or <hi>Pataje,</hi> a pinasse: <hi>Algedréz, Aljedréz,</hi> or <hi>Axedréz,</hi> chesse-boord or chesse-play. The like to these would I wish the Reader if he finde them not in one letter or Alphabet, to turne to the other, and no doubt he may be satisfied.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Moreouer, when you finde not a word in the single letter, looke in the double; or not in the double, looke in the single, as <hi>Eféto,</hi> or <hi>Efféto,</hi> effect: <hi>Asalto, Assalto,</hi> an assault: <hi>Atónito, Attónito,</hi> astonished, &amp;c. But take heed you take not this double letter with a crooked line ouer him thus n̄: for this single n, as <hi>Pen̄a,</hi> a rocke, pronounced <hi>Pénnia</hi> for <hi>Pena,</hi> punishment or paine: nor the single l for the double ll, nor the double for the single: both which letters alwaies make a differing signification and pronuntiation.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Be in like maner well aduised whether two words be ioyned in one (a thing too common with Spanish writers) as <hi>Encasa,</hi> for <hi>en Casa,</hi> in the house: <hi>Eneféto,</hi> for <hi>en Eféto,</hi> in effect: <hi>Decáda,</hi> for <hi>de Cáda,</hi> of euerie: <hi>Defuéra,</hi> for <hi>de Fuéra,</hi> without: <hi>Dél,</hi> for <hi>de El,</hi> of him: <hi>Deléxos,</hi> for <hi>de Léxos,</hi> from farre.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="0"/> Furthermore, marke <hi>Amálle,</hi> for <hi>Amár le,</hi> to loue him: <hi>Castigálle,</hi> for <hi>Castigár le,</hi> to chastise him: <hi>Hablálle,</hi> for <hi>Hablár le,</hi> to speake vnto him: <hi>Creélle,</hi> for <hi>Creér le,</hi> to beleeue him: <hi>Dezille,</hi> for <hi>Dezír le,</hi> to tel him.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> Also <hi>Castigálde,</hi> for <hi>Castigád le,</hi> do yee chastise him: <hi>Leéldo,</hi> for <hi>Leéd lo,</hi> read yee it: <hi>Dezilde,</hi> for <hi>Dezíd le,</hi> tell yee him.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> For the learners more readie finding out of wordes in this Dictionarie, I bestowed a good deale of time and paines in bringing the wordes into the Alphabet, I heere vse in this booke differing from <hi>Nebrissensis, Cristóuall de Casas,</hi> and M. <hi>Perciuals</hi> in English: which place next Ca Cl, and not Ce Ch, and place Ch after the ende of Cu, &amp;c. And for the giuing notice of what I haue done without defrauding any thing from the labours of any that haue trauelled in this kinde, I haue made a difference of the words I haue merely added by a starre thus*, whereby it may be seene what and how much I haue enlarged by my long labour and paines: and for the most part of the rest of the wordes I haue augmented with diuers Englishes more then hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath beene set downe, as I haue found them in Authors, which the nature of the word may and will containe: as also put out, and quite altered the English of sundry of them mistaken: which, if gentle Reader desirous of this toong, it may further thy knowledge to thy good liking, it shall further encourage me (after this my first beginning) hereafter to do my best to satisfie thy desire.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>IOHN MYNSHEU.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>