<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MEMORY OF HIS DEARE BROTHER Mr THO. RANDOLPH.</title>
           <author>Randolph, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115618_Fr1_2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10411</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20694</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115618</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MEMORY OF HIS DEARE BROTHER Mr THO. RANDOLPH.</title>
                 <author>Randolph, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Poems : with the Muses looking-glasse: and Amyntas· By Thomas Randolph Master of Arts, and late fellow of Trinity Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Randolph, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Bowman, Francis.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lichfield, Leonard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 128, 2, 93, 7, 114 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>TO THE MEMORY OF HIS DEARE BROTHER M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> THO. RANDOLPH.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>IN such a solemne traine of freinds that sing</l>
      <l>Thy Dirge in pious lines, and sadly bring</l>
      <l>Religious Anthemes to attend thy Hearse,</l>
      <l>Striving t'embalme thy precious name in verse:</l>
      <l>I, that should most, have no more power to raise</l>
      <l>Trophies to thee, or bring one graine of praise</l>
      <l>To crowne thy Altar, then the Orbes dispence</l>
      <l>Motion without their sole Intelligence.</l>
      <l>For I confesse that power which workes in mee</l>
      <l>Is but a weake resultance tooke from thee;</l>
      <l>And if some scatter'd seeds of heate divine</l>
      <l>Flame in my brest, they are deriv'd from thine:</l>
      <l>And these low sickly numbers must be such,</l>
      <l>As when steel moves, the Loadstone gives the touch.</l>
      <l>So like a spungy cloud that sucks up raine</l>
      <l>From the fat soile to send it back againe;</l>
      <l>There may be now from me some language showne</l>
      <l>To urge thy merit, but 'twas first thy owne:</l>
      <l>For though the Doners influence be past</l>
      <l>For new effects, the old impressions last;</l>
      <l>As in a bleeding trunk we oft descry</l>
      <l>Leaps in the head, and rowlings in the eye,</l>
      <l>By vertue of some spirits, that alone</l>
      <l>Doe tune those Organs though the soule be gone.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="4"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb facs="4"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb facs="5"/>But since I adde unto this generall noise</l>
      <l>Only weake sounds, and Echoes of thy voice;</l>
      <l>Be this a taske for deeper mouthes, while I</l>
      <l>That cannot bribe the Phansy, thaw the eye:</l>
      <l>And on that Grave where they advance thy praise</l>
      <l>Doe plant a sprigge of Cypresse not of Bayes.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Yet flow these teares ▪not that thy Reliques sit</l>
      <l>Fix'd to their cell a constant Anchorit:</l>
      <l>Nor am I stirr'd that thy pale ashes have</l>
      <l>O're the darke Climate of a private Grave</l>
      <l>No faire inscription: such distempers flow</l>
      <l>From poore lay-thoughts, whose blindnesse cannot▪ know</l>
      <l>That to discerning Spirits the Grave can be</l>
      <l>But a large wombe to Immortality:</l>
      <l>And a faire vertuous name can stand alone</l>
      <l>Brasse to the Tombe, and marble to the Stone.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>No, 'tis that Ghostly progeny we mourne,</l>
      <l>Which carelesse you let fall into the Vrne:</l>
      <l>We had not flow'd with such a lavish tide</l>
      <l>Of teares and greife, had not those Orphans dy'd.</l>
      <l>For what had been my losse, who reading thine,</l>
      <l>A Brother might haue kiss'd in every line.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>These that are left, Posterity must have;</l>
      <l>Whom a strict care hath rescu'd from the Grave</l>
      <l>To gather strength by Vnion; as the beames</l>
      <l>Of the bright Sunne shot forth in severall streames,</l>
      <l>And thinly scatter'd with lesse fervour passe,</l>
      <l>Which cause a flame contracted in a Glasse.</l>
      <l>These, if they cannot much advance thy fame,</l>
      <l>May stand dumbe Statues to preserve thy name:</l>
      <l>And like Sun-dialls to a day that's gone,</l>
      <l>Though poore in use, can tell there was a Sunne.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Yet (if a faire confession plant no Bayes,</l>
      <l>Nor modest truth conceiv'd a lavish praise)</l>
      <l>I could to thy great glory tell this age</l>
      <l>Not one invenom'd line doth swell the page</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="5"/>With guilty legends; but so cleare from all</l>
      <l>That shoot malicious noise, and vomit gall,</l>
      <l>That 'tis observ'd in every leafe of thine,</l>
      <l>Thou hast not scatter'd snakes in any line.</l>
      <l>Here are no remnants tortur'd into rime</l>
      <l>To gull the reeling judgments of the time;</l>
      <l>Nor any stale reversions patch thy writ</l>
      <l>Gleand from the ragges and frippery of wit.</l>
      <l>Each syllable doth here as truly runne</l>
      <l>Thine, as the light is proper to the Sunne.</l>
      <l>Nay in those feebler lines which thy last breath</l>
      <l>And labouring brains snatch'd from the skirts of death</l>
      <l>Though not so strongly pure, we may descry</l>
      <l>The father in his last posterity,</l>
      <l>As clearly showne, as Virgins looks doe passe</l>
      <l>Through a thinne lawne, or shaddowes in a glasse:</l>
      <l>And in thy setting, as the Suns, confesse,</l>
      <l>The same large brightnesse, though the heate be lesse.</l>
      <l>Such native sweetnesse flowes in every line,</l>
      <l>The Reader cannot choose but sweare 'tis thine.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Though I can tell a rugged sect there is</l>
      <l>Of some fly-wits will judge a squint on this;</l>
      <l>And from thy easy flux of language guesse</l>
      <l>The fancies weake, because the noise is lesse;</l>
      <l>As if that Channell which doth smoothly glide</l>
      <l>With even streames flow'd with a shallow tide.</l>
      <l>But let a quick-discerning judgment looke,</l>
      <l>And with a peircing eye untwist thy book</l>
      <l>In every loome, I know the second veiw</l>
      <l>Shall finde more lustre then the first could doe.</l>
      <l>For have you seene when gazing on the skies</l>
      <l>With strict survey a new succession rise</l>
      <l>Of severall starres, which doe not so appeare</l>
      <l>To every formall glance that shootes up there:</l>
      <l>So when the serious eye has firmly been</l>
      <l>Fix'd on the page, such large increase is seen</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="6"/>Of various fancy, that each severall veiw</l>
      <l>Makes the same fruitfull book a Mart of new.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But I forbeare this mention; since I must</l>
      <l>Ransack thy ashes, and revile thy dust</l>
      <l>With such low characters, I mean to raise</l>
      <l>Thee to my contemplation, not my praise:</l>
      <l>And they that wish thy Picture clearly showne</l>
      <l>In a true Glasse, I wish would use thy owne:</l>
      <l>Where I presume how e're thy vertues come</l>
      <l>Ill shap'd abroad, th'art fairly drest at home.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>RO. RANDOLPH. M. A. Student of C. Church.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>