<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ TO THE RIGHT HONO∣rable, truly Noble, ver∣tuous, and most worthy Lady, the Lady CATHERNE, Mar∣chionesse Buckingham, wife vnto the right Honorable GEORGE, Marquesse of uckingham, Vicount VILLERS, Baron of Whaddon, Lord High Admirall of Eng∣land, &amp;c. grace and peace from God the Father, through our Lord Iesus Christ.</title>
           <author>Andrewes, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115930_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19494</idno>
           <idno type="STC">592</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115930</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ TO THE RIGHT HONO∣rable, truly Noble, ver∣tuous, and most worthy Lady, the Lady CATHERNE, Mar∣chionesse Buckingham, wife vnto the right Honorable GEORGE, Marquesse of uckingham, Vicount VILLERS, Baron of Whaddon, Lord High Admirall of Eng∣land, &amp;c. grace and peace from God the Father, through our Lord Iesus Christ.</title>
                 <author>Andrewes, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A celestiall looking-glasse : to behold the beauty of heauen. Directed vnto all the elect children of God, very briefly composed, and authentically penned, that it may be effectually gained</title>
                 <author>Andrews, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 <publisher>Andrewes, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 38, 2 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧ TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, truly Noble, <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and most worthy Lady,</hi> the Lady CATHERNE, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chionesse <hi>Buckingham,</hi> wife vnto the right Honorable GEORGE, <hi>Marquesse of</hi> uckingham, <hi>Vicount</hi> VILLERS, Baron of <hi>Whaddon, Lord High Admirall of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> &amp;c. grace and peace <hi>from God the Father, through our Lord</hi> Iesus Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Ladie, so farre forth as the holy Scripture maketh mention of the Titles, Magnitude, Ioyes, and Eternity of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,
<pb facs="3"/>
(the which I haue here intreated of) or any other diuine matter whatsoeuer: so farre I may bee bold, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to speake, write, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate of, and no further; <hi>for the secret things belong vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, but the reuealed belong vnto vs, and to our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren for euer, Deut.</hi> 29.29. But yet it may bee thought great boldnesse in mee, that am altogether vnacquanted or knowne vnto your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, being a Minister, and Preacher of Gods Word, to presume to shrowde from the preiudice of contempt, this my small and vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Treatise, Intituled, A Celestiall Looking-glasse, to be patronized vnder your Honors protection, beeing
<pb facs="3"/>
a Lady of such dignity and vertue; (and so in some sort I do my selfe acknowledge.)</p>
   <p>Yet as the Lord hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned you among other religious Ladyes, with whō yee shine as a cleere Lamp of light in the world, through your vnfeigned loue, and sincere profession of the Gospell, (whereby you are an honor not onely to your house, but vnto your whole degree and Sexe:) which as it is a sweete testimony to your owne heart, that you are beloued of God, and hath made you far and neere honored of all those that loue God: so also as your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious zeale towards Gods Word doth exceed your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor or Greatnesse, it likewise
<pb facs="4"/>
maketh me very confident, that it will excuse my bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; the rather, because I haue receiued the ground of my worke from the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the word of God: but the method I submit to the correction of man, and am sorry it is no more worthy your honorable view. But although it bee rawly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized in a fewe scattered leaues, and as rudely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed in a sort of scribled and vnlettered lines, as the fruit of whose outward husk being vnpolished, may seeme vnpleasant; yet (no doubt) the inward kernell once ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted, and well digested, may proue cordiall, and right fruitfull.</p>
   <p>Right Honorable, and
<pb facs="4"/>
Christian deuoted La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, like as the <hi>Moralists</hi> sheweth me, that where on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the quality of the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not the quantity of the present, is to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, <hi>Modicum non differt à magno,</hi> it is no matter whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the present bee great or small. So was it with <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi>, who receiued a fewe harsh lines of verse from <hi>Choerilus; Artaxerxes</hi> a handful of water from poore <hi>Sinaeta,</hi> and our Sauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ the poore wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes mite.</p>
   <p>In like manner I am loth to trouble your Honor with a treatise of long circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, lest I should feare you with the losse of time, and so make an end before I
<pb facs="5"/>
beginne. But if the good liking of this Mite of my poore labours, could winne the hope of your fauour, to intreat you with patience, to peruse the same: and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, vouchsafe to grace mee with your honorable accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to patronize this small worke, which I in all dutifull manner, with as tender af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection (as euer mother or nurse gaue their brests to their children, or the <hi>Pellican</hi> peckt out her blood to feed and cherish her young) doe here as kindly dedicate and present: then shall I (if God spare me life) be comforted and encouraged vnder so worthy a fauourer, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede in the like studies, and according to my bounden
<pb facs="5"/>
duty, incessātly with al humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity pray to Amightie God, for his glory, not onely to preserue your Honor in all happinesse, to continue you honorable vpon earth, but also to bee farre more ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to reigne with a Celesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Crowne of glory in the Kingdome of heauen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors in all Christian duty to be commanded: <hi>I. A.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>