<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONOV∣RABLE GOOD KNIGHT Sir Iohn Egerton, multiplication of Grace in this life, and con∣summation of Glory in that other.</title>
           <author>Rawlinson, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115696_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10499</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20775</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115696</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONOV∣RABLE GOOD KNIGHT Sir Iohn Egerton, multiplication of Grace in this life, and con∣summation of Glory in that other.</title>
                 <author>Rawlinson, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The romish Iudas : A sermon preached at Saint Maries in Oxford the fifth of Nouember, 1610. By Iohn Ravvlinson Doctour of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Rawlinson, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Hall, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hodgets, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HONOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE GOOD KNIGHT Sir <hi>Iohn Egerton,</hi> multiplication <hi>of</hi> Grace <hi>in this life, and</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>summation <hi>of</hi> Glory <hi>in</hi> that other.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>HONOVRABLE SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough <hi>Nihili ad om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne nullaest proportio,</hi> there is no proportion betweene such a <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> as this, and the <hi>All</hi> of your all-deseruing fauours to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards mee; yet because the <hi>Moralist</hi> tells me, that where onely the <hi>qualitie</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>of the affection, and not the <hi>quantitie</hi> of the present is to bee attended, <hi>Modicum non differt à magno:</hi> it skilles not, bee the present great or small. And, <hi>Testes inhabiles tunc admittuntur, cùm ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oquì veritas haberi nequit,</hi> say the <hi>Lawyers:</hi> Witnesses lesse sufficient are admitted, when the truth cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them be sufficiently tried; J will not once question your kinde and fauourable construction of this either little <hi>Modi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</hi> of my loue, or <hi>insufficient witnesse</hi> of the <hi>truth</hi> of my affection towards you, to whom (vnlesse I would bee impudently bashfull) I cannot but ingenuously con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, that whatsoeuer is within the <hi>sphere of my actiuitie,</hi> hath long since been deseruedly due.</p>
   <p>Hauing therfore <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ssed</hi> this <hi>Sermon</hi> for a <hi>Souldiour</hi> to fight against the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish
<pb facs="3"/>Judas, the Priests and Jesuites,</hi> who are euer like<note n="a" place="margin">Ier. 2.24.</note>
      <hi>Jeremies wilde Asse, great with foale,</hi> and so the fitter to bee pursued, I know not vnder whose <hi>colours</hi> it should rather <hi>serue</hi> than yours; both because the many sweet influences of your fauours haue taken such hold and handfast of me, that though by the <hi>Ciuil Law, Ecclesiae res vltra triennium lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cari non possunt,</hi> Church-liuings can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be let forth for more than three yeers, yet by the <hi>Law of Ciuilitie,</hi> my selfe a Church-man, am bound to let and set my selfe to your seruice for euer; as also be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause you haue vowed your <hi>Knights ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice</hi> to the defense of our <hi>Head-Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Christ,</hi> against his and our <hi>Head-enemie</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>Muster-master</hi> of the <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Jesuites:</hi> a sort of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manists,</hi> of whom I would wee might
<pb facs="4"/>not truly say what<note n="b" place="margin">Cor. Tacit.</note>
      <hi>Tacitus</hi> sometimes said of the <hi>Roman Augurs, Hoc ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus hominum semper vetabitur, sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per tamen in Ciuitate retinebitur.</hi> They will euer be forbidden, yet will this Land of ours neuer be rid of them. To put by many other their <hi>matchlesse,</hi> more than <hi>Machiauellian</hi> Practises both at home and abroad, hee that shall but looke into their practise of the <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-plot,</hi> which I haue made the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectum adaequatum</hi> of this <hi>Sermon,</hi> it cannot but resolue his heart (if truly honest) into that poeticall furie, <hi>Odero, si potero: si non, inuitus amabo.</hi> J know their cunning to be such, that they will disclaime what they cannot excuse, and rather than stand burdened with so foule a crime, disburden themselues of it what they may, by terming it the <hi>rash</hi>
      <note place="margin">c Ouid.</note>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>attempt</hi> of certaine <hi>vnfortunate Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen,</hi> whom yet they account in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing so much vnfortunate, as that it was not their fortune to speede in that dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall enterprise. Howbeit, J verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that had they sped, it would haue extorted teares from the Priests and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suites their taske-masters; teares, not of sorrow, but of ioy, such as <hi>Caesar</hi> shedde when <hi>Pompeys</hi> head was brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him.</p>
   <p>I trust, my <hi>loyaltie</hi> to my most graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soueraigne, will excuse my presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that I suffer my pen to trauell in the same path after<note n="d" place="margin">The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of <hi>Lincolne.</hi> The Deane of <hi>Christ. church.</hi>
      </note> two of the most bright and orient Lights of our Church, after whose haruest I am farre vnworthie to gleane: and my <hi>loue</hi> to your honourable selfe obtaine my pardon for entitling you to these my poore trauels: for whom,
<pb facs="5"/>as for my most honorable Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster your Father, the most noble Foster-father of the whole Clergie, with each branch and sprig of so noble a Root, my praier is and euer shall be to God:</p>
   <q>
      <l>
         <note n="e" place="margin">Michael Serinius in antiquitat.</note>Stet Domus haec donec fluctus Formica marinos,</l>
      <l>Ebibat, &amp; totum Testudo perambulet orbem.</l>
   </q>
   <q>
      <l>Vntill a little-little Ant</l>
      <l>Shall drinke the brackish Sea-waues dry;</l>
      <l>And a Snaile compasse all the world,</l>
      <l>Stand may that noble <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>milie.</l>
   </q>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours to the vtmost streine of his best seruice,</hi> Iohn Rawlinson.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>