<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONO∣RABLE ROBERT EARLE OF Salisbury, Viscount Cranborne, Baron of Essingdon, Lord High Treasurer of England, Principall Secretarie to the Kings most excellent Maiestie, Maister of the Courts of Wards and Liueries, Chancellor of the most famous Vniuersitie of Cambridge, Knight of the most Noble Order of the Garter, and one of his Maiesties most honourable Priuic Counsell.</title>
           <author>Woodwall, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115197_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08534</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18853</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115197</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONO∣RABLE ROBERT EARLE OF Salisbury, Viscount Cranborne, Baron of Essingdon, Lord High Treasurer of England, Principall Secretarie to the Kings most excellent Maiestie, Maister of the Courts of Wards and Liueries, Chancellor of the most famous Vniuersitie of Cambridge, Knight of the most Noble Order of the Garter, and one of his Maiesties most honourable Priuic Counsell.</title>
                 <author>Woodwall, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Andreas Ornithoparcvs his Micrologvs, or Introduction: containing the art of singing : Digested into foure bookes. Not onely profitable, bvt also necessary for all that are studious of musicke. Also the dimension and perfect vse of the monochord, according to Guido Aretinus By Iohn Dovland lvtenist, lute-player, and Bachelor of Musicke in both the Vniuersities. 1609</title>
                 <author>Ornithoparchus, Andreas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Adams, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 80, that is 90, 2 pages, music, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE <hi>ROBERT</hi> EARLE OF <hi>Salisbury,</hi> Viscount <hi>Cranborne,</hi> Baron of <hi>Essingdon,</hi> Lord High <hi>Treasurer</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> Principall <hi>Secretarie</hi> to the Kings most excellent Maiestie, Maister of the Courts of Wards and Liueries, <hi>Chancellor of the most famous Vniuersitie of</hi> Cambridge, <hi>Knight of the most Noble Order of the Garter, and one of his Maiesties</hi> most honourable Priuic Counsell.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our high Place, your princely Honours and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, the hereditary vigilance and wisedome, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with</hi> Hercules-<hi>like, you assist the protection of the whole State: Though these (most honoured Lord) are powerfull encitements to draw all sorts to the desire of your most Noble protection. Yet besides all these (in more particular by your Lordships speciall Fauors and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) am I emboldened to present this Father of Musicke</hi> Ornithopar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus <hi>to your worthyest Patronage, whose approoued Workes in my tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailes (for the common good of our Musitians) I haue reduced into our English Language. Beseeching your Lordship (as a chiefe Author of all our good) graciously to receiue this poore presentment, whereby your Lordship shall encourage me to a future taske, more new in subiect, and as memorable in worth. Euery Plant brings forth his like, and of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitians,</hi> Musicke <hi>is the fruit. Moreouer such is your diuine Disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that both you excellently vnderstand, and royally entertaine the Exercise of Musicke, which mind-tempering Art, the graue</hi> Luther <hi>was not affraid to place in the next seat to Diuinity. My daily prayers (which are a poore mans best wealth) shall humbly sollicite the Author of all Harmonie for a continuall encrease of your Honors present happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse with long life, and a successiue blessing to your generous posteritie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Your Lordships humbly deuoted</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Iohn Douland.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>