<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Gibson, Abraham</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115299_Ba1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09002</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19294</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115299</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Gibson, Abraham</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A scholasticall discourse against symbolizing with Antichrist in ceremonies: especially in the signe of the crosse</title>
                 <author>Parker, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schilders (Grapheus, Painter), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Middelburg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 196, 18, 144, 8 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="109"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>CChristian Reader, I must advertise thee, that, either through the negligence of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or for want of a diligent Correctour, many faults haue escaped in the printing of this Booke. Diverse of them are very grosse, and do quite marre the sense of the place, which I would pray thee to amend with thy Pen, before thou beginne to reade. As for the rest which bee but literall, I would intreat thee in loue to pardon them, or to correct them as thou readest. Amongst other things, I thinke it not amisse, here in this place, to admonish thee of one in particular, namely that the figures set to number the pages are very faultily set; after the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 120. there following the number 129.130. and so on forward, till thou come to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 135. and after that there beginning againe the number 128.129, &amp;c. from which number 128. till thou come to the number 136. I am constrained in the Table to ad to the number of the page, the letter and page of the sheete: for example, pa. 128. Q. p. 129. R. and so in the rest: which I thought good to let thee vnderstand, lest thou shouldest be mistaken in seeking for any thing contained in this Table.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>