<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the pious Memory of my deare Brother in-Law Mr Thomas Randolph.</title>
           <author>West, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115618_Fr1_2_12</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10411</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20694</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115618</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the pious Memory of my deare Brother in-Law Mr Thomas Randolph.</title>
                 <author>West, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Poems : with the Muses looking-glasse: and Amyntas· By Thomas Randolph Master of Arts, and late fellow of Trinity Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Randolph, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Bowman, Francis.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lichfield, Leonard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 128, 2, 93, 7, 114 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>To the pious Memory of my deare Brother in-Law M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Thomas Randolph.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>REaders, prepare your Fayth; who truly tells</l>
      <l>His History, must needs write miracles.</l>
      <l>Hee lisp'd Wit worthy th'Presse, as if that hee</l>
      <l>Had us'd his Cradle as a Librarie.</l>
      <l>Some of these Fruits had birth, when other Boyes</l>
      <l>(His Elders) play'd with Nuts; Books were his Toyes.</l>
      <l>Hee had not long of Playes Spectatour beene</l>
      <l>But his small Feete wore <hi>Socks</hi> fit for the Scene.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Hee was not like those costive Wits, who blot</l>
      <l>A quire of paper to contrive a Plot.</l>
      <l>And e're they name it, crosse it, till it look</l>
      <l>Rased with wounds like an old Mercers Book.</l>
      <l>What pleas'd this yeare, is next in peices torne,</l>
      <l>It suffers many deaths e're it be borne.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For Humours to lye leidger they are seene</l>
      <l>Oft in a Taverne, and a Bowling-greene.</l>
      <l>They doe observe each place, and company,</l>
      <l>As strictly as a Traveller or Spie.</l>
      <l>And deifying dunghills, seeme t'adore</l>
      <l>The scumme of people, Watchman, Changling, Whore.</l>
      <l>To know the vice, and ignorance of all,</l>
      <l>With any Ragges they'le drink a pot of Ale;</l>
      <l>Nay, what is more (a strange unusuall thing</l>
      <l>With Poets) they will pay the reckoning;</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="13"/>And sit with patience an houre by th' Heeles</l>
      <l>To learne the Non-sence of the Constables.</l>
      <l>Such Iig▪like flim-flams being got to make</l>
      <l>The Rabble laugh, and nut-cracking forsake,</l>
      <l>They goe Home (if th' have any) and there sit</l>
      <l>In Gowne and Night-cap looking for some wit.</l>
      <l>E're they compose, they must for a long space</l>
      <l>Be dieted as Horses for the race.</l>
      <l>They must not Bacon, Beefe, or Pudding eate,</l>
      <l>A jest may chance be starv'd with such grosse meate.</l>
      <l>The Good Houre come, and their Braine tun'd, they write,</l>
      <l>But slow as dying men their Wills indite.</l>
      <l>They pen by drams and scruples, from their quill</l>
      <l>Words (although dreggy) flow not, but distill.</l>
      <l>They sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e, and sowre their faces; nay to vent</l>
      <l>The Braines they eate their fingers excrement:</l>
      <l>And scratch their Heads, as if they were about</l>
      <l>(Their wit so hide▪ bound is) to pull it out.</l>
      <l>Ev'ry bald speech though Comicall it bee</l>
      <l>To their rack'd members proves a <hi>Tragoedie.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>When they have had the Counsell of some freind,</l>
      <l>And of their begging <hi>Epilogue</hi> made an end,</l>
      <l>Their Play salutes the world, and claimes the Stage</l>
      <l>For its inheritance, being now of Age.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But while they pump't their Phansy day and night;</l>
      <l>Hee nothing harder found then not to write.</l>
      <l>No dyet could corrupt, or mend his straine;</l>
      <l>All tempers were the best to his sure Braine.</l>
      <l>He could with raptures captivate the King,</l>
      <l>Yet not endanger Button, or Bandstring.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Poems</hi> from him gush'd out so readily</l>
      <l>As if they'd only been in's Memory;</l>
      <l>Yet are they with as marble fancies wrought,</l>
      <l>As theirs whose pen waits for the thirteenth thought.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="13"/>They erre who say things quickly done soone fade;</l>
      <l>Nature and Hee all in an Instant made.</l>
      <l>Those that doe measure Fansies by the glasse,</l>
      <l>And dote on such as cost more time, may passe</l>
      <l>In rank with Gulls, whom folly doth e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>tice</l>
      <l>To thinke that best which has the greatest price.</l>
      <l>Who poreing on, their Spungy Braine still squeeze,</l>
      <l>Neglect the creame, and only save the Lees.</l>
      <l>Stopping their flying quill, they clip Fames wing,</l>
      <l>Make <hi>Helicon</hi> a puddle that's a Spring.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Nor was his Hast hood winkt; his Rage was wise,</l>
      <l>His Fury counsell had, his rashnesse eyes.</l>
      <l>Though hee (as Engines arrowes) shot forth wit,</l>
      <l>Yet aim'd with all the proper marks to hit.</l>
      <l>His Inke ne're stain'd the Surplice; he doth right</l>
      <l>That sometimes takes a care to misse the <hi>White.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Hee turn'd no Scripture phrase into a jest;</l>
      <l>Hee was inspir'd with raptures, not possest.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Some Divelish Poets thinke their <hi>Muse</hi> does ill</l>
      <l>Vnlesse their verses doe prophane or kill.</l>
      <l>They boldly write what I should feare to thinke,</l>
      <l>Words that doe pale their paper, black their Inke.</l>
      <l>The Titles of their <hi>Satyrs</hi> fright some, more</l>
      <l>Then <hi>Lord have mercy</hi> writ upon a doore.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Although his wit was sharp as others, yet</l>
      <l>It never wounded; thus a Razer set</l>
      <l>In a wise Barbers hand tickles the skin,</l>
      <l>And leaves a smooth not carbonaded chin.</l>
      <l>So soveraigne was his Phan sy, that you'd think</l>
      <l>His quickning pen did Balsam drop not Inke.</l>
      <l>Read's <hi>Elegies</hi> and you will see his praise</l>
      <l>Doth many soules 'fore th' Resurrection raise</l>
      <l>No venom's in his Book; his very <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>ake</hi>
      </l>
      <l>You may as safely as a Flower take.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="14"/>There's none needs feare to surfet with his phrase,</l>
      <l>He has no <hi>Gyant</hi> raptures to amaze</l>
      <l>And torture weake capacities with wonder:</l>
      <l>He (by his Laurell guarded) nere did Thunder</l>
      <l>As those strong bumbast Wits, whose Poetrie</l>
      <l>Sounds like a Charme, or <hi>Spanish</hi> Pedigree.</l>
      <l>Who with their Phancy towring 'bove the Sun,</l>
      <l>Have in their stile <hi>Babells</hi> confusion.</l>
      <l>If puny eyes doe read their verses, they</l>
      <l>Will think 'tis <hi>Hebrew</hi> writ the <hi>English</hi> way.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>His Lines doe runne smooth as the feet of time;</l>
      <l>Each leafe though rich, swells not with gouty rime.</l>
      <l>Here is no thrum, or knot; <hi>Arachne</hi> ne're</l>
      <l>Weav'd a more even webb; and as they are</l>
      <l>Listed for smoothnesse, so in this againe</l>
      <l>That each Thread's spun, and warp'd by his own braine.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>We have some <hi>Poetasters,</hi> who although</l>
      <l>They ne're beyond the writing-Schoole did goe,</l>
      <l>Sit at <hi>Apollo's</hi> Table, when as they</l>
      <l>But midwives are, not Parents to a Play.</l>
      <l>Were they betray'd, they'd be each Coblers scoffe,</l>
      <l>Laught at, as one whose Periwig's blowne off.</l>
      <l>Their Braines lye all in Notes; Lord! how they'd looke</l>
      <l>If they should chance to loose their Table-book!</l>
      <l>Their Bayes, like Ivy, cannot mount at all</l>
      <l>But by some neighbouring tree, or joyning wall.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>With what an extasy shall we behold</l>
      <l>This Book, which is no Ghost of any old</l>
      <l>Wormeaten Authour; heres no jest, or hint,</l>
      <l>But had his Head both for it's Ore an' mint.</l>
      <l>Wer't not for some Translations, none could know</l>
      <l>Whether he had e're look'd in Book or no.</l>
      <l>He could discourse of any subject, yet</l>
      <l>No cold premeditated sence repeat;</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="14"/>As he that nothing at the Table talkes,</l>
      <l>But what was cook'd in's study or the walkes;</l>
      <l>Whose wit (like a sun-diall) only can</l>
      <l>Goe true in this, or that <hi>Meridian.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Each Climate was to him his proper Spheare;</l>
      <l>You'd think he had been brought up every where.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Was he at Court? his Complements would be</l>
      <l>Rich wrought with Phansies best embroderie;</l>
      <l>Which the spruse Gallants <hi>Echo</hi> like would speake</l>
      <l>So oft, as they'd be thread-bare in a weeke.</l>
      <l>They lov'd even his Abuses, the same <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>eere</l>
      <l>So witty 'twas, would sting and please their eare.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Read's flowry <hi>Pastoralls,</hi> and you will sweare</l>
      <l>Hee was not <hi>Iohnsons</hi> only, but <hi>Pans</hi> Heire.</l>
      <l>His smooth <hi>Amyntas</hi> would perswade even me</l>
      <l>To think he alwaies liv'd in <hi>Sicilie.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Those happier Groves that shaded him, were all</l>
      <l>As <hi>Trees of knowledge,</hi> and Propheticall:</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Dodon's</hi> were but the type of them, Leaves were</l>
      <l>Books in old time, but became Schollers here.</l>
      <l>Had he liv'd till <hi>Westminster Hall</hi> was seen</l>
      <l>In <hi>Forrest Townes,</hi> perhaps he <hi>fin'd</hi> had been.</l>
      <l>Whilst others made Trees <hi>Maypoles,</hi> he could doe</l>
      <l>As <hi>Orpheus</hi> did, and make them Dancers too.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But these were the light sports of his spare time;</l>
      <l>He was as able to dispute, as rime.</l>
      <l>And all (two gifts ne're joyn'd before) outwent</l>
      <l>As well in Syllogisme as Complement.</l>
      <l>Who looks within his clearer <hi>Glasse,</hi> will say</l>
      <l>At once he writ an <hi>Ethick Tract</hi> and <hi>Play.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>When he in <hi>Cambridge Schooles</hi> did <hi>moderate,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>(Truth never found a subtler Advocate)</l>
      <l>He▪ had as many Auditours, as those</l>
      <l>Who preach, their mouths being <hi>Silenc'd,</hi> through the Nose.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="15"/>The Grave Divines stood gazing, as if there</l>
      <l>In words was colour, or in th' eye an eare:</l>
      <l>To heare him they would penetrate each other,</l>
      <l>Embrace a Throng, and love a noy some smother.</l>
      <l>Though plodding Pates much time and oyle had spent</l>
      <l>In beating out an obscure Argument;</l>
      <l>He could untie, not break, the subtlest knot</l>
      <l>Their puzling Art could weave; nay he had got</l>
      <l>The trick on't so, as if that he had been</l>
      <l>Within each Braine, and the nice folding seen.</l>
      <l>Who went to th' <hi>Schooles Peripateticks,</hi> came,</l>
      <l>If he disputed, home in <hi>Plato's</hi> name.</l>
      <l>His <hi>Oppositions</hi> were as <hi>Text;</hi> some le'd</l>
      <l>With wonder, thought he had not <hi>urg'd</hi> but read.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Nor was his Iudgment all <hi>Philosophy;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>He was in points of deepe <hi>Divinitie</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Only <hi>Not</hi> Doctor; his true Catho'lique Braine</l>
      <l>The Learning of a <hi>Councell</hi> did containe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But all his <hi>Works</hi> are lost, his <hi>Fire</hi> is out;</l>
      <l>These are but's Ashes, which were throwne about</l>
      <l>And now rak'd up together; all wee have</l>
      <l>With pious sacriledge snatch'd from his Grave</l>
      <l>Are a few meteours; which may make it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e'd</l>
      <l>That TOM is yet alive, but <hi>Randolph's</hi> dead.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Thus when a Merchant posting o're the sea</l>
      <l>With his rich loaden shippe is cast away;</l>
      <l>Some light small Wares doe swim unto the shore,</l>
      <l>But th▪ great and solid Prizes ne're rise more.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>RIC. WEST.</hi> Bac. of Arts, and Student of Chr. Church.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>