<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTY PRINCE, IAMES, BY THE Grace of God, King of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Holland, Philémon</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115981_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09800</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20063</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115981</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTY PRINCE, IAMES, BY THE Grace of God, King of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Holland, Philémon</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The philosophie, commonlie called, the morals vvritten by the learned philosopher Plutarch of Chæronea. Translated out of Greeke into English, and conferred with the Latine translations and the French, by Philemon Holland of Coventrie, Doctor in Physicke. VVhereunto are annexed the summaries necessary to be read before every treatise</title>
                 <author>Plutarch</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hatfield, Arnold.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ponsonby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 1363, 65 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Classical authors</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTY PRINCE, IAMES, BY THE <hi>Grace of God, King of</hi> England, Scotland, France and Ireland, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>IN this generall joy of affectionate and loyall subjects, testified by their frequent confluence from all parts, longing for nothing so much as the full fruition of that beautiful starre, which lately upon the shutting in of the evening with us after our long Summers day, immediatly by his radiant beames mainteined still a twi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light from the North, and within some few houres appeared bright shining above our Horizon, suffering nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the dark night and confused <hi>Chaos</hi> of <hi>Anarchie</hi> to overspred and subvert, nor the turbulent tempests and bloudy broiles of facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous sidings to trouble and pervert our State: I also, for my part could not stay behinde, but in testimony of semblable love and alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance shew my selfe; and withall, most humbly present unto your Highnesse, <hi>This Philosophie of PLUTARCH:</hi> which being first naturally bred in <hi>Greece;</hi> then, transplanted in <hi>Italie, France</hi> and other regions of the continent; after sundry Nativities, if I may so speake, reserved (not without some divine providence) unto these daies, is now in this our Iland newly come to light; ready both to congratulate your Majesties first entrie upon the inheritance of these Kingdomes, and desirous also to enjoy the benefit of that happy <hi>Horoscope</hi> and fortunate <hi>Ascendent,</hi> under which it was borne; even the favourable aspect of your gracious countenance: by vertue whereof, it may not onely be marked to long life, feeble otherwise of it selfe, but also yeeld pleasure with profit to the English nation.</p>
   <p>Vouchsafe therefore, my deere Lord and dread Soveraine, to
<pb facs="3"/>
accept that now at my hands, whole &amp; entire, which in part <hi>Traja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> the best Romaine Emperour that ever was, received sometime from the first Authour and Stock-father himselfe: Protect the same in English habit, whom in French attire <hi>Amiot</hi> dedicated to the late most Christian King: and deigne unto her no lesse favour and grace, than her yoonger sister, to wit, the History or Parallele Lives, hath already obtained: which being transported out of <hi>France</hi> into <hi>England</hi> by that woorthy Knight <hi>Sir Thomas North</hi> our countryman, was patronized by our late Soveraigne Lady of famous memory <hi>Elizabet.</hi> And the rather, for that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering the prerogative of birth-right, and the same accompanied with more variety and depth of knowledge, I may be bold to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce as much in her commendation, as the Poet wrote of <hi>Iupiter</hi> in comparison of his brother <hi>Neptune:</hi>
      <q>
         <l>
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <note place="margin">Homer. Iliad. v.</note>
         </l>
         <l>
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </l>
      </q>
These regards, albeit they were sufficient motives in themselves to induce me, for to attempt none other patronage than the Name of my Liege Lord so gracious; nor so submit my labours to the censure of any person, before a King so judicious: yet was I more animated to enterprise the same, by the former experience that I had of a Princes benignity in that behalfe: what time as I consecrated my English Translation of the Romane Historie written by <hi>Titus Livius,</hi> unto the immortall memory of the said Noble and renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Queene. Now, seeing that with her Realmes and Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the best parts and gifts that were in her, be likewise haeredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily descended upon your roiall person, and the same multiplied in greater measure, proportionable to the dignity of sex, the addition of scepters and diademes, and the weighty charge of so puissant and populous an Empire; it were in me a grosse absurdity, if not meere impiety, to make any doubt of that excellent vertue of all others, whereby Princes come neerest unto the Nature of God, whose Majesty heere upon earth they represent. To say nothing, how the world hath taken knowledge already, as well by your vertuous life and politicke regiment hitherto, as also by the prudent and religious designements delivered in those sage and learned Compositions of
<pb facs="3"/>
your Highnesse penning, That your blessed intention is to holde on the same course still, not onely <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> a point that the Indian Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate <note place="margin">Plutarch. De fortun. vel Virtut. Alexandri. Orat. 1.</note>
      <hi>Porus</hi> required of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great: but also <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> the singular note that our present Author set upon all the actions of the said mighty Monarch; <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
   </p>
   <p>Since then both these attributes concurre in your Noble person, just cause have we, in all devout thankefulnesse to acknowledge the goodnesse of the Almighty, who from heaven above hath sent us so wise a Prince, under whose reigne we (if ever any Nation under the Sunne) may assuredly expect that felicity and happinesse, which the divine Philosopher <hi>Plato</hi> so much recommendeth: and in due <note place="margin">Dialog. 5. Derep.</note> reverence unto your Majesty, with one heart and voice, both sing and say:
<q>
         <l>Hîc ames dici Pater at{que} Princeps: <note place="margin">Horat. 1. Carm. od. 2.</note>
         </l>
         <l>Serus in coelum redeas, tuo{que}</l>
         <l>Laetus intersis populo, <hi>Britannûm</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Prime Monarcha.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Majesties most humble and obedient subject, Philémon Holland.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>