<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Pleaseth it the curteous Reader furthermore to vnderstand a Mysterie.</title>
           <author>Brereley, Roger</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115095_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07799</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18176</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115095</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Pleaseth it the curteous Reader furthermore to vnderstand a Mysterie.</title>
                 <author>Brereley, Roger</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A catholike appeale for Protestants, out of the confessions of the Romane doctors : particularly answering the mis-named Catholike apologie for the Romane faith, out of the Protestants: manifesting the antiquitie of our religion, and satisfying all scrupulous obiections which haue bene vrged against it. Written by Th. Morton Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Morton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 680, 20 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>Pleaseth it the curteous Reader furthermore to <hi>vnderstand a Mysterie.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Letter was sent me by M. <hi>Roger Brereley,</hi> together with a booke of M. <hi>Iohn Brereley,</hi> being the second edition of their <hi>Romane Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie:</hi> the tenour of which Letter followeth.</p>
   <floatingText type="letter">
      <body>
         <head>
            <hi>To the worshipfull M. Doctor Morton, Deane of</hi> Glocester, these be deliuered with all speed possible.</head>
         <p>
            <hi>Worshipfull Maister Doctor, I haue met by good chance with this booke, which I send you here inclosed: I take it to be another Edition of that booke, which I vnderstand you are in answering, which is the cause that I make so much speed to send you it, lest that you should haue committed some ouersights, which are discouered in this, and may tend to your great disgrace, if you vse not due preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It seemeth to me not to be an easie matter to satisfie any iudicious Reader, for this Author is very exact, and quoteth your owne Authors, which are extant, and cannot be denied: and if you should not answer very directly, but runne to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not so pertinent discourses, I feare your credit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will not be a little stained. I wish you well, but my chiefe desire is that truth may be discouered in such important affaires as these are. Wherefore be sure to helpe to set forward this, or else suppresse your bookes, and impose silence to your selfe. And I will be glad to heare of your best resolutions, and euer rest</hi>
         </p>
         <closer>
            <signed>Your louing friend,
Roger Brereley.</signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </floatingText>
   <floatingText type="letter">
      <body>
         <head>My Answer.</head>
         <p>I Receiued this letter, being without date, and brought vnto my lodging by a messenger, who meant for that present to be without name, promising to retume the next day, but did not, except it were without appearance. The booke was printed, Anno 1608. but was not tendered vnto me vntill Anno 1609, October 28. being the next day after that I had presented this my <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale</hi> vnto his Maiestie. And is it credible that maister Roger Brereley should onely by chance happen vpon their so famous an <hi>Apologie,</hi> not vntill almost a yeare after it was printed? Shall we thinke that there could be no better cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>respondence betweene these two, brothers (as I am informed) both by Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and blood? Or can any imagine that he seeking to premonish me <hi>with all speed possible,</hi> could find no possible meanes of conueyance in almost a yeares space? I cannot thinke that he was then amongst the <hi>Antipodes,</hi> but rather <hi>antepedes,</hi> whose letters, sent for the <hi>preuention</hi> of this <hi>Appeale,</hi> were not deliuered vnto me, before the very day next following the publication thereof. Vncourteously (I might haue said, vnconscionably) done: euen to this <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </p>
      </body>
   </floatingText>
   <floatingText type="letter">
      <body>
         <pb facs="8"/>
         <head>An answer to the exceptions made against me in the second Edition of this Romish Apology.</head>
         <p>The first, pag. 10. line 16. My calling of a <hi>Loyall</hi> Romane <hi>subiect a white Aethiopian,</hi> you should haue added, <hi>In a Protestant state:</hi> and haue vnderstood, with me, such Romanists onely as are led by those guides, whose positions were there discouered to be altogether rebellious; but consult you with your selfe, and then tell me, I pray you, of what <hi>colour</hi> that <hi>loyaltie</hi> is, which denieth the oath of <hi>Allegeance?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The second, pag. 18. I, indeed, excused this saying of <hi>Caluine, When Kings command any thing against God, they berea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e themselues of all authoritie;</hi> shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he meant not thereby that they were absolutely no Kings; but so far onely as they commanded any thing against God, in such a case not man but God must be obeyed. <hi>This</hi> (say you) <hi>is vnworthie D. Mortons iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and learning.</hi> And why? I will still stand to my former promise, which was <hi>vtterly to abandon Caluine his iudgement,</hi> if my exposition of his words be not euincible out of the place of Caluin: viz. <hi>Daniel will not obey King Darius forbidding him to pray vnto the true God: he is therefore cast vnto the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: God deliuereth him: the king is glad, and Daniel said vnto the king, O king liue for euer. &amp;c.</hi> Daniel disobeyed Darius his vnlawfull command, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in onely did not acknowledge his authoritie, which otherwise he did still ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and proclaime, saying <hi>from his heart</hi> (saith Caluine) <hi>O king liue for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer:</hi> or, <hi>God send thee a long reigne.</hi> What can be more plaine?</p>
         <p>The third, pag. 180. That which you obiect concerning <hi>Syricius,</hi> is confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from your owne Authors in this <hi>Appeale.</hi> See lib. 4. cap. 9. §. 1. &amp;c.</p>
         <p>The fourth, pag. 443. (note *) in the marg. I alledged nothing but the testimonie of your <hi>Alfonsus de Castro.</hi> You say it is vnfitting. Trie this. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall Bellarmine denied that any did <hi>mox cognoscere Lutherum,</hi> that is, <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently acknowledge Luther,</hi> at his first renouncing of Poperie. <hi>Alfonsus</hi> nameth diuerse, <hi>qui illum expectasse videntur, &amp; statim illi adhaeserunt;</hi> that is, <hi>who might seeme to haue expected him before he came, and as soone as he was come did cleane vnto him.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The <note n="d" place="margin">Memoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, <hi>that the Treatise of the</hi> Kingdome of Israel, and of the Church, dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto Q. Elizabeth, <hi>was the worke of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother</hi> Tho. Morton, <hi>who was of Christs Colledge: for I neuer published any booke in her Maiesties reign.</hi>
            </note> last exception, pag. 740. in the margent, you charge me with <hi>frauds</hi> out of the testimony of <hi>Delrio</hi> the Iesuite, cōcerning the <hi>diuels apparition</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an <hi>Abbot, perswading him to say Masse.</hi> Which my error in that allegation I confessed in mine own <hi>Animaduersions,</hi> at the end of my <hi>Apologie,</hi> and repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it with another example of the same kind out of the same Author <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio:</hi> therefore this your taxation might haue bin left vnto your <hi>M. Theoph.</hi>
            <note n="e" place="margin">
               <hi>M. Higgons obiected the same error. See my answer vnto him, pag.</hi> 8.</note>
            <hi>Higgons.</hi> I pray you, good M. Breerly, know that this manner of dealing cannot consist with any <hi>modest Replie.</hi> Our Lord Iesus blesse vs to the glorie of his sauing grace.</p>
         <closer>
            <signed>Yours,
THO. MORTON.</signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </floatingText>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>