<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115025_Fr2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09898</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20161</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115025</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The life of Alfred, or, Alvred: the first institutor of subordinate government in this kingdome, and refounder of the Vniversity of Oxford : Together with a parallell of our soveraigne lord, K. Charles untill this yeare, 1634. By Robert Povvell of Wels, one of the Society of New-Inne</title>
                 <author>Powell, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Badger, Richard 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Alchorn, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 96, 99-156, 2 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="59"/>
   <pb facs="60"/>
   <pb n="87" facs="60"/>
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome write the lives of dead Princes, to eclipse the glory of the living; in such, a lawlesse humour discontented with the present State, over. swayes the legiance of a loyall heart. This Treatise aimes at no such end, nor other; but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an impartiall Parallell of two such Princes, the one dead, yet living in the other, and the living, raised as it were, out of the ashes of the dead, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="88" facs="61"/>
ages have not knowne the like. You have observed in the past discourse, the life of the dead; and now survey the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of his vertues surviving in him that lives, <hi>CHARLES,</hi> our great and dread Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, the <hi>Constantine,</hi> and <hi>Carolus magnus</hi> of our age: and if the stile of <hi>Magnus</hi> may seeme to bee borrowed from <hi>CHARLES the great,</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet I must adde <hi>Primus,</hi> and I should write but truth, if <hi>Primus ante omnes:</hi> and none who will observe that sacred rule, <hi>In cogitatione tua Regi ne</hi>
      <pb n="89" facs="61"/>
      <hi>detrahas,</hi> will harbour so dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyall a thought of his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, as to thinke I flatter: adulation, like a false Glasse, makes things seeme to be what they are not, and exalteth ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue from its proper Sphere; in this subject of Soveraignety there is no need of such impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture, all mens eyes and co sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences may see and know, that the radiant splendor of his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious goodnesse doth exceed the expression of any tongue or penne.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>