<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the gentle and friendly Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115900_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68649</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20979</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115900</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the gentle and friendly Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Allarme to England : foreshewing what perilles are procured, where the people liue without regarde of martiall lawe. With a short discourse conteyning the decay of warlike discipline, conuenient to be perused by gentlemen, such as are desirous by seruice, to seeke their own deserued prayse, and the preseruation of their countrey. Newly deuised and written by Barnabe Riche Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Middleton, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Barker, Christopher</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>102 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the gentle and friendly Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Llarmes (gentle Reader) as they are giuen vpon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse and sundrie occasions, so they are many times offred aswel by friends as foes.</p>
   <p>By foes to further their pretences when they practise to deceyue: by friendes, but to see howe they be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and in what readines they stande. Who if they shall be negligent or vnprouided, to giue them as it were a friendly <hi>caueat,</hi> hereafter to vse greater circumspection and care.</p>
   <p>I haue in like maner aduentured to giue a friendly warning, the which I haue termed by the name of an <hi>Allarme,</hi> wherein, I knowe, there be a great number wil confesse I haue bewrayed mine owne simplicitie, in that I should thinke to giue any <hi>Allarme</hi> to those that stande in doubt neither of King nor Keyser.</p>
   <p>But because I would not be thought to arrogate so great presumption to my selfe, I haue rather but vsed the parte of some poore bel ringer, or of some other inferiour person, that sometymes being more afrayde then hurt, hath rong the larume bell, or hath runne through the campe in great haste, crying, Arme, arme, arme, wherewith euery one hath runne to his furniture, and being prepared to make defence, seeking on euery side where the foe should make assault, it hath in the ende fallen out, that the poore man was but stared in his owne conceyte, or else afrayde of some shadowe in the Mooneshine. Now it may be likewyse, that I am but afrayde of myne owne shadowe, the which if it be so, my simplicitie yet ought the rather to be borne withal, considering it procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth of good wil that I beare to my countrey.</p>
   <p>But what excuse might seeme here sufficient, wherewith to auoyde me from so many quipping tauntes, which I knowe wil be pronounced against me, by our carping cauillers, such as wil be correcting of euery mans doing? Some wil find faulte with my homely maner of inditing, and wil say, This is no good sense, or this is no true Englishe, here he hath bene something to tedious, and this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter asked longer circumstance, this maner of phrase is but bad, and by this he shewed his eloquence was but small, and here it is not well poynted, and so forth with many other faultes, I know not what.</p>
   <p>Wherefore I would these superficial heades would take this for myne an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere, that what I haue written, it hath not bene to prooue my selfe artificiall or eloquent, but to shewe things more needfull, which I haue noted by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience.</p>
   <p>Some others there be, which are of such excellent memorie, that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing may be written which they do not already knowe, and wil say, This is but borowed in such a place, and this I haue read in this or in that booke.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>Surely I must confesse I haue vsed the helpe of sundrie writers, but not of so many as I would haue done, if I had bene in place where I might haue come by them: for what I haue written, was onely done in <hi>Ireland,</hi> where there is no great choyce of bookes to be had▪</p>
   <p>But what then? Is this sufficient cause to condemne what I haue written? is not the bee accustomed to gather out of euery flower what liketh her best, wherewith she maketh hony? Or I pray you, what is the medicine the worse, although the Physition be sometimes driuen to borowe a handful of herbes out of his neighbours garden, shal his composition be any thing the vnwhole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somer, because the simples were not al his owne?</p>
   <p>There is yet an other sorte, that because they thinke it a shame to reade o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any thing, &amp; not to be able to minister some correctiō, because they wil not be thought to be so dul witted, wil finde some fault, if it be but with the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphie, and wil say, It was pitie this man would take in hande to write before he could spell.</p>
   <p>To these I answer, As great folly might be ascribed to those that were their bringers vp, that would learne them to goe, before they had taught them to speake well.</p>
   <p>But such is the delicacie of our readers at th<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> time, that there are none may be alowed of to write, but such as haue bene trained at schoole with <hi>Pallas,</hi> or at the lest haue bene fostered vp with the <hi>Muses,</hi> and for my parte (without vaunt be it spoken) I haue bene a trauayler, I haue sayled in <hi>Grauesende Barge</hi> as farre as <hi>Billings gate,</hi> I haue trauayled from <hi>Buckelers bery</hi> to <hi>Basingstocke,</hi> I haue gone from <hi>S. Pankeridge</hi> church to <hi>Kentish</hi> towne by lande, where I was combred with many hedges, ditches, and other slippery bankes, but yet I could neuer come to those learned bankes of <hi>Helicon,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was I euer able to scale <hi>Parnassus</hi> hyl, although I haue trauailed ouer <hi>Gaddes</hi> hyll in <hi>Kente,</hi> and that sundrie tymes and often.</p>
   <p>No marueill then good reader, although I want such sugered sape, wherwith to sauce my sense, whereby it might seeme delightfull vnto thee: such curious <hi>Coxcombes</hi> therefore, which can not daunce but after <hi>Apollos</hi> pype, I wish them to cease any further to reade what I haue written: but thou which canst endure to reade in homely style of matters, more behooueful and necessarie, then eyther curiouse or fyled, goe thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward on Gods name, and I doubt not, but by that time thou hast perused to the end, thou shalt find some thing to satisfie thy desire, whereby thou wilt confesse that al thy labour hath not bene bestowed in vayne. And thus I bid thee hartily Fare<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>