<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL AND my very good friends, Sr. LESTRAVNGE MORDAVNT of Massingham Hall, in the County of Norfolke, Knight Baronet: And to the Vertuous LADY, the LADY FRAVNCIS MORDAVNT, his louing Bedfellow: Eternall wel-fare, and euerlasting happinesse, in Christ Iesus our Lord and Sauiour.</title>
           <author>Greenwood, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115797_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02186</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12329</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115797</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL AND my very good friends, Sr. LESTRAVNGE MORDAVNT of Massingham Hall, in the County of Norfolke, Knight Baronet: And to the Vertuous LADY, the LADY FRAVNCIS MORDAVNT, his louing Bedfellow: Eternall wel-fare, and euerlasting happinesse, in Christ Iesus our Lord and Sauiour.</title>
                 <author>Greenwood, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Greenvvoods vvorkes : contayned in fiue seueral tractates. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. of the Day of iudgement. Lords Prayer. Race to saluation. Torment of Tophet. Baptisme of Christ</title>
                 <author>Greenwood, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bell, Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Clarke, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 117, 1, 6, 92, 12, 8, 82, 6, 10, 43, 11 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL <hi>AND</hi> my very good friends, S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. LESTRAVNGE MORDAVNT of <hi>Massingham</hi> Hall, in the County of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> Knight Baronet: And to the Vertuous LADY, the LADY FRAVNCIS MORDAVNT, <hi>his louing Bedfellow:</hi> Eternall wel-fare, and euerlasting <hi>happinesse, in Christ Iesus our Lord and Sauiour.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing earnestly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quested, and often intreated (Right Worshipfull) by many of my good friends, to put in print this small Treatise of the Generall day of
<pb facs="4"/>
Doome, which I lately preached, and in publike place deliuered: I haue (being ouercome with their perswasions) condescended to their earnest demaund, although very vnapt, and exceedingly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, for the penning of so wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy a matter.</p>
   <p>Wherfore I haue made choyse (crauing pardon for my presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion herein) of your wel-disposed Worships at this time (being the <hi>Alpha</hi> of my tender and slen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der indeuours) to sound in your sacred eares this last and generall Trumpe, and to Dedicate to your Worships the same, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the demonstration of my true, vnfeined, and lasting thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse to your benigne Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships (for, sayth <hi>Seneca: Beneficium hominem gratum semper delectat, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratum semel: id est;</hi> A thankefull
<pb facs="4"/>
man will alwayes remember a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite; but an vnthankefull person will soone forget it) for your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary kindnesse bestowed vpon mee, <hi>Absque vllo commerito,</hi> without any desert in the World: as also in regard of the great affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, good deuotion, and thrice welcome entertainment you beare to Diuine and Spirituall Tractates, which appertaine to the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting blisse of the Soule, accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them blessed, which bring glad tidings of saluation. I desire therefore (<hi>id{que} more humillimo,</hi> in most submissiue manner) this one thing at your Worships hands, that you would (pardoning my boldnesse) vouchsafe <hi>aequi boni{que} consulere,</hi> to take in good worth this simple and slender gift. Which thing if your Worships shal vouch safe to doe, it shall not onely bee
<pb facs="5"/>
an incouragement to my future proceedings, but also it shall bee <hi>Vinculum indissolubile,</hi> an inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bond to tye mee in all duety, and in all loue to your Worships: <hi>Dum memor ipse mei, dum spiritus hos regit artus;</hi> so long as life shall last.</p>
   <p>Thus humbly taking my leaue of your good Worships, (no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doubting of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of your natures in the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of these my first presented fruits) I commit you with yours to the safe protection of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, alwayes begging before the Throne of his most Glorious Maiesty, that he would in this life, infuse his Holy Spirit, with all his Graces, into your hearts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly, and in the World to come, crowne you with the Crowne of immortall Glory:
<pb facs="5"/>
And that for CHRIST IESVS his sake, our LORD and onely SAVIOVR Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From Hempsted in Essex.</hi>
         <date>Ian. 10. 1620.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Worships in all duety, for<lb/>
euer to command:<lb/>
HENRY GREENWOOD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>