<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PROLOGVE,</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115421_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19758</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6185</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115421</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PROLOGVE,</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie, life, and miracles, extasies and revelations of the blessed virgin, sister Ioane, of the crosse, of the third order of our holy Father S. Francis : Composed by the Reuerend Father, brother Anthonie of Aca, diffinitor of the prouince of the conception, and chroinckler [sic] of the Order aforesaid. And translated out of Spanish into English, by a father of the same order</title>
                 <author>Daza, Antonio</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Boscard, Charles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Heigham, John (Roger)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 3-298, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>THE PROLOGVE,</head>
   <head type="sub">An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> aduertisements to the Reader, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
is declared what is Vision, Exta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies,
Raptes and other thinges most im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant
for the vnderstanding of this
historie.</head>
   <p>WIth tongues of Seraphins and spirit from
heauen I wold manifest to the worlde
the things so soueraigne, which for his honour
and glory God wrought in his faithfull and lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
espouse sister Ioane of the crosse, with whō
he so enlarged the hand of his mercie, as being
so singular as they are, they require singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
attention to reade them, and particular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion
to write them. And that I might obtaine
the same, &amp; the end of my desire, hauing visited
her holie bodie, and the places where she was
borne, liued, and dyed, and seeking with parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
care the truest papers that could be had, for
to write her life, I follow fourteene authenticke
<pb facs="7"/>
informations, and a very auncient manuscript
(which shee her selfe dictating, by commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of her Angell keeper) sister Marie Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>list
a disciple of hers did write, to whom miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously
to this effect, and to write, the booke of
sermons which the seruant of God preached, our
Lord gaue the grace to reade and write, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
she did not know it, according as by many
witnesses hath beene proued: and that after the
death of this blessed woman, she appeared to
another religious in the quire vested with splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor,
with a booke of gold open in her handes,
representinge that which she had written of
the thinges of the glorious Ioane. And to all
this authoritie, as great as it is, another is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
no lesse, which is, the miracle of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptibilitie
of her bodie, seene with my
eyes, and handled with my handes, when I
wrote this, she being incorrupte, intire, and of
excellent sauour, accordinge as to the honour
and glorie of God we will speake hereafter more
at large.</p>
   <p>So admirable are the thinges of this seruant
of God, as they oblige me, that they may better
be vnderstood, to doe not only the office of an
historian, but also of a paraphraste, with particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
annotations &amp; scholia in the margent, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
are explained many difficulties: in such sort
<pb facs="8"/>
as whosom-euer may read them, and draw most
sauorie fruite out of them. And because to some
it seemed not conuenient that they should goe
in a vulgar tongue, they haue beene reformed in
this last impression: and let this be the first ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertisement
of this Prologue.</p>
   <p>The second, that writing the life of a seruant
of God, so full of visions, reuelations, extasies,
and apparitions of Angels, and deuils, I am
bound to giue some notice of these thinges, at
least as much as a briefe Prologue permitteth.
For the which it shall be of much importance,
somewhat to vnderstand by roote the force and
proprietie of the word vision, with which ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally
are comprehended and declared all these
thinges; as with particular energie the holie
tongue declareth deriuing it from the verba Raa,
which signifieth to see with the eyes of the body
the thinges which God reuealeth, and to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand
them with the spiritual eyes of the sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le.
And hence it is, that to the Prophets to whom
God shewed so many visions and merueils, the
sacred scripture calleth them <hi>videntes</hi> with the
participle of the same verbe Haroe; and vision,
the reuelation communicated to them, which is
a kind of supernaturall knowledge. And because
in man there are three principles of knowledge,
the exterior sense, the imagination, and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding:
<pb facs="8"/>
so also the Doctors and Saints doe
reduce to three kindes of visions, all kinde of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelations
which God maketh to his seruants:
conforme to one of these principles with which
a man knoweth them. <hi>S. Banauentur. de profectu
religiosor. lib. 2. cap. 75. S. Tho. 2. 2. q. 174. a. 1.
ad.</hi> 3.</p>
   <p>The first of these visiōs, which is called, <hi>sēsitiue</hi>
is whē with the eyes of the body are seene some
things by meane of sensitiue or corporall figures,
representing to the exterior senses, which are as
it were signes or likenesses of that which God
signifieth by them, the which can not be seene
without supernaturall light, as when God shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to Abraham the misterie of the passion of his
only begotten sonne, in the lambe intangled in
the thornes. (<hi>Glossa ordinaria in the Prothe. Apocal.
ad princip. and vpon the 2. epist. ad Cor. cap. 12. Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert.
Pictaue en Glossa ord. in the preface vpon the
Apoc. Nicolas de Lyra as vpō the Prologue of Gilbert.
and cap. 1. Apoc.</hi>) The second is called, <hi>Imaginary,</hi>
when the soule without helpe of the corporall
eyes, seeth the things which God reuealeth her,
by meane of some imaginarie figure. Of this kind
of visions were those which S. Iohn saw in his
Apocalipse, being in that vniust banishment in
the ile of Patmos. The third and last of these vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions,
is, when the soule seeth &amp; knoweth cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb facs="9"/>
that which God reuealeth to her. And it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<hi>Intellectuall,</hi> because the vnderstanding, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
hauing for meane any figure of sensible thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
or imaginarie, doth know all that which
God reuealeth to her. And this last is held for the
highest and most principall of all, because it is
most like to the vision which the blessed enioy
in glorie.</p>
   <p>The raptes which the Hebrewes call Tarde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach,
which is to say, a profound sleepe, and
the Greekes Extasie, which signifieth a going
out or flight of the soule (not because the soule
goeth out of the body, and returneth to it, which
would be to grant a great error, and euery foote
death and resurrection of the bodies) but because
in raptes he which suffereth them, is as if he were
dead, or a sleepe, an effect proper to loue, which
according to S. Denis is that which causeth exta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies
in the soule, &amp; draweth a mā out of himselfe,
transforming him into that he loueth. (<hi>S. Dionis.
de diuinis nominibus cap.</hi> 4.) And this eleuation
the diuines call extasies. (<hi>S. Thomas 2. 2. q. 28. ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulo.</hi>
3.) Vnto the which rapte addeth, a certeine
kind of violēce on the parte of the obiect, which
moueth the power of the soule which rauisheth
it and strongly draweth it to it selfe (although
with mightie sweetnesse) drawing her from her
senses; the which when she is rapte in God with
<pb facs="9"/>
the force of loue, in such sorte transformeth her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
into him, that suspēding her powers, she re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paireth
for ayde to the superior portion of the
soule: and not hauing forces to resist the super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall
violence, nor able withall to repaire to
the corporall senses, she is wanting to them and
doth not giue them strength, nor sendeth the ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall
facultie to the partes of the bodie; without
the which, neither the eares can heare, nor the
eyes see, nor the nose smell, nor the taste, nor
the feeling touch. (<hi>Medina. 1. 2. q. 8. a. 3. S. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas
2. 2. 175. artic.</hi> 1.) for the which those
which are rapte, neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eele colde, nor heat,
hunger, thirste, nor wearinesse.</p>
   <p>And therefore some thinke, that when the
soule enioyeth these extasies &amp; raptes she doth
not merite in the same, nor demerite, thinking
that her libertie remayneth not entire, freely to
vse reason, as a bodie that were a sleepe. But
the same iudgement is not to be made of them
as is of ordinarie and common sleepes: for if in
these the vse of reason be hindered and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding,
in raptes it is not so, but more free
and disburdened to vnderstand and contemplate
the things which God communicateth in them
to the soule, as is easily vnderstood in looking to
the ende which God hath in these extasies and
raptes, which he giueth not to the end his fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="10"/>
lose time in them and remaine for that space
without iudgement, but that the soule gathered
together, disburdened and free of the disquiet
of the senses, more feruorously and freely may
worke. And so the workes which they doe in
the extasies and raptes, are of virtue, and done
with more light and claritie then those which
are done out of it, according as is gathered out
of the doctrine of the Saints, and we are taught
by persons, to whom God hath done so singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
fauours. (<hi>S. Thom. 1. 2. q. 113. a. 3. ad 2. so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutio</hi>
2. And thus we might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ay that Extasie, is a
profound sleepe of the soule, in which the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>g
and will are watching, and occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pying
themselues in a worke so high, the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall
sences doe faile, and remaine as it were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sleepe
to exterior things.</p>
   <p>To conclude with this matter, because I wold
neither enlarge my selfe in it, nor leaue it fasting
of so sauorie bittes, let it be cōsidered, that when
God speaketh to men, most cōmonly it is wont
to be by ministerie of the Angels, representing
the diuine person, and in his name they receiue
messages, and dispatch them, speaking not in a
third person as messingers do, who in anothers
name giue their errand, and carrie backe the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere;
but as legates, and viceroyes, who hold
the turne &amp; place of himselfe that sendeth them.
<pb facs="10"/>
This was more vsed in the old law, then in the
law of grace; in which, for the dignitie of it,
and for the loue which Christ beareth to soules,
sometimes himselfe appeareth to them, visiteth
them and comforteth them, as is manifest by
expresse places of the new testament, and the
Saints doe relate in manie histories. (<hi>S. Thomas
3. p. q. 57. a. 6. ad 3. &amp; Caiet. Suarez. 3 p. Tom.</hi> 2.)
The historie of the woundes of our holie Fa. S.
Francis is well knowen, whom our Lord Iesus
Christ visited, not by ministerie of Angels, but
in his proper person when he imprinted his
most sacred woundes in his feete, handes, and
side, as speake the Popes of glorious memorie,
Gregorie the 9. Alexander the 4. Nicolas the 3.
and Sixtus the 4. in diuerse Bulles: and is the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
of manie Saints, and authors. (<hi>Disp. 15.
sect. 4. Belarm. de Sacrament. Euchar. lib. 3. cap. 3.
Actor. cap. 9. 22. &amp; 26. ad Corinth. cap. 9. &amp; 19.
Dionis. epist. 8. ad Demophil. 8. Antonin. in vita S.
Antonij. S. Gregor. lib. 4. Dialog.</hi> 16.) And the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphicall
Father himselfe, after his death appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe
to a holie religious, told it him, in these
wordes: <hi>Ille qui mihi apparuit, non fuit Angelus,
sed fuit Dominus meus Iesus Christus, in specie se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raph.
qui sicut vulnera ipsa sacra in cruce suscepit,
ita manibus suis benedictis in corpore meo impressit:
primo manibus, deinde pedibus, postea lateri. Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta
<pb facs="11"/>
ordinis tract. 1. &amp; 2. S. Bonauent. in Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia
pauperum Tom. 7. p. 4. &amp; de sex alijs Seraphim.
Tom. 7. p.</hi> 3▪ <hi>S. Anto. 3. p. hist. tit. 24. c.</hi> 1. §. 8. <hi>S.
Bernardin. de Sena. de euangel. aetern. serm. 60. a.
1. cap. 1. &amp; serm. de stigmatib. S. Francis. a 1. cap.
1. Tom. 2. Angel del Pus in expositione symboli Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolor.
lib. 8. cap. 19. Chroni. antiq. 1. p. lib. 2. cap.
55. Rodulph. historia seraphica lib. 1. cap. 12. &amp; lib.
2. fol. 264. Bartholome. de Pisa. in conform. lib. 2.
&amp; 3. Boragines serm. 1. de stigmatibus S. Francisci.
Robertus de Licio Bishop of Aquitania serm. de S.
Catharina de Sena. cap. 3. &amp; serm. S. Francisci Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaga
Bishop of Mantua. 2. p. fol. 327. &amp; 241. specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum
B. Francisci. fol. 98. Gerardus Odon. in offici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
stigmatum B. Francisci. Leonardus de Vtino. serm. de
B. Francis. Biga salutis. serm. de sacris stigmatibus.
S. Franc. Bernardinus de Bustis in rosario serm. 72.
Mathew Palmerius in additionibus ad Chronicon Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sebij.
Mairones serm. de S. Francis. Truxille in thesau.
serm. de S. Francisco. Bartholo. de Pisa. confort. 31.
lib.</hi> 3.</p>
   <p>And our Lord is wont to make these appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
descending to the earth, and together re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining
in heauen; which although to our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parance
difficult, is not to God impossible, yea
rather among learned men, it is an opinion ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
probable and secure, as also it is in good phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke,
and theologie, which Scotus teacheth with
<pb facs="11"/>
manie others which follow him, that one and
the same bodie, by the power diuine, may be
at once quantitatiuely in two places distinct and
different. The Angels when they appeare and
speake to the Saints, and the diuels when they
torment and scourge, take (for to exercise these
actions) bodies apparant and phantastike of ayre
imperfectly mixte, applying actiue things to pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siue,
as teaceth the subtilitie of Scotus, and the
glorious Father. S. Augustine. And although
it be true, that these bodies in which they shew
themselues and appeare, are not true bodies of
flesh and bloud as ours are, (for according to S.
Thomas, to worke properly these things, which
are vitall actions, they ought to be the soule of
the same bodie in which they appeare, and as the
forme thereof to animate it:) yet for all this, so
great is the force which the spirites haue aboue
all things corporall and visible, as they doe with
them what they wil, moouing the tongue of the
body feinedly, to speake, the feete to go, the eyes
to see, and with the same facilitie, that the soule
doth serue her selfe of her members, the spirite
serueth it selfe of these which it maketh. For to
as much as this commeth the power of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell
good or euill. And let this serue the curious
reader, for the vnderstandinge of manie thinges
which shall occurre vnto him in the discourse of
<pb facs="12"/>
the life of this seruant of God. <hi>Ioannes Mai. 4.
sent. d. 10. q. 4. Suar. 3. p. Tom. 2. q. 58. disp. 51.
sect. 4. Scotus lib. 4. dist. 10. per multas qq. &amp; in 2.
Alex. de Hales, 4. p. q. 11. a. l.</hi> §. <hi>vlt. Gab. lib. 4.
q. 1. a. 1. &amp; lect. 46. in Canon. Belar. lib. 3. de Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char.
cap. 3. &amp; 4. &amp; tract. 4. physicor. q. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Scot.
2. senten. dist. 18. q. 1. S. August. lib. de Gen. ad li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teram
cap. 10. S. Tho. 1. p. q. 51. a.</hi> 3.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>