<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE NOBLE AND Right virtuous Knight, Sir IOHN EGERTON, increase of true honour in this life, and fruition of true glory in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Rawlinson, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115678_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10496</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20772</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115678</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE NOBLE AND Right virtuous Knight, Sir IOHN EGERTON, increase of true honour in this life, and fruition of true glory in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Rawlinson, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Fishermen fishers of men : A sermon preached at Mercers Chapell on Mid-Lent Sunday the 26. of March 1609. By Iohn Ravvlinson Doctour of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Rawlinson, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Barrett, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Blount (Blunt), Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hatfield, Arnold</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE NOBLE AND Right virtuous Knight, Sir IOHN EGERTON, increase of <hi>true honour</hi> in this life, and fruition of <hi>true glory</hi> in the life to come.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>WORTHY SIR;</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> Must acknowledge my selfe to haue long run vpon the score; so long, till <hi>Vsura superat sortē;</hi> the <hi>interest</hi> of your loue exceeds the <hi>principall</hi> of my abilities: all which (if they be ought) you may therfore challenge as due debt, and arrest them to bee continually at your seruice.</p>
   <p>Yet rather than I will shew my selfe a right bank-rupt, most vnkinde to him that hath best deserued, and play off so kinde a Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour with <hi>Non sum soluendo;</hi> I will grow to a faire and honest composition, and pay you (as I may) though it be but <hi>Vnciatim.</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>O that I could truly say with that seruant in the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 18 26.</note> Gospel! <hi>Sir, haue patience with me, and I will pay you all.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But<note n="(b)" place="margin">Bernar.</note>
      <hi>exonerando me magis onero;</hi> The more J labour to requite, the more J ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige my selfe. For what doe J now but <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suram soluere,</hi> borrow both of your pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and protection to cleare the debt of your former fauours?</p>
   <p>Ʋery likely that while J thus launch forth into the deep, and cast my nette vpon the face of the waters, it will fare with me as with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fisher-men, who among many fish meet with some <hi>Carps</hi> and if (by chance) they alight vpon a sturdy <hi>Iack,</hi> there is great tug betwixt them, whether they shall catch the Jack, or the Jack them. But in this case J am of <hi>Seneca's</hi> resolution;<note n="(d)" place="margin">Senec. epist. <hi>59.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Cupio, si fieri potest, proitijs auribus quid senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, dicere; sin minus, dicam &amp; iratis.</hi> And yet I hope without breach of charity too.
<pb facs="3"/>
      <note n="(e)" place="margin">Gloss. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlin.</note>
      <hi>Charitas ad saluandum violenta est.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>What allowance soeuer it shall find abroad, it humbly craues your fauourable acceptance at home: yea, it also presumes, that because it is your <hi>infant</hi> (for, but for you, it had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer seene light) it shall also be <hi>heire</hi> of your fauour; <hi>Nato filio nata portio.</hi> And that because<note n="(f)" place="margin">Marsil. Ficin. in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist.</note>
      <hi>Mercurius ante omnes stel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Phoebo semper est domesticus;</hi> Your self, who are learned <hi>Suprasortem supra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulgarem,</hi> will gladly patronise <hi>the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> of Diuines, which is the maine matter of this Sermon;</p>
   <p>A matter (if any other) very materiall &amp; necessary for these daies, because as a spice of all other diseases attends vpon the ague; and, <hi>Ad ignorationem elenchi reduci possunt omnes paralogismi:</hi> So the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and slender regard of Gods Ministers is the matter and mother of all other enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb facs="4"/>which so plentifully reigne in this irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular age of ours.</p>
   <p>Whatsoeuer it is else, it is the <hi>Votoria ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bula</hi> of my loue consecrated to the <hi>Temple</hi> of your <hi>Honor,</hi> which shall daily be frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with my praiers vnto God; That as you, and your honourable good Lady are here <hi>Gemini in terra caro vna;</hi> so hereafter ye may be for euer <hi>Gemini in coelo, sydus vnum:</hi> And that both the <hi>hopefull</hi> and <hi>hoped fruits</hi> of both your bodies may bee as truly heires of both your virtues, as your self are of the manifold graces and blessings of your most honoured and honour-worthy <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> whose vnworthy, but most obseruant <hi>seruant</hi> J am, and hartilie ioy to be.</p>
   <p>And, as <hi>Coelum quietem suam sorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in motu;</hi> So in continuance of these my humble and hartie praiers vnto God for you, and yours, J shall euer rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your most deuoted debtor, <hi>Iohn Ravvlinson.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>