<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honorable, the Lord Ro∣bert Dudley, Earle of Leice∣ster, one of her Maiesties priuie Councell, and Chauncellour of the Vniuersitie of Oxford, grace and peace be multiplied.</title>
           <author>Reynolds, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115546_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10345</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20626</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115546</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honorable, the Lord Ro∣bert Dudley, Earle of Leice∣ster, one of her Maiesties priuie Councell, and Chauncellour of the Vniuersitie of Oxford, grace and peace be multiplied.</title>
                 <author>Reynolds, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The summe of the conference betwene Iohn Rainoldes and Iohn Hart : touching the head and the faith of the Church. Wherein by the way are handled sundrie points, of the sufficiencie and right expounding of the Scriptures, the ministerie of the Church, the function of priesthood, the sacrifice of the masse, with other controuerises of religion: but chiefly and purposely the point of Church-gouernment ... Penned by Iohn Rainoldes, according to the notes set downe in writing by them both: perused by Iohn Hart, and (after things supplied, &amp; altered, as he thought good) allowed for the faithfull report of that which past in conference betwene them. Whereto is annexed a treatise intitled, Six conclusions touching the Holie Scripture and the Church, writen by Iohn Rainoldes. With a defence of such thinges as Thomas Stapleton and Gregorie Martin haue carped at therein</title>
                 <author>Rainolds, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>475, 1, 479-674, 659-750 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Honorable, the Lord Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Dudley, Earle of Leice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, one of her Maiesties priuie Councell, and Chauncellour of the Vniuersitie of Oxford, grace and peace be multiplied.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He beginning of Schooles and Vniuersities (right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable) in the Church of God, doth shew that they were planted to bee <note n="a" place="margin">1. Sam. 19.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>▪ 2. King. 2.5. &amp; 4.8.</note> nurse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>Prophets</hi>: who, being instructed in the truth of his word, might deliuer it to men; and lighten, as starres, the darkenesse of the world with the beames of it. But it hath come to passe by deuises of the <hi>dragon,</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Reue. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>whose taile drew the third part of the starres of heauen, &amp; cast them to the earth,</hi> that they haue bene turned into seminaries of false Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: to maintaine errours and the power of darkenesse, against the light and truth of Christ.
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>
The primitiue Church had experience hereof in them <note n="c" place="margin">Act. 6. ver. 9.</note>
      <hi>of the Synagogue of Libertines, and Cyrenians, who disputed with Steuen.</hi> A lesson for the faithfull in the ages to folow, that they should not thinke it strange, or be dismayed, if Schooles &amp; Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities of men professing wisedome were posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed of folie, and sought to peruert the straight wayes of the Lord. The consideration whereof, as it was needefull for our predecessours, when Rabbines of the Iewes, Philosophers of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thēs, Sorbonists amōg Christians, being seduced themselues, seduced others: so haue the Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of our English students (erected by the Pope of late at Rome and Rhemes) made it needeful also for vs at this day. The more: how much the nerer their dealings do come to those of <hi>the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of Libertines &amp; Cyrenians.</hi> For as they defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <note n="d" place="margin">ver. 14.</note> the Iewish opinions receiued by tradition from their Fathers: so do the Seminaries the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish superstitions. As they did pretend the care of religion, <note n="e" place="margin">ver. 11.</note> of <hi>Moses, and God,</hi> the law, &amp; the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: so do the Seminaries, of the Catholike faith, the Scriptures, and the Church. As the meanes they vsed were sclanders of Steuen, <note n="f" place="margin">ver. 13.</note> that <hi>he spake blasphemous wordes against the holy place, and the law</hi>: so do the Seminaries charge vs with reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="5" facs="3"/>
from the holy Church, and corrupting the Scriptures. I am not worthie to be compared with the least ofthe seruants of God, who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at that time, in which he powred the giftes of his holy spirit from heauen so a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly. Howbeit, as it pleased him to rayse Steuen to <hi>dispute with some of the Iewish Synagogue</hi>: so hath he vouchsafed me of this fauour, that I should be called to conferre with certaine ofthe Popish Seminaries. Of whom, one, contented to proceede farther therin then the rest; by writing, not by word onely: hath giuen occasion ofthis, which here I publish. Wherein how indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he hath bene dealt with: himselfe hath decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. My conscience, for mine owne part, beareth me witnesse that I haue endeuored to defend the cause of the same truth, with the same purpose, by the same principles, &amp; groūds, that <note n="g" place="margin">Act. 7.2.</note>
      <hi>Steuē</hi> did. Wishing from my hart, (if so it please God,) that it may preuaile more with English Papists, then <hi>Steuens</hi> speech did with the Iewish Priests. But ready (by his grace) to endure their spite, ifthey hate me for telling them the truth, as the Iewes did him. Now, sith Luke, who penned the story of <hi>Steuen,</hi> sent it to <note n="h" place="margin">Act. 1.1.</note>
      <hi>Theophilus,</hi>
      <note n="i" place="margin">Luk. 1.3.</note>
      <hi>most noble The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophilus:</hi> I haue bene the bolder to present my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
<pb n="6" facs="4"/>
vnto you, right Honorable; aduanced, in state, to be of the <hi>most noble</hi>; in minde, a <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus,</hi> and louer ofthe truth. Your benefites both publikely to our Vniuersitie, in maintenance of our priuileges; &amp; priuately to me ward, a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thereof: haue bound me to offer this testifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>on of a thankefull minde. And sith it hath bene (I know) a greefe vnto you, that the Popish <hi>Synagogue</hi> hath drawne <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 23.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>proselytes</hi> thence: I thought it most meete that the labours spent with one so withdrawne, and printed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime them who are gon, if may bee, or at least to stay them who are not gon, should bring him the salue whom the sore had touched neerest. Which moueth me withall to beseech your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, that, as you haue begoon, so you will go forward in being carefull for our nurserie: that they, who haue the charge of husbanding it, may fense it and dresse it faithfully and wisely; that neither the wild boare of the forest, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vermin may anoy it; that <note n="l" place="margin">Ezek. 47.12.</note>
      <hi>the fruites of the trees therof</hi> may <hi>serue for meate, &amp; the leaues for me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, through waters running out of the sanctuarie</hi>; and <note n="m" place="margin">Gen. 3.9.</note>
      <hi>the tree of life</hi> may <hi>grow in the middest of it,</hi> as in the garden of <hi>Eden</hi> planted by the Lord. So shall you leaue a most worthie monument of
<pb n="7" facs="4"/>
a <hi>noble Theophilus</hi>: the reward whereof shall folow from God, <note n="n" place="margin">Psal. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>▪ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>who will render to euery man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his workes</hi>; the remēbrance shall rest in the Christian Church and common wealth ofEngland, to your eternall praise throughout all posteritie. The Lord of his mercie blesse you with continuall increase of the graces of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly spirite: specially of that, <note n="o" place="margin">1. Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>▪</note>
      <hi>which hath the promise of this life, and of the life to come,</hi> to your endlesse comfort, through Iesu Christ the Lord of life. At London, the eighteenth of Iuly. 1584.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours in Christ at commaundement, Iohn Rainoldes.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>