<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY CHRISTIAN AND LOVING PARISHIO∣NERS OF CHRISTS CHVRCH IN LONDON.</title>
           <author>Price, Sampson</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115217_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10080</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20334</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115217</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY CHRISTIAN AND LOVING PARISHIO∣NERS OF CHRISTS CHVRCH IN LONDON.</title>
                 <author>Price, Sampson</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The two twins of birth and death : A sermon preached in Christs Church in London, the 5. of September. 1624. By Samson Price, Doctor of Diuinitie, one of his Majesties chapleins in ordinarie. Vpon the occasion of the funeralls of Sir William Byrde Knight. Doctor of the Law, deane of the Arches, and iudge of the Prerogatiue Court of the Archbishop of Canterburie</title>
                 <author>Price, Sampson</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Hodgets, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 47, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO MY CHRISTIAN AND LOVING PARISHIO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NERS OF CHRISTS CHVRCH IN LONDON.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <hi>Beloued</hi> in Christ
<hi>Jesus:</hi>
      </salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T</hi> is the promise of the Word, that the
<hi>righteous</hi> shall be in euerlasting remembrance,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 112.6.</note> as registred in the booke of
<hi>eternall</hi> life, so graciously mentioned to the ioy of posterity in <hi>this</hi> life.<note place="margin">Chrisost:</note> The best
<hi>monument</hi> is not in stately houses, strong walls, high Towers, glorious Sepulchers,<note place="margin">Antomin: <hi>1.</hi> P. Tit. <hi>2.</hi> C. <hi>9.</hi> S. <hi>2.</hi>
      </note> but in righteous actions, grounded vpon
<hi>memory,</hi> which considering the infirmity of nature, losse by sinne, examples of the good, folly of the wicked, necessity of the miserable, and looking vpon God, as a Creatour, Redeemer, Rewarder, maketh a man liue according to his will reuealed in his Word;<note place="margin">
         <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.8.</note> in doing <hi>iustly,</hi> louing
<hi>mercy,</hi> and walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>humbly.</hi> The memoriall of such a one I
<pb facs="3"/>present to you (and to those whosoeuer shall reade this passage from <hi>birth</hi> to <hi>death</hi>) in Sir
<hi>William Byrde</hi> deceased and gone to the <hi>Lord,</hi> whom I know
<hi>you</hi> esteemed <hi>Inter raros &amp; paucos ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellentissimae gratiae viros,</hi> Amongst those few choise <hi>pearles</hi> of excellent parts,<note place="margin">Aug. de Cyp. li. <hi>6.</hi> de Baptismo</note> left in these de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying times. Vnperfect it is, and this <hi>birth</hi> had died as soone as it had beene borne (<hi>without pressing</hi>) had not I perceiued how tender it was taken among some, and earnestly desired to be published by others. We shall learne to liue well by remembring our
<hi>death,</hi> and wee shall liue to <hi>God</hi> if we dye to the world. As long as I am in this <hi>Tabernacle</hi> I shall put you in remembrance of this,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Peter</hi> 1.13.</note> that you may loue the
<hi>Lord</hi> your <hi>God,</hi> walke in his wayes, keepe his commaundements, statutes, iudgments, &amp; liue, &amp; multiply, &amp; that the <hi>Lord</hi> our <hi>God</hi> may blesse you: and we may be preserued and deliuered at the houre of <hi>death</hi> and day of <hi>iudgement.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From the new Rents in your Parish,</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>Octob. 18. 1624.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Yours in Christ Jesus, <hi>Samson Price.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>