<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONO∣RABLE, L. IOHN LVM∣LEY, BARON OF LVMLEY. &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Hood, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115226_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03580</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13701</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115226</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONO∣RABLE, L. IOHN LVM∣LEY, BARON OF LVMLEY. &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Hood, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vse of the two mathematicall instruments : the crosse staffe, (differing from that in common vse with the mariners:) and the Iacobs staffe: set foorth dialogue wise in two briefe and plaine treatises: the one most commodious for the mariner, and all such as are to deale in astronomicall matters: the other, profitable for the surueyor, to take the length, height, depth, or breadth, of any thing measurable. Set forth by Th. Hood. mathematicall lecturer in the citie of London. Newly reviewed, and the second time imprinted. The staues are to be sold in Marke lane, at the house of Francis Cooke</title>
                 <author>Hood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Dexter, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE, L. IOHN LVM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEY, BARON OF LVMLEY. &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that I had penned (Right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable) the vse of the Crosse staffe, I was desired by mine acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to take the paines in the Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs staffe. I did so: my paines were liked and called (as the former) vnto the presse. Without a Patrone I would not haue it come forth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I would not be thought to bee without a Patrone. To rrouble one man with them both, I thought it not good, least I should seeme forgetfull of other my well-willers: among whom your good will, shewed vnto me at diuerse times, hath emboldened me to craue your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage for the thing, which if it shall please your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to vndertake, I shall accompt it as a speciall token of your louing fauour, and acknowledge myselfe in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence, bound to pray for your Honours daily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease in all kindes of blessings.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours most <hi>humble. Th. Hood.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>