<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Vision of Sir George Ripley, Chanon of Bridlington.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115988_Fr1_9</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10786</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21057</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115988</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Vision of Sir George Ripley, Chanon of Bridlington.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The compound of alchymy. Or The ancient hidden art of archemie : conteining the right &amp; perfectest meanes to make the philosophers stone, aurum potabile, with other excellent experiments. Diuided into twelue gates. First written by the learned and rare philosopher of our nation George Ripley, sometime Chanon of Bridlington in Yorkeshyre: &amp; dedicated to K. Edvvard the 4. Whereunto is adioyned his epistle to the King, his vision, his wheele, &amp; other his workes, neuer before published: with certaine briefe additions of other notable writers concerning the same. Set foorth by Raph Rabbards Gentleman, studious and expert in archemicall artes</title>
                 <author>Ripley, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>104 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>The Vision of Sir <hi>George Ripley,</hi> Chanon of Bridlington.</head>
   <l>WHen busie at my booke I was vpon a certaine night,</l>
   <l>This Vision here exprest appear'd vnto my dimmed sight,</l>
   <l>A toade full rudde I saw did drinke the iuice of grapes so fast,</l>
   <l>Till ouercharged with the broath, his bowells all to brast,</l>
   <l>And after that from poysoned bulke, he cast his venome fell,</l>
   <l>For griefe and paine whereof his members all began to swell;</l>
   <l>With drops of poysoned sweate approching thus his secret den,</l>
   <l>His caue with blasts of fumous ayre, he all bewhited then:</l>
   <l>And from the which in space a golden humor did ensue,</l>
   <l>Whose falling drops frō high did staine the soile with ruddy hew,</l>
   <l>And when his corps, the force of vitall breath began to lacke,</l>
   <l>This dying toade became forthwith like coale for colour black:</l>
   <l>Thus drowned in his proper Veynes of poysoned flood,</l>
   <l>For tear me of eightie dayes and foure he rotting stood:</l>
   <l>By tryall then this venome to expell I did desire,</l>
   <l>For which J did commit his carkase to a gentle fire:</l>
   <l>Which done, a wonder to the sight, but more to be rehearst,</l>
   <l>The toade with colours rare through euery side was pearst:</l>
   <l>And white appear'd when all the sundry hewes were past:</l>
   <l>Which after being tincted, rudde for euermore did last:</l>
   <l>Then of the venome handled thus a medicine I did make,</l>
   <l>Which venom kills, and saueth such as venome chaunce to take,</l>
   <l>Glory be to him the graunter of such secret wayes,</l>
   <l>Dominion, and Honour, both with worship and with prayse.</l>
   <closer>AMEN.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>