<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE QUEENE OF GREAT BRITAINE.</title>
           <author>Serre, P. de la</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115329_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68615</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20490</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115329</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE QUEENE OF GREAT BRITAINE.</title>
                 <author>Serre, P. de la</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The mirrour which flatters not : Dedicated to their Maiesties of Great Britaine, by Le Sieur de la Serre, historiographer of France. Enriched with faire figures. Transcrib'd English from the French, by T.C. And devoted to the well-disposed readers</title>
                 <author>Puget de La Serre, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, Elizabeth</publisher>
                    <distributor>Thrale, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 48, 45-59, 1, 71-228, 18 pages, illustrations (metal cuts), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>TO THE QUEENE OF GREAT <hi>BRITAINE.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MADAME,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> Could not <hi>approach,</hi> but with a <hi>MIRROVR</hi> in my <hi>hand,</hi> before your <hi>Majestie,</hi> the <hi>splendour</hi> of whose <hi>mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence</hi> dazles so power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully all the <hi>world,</hi> that I am not able to behold the <hi>immediate presence</hi> on't, but by the <hi>reflection</hi> of its <hi>Rayes.</hi> Without fiction, <hi>MADAME,</hi> your <hi>Glory</hi> is
<pb facs="7"/>arrived to the <hi>point</hi> of rendring your <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections</hi> so unknowne, as being so above the <hi>commune;</hi> that I beleeve most men <hi>honour you</hi> now by <hi>observance</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample</hi> onely, as not able <hi>otherwise</hi> to <hi>reach</hi> the depth of the <hi>just reasons</hi> they might have for it. Nor is this <hi>All,</hi> to say that you are <hi>solely faire,</hi> and <hi>perfectly chaste;</hi> but it is <hi>necessarie,</hi> beyond all <hi>this,</hi> to <hi>intimate secretly,</hi> in the <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage</hi> of <hi>Thought,</hi> all the <hi>divine qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities</hi> which you <hi>possesse</hi> of <hi>Super-emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence</hi> in all <hi>things,</hi> since their <hi>puritie</hi> cannot discend to the <hi>capacitie</hi> of our <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course,</hi> without suffering a kind of <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation.</hi> From hence is it, that if I should call you, <hi>THE COMPLEATLY-PERFECT,</hi> I might well say in effect that which you are; but <hi>never</hi> thus should I represent the <hi>greatnesse</hi> of your <hi>merits,</hi> since every of <hi>them</hi> in it selfe has such <hi>particular perfections,</hi> as might challenge
<pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>Altars</hi> from us, if your <hi>humilitie</hi> could permit it. These are such <hi>Truths (MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAME)</hi> as hinder me from <hi>praysing</hi> your <hi>Majestie,</hi> not knowing how to <hi>expresse</hi> my selfe <hi>condignely.</hi> Well might I perhaps suggest it to <hi>remembrance,</hi> that your <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular inclinations</hi> are the <hi>publike Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues</hi> which we <hi>adore,</hi> and that of the same <hi>temperament</hi> of humour, <hi>Nature</hi> composed heretofore the <hi>Sages</hi> of the <hi>World:</hi> But of all these <hi>discourses</hi> notwithstanding, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not frame one onely <hi>prayse</hi> sufficiently <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aequate</hi> to your <hi>worth,</hi> seeing 'tis <hi>elevated</hi> beyond all <hi>Eulogiums.</hi> Insomuch, that if <hi>Admiration</hi> it selfe teach not a new <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage</hi> to <hi>posteritie,</hi> wherein to proclaime <hi>aloud</hi> the <hi>favours</hi> and <hi>graces</hi> wherewith <hi>Heaven</hi> hath accomplisht you; it must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent it selfe, to <hi>reverence</hi> your <hi>Name,</hi> and <hi>adore</hi> your <hi>Memorie,</hi> without presumption of <hi>speech</hi> of your <hi>actions,</hi> as being <hi>ever</hi> above all <hi>valuation,</hi> as well as <hi>imitation.</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>To instance the <hi>immortalitie</hi> of your <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GUSTICK Race,</hi> although it be a pure <hi>Source of Honour,</hi> which can never be <hi>dry'd up;</hi> yet all these <hi>Titles</hi> of a <hi>Kings Daughter, Sister,</hi> and <hi>Wife,</hi> can never adde to your <hi>Renowne,</hi> which derives its <hi>value</hi> rather from the <hi>admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities</hi> of your <hi>Life,</hi> then the <hi>greatnesse</hi> of your <hi>Birth.</hi> Insomuch <hi>(MADAME)</hi> that the <hi>Scepters</hi> and <hi>Crownes</hi> of your <hi>Royalties,</hi> are the meanest <hi>Ornaments</hi> wherewith your <hi>Majestie</hi> can <hi>decke</hi> it selfe; since the least glympse of the least of your <hi>Actions,</hi> duskes the luster of all the other <hi>magnificences,</hi> which environ you. And I beleeve, had those <hi>Wonders of the World</hi> beene of such a <hi>worth,</hi> as every day you <hi>descry,</hi> they had power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully <hi>resisted</hi> against the <hi>assaults</hi> of <hi>Ages:</hi> but as they had nothing <hi>admirable</hi> in them, but the <hi>Name, Memorials</hi> have <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served that,</hi> and let <hi>them perish.</hi> But
<pb facs="8"/>yours <hi>(MADAME)</hi> which are <hi>too perfect</hi> for a <hi>sutable Name,</hi> shall not cease to <hi>survive</hi> the <hi>revolutions</hi> of <hi>Times,</hi> as being <hi>enlivened</hi> by <hi>Vertue,</hi> which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone can exempt from <hi>Death.</hi> Let it not seeme <hi>strange</hi> then, if I hazard the <hi>perils</hi> of the <hi>Sea,</hi> to render <hi>Homage</hi> to a <hi>QUEENE,</hi> whose <hi>Greatnesse</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force <hi>humbles</hi> the most <hi>arrogant spirits,</hi> being not able, so much as in <hi>thought,</hi> to <hi>reach</hi> to the <hi>first degree</hi> of her <hi>Glory.</hi> The <hi>GRACES</hi> themselves are <hi>hers,</hi> and the <hi>VERTUES</hi> have <hi>allianced</hi> their <hi>owne</hi> and <hi>her Name;</hi> and all the <hi>adorable qualities</hi> which are found here <hi>below,</hi> are <hi>admirable</hi> in her <hi>alone,</hi> as in their <hi>Source.</hi> I am constrained to be <hi>silent (MADAME)</hi> being over-charged with too much <hi>subject</hi> of <hi>speech.</hi> The <hi>number</hi> of your <hi>Perfections</hi> astonishes me, the <hi>greatnesse</hi> of your <hi>Merit</hi> ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes me, the <hi>splendour</hi> of your <hi>Vertue</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>dazles me: And in this <hi>dazle,</hi> this <hi>trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,</hi> this excesse of <hi>admiration,</hi> wherein my <hi>senses</hi> and <hi>spirits</hi> are all alike <hi>enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,</hi> I am compell'd to cast my selfe at the <hi>feet</hi> of your <hi>Majestie,</hi> and demand <hi>pardon</hi> of the boldnesse which I assume onely to enjoy the <hi>stile</hi> of</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>MADAME,</salute>
      <signed>Your <hi>MAIESTIES Most humble, and most obeysant Servant, P.</hi> De la <hi>SERRE.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>