<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ADVERTISMENT TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115551_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10352</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20632</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115551</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ADVERTISMENT TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A refutation of sundry reprehensions, cauils, and false sleightes, by which M. Whitaker laboureth to deface the late English translation, and Catholike annotations of the new Testament, and the booke of Discouery of heretical corruptions. By William Rainolds, student of diuinitie in the English Colledge at Rhemes</title>
                 <author>Rainolds, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Verstegan (Rowlands), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>France--Paris</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>92, 4, 561, 27 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>AN ADVERTISMENT TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEREAS of late in the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer disputations we haue seene that learned and holy man F. Campian, so much disgraced both in priuate speach and publike writing, because in citing a place of Luther touching S. Iames epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, he missed the print wherin the place was to be founde, the later editions of his workes differing notably from the
<pb n="85" facs="43"/>
former,<note place="margin">The hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes alter their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually.</note> which chopping &amp; chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging is cōmon to the most heretical writers of our time: for feare of like inconuenience, I haue thought it good amongst many, to note the print of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine bookes, which in this treatise are oftē times alleaged. Know thou there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (Christiā reader) that in citing Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I alwaies meane the print of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tēberg set forth by Melanch. in diuers yeres, the second Tome the yere 1551. the fift 1554. the seuenth 1557. In citing Zuinglius I meane his workes as they were set forth after his death by his sonne in law Rodolphus, without name of place or printer. M. Foxes Actes and Monumentes, I vnderstād as they were printed the yere 1563 by Iohn Day. Bezaes notes vpon the new testament I meane as they were printed at Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua, the yere 1556. Sleidan I cite after the printe of Strasburg the yere 1566. Castalios bible, after the printe of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sile, the yere 1556. Caluins Institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as he last of al digested them into bookes and chapters, and printed them at Geneua. Thus generally, except I note otherwise in the margent. Other bookes which haue not so much vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie (although some be in more prints
<pb n="86" facs="44"/>
then one) be they latin or english, I commonly note not only according to the chapter, but also according to the page or leafe, as I do also the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named, that thou maist with so much the more facilitie finde out the places quoted, and so better iudge of the matter rreated.</p>
   <p>Next, whereas some are offended with vs, for that in writing or speaking of them,<note place="margin">Of the name, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants and Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries.</note> we vse the names of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries, Zuinglians or Caluinistes, Puritanes, and Parlament Protestantes, which they say are odious nicknames found out of vs,<note place="margin">Ful. in the Answere to M. Martins preface. pa. 17.</note> and therefore one of their writers of late chargeth vs in speaking of them to vse no other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes then <hi>Christians and Catholikes</hi>: for our discharge herein thus much I must signifie vnto thee, that if ether truth &amp; learning would beare vs vsing such termes as they require, or any reader ether Catholike or Protestant vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand vs, we would most gladly for loue of the truth and their conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation so speake and write. But now consider thou how intolerably such speaches would soūd in the eares of any indifferent reader. I haue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion sometimes to produce Luther
<pb n="87" facs="44"/>
writing <hi>Contra fanaticos Sacramētariorū spiritus, against the fanatical spirites of the Sacramentaries,</hi> sometimes <hi>Contra Zuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glium et discipulos eius, against Zuinglius &amp; his disciples,</hi> sometime D. Whitgift against the <hi>Puritanes,</hi> (for so he calleth them) sometimes the Puritanes against him and such as maintaine the Cōmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion booke and religion of England, in such sort and so far forth as is appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by Acte of parlament. Now citing these writers how can we cite them without a lie, if we cited them in other wordes then themselues vse? If I said <hi>Luther in his booke against the fanatical spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of the Christians &amp; Catholikes,</hi> or, <hi>D. VVhitg. in his Defense against the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and Catholikes,</hi> who could ether per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue what I meant, or who would not iudge that I did them great iniury in making them to write against <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> which none do but Iewes &amp; Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, or against <hi>Catholikes</hi> vvhich none do but heretikes and Apostataes. And marueil it is, that the name of <hi>Protestātes</hi> is novv grovven into so great dislike, vvhich hitherto hath bene so magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in bookes, pulpits, and ordinarie phrase of talke, and vvhich M.<note place="margin">Pag. 653. &amp; 1717.</note> Fox in his huge volume of Actes and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes
<pb n="88" facs="45"/>
alvvayes vseth as most proper to their gospel, &amp; maketh it opposite sometimes to <hi>Papistes,</hi> somtimes to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes,</hi> which he vseth for one.</p>
   <p>But the truth is, those that professe the English faith and religion,<note place="margin">Those that professe the English re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, are not Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes.</note> ether haue no name at al to be knovven by but the common name of heretikes, vvhich is to general, and vvould be to odious, or their most propre name is <hi>Zuinglians</hi> or <hi>Sacramentaries.</hi> For to cal them <hi>Catholikes</hi> and <hi>Christians,</hi> besides that it is false and ridiculous, and may vvith like probabilitie be cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged of euery other kind of secte, Lutheran,<note place="margin">Brentius et Lutherani passim. See before. pa. 39.</note> Brentian, Arrian, Puritan, besides that their greatest vvriters mocke and scorne at the name <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike</hi> as Popish and superstitious, besides this I say, it expresseth not that particular religion, in vvhich they differre from the rest of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian vvorld, for vvhich vve vvrite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them, and for vvhich the Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranes oppose thē selues against them, and vvhich by their name ought spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to be signified.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Nor Protes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants.</note>The name of <hi>Protestantes,</hi> which commonly they vsurpe, is wrongfully chalenged of them, as which duely &amp;
<pb n="89" facs="45"/>
only belongeth to the Lutheranes,<note place="margin">Sleidan. li. 6 fol. 102.101.109.</note> who for opposing them selues against the decrees of the Empyre &amp; Emperour touching Catholike religion, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testing that they would stand in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of their owne, according to the Confession exhibited at Auspurg, were first for their so doing and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testing, named <hi>Protestantes,</hi> as much to say, as men that stood and protested against the Catholike faith for their priuate, in such sort as hath bene no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. From which Confession of theirs as likewise from al other communion,<note place="margin">Ibid. lib. 7. fol. 110. et 114. et lib. 8. fol. 128.131.</note> those of the English religion, vvere by the name of <hi>Zuinglians</hi> expresly excluded.</p>
   <p>And briefly, that no other name can be duely applied vnto them besides the name of <hi>Zuinglians,</hi> by this reason it may playnely appeare.<note place="margin">Those of the English fayth, are most pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly called Zuinglians, or Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries.</note> When they brake from the rest of the Christian vvorld, vvhich they say vvas couered vvith palpable darkenes, and betooke them selues to that light of the gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, vvhereof novv they so much brag and boast, vvho vvas their maister, ringleader, and Apostle therein, but Huldericus Zuinglius? So much they vvrite most euidently in the Apologie
<pb n="90" facs="46"/>
of their English church.<note place="margin">Apol. Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siae Anglica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae. d. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>In the middest of that darknes</hi> (say they) <hi>those most excellent men, Martin Luther, and Hulderike Zuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glius sent from God to illuminate the vvhole vvorld, first came to the Gospel. Missi à Deo ad illustrandum terrarum orbem, primū accesse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt ad Euangelium.</hi> Now whereas them selues &amp; al other, name those gospel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers which folow Luthers sense and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, by the name of <hi>Lutherans,</hi> they vvho prefer Zuinglius before Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and professe them selues to haue receaued the light of the Gospel from him, hovv should they be called but <hi>Zuinglians</hi>? not only for like reason, vvhich hath bene vsed in al times and ages from the first beginning of the primitiue Church, vvhere the Secte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maisters haue geuen appellation to their after-commers, as in Marcion, Va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lentinus, Carpocrates, Nouatus &amp; the rest, but much more and especially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause them selues chalenge him for their maister in their particular faith and religion. And therefore it can not be avoided, but as <hi>Luthers</hi> scholers, are called <hi>Lutherans,</hi> so <hi>Zuinglius</hi> disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ought of like right to be called <hi>Zuinglians.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And to end this quarel, our aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="91" facs="46"/>
them selues who haue written of these matters, shal serue to quite vs of al fault. M. Fox in his storie when soeuer he speaketh of that sect vvhich him self best-liked,<note place="margin">
         <p>Protestants Hussites. Gospellers. See before pa. 16.</p>
         <p>Actes and monumen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes pa. 901.902.</p>
         <p>Ibid pa. 993. aeditionis postremae. Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries.</p>
         <p>Lutherans. Zuinglians. These na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes them selues vse, besides a more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral name vsed and confirmed by Act of Parlament. see before pag 21. Sleid. lib. 8. fol. 128.131.133. et lib. 9. fol. 150. Ibid. lib. 7. fol. 107. et lib. 20. fol. 368. lib. 21. fol. 382.390 ibid. lib. 5. fol. 75.78.</p>
      </note> ordinarily calleth them, sometime <hi>Protestants,</hi> sometime <hi>Hussites,</hi> sometime at large, <hi>men forward in promoting the proceedings of the gospel,</hi> sometime more briefly, <hi>Gospellers.</hi> And writing precisely of the diuision be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvvene Luther and Zuinglius he saith, <hi>VVith Luther in the opinion of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment consented the Saxons: vvith the other side of Zuinglius, vvent the Heluetians and as time did grow, so the diuision of these opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions increased in sides, and spread in far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther realmes and countries, the one part be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called of Luther, Lutherans, the other hauing the name of Sacramentaries.</hi> So in Sleidan vve haue very common the name of <hi>Zuinglians</hi> and <hi>Sacramentaries,</hi> as likewise he calleth the other part <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and their religion <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranisme,</hi> and euen so they termed them selues. It were tedious to iustifie this out of Luther, Zuinglius, &amp; especially al historigraphers of our age. And in truth it is much like, as if a man should light a candle at noone-tide. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this we must desyre our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries
<pb n="92" facs="47"/>
to beare with vs, if we speake not only as al Catholikes, but as al Protestants, as Luther, as Sleidan, as M. Fox, as generally al writers in their bookes and volumes are accusto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to speake, and as the world of thē hath learned, and as the aduersaries them selues by al reason induce vs to speake, and as of necessitie we must speake, if we wil speake and be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoode.</p>
   <p>Touching any other fault, I shal be ready ether to defēd it, or to correct it. to correct it, if it be noted against me iustly, to defend it if it be obiected vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deseruedly. &amp; this I protest not only in words, as cōmonly do al Protestantes, but in simplicitie of truth, as meaning to performe the same. And therefore willingly I submit what so euer I haue written, to the iudgment of al Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, symply and with out exception to whom iudgment of these matters appertaineth. to the iudgment of al Protestants, euen of M. W. him selfe, so far furth as he shal geue censure of it and refel it by the written word of God, expounded according to the ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie of faith.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>