<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Fra. Giacomo Affinati to the Reader,
yeelding a reason for the title of his Booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115940_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08695</idno>
           <idno type="STC">190</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115940</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Fra. Giacomo Affinati to the Reader,
yeelding a reason for the title of his Booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The dumbe divine speaker, or: Dumbe speaker of Diuinity : A learned and excellent treatise, in praise of silence: shewing both the dignitie, and defectes of the tongue. Written in Italian, by Fra. Giacomo Affinati d'Acuto Romano. And truelie translated by A.M</title>
                 <author>Affinati, Giacomo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bradock, Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Leake, William 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 283, 65 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>Fra. Giacomo Affinati to the Reader,
yeelding a reason for the title of his Booke.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>EE knowes my heart, that rules
the affections of euery soule,
how desirous I haue beene
from time to time, to be anie
way helpfull to my neighbour,
to declare my selfe no vnfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
tree, planted within the
flourishing bosome of the
Church. And therefore with
the occasion of a most gentle
spirite, bemoaning the infinite vaine trauailes of many,
such as (indeede) deserue no acknowledgement of the
world: I imposed an eternall silence vpon my selfe, and to
assist the world (thereby) so much as lay in me, and to raise
it vp from those weightie oppressions of wicked molesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiōs
(according to the ability of mine own weak strength)
First I published the Mount of holy tribulation, and now
my Dumb diuine Speaker, in prayse of Silence, So called,
because I approoue by authoritye of sacred Scripture,
that whensoeuer we speake well, and as becommeth vs: it
is not we that speake, but the holy ghost, which then mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
the organe of our speeche. <hi>Non enim vos estis qui lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quimini,
sed spiritus patris vestri qui loquitur in vobis.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Heereupon, Christ casting foorth the diuell that was
dumbe, out of the possessed bodie, the holy Euangeliste
<pb facs="3"/>
telles vs, that the dumbe spake. <hi>Erat Iesus eijciens Demoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,
&amp; illud erat mutum. Et cum ciecisset Demonium, loquutus
est mutus.</hi> Wherein we haue to noate, how the Euangelist
sayth, that the diuell was dumb, who being cast out of the
possessed bodie, he doeth not say, that the diuell spake
which was dumbe, but he that was possessed: referring the
dumbnesse, not to the diuell as first was affirmed, but to
the bodie possessed, which (hauing beene dumbe) spake.
<hi>Et cum eiecisset Demonium, loquutus est mutuis.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now although the right sense be, that he who first was
dumbe, spake, the diuell being throwne out: yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing,
agreeing with the hidden voyce of the letter, it is
true that the dumb spake, abyding also in his dumbnesse,
because he spake well, as the Euangelist noteth; <hi>Et loque.
batur rectè:</hi> hee being dumbe, and yet speaking by the
meanes of the holy spirite, therefore wee also are silent,
and God speaketh in and by vs, when we speake well and
decentlie, and thus is it true that the dumbe man spake.</p>
   <p>This haue I set downe in fauour and defence of the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
of this Treatise, wherein I purpose to deliuer the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie
of Silence, and how it is much better to keepe si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,
then to talke, in regard of the numberlesse offences,
that men do fall into by their tongues only. Which labor,
if I may perceiue the worlde gratefully to accept, or the
least apparant signe of thankefulnesse to proceede from
thence: I promise, that speedily I will deliuer to the Presse,
another as excellent and profitable a worke, entitled: <hi>The
world turned topsie turuie:</hi> or, <hi>the vpside downward;</hi> discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
of God, of the Angelles, of the heauens, of subluna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie
things, and of <hi>Microcosmus,</hi> or the little world man, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proouing
how they are all ouerturned.</p>
   <p>In the meane while, vouchsafe with gentlenesse to read
this treatise, which may the more speedily hasten on the
other. And pray vnto the Lord for me, that I may be a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent
<pb facs="4"/>
ligēt obseruer ofsilēce, which is ful of al securitie &amp; safety,
and abounding in all sacred blessings. Whereupon <hi>Dauid</hi>
sayde, that the Israelites reioyced when they were quiet,
which made them afterward be brought to the porte of
their owne pleasures. <hi>Laetati sunt quia siluerunt, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duxit
eos in portum voluntatis corum.</hi> For great ioy
haue they that keep silence, because therby
they offend not god, but in their silence
they do alwaies contemplate theire
cheefeste happinesse, and (euen
as in a safe harbour) haue
perpetuall quietnesse.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>