<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To The Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1556</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115941_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10777</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21048</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115941</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To The Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certe [n] godly, learned, and comfortable conferences : betwene the two reuerende fathers, and holye martyrs of Christe, D. Nicolas Rydley late Bysshoppe of London, and M. Hughe Latymer sometyme Bysshoppe of Worcester, during the tyme of theyr emprysonmentes. Wherunto is added. A treatise agaynst the errour of transubstantiation, made by the sayd reuerende father D. Nicolas Rydley. M.D.LVI</title>
                 <author>Ridley, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Rihel, Wendelin</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Strasbourg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1556</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>67 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To The Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Race <abbr>and</abbr> peace / &amp;c. Good Christian Reader her are sett forthe for thine instruction / and comforte / certen learned / and comfortable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences / Betwene the two Reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / and godly fathers M. Rydley / and M. Laty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: whose bodies the Romishe tyrannie of late ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the tormented / and fier hathe consumed: whose sowles mercie hathe embraced / and heauen hathe receiued / yelding thone vnto the enemie to deathe / for testimonie of the truthe / commending thother vnto god in suer hope of lyfe. Wher vnto is also ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded a learned treatise / and a cleare confutation of the fonde / and wicked opinion of Transubstantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion written by the said M. Ridley. And forasmu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che as these their scrolles / and writynges wer by goddes good prouidence preserued / and as it wer raked owte of the asshes of thauthors: cōteinīge as well cōfortable cōsolatiō for suche as are in the scho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le of the crosse / as also goode / ād profitable admo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nitiō for them which eyther of ignorāce / either of infirmitie / or by flattering of them selfes with vay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne pretenses / do yelde vnto the wicked worlde: the reuerence due to the reuerende fathers / the zeale towardes the setting forthe of the tried truthe / and the readye goode will to conforte / and confirme weake consciences / would not suffer the any len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to wante these smalle treatises / and yett no
<pb facs="3"/>
smalle treasures. That as in life thei profited the by teaching / and in deathe by example / so after death they may doe the goode by writing. And albeit the matter of it selfe is sufficiente to commend it selfe / yet it cannot be but the worthines of the writers / will encrease creditte / and giue no small authoritie to the writynges. M. Latymer came earlier in the morning / and was the more auncient wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keman in the lordes vineyarde / <note place="margin">
         <hi>Matt.</hi> 20.</note> who also may ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie well be called (as diuerse learned men haue ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med hym) the Apostle of Englād: as one much mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re worthie of that name / for his true doctrine / for his sharpe reprouinge of sinne / and superstition / then was Augustine bisshop of Canturburie for bringing in the popes monkerie / and false religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. M. Ridley came later aboute theleuenth how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / but no doubte he came when he was effectual<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye called / and frō the time of his calling / became a faithfull / labourer terrible to the enemies for his excellent learning / and therfore a meete man to rid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de owte of the lordes vineyarde the sophisticall thornes of the wrangling aduersaries / which dyd well appeare in all disputations / and conferences that wer in his tyme / and partlye doth appeare in these shorte treatises folowing. But what shal it nede in manye wordes to prayse them / whose ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes wer moste commendable / whose deathes wer most glorious? in office and vocation bothe lyke / in labour and trauail bothe faithfull / in learning and iudgemēt both sounde: in minde and maners
<pb n="3" facs="3"/>
bothe milde / but in goddes cause bothe stoute. For neither threatned deathe / neither loue of present lyfe / could shake the foundation of theyr faithe / fir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mely grounded apon the suer rocke Christe.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Matt.</hi> 7.</note> They re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demed libertie of conscience / with the bondage of the bodie / and to saue their lyfes / they wer content to lose their lyfes. This was not the worke of the fleshe / but the operation of goddes mightie spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te: who hathe euer frome the beginning not onlye builded / but also enlarged his churche by the suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his sainctes / and sealed his doctrine with the bloude of his martyrs: as S. Augustine spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the persecutions in the primatiue church doth well declare in theis wordes.</p>
   <q>Ligabantur, includebantur, caedebantur,<note place="margin">De ciuita. Dei lib. 22 cap. 6.</note> torque bantur, urebantur, &amp; multiplicabantur.</q>
   <p>That is to saye. The Christians wer bounde / wer emprisoned / wer beaten / wer tormented / wer bren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te / and yet wer multiplyed.</p>
   <p>Yf Iustinus Martyr when he was yet an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Philosopher (as he confesseth of hym selfe) was moued to embrace the fayth and religion of Christe / <note place="margin">
         <hi>Apolog.</hi> 1</note> in beholding the constante patience of the martyrs which suffred for Christe in his tyme: how muche more oughte the patiente suffringe / and vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>luntarie death of these notable fathers / with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other learned / godlye men / in our dayes / whose names are writtē in the booke of lyfe / not only mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue / but also pearce / ād perswade all godly heartes constantely to remayne in the truthe knowen? For
<pb facs="4"/>
vndoubtedly the truthe of the cawse they suffred for / is moste euidente by goddes worde / and hath ben so fully taughte / so clearly sette forthe by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and sundrye writynges / that it is open to the Consciences of all the worlde / euen of the verie ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries themselfes that persequute it (greater is theyr damnation) excepte it be to such / whome the godde of thys worlde / <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.</note> malice / ambition / auarice / or ignorance hath blynded. Which thynge nedeth none other proofe (especially for the realme of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande) but only to call to mynde with what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science and constancie / these pyllers of the church that can nott erre / haue walked in Religion these twentye yeares by paste / how they not longe agoo receiued and allowed thynges / which with fyre / and fagotte / they persequute now / and shranke fro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me that thē / which now they moste earnestly main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyne. And allthoughe ther appeared in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dayes a shadow of stowtenesse in a few / yet it was in dede nothynge. For it sprange not owte of any zeale to the cawse / or clearenesse of conscience / but rather owte of a lyke subtylle / and foxye pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption / as the Syrians once conceiued / when they putte themselfes in the daunger of Kinge A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chab sayeng.<note place="margin">3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 20.</note> Beholde we haue hearde that the kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges of the howse of Israel are pitefull / and mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. For owte of all dowte K. Henry theyghte coulde as easely haue obteined at winchesters han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des / and others a conformytee in puttyng downe the Masse / and all the reaste / what so euer hath
<pb n="4" facs="4"/>
ben done (by order) sence / if he hadde earnestly min<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded it / as the abolisshinge of the pope / monkerye / pylgremages / reliques / with lyke baggage: all which are now agayne / thinges well estemed / and couered (as all the resydew is) with the clooke of the Catholike church. But to returne to the matter we haue in hāde / in this littel treatise (goode <abbr>read</abbr>) thow shalte perceiue another māer of spirite thow shalte thīke (if thow thi selfe be not verie dulle) that thow hearest men speake which hadde learned the lessō of thapostles / that is / <note place="margin">
         <hi>Acto.</hi> 4.</note> to obei godde rather thē mā: ād hadde not learned the Romisshe Epicures lesson / to applye fayth / and religiō to the presente state of policie / to turne with the tyme / and serue all seasons: men before death / deade vnto the worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / accowmptynge with S. Paule / all other thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges to be dāmage / losse / and vile / <note place="margin">
         <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.</note> that they mygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te wynne Christe: mē zealouse for the howse of god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / and the glorie of hys name: suche as hadde all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readye layed open theyr consciences / and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees before the iudgemēte seate of godde / and had<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de agayne (throughe Christe) receiued the effecte of fayth and true righteousnes / that is / peace of conscience / and ioyfullnes in the holy ghooste:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.</note> and so hadde a fulle taste in thys mortalle body of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitee / in miserie of happinesse / in earth of hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen. O Englande / Englande / how greate is thy losse for the wante of them? how horrible is thyne offense for killinge of them? how greuouse will thy plage be / when the reuenger of innocente bloude
<pb facs="5"/>
shall call the to an accowmpte for them / if thow doo not repente in tyme? Godde graunte that the admonitions of these and other godly martyrs maye so warne vs / theyr doctrine so instructe vs / and theyr example so cōfirme vs in the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege and feare of godde / that flyenge and abhorrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge Idolatrye / and superstition / we maye embrace true religion and pierce / forsakinge the phantasyes of men / we maye humblye obey the written worde of godde / and ruled therby / directe all our doyngs to the glorie of his name / and our owne endeles saluation in Christe Iesu / Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>