<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND Father in God, his Honourable Diocesan, the Bi∣shop of EXETER, and Visitor of Exeter College.</title>
           <author>Price, Daniel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115209_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10053</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20299</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115209</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND Father in God, his Honourable Diocesan, the Bi∣shop of EXETER, and Visitor of Exeter College.</title>
                 <author>Price, Daniel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Prince Henry his first anniversary. By Daniel Price Doctor in Divinity, one of his Highnesse chaplaines</title>
                 <author>Price, Daniel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barnes, Joseph</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND Father <hi>in God, his Honourable</hi> Diocesan, <hi>the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of</hi> EXETER, <hi>and</hi> Visitor <hi>of</hi> Exeter College.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Reverend <hi>Father,</hi> my duty hath often incited me to performe some due <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servance</hi> to your <hi>Lordship.</hi> Your honourable <hi>care</hi> of our flourishing College, hath been my <hi>remembrancer,</hi> &amp; <hi>pleaded</hi> with me as the <hi>Elders</hi> did with our <hi>Saviour,</hi> for the Cē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion. Hee <hi>is worthy that thou shouldst doe this to him, he loueth vs,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luk. 7.5.</note>
      <hi>and</hi> his predecessour <hi>built our synagogue.</hi> Your L<seg rend="sup">P</seg>. hath been long, a <hi>painefull, carefull</hi> father, to the <hi>Church,</hi> to our <hi>tribe,</hi> to our <hi>College,</hi> and God hath extraordinarily blessed you, that before your <hi>eyes,</hi> your two <hi>eyes,</hi> your two learned, worthy <hi>sonnes,</hi> in your <hi>dayes,</hi> and in your <hi>Church,</hi> serue at the <hi>Altar.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The <hi>reason,</hi> that I presume to <hi>present</hi> this to your <hi>Honour,</hi> is, because you truly <hi>honoured</hi> him, whom it concernes, that was the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb facs="3"/>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>ornament</hi> of his age <hi>present,</hi> and true <hi>mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi> to <hi>posteritie.</hi> Your especiall <hi>observance</hi> of him, in his life, being made knowne to his <hi>Highnesse,</hi> by the <hi>worthy Gentleman,</hi> my ever ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noured <hi>friend,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>Richard Connock,</hi> had beene as truly <hi>rewarded,</hi> as it was <hi>gratiously receaued,</hi> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d he <hi>liued.</hi> But he is <hi>translated,</hi> and now <hi>raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth</hi> in <hi>heaven,</hi> not for a <hi>day</hi> as <hi>Adontah,</hi> or for a <hi>weeke,</hi> as <hi>Zimri,</hi> for a <hi>moneth</hi> as <hi>Shallum,</hi> for six months as <hi>Zachary,</hi> for two <hi>yeares</hi> as <hi>Elah,</hi> for three yeares as <hi>Asa,</hi> for forty yeares as <hi>David,</hi> or fifty fiue as <hi>Manasses,</hi> but forever and ever, where in time, you shall meet him, to remaine with him without all time.</p>
   <p>My selfe, with my best <hi>devotions</hi> shal ever rest, at your honourable <hi>disposall,</hi> while I am</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>DANIEL PRICE.</signed>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Exeter Coll.</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>Decemb. 7.</hi>
         </date>
         <hi>The fatall day of</hi> Prince Henries <hi>funerall.</hi>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>