<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PRINTER to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115571_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06531</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1700</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115571</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PRINTER to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A defence of the Roman Church : VVherin is treated, vvhether the said Church of Rome hath fallen in faith, or no? Written in Latin by the R. F. Martinus Becanus of the Society of Iesus, Professour in Diuinity: and now translated into English</title>
                 <author>Becanus, Martinus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 44 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PRINTER to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OOD Reader, this short Treatise being sōt vnto me long since from a friend, who had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed it to be translated out of Latin into English; I haue iudged it wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be imparted vnto theo, for that it will giue thee light in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which greatly importeth thee to know, and on which the Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries do imploy their whole endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours to cast a cloud of obscurity.</p>
   <p>The matter in Controuersy is, <hi>Whether the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>hath fallen from her ancient faith?</hi> The Protestants affirme the same: and if they could in place of often saying
<pb facs="3"/> it, once proue it, their cause were much the better. The Catholiques on the contrary side deny, that She euer admitted the least change in any point of faith. Which if thou find to be so, as by reading this little Phamphlet, I hope thou shalt, then hast thou a cleere and sure way laid before thee, to resolue thyselfe of all doubtes, that may concerne Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
   <p>Bestow therfore the reading ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and thou shalt find the profit to counteruaile thy paynes. And so wishing thee euerlasting happines, I bid thee farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>