<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Honorable Sir Edward Fines, Earle of Lin∣colne, Baron of Clinton and Say, Knight of the noble order of the Garter, Lord high Admirall of England, Ireland, and Wales, and the Dominions and Iles thereof, of the towne of Ca∣lice, and marches of the same, Normandie, Gascoigne and Guian, and Captaine generall of the Queenes Maie∣sties Seas and Nauie royall.</title>
           <author>Digges, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115715_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69046</idno>
           <idno type="STC">435.59</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115715</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Honorable Sir Edward Fines, Earle of Lin∣colne, Baron of Clinton and Say, Knight of the noble order of the Garter, Lord high Admirall of England, Ireland, and Wales, and the Dominions and Iles thereof, of the towne of Ca∣lice, and marches of the same, Normandie, Gascoigne and Guian, and Captaine generall of the Queenes Maie∣sties Seas and Nauie royall.</title>
                 <author>Digges, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A prognostication euerlasting of right good effect : fruitfully augmented by the author, containing plaine, briefe, pleasant, chosen rules to iudge the weather by the sunne, moone, starres, comets, rainbow, thunder, clowdes, with other extraordinary tokens, not omitting the aspects of planets, with a briefe iudgement for euer, of plentie, lacke, sicknes, dearth, warres, &amp;c. opening also many naturall causes worthie to be knowne. To these and other now at the last, are ioyned diuers generall, pleasant tables, with many compendious rules, easie to be had in memorie manifold wayes profitable to all men of vnderstanding. Published by Leonard Digges Gentleman. Lately corrected and augmented by Thomas Digges his sonne</title>
                 <author>Digges, Leonard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 42, 12 leaves, 2 leaves of plates, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Honorable Sir Edward Fines, Earle of Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne, Baron of Clinton and Say, Knight of the noble order of the Garter, Lord high Admirall of England, Ireland, and Wales, and the Dominions and Iles thereof, of the towne of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and marches of the same, Normandie, Gascoigne and Guian, and Captaine generall of the Queenes Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Seas and Nauie royall.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable, hauing of long time sundrie waies found your Lordships great fauour, not only toward my father in his life time, but also toward his, most bountifully continued sithence his death: I haue carefully thought which way I might some way yeeld a testimonie of a greatefull mind. And perusing of late a Book of my fathers to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship dedicated, by negligence, or ignorance of Correctors many wayes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praued: I determinde both to amend the faults, and with some additions to amplifie the same, briefely also to touch and discouer certaine errors touching matters of Nauigation, transferred into our language. And although I haue in a peculiar volume for that purpose prepared to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat at large, deliuering new Rules and Methods, hitherto in no lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage published, nor to my knowledge of any forraine Nation practised, not onely in demonstration void of all error, but also in practise feazible: Yet in the meane, least further boldnes by ignorance should encrease, to deriue vs mo erros from other nations, whereof our Seamen haue learned too many already: I thought good at the end of this booke to note some of the most vsed and esteemed, and among that faction held for Oracles, whereby indeede they haue been and are (in all nauigations) so misled, that were they not by sight of the coast, and soundings better directed, then by any troth in their Art, many mo vessels should daily perish. This present token therefore of dutifull goodwill, I shall humbly desire your Lordship in good part to accept, meaning hereafter (God sparing life) to honor your Lordship, and profit my countrey with matters more rare. And in the meane while I humblie take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>At your Lordship commandement Thomas Digges.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>