<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONOVRA∣ble, Religious, and worthy Gen∣tlemen, the great Officers to the late renowmed Prince.</title>
           <author>Price, Daniel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115213_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10049</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20295</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115213</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONOVRA∣ble, Religious, and worthy Gen∣tlemen, the great Officers to the late renowmed Prince.</title>
                 <author>Price, Daniel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lamentations for the death of the late illustrious Prince Henry: and the dissolution of his religious familie : Two sermons: preached in his Highnesse chappell at Saint Iames, on the 10. and 15. day of Nouember, being the first Tuesday and Sunday after his decease. By Danie Price, chaplaine then in attendance</title>
                 <author>Price, Daniel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <publisher>Jackson, Roger.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 38 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HONOVRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Religious, and worthy Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, the great <hi>Officers</hi> to the late renowmed Prince.</head>
   <head type="sub">To the Ho. worthy, Gentlemen of the <hi>Bed-chamber:</hi> to his Reuerend Brethren the Chaplaines; and to all the rest of the Gentlemen and Officers of that <hi>Princely familie.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He importunity</hi> of some, the <hi>expectation</hi> of many, and the kinde <hi>acceptation</hi> of all of you, hath caused me to cast these <hi>two Mites</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Treasure</hi> of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>sorrow,</hi> and to present, that now to your <hi>hands,</hi> which in my attendance in this woefull time J prouided for your <hi>hearts:</hi> They are <hi>plaine,</hi> both because <hi>sorrow</hi> dislikes <hi>descant,</hi> and <hi>plaine</hi> stuffes are fittest for <hi>Mourners:</hi> they are <hi>passionate,</hi> for in my meditation <hi>by the riuers of sorrow I sat downe, &amp; wept, and hanged my Harpe vpon the willow,
<pb facs="3"/>trees,</hi> for euer <hi>tuning</hi> it to <hi>comfort</hi> or <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody</hi> againe: and <hi>when</hi> ye required this <hi>song</hi> of mee in my <hi>heauinesse,</hi> I knew not how to <hi>sing</hi> any <hi>song of the Lord,</hi> but a song of <hi>sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,</hi> in this <hi>strange land;</hi> strange for the <hi>sinnes,</hi> strange for the iudgements. They are <hi>yours,</hi> they once breathed with you, and now euer shall <hi>liue</hi> with you, a pledge of that hart that neuer reioyced in any sublunary <hi>obiect,</hi> more, then to see, while our <hi>Sunne</hi> did <hi>shine</hi> such an happy, friendly <hi>aspect</hi> of so many prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall <hi>Planets,</hi> and sweet <hi>plants</hi> in this place: let <hi>Charity</hi> interpret me, and none will be <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended</hi> that vpon impetuous importunity I publish these last offices, to the memory of that <hi>illustrious Prince,</hi> our Maister, for whom the <hi>sound</hi> of all <hi>tongues</hi> and applause of all hands testifie, neuer was any more <hi>honoured</hi> in his life, neuer any more <hi>lamented</hi> in his death, that euer beheld the light of <hi>heauen</hi> in this <hi>land.</hi> My best deuotion, &amp; faithfulest <hi>seruices</hi> are presented with these; and so I remaine</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours in all Christian dutie</hi> Daniell Price.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>