<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Goodwin, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115629_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10384</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20660</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115629</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Goodwin, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A gleaning in Gods harvest : Foure choyce handfuls; the gate to happinesse. Wounded saviour. Epicures caution. Generation of seekers. By the late judicious divine, Henry Ramsden, sometime preacher in London</title>
                 <author>Ramsden, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Slater (Slaughter), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <distributor>Dawson, John 2</distributor>
                            <distributor>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 56, 67-231, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Epistle to the Reader.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>GOOD READER,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Author of these Sermons, having served his time, and being fallen asleepe, before their time came to looke out, and doe service in the world; I conceived it might beare the construction of a peece of some light charitie to lead them out in their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan-like condition by the hand of a recommendatorie Epistle into the world. Men
<pb facs="3"/>for the most part desire in Bookes, to know first what is said of them, before they care to know what they say; and sometimes an Author worthy of prime inspection, for want of an Agent to make his worth his harbenger, may lie as long neglected and unread, as the poore Cripple at the poole of <hi>Bethsaida</hi> lay uncured for want of one to cast him into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
   <p>The subject (indeed) here principally discoursed, and brought out of darknesse into light (Christian mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) seemeth to disdaine all me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation, and petitioning for it, it being of so great weight and
<pb facs="3"/>transcendent importance, that it commands all hearts and eyes to looke up unto it; and threatens with power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie from on high, even the greatest on earth that shall turne their backe, and not their face upon it.</p>
   <p>There are three things espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially (among others) that will say well to make this rough and hidden way of Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, smooth and plaine. The first is, the greatnesse of the Author, and founder of that honourable order of Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and who was the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous President of it himselfe; Even the Lord Iesus Christ: the apprehension and sense of
<pb facs="4"/>such fellowship with us in our way, cannot but devoure and drowne all sense and thought of what otherwise might be dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult and distastfull in it. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Romans, the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall being slaine in the battell, there was scarce any Souldier that regarded his life; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chose to make an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of it, for such a death, wherein hee might beare his Generall company; and if any did returne home alive, in such a case there was a brand of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minie set upon him ever after. The truth is, were not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration of sin, and the mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of unbeliefe in the world at hand to qualifie the matter,
<pb facs="4"/>and give satisfaction; it were the most astonishing wonder that ever the world saw, that Iesus Christ being dead, the whole world should not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently resolve to die with him.</p>
   <p>The second is the greatnesse of the helpe, or mighty arme of assistance that is ready to joyne with us in this great worke of mortification if our hearts bee once set upon it: this is the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God and of Christ; <hi>If you mortifie the deeds of the body by the spirit, you shall live,</hi> Rom. 8. This Spirit of God residing and dwelling in those that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, to whom hee is given, is alway at hand, ready; yea, desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and longing to bee set on
<pb facs="5"/>worke in their soule; to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in this honourable ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice against sin, and all inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate affections, evill-concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scence, uncleannesse, pride, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetousness, &amp;c. And being stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up, and set on to purpose, it carries on his worke before him with an high hand; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king havock and desolation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the fleshly lusts and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of the soule. The greatest and most difficultest undertakings, and such which the soule of man would other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise abhorre, and turne aside from altogether, are yet dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted and carried on with a sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and pleasantnesse of hope, when a man sees measure for
<pb facs="5"/>strength for strength, as much in his meanes, as in his oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, as many with him as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him: Now the Spirit of God within us, is of more might then all the <hi>hills of the robbers</hi> (as <hi>David</hi> speakes in another case) hee is stronger than all their strong holds; he is above all the high things and imaginations that lift up themselves to the highest with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us against the knowledge of God. Mortification can bee no other, but a solid delight and spirituall recreation to him, that duly and deeply considers what oddes and advantage hee hath of his enemie, the flesh, by the partaking, and close stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="6"/>of that blessed friend of his, the Spirit.</p>
   <p>The third and last is, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding greatnesse of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward which the God of recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences (as the Scripture ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth him) hath sealed and set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled by purpose and promise, both Yea and Amen upon this worke of Mortification. If wee be dead with Christ we beleeve, that is, wee easily beleeve, or have ground sufficient to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, that wee shall live with him; as the foundation of the ensuing discourse proclaimes aloud to the world: whereby li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with Christ is not meant of an everlasting being in his presence only (though his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence
<pb facs="6"/>alone be a Paradise of joy and blessedness in abundance) but an admittance or taking up into an intire communion with him in all his glory; or as himselfe is pleased with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.21. a sitting downe with him upon his Throne: Men for the most part can bee content that any man should chuse or appoint their worke for them, if it might bee permitted to themselves to choose their wages, and have good securitie for it: Who would refuse with <hi>Sampson</hi> to encounter Lyons, if they could be secured to eate honey out of their carkasses? Who would not have cast in his lot with
<pb facs="7"/>those three faithfull servants of GOD, and have beene content to have taken part with them in that hotte ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the fierie furnace, could they have beene satisfie for their safe comming off with their lives untouched, and like advancement afterward in the Kingdome? Low wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and slender recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces make even light worke heavie; the only way to drowne the sowernesse or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasantnesse of any taske, is to make it swimme in an Ocean of reward. It is a principle in reason, <hi>Finis dat amabilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem mediis,</hi> Good ends make hard wayes or meanes lovely
<pb facs="7"/>and desireable. If Mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had as bitter and irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable an opposition, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnancie to nature, as the grave it selfe, yet the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent vastnesse of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, that same farre more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, eternall weight of glory (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had much adoe to bring out his notion of it in words, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out losse, and leaving some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what behinde, 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 4.17.) dearely apprehended and beleeved, mightily and effectuously considered, is able fully to reconcile the dispro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion.</p>
   <p>I am loth to exceed the time and measure of an Epistle. The
<pb facs="8"/>nature, necessitie and meanes of this great Master-peece of Mortification with some other things of Affinitie with them, are well laid downe in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons following; Some straines (I beleeve) thou wilt meet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that have beene strangers to thee heretofore, and which will doe lively execution, and quit themselves like the words of the wise, whose propertie is (as the wise man informes) to be as goades or nailes through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fastned. Holy and learned men (amongst whom not to number were doubtlesse to injure much mine Author) are not to bee too deeply char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, or too troublesomely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postulated
<pb facs="8"/>with for some pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarities of expressions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in perhaps they give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves more satisfaction than others: And indeed it is a hard thing for any man to write so savourly or warily, but that the Reader hath need still to bring a graine of salt with him to make the nourishment whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some.</p>
   <p>The blessing of the God of heaven bee with this little peece in its going forth into the world, that it may goe forth in its might, and doe worthily in Israel, teaching &amp; perswading many to desire (with <hi>Paul</hi>) the knowledge of the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of Christs sufferings, and
<pb facs="9"/>how to bee made conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his death, which is one of the greatest and most hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den misteries of Christianitie, and requireth the best and greatest Masters in Israel for its Teachers.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord Jesus, IOHN GOODWINE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>