<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1555</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115973_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68658</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21046</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115973</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A brief declaracion of the Lordes Supper, written by the syngular learned man, and most constaunt martir of Iesus Christ, Nicholas Ridley Bishop of London prisoner in Oxforde, a litel before he suffred deathe for the true testimonie of Christ</title>
                 <author>Ridley, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Erve, Egidius (Gillis) van der (Gellius Ctematius)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Emden</pubPlace>
                    <date>1555</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>80 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>VNderstande (good reader) that this great clearke and blessed Martir, bishop Nicholas Ridley sought not (by setting furthe this notable godly piece of learned worke) the vayne glorie of the world, nor temporal frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of men for his present aduauncement, muche lesse he hunted hereby for Bishoprikes and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, as all his aduersaries (the enemies of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes truthe and ordinaunce) the Papistes cōmonly doo: but hauing consideracion of the great charge of soule committed vnto him, and of thaccompte therof which the iustice of God wolde require at his handes, intending therwithall to be founde blameles in the great daye of the Lorde, seing he was put aparte to defende the Gospel. he not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forsoke landes, goodes, world, frendes, and him selfe withall, and testified the truthe specified in this boke by his learned mouthe in the open pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of the worlde: but also (to leaue a sure mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument and loue token vnto his flocke) he hathe regestred it by his owne penne in this forme en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suyng, and sealed it vp with his blood. Forasmuch than as he hath approued him selfe no vayne dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putour, no wethercocke, nor hipocrite, seyng he hathe willingly geuen his lyfe for the truthe: and inasmuche also as his loue and most constaunt christian conscience speaketh frely vnto thee, gentill reader: I beseche thee for Christes sake and thyne owne, lende him thine indifferent heart, and pacient hearyng. ❧</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>