<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115025_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09898</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20161</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115025</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The life of Alfred, or, Alvred: the first institutor of subordinate government in this kingdome, and refounder of the Vniversity of Oxford : Together with a parallell of our soveraigne lord, K. Charles untill this yeare, 1634. By Robert Povvell of Wels, one of the Society of New-Inne</title>
                 <author>Powell, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Badger, Richard 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Alchorn, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 96, 99-156, 2 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>ISTORY is the Herauld of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, and the life of time, and well deserves <hi>Cicero</hi> his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation, <hi>Magistram vitae:</hi> it preserves and presents un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our understanding, and knowledge in the booke of nature (as it were in a <hi>Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>optick</hi> glasse) the life and light of the boundlesse and beautifull theatre of the
<pb facs="8"/>
whole world, the heavens, the elements, the glorious lights, the nature of al herbs and plants, and all creatures whatsoever both of sea, and land; yea, even subterrane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous things, treasured up in the bosome and bowels of the earth; the variety of all precious gems, and all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall bodies and materials whatsoever; and not onely the life &amp; light of this great universe, but of all persons and actions memorable and worthy to be recorded, either for imitation of good, or eschewing of evill, ever
<pb facs="8"/>
since the world it selfe had its first created light: it presents our first Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in their innocence and naked purity, and after their fall, in their sinfull<note place="margin">Gen. 9 21</note> robes of figleaves. <hi>Noah</hi> in the Arke (the type of the Church militant) and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards uncovered in his Tent.</p>
   <p>It brings to our memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, the gracious and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly government of <hi>David, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hosaphat, Ezechias,</hi> and many other blessed Kings; and on the contrary, the tyrannicall and cruell oppressions of
<pb facs="9"/>
      <hi>Pharaoh, Astyages,</hi> and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi> and many others, with their wofull and exemplary punishments, the lives of good and bad subjects; an undermining <hi>Ziba,</hi> and a faithfull <hi>Mephibosheth,</hi> a proud <hi>Haman,</hi> and a loyall <hi>Mordecai,</hi> an incorrupted <hi>Naaman,</hi> and a bribing <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hazi;</hi> in a word, a Pharisai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call <hi>Thraso</hi> and a penitent <hi>Publican:</hi> it presents unto us from the mouth of God, by the hand of <hi>Moses</hi> the Law of God, or the deca. logue proceeding from the eternall wisdome and rule
<pb facs="9"/>
of justice in God; by which, as by a Rule or Levell, all the counsels and consulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, all the actions and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprises of men are to bee directed and squared.</p>
   <p>This great Mistresse hath two eyes, and by them she surveyes the whole world, <hi>Topographie,</hi> and <hi>Chronology,</hi> and exact knowledge of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and of times, which like the <hi>Cynosura</hi> are able to guide and conduct every studious reader in the vast Ocean of the affaires of the world unto the haven of true knowledge.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="10"/>History is either univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall, describing the whole fabricke of the world, or ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall containing a national or provinciall description, <hi>Quae mores hominum cognovit &amp; urbes,</hi> or speciall, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending the lives and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of particular Princes or persons; this last I shall walke in.</p>
   <p>To be versed in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of forreigne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and affaires, and to be a stranger at home, were great folly, and a way to forget the legiance and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience which wee owe to
<pb facs="10"/>
our Soveraigne and his Lawes.</p>
   <p>Vnder the service of that great Commandresse, that yeelds subjection to none but eternity it selfe, I shall humbly presume, to present unto the world for the glory of our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> Nation such a Prince, as <hi>Constantine</hi> the great Emperour of <hi>Rome,</hi> (who rescued the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of his time from the persecution,) would have owned and honoured for a Compeere, if he had lived in his time; <hi>Alfred,</hi> or, as
<pb facs="11"/>
some name him <hi>Aelfred,</hi> or <hi>Alvred,</hi> the 23. King of the <hi>West-Saxons,</hi> and the first Monarch of England; who not only rescued and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his Christian Subjects from Pagan persecutions, but was the Author of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling and adopting a <hi>Danish</hi> King, and many Nobles and others to the Christian faith.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>