<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>BROTHER BAR∣THOLOMEVV VNVVORTHY Seruant of Iesus Christ cruci∣fied, to his moste endeared Si∣ster, S. Marie Magdalen glo∣rious spouse of blessed Iesus in heauen.</title>
           <author>Bartholomew, Brother</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115141_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17731</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4469</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115141</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>BROTHER BAR∣THOLOMEVV VNVVORTHY Seruant of Iesus Christ cruci∣fied, to his moste endeared Si∣ster, S. Marie Magdalen glo∣rious spouse of blessed Iesus in heauen.</title>
                 <author>Bartholomew, Brother</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The seaven trumpets of brother Bartholomevv Saluthius of the holie order of S. Francis; exciting a sinner to repentance. A worke very profitable for the saluation of all such soules, as are bound with sinne. Now lately translated out of the Latin, into the English tongue, b Br. G. P. of the same order and obseruance</title>
                 <author>Cambi, Bartolomeo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 <publisher>Boscard, Charles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Heigham, John (Roger)</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>399, 9 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb n="29" facs="15"/>
   <head>BROTHER BAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THOLOMEVV VNVVORTHY Seruant of Iesus Christ cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, to his moste endeared Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, S. Marie Magdalen glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious spouse of blessed Iesus in heauen.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eholde my moste deare Sister Magdalen, the spouse of Christ cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, once as blacke as the tents of Cedar, (<hi>Cant.</hi> 1.) but afterwards as beautifull as the courtaines of Salomon, portresse of loue, and patronesse of all sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, now blessed with celestiall glorie, beholde I say, I haue fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed a little booke, entituled by
<pb n="30" facs="16"/> mee, The Seauen Trumpets, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing a sinner to repentance; And because I haue written of thee, being assisted with thy holy prayers, not any that I could find, might with such equitie challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the patronage of this booke, as thy selfe; For to whom might I with more conuenience present this little worke, out of which, proceedeth such a sound, that terrifieth the greatest malefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, and awakneth the securest offender, thē to S. Mary Magdalē a sinner? To whom, I say, rather then vnto thee, should I the most abiect and vnworthiest of all sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, dedicate this booke, that treateth of the saluation of sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners? To thee therfore my sister Magdalen, I commend it, that thou beeing a daily assistant ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, mightest cause it to bringe forth its intended frutes, which <pb n="31" facs="16"/> is the safetie, health, and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of all distressed, wretched, and sinfull soules. Remember, oh blessed Magdalen, that thou wast once a loste sheepe, farre strayed from the folde of Christ, and if our deare Sauiour Iesus the care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full shepheard of thy soule, had not called thee vnto him, thou hadst beene deuoured of the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening wolfe: thou knowest that our Iesus did vndergoe death for the life of soules. <hi>Christas venit in hunc mundum &amp;c.</hi> (1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15.) Christ Iesus came into the world to saue sinners, of whom I am the cheefe, and Christ himselfe saith,
<hi>Non est opus valentibus medico, sed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lè habentibus.</hi> (<hi>Math</hi> 9.12.) They that be well neede not the phisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, but they that be sicke, and thou art not ignorant of that which is written of him, in the Gospell of Saint Luc. <hi>Hic peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res <pb n="30" facs="17"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb n="31" facs="17"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb n="32" facs="18"/> recipit &amp;c.</hi> (<hi>Luc.</hi> 15.2.) This man receaueth sinners, and eateth with them: Oh therfore Magdalen, let thy eyes of pittie be euer watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ouer miserable sinners, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede for the conuersion, and sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of so many soules, which are running headlong into the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bisse of eternall perdition; Thou seest and knowest, moste deare Magdalē, what a number of sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les doe daily and hourely descēd into the bottomlesse pitte of hell: succour, aide, and stretch forth thy helping hand therfore to the perishing &amp; languishing soules: remember, oh Sister that all those soules were redeemed and bought with the pretious blood of sweete Iesus, the Sauiour and Redeemer of vs both: Thou knowest right well, the inexcogitable sufferings of our louing Iesus vpon mount Caluarie, for all vs rebellious <pb n="33" facs="18"/> wretches: I am certaine thou well remembrest that pretious blood which whilest he hāged vpon the crosse, thou sawest distill and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne downe from his sacred bodie, vpon the earth. Remember, oh Magdalen; the anxiety of his sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, when as thou didst behold him yeelding vp his spirit with such bitter paines vpon the holy wood of the crosse: procure by thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercession, that these soules which were redeemed with the pretious blood, which did so abundantly flow out of his diuine head being prickt, and goared with an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard-of crowne of thornes, may be deliuered from the power of sinne, and brought into the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious liberty of the sōnes of God: succour those poore soules, which are bought with such an abūdan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of blood, running like a tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from the most sacred hands, <pb n="34" facs="19"/> and feet of thy Master Iesus cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, obtaine by thy holy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that those soules may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented pure before God, which were washed with that blood and water that issued out of thy Iesus his side, euē vnto his most bitter death; Thy prayers, oh Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len which are enflamed with the burning loue of thy dearest spou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se, are of no small virtue to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the helpe of the Angel of the couenāt, to put the diseased sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of miserable sinners into the all curing waters of Bethsaida. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 5.4.</p>
   <p>To thee therefore in the name of our gratious Iesus, &amp; his bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Mother, he a louing Father, she a tender Mother of al sinners, I present &amp; offer this litle worke, which I acknowledge to be thine; In the name of the moste holie Trinitie, Father, Sonne and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb n="35" facs="19"/> Ghost, in the vertue of the name of Iesus, and the B. V. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, together with thy helpe, oh Blessed Magdalen, these my Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Trumpets are come to bee sounded abroad, which by the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacie of the blood, death, and passion of Christ, who is Sonne of God, and also him selfe true God and man I implore, beseech, and desire, that they terrifie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert and reduce to repentance an innumerable company of soules, which lie demerged, ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and plunged in the pitt, of sinne, and iniquitie: Amen: In the name of the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghost, Amen.</p>
   <p>Let thy benedictiō oh my Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen, descend vpon the soule and bodie of mee, and all other sinners, which shall peruse this booke, by the vertue of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious body and blood of our Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb n="36" facs="20"/> Iesus which is cōtained in the most holy Sacrament of the altar,</p>
   <trailer>Amen: Pray for mee:</trailer>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From Rome: our place of S. Fran. Transtib.</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>Iun.</hi> 14. 1612.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Thy most deuoted Brother in our Lord, Brother Bartholomew.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>