<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his worthy friend Mr ROBERT RANDOLPH of Ch. Ch. on the publishing of his Brothers Poems.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115618_Fr1_2_9</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10411</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20694</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115618</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his worthy friend Mr ROBERT RANDOLPH of Ch. Ch. on the publishing of his Brothers Poems.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Poems : with the Muses looking-glasse: and Amyntas· By Thomas Randolph Master of Arts, and late fellow of Trinity Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Randolph, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Bowman, Francis.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lichfield, Leonard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 128, 2, 93, 7, 114 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>To his worthy friend <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> ROBERT RANDOLPH</hi> of <hi>Ch. Ch.</hi> on the publishing of his Brothers Poems.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>WE thank you, worthy sir, that tis our hap</l>
      <l>To praise even <hi>Randolph</hi> now without a clap,</l>
      <l>And give our suffrage yet, though not our voice,</l>
      <l>To shew the odds betwixt his fame and noyse:</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="9"/>Whose only modesty we could applaud,</l>
      <l>That seldome durst presume to blush abroad;</l>
      <l>And bear his vast Report, and setting forth</l>
      <l>His vertues, grow a suff'rer of his worth,</l>
      <l>Was scarce his own acquaintance, and did use</l>
      <l>To hear himselfe reported but as newes,</l>
      <l>So distant from himselfe, that one might dare</l>
      <l>To say those two were nere familiar:</l>
      <l>Whose pollisht Phancy hath so smoothly wrought,</l>
      <l>That 'tis suspected, and might tempt our thought</l>
      <l>To guesse it spent in every birth, so writ</l>
      <l>Not as the guift but Legacy of his wit:</l>
      <l>Whose unbid braine drops so much flowing worth,</l>
      <l>That others are deliver'd, he brought forth;</l>
      <l>That did not course in wit, and beat at least</l>
      <l>Ten lines in fallow to put up one Iest;</l>
      <l>Which still prevents our thought, we need not stay</l>
      <l>To th'end, the Epigram is in the way.</l>
      <l>The Towne might here grow Poet, nay tis se'd</l>
      <l>Some <hi>May'ors</hi> could hence as eas'ly rime as read;</l>
      <l>Whose losse we so much weepe, we cannot heare</l>
      <l>His very <hi>Comedyes</hi> without a teare;</l>
      <l>And when we read his mirth, are faine to pray</l>
      <l>Leave from our griefe to call the worke a play:</l>
      <l>Where fancy plaies with judgement; and so fits</l>
      <l>That 'tis enough to make a guard of wits;</l>
      <l>Where lines fulfill themselues, and are so right</l>
      <l>That but a combats mention is a fight.</l>
      <l>His phrase does bring to passe, and hee has lent</l>
      <l>Language enough to give the Things Event;</l>
      <l>The lines pronounce themselves, and we may say</l>
      <l>The Actors were but Echoes of the Play:</l>
      <l>Me thinkes the book does act, and we not doubt</l>
      <l>To say it rather Enters then Comes out;</l>
      <l>Which even you seeme to envy, whose device</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="10"/>Has made it viler even by its price,</l>
      <l>And taught its value, which we count so great</l>
      <l>That when we buy it cheapest we but cheat;</l>
      <l>And when upon one Page we bles<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e our look,</l>
      <l>How-ere we bargaine we have gain'd the book;</l>
      <l>Fresh-men in this are forc't to have their right,</l>
      <l>And 'tis no purchase though 'twere sold in spight;</l>
      <l>So doe we owe you still, that let us know</l>
      <l>He gave the world the Playes, and you the Show.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>IOS. HOWE. <hi>Trin. Coll.</hi> OXON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>