<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR ROBERT Nanton, Knight, chiefe Secretary to his Ma∣iesties state and one of his Maiesties most Honorable Priuie Councell.</title>
           <author>Harding, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115165_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02628</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12756</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115165</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR ROBERT Nanton, Knight, chiefe Secretary to his Ma∣iesties state and one of his Maiesties most Honorable Priuie Councell.</title>
                 <author>Harding, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A recantation sermon preached in the gate-house at VVestminster the 30. day of Iuly 1620 : In the presence of many worshipfull persons, by Iohn Harding, late Priest and Dominican Fryar. Wherein he hath declared his iust motiues which haue moued him to leaue the Church of Rome, and to vnite himselfe with the reformed Church of England, whose faith and doctrine, the ancient fathers and holy martyrs haue confirmed both by bloud and writing. Shewing herein the grose errors of Rome, in matters of faith, their corrupting the Fathers, and their present declining to some strange and future ruine</title>
                 <author>Harding, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Bernard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 25, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR ROBERT <hi>Nanton,</hi> Knight, chiefe Secretary to his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties state and one of his Maiesties</hi> most Honorable Priuie Councell.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that hath passed a dangerous <hi>sicknesse,</hi> and hath recouered his former <hi>health</hi> againe, is bound in a double <hi>Obligation:</hi> The one is to bee gratefull to the <hi>Person</hi> by whose meanes he recouered his <hi>health:</hi> The other is to vse all meanes possible, that those which be <hi>sick</hi> of the like <hi>disease,</hi> may by his <hi>recouery</hi> be the better: Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of our Sauior, <hi>Et tu cōuersus confirma fratres tuos:</hi> And therefore right Honourable, although it be somewhat besides custome to make <hi>Dedications</hi> of printed <hi>Sermons;</hi> yet it is my <hi>duty</hi> to offer to your <hi>Honour</hi> the first fruits of my <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersion:</hi> Your <hi>Honor</hi> being next and immediately vnder <hi>God</hi> the chiefe <hi>worker</hi> thereof. The which as it is a gretaer <hi>benefite</hi> then any worldly thing can afford <hi>me,</hi> so doth it require a fuller <hi>acknowledgement</hi> then as yet, I could at any time <hi>manifest:</hi> howsoeuer I haue most earnestly desiredit. In which respect be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouer intreated by some of my <hi>friends</hi> to publish this <hi>Sermon</hi> of my <hi>Recantation,</hi> and to set downe to the open <hi>view</hi> of <hi>all,</hi> the
<pb facs="3"/>iust <hi>reasons,</hi> and sollid <hi>grounds</hi> that moued mee there unto. I haue made hold to passe it vnder your <hi>Honours</hi> name, hoping by your former encouragements, of your loning acceplance. And albeit they be but my first <hi>Assayes</hi> in this kind, and therefore may chance to seem: but harsh, yet because my desire is only to set forth <hi>God;</hi> mercy towards me: your <hi>Honors</hi> louing kindnesse shewed to me, And to stop the mouthes of some malicious <hi>Papists</hi> that rayle against me, I trust that your <hi>Honour</hi> will accept of this my weake endeauour as a <hi>token</hi> of my thankefull <hi>mind,</hi> which I in all <hi>duty</hi> recommend vnto your <hi>Honours</hi> fauour, and your <hi>selfe</hi> and yours, in your <hi>affaires</hi> vnto the <hi>mercy,</hi> and blisse of the blessed <hi>Trinity,</hi> who ever so asssist your <hi>Honour</hi> in all your proceedings, as that after these present toyles and troubles, your <hi>Honor</hi> may receine that happy <hi>Crowne</hi> of glory, <hi>Quam repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miscit Deus diligentibus se.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honors euer in Christ Iesus</hi> Iohn Harding,</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>