<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A POST-SCRIPT</title>
           <author>B., E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115852_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00200</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1025</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115852</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A POST-SCRIPT</title>
                 <author>B., E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The curse of sacriledge : Preached in a priuate parish church, the Sunday before Michaelmas last. To which are annexed some certaine quære's, which are pertinent to the vnmasking of our homebred church-robbers. D.E.B</title>
                 <author>Brouncker, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lichfield, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 38, 6 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="postscript">
   <pb facs="23"/>
   <head>A POST-SCRIPT</head>
   <p>READER I iudge it requisite to acquaint you with two things thereby to prevent the iniury thou may'st o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise doe thy selfe and mee, The on is That I am farre from doubting of the <hi>ius diuinum</hi> of Tithes, though I say little of it in this Sermon; yea so farr, as my beleife of it is but one degree short of his, who made the Tenent of the Popes being Anti-Christ part of his Creed, I haue of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose forborne that Tract, because I finde it already made smooth and plaine by the happy industrie of many a <note n="*" place="margin">The late R. B. of Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegue Net<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tells Perrot S<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Iames Simple &amp; others.</note> learned pen, when as this other on which I shall set footing, is toucht by few, and those too <hi>obiter</hi> rather then <hi>de industria.</hi> The other particuler of which I am to informe thee is, That I quarrell not Bishops and Prebendaries enioying of Tithes, so that two things may passe for currant truth, the one that those Bishops and Prebendaries are to bee thought to haue the cheife charge of those mens soules from whome they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Tithes, and not the Vicars who indeed are but their Curats. The other that it were fitt they were interdicted from letting, and setting their Tithes (especially to Laicks) for longer space then their owne liues And thus friendly Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thou hast my inside turned outward in the poynt of conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated dewes. The censure of which I only submit to that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sanedrim the house of Conuocation as taking that body to bee the only competent and fit decisiue iudge in businesse of this nature. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>D. E. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>