<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HYGH AND MIGHTY PRINCE HENRIE, THE Most Royall Heyre apparant, to the vnited Kingdomes of great BRITTAYNE, FRANCE, and IRELANDE. &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115901_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10699</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20981</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115901</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HYGH AND MIGHTY PRINCE HENRIE, THE Most Royall Heyre apparant, to the vnited Kingdomes of great BRITTAYNE, FRANCE, and IRELANDE. &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A Catholicke conference betvveene Syr Tady Mac. Mareall a popish priest of VVaterforde, and Patricke Plaine a young student in Trinity Colledge by Dublin in Ireland : VVherein is deliuered the certayne maner of execution that was vsed vpon a popish bishop, and a popish priest, that for seueral matters of treason were executed at Dublin the first of February, now last past. 16ll. Strange to be related, credible to be beleeued, and pleasant to bee perused. By Barnabe Rych, Gent. seruant to the Kinges most excellent Maiestie</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Adams, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 26 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HYGH AND <hi>MIGHTY PRINCE</hi> HENRIE, <hi>THE</hi> Most Royall Heyre apparant, to the vnited <hi>Kingdomes of great</hi> BRITTAYNE, FRANCE, <hi>and</hi> IRELANDE. &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost worthy and renowned PRINCE, I am in hope it shall seeme no presumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to offer this my vnlettered dilligence to the sight and view of your Highnesse, the cause especially belonging to the set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth of Gods glory, and after a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine maner, doth very nearely concerne the seruice of your royall Father, of whose Christian inclination to plant piety, and to releeue innocency, the world hath had long experience. To none more rather thē to your Highnesse therefore belongeth these mine endeuours, whom nature and rare vertues with liberall minde hath adorned with singular indowments: and education a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine furnished with knowledge and exquisite learning belonging to a Prince. May it now please your Grace, my selfe hauing heere (according to my little skill) stood in defence of our religiō against the eager assaults of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse and malicious papistes: Although I must confesse, with more breuity then the amplenesse of the matter, or the necessity of the cause required: I am therefore most humbly to craue pardon of your Highnesse, for passing of those bounds that custome prescribeth in that case: yet if there were no further cause to presse your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, for the Patronage of so good a purpose this might suffice: It is meant for the glory of God, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides this inducement, there is yet one other especiall
<pb facs="3"/>
inforcement to leade me to this on-set namely when in that infortunate Country of <hi>Irelande,</hi> the <hi>Popes Vermine</hi> (your royall Fathers mortall enemies) haue such scope and liberty, that they drawe the people after them, to runne headlong into that extreame perdition, both of body and soule, and into that horrible downefall of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience both to God and their Prince.</p>
   <p>Nowe where their resteth so much presumption in Priestes to Impugne the sworde of gouerment, there must be courage in Princes to defend their owne. I will wade no deeper, but in all humble and submissiue maner will leaue these lines to your Gratious vewe. And thus layinge my handes vnder your Highnes feete will rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces Souldier euer more deuoted to doe your Highnes seruice
BARNABE RICH</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>