<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS RIGHT Worthy, much-beloued, and singularly approued good friend, Maister Iames Risley, all prosperous well-fare tending to eternall safee.</title>
           <author>Bernard, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115305_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09333</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1964</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115305</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS RIGHT Worthy, much-beloued, and singularly approued good friend, Maister Iames Risley, all prosperous well-fare tending to eternall safee.</title>
                 <author>Bernard, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Two twinnes: or Two parts of one portion of scripture. I. Is of catechising. II. Of the ministers maintenance. By Richard Barnard, preacher of the word of Worsop in Nottinghamshire</title>
                 <author>Bernard, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Norton, George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 51, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HIS RIGHT Worthy, much-beloued, and singularly approued good friend, Maister <hi>Iames Risley,</hi> all prosperous well-fare tending to eternall safe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>YR:</hi> I cannot but often thinke of your singular good respect towards me, in whom, as now it appeareth, long acquaintance in true loue hath bred a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant readinesse to doe me good, not only when I am present with you (as if you were, as many be, a friend to the face, without sound affection fixed in the heart) but also in my absence, and that a far off, when I supposed (which was mine errour) my selfe least in your thoughts, and therefore farre enough from expecting so great kindenesses as I haue now receiued at your hands.</p>
   <p>Surely, <hi>SYR,</hi> as I acknowledge that you haue suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently witnessed on your part, beyond my expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a minde fully bent to procure my well-fare, so I pray you out of this your true loue, to iudge me ready on my part to requite, if I were able to recompence so great kindenesses, vnto the full: but I am indebted beyond mine hability to pay; your satisfaction there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from mee is onely my good will, and your owne friendly acceptance of a thankefull heart; a true
<pb facs="3"/> token and sure testimony whereof be this my late and last labour, which I bequeath vnto you, till there be more fit meanes of recompencing your farre better deseruings. In the meane space let it stand for a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of my thankefulnesse, which I haue euer desired to shew vnto all, for euery little fauour receiued of any friendly well-willer.</p>
   <p>This my labour, in part concerneth the Laity, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you may, in your place, occasionally, be a very good instrument all meanes to further my intendment, for the maintenance of the Ministerie. In part also it touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth many of vs of the Clergie, in our too much neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected duty of Catechising; the Antiquity, vtility, and right forme whereof is here set downe; the godly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration of which I humbly recommend to my Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend brethren of the Ministery in these parts; to whose wise and indicious censure I submit this my best endeuour in this point, crauing for it their friendly interpretation, and for my selfe their fauourable coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, which I much desire, and which, if I may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, I will account, as an addition of Gods blessing to my Lords most honourable fauours; and as you, one well knowne and approued, shall be the instrument to effect it, so will I value it, as a part of high price in your vnfeigned loue towards me.</p>
   <p>Thus thankfully remembring my selfe, I commend my labour and my selfe to your friendly and kinde ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, remayning</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> much beholden Richard Barnard.</signed>
      <dateline>From Worsop in Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinghamshire. <date>Sept. 24.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>