<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Benet, B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115066_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68048</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10928.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115066</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Benet, B.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The rule of perfection : contayning a breif and perspicuous abridgement of all the wholle spirituall life, reduced to this only point of the (vvill of God.) Diuided into three partes. The first treating of the exteriour will of God, contayning the actiue life. The second o the interiour vvill contayning the contemplatiue life. The third of the essentiall vvill concerning the life supereminent. Composed by the R.F. Benet Capucin, preacher, of the holie order of Saint Francis, novv of the prouince of France, heertofore called VV. Fitch, of Canfeld in Essex</title>
                 <author>Benoît, de Canfield</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hamillon, Cardin 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 179, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE Reader, There is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
booke intituled the <hi>Method
to serue God</hi> in <hi>Latin, Franch,</hi> and <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish</hi>
which in the beginning, spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
of the <hi>vvill of God:</hi> Least therfore thow
mayst think that this booke be (as it were)
the same, or not much different, and so thy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
to read this be diminished, thow shalt
vnderstand, that they differre in all matters;
in subiect, method, and pretended scope: For,
that booke hath but some one Chapter or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cument
of the <hi>vvill of God,</hi> but this, three boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes
or partes; that goeth to other discourses
of vertues and vices, but this pursueth this
only point of the <hi>vvill of God;</hi> that propown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
it as the end of our actions, but this as
the beginning, progresse, and ending, of the
wholle spirituall life, geuing precepts for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
one: Yea, that booke in the place where it
toucheth the <hi>vvill of God,</hi> sheweth not how to
know it, but this geueth meanes how to know
the same; that, speaketh of the <hi>vvill of God,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
distinction, but this distinguisheth it mys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically
into three; Finally, that booke spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
of the Exteriour will, but this entreth
<pb facs="10"/>
into the knowledge, tast, and feeling of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall
will as it is spirit and life, yea, and es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentially
God himself, as is shewed in the third
part. But it is needlesse to speak of all the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences
which by reading thow shalt find to
be such, as that there is no conueniencie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
them: only the <hi>vvill of God</hi> which is heer
taught throughout the <hi>Actiue, Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue,</hi>
and <hi>Supereminent</hi> lyfe, is thear touched
in the beginning of that booke of <hi>Actiue</hi> lyfe.
And if this had affinitie with that, it would
neuer haue bein so required and published in
<hi>France,</hi> especially so paynfully by writing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
it was printed, and (particularly) amongst
religious Orders, whear that booke is so com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.
As for the other three bookes mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
they be not yet printed, though readie to
goe to the prefle. And if this or they
bring vnto thy sowlle any profit
or consolation, I desire for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compense
some memorie
of mee in thy holie
prayers. Fare
well.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ Iesus
B. Benet.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>