<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The prologue of Ptholomeus.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1530</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115325_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10201</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20480</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115325</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The prologue of Ptholomeus.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Here begynneth the compost of Ptholomeus, prynce of astronomye: translated oute of Frenche in to Englysshe, for them that wolde haue knowlege of the compost</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wyer (Wyre), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1530</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>136 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div n="Ptolomy" type="prologue">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>¶ The prologue of Ptholomeus.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O as we vnderstāde Ptholomeus saythe / that lyuynge and dyeng is all at the pleasure of almygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty god. Yet he sayth that a man may lyue by the cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>se of nature .lxxii. yere or more. And he sayth also as moche tyme / as a man hath to growe in beaute / length / bredthe / and strengthe. So moche tyme hathe he to waxe olde and feble to his ende. But the terme to growe in beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / hyghte / and strength / is .xxxvi. yere. And the terme to waxe olde / feble / and weyke / to tourne to the erthwarde / whiche is in all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyther .lxxii. yere / that he ought to lyue after the course of nature. And they that dye before this tyme / often it is by the vyolence and out rage done to theyr Complexion and nature. But they that lyue aboue this terme / it is by good regyment &amp; ensygnement{is} / after whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che a man hathe gouerned hymselfe. To this purpose of lyuynge and dyeng: Ptholomeus sayth / that the thynge that we desyre moste in this worlde is to lyue longe: And the thynge that we moste fere is to dye soon. ¶ Thus he trauayled his vnderstandyng / &amp; made great
<pb facs="6"/> dylygence to knowe and to do thyng{is} possy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; requysyte for to lyue longe / hole / &amp; ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully / whiche this present Compost sheweth &amp; techeth. wherefore we wyll shewe you of the bodyes Celestyall / &amp; of theyr nature &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynges: &amp; this p̄sent boke is named the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>post of Ptholomeus / for it cōprechendeth ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all the Compost. And this present boke is made for them that be of small lernynge / to brynge them to great vnderstandyng. Thus Ptholomeus sayd also that the desyre to lyue longe was in his soule / the whiche alwaye lasteth / wherfore he wold that his desyre we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re accomplysshed after his deth / as before. He sayde syth the foule dyeth nat / and in it is the desyre to lyue longe / it shuld be an infallable payne (nat to lyue after deth: as before) for he that lyueth nat after his corporall deth / shall nat haue that / that he hathe desyred (that is to wete) to lyue longe
/ &amp; shuld abyde in eternal payne / if his desyre were nat accomplysshed. So concluded the sayd Ptholomeus necessa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry thynges for hym and other / to knowe and to do that whiche appertayned / to lyue after deth as before. And truthe it is that he that ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth / but the lyfe of this worlde onely / and thoughe he lyued an .C. yere / yet he lyued nat properly longe. But he shuld lyue longe that
<pb facs="6"/> at the ende of this present lyfe / shulde begyn the lyfe eternall (that is to saye) the lyfe euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lastynge in heuen. So a man oughte to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme his lyfe in this worlde corporally / that they may lyue spiritually without ende. For as he sayd / one shal lyue euerlastyngly with out dyenge / and whan he hathe the pardura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble lyfe he shall be parfyte. And also by this poynt and none otherwyse shalbe accomplys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed the desyre of longe lyuynge in this worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. The foresayd Ptholomeus also knowle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged / that the lyfe of this worlde was soone paste and gone. wherfore this Ptholomeus thought that .lxxii. yeres / here in this vale of wretched mysery / is but a lytell and a small terme of lyfe / to the lyfe euerlastyng: the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che neuer shal haue endynge. And therfore he saythe
/ he that offeryth hym selfe here to lyue vertuously in this worlde / after this lyfe he shall receyue the swete lyue / that is sure and lasteth euer without ende. For though a man lyued here a .C. yere and more: it is but a lytell terme to the lyfe to come. Therfore sayth this Ptholomeus / I wyl lyue soberly with these small temporal goodes that Ihesu hath lende me: and euer to exyle the desyre of worldly ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches and worldly worshyp. For they that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for it: &amp; haue loue to theyr good{is} &amp; vayne
<pb facs="7"/> worshyppes / ofte it departeth mary from he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly treasoure. It shytteth mānes herte that god may nat entre. And buyldeth man a pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of no rest in the lowe lande of derkenesse</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>