<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST ILLVSTRI∣OVS PRINCE HENRY, PRINCE of Wales, Duke of Cornwaile, and Earle of Chester, the confluence of those choise blessings Peace, Grace, and Glory.</title>
           <author>Price, Daniel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115193_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10046</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20292</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115193</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST ILLVSTRI∣OVS PRINCE HENRY, PRINCE of Wales, Duke of Cornwaile, and Earle of Chester, the confluence of those choise blessings Peace, Grace, and Glory.</title>
                 <author>Price, Daniel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The defence of trvth against a booke falsely called The trivmph of trvth sent over from Arras A.D. 1609. By Hvmfrey Leech late minister : Which booke in all particulars is answered, and the adioining motiues of his revolt confuted: by Daniell Price, of Exeter Colledge in Oxford, chaplaine in ordinary to the most high and mighty, the Prince of Wales</title>
                 <author>Price, Daniel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barnes, Joseph</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 379, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST ILLVSTRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OVS PRINCE HENRY, PRINCE of <hi>Wales,</hi> Duke of <hi>Cornwaile,</hi> and Earle of <hi>Chester,</hi> the confluence of those choise blessings <hi>Peace, Grace,</hi> and <hi>Glory.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST GRATIOVS PRINCE with all reverence and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, I present to your <hi>Highnesse this labour.</hi> To whom shoulde I dedicate it? But to your Princelie goodnes, to whose service I haue consecrated my tongue, and pen, and heart, and all the offices of my life: it is an answer to a revolted late Minister, a busines (I may say) imposed me, by some, of very ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable respect, &amp; much encouraged by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, especially the most Reverend <hi>Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop:</hi> our late <hi>Chancelour.</hi> It is the <hi>maintenance</hi> of <hi>truth,</hi> O let it receiue <hi>countenance</hi> from the
<pb facs="3"/> royall heire apparant of <hi>the defender</hi> of the truth. The <hi>infection</hi> of Popery spreads too farre: some come not to our <hi>Church,</hi> others fly our <hi>Land</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> both revile and slander the <hi>Church.</hi> The eies, and harts, and hopes of all the Protestant world, be fixed vpon your <hi>Highnesse,</hi> all expecting your <hi>Gracious</hi> faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, &amp; readines in the extirpation of that man of sinne. March valiantly herein, <hi>Most Gracious Prince,</hi> and the God of Princes shall protect you, his Grace and <hi>Providence</hi> shall reward your faith and <hi>Confidence,</hi> and shall heape vpon your <hi>Highnesse,</hi> favor, and honor, and glory, in both worldes. For which, as long as I haue being, I shall never cease praying.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Highnesse most humbly devoted, and faithfull servant <hi>DANIELL PRICE.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>