<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE, declaring briefely the commodi∣ties of Geometrye, and the necessitye thereof.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1551</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115664_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10541</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20812</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115664</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE, declaring briefely the commodi∣ties of Geometrye, and the necessitye thereof.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pathvvay to knowledg : containing the first principles of geometrie, as they may moste aptly be applied vnto practise, bothe for vse of instrumentes geometricall, and astronomicall and also for proiection of plattes in euerye kinde, and therfore much necessary for all sortes of men</title>
                 <author>Record, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe, Reyner (Reginald)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1551</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>184 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>
      <hi>THE PREFACE,</hi> declaring briefely the commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Geometrye, and the necessitye thereof.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Eometrye may thinke it selfe to sustaine great iniury, if it shall be inforced other to show her mani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fold commodities, or els not to prease into the sight of men, and therefore might this wayes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere briefely: Other I am able to do you muche good, or els but litle. If I bee able to doo you much good, then be you not your owne friendes, but greatlye your owne enemies to make so little of me, which maye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite you so muche. For if I were as vncurteous as you vnkind, I shuld vtterly refuse to do them any good, which will so cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously put me to the trial and profe of my commodities, or els to suffre exile, and namely sithe I shal only yeld benefites to other, and receaue none againe. But and if you could saye truely, that my benefites be nother many nor yet greate, yet if they bee anye, I doo yelde more to you, then I doo receaue againe of you, and therefore I oughte not to bee repelled of them that loue them selfe, althoughe they loue me not at all for my selfe. But as I am in nature a liberall science, so canne I not againste nature contende with your inhumanitye, but muste shewe my selfe liberall euen to myne enemies. Yet this is my comforte againe, that I haue none enemies but them that knowe me not, and therefore may hurte themselues, but can not noye me. Yf they dispraise the thinge that they know not, all wise men will blame them and not credite them. and yf they thinke they knowe me, lette theym shewe one vntruthe and erroure in me, and I wyll geue the victorye.</p>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <p>Yet can no humayne science saie thus, but I onely, that there is no sparke of vntruthe in me: but all my doctrine and workes are without any blemishe of errour that mans reason can dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne. And nexte vnto me in certaintie are my three systers, Arithmetike, Musike, and Astronomie, whiche are also so nere knitte in amitee, that he that loueth the one, can not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spise the other, and in especiall Geometrie, of whiche not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly these thre, but all other artes do borow great ayde, as part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hereafter shall be shewed. But first will I beginne with the vnlearned sorte, that you maie perceiue how that no arte can stand without me. For if I should declare how many wayes my helpe is vsed, in measuryng of ground, for medow, corne, and wodde: in hedgyng, in dichyng, and in stackes makyng, I thinke the poore Husband man would be more thankefull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, then he is nowe, whyses he thinketh that he hath small benefite by me. Yet this maie he coniecture certainly, that if he kepe not the rules of Geometrie, he can not measure any ground truely. And in dichyng, if he kepe not a proportion of bredth in the mouthe, to the bredthe of the bottome, and iuste slopenesse in the sides agreable to them bothe, the diche shall be faultie many waies. When he doth make stackes for corne, or for heye, he practiseth good Geometrie, els would thei not long stand: So that in some stackes, whiche stand on foure pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and yet made round, doe increase greatter and greatter a good height, and then againe turne smaller and smaller vnto the toppe: you maie see so good Geometrie, that it were very difficult to counterfaite the lyke in any kynde of buildyng. As for other infinite waies that he vseth my benefite, I ouerpasse for shortnesse.</p>
   <p>Carpenters, Karuers, Joyners, and Masons, doe willingly acknowledge that they can worke nothyng without reason of Geometrie, in so muche that they chalenge me as a peculiare science for them. But in that they should do wrong to all other men, seyng euerie kynde of men haue som benefit by me, not on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in buildyng, whiche is but other mennes costes, and the arte of Carpenters, Masons, and the other aforesayd, but in their
<pb facs="9"/>owne priuate profession, whereof to auoide tediousnes I make this rehersall.</p>
   <lg>
      <l>Sith Merchauntes by shippes great riches do winne,</l>
      <l>I may with good righte at their feate beginne.</l>
      <l>The Shippes on the sea with Saile and with Ore,</l>
      <l>were firste founde, and styll made, by Geometries lore,</l>
      <l>Their Compas, their Carde, their Pulle is, their Ankers,</l>
      <l>were founde by the skill of witty Geometers.</l>
      <l>To sette forth the Capstocke, and eche other parte,</l>
      <l>wold make a greate showe of Geometries arte.</l>
      <l>Carpenters, Caruers, Ioiners and Masons,</l>
      <l>Painters and Limners with suche occupations,</l>
      <l>Broderers, Goldesmithes, if they be cunning,</l>
      <l>Must yelde to Geometrye thankes for their learning.</l>
      <l>The Carte and the Plowe, who doth them well marke,</l>
      <l>Are made by good Geometrye. And so in the warke</l>
      <l>Of Tailers and Shoomakers, in all shapes and fashion,</l>
      <l>The woorke is not praised, if it wante proportion.</l>
      <l>So we auers by Geometrye hade their foundacion,</l>
      <l>Their Loome is a frame of straunge imaginacion.</l>
      <l>The wheele that doth spinne, the stone that doth grind,</l>
      <l>The Myll that is driuen by water or winde,</l>
      <l>Are workes of Geometrye straunge in their trade,</l>
      <l>Fewe could them deuise, if they were vnmade.</l>
      <l>And all that is wrought by waight or by measure,</l>
      <l>without proofe of Geometry can neuer be sure.</l>
      <l>Clockes that be made the times to deuide,</l>
      <l>The wittiest inuencion that euer was spied,</l>
      <l>Nowe that they are common they are not regarded,</l>
      <l>The artes man contemned, the woorke vnrewarded.</l>
      <l>But if they were scarse, and one for a shewe,</l>
      <l>Made by Geometrye, then shoulde men know,</l>
      <l>That neuer was arte so wonderfull witty,</l>
      <l>So needefull to man, as is good Geometry.</l>
      <l>The firste findinge out of euery good arte,</l>
      <l>Seemed then vnto men so godly a parte,</l>
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <l>That no recompence might satisfye the finder,</l>
      <l>But to make him a god, and honoure him for euer.</l>
      <l>So Ceres and Passas, and Mercury also,</l>
      <l>Eosus and Neptune, and many other mo,</l>
      <l>were honoured as goddes, bicause they did teache,</l>
      <l>Firste tillage and weuinge and eloquent speache,</l>
      <l>Or windes to obserue, the seas to saile ouer,</l>
      <l>They were called goddes for their good indeuour.</l>
      <l>Then were men more thankefull in that golden age:</l>
      <l>This yron worlde no we vngratefull in rage,</l>
      <l>wyll yelde the thy reward for trauaile and paine,</l>
      <l>with sclaunderous reproch, and spitefull disdaine.</l>
      <l>Yet thoughe other men vnthankfull will be,</l>
      <l>Suruayers haue cause to make muche of me.</l>
      <l>And so haue all Lordes, that landes do possesse:</l>
      <l>But Tennauntes I feare will like me the lesse.</l>
      <l>Yet do I not wrong but measure all truely,</l>
      <l>And yelde the full right to euerye man iustely.</l>
      <l>Proportion Geometricall hath no man opprest,</l>
      <l>Yf anye bee wronged, I wishe it redrest.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>But now to procede with learned professions, in Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gike and Rhetorike and all partes of phylosophy, there nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth none other proofe then Aristotle his testimony, whiche without Geometry proueth almost nothinge. In Logike all his good syllogismes and demonstrations, hee declareth by the principles of Geometrye. In philosophye, nether motion, nor time, nor ayrye impressions coulde hee aptely declare, but by the helpe of Geometrye as his woorkes do witnes. Yea the faculties of the minde do the hee expresse by similitude to sigures of Geometrye. And in morall phylosophy he thought that iustice coulde not wel be taught, nor yet well executed without proportion geometricall. And this estimacion of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ometry he maye seeme to haue learned of his maister Plato, which withoute Geometrye wolde teache nothinge, nother wold admitte any to heare him, except he were experte in Geometry. And what merualle if he so muche estemed geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye, seinge his opinion was, that Godde was alwaaies wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge
<pb facs="10"/>kinge by Geometrie? Whiche sentence Plutarche declareth at large. And although Plat o do vse the helpe of Geometrye in all the most waighte matter of a common wealth, yet it is so generall in vse, that no small thinges almost can be wel done without it. And therfore saith he: that Geometrye is to be lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned, if it were for none other cause, but that all other artes are bothe soner and more surely vnderstand by helpe of it.</p>
   <p>What greate help it dothe in physike, Galene doth so often and so copiousely declare, that no man whiche hath redde any booke almoste of his, can be ignorant thereof. in so much that he coulde neuer cure well a rounde vlcere, tyll reason geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metricall dydde teache it hym. Hippocrates is earnest in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyshynge that study of geometrie must prepare the way to physike, as well as to all other artes.</p>
   <p>I shoulde seeme somewhat to tedious, if I shoulde recken vp, howe the diuines also in all their mysteries of scripture doo vse healpe of geometrie: and also that lawyers can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vnderstande the hole lawe, no nor yet the firste title ther of exactly without Geometrie. For if lawes can not well be established, nor iustice duelie executed without geometricall proportion, as bothe Plato in his Politike bokes, and Aristotle in his Moralles doo largely declare. Yea sithe Lycurgus that cheefe lawmaker amongest the Lacedemonians, is moste praised for that he didde chaunge the state of their common wealthe frome the proportion Arithmeticall to a proportion geometricall, whiche without knowledg of bothe he coulde not dooe, than is it easye to perceaue howe necessarie Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrie is for the lawe and studentes thereof. And if I shall saie preciselie and freelie as I thinke, he is vtterlie destitute of all abilitee to iudge in anie arte, that is not sommewhat experte in the Theoremes of Geometrie.</p>
   <p>And that caused Galene to say of hym selfe, that he coulde ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer perceaue what a demonstration was, no not so muche, as whether there were any or none, tyll he had by geometrie gotten abilitee to vnderstande it, although he heard the beste teachers that were in his tyme. It shuld be to longe and nede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse
<pb facs="11"/>also to declare what helpe all other artes Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call haue by geometrie, sith it is the grounde of all theyr cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teintie, and no man studious in them is so doubtful therof, that he shall nede any persuasion to procure credite thereto. For he can not reade .ij. lines almoste in any mathematicall science, but he shall espie the nedefulnes of geometrie. But to auoyde tediousnesse I will make an ende hereof with that famous sentence of auncient Pythagoras, That who so will trauayle by learnyng to attayne wyfedome, shall, neuer approche to any excellencie without the artes mathematicall, and especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Arithmetike and Geometrie.</p>
   <p>And yf I shall somewhat speake of noble men, and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of realmes, howe needefull Geometrye maye bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, then must I repete all that I haue sayde before, sithe in them ought all knowledge to abounde, namely that maye appertaine either to good gouernaunce in time of peace, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wittye pollicies in time of warre. For ministration of good lawes in time of peace Lycurgus example with the testi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monies of Plato and Aristotle may suffise. And as for war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, I might thinke it sufficient that Vegetius hath written, and after him Valturius in commendation of Geometry, for vse of warres, but all their woordes seeme to saye nothinge, in comparison to the example of Archimedes worthy woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes made by geometrie, for the defence of his countrey, to reade the wonderfull praise of his wittie deuises, set foorthe by the moste famous hystories of Liuius, Plutarche, and Plinie, and all other hystoriographiers, whyche wryte of the stronge siege of <hi>Syracusae</hi> made by that vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant capitayne, and noble warriour <hi>Marcellus,</hi> whose po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer was so great, that all men meruayled how that one ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee coulde withstande his wonderfull force so longe. But much more woulde they meruaile, if they vnderstode that one man onely dyd withstand all Marcellus strength, and with coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter engines destroied his engines to the vtter astonyshment of <hi>Marcellus,</hi> and all that were with hym. He had inuented suche balastelas that dyd shoote out a hundred dartes at one
<pb facs="11"/>shotte, to the great destruction of <hi>Marcellus</hi> souldiours, wherby a fonde tale was spredde abrode, how that in Syracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sae there was a wonderfull gyant, whiche had a hundred han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and coulde shoote a hundred dartes at ones. And as this fable was spredde of Archimedes, so many other haue been fayned to bee gyantes and monsters, bycause they dyd suche thynges, whiche farre passed the witte of the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. So dyd they feyne Argus to haue a hundred eies, bicause they herde of his wonderfull circumspection, and thoughte that as it was aboue their capacitee, so it could not be, onlesse he had a hundred eies. So imagined they Janus to haue two faces, one lokyng forwarde, and an other backwarde, bycause he coulde so wittily compare thynges paste with thynges that were to come, and so duely pondre them, as yf they were all present. Of like reasō did they feyn Lynceus to haue such sharp syght, that he coulde see through walles and hylles, bycause peraduenture he dyd by naturall iudgement declare what cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditees myght be digged out of the grounde. And an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite noumbre lyke fables are there, whiche sprange all of lyke reason.</p>
   <p>For what other thyng meaneth the fable of the great gyant Atlas, whiche was ymagined to beare vp heauen on his shul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders? but that he was a man of so high a witte, that it reached vnto the skye, and was so skylfull in Astronomie, and coulde tell before hande of Eclipses, and other like thynges as truely as though he dyd rule the sterres, and gouerne the planettes.</p>
   <p>So was Eolus accompted god of the wyndes, and to haue theim all in a caue at his pleasure, by reason that he was a wit tie man in naturall knowlege, and obserued well the change of wethers, and was the fyrst that taught the obseruation of the wyndes. And lyke reson is to be geuen of al the old fables.</p>
   <p>But to retourne agayne to Archimedes, he dyd also by arte perspectiue (whiche is a parte of geometrie) deuise such glas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses within the towne of Syracusae, that dyd bourne their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies shyppes a great way from the to wne, whyche was a meruaylous politike thynge. And if I shulde repete the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietees
<pb facs="12"/>of suche straunge inuentions, as Archimedes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue wrought by geometrie, I should not onely excede the order of a preface, but I should also speake of suche thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges as can not well be vnderstande in talke, without somme knowledge in the principles of geometrie.</p>
   <p>But this will I promyse, that if I may perceaue my pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to be thankfully taken, I wyll not onely write of suche pleasant inuentions, declaryng what they were, but also wil teache howe a great numbre of them were wroughte, that they may be practised in this tyme also. Wherby shall be plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly perceaued, that many thynges seme impossible to be done, whiche by arte may very well be wrought. And whan they be wrought, and the reason therof not vnderstande, than say the vulgare people, that those thynges are done by negroman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. And hereof came it that fryer Bakon was accompted so greate a negromancier, whiche neuer vsed that arte (by any coniecture that I can fynde) but was in geometrie and other mathematicall sciences so experte, that he coulde dooe by theim suche thynges as were wonderfull in the syght of most people.</p>
   <p>Great talke there is of a glasse that he made in Oxforde, in whiche men myght see thynges that were doon in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and that was iudged to be done by power of euyll spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites. But I knowe the reason of it to bee good and naturall, and to be wrought by geometrie (sythe perspectiue is a parte of it) and to stande as well with reason as to see your face in cōmon glasse. But this conclusion and other dyuers of lyke sorte, are more mete for princes, for sundry causes, than for other men, and ought not to bee taught commonly. Yet to repete it, I thought good for this cause, that the worthynes of geometry myght the better be knowen, &amp; partly vnderstanding geuen, what wonderfull thynges may be wrought by it, and so consequently how pleasant it is, and how necessary also.</p>
   <p>And thus for this tyme I make an end. The reason of som thynges done in this boke, or omitted in the same, you shall fynde in the preface before the Theoremes.</p>
   <pb facs="12"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>