<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE TRVLY HONOVRABLE, MY MOST HONO∣red Cousins, Sir WAL∣TER ROBERTS, Knight and Baronet: and to his gracious Lady, everlasting Consolaios of the Eternall Com∣forter.</title>
           <author>Fletcher, Phinees</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115109_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00975</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11080</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115109</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE TRVLY HONOVRABLE, MY MOST HONO∣red Cousins, Sir WAL∣TER ROBERTS, Knight and Baronet: and to his gracious Lady, everlasting Consolaios of the Eternall Com∣forter.</title>
                 <author>Fletcher, Phinees</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ioy in tribulation. Or, Consolations for the afflicted spirits : By Phinees Fletcher, B.D. and minister of Gods Word at Hilgay in Norfolke</title>
                 <author>Fletcher, Phineas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Boler (Bowler), James 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 339, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE TRVLY HONOVRABLE, MY MOST HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Cousins, Sir WAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER ROBERTS, Knight and Baronet: and to his gracious Lady, everlasting Consola<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s of the Eternall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, your very anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Gentry doth not so enoble you in the eyes of the
<pb facs="3"/>
world, as your new man in the sight of the Church:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Greg. Naz.</hi>
      </note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, saith that ancient &amp; eloquent Father, <hi>The new birth is the noblest birth</hi>: In the Creation, Man was the first, and last creature; last in time, first in place and dignily, being made the <hi>Sonne of God,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luk 3. 38.</note> and the great Favourite of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. And now the New Creature, though last borne, as <hi>Iacob,</hi> yet as <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>b,</hi> obtaines the birth-right, and over-tops the elder. The best Herald,
<pb facs="3"/>
Gods blessed Spirit, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferres the <hi>Beraeans</hi> as more Noble, or best borne,<note place="margin">Acts 17.11</note> who <hi>received the Word with all readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of minde, &amp;c.</hi> And surely if high bloud of Generous parents sets us aloft in the eye of the world, how much more lustre among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians will that immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall seede give you, whereby you <hi>are borne,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.13<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>not of bloud, nor of the will of the flesh, nor of the will of man, but of God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>Now though I well know that the neare relation of fleshly Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and bloud which is betwixt us, (beside many other knots of friendship) have tyed my heart, long since, unto you both, in all unfeyned affection, yet this spirituall kindred is a much dearer, and nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer linke, uniting my soule unto you in the bond of the Spirit; so that I can truly say with that blessed Apostle,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>es. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.8</note>
      <hi>I am affectionately desirous
<pb facs="4"/>
of you, and willing to impart to you</hi> (not onely this slender fruit of) <hi>the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell</hi> (but) <hi>mine owne soule, bebause you were deare un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee.</hi> I am confident you will receive this pledge of love with the same af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ection with which it is presented, and therefore leaving these few Consolations to the application of that great Comforter, and your selves with all your Olive branches, unto the Vnction of that holy one, and perfect growth
<pb facs="5"/>
of the blessed Spirit, I commend the weake Author to your Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an love, and prayers, who while hee is, shall ever be</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your willing servant in the Lord Iesus,
PHINEES FLETCHER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>