<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS MVCH HONOVRED FRIEND.</title>
           <author>O., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115112_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01008</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11113</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115112</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS MVCH HONOVRED FRIEND.</title>
                 <author>O., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A plea for the reall-presence : Wherein the preface of Syr Humfrey Linde, concerning the booke of Bertram, is examined and censured. Written by I.O. vnto a gentleman his friend</title>
                 <author>Floyd, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Boscard, Charles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 62, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HIS MVCH HONOVRED FRIEND.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>YR, I haue recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Booke of <hi>Bertram,</hi> translated into English, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed by <hi>Syr Humfrey Linde,</hi> with a dedicatory, and a longe Preface before it, and togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your request to haue my iudgement, aswell concerning the credit of the treatise, as the verity of the Preface. Your sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular affection and manifold curtesies shewed towards me,
<pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="3" facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="4" facs="4"/>
ioyned with your so religious loue of the Catholike truth, haue so obliged my selfe and my studyes vnto you, as I may not be backeward in yeelding vnto your so pious and iust re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest. For I know your require this Censure not for your own satisfaction (who are better grounded, then to be remoued, or moued with the vanity of such a trifle) but for the more full information of some of your friends, whome <hi>Syr Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey</hi> would engage to run the same vnaduised course with himselfe, who doth<note n="(a)" place="margin">Praefa. fol. 3. b. lin 21. &amp; fol. 14. b. lin. 16.</note>
      <hi>engage the credit of his Religion, &amp; the surety of his Saluation vpon the worthines of this Tracte.</hi> I haue
<pb n="5" facs="4"/>
heerin exceeded the breuity of a Censure, as being desirous to lay open not only the insuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of <hi>this Preface,</hi> to preuent the Readers danger, but also briefly the verity of the Reall-presence, for the Prefacers, by me desired, conuersion vnto the Catholike church. The worke being wholly and total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yours by the free &amp; full gift of the Authour, you may dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose thereof at your pleasure, and if you iudge the same pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixe, you may select such par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles thereof, as you shall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steeme most fit to be sent to your friends, and to accept of the whole (as I know you will)
<pb n="6" facs="5"/>
with the same affection as it is offered vnto you by him, who doth euer rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your seruant in Christ Iesus. <hi>I.O.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>