<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right VVorshipfull, Master RALPH FREEMAN, Alderman of LONDON, all increase of true Happinesse.</title>
           <author>Procter, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115290_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B15398</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20405</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115290</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right VVorshipfull, Master RALPH FREEMAN, Alderman of LONDON, all increase of true Happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Procter, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvatchman vvarning : A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the 26. of September, 1624. By William Procter, Master of Arts, and minister of Gods Word</title>
                 <author>Procter, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 55, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right VVorshipfull, Master RALPH FREEMAN, <hi>Alderman of</hi> LONDON, all increase of true <hi>Happinesse.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Sir, I haue been sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by sundry well affected ones, not to suffer this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon (being a forewarning of this famous Citie especially, and whole kingdome also) to die in obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uion. As, many elaborate Sermons, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after sore labour &amp; trauaile they are brought into the world, they are reuiued (perhaps) with your accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and applause; but their life and being in mens memories, doth scarce equalize the life of that beast, whereof both <hi>Aristotle</hi> and <hi>Plutarch</hi> doe write, called <hi>Ephemeron,</hi> the length of whose
<pb facs="3"/>life was but for the space of one day, as the name signifieth.</p>
   <p>Amongst many titles, which the Lord in holy Scripture hath vouchsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed vs his Ministers, hee hath called vs <hi>Watchmen.</hi> Wherefore I being called to this great place, and appointed to be set (this were) in the <hi>Watch-tower:</hi> during my allotted time of watching, I haue carefully indeauored to warne the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to forewarne them of those euils, which their sinnes are ready to hale vpon them.</p>
   <p>Howsoeuer the subiect of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon doth concerne this whole most honourable Corporation, and especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the supreme Officers, who in their seuerall places should (as <hi>Moses</hi>) stand in the gap, &amp; with the Pruning-hooke of Iustice, cut downe bundles of vices, that so the incursion of Gods wrath may be stopped. Yet I haue presumed (right worthy Sir) to single out your selfe, and to affixe onely your Name to
<pb facs="3"/>the Dedication; both for the good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port which I haue receiued concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning your pious zeale in the discharge of that great Place and Office, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in lately you were imployed; and (I hope) that others in eminent places and offices will imitate your vertues; As also to testifie my thankefulnesse, for some expressions of your Loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me. Accept (I beseech you) of this my good intendment, who shall bee euer ready to demonstrate my selfe</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours most humbly deuoted to be commanded in the Lord, <hi>WILLIAM PROCTER.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>