<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull and my verie deare friends, Sir Lestraunge Mordaunt of Massingham Hall, in the Countie of Norfolke, Knight Baro∣net, and Lady Frances Mordaunt, his most louing Bed-fellow: HENRY GREENVVOOD. Wisheth all increase of Grace in this Life, and Eternall Life in Life to come.</title>
           <author>Greenwood, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115797_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02186</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12329</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115797</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull and my verie deare friends, Sir Lestraunge Mordaunt of Massingham Hall, in the Countie of Norfolke, Knight Baro∣net, and Lady Frances Mordaunt, his most louing Bed-fellow: HENRY GREENVVOOD. Wisheth all increase of Grace in this Life, and Eternall Life in Life to come.</title>
                 <author>Greenwood, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Greenvvoods vvorkes : contayned in fiue seueral tractates. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. of the Day of iudgement. Lords Prayer. Race to saluation. Torment of Tophet. Baptisme of Christ</title>
                 <author>Greenwood, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bell, Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Clarke, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 117, 1, 6, 92, 12, 8, 82, 6, 10, 43, 11 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="122"/>
   <pb facs="122"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull and my verie <hi>deare friends, Sir</hi> Lestraunge Mordaunt <hi>of</hi> Massingham <hi>Hall,</hi> in <hi>the Countie of</hi> Norfolke, <hi>Knight Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, and Lady</hi> Frances Mordaunt, his most louing Bed-fellow: HENRY GREENVVOOD. Wisheth all increase of Grace in <hi>this Life, and Eternall Life in Life to come.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is, and hath beene long since (Right Worshipfull) the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome of the Learned, that when they commended to publike view (therein ayming a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> common good) their Christian
<pb facs="123"/>
pains and diuine indeuors (know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the truth hath and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes had many oppositions and detractions) to present them to men of high place, and well affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in Religion, that so their works might passe with lesse feare, and danger of disgrace and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probry: I (though vnlearned) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king bold to imitate their Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an policie herein, haue presumed to present that doctrine to your Worships eyes, that lately in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like place was sounded in your eares, both of which senses are great instruments in the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of our soules in the way of Gods Kingdome; for as the eare conuayeth grace to the affections of the soule; so the eye bringeth much matter to the vnderstanding of the minde; nay, the eare cannot so often be an Andito, as the eye
<pb facs="123"/>
an Oratour to the Conscience.</p>
   <p>For which cause (your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships nothing more affecting than growth in grace and Religion) I haue attempted to commend to your often consideration, <hi>Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Tophet:</hi> for as nothing allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the heart to grace, more then Gods mercies, so nothing is more preualent against sinne than his fearfull and terrible Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
   <p>If therfore your gracious Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships shall vouchsafe to accept of these my poore presented pains, it will giue much content to mine own heart, &amp; (doubtlesse) answera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble comfort to your owne soules.</p>
   <p>And to conclude, as the Lord hath aboundantly blessed your Worships with graces internal, &amp; blessings externall; So (to vse the words of the Apostle) <hi>the very God
<pb facs="124"/>
of peace sanctifie you still throughout, and I pray God that your whole spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and Soules, and bodies, may be kept blamelesse to the comming of our Lord Iesus Christ,</hi> Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From Hempsted in Essex, <date>Ianuary, 10. 1629.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Worships alwaies ready<lb/>
to be commanded in the<lb/>
LORD.<lb/>
         <hi>Henry Greenwood.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>