<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Addendum]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115279_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17298</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4140.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115279</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Addendum]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A divine tragedie lately acted, or A collection of sundry memorable examples of Gods judgements upon Sabbath-breakers, and other like libertines, in their unlawfull sports, happening within the realme of England, in the compass only of two yeares last past, since the booke was published : worthy to be knowne and considered of all men, especially such, who are guilty of the sinne or arch-patrons thereof</title>
                 <author>Burton, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stam, Jan Fredericksz</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 46, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="addendum">
   <pb n="43" facs="27"/>
   <p>Christian Reader, as these examples have beene displaced, so one of<note place="margin">Examp. 57.</note> them hath beene omitted in the printing, which because it is notable and worthy consideration, I shall here adde for a conclusion. M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Noy,</hi> that great <hi>Gamaliel</hi> of the Law, his Majesties late Aturney generall, as he had a great hand in compiling and republishing the late Declaration for pastimes on the Lords day (thrust out by his, and a great Prelates practise, to thwart Iudge <hi>Richardsons</hi> good order for the suppressing of Wakes and Revels in <hi>Somersetshire,</hi> and the Iustices of that Shires Petition to his Majesty for the continuance of it, and to make way for a Starchamber censure against M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Prynne</hi>) so he eagerly persecuted this wel-deserving Gentleman of his own Profession and Society, (to whom he was formerly a friend in appearance, but an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veterate enemy in truth) for his <hi>Histrio-Mastix,</hi> compiled onely out of the words and sentences of other approved Authors of all sorts, against the use and exercise of Stage-plaies, Enterludes, Morisdances, Maygames, May-poles, Wakes, lascivious mixt Dancing, and other Ethnick pastimes, condemned in all ages, without any thought or su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spition of giving the least offence, either to the Kings most excellent Majesty, the Queene, or State, as he averred in his Answer upon Oath. And although this book was written 4. yeares, licensed almost three, printed fully off a quarter of a yeare, and published 6. weekes before the Queenes Majesties <note n="*" place="margin">One of the actors wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of and hee who first shewed his Booke to the King with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in few mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths after came to bee his fellow prisoners in the Tower for a reall comentary on his mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>applyed text</note> Pastorall, against which it was falsely voiced to have beene principally written; diligently perused and licensed by M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Thomas Buckner</hi> the then Archbishop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> his Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine, both before and after it came from the Presse, entred in the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners Hall under the Wardens hand, printed publikely in three au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized Printing-houses, without the least controll, and published by the said Licensers direction, who would have nothing new-prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in it, as appeared upon oath at the hearing: and although M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Noy</hi> himselfe (to whom he presented one of the Bookes) upon the first reading of it, commended it, thanked him for it, oft affirmed that he saw no hurt in it, and at the hearing confessed, that the worst and most dangerous phrase and passage in it, might have a good and faire construction, and Schollers would all take it in a good sence; yet he handled the matter so (by <note n="*" place="margin">The Iudge who upon his reference suppressed these exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to law &amp; promise to the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, was himselfe not long after unexpected<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thrust out of his place before he knew of it.</note> suppressing the Gentlemans exhibits and defence, wresting his words and meaning, refusing to discover the particulars of the booke on which he would insist, though ordered so to doe by the Court, it being else impossible to instruct Counsell how to make a reply, and by tampering under hand with some of his


<pb n="44" facs="28"/>
Counsell by no meanes to make any justification or defence to cleare his innocency though the party earnestly intreated, and gave them instructions to the contrary) that the poore Gentleman at last recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the heaviest<note n="y" place="margin">The great Lord that began this censure lost his Lady in childb<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d some three dayes after, who much grieved at this sentence and blamed him for it. Which Lord riding the last Christ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide into the Country to keepe his Christmas on the Lords day, his Coach and honor in the plaine street at <hi>Brain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> were both over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned and laid in the dirt, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe sore bruised, and thereupon forced to keepe his chamber a good space, there being some doubt of his reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very for a time.</note> censure that this latter age hath knowne, all cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances considered, being expelled the Vniversity of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Lincolnes Inne,</hi> thrust from his profession in which hee never offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, fined 5000. pound to the King, ordered to stand on two severall Pillories, and there to lose both his eares, his bookes to be there bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned before him, and to suffer imprisonment during life besides. Which Sentence thought by most that heard the cause to bee meant only in <hi>terrorem,</hi> without any intention at al of execution, being respi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for above three moneths space, and in a manner remitted by the Queenes most gracious mediation; was yet by this Atturnies and a great Prelates importunity, beyond all expectation suddenly and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely executed, without any the least mitigation, few of the Lords so much as knowing of it. The Gentleman hereupon is set on the Pillory at <hi>Westminster</hi> and there lost an eare; Mr. <hi>Noy</hi> like a joyfull Spectator laughes at his sufferings, and this his great exploit he had brought to passe, which divers there present observed and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in him. The Gentleman like an harmelesse Lambe tooke all with such patience, that hee not so much as once opened his mouth to let fall any one word of discontent. Yet that just God and Soveraigne Lord of heaven and earth, <note n="z" place="margin">Psal. 10. 14.</note>
      <hi>Who beholdeth mischiefe and spite to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite it with his hand,</hi> and avengeth the innocent bloud of his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, took this his mirth and malice so hainously, that the same day (as some about him, and of his owne society reported) he who thus shed his brothers and companions bloud, by the just hand of God fell a voyding and pissing out his owne: which so amazed him, that he used all meanes he could to smother it from the world, charging his Laundres, and those about him, not to speake of it, refusing to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint his Physicians with it: hereupon hee growes very palid and ill, the Physicians wonder at it; he complaines to them onely of the gravell and stone in his kidnies, till at last he grew so ill with this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine stroke, that he was forced to disclose his griefe to them, yet so as they must faithfully promise to disclose it to no man, for feare peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple should say it were a just judgement of God on him for shedding Mr. <hi>Prynnes</hi> blood: But God would not have this secret long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed; his Laundres, men, &amp; some Gentlemen of his society discover and talke of it: he much vexed in mind, in stead of repenting of what


<pb n="45" facs="28"/>
he had done, and seeking to right the party wronged for his irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable dammage, like a Hart or Beast once mortally wounded, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds on in his former fury, seeks to bring the poore distressed Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman into fresh trouble &amp; a further censure, brings him Oretenus, into the Starchamber, reviles him with all maner of uncivell words, moves to have him close prisoner among the rogues in Newgate, sels his Chamber as forfeited to the House by his expulsion, seiseth his books: and when as the Court would not grant his unreasonable ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious motion, above 5. weeks after in the long vacation, when most of the Lords were gone, and his Majesty in his progresse, drawes up an order of his own making in Starchamber for the Gentlemans close imprisonment (the last order he ever made) caused the register to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, and sends it to the Tower to be executed the same day he went to <hi>Tunbridge</hi> waters, without the Lords or Courts privity. The day following drinking of those waters he was in miserable torture, in so much that most dispaired of his life, and some reported he was dead: and hearing there, that his disease of voyding bloud was then pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely known and talked of in <hi>London,</hi> he was so vexed at it, that hee fell out with his Physicians and servants, rayling on them like a fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick man, as if they had betrayed him, and disclosed his secrets; Yea it so fretted and gnawed his heart &amp; conscience, that it made his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry heart &amp; intrails to perish: and about a fortnight after brought him to his end. Being opened after his death, ther was not a drop of bloud found in his body, for he had voided al out before, his false malicious hard heart with inward fretting &amp; vexing was so consumed &amp; shrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked up, that it was like an old rotten leather purse or meere scurfe, the Physicians never seeing the like before, his flesh and kidnies were as black as an hat, his intrails (except his lungs onely) all putred; and his carkas a miserable spectacle, but no stone that could trouble him was found about him: his funerall according to his desire was so private, that there were hardly Gentlemen enough to carry him to his grave, but that some came in by accident. His clients the Players, for whom he had done knight-service, to requite his kindnes, the next Terme following make him the subject of a merry Comedy, stiled; <hi>A Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jector lately dead;</hi> wherein they bring him in his Lawyers robes upon the Stage, and openly dissecting him, find 100. Proclamations in his head, a bundle of old motheaten records in his maw, halfe a barrell of new white sope in his belly, which made him to scoure so much, and yet, say they, he is still very black &amp; foule within. And as if this voiding of all his owne blood, &amp; publike disgrace on the Stage were


<pb n="46" facs="29"/>
not sufficient to expiate the wronged Gentlemans bloud &amp; infamy: himselfe in his last will layes a brand on his owne son and heire: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathing all his goods and lands not therein given to others, to <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> his eldest son to be scattered and spent, <hi>nec de eo melius speravi:</hi> enough to make a dutifull child turne unthrift, &amp; a signe of a dispay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring man. Which son of his upon his own challenge &amp; rashnes hath since beene slaine in a duell in <hi>France</hi> by Captaine <hi>Byron,</hi> who escaped scotfree and had his pardon. Thus hath God punished bloud with bloud: thus hath he dealt with one of the chiefe occasioners of this <note n="*" place="margin">The occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of most of these tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.</note> Declaration, &amp; burner of that book, which learnedly manifested the unlawfulnes of the severall sports and pastimes countenanced in it, especially on the Lords own sacred day out of old and new Writers of all sorts, &amp; specified divers judgements of God upon the authors, actors, &amp; spectators of them, not unworthy consideration in these sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble times of plagues and judgements. O consider this &amp; all other the foregoing examples, ye impious Prelates, that so far forget the Lord, as still to silence, excommunicate &amp; persecute godly Ministers for not reading this Declaration (though there be no Canon, Statute, Law or Precept extant that requires it) to the ruine, not so much of them, as their poore innocent peoples soules: ye that in these dolefull daies of Plague and pestilence suppresse, neglect all publike fasting, preaching and praying, which now if ever should be cried up &amp; practised, and in stead thereof give your selves over to <note n="*" place="margin">Neh. 13. 17. 18.</note>
      <hi>dancing,</hi> feasting, playing, <note n="*" place="margin">Bishops saith <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine Cont. Btil. l. 3. c. 6.)</hi> were all wont vaine dances to reprove, But now they are so farre from it, that they to dance doe love. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Lovel his Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue.</hi> Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes their late <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> pro phane plaies and dances.</note>
      <hi>Sabbath breaking, to draw downe more wrath and plagues upon us.</hi> You who oppresse &amp; maliciously persecute godly men, for crossing you in your delights of sin, lest ye now perish as these have done, &amp; so much the rather, because you have al these presidents to admonish you, and yet will not be warned. Well, if you will not be admonished but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed as you have done, if you perish, thanke your selves; I can say no more to you but this: <note n="*" place="margin">Virgil.</note>
      <hi>Discite justitiam moniti &amp; non temnere divos.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>