<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most High and mighty Princesse Elizabeth, by the grace of God Queene of England, Fraunce and Ireland, de∣fendres of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1587</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115957_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10716</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20995</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115957</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most High and mighty Princesse Elizabeth, by the grace of God Queene of England, Fraunce and Ireland, de∣fendres of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A path-vvay to military practise : Containinge offices, lawes, disciplines and orders to be obserued in an army, with sundry stratagems very beneficiall for young gentlemen, or any other that is desirous to haue knowledge in martiall exercises. Whereunto is annexed a kalender of the imbattelinge of men: newlie written by Barnabe Rich souldiour, seruaunt to the right honorable Sir Christopher Hatton Knight. Perused and allowed</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1587</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Walley (Waley), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the most High and mighty Princesse</hi> Elizabeth, by the grace of God Queene of <hi>England, Fraunce and Ireland,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendres of the Faith, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Souldiour, <hi>(most excellent Princesse,) hauing receiued so manie gratious wordes for other of his writinges, the which it hath pleased your Maiesty so fauorably to vouchsafe, is not therby onely incouraged, now once againe to betake him to his Penne, but also he is imboldned to present to your gratious viewe, this litle labour, containing</hi> A Path-way to Military Practise. <hi>The title best befitting to come from a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour, yet the circumstaunces not vnnecessarie to bee considered of, by such as be in authoritie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>And although I knowe the greatest number (which can not abide to here of warres) are as vnwilling to admit of any thinge appertaining to Martiality when they haue so longe continued in Peace, yet as in the time of warre, circumspect care of peace may not be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, so in the time of peace, such thinges must bee foreseene appertaininge to the wrrre, that the want of warlike prouiisons, bee not preiudiciall to this sweete</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
and quiet peace, for as <hi>Valerius Maximus</hi> faith, <hi>the custodie of blessed Peace consisteth in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of VVarre: Plato</hi> praising the Arte, commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that children should learne it so soone as they were of abilitie, <hi>Cirus</hi> sayd it was as necessarie as hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandriē, <hi>Augustine</hi> and <hi>Barnarde,</hi> both Catholique doctours of the Church doo approoue it.</p>
   <p>The <hi>Romaines</hi> appointed a longe and spacious field which they called <hi>Campus Martius,</hi> wherein they exercised their youth in the knowledge of Martiall feates: They likewise inuented glorious triumphes, which was to no other ende but to stirre vp the minds of their people to magnanimitie and martiall exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cises. <hi>Cambises</hi> the father of <hi>Cyrus</hi> being asked by what meanes countries might best be kept in safety, aunswered. <hi>If the gouernours of the same coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, thinkes they can neuer bee warie inough of their enemies.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And although <hi>Salomon,</hi> (who in the holy scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is called <hi>Rex Pacificus)</hi> beeing promised by the mouth of God a peaceable raigne, and was still busied in the building of the holie temple, forgat not yet to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishe himselfe more strongly with all manner of war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like prouisions, then his father <hi>Dauid</hi> had done before him, notwithstanding he was still exercised and busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the warres</p>
   <p>Here I could alleadge infinite examples, and as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie probable reasons might be geathered, all in defence of martiall practise, for he that taketh away the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of feates of armes, worketh the ouerthrowe of his
<pb facs="3"/>
owne countrey and common wealth: And as by the knowledge of warre and exercise of armes, Empires haue beene purchased, Kingdomes enlarged, Princes preserued, Iustice maintained, good Lawes protected, and the Common wealth defended, so in neglectinge martiall exercises and laying aside of their weapons, how many kingdomes hath beene brought to calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, howe many countries ruinated, and howe many florishinge Citties sacked, beaten flatte to the ground, couered ouer with moulde, and almost worne out of memorie. But as your maiesty, hauing most prouident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie furnished euery parte of your Realme, withall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of warlike prouision, in such sorte, as none of your predecessours hath euer heeretofore come neere, so could I wishe, that in England wee were as well fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, with practised Souldiours and expert warri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, although I doo not meane, that they should bee warre loouers.</p>
   <p>And as it is most apparaunt, that the regarde your maiestie haue had (euen sith you first became our soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne) in all manner your princely proceedinges, hath so wonderfully blessed your estate, that all Christian Princes doo honour and renowne you, so wee your loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge subiectes (feeling the benefit of your peaceable gouernement) haue no lesse cause to giue God all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory, and daily to pray for the longe conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuaunce of so gracious a princesse. And as it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed God, so wonderfully to defende your maiesty, from such seueral practises, intended against your roiall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son by Papistes, let their treasons (most humbly I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeche
<pb facs="4"/>
you) be made examples (aswell for your owne safetie, as also for the benefit of the whole common wealth of England) whom your maiesty may hereafter trust.</p>
   <p>These be the men (O most gratious Princesse) that he sworn your mortal enimies, these be the men, O noble England that seekes thy wracke &amp; ouerthrow: Let thē haue no gouernement within your maiesties domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, let them beare no sway in any part of your terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories: Plucke him from the bench though he sit robed in purple, dismisse him the barre, though he be called Sergiant at the Law, put him out of comission, though hebeare the name of Iustice of Peace: pardō me (most gracious Princesse) in discharging my dutie, though simplie yet truely, Souldiours are but blunte, but sure they looue plainnes.</p>
   <p>Thus desiringe God most earnestly and according to my duety, that as he hath hether to wonderfullie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued you in most magnificent and Princely regality, (in dispite of all the enterprises and practises of trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terours Papistes) so he would continue your maiesty longe to raigne ouer vs, to the great comfort of all your loouing subiectes, and for the prosperity and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing estate of the common wealth of England.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties Souldiour most humble and dutifull to bee commaunded: Barnabe Riche.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>