<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONORABLE Companie of Merchants of the Citie of London.</title>
           <author>Price, Daniel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115212_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10050</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20296</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115212</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONORABLE Companie of Merchants of the Citie of London.</title>
                 <author>Price, Daniel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The marchant : A sermon preached at Pavles Crosse on Sunday the 24. of August, being the day before Bartholomew faire. 1607. By Daniell Price Master of Arts, of Exeter Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Price, Daniel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barnes, Joseph</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 31, 34-38 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HONORABLE Companie of Merchants of the Citie of London.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Onourable, worshipfull, &amp; belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, at the last I am come to the execution of my first in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to the dedication of this Crosse labour. It was long since prepared for you, and now at the length presented vnto you, the Lord giue all of you a spirituall blessing by it. Some honourable, and many favourable gales of winde haue at length brought home this
<hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant</hi> vnto you, though in my labour in conducting ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I haue ventured my credit to the wide sea of common opinion. I confesse it is not the <hi>Merchant Royall</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to <hi>Salomon,</hi> laden with gold, and silver, ivory, and apes and Peacocks: But yet is such a
<hi>Merchant</hi> as <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> in all his riches was not so great as he. It is a holie and heavenly Merchant carefull in search, happy in successe whom neither the tediousnesse of the way, nor difficultie of the straites could hinder, but that he pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth through the worlds Ocean, with speede, and gaine, and glorie, Christ being his Pilot, faith his sterne, hope
<pb facs="3"/>his ancor, Conscience his carde, good works his lading, happinesse his landing, and his haven heaven.</p>
   <p>At that great Marte whereas I was commaunded this businesse I fitted the time with this Text, I hope this Text fitted some of you at that time, and my praier vnto God shall be that you may be fitted by this vnto the attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of your eternall salvation, and so I commend these labours vnto you, and your selues and them vnto God.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From Exeter Colledge</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>this 20. of Aprill. 1608.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Yours in the Lord Iesus <hi>DANIEL PRICE.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>