<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ Bertram the Priest, his Preface, concerning the body and blood of the LORD, written to Charles the great, being Emperour.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115659_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10472</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20752</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115659</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ Bertram the Priest, his Preface, concerning the body and blood of the LORD, written to Charles the great, being Emperour.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A booke of Bertram the priest, concerning the body and blood of Christ : written in Latin to Charles the Great, being Emperour, aboue eight hundred yeeres agoe. Translated and imprinted in the English tongue. Anno Dnj. 1549</title>
                 <author>Ratramnus, monk of Corbie</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>38, 80, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="18"/>
   <head>¶ <hi>Bertram</hi> the Priest, his Preface, concerning <hi>the body and blood of the</hi> LORD, written to Charles <hi>the great,</hi> being Emperour.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am commanded by you (famous Prince) to declare vnto your Highnesse, What iudgement I am of, concerning the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie of the Bodie and Blood of Christ. Certaine it is, that as this commandement, doth well beseeme your magnificall and Princely estate: so is it a most hard thing to be performed by my poore and small power. For what is
<pb facs="19"/>
more meete for your Kingly Providence and government, than in respect of your selfe to be vniversally wise, concerning his holy mysteries, who hath vouchsafed you worthy of the Kingly seate: and in respect of your Subiects, not to suffer them to thinke divers things, concerning the bodie and blood of Christ, in which, doubtlesse, consisteth the whole summe of Christian Redemption? For while some of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full affirme, that the mysterie or Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the body and blood of Christ (which is daily celebrated and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred in the Church) is done vnder no fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, and vnder no cover at all, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>med vnder the naked manifestation &amp; shew of the truth it selfe: and againe, while other some testifie, that these things are conteined vnder the figure of the mystery, and that it is one thing which appeareth to our bodily senses, and another thing that our faith looketh vpon, it plainly appeareth that there is no small diversitie and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence amongst them. And whereas the Apostle writeth vnto the faithfull people, <hi>That all of them should savour one thing,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.10.</note>
      <hi>and speake one thing, and that
<pb facs="19"/>
no schisme should appeare amongst them,</hi> we must needs say, that they are by no small schisme divided, and rent asun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, who not thinking the selfe same things doe speake diversly of the mysterie of the bodie and blood of Christ. Wherefore your Kingly Maiestie and Highnesse being provoked no doubt with the zeale of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion (though perhaps not quietly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently considering of these things) and desiring also, that all men should (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Apostles Commandement) <hi>thinke and speake one thing</hi> doth dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently search for the mysterie and secret of truth, that so you may call backe such therevnto, as haue wandred and strayed. Wherevpon also it commeth to passe, that you disdaine not, to demand and aske the truth of this matter, even of very poore and base men, perswading your selfe, that the mysterie of so great a secret, cannot be knowne, but by inspiration and revelation from God, who having no respect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, sheweth forth the light of his truth, by whomsoever he himselfe hath chosen to so great a matter. Now, as it is very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant for me poore man, to obey your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement:
<pb facs="20"/>
so I confesse it is a very hard matter for me, to dispute and reason of a matter so farre estranged from mans vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding and senses, and into which a man cannot pearse or enter, but by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction and teaching of the holy Spirit. Wherefore, I being at this present subiect, to your Highnesse commandement, and yet trusting and cleaving to the ayde and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance of him of whom we will speake, will assay by what words I can to open my iudgement concerning this matter, not leaning in the treatie thereof to mine owne wit, but pursuing and treading in the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steps of the holy and auncient Fathers.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>