<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO ALL FATHERS AND SONNES OF WORTHY FAMILIES, VVhome Vertue, Birth, and Learning haue iustly stiled Gentlemen: Health, Happi∣nesse, and Increase of the best Knowledge.</title>
           <author>Ap-Robert, I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115725_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20768</idno>
           <idno type="STC">715</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115725</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO ALL FATHERS AND SONNES OF WORTHY FAMILIES, VVhome Vertue, Birth, and Learning haue iustly stiled Gentlemen: Health, Happi∣nesse, and Increase of the best Knowledge.</title>
                 <author>Ap-Robert, I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The yonger brother his apology by it selfe. Or A fathers free power disputed : for the disposition of his lands, or other his fortunes to his sonne, sonnes, or any one of them: as right reason, the laws of God and nature, the ciuill, canon, and municipall lawes of this kingdome do command. By I. Ap-Robert Gent</title>
                 <author>J. A. (John Ap Robert)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 62, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO ALL FATHERS AND SONNES OF WORTHY FAMILIES,</hi> VVhome Vertue, Birth, and Learning haue iustly stiled Gentlemen: Health, Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and Increase of the best Knowledge.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in the front of this briefe Discourse, there is (Right Worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) already deliuered vnto you some light of that which concerneth the Quality, Reason, and Scope of the same: so do I heere sincerely professe, that I did not priuately write it at first but for priuate
<pb facs="3"/>satisfaction; neither do I now make it publique, but with due relation to the generall good of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> and for the exercise of Honourable Spirits, in this our much-speaking, &amp; Paradoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Age.</p>
   <p>Not vpon the least presumption of a self-sufficiency, to confront there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by any receiued Custome (if any such bee) nor to diminish the naturall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, due by Younger Brothers to their Elder; not to enkindle emulatiōs in families; nor to innouate any thing to the preuidice of publique; or priuate quiet (which none I hope wilbe so ill affected as to suppose;) neither myne inoffensiue zeale for younger brothers (among whom I am rancked one;) nor the absolute consent of Imperiall and Ecclesiasticall Laws (which I hauing a little studied, do not a little respect;) nor the particuler honour I beare to the vsages, in this point, of our anciēt Britans (from whom I am descended;) nor disire to maintaine and iustify an
<pb facs="3"/>act in this Kind, done by a Friend, (whom I must euer reuerence;) nor yet the hope of bettering my priuate for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes (which mooues men much in these our tymes) hath drawne me to this vndertaking: but principally (as before is sōwhat touched) the singuler Respect which (as a <hi>Patriote</hi>) I beare to the glory, and good of Gentlemens Houses, whose best Originalls, surest means of Maintenance, and principal Ornaments are Vertue, or Force of mynd: The want whereof, is a comon cause of ruine.</p>
   <p>The free Power therefore of You who are Fathers, is heere in some special cases argued and defended, to giue you occasion therby to consider with the cleerer eye-sight, for the establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and continuance of families. Heere also the Naturall rights of vs that are children, be so discoursed and discussed, as that we younger Brothers may haue cause and courage, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour by vertuous means, to make our
<pb facs="4"/>selues (without the least wrong to any) capable (if need shalbe) of the chiefest vses. And both, and all are so handled, as that no offence can reasonably arise in any respect: much lesse for that the whole is conceiued, and written in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture only of an Essay or Probleme, to which I bynd no man to affoard more beliefe, then himselfe hath liking of, &amp; is free to refute the whole, or any part at his pleasure, as he feeles himself able and disposed.</p>
   <p>If I may seeme among some, to haue handled this subiect with more earnestnesse and acrimony then they think expedient: let them be pleased to weigh the <hi>Decorum</hi> of Disputes, which is principally herein obserued their Nature absolutly requiring quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knes, and vehemency on whether syde soeuer. Neither let this length of Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle seeme vnto you like the gates of <hi>Myndus,</hi> which were so great and the Citty so little, that they ministred oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to the <hi>Cynick</hi> to scoffe at the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion,
<pb facs="4"/>bidding the Townsemen shut their Gates, for feare the Citty should run out through them, seeing that in a new Matter a necessity lyeth vpon me to vse so large a Preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
   <p>As for the remedies of Euils, by way of enacting Lawes, that is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per office of Magistrates, and Courts of publick Counsell: neuerthelesse to speak and treat of them (vnder the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and correction of Superiours, to whome I do alwaies very dutifully sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit) is a thing which may well belong to euery man. But as for those graue, and learned Censors, vnto whom I may seeme to haue bestowed my pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in very needlesse arguments, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause no lesse then I my self, they hould the case (as heere it is put) to be most cleere, and out of Controuersy: to such I answere, that I wrote it not for them, vnlesse perhaps to confirme their iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gments; but for others, who are not altogeather so perswaded. Nor to any,
<pb facs="5"/>as to prescribe, or bynd further then their owne Consciences shall thinke good. For that were far too peremto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
   <p>Finally, nothing being heer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended but by Authority, Reason, and Exāple, nor any person taxed, nor par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler personall vices; if neuerthelesse I haue not performed my part in the worke so well as I desyre, or as the Cause deserues (which I feare I haue not:) yet my hope is (Right Worthy Fathers, and Worthy Sonnes of Right Worthy Families) that for my honest meaning, and good intentions sake, your will euer conceiue well of, and taken into your speciall protection,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your vnfayned vvel-vvisher, I. Ap-Robert.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>