<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the yonger sort of Reuerend and Vertuous Cath. Priestes, and Stu∣dents in the English Seminaries.</title>
           <author>P., N.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115142_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69143</idno>
           <idno type="STC">576</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115142</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the yonger sort of Reuerend and Vertuous Cath. Priestes, and Stu∣dents in the English Seminaries.</title>
                 <author>P., N.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Miscellania or a treatise : Contayning two hundred controuersiall animaduersions, conducing to the study of English controuersies in fayth, and religion. VVritten by N.N.P. and dedicated to the yonger sort of Catholike priests, and other students in the English seminaries beyond the seas. With a pareneticall conclusion vnto the said men</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>398, 10 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>To the yonger sort of Reuerend and Vertuous Cath. Priestes, and Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents in the English Seminaries.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>EVEREND</hi> and <hi>Vertuous men,</hi> though I hope, that this ensuing <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise</hi> will become profitable to diuers of the Catholike Laity; yet ingenuously I confesse, that it was chiefly and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lly vnde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>taken for the aduancement of your Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ntrouersies of Fayth:</hi> I meane, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> such of you, who haue spent your last yeares in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>umane learning, and points of <hi>School-Diuinity,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd are therefore in regard of such your want of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>rage, as yet litle conuersant in <hi>Controuersies of fayth,</hi> ventilated at this day betweene the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike and the Protestant. To those others of your owne function, which are of full, and great yeares, this <hi>Discourse</hi> (I confesse) is lesse seruiceable; since themselues through their owne reading are (no doubt) well acquainted with most of the <hi>Animaduersions</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ere set downe; and therefore I would not haue any such graue and learned men thinke, that I adresse this Worke vnto them for their further benefit: for I willingly grant, that though my selfe be of their owne
<pb n="4" facs="3"/> course of lyfe, I shall be euer ready rather to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed by them, then vndertake to instruct any of them.</p>
   <p>Touching the Subiect of this <hi>Treatise,</hi> it contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth certaine <hi>Controuersiall Animaduersions</hi> (for so I here call them about Matte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s of Religion. These <hi>Animaduersions</hi> are of most different a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d seuerall points and in regard of such their diuersi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y they can hardly be reduced to any certaine Heads <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> can be set downe in any praecise <hi>Method,</hi> with m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall dependency one to the other. And therefore i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> regard of the want of such Method, I haue entituled the whole Worke <hi>Miscellania,</hi> as being a mixture of things in themselues <hi>heterogeniou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> and of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent natures. And although some of them might (as touching the same point) be ranged and set downe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather (and this chiefly in those which do concerne the <hi>Reall Presence;</hi>) yet I haue purposely, for the most part, marshalled them in different places, the better to obserue the <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, required in the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Method of <hi>Miscellania;</hi> that so no one part of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Booke</hi> shall differ in fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>me from the rest, or fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> the whole: imitating herein the vsuall Order of <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grams,</hi> whose <hi>Method</hi> in setting them downe co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sists in not obseruing of <hi>Method.</hi> There except ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine <hi>Animaduersions</hi> in defence and proofe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Deity,</hi> and of the <hi>Immortality of the Soule,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the end of the Booke, which I haue thought ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dient to amasse together, against such Men, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ke their Infidelity vnder the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ecture of <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy.</hi>
      <pb n="5" facs="3"/> And as these <hi>Animaduersions</hi> (being promiscuously deliuered, without any punctuall order) do in part resemble a great plot of ground (not deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into any certaine beds or quarters) wherin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusedly and scatteringly grow many flowers of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent kinds &amp; odours: So here you shall find sparsed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Obseruations</hi> of so many points in number, and of such different Natures, as that I hold it more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient to refer the <hi>Reader</hi> immediatly to the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>using of them, then to particularize but any few <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eads, in this <hi>Dedicatory Epistle.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Let no man muse at this vnexpected <hi>Method:</hi> We see, the world in most things is extrauagant; the <hi>Method</hi> here vsed is also (through a kind of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity) extrauagant; and thus I am forced at this present to humour the World. And I adde hereto that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e vncertanity contayned in this Method, may beget <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the Reader (as often it doth in Bookes of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>re and forme) <hi>an inquisitiue desire</hi> to see what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lloweth in ech ensuing <hi>Animaduersion;</hi> as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ming them to be of different Subiects; and so may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ore easely draw on the Reader, to the perusall of the whole Treatise.</p>
   <p>This <hi>Rapsody</hi> of Obseruaions (if it be lawfull so far to impropriate the word) is taken partly out of that most Eminent <hi>Cardinall Bellarmine,</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>orthy memory; partly out of the most paynefull and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>rned worke of the <hi>Protestants Apology;</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>t of other of the said Authours writings, (out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hich, many choyse <hi>Obseruations</hi> are now
<pb n="6" facs="4"/> fully published, which (before, and till now) did ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> much hidden &amp; concealed in Marginall references; partly also out of all the chiefe Bookes written by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Catholikes, during these last thirty, or fourty yeares and partly out of the diligent perusall of the chiefe Protestant Writers.</p>
   <p>And as we obserue, that a man comming into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> curious Garden, layeth not hold of euery flower, which first presenteth it selfe to his sight, but will ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther here and there such, as are most pleasing to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> eye, &amp; smell; So I hope, I may here boldly say, I haue forborne all vulgar and obuious <hi>Obseruations</hi> (as presuming them to be knowne to you allready) resting only (and this with the iudgment of other graue me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of my Coate, already acquainted with this <hi>Worke</hi>) in such, as are choyse, selected, and full of matter; the which <hi>(Vertuous Men)</hi> you may vse, as so many sho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Prolegomena,</hi> or briefe instructions, cond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to your future more full, and exact study of <hi>Controuersies.</hi> Here now you haue in these fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> sheets, a full <hi>Synopsis,</hi> or view of the most weighty <hi>Obseruations;</hi> which being made familiar an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> knowne to you aforehand, may much facilitate a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> make easy your otherwise more painefull search an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> study hereafter in those matters, and may furni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> you with extemporall and present discourse touchi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> most Controuersies: all which seuerall <hi>Obserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> being (as it were) a formlesse <hi>materia prim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> of Controuersies, or to speake in the Poets <hi>Dialect — rudis, indigestaq́ue moles,</hi> would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="7" facs="4"/> no small labour, toyle, and disquisition in any of you to collect out of the Authors themselues.</p>
   <p>The <hi>Animaduersions</hi> in this Treatise set downe, are in number, only <hi>two hundred.</hi> Many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ore (I grant) might be added for the increase of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he Number: But these I hold to be most forcing; &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> am loath, that this worke through any affected pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>xity, should become fastidious, or wearisome vnto you. And wheras you shall find some acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Protestants, to be oftener set downe, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>nce, you may conceaue the reason therof to be, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the seuerall or different Illations, or Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, drawne from the said acknowledgments, in seuerall <hi>Animaduersions.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If any of you reape profit by this my Labour (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> hope diuers of you may, and will) my humble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uest then in recompence of my paynes taken herein, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> that you w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ld vouchsafe your remēbrance of me in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ur prayers, at the chiefest tymes of your Deuotions. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> knowe many, of Custome and Vse, in Dedicating <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>eir Bookes to Catholikes, do intreate of them this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>nd of fauour; But as for my selfe, my desire and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>irituall need of your good prayers is so vehem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>d vnaffected, as that I earnestly beseech you, euen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the most <hi>precious Passion of our Lord and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>auiour,</hi> suffered for the cancelling of our sinnes, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ur owne charitable Disposition towards others, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>resume those words of the Apostle to be imprinted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> your soules<note n="(a)" place="margin">Rom. 5.</note>: <hi>Charitas Dei diffusa est in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ordibus vestris.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb n="8" facs="5"/>
   <p>Finally by what is most sacred and holy, that yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> would vouchsafe (now and then) your particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of me (either yet aliue, or hereafter dead in that your most retired and Religious <hi>Memento</hi> (vsed in the celebration of the most Blessed and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Sacrifice of the Masse</hi>) for the expiating of my manyfold sinnes. This I humbly beseech; this in all prostration of soule I implore, and begge a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> your hands; and in such your performance, ech of yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> iustly may comfort your selues in those words of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Sauiour: <hi>Beati</hi>
      <note n="(b)" place="margin">
         <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.</note>
      <hi>misericordes, quoniam ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>si misericordiam consequentur.</hi> And thus in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> good hope thereof I cease, referring you to the peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall of the <hi>Treatise</hi> it selfe.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in our Lord Iesus, N. N. P.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>