<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An Advertisement.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115773_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10557</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20829</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115773</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An Advertisement.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christian divinitie, contained in the divine service of the Church of England : summarily, and for the most part in order, according as point on point dependeth, composed; and with the holy Scriptures plainly and plentifully confirmed: written for the furtherance of the peoples understanding in the true religion established by publike authoritie, and for the increase of vnitie in that godly truth eternall. By Edmund Reeve Bachelour in Divinitie, and vicar of the parish of Hayes in Middlesex</title>
                 <author>Reeve, Edmund</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 <publisher>Fussell, Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Moseley, Humphrey</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 392 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>An Advertisement.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince the<note n="a" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.1.2.3.4.</note> time that<note n="b" place="margin">Isa. 5.21.</note> Wisedome in ones owne eyes, and prudence in ones owne sight, hath so much abounded, it is familiar with very many, when they see or heare any thing delivered concerning religion, if it be a matter which they affect not, presently to passe an hard censure thereon, though the deliverie be the very established doctrine or discipline of the Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Church of <hi>England</hi> by Law established under the Kings Majesty. The<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 3.13.14 Ps. 140.3.</note> poyson of aspes is under the lips of many, <hi>Who say, with our</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">Ps. 14.4.3.</note>
      <hi>tongue will we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, our lips are our owne, who is Lord over us?</hi> The holy Prophet saith, <hi>The Lord shall cut off the tongue that speaketh proud things.</hi> The holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle saith,<note n="e" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.16.</note>
      <hi>Without controversie great is the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie of godlinesse:</hi> And though the men of God have signified that the Holy Scriptures divinity is partly<note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 5.12.</note> milke for babes or little children in<note n="g" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.3.</note> Christ, partly<note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 5.14.</note> strong meate for the<note n="i" place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.13.14.</note> young men, and partly hidden<note n="k" place="margin">Rev. 2.17.</note> Manna for the fathers in God; also that naturall ones<note n="l" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.14.</note> cannot know the things of the Spirit of God, because they are spiritually discerned; yet notwithstanding so out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious is the pride and arrogancie of many, (who since they came to the yeares of discretion, have made no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse in regeneration or the new birth, unto the<note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 2.2.</note> renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their mind, and the amendment of their<note n="n" place="margin">Philip. 1.27. 1 Pet. 2.12. 1 Pet. 1.15. Eph. 4.22.</note> conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation, according to Gods Holy word) that rashly they<note n="o" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.12.</note> will speake evill of the things, which they understand not: and (as the Apostle saith)<note n="p" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.7.</note>
      <hi>desire to be teachers, understanding neither what they say, nor whereof they affirme.</hi> Moreover how contrary minded soever
<pb facs="9"/>each is to other, yea, how greatly different they are from the minde and life prescribed in the Divine Service of the Church, (whom some of them sometimes will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to be their Mother;) Yet each one taketh for gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that the grounds in his<note n="q" place="margin">Prov. 21.2. Prov. 12.15.</note> owne minde are the right, and that the grounds in all<note n="r" place="margin">Philip. 2.3.</note> others mindes, in any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner differing from his, are the wrong: and withall every one for the most part of the aforesaid unhumbled heart, by his owne imagined-right groundes, without any feare of the Eternall Almighty God, and without any reverence unto the Supreame divine Wisedome of Christs holy Church, contained in the bookes of her publike worship, will<note n="s" place="margin">2 Pet 2.10.</note> presume to be able to judge of, yea, will assume con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence and boldnesse (or rather most damnable audacious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse) to condemne deliveries in the aforesaid bookes, which the Soveraigne Majesty hath ratified, and the most reverend Fathers the Archbishops, and all the right re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend fathers the Bishops, and the rest of the whole Clergie (not any one excepted,<note place="margin">Quod medico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m est, promit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>edi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>: tractant Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia fabri, Sola Scripturarum ars est, quam si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>i pass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> omnes vendicant. Hanc garrula anus, hanc delirus se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, have Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sia ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>sus, ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> universi praesumant, lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>, docent ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam discant. Hier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nymus in epissola a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aum presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum de om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>bus divine h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>storia. libris.</note> which hath entred into holy orders according to such manner and sort, as by the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall Law it is appointed) have allowed, and by sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription have witnessed the same. But let the unpartiall reader of this treatise following, where doubt about any matter may arise, throughly consider the Holy Scriptures, which either are expressed, or in the margent but quoted, for the confirmation of the point mentioned. And let none except here against, because the deliveries are in no Philosophicall method, but in the most vulgar plainnes: for all hereof is written for the furtherance of the laity; and aswell in termes, as in forme and manner accommodated unto the meanest capacity. All teachers which study to edifie their auditory, doe well know, that it is farre easier to expresse their mindes in divine matters, so as the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned may comprehend, than as the unlearned may but a
<pb facs="10"/>litle apprehend. It is written concerning Christ for our example, that<note n="t" place="margin">Mark. 4.33.</note>
      <hi>hee spake the word unto the people, as they were able to heare it.</hi> There are now extant in English sundry bookes very profitable, which few of the common people doe make use of, for that their style and words for the most or a great part are for Schollers read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely. Great was the divine Wisedome of the Church in setting forth her Homilies in so familiar a manner. And by those most sacred Sermons all Pastours and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers should take<note n="u" place="margin">2 Tim. 1.13.</note> example how to frame their meditations unto their auditories easiest and speediest edification. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, let none expect to finde any common place of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity here fully handled; but let this worke be accounted only an introduction into the bookes of the divine Service, where, as in an Ocean of divine truth, there may bee had a great abundance of information both touching he mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ensuing, and also concerning many more. This book may be used as a finger of one, that pointeth us unto such places, as we have not throughly taken notice of afore. Also the godly reader shall perceive that every one which<note n="w" place="margin">Mat. 5.6.</note> hungreth and thristeth after righteousnesse, to have within him more and more the<note n="x" place="margin">Phil. 2.5. 1 Cor. 2.16.</note> minde of Christ, and to have the life of Iesus more and more made<note n="y" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.10, 11.</note> manifest in his body, may forth of every Chapter following receive some light unto the apprehending of everlasting truth in the matter there treated on. Lastly, Seeing that in the bookes of divine Service there are such heavenly senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and speeches; even as the learned are delighted in reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the sayings of the Fathers of the <hi>Greeke</hi> &amp; <hi>Latine</hi> Churches; so should wee unto<note n="z" place="margin">Exod. 20.12. 1 Cor. 4.15. Ecclus. or Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticus. 8.8.9.</note> due honouring of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of our owne <hi>English</hi> Church, enable our selves to say on every point of divinity, that which they have with one consent, out of their farre most profound judgements delivered unto us in an incomparable divine manner.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>