<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RELIGIOVS GENTLEVVOMAN, Mris THOMASIN OVVEFIELD, All happinesse in this life, and that which is to come be multiplied.</title>
           <author>Holbrooke, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115634_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10393</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20675</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115634</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RELIGIOVS GENTLEVVOMAN, Mris THOMASIN OVVEFIELD, All happinesse in this life, and that which is to come be multiplied.</title>
                 <author>Holbrooke, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The necessitie of righteousnes. Or A profitable and fruitfull sermon vpon the fift chapter of the Gospell of S. Mathew. vers. 20. Preached and penned by that famous, learned, iudicious, orthodoxall, holy, wise, and skilfull preacher and servant of God, now deceased, and with his God triumphing in Heaven, Iohn Randall, Batchelour of Divinitie, pastour of St Andrewes Hubbart in little East-cheape London, sometimes fellow of Lincolne Colledge in Oxford. And now published, to the glory of God, the edification of his Church, and the honourable memoriall of the author, by William Holbrooke, preacher of the Word of God in the church aforesaid</title>
                 <author>Randall, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newbery, Nathaniel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sheffard, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE RELIGIOVS GENTLEVVOMAN, M<seg rend="sup">ris</seg> THOMASIN OVVEFIELD, All happinesse in this life, <hi>and that which is to come be multiplied.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood M<seg rend="sup">ris</seg> Owefield;</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>Considering your case to be the same with the Lady <hi>Bennets</hi> aforesaid, both in respect of your losse in <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Randall,</hi> who was, as to her, so to you, a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Counseller every way, as you haue often confessed, and also in respect of your loue to him, both in life, sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, death, and since, onely the odds is on your side, in that you haue not onely in your owne particular, sustey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a losse, but your Family also, by the death of that worthy servant of God, who oft instructed them in the way of the Lord: considering, I say, your case to be like vnto the foresaid Ladies, in the foresaid respects, I haue made bolde, as a testimony of my thankefulnes, for your loue divers times shewed vnto me, to Dedicate this
<pb facs="5"/> Worke also to you, that your losse may (in some sort) be supplyed, by seeing and hearing him speaking to, and counselling you, in <hi>Print,</hi> whom you so reioyced to see and heare speake, when he was living by word of mouth, I make no question of your acceptance of what was his, as this was both penned and Preached by him, as here it commeth to your View: My desire shall be to God for you, to blesse this and all the labours of his, which you haue inioyed, any way, to the furthering, edifying, and confirming of you and yours vnmoueably in your present faith, which God grant for his Christs sake, in whom I am,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>And rest your much bounden Friend WILLIAM HOLBROOKE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>