<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHORS PREFACE OF PICTVRES IN GENERALL.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115932_Bo1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10745</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21022</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115932</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHORS PREFACE OF PICTVRES IN GENERALL.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Holy pictures of the mysticall figures of the most holy sacrifice and sacrament of the Eucharist: set forth in French by Lewis Richome, prouinciall of the Societie of Iesus; and translated into English for the benefit of those of that nation, aswell protestants as Catholikes. By C.A</title>
                 <author>Richeome, Louis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Birchley Hall Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Lancashire</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 300, 12 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_preface">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <pb n="1" facs="8"/>
   <head>THE AVTHORS PREFACE OF PICTVRES <hi>IN GENERALL.</hi>
   </head>
   <head type="sub">What a Picture is, and how many kindes of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures there are.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Sacrament and Sacrifice of the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rist, is a worke of God so high and so great, that no tongue of man or of Angels can suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently speake, or worthily discourse there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; wee haue said some thing in the foure bookes of the holy Masse, confuting errour, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Catholike Faith; we addresse now this Treatise without mingling of Controuersies, to the honor of this mysterie, confirmation of our saith concerning the same, and in fauour of those who haue not had the leasure to reade the former worke; wee take for the subiect of our discourse, the most notable Figures of this mystery, drawn from the booke of God, which for this occasion we haue intituled <hi>Sacred Pictures,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The inscripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this worke.</note> which setting before our eyes the holy Images and propheticall Figures of the mysterie that we adore. Such as haue seene the truth in armour of proofe, laying about her in the field of dispute, will also take pleasure to see her sit heere triumphant in her roabes of peace: those which haue not seene her in the field, shall haue occasion to confirme themselues without noyse of warre, and without contention, in the beleefe of the Church of God.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="2" facs="9"/>
For Prologue of all this worke,<note place="margin">The subiect of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> we ought briefly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what a <hi>Picture</hi> is, how we take it heere, and of how many sorts there be. Moreouer, why God would that in the Law of Nature, and of <hi>Moses,</hi> there should bee set downe so liuely Figures of the mysteries appertaining to the Law of Grace.</p>
   <p>By the first declaration we shall haue a generall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of those <hi>Pictures,</hi> which hereafter shall bee decyphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to vs more particularly. By the second wee shall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, that God hath most wisely vsed this fashion to teach vs his Law, as well for the manifestation of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as also for the profit of his children, which are the two feete or Bases, whereon our <hi>Figures</hi> or <hi>Pictures</hi> are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected.</p>
   <p>First then we are to note,<note place="margin">Naturall Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures.</note> that a <hi>Picture</hi> or <hi>Figure,</hi> if we take it naturally, doth according to the name signifie no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else, but the exterior forme of some body. So as the outward forme, the lineaments, and the proportion of the parts of a Plant, of a Beast, or a Man, is a figure of each of these; but a naturall figure,<note place="margin">Artificiall Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures.</note> of which we speake not heere, this subiect appertaining to the Naturalists. Wherefore according to our sense and meaning heere, it is a thing made or framed to represent and signifie another thing; and this is an artificiall Figure, otherwise called a <hi>Picture,</hi> of which we finde three sorts.<note place="margin">Dumbe Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures.</note> The first is that, which to our eyes representeth by lineaments and colours some things without words, called for this cause by the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, <hi>Dumbe Pictures:</hi> such are the Images as well of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bosted worke, as of painted fables.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Numar,</hi> the Cherub. <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</hi> 6.29.</note> Such was the Serpent of Brasse, cast in mettall, by <hi>Moses;</hi> the Cherubims, the Palme-trees, and the other Images portraited in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Salomon;</hi> also the Pictures of the Seasons of the yeere, of Vices, of Vertues, and other fained peeces repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented by the Cheesell in caruing, or by the Pensell vpon a plaine boord. Of this sort also are the Visions framed in our Imagination; for though these be in some sort spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all:
<pb n="3" facs="9"/>yet notwithstanding in the likenes of corporal obiects, so they are represented to the sight of our inward sense.</p>
   <p>The second sort of <hi>Pictures</hi> serues for the eare,<note place="margin">Speaking Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures.</note> and for that qualitie we may call them <hi>Speaking Pictures;</hi> such are the descriptions or fictions which the Poets or Historians make in words of a Tree, of a Riuer, of a liuing Creature, of a Tempest, of a Vertue, of a Vice, or of other imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie things. This sort containes also the declarations which are made to explane some artificial figures either present, or fained as present. Such are the discourses of <hi>Philostra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> for in them there is neither colour nor painting, but the bare word which faines the Images and Figures, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciphers the phantasies of the Author, as hauing the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures before his eyes.</p>
   <p>The third sort of figures are any things or actions insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted to represent other mysteries.<note place="margin">Allegoricall or mysticall Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures,</note> And if the mysterie be ciuill or prophane, the Figure is ciuill or prophane; as was the <hi>Hierogliphes</hi> of the old <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> consisting in certaine figures of beasts, or of instruments, put for to signifie some hidden thing; as a Crocodile was the figure of a Traytor; the Eagle the figure of the soule. But if it be a mystery of Religion, it is an holy figure. So Manna was an holy Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, not in regard of colours or of words; but of signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; so Circumcision was an action signifying and figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Baptisme. This kinde of Figure is otherwise called an Allegorie, that is to say, a mysticall Picture, containing in it selfe a spirituall sense, knowne to spirituall people, and hid to the rude. This last sort makes the fundamentall subiect of our holy Tables or Pictures of the <hi>Eucharist.</hi> For our principall end is to explane the things, and the remarkable actions instituted in the Law of Nature, and of <hi>Moses,</hi> to signifie the Sacrifice and Sacrament of the body of our Sauiour. Notwithstanding in displaying the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume of these figures, we haue serued our selues of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two kindes of Pictures; that is to say, of the <hi>Dumbe Picture</hi> in the printed figures themselues; and of the <hi>Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="4" facs="10"/>Picture,</hi> in our descriptions or declarations of them. We haue also made many excursions in recommendation of Vertue, and in detestation of Vice, for the institution of manners; and often encited the Reader to the contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and loue of the celestiall countrey; touching by this meanes the foure Cardinall Senses,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ure Sences of Scripture. <hi>S. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>m. Wart. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>. Greg lib.</hi> 10. <hi>nor. cap.</hi> 1. The Literall. The Allegori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call. The Morall. The Anagogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call.</note> which commonly are found in the treasures of the holy Scripture; the Literall or Historicall, which goeth the first; the Allegoricall or Figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue, which is the spirit of the Literall; the Tropologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call or Morall, which formes the manners, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogicall, which shewes the triumphant Church: the Literall is the foundation of the other three; the Allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical is the mysticall signification of the Literall; the Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologicall, is the fruit of the one and of the other; and the Anagogicall is the end of them all. And in this fashion haue wee comprehended foure sorts of Expositions, and three sorts of Pictures, to teach with fruit and pleasure the most great mystery of our Religion: for if there be no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther better nor profitable Methods, then these foure: and if there bee nothing more delightfull then a picture, not which makes a thing glide more sweetly within the soule then a picture: nor which more profoundly engraues it in the memorie: nor more effectually calls foorth the will to loue or hate any obiect, good or euill, which to it shall be proposed: I see not in what manner one can more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably, liuely, and delitiously teach the vertues, the fruits, and the delicatenesse of this diuine and holy meate, of the body of the Sonne of God, then with the aboue named Expositions, and with this triple picture of the pensell of the Word and of the signification.</p>
   <p>If my labour in this excellent matter,<note place="margin">To all Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Writers.</note> (truely Christian, and worthy of the attention of all honorable men) bring any profit or luster to our faith, or to the publike weale, as I desire with all my heart it should: all the praise be to God, which hath furnished me with spirit and body, inke and paper, to write thereof. And if by the example of
<pb n="5" facs="10"/>these Pictures any men of good spirit take occasion to vse the like method, in discoursing pleasantly on some worthy subiect, to teach with honest recreatiō &amp; profit, the means to follow Vertue, and flye Vice; I shall receiue my part thereby of singular contentment and solace, and they their recompence of honor and glory, from the hand of him, which neuer leaues any good worke done for his name without reward; nor any ill committed against his Lawes, without punishment.</p>
   <p>Truely (to say this by the way) it is a misery as worthy of compassion as shame, that so many Poets and Orators amongst Christians, and namely heere in <hi>France,</hi> Employ the goodnesse and fruitfulnesse of their spirits, to write tales and fables, of Loue, and other things, either vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable or pernitious, and who like to Spiders (that draw out their owne bowels in making copwebs to catch Flies) doe occupie themselues in such vanities, letting passe a thousand faire subiects, vpon which they might with eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall praise, both learnedly and eloquently write. It is a great shame to the name of Christians, to see a Pagan <hi>Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darus,</hi> an <hi>Euripides,</hi> a <hi>Virgil,</hi> an <hi>Appelles,</hi> a <hi>Philostratus,</hi> and other like prophane Authors, trauaile so carefully to set foorth, sing, paint, and represent their Captains, their Acts, their Gods, their Vices, and their Vanities, for the glory of their superstition: and that many Christians know not how to choose, neither matter nor maner a greeing to their name, for to write Christianly to the praise of the true God, or to the honor and illustration of their onely true Religion. A thing yet farre more vnworthy, and yet most deplorable it is, to see others temper their pensel and their pen in the sinke and puddle of prophane things,<note place="margin">Pictures of scandall.</note> to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Pictures of abomination and scandall, and to write and paint foorth such fooleries, and vilonies as they doe, more prophanely, then the prophanest themselues, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out care of losing their soules; so they may gaine some brute of reputation amongst the lighter sort. And what
<pb n="6" facs="11"/>lamentable folly is it to purchase at so deare a rate the smoake of vanitie? to incurre ignominy and eternall paine, only to haue their names swimme in the mouthes and esti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of fooles, for cunning Artizans of folly. But let vs come to the second point of our introduction, and declare wherefore God hath of old vsed such Figures going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Law of Grace.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>