<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL Mr. IOHN CREVV, Mr. EDVVARD STEPHENS, and Mr. Iohn Curson, Esquires; together with their faithfull Yoke-fellowes, grace, mercy, and peace be multiplyed.</title>
           <author>Cleaver, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115588_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18961</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5379</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115588</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL Mr. IOHN CREVV, Mr. EDVVARD STEPHENS, and Mr. Iohn Curson, Esquires; together with their faithfull Yoke-fellowes, grace, mercy, and peace be multiplyed.</title>
                 <author>Cleaver, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A declaration of the christian sabbath : Wherein the sanctifying of the Lords-day, is proued to bee agreeable of God, and to the Gospell of Iesus Christ. By Robert Cleaver</title>
                 <author>Cleaver, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 156 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. IOHN CREVV, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. EDVVARD STEPHENS, and M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Iohn Curson,</hi> Esquires; together with their <hi>faithfull Yoke-fellowes,</hi> grace, mercy, and peace be multiplyed.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath pleased the <hi>Almighty,</hi> by the goodnes of his providence to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne <hi>you</hi> together in one <hi>earthly</hi> family,
<pb facs="3"/> that by <hi>relation,</hi> and <hi>bond</hi> of <hi>kindred,</hi> and <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity,</hi> you should all cal the same man, your <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> and according to the riches of his grace, to vnite <hi>you</hi> together in one heauenly family that by vertue of <hi>Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and <hi>spirituall child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> you should all call the same <hi>God,</hi> your <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and so more truely become <hi>brethren</hi> or <hi>sisters,</hi> each one of you to others in the Lord. For this cause, &amp; diuers
<pb facs="3"/> other reasons, I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to make choyse of <hi>you</hi> for my <hi>speciall, &amp; selected Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> (so farre I presume of your favour, &amp; kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) and ioyntly to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure you, in <hi>publike,</hi> as <hi>professed friends</hi> to the cause wherein I deale, and <hi>Religious obseruers</hi> of that <hi>sacred Ordinance</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> for which I con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tend: for that, I confesse is a great part of my businesse in this briefe discourse ensuing, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<pb facs="4"/> the adversaries of the <hi>Sabbath.</hi> And yet I humbly intreate both <hi>you,</hi> and all other <hi>good Readers,</hi> not to regard the <hi>Sabbath</hi> the lesse, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause there is <hi>contention</hi> about it, nor suddenly to censure the act of <hi>contending,</hi> vntill you be acquainted with the causes, and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of it. There are divers <hi>Texts</hi> of <hi>Scripture,</hi> indeed, which in shew, &amp; appearance do seeme to condemne
<pb facs="4"/> it, as that to <hi>Timothy. The seavant of the Lord must not striue, but must be gentle toward all men. 2. Tim.</hi> 2. 24. And that to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> I beseech you brethren, by the name of our Lord Iesus Christ, that ye al speake one thing, &amp; that there be no dissensions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 10 And <hi>that</hi> to the <hi>Romans</hi> If it be possible, as much as in you is, haue peace With all men,
<pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 18. but none of these, nor any other that can be produced, do absolutely prohibit al maner of <hi>striving.</hi> To <hi>striue</hi> for <hi>error,</hi> and <hi>sinne</hi> is vnlawfull: to <hi>striue</hi> about things that be <hi>doubtful,</hi> and <hi>vncerten,</hi> is vnlawfull: to <hi>striue</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>curious,</hi> and <hi>needles questions</hi> or matters ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to no edification, or profit, is vnlawfull. And so is <hi>striuing</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull when <hi>carnall corruptions, as make-bates</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/> be the mouers of it, or stirrers in it; as when through <hi>pride,</hi> we seeke our owne <hi>vaineglory;</hi> or through malice, and enuy we depraue our brethren. In these, and such like cases, is <hi>conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> forbidden, but not simply: for then would not the Apostle <hi>Iude</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iude 3.</note> haue exhorted the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>with earnestnes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for the faith:</hi> neither<note place="margin">Isa. 59. 4.</note> would the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> so sharply haue taxed the people of his
<pb facs="6"/> time, for <hi>not conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> for the truth. <hi>Paul</hi> was a peaceable man, and yet he <hi>stroue against the false Apostles and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers:</hi> and <hi>Christ</hi> is the perfect <hi>peace-maker,</hi> and author of peace, &amp; yet he mightily opposed the rabble of <hi>Scribes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Pharisees.</hi> And now to pleade for <hi>my selfe,</hi> and <hi>my brethren,</hi> which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by writinge, or preaching, haue trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the same subiect, have as I done, we are
<pb facs="6"/> not meere voluntaries in this controversie, but necessarily vrged thereto, as prested soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers: we begin not the quarrell, as As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sailants, but onely iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifie the truth of our doctrine, and cause, as Defendants; <hi>our Bookes,</hi> and <hi>Sermons,</hi> being particularly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugned, although (I trust) more <hi>sound,</hi> &amp; <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxe,</hi> then can be con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>futed. We are far from <hi>Innovations,</hi> &amp; <hi>Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/> in our positions, and tenents: we wish all good to our <hi>Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sites,</hi> with a desire, rather to informe them, by arguments and reasons, then to disgrace, or provoke them, by taunts or invectives. The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of <hi>your wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, loues,</hi> and <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous dispositions</hi> assure mee, that <hi>you</hi> will be easily perswaded of the veritie of <hi>mine Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie,</hi> and therefore I
<pb facs="7"/> shall not neede with multiplicity of words, to enlarge it, neither doe I thinke it decent to taske <hi>you</hi> with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of other imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent matters, which neither necessitie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, nor conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencie approoueth of; especially, seeing there is as little <hi>Decorum</hi> kept in prefixinge a <hi>long Preface</hi> before <hi>a short Treatise,</hi> as in making a <hi>wide dore</hi> for a <hi>narrow building.</hi> And
<pb facs="8"/> therefore to spare both <hi>you,</hi> and my selfe from further labour, I briefly conclude, and with due respect, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend you to the protection, grace, gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, and blessing of the most High, and remaine</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your worships for all Christian services. Robert Cleaver.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>