<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL SIR VVILLIAM VVALGRAVE KNIGHT, OF BVERS IN ESSEX.</title>
           <author>B., C.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115853_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17332</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4179.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115853</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL SIR VVILLIAM VVALGRAVE KNIGHT, OF BVERS IN ESSEX.</title>
                 <author>B., C.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The narrovv vvay, and the last iudgement : deliuered in two sermons: the first at Pauls Crosse, the other elsewhere, by G.B. preacher of the word at Alphamston in Essex</title>
                 <author>Bury, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Lownes, Matthew</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL SIR VVILLIAM VVALGRAVE KNIGHT, OF BVERS IN ESSEX.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worshipfull, the generall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of your worthinesse, your pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar affection to the Author (as I vnderstand) and the knowne dignitie of this his worke, are the onely motiues of this my seeming boldnesse in committing this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to the generall view, vnder your countenance and protection: which though I confesse I haue done without his leaue (as being modestly vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to encounter censure, or to oppose himselfe an obiect to enuie) yet in that it hath receiued the currant stampe of approbation in the iudgement of the wisest, and your self (as I haue heard) an auricular iudge of the gracefull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuery; I haue in my selfe dissolued doubt, and confidently thwart imputation with this assurance, that it cannot but be gratefull to the Reader, and come no lesse acceptable to you. And though my selfe am vtterly vnknowne to you, yet as one bound to loue vertue euen in strangers, I honour it in you, and haue bene so much the rather induced to this dedication, by how much (I am informed) you are truly
<pb n="4" facs="3"/> affected to this my deare friend, and a cherisher of his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuors. Sir, you cannot lose by it; for learning will still be prest to honour her <hi>Mecaenas,</hi> and such as fauour Arts, chiefly those that labor in Gods vineyard, &amp; (like lamps) consume thēselues to giue light to others: I say such good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and loue extended to religion and the professors therof, is the treasure layd vp in heauen, and shall remaine with the world of perpetuall record. Thus hauing done (as I thinke) a thankfull office, not greatly fearing the Authors displeasure, if you but approue my act, I referre you to the ensuing matter: resting</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in deuotion, for your vertue-fauouring inclination, <hi>C. B.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>