<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115849_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00166</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1017</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115849</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A defence of Nicholas Smith : against a reply to his discussion of some pointes taught by Mr. Doctour Kellison in his Treatise of the ecclesiasticall hierarchy. By A.B</title>
                 <author>A. B.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Courant, Nicolas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 82, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER.</p>
   <p>MAISTER Doctour <hi>Kellison</hi> wrote a Booke intituled, <hi>A Treatise of the Eccesiasticall Hierarchy,</hi> wherein among other points, he chiefly intended to proue, that English Catholikes could not in conscience refuse a Bishop, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though, by his comming, their Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were to be increased.</p>
   <p>This Treatise of <hi>M. Doctour</hi> was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered by <hi>A modest Discussion;</hi> against which was set forth in Print, a litle Booke with title of <hi>An Inquisition</hi> &amp;c. of which some Copies, euen in print, haue
<pb facs="3"/>that false slaūder about the <hi>Pouder-Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> (which Copies were spread abroad both in the North, &amp; South of <hi>Englād.</hi>) Others haue it not.</p>
   <p>The <hi>Inqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>on</hi> was presently confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a <hi>Charitable Qualificatiō;</hi> to which was adioyned an <hi>Admonition to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</hi> The Author whereof had not, at that tyme, seene in Print, any of those Copies, which mentioned the forsayd slaunderous poynt; which I thought good heere to note, for thy knowledge.</p>
   <p>After the <hi>Inquisition,</hi> there is newly come forth a second answere to the <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cussion,</hi> called, <hi>A Reply to Nicolas Smith his Discussion &amp;c.</hi> To this <hi>Reply,</hi> I now answere, in defence of <hi>Nicolas Smith.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thou mayst perhaps wonder, that the <hi>Reply</hi> (which if we haue an eye to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fference of print, in bulke is greater thē <hi>M. Doctours Hierarchy</hi>) should be answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in so few leaues of paper. And I must confesse, I did not at first hope, to haue ended the <hi>Defence,</hi> in so few, eyther <hi>lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues,</hi> or <hi>daies,</hi> which were but <hi>seauen,</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>respōding to the <hi>seauen</hi> Questions hād<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the <hi>Replyer:</hi> within which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe
<pb facs="3"/>of tyme, I was confined both to reade, and answere the <hi>Reply:</hi> and yet in all sincerity I do auouch, not to haue omitted the answere of any one thing, wherein I conceaued there myght be the least apparence of difficulty. The reason of this breuity was double.</p>
   <p>The one, because many chiefe obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions made by the <hi>Replyer,</hi> were afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand fully answered by the <hi>Qualification</hi> before the <hi>Reply</hi> came out; to which therfore it will be sufficient to referre thee in such points. Besides, there is pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished a learned &amp; elegant booke, with Title of <hi>An Apology of the holy Sea Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoliques proceeding, for the gouernment of the Catholikes of England, during the tyme of Persecution,</hi> which may not only see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to answere the <hi>Reply,</hi> but it alone in lieu of al others, were sufficient to shew the manifold deficiency of <hi>M. Doctours</hi> Treatise, with, I can hardely say whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thy more pleasure, or profit.</p>
   <p>The other reason was, because the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyer</hi> taketh all occasions, to dilate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe in diuers points, which eyther are vulgarly knowne in Schooles, or were
<pb facs="4"/>neuer denyed by <hi>Nicolas Smith,</hi> or may be equally spoken by both parts, or els are answered, by the only perusall of the <hi>Discussion</hi> it selfe; which I earnestly intreat thee to reuiew, if thou fynd any thing obiected by the <hi>Replyer,</hi> which may seeme to haue difficulty; and I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, the only reading will serue for answere. Which to be true, I found by my owne experience; in so much, as for answering the Reply, I did in truth vse no booke, besides the <hi>Hierarchy, Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cussion,</hi> &amp; <hi>Qualification,</hi> although I could not doubt, but that the examination of diuers Authors cited by the <hi>Replyer,</hi> would haue administred no small aduā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage against him.</p>
   <p>I verily belieue, if thou read the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyer</hi> with indifferency, and attention, thou wilt perceaue, that he rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth <hi>Nicolas Smith,</hi> then <hi>M. Doctour,</hi> whose wordes he is forced to excuse, by the common Rule of Charity, that in them he had a good meaninge; but in the cheifest poynts of substance, at length he commeth to ioyne with the <hi>Discussour.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <p>Diuers things of moment, he wholy omitteth without answering, or mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them. Vpon the whole matter, I cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, this iudgement may be giuen, of the quantity, &amp; quality of this worke in general; That he hath taken great pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to procure, that few will haue pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to reade ouer his whole Booke.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>M. Drs.</hi> modesty is by him much extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, &amp; <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> sore blamed, for the contrary. Indeed he that without cause giueth the first stroake, as <hi>M. Doctour</hi> did, hath no great reason to be angry with the party, that beareth the blow. And whatsoeuer the <hi>Replyer</hi> sayth in his <hi>Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,</hi> adioyned by his Reply, <hi>Nicolas Smiths Discussion</hi> will be proued to be truly modest, if the passages be read as they lye in the <hi>Discussion,</hi> &amp; not as they are lamely cited by the <hi>Replyer,</hi> as I could shew in euery particular, if I had not resolued to be very briefe.</p>
   <p>It is ordinary with the <hi>Replyer,</hi> to blame <hi>Nicolas Smith,</hi> as if he had accused <hi>M. Doctour</hi> of some doctrins which <hi>Nic-Smith</hi> layd not to his charge, but only shewed, that out of his <hi>Tenets,</hi> certayne
<pb facs="5"/>Conclusions would follow, which ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he, nor any other could defend; but he did not say, that <hi>M. Doctour</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saw, or intended such Conclusions.</p>
   <p>In this manner <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> tearmed a certayne Argument, a Doughty one, which yet he did not affirme, to be <hi>M. Doctours</hi> argument, but only that out of S. <hi>Cyprians</hi> wordes, rightly vnderstood, no better Argument could be drawne in fauour of <hi>M. Doctour,</hi> who out of the same words, framed an argument, quite different from that, which <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> tearmed <hi>doughty,</hi> as may be seene in the <hi>Discussion q.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 5.6.</p>
   <p>The like I could shew, in all the rest, but content my selfe with requesting thee, vnpartiall Reader, still to suspend thy iudgment, till, in particulars, thou hast seene the words, and connexion of <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> his discourse.</p>
   <p>The <hi>Replyer</hi> himselfe, is farre from <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> his modesty. Scarcely he giueth any one answere, not accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed with some taunt; So that, to set downe all his sharpe speaches, were but to re-coppy the Booke.</p>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <p>Within the compasse of two <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions,</hi> he hath these charitable sayings: <hi>He fauoureth Heretikes. pag.</hi> 26. <hi>Behould</hi> Nicolas Smith <hi>his little subtility. pag.</hi> 31. <hi>Which is no lesse then a false calumniation. pag.</hi> 32. <hi>I pitty</hi> M. Nicolas Smith <hi>his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing, and the necessity he is driuen to, which</hi> cogit ad turpia. <hi>pag.</hi> 43. Nicolas Smith <hi>ioyneth with heretikes in this poynt pag.</hi> 96. And the same agayne <hi>pag.</hi> 110. <hi>What Deuine, yea Cathecumen, who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Cathechisme, would haue giuen such an answere? pag.</hi> 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. <hi>He fauoureth Caluin. pag.</hi> 111. And in the same page, <hi>I cannot tell how heerafter he can looke them in the face:</hi> although in this he haue reason, for he spake of some Iesuites, who dyed longe since, and it would be hard for the <hi>Discussour</hi> to looke them in the face, if he be yet liuinge, as the <hi>Replyer</hi> will haue him, in his Preface to the Reader: where also <hi>pag.</hi> 16. he sayth, <hi>That the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cussour seemeth to shew litle of the spirit of a Religious man:</hi> for which, if it be true, the <hi>Discussour,</hi> I graunt, ought to be sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and endeauour to correspond bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to his vocation. Howsoeuer, I dare
<pb facs="6"/>say for <hi>Nicolas Smith,</hi> that, if he were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, he would hartily thank the <hi>Replyer,</hi> for the occasion he affoardeth him of merit, and so do I, in his behalfe; wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing, that as we are all <hi>domestici fidei,</hi> so we may be <hi>charitatis,</hi> of one <hi>beliefe,</hi> and <hi>heart.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>