<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT REVE∣rend Fathers in God, GEORGE Archbishop of Canturburie, and Metropolitan of England: and IOHN Bi∣shop of London.</title>
           <author>Lennard, Samson</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115092_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07768</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18147</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115092</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT REVE∣rend Fathers in God, GEORGE Archbishop of Canturburie, and Metropolitan of England: and IOHN Bi∣shop of London.</title>
                 <author>Lennard, Samson</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The mysterie of iniquitie: that is to say, The historie of the papacie : Declaring by what degrees it is now mounted to this height, and what oppositions the better sort from time to time haue made against it. Where is also defended the right of emperours, kings, and Christian princes, against the assertions of the cardinals, Bellarmine and Baronius. By Philip Morney, knight, Lord du Plessis, &amp;c. Englished by Samson Lennard</title>
                 <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 661, 3 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Fathers in God, GEORGE Archbishop of <hi>Canturburie, and Metropolitan of England: and</hi> IOHN <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of London.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Reuerend and my verie good Lords, I am bold, out of that duetie I owe to two so great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats and pillars of this our Church of England, to present vnto your learned and judicious censures, my vnlearned and simple labours, bestowed vpon a worke worthie the reading in it selfe, howsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer by my vnskilfull pen it may be disfigured. I confesse I was vnfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, amongst a thousand, to vndertake a worke of such conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and yet better I (as I thought) than none, being a Mysterie fit to be layd open to as many as can read it in their mother tongue. My good Lords, pardon such faults as either by too much speed, or too little skill, or otherwise, haue slipt my pen: There is nothing past that may not be amended in a second edition, if your Grace shall be pleased to giue the encouragement. The God of heauen, as he hath multiplied his gifts and graces vpon you, fit for so high a calling, euen in the highest measure, so euer assist you with his holie spirit, in that great worke you haue vndertaken, to his glorie, and the good of his Church.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces and Lordships in all dutie to be commaunded, <hi>SAMSON LENNARD.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>