<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>J.D. gent: in praise of the Author, and his Worke.</title>
           <author>Tyro, T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115988_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10786</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21057</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115988</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>J.D. gent: in praise of the Author, and his Worke.</title>
                 <author>Tyro, T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The compound of alchymy. Or The ancient hidden art of archemie : conteining the right &amp; perfectest meanes to make the philosophers stone, aurum potabile, with other excellent experiments. Diuided into twelue gates. First written by the learned and rare philosopher of our nation George Ripley, sometime Chanon of Bridlington in Yorkeshyre: &amp; dedicated to K. Edvvard the 4. Whereunto is adioyned his epistle to the King, his vision, his wheele, &amp; other his workes, neuer before published: with certaine briefe additions of other notable writers concerning the same. Set foorth by Raph Rabbards Gentleman, studious and expert in archemicall artes</title>
                 <author>Ripley, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>104 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>J.D. gent: in praise of the Author, and his Worke.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>LOe here a Worke, conteining rare effects,</l>
      <l>Repleate with ripest frutes of <hi>Ripleys</hi> toyle,</l>
      <l>Whose mellowed sauour studious mindes directs</l>
      <l>T'attaine the skill that may enrich their soile:</l>
      <l>And though his Booke be carped at by <hi>Zoile,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Yet doth the same comprize such depth of Art,</l>
      <l>As makes his fame eternizd by desart.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The learned will (no doubt) delight therein,</l>
      <l>And their delight will draw them on to skill:</l>
      <l>Admit the simple force it not a pin,</l>
      <l>So much the more the wise embrace it will.</l>
      <l>Who seekes by Arte to clymbe vp Honors hill,</l>
      <l>To such perteynes this precious Stone diuine,</l>
      <l>For pease are fitter farre, than Pearle for Swine.</l>
   </lg>
   <epigraph>
      <q>Tam Arte, quam Marte.</q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>