<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To Sir Henrie Gaudie, sir Miles Corbet, sir Ham∣mond Le-Strang, sir Henrie Spel∣man Knights, my verie kinde friends.</title>
           <author>Gardiner, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115164_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01449</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11572</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115164</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To Sir Henrie Gaudie, sir Miles Corbet, sir Ham∣mond Le-Strang, sir Henrie Spel∣man Knights, my verie kinde friends.</title>
                 <author>Gardiner, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A booke of angling, or fishing : Wherein is shewed, by conference with scriptures, the agreement betweene the fishermen, fishes, fishing of both natures temporall, and spirituall. By Samuel Gardiner Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Gardiner, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 162 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To Sir <hi>Henrie Gaudie,</hi> sir <hi>Miles Corbet,</hi> sir <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Le-Strang,</hi> sir <hi>Henrie Spel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Knights, my verie kinde friends.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>
      <hi>Hiah</hi> the Prophet,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 11.30.</note> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king hold of <hi>Ieroboams</hi> newe garment, &amp; tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it out into <hi>12.</hi> peeces, tooke occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereupon to prohecie:
<note place="margin">1. <hi>king.</hi> 17, 14.</note>
      <hi>Elias</hi> ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned on the little meale vessell, and cruise of oyle of his Hostesse, the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of <hi>Zarephath:</hi> and his scholler <hi>Elizeus</hi> did the like,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 4.7</note> preaching vpon the pitcher of oyle, of the Preachers widdow. By the line of such ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, I am led to giue the Church such spirituall Meditations, as in time I haue deducted from mine angling
<pb facs="4"/>recreation. The comparisons that lay between the fishers, and fishes of both kindes, without ransacking fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reading, are my onely store, and will serue sufficiently for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon both instruction and comfort. I put these labours foorth vnder your names, as a seale of my zeale and loue towards you, for that loue which in some of you hath been ancient, and in all of you, very good to me. I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them vnto you, and you vnto God, who more and more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large his holy spirit in you, to his glory, and your felicity.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours in all loue in the Lord,</hi> Samuel Gardiner.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>