<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115482_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10264</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20549</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115482</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of Samson: written by Fra: Quarles</title>
                 <author>Quarles, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Marriot, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 142, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE tyranny of my Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires was never yet so imperious, but I could steale some howers to my private Meditations; the fruits of which stolne time I here present thee with, in the <hi>History</hi> of <hi>Samson:</hi> Wherein, if thy extreme severity checke at any thing, which thou conceivest may not stand with the majesty of this sacred Subject; know, that my intention was not to offend my brother: The wisest of Kings, inspired by the King of Wisedome, thought it no detraction from the gravity of his Holy Proverbs, to describe a Harlot like a Harlot, Her whorish Attire; her immodest Gesture, her bold Countenance; her flattring Tongue; her lascivious Embraces; her unchast Kisses; her impudent Invitations: If my descriptions in the like kinde, offend; I make no question but the validitie of my Warrant will give a reasonable satisfaction: Hee that lifts not his
<pb facs="3"/>
feet high enough, may easily stumble: But on the contrary, If any be, whose worse then Sacrilegious mindes shall prophane our harmelesse intentions with wanton conceits, to such I heartily wish, a <hi>Procul ite;</hi> Let none such looke farther then this Epistle, at their owne perils: If they doe, let them put off their shooes, for <hi>this is holy Ground:</hi> Foule hands will muddle the clearest waters: and base mindes will corrupt the purest Text: If any offence be taken, it is by way of stealth, for there is none willingly given: I write to <hi>Bees,</hi> and not to <hi>Spiders:</hi> They will suck pleasing hony from such flowers: These may burst with their owne poyson: But you, whose well-seasond hearts are not distempered with either of these extremities, but have the better rellish of a Sacred understanding; draw neere, and reade.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>