<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE courteous Readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115254_Fr1_9</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08347</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18673</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115254</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE courteous Readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The gunner : shevving the vvhole practise of artillerie: vvith all the appurtenances therevnto belonging. Together with the making of extra-ordinary artificiall fireworkes, as well for pleasure and triumphes, as for warre and seruice. VVritten by Robert Norton, one of his Maiesties gunners and enginiers</title>
                 <author>Norton, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Robinson, Humphrey</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 100, 99-158, 4 pages, 27, 2 leaves of plates (25 folded), illustrations (woodcuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                    <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE courteous Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Practise</hi> of <hi>Artillery</hi> (the subiect of this present <hi>Treatise</hi>) being as <hi>Bianco</hi> saith, the Crowne and Palme of the <hi>Warres</hi> and Millitary discipline, teaching how to ouerthrow &amp; demollish Citties, Towns and Castles, to sinke Shippes, and inhumanely euen to teare the life and soules from the bodies of innocent men, women, and children, <hi>viet armis,</hi> to get the possession of the Goods and Lands that rightly belong to others for our selues: it may therefore at the first blush seeme to be absolutely contrary to all Christian charity. But when on the contrary wee come to finde, that <hi>Warre</hi> is euen the <hi>Mother</hi> and <hi>Nurse</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> the Rampart of <hi>Iustice,</hi> and the Law of the <hi>World;</hi> yea, the Scriptures affirme that <hi>War</hi> was a thing authorized by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, who commanded <hi>Saul</hi> thereby to destroy the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> and not to spare either Man or Beasts, &amp;c. As also that <hi>Warre</hi> was exercised in Heauen by the good Angels against the bad: So likewise hath <hi>Nature</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Beasts of the Field, the Fowles of the Ayre, and the Fishes of the Sea, and as it were by instinct, taught them with their Hornes, Tallents, Teeth, and Finnes, to fight one with another, to defend themselues, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend others. But more especially, when wee truly consider, how that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Warre</hi> and <hi>Warlike Amonition,</hi> and Discipline, no Kingdome or Common-weale can long subsist in <hi>Peace,</hi> or be able to defend it selfe, nor offend their Enemies: the case will then seeme to be much altered. These then, and the great preparations, the Martiall pollicies, cruell stratagems, and deuillish inuentions of the common Enemies of our King and Country (whereby they intend, and with malicious greedinesse daylie endeuour to destroy vs all with our Wiues, Children, and Families, to the end to possesse our goods and lands.) These I say may more then incite vs now (though late) to learne, know, and vse to practise this principall and potent part of <hi>Warre,</hi> so that thereby with Gods assistance (alwayes making him on our
<pb facs="6"/>side) we may become able and prosperous in resisting those their intended mischiefes, and breake the necks of their cursed designes, and so consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly escape those eminent and threatned dangers.</p>
   <p>Now for as much as the most presperous effects haue vsually succeeded and most vigorously preuailed, when ingenious inuentions and religious politique diligences hath beene ioyned with <hi>Armes</hi> (good <hi>Pollicie</hi> farre exceeding <hi>Force.</hi>) Therefore for the better vnderstanding of the sequent <hi>discourses,</hi> we shall doe well first to conceiue that euery <hi>materiall thing</hi> is either to be lineally described, or else intellectually vnderstood by some proper Figure, or apt word, name, or definition, which properly belongeth thereunto: For as euery <hi>Art</hi> hath certaine <hi>Rules</hi> and <hi>Principles</hi> (to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceade) without the knowledge of which no man can attaine vnto a necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie perfection for practise thereof, vnlesse hee first endeuour to learne (ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by <hi>Reason</hi> then by <hi>Roate</hi>) what each part thereof is, with the Name and <hi>Nature</hi> of each Member and part of it (without which first obtained) And I say, let a man take neuer so much paines and studie therein, he shall but in vaine pusle his braines and not benefitting himselfe. The neglect of which is the cause why many (otherwise well affected to Art) doe so fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesly bestowe both their Time, Labour, and cost, to no purpose, often condemning the Art as too hard for them, when (God knowes) the onely cause is their disorderly progresse in the studie and practise thereof: And I dare say for the <hi>Gunners Art,</hi> although it be deepe (euen able to spose the knowne parts of <hi>Naturall Philosophy, Arithmetick, Geometry,</hi> and <hi>Perspectiue,</hi> each of which her handmayd is) yet by the <hi>Definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Theorems,</hi> and <hi>Questions</hi> contained in my former Booke extant, <hi>Of the Art of great Artillery,</hi> and in this of the <hi>Practise of Artillery,</hi> I hope the willing may (with small paines ioyned with orderly and diligent practise) wade ouer this <hi>Ocean</hi> safely satisfied; neuerthelesse that if <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimides</hi> (were he now liuing) without experience and long practise there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in) with sundry tryals he could not possibly demonstrate the manifold va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties of that <hi>Mixthelicall arch</hi> or circuit of the <hi>Bullets</hi> courses, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of <hi>violent</hi> and <hi>naturall</hi> motions, and receiuing infinite diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities, according to the seuerall proportions and temperatures of the <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, length of the Peece, matter of the Shot, Mounture, and Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall,</hi> lead on by Experience the Mistris of all Arts, Action being the best Tutor: Much lesse I (the most vnable of many) who haue endeuoured herein more to respect a few experimented truthes, then many Rhethori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call imbellishments of words. Therefore neither can, or will, I presume to
<pb facs="6"/>assume so exact perfection to bee herein: although I haue endeuoured to auoyde the apparant errors of <hi>Santbech,</hi> the erronious principles of <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taglia</hi> the false rules of <hi>Rosselli,</hi> the time-ouerwerne directions of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneo,</hi> the grosse allowances of <hi>Collado</hi> for Mountures &amp; Imbasings, but especially the arch false proportionality taught in Mr. <hi>Smiths Art of Gunnery,</hi> now entituled the <hi>Complete Souldier</hi> (many of which are by Mr. <hi>Diggs</hi> and my selfe noted, at the end of my said Booke of the <hi>Art of great Artillery,</hi> and a number more there are most intollerable false, For the positions which hee there incerteth, are fit onely to leade young Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners out of the right path and way they should walke in, with a seeming easinesse by tying (as he would) such things to Arithmeticall works and proportions, as are directly contrary, and of another nature, as a small tryall will manifest, which in crutesie, I thought fit to aduertise the Reader of: But as <hi>Palingenius</hi> saith,
<q>
         <l>Friuola si fuerint fundamina tempore paruo</l>
         <l>Deficiet, quiquid super his fabricare volimus.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Some men also may imagine because the figures heerein are many of them, the same that were cut for Captaine <hi>Vffanoes</hi> Booke of <hi>Artillery,</hi> Printed at <hi>Frankford,</hi> that therefore I haue onely translated the same. I confesse the figures most of them being good, and he for this and the most part he hath written of this practise, being the best of any the Authors that I euer read: yet had I onely translated him, I should but little haue helped English Gunners their Measures, Waights, Ordnance, and Powder so much differing from our English, as in their places I haue shewed, it would not haue been <hi>operae pretium</hi> so to haue done: But that I haue from him and other Authors made choise of some things, and refined &amp; applied others for our benefits, I am not to denie; nor that the Figures are many of them his that I haue herein written vpon, which was by reason of their goodnes, faireness, and cheapenes; for the Figures, had they beene cut of purpose in <hi>England,</hi> would haue made these Bookes too deare for Gunners, for whose good they were originally destined, wherein I haue roughly endeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in well meaning, which if it be well taken, I shall be therewith well sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, and restreadie to explaine whatsoeuer shall herein seeme difficill.</p>
   <p>Now that this my Treatise for the practise of Artillery, may the more currantly proceede, &amp; be the playner to the vnderstanding and satisfaction of the Reader, I held it necessarie first to shew by certaine <hi>Definitions, Demands, Axioms,</hi> &amp; <hi>Theoremes</hi> (besides those in my former Book) called the <hi>Art of great Artillery</hi> (which I wish euery young Gunner to
<pb facs="7"/>peruse also with diligence) the names, natures, and operations of such things as are necessarie to be knowne, vsed, and done in the Practick part thereof, without which it were impossible to conclude any thing well, and as it ought to be. Therefore as in the <hi>Warres</hi> of our age, there is no <hi>earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly force</hi> that can more command the Fortified, or resist the assaulting <hi>Enemie</hi> then great Ordnance duly vsed. So the <hi>Gunners</hi> therefore ought to endeuour to vnderstand these so well, that they discharge them not in vaine. First, in regard of the great expences of Amunition thereby cast away: Secondly, least thereby they frustrate the wished seruice. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in laying themselues and their Companies open and vndefenced to the <hi>Enemies</hi> Forces, which will (in them) encrease valour, and in your selues terrour, thereby also deseruing to purchase great blame and disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour from the hands of their Commanders, with the losse of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces fauour, and vtter ouerthrow of their owne preferment euer after. Wherefore seeing that such fruitless discharging of Ordnance in the time of seruice, is so great an inconuenience, and happeneth most commonly for want of knowledge, or ready meanes to direct the Peeces precisely to the marke; I haue thought it worthy my labour therein to shew Artificiall meanes (to such as are desirous to learne) how to know, direct, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the Peeces committed to their charge; so, that in time of neede they may bee assured to make their Shotts take good effect, onely by applying themselues to vnderstand and practise these fewe things following.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>