<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Gentlemen that are disposed.</title>
           <author>R., B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115897_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10701</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20983</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115897</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Gentlemen that are disposed.</title>
                 <author>R., B.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Faultes faults, and nothing else but faultes</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Chorlton (Charlton), Jeffrey (Geoffrey)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>3, 63, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Gentlemen that are disposed.</head>
   <p>GEntlemen, if I haue fitted your humors with this fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, much good doe it yee, I would it were for you: if it be offensiue to some queasie stomacke, it proceedeth rather vpon some distempered humour in the partie so offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, then of any fault of mine: and yet to speake truly, I meant not to please all. For when I first vndertooke the subiect, I knew it could not be handled without offence: but as I haue not detec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any one particularly of mine owne knowledge, so if any man vpon a guiltie conscience will accuse himselfe, his fault be vpon his owne head: should we forbeare to speake against vice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the vicious will be offended? if that might once be brought to passe, it were high time to follow <hi>Tarltons</hi> aduice, to pull downe the <hi>Church,</hi> and set vp the <hi>Ale-house.</hi> And how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inferiour officers would then fall to decay: amongst the rest, the poore hang-man would miscarie for want of maintenance, but let them comfort themselues, vice must be corrected, and sinne will be punished.</p>
   <p>And for the hangman me thinks I durst warrant him worke, so long as there is a Pope in <hi>Rome,</hi> or a Papist in great Bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</p>
   <p>Now for mine owne part, that haue taken vpon me to speake of so many faults, let me first manifest mine owne, I confesse I haue iested at abuse, and I haue a little scoffed at those that doe vse themselues to make a scoffe at vertue. In the setting downe whereof I haue imitated the Painter, who applieth colours but according to his picture. So in these discourses, I haue kept a Souldiers <hi>Decorum,</hi> expressing matter of little regard, with words and phrases best befitting the subiect. And where I haue to deale with more serious circumstance, I haue tempered my stile with words and tearmes thereafter.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>B. R.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>