<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the CHRISTIAN Reader.</title>
           <author>Greenwood, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115797_Fr4_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02186</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12329</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115797</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the CHRISTIAN Reader.</title>
                 <author>Greenwood, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Greenvvoods vvorkes : contayned in fiue seueral tractates. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. of the Day of iudgement. Lords Prayer. Race to saluation. Torment of Tophet. Baptisme of Christ</title>
                 <author>Greenwood, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bell, Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Clarke, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 117, 1, 6, 92, 12, 8, 82, 6, 10, 43, 11 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="183"/>
   <head>To the CHRISTIAN Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>A</hi> Religious and right vertuous Gentlewoman, <hi>curteous and</hi>
      <note place="margin">I. M.</note>
      <hi>Christian Reader,</hi> much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuning mee for a written Copie of this extant worke (vpon good conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration) proues the onely occasion of this printed Tractate: for things writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, as they are more tedious, so are they lesse profitable; but printed Tractates lesse tedious and more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable: I am not borne alone to my selfe, my particular friends I loue to satisfie, but the generall good still shall be my ayme.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="184"/>And that my penne thus happily should turned bee to Presse, I am no whit vnwilling: both because few haue written vpon this worthy subiect; as also for that I see this heauenly Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment seldome made right vse of, the most contenting themselues with the bare signe, very few acquainting themselues with the blessed power of the signified. That therefore our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession may not be (as in many Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christian parts of the world) in super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall signe and shew alone, but in sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, life, and power: I commend vnto thy view (for the better infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of thine head, and reformation of thine heart) this short (yet I trust profitable) Treatise of that blessed Baptisme of our blessed Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Iesus Christ.</p>
   <p>Here (Christian friend) mayst thou learne a double lesson to liue to dye: to dye to that, which otherwise must bee
<pb facs="184"/>
thy death: to liue that Christian and happy life, wherewith who-euer is not acquainted, euerlastingly must dye.</p>
   <p>The Lord God (from my very soule I heartily desire) blesse these my poore paines to the best good of thine owne Soule, and worke in thine heart a death to all that is euill, and a life to all grace and godlinesse, that his glory more and more by thee may be aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and thine owne soule more &amp; more by him refreshed: and that for his owne mercy sake; to whose most happy protection, I commend thee both in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Soule in his deare Sonne Christ Iesus, and rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine euer-louing in the Lord,<lb/>
         <hi>Henry Greenwood.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>