<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY LORD, THE Abbot of Dorak, one of his Maje∣sties Privie Counsellors, and Trea∣surer of the Holy Chappell at Paris.</title>
           <author>Serre, P. de la</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115331_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10214</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20491</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115331</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY LORD, THE Abbot of Dorak, one of his Maje∣sties Privie Counsellors, and Trea∣surer of the Holy Chappell at Paris.</title>
                 <author>Serre, P. de la</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The secretary in fashion: or, A compendious and refined way of expression in all manner of letters. Composed in French by P. Sr de la Serre, historiographer of France. And translated into English, by John Massinger, Gent</title>
                 <author>Puget de La Serre, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Emerson (Emondson, Edmonds), Godfrey</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bulkley (Buckley), Stephen</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 48 pages, 49-56, a-d leaves, 57-131, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO MY LORD, THE Abbot of Dorak, one of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Privie Counsellors, and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surer of the Holy Chappell at Paris.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>My Lord,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Particular esteeme I have of your Merit, obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged me to these Publick Proofes; being Ambitious the world should know, that though my inclinations be not strong enough to follow vertue, yet I never cease to build her Altars, in al places where I find her Image. To maintain (my Lord) that you are one of the most lively, the Eloquence of your actions surpassing that of my Discourse, has
<pb facs="4"/>
already perswaded it to al the world, so that your Honesty having made it selfe known every where, I satisfie my selfe in praising you worthily, to declare your name, being one of the most accomplished Prelates of this Age. I speake not of those negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Importance which you have finished, to the Honour of the King, and Satisfaction of his Emminence who knew right well that the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Employments were under the reach of your Capacity. I wish with Passion, I had any in your service, wherby I might force you to beleeve that I am extreamly</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>My Lord,</salute>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your most humble, and most faithfull servant,</hi> P. de La. Serre.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>