<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115863_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20518</idno>
           <idno type="STC">693</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115863</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Strange newes from Antvvarpe : which happened the 12. of August last past. 1612. First printed in Dutch at Bergen ap Zoame by Ioris Staell and now translated into English by I.F</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Blower (Blore), Ralph</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 10 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not vnknowne vnto most men of sort, what a famous Citty the Citty of Antwarp is, wherein of late, the wonderfull power of Sathan, hath (by the permission of the Almighty God) bin there done &amp; showen in the Cloyster of S. Michaells in the said Citty, which is not onely worthy: but also very requisite &amp; meete to be made knowne and manyfested vnto all men, in regard of the sinnes and wickednes which now in thiese dayes remaineth to common amongst all nations, and forasmuch as of late the foule Finde (by Gods permission) shewed his wrath and indingnation against the same Citty by consuming and spoyling of a great part of the Cloyster there, as it is most truely made knowne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to diuers and sundry persons already, as well by letters as otherwise: Therefore to the ende that all persons should vnderstand of the strange Accidents there happened, I thought it meete to set foorth a small
<pb facs="3"/>
and briefe treatise thereof, whereby euery one may vnderstand, and be truely aduertised thereof to their owne contentments, wishing all people to pray vnto the omnipotent Maiestie of God, for to defend vs all from such, and the like Sathanicall Actions of the most tempting and wicked Sathan, who seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth dayly for the distrction of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, as in the matter following is at large truely declared.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>