<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[To The Reader]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115807_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10659</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20934</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115807</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[To The Reader]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Three treatises : of the vanity of the creature. The sinfulnesse of sinne. The life of Christ. Being the substance of severall sermons preached at Lincolns Inne: by Edward Reynoldes, preacher to that honourable society, and late fellow of Merton Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Reynolds, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bostock, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 100, 99-535, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <p>
      <hi>Christian Reader, Importunitie of Friends hath over-rul'd me to this Publication; and importunitie of businesse crossing me in the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of these pieces together, hath made the whole savour of my distra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and caused more escapes in the Print, then otherwise should have been. The principall I have here corrected; those which are smaller may in the reading be easily discerned.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Page 92. line 17. for Ieroboam, reade <hi>Iehosaphat▪</hi> p. 122. l. 16. f. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant, r. <hi>dependence.</hi> p. 130. l. 16▪ f. hastned, r. <hi>hartned.</hi> p. 134. l. 21. f. enticeth, r. <hi>entitleth.</hi> p. 140. l. 14. f. bow, r. <hi>bough.</hi> p. 148. l. 9. f. he, r <hi>me.</hi> p. 159. l. 33. f. honour in, r, <hi>honour of God in.</hi> p. 167. l. 6. blot out <hi>the.</hi> p. 212. l. 15. leave out <hi>these.</hi> p. 278. l. 20. f. rageing r. <hi>raigning.</hi> p. 295. l. 18. f. darkenes, r. <hi>darke.</hi> p. 299 l. 28. f. possessions, r. <hi>passions.</hi> p. 355. l. 16. f. we, r. <hi>hee.</hi> p. 401. l. 34. f. fulfill, r. <hi>fulfild.</hi> p. 405. l. 26. f. terrifire, r. <hi>testifies.</hi> p. 407. l. 27. f. discourses, r. <hi>discoveries.</hi> p. 434. l. 23. after, even as wee are knowne. adde, <hi>Secondly, in regard of accomplishment and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>summation.</hi> p. 440. l. 33. f. reiect, r. <hi>eiect.</hi> p. 442. l. 16. f. that faith, or made unable, r. <hi>faith, or made that unable.</hi> p. 464. l. 34. f. it, r. <hi>them.</hi> p. 484. l. 34. f. as, r. <hi>was.</hi> p. 485. l. 19. f. conviction. r. <hi>conclusion.</hi> p. 487. l. 26. f. were, r. <hi>weare.</hi> p. 501. l. 11. f. the, r. <hi>these.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>