<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE VVORTHILY HONOVRED, AND MOST WOR∣THY TO BE WORTHILY HONOVRED, the LADY SAINT IONES, wife to the Right Honourable SIR OLIVER SAINT IONES, Knight Lord Depu∣tie of Ireland.</title>
           <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115904_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10711</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20991.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115904</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE VVORTHILY HONOVRED, AND MOST WOR∣THY TO BE WORTHILY HONOVRED, the LADY SAINT IONES, wife to the Right Honourable SIR OLIVER SAINT IONES, Knight Lord Depu∣tie of Ireland.</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>My ladies looking glasse : VVherein may be discerned a wise man from a foole, a good woman from a bad: and the true resemblance of vice, masked vnder the vizard of vertue. By Barnabe Rich Gentleman, seruant to the Kings most excellent Maiestie</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 74 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE VVORTHILY HONOVRED, AND MOST WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THY TO BE WORTHILY HONOVRED, the LADY SAINT IONES, wife to the <hi>Right Honourable</hi> SIR OLIVER SAINT IONES, Knight Lord Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Ireland.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adame, to auoide Idlenesse, I haue beta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken my selfe to those endeauours, that the world will repute to be more idle, than idlenesse it selfe; and perhaps some will not let to say, that it had beene better for me to haue continued idle still, than to <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ue been thus ill occupied. For it is now accounted sinne to reprooue sinne, and there is no exercise accounted to be more idle, than to reprehend the idle fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of this madding age, that Time hath now hatched vp, and are long sithens become so flush and fligge, that they are flowne into the world, and they haue there nestled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues amongst the <hi>Chickins of vertue,</hi> so disguising them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues vnder the habit of <hi>vertue,</hi> that they are reputed to be of <hi>vertues Broode,</hi> and are not easily to be discerned by their <hi>plumes,</hi> or outward shew.</p>
   <p>To discouer them therefore, to those that haue any list to eschue them, I haue composed this looking Glasse, which I haue fronted in the forehead with the title of <hi>My Ladies Looking Glasse.</hi> Not that it is any thing lesse behoouefull for my Lord, than it is for my Lady to looke in; for although women doe vse their looking glasses, but to espie the defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of their bodily beautie, yet this looking Glasse is
<pb facs="3"/>
composed of a contrarie constitution: for this maketh ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest the diseases of the minde, and discouereth the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections aswell of men as of women, that doth behold themselues in it.</p>
   <p>It taxeth the abuses of the time and here is to be seene (though in a few lines) many actuall breaches of Gods holy lawes. I haue presumed to present it to your Ladiships pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and although I know it be not fit for euery one to reade, that perhaps would winch, if they found themselues to be rubd: yet your vntainted vertues being free from all detection, you may with a cleare conscience, and an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bended brow, aswell vouchsafe to reade, as likewise to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect, when their is nothing therein conteined but iustifia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble truth; the iniquities of these times being so palpable, that it is as easie to proue, as it is to reproue them. I haue not presumed to present these lines whereby to instruct your knowledg, nor, to set down precepts for your Ladish▪ to follow; but knowing your Ladiship how worthily famed, of whom could I make better choice than of a Lady so highly renowned both for wisedome and vertue?</p>
   <p>I might here indeauour your Ladiships further praises, and that without either fraud or flatterie, but as the vnskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full painter, that would take vpon him the draught of some rare perfection that were more then ordinary, how well so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he might be furnished with colours, yet wanting art, he might rather blemish than grace the worke he tooke in hand: I will therefore here stay my selfe, beseeching your Ladiship to pardon his bold presumption, that will rest to doe you seruice during life,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Ladiships, to command, BARNABE RICH.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>