<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Speech]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115239_Fr6_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03888</idno>
           <idno type="STC">140.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115239</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Speech]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ta tōn Mousōn eisodia: = The Muses welcome : to the high and mightie prince Iames by the grace of God King of Great Britaine France and Ireland, defender of the faith &amp;c. At His Majesties happie returne to his olde and natiue kingdome of Scotland, after 14 yeeres absence, in anno 1617. Digested according to the order of his Majesties progresse, by I.A</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hart, Andro</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 44, 2, 45-138, 137-289, 1 page, portraits (woodcut), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
   <pb n="105" facs="57"/>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LBEIT THE COMMOUNE feares which perplex most confident Orators, may dash and confound my spirit, justlie suspecting my owne weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in speaking to your Sacred Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, MOST MIGHTIE KING, <hi>and our most gracious Soveraine Lord:</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Yet being vpholdin by the long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience which I haue had from time to time of your Majesties most myld and gracious acceptance of the speaches delivered by your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties most humble subjects, of whose number I doe acknowledge my selfe one of the meanest: I am emboldned, at the desyre of the Magistrats Counselours and whole bodie of this your Majesties an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, frie Regal burgh, to offer to your most excellent Majestie, that hartie welcome from them, whose inward greife conceaved for your Majesties long absence, is turned in excessive Joy in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaird of your Majesties most Princelie resolution (now reallie effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuat) to honour this your Majesties most ancient Kingdome with your Royall and most comfortable presence: An inestimable bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to all, bot cheiflie to vs who haue not onlie participat of the cōmoun benefits which all your Majesties good subjects doe injoy vnder your Maiesties most happie governament, I meane puritie of Religion, peace and securitie, by sea and by land, at home and abroad, So that no haeresie hath toleration, no oppression the bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of authoritie, no insolence the mark of greatnes, within all your Maiesties Dominions, the meanest living vnder his owne figtrie, but feare of wrong, both in the high-lands and borders, and the mightiest kept vnder your Maiesties obedience, and feare of the Lawes, but also besids these, a more particular blessing to vs, who haue teasted so abundantlie of your Majesties bountefull goodnes and fathersie care laitlie kythed in the quenshing and extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing (by your Maiesties most Princelie and prudent directions
<pb n="106" facs="58"/>
giuen to the Lords of your Maiesties most honorable Privie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sale) of that fire of sedition which was kindled within our bowels, to the apparent overthrow and combustion of our whole estate: And in the setling and establishing of a solid peace amongs vs by the meanes of Justice, whereof wee haue most sensiblie found both sweit and profitable fruits ever since. Of these manifold blessings to speak what wee can is not now convenient, and to speak what we shuld is not possible. This one thing wee must say, that wee haue more then iust cause to welcome to these our meane territories your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Maiestie, whome wee haue euer ludged in our hearts since the first houre of your Maiesties most happie natiuitie.</p>
   <p>Receaue then, <hi>Most gracious Soveraine,</hi> that hartie welcome which wee all most humblie offer from true and weell approved hearts: And here wee doe lay doun at your Maiesties feete Oure lyves, our liberties, our goods, and all vther meanes granted to vs by GOD, to be sacrificed in your Maiesties service, without any privat respect or consideration whatsoeuer: Praying the King of Kings that your Maiesties Royall person may bee euer saife from all reasonable practises, your H. naturall lyfe extended to the pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibilitie of Nature, and your royall progenie and race, by lineall succession sitting vpon your Imperiall throne, may haue one pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod with the World.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>