<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>
AN EXPLANATION OF SUNDRY TEARMES SOMEWHAT obscure, in this translation of Plutarch, in favour of the unlearned Reader; after the order of the Alphabet.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115981_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09800</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20063</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115981</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>
AN EXPLANATION OF SUNDRY TEARMES SOMEWHAT obscure, in this translation of Plutarch, in favour of the unlearned Reader; after the order of the Alphabet.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The philosophie, commonlie called, the morals vvritten by the learned philosopher Plutarch of Chæronea. Translated out of Greeke into English, and conferred with the Latine translations and the French, by Philemon Holland of Coventrie, Doctor in Physicke. VVhereunto are annexed the summaries necessary to be read before every treatise</title>
                 <author>Plutarch</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hatfield, Arnold.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ponsonby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 1363, 65 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Classical authors</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="glossary">
   <pb facs="689"/>
   <head>
      <pb facs="689"/>
AN EXPLANATION OF SUNDRY TEARMES SOMEWHAT obscure, in this translation of <hi>Plutarch,</hi> in favour <hi>of the unlearned Reader; after the order of the Alphabet.</hi>
   </head>
   <div n="a" type="part">
      <list>
         <head>A.</head>
         <label>AUlus,</label>
         <item>A forename a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong <note place="margin">A.</note> the Romans. <hi>Abyrtace,</hi> A deintie kinde of meat, with the Medes &amp; other Barbarous nations, sharpe &amp; quicke of taste to provoke and please the appetite, composed of Leeks, Garlike, Cresses, Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie, Pomgranate kirnels, and such like.</item>
         <label>Academie,</label>
         <item>A shadowy place full of groves, a mile distant from <hi>Athens,</hi> where <hi>Plato</hi> the Philosopher was borne, and wherein hee taught. Of it, the Academicke Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers tooke their name; whose maner was to discourse and dispute of all questions, but to determine and resolve of nothing. And for the great frequence and concourse of scholars to that place, our Universities and great schooles of learning, be named Academies.</item>
         <label>Aediles,</label>
         <item>Certeine magistrates or officers in <hi>Rome:</hi> who were of two sorts; <hi>Plebeij</hi> and <hi>Curules. Plebeij,</hi> of the Commons onely, two in number, more ancient than the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; chosen by the people alone, to second and assist the Tribunes of the Commons, as their right hands. This name they tooke of the charge which they had to mainteine temples and chapels: albeit they registred the Sanctions and Acts of the people, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Plebiscita,</hi> and kept the same in their owne custodie; were Clerks of the Market, and looked to weights and measures, &amp;c. yea, and exhibited the games and playes named <hi>Plebeij. Curules</hi> were likewise twain, elected out of the order and degree of the <hi>Patritij:</hi> so called of the Yvorie chaire wherein they were allowed to sit, as officers of greater state; and by vertue whereof, in some cases, and at certein times they might exercise civill jurisdiction. It belonged un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to these to set forth the solemnities, called <hi>Ludi Magni</hi> or <hi>Romani:</hi> overseers they were likewise of the buildings thorowout the city, aswell publike as private, in maner of the <hi>Astynomi</hi> in <hi>Athens:</hi> they had regard unto the publike vaults, sinks, conveiances, and conduits of the waters that served the city, as also to the Arcenall, &amp;c. Moreover, they had power to attach the bodies of great persons: and were charged to see un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the provision of corne and victuals. At the first, none but of noble families or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricians were advanced to this place: but in processe of time, Commoners also attei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thereto. More of them; &amp; how in <hi>Iulius Casars</hi> time there were elected six <hi>Aediles,</hi> whereof two were named <hi>Cereals;</hi> See <hi>Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xander</hi> at <hi>Alexander, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>Genial.</hi> dieth.</item>
         <label>Aegineticke, Mna <hi>or</hi> Mina,</label>
         <item>Seemeth to be the ancient coine or money of <hi>Greece:</hi> for they were the first that coined money: and of them came <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>. <hi>Caelius Rhodig.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Aeolius Modus,</label>
         <item>In Musicke a certeine simple, plaine and mild tune, apt to procure sleepe and bring folke to bed.</item>
         <label>Aequinox,</label>
         <item>That time of the yeere, when the daies and nights be of equall length; which hapneth twice in the yeere, to wit, in March and September.</item>
         <label>Aestivall,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Of the Summer: as the <hi>Aestivall</hi> Solstice or Tropicke of the Sunne, when he is come neerest unto us, and returneth Southward from us.</item>
         <label>Aloïdae <hi>or</hi> Aloïadae,</label>
         <item>were <hi>Othus</hi> and <hi>Ephialtes,</hi> two giants, so named of <hi>Aloëus</hi> the giant their supposed father: for of his wife <hi>Iphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>media, Neptune</hi> begat them. It is said, that every moneth they grew nine fingers.</item>
         <label>Alphabet,</label>
         <item>The order or rew of Greeke letters as they stand; so called of <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Beta,</hi> the two formost letters: and it answereth to our A.B.C.</item>
         <label>
            <pb facs="690"/>
Alternative,</label>
         <item>By course or turnes, one after an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; going and comming, &amp;c.</item>
         <label>Amphictyones,</label>
         <item>Were a certein solemne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell of State in <hi>Greece,</hi> who held twice in the yeere a meeting, in the Spring and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunne, at <hi>Thermopyle;</hi> being assembled from the 12 flourithing cities of <hi>Greece:</hi> there to consult of most important affaires.</item>
         <label>Amphitheatre,</label>
         <item>A spacious shew place; in forme round, and made as it were of two Theaters. See <hi>Theater.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Amphora,</label>
         <item>A measure in <hi>Rome</hi> of liquors only. It seemeth to take that name of the two eares it had, of either side one: it conteined eight <hi>Congios,</hi> which are somewhat under as many of our wine gallons.</item>
         <label>Amnets,</label>
         <item>Preservatives hung about the necke, or otherwise worne, against witchcraft, poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, eiebiting, sicknesse, or any other evils.</item>
         <label>Anarchie,</label>
         <item>The state of a city or countrey with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out government.</item>
         <label>Andria,</label>
         <item>A societie of men, meeting together in some publicke hall for to eat and drinke: Instituted first among the Thebans, like to the <hi>Phiditia</hi> in <hi>Lacedaemon.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Annales,</label>
         <item>Histories, Records, or Chronicles, conteining things done from yere to yeere.</item>
         <label>Anniversarie,</label>
         <item>Comming once enery yeere, at a certeine time: as the Nativity of <hi>Christ,</hi> and Sturbridge faire, &amp;c.</item>
         <label>Antarcticke,</label>
         <item>That is to say, Opposit unto the Arcticke. See <hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> .</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Antidote,</label>
         <item>A medicine, properly taken inwardly against a poison or some pestilent and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous disease. A counterpoison or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servative.</item>
         <label>Antipathie,</label>
         <item>A repugnance in nature, by reason of contrarie affections; whereby some can not abide the smell of roses, others may not endure the sight of a Cat, &amp;c.</item>
         <label>Antiparistasis,</label>
         <item>A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> or restraint on every side; whereby either colde or heat is made stronger in it selfe by the restraining of the contrary: as the naturall heat of our bodies in Winter, through the coldnesse of the aire compassing it about: likewise, the coldnesse of the middle region of the aire in Summer, by occasion of the heat on both sides cansing thunder and haile, &amp;c.</item>
         <label>Antiphonie,</label>
         <item>A noise of contrarie sounds.</item>
         <label>Antipodes,</label>
         <item>Those people who inhabit under and beneath our Hemisphaere, and go with their feet full against ours.</item>
         <label>Apathte,</label>
         <item>Impassibilitie, or voidnesse of all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and passions.</item>
         <label>Apaturia,</label>
         <item>A feast solemnized for the space of foure daies at <hi>Athens</hi> in the honour of <hi>Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus.</hi> So called of <hi>Apate,</hi> that is to say, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit: because <hi>Xanthius</hi> the Boeotian was in single fight slaine deceitfully by <hi>Thimoeles</hi> the Athenian. For the tale goeth, that whiles they were in combat, <hi>Bacchus</hi> appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red behind <hi>Xanthius,</hi> clad in a goats skinne: and when <hi>Thimoeles</hi> charged his concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent for comming into the field with an as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistant; as he looked backe, he was killed by <hi>Thimoeles</hi> abovenamed.</item>
         <label>Apologie,</label>
         <item>A plea for the defence or excuse of any person.</item>
         <label>Apothegme,</label>
         <item>A short sententious speech.</item>
         <label>Apoplexie,</label>
         <item>A disease comming suddenly in maner of a stroke, with an universall asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment and deprivation of sense and motion, which either causeth death quicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; or else endeth in a dead palsey.</item>
         <label>Archontes,</label>
         <item>Were chiefe magistrates at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> at first every tenth yeere; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards yeerely chosen by lot, unto whom the rule of the common-welth in their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular state was committed: of whom the first was named <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, that is to say, King: the second, <hi>Archon,</hi> that is to say, Ruler: the third, <hi>Polemarchus:</hi> and the other six, <hi>Thesmothelae.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Arctick,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Northerly; so called of <hi>Arctos</hi> in Greeke, which signifieth the Beare, that is to say, those conspicuous sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven starres in the North, named <hi>Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matns</hi> waine; neere unto which is that pole or point of the imaginarie axell-tree, about which the heavens turne, which thereupon is named, The pole Arctick: and over against it, underneath our Hemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sphaere, is the other pole, called Antarctick, in the South part of the world.</item>
         <label>Aristocratre,</label>
         <item>A forme of Government, or a State wherein the nobles and best men be Rulers.</item>
         <label>To <hi>Aromatize,</hi>
         </label>
         <item>that is to say, To season or make pleasant, by putting thereto some sweete and odoriferous spices.</item>
         <label>Astragalote Mastis,</label>
         <item>A scourge or whip, the strings whereof are set and wrought with ankle-bones, called <hi>Astragali,</hi> thereby to give a more grievous lash.</item>
         <label>Atomi,</label>
         <item>Indivisible bodies like to motes in the Sunne beames; of which <hi>Democritus</hi> and <hi>Epicurus</hi> imagined all things to be made.</item>
         <label>Atticke pure,</label>
         <item>that is to say, The most fine and eloquent: for in <hi>Athens</hi> they spake the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest Greeke; insomuch as <hi>Thucydides</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="690"/>
it <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, that is to say, Greece of Greece, as one would say, the very quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenssence of Greece.</item>
         <label>Averrunct <hi>or</hi> Averruncani,</label>
         <item>Were gods a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Romans, supposed to put by and chace away evils and calamities: such as <hi>Hercules</hi> and <hi>Apollo</hi> among the Greekes, called thereupon <hi>Apotropaei.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Auspices,</label>
         <item>
            <hi>Plutarch</hi> seemeth to take for <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi> that is to say, Certeine priests or sooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saiers, who by the inspection and observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of birds did foretell future things.</item>
         <label>Axiomes,</label>
         <item>Were principal propositions in Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke, of as great authoritie and force as Maximes in law: and it should seeme that those Maximes be derived corruptly from Axiomes.</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="b" type="part">
      <list>
         <head>B</head>
         <label>BAcchanalta,</label>
         <item>named also <hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ,</hi> Certein licentious festivall solemnities in the honor of <hi>Bacchus,</hi> performed at the first by day light, and afterward in the night season, with all maner of filthy wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: instituted first in <hi>Athens,</hi> and other cities of <hi>Greece</hi> euery three yeeres: in <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> also: at last they were taken vp in <hi>Italy</hi> and at <hi>Rome.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Bacchiadae,</label>
         <item>A noble familie in <hi>Corinth,</hi> who for the space almost of 200. yeeres there ruled.</item>
         <label>Bachyllion,</label>
         <item>A song or daunce, which seemeth to take the name of a famous Tragoedian poet named <hi>Bachyllus,</hi> who devised and practised it; like as <hi>Pyladion,</hi> of <hi>Pylades,</hi> as notable a Comoedian.</item>
         <label>Barbarisme,</label>
         <item>A rude and corrupt maner of speech, full of barbarous and absonant words.</item>
         <label>Basis,</label>
         <item>The flat, piedstall or foote of a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumne, pillar, statue, or such like, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it standeth.</item>
         <label>Baeotarches, <hi>or</hi> Baeotarchae,</label>
         <item>The soueraigne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate or Ruler of the Boeotians.</item>
         <label>Baeotius,</label>
         <item>a kinde of Mesure or Note in Musick used in <hi>Baeotia.</hi>
         </item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="c" type="part">
      <list>
         <head>C</head>
         <label>CAius,</label>
         <item>A common forename to many <note place="margin">C.</note> families in <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Caia</hi> to the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man kinde: as usuall as <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Jone</hi> with us, as appeereth by this forme of speech or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary in mariage; Where thou art <hi>Caius,</hi> I will be <hi>Caia.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Calends.</label>
         <item>
            <hi>See</hi> Kalends.</item>
         <label>Callasitres,</label>
         <item>Hardnesse in maner of brawn, as in the skinne of hands or feet, occasioned by much labour and trauell.</item>
         <label>Cancerous,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Resembling a certeine hard tumor or swelling, occasioned by me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholicke bloud, named a Cancer, for the likenesse it hath to a crab-fish, (named in Latine <hi>Cancer</hi>) partly, for the swelling veines appearing about it, like unto the feet or cleis of the said fish: and in part, for that it is not easily remooved, no more than the crab if it once settle to a place: &amp; lastly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the colour is not much unlike. This swelling if it breake out into an ulcer, hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or unneth admitteth any cure, and by some is called a Wolfe.</item>
         <label>Candyli,</label>
         <item>A kind of dainty meat made with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and milke.</item>
         <label>Candys,</label>
         <item>an ornament of the Persians, Medians, and other East nations; much like to a Diademe.</item>
         <label>Catamite,</label>
         <item>A boy abused against kinde: a bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage.</item>
         <label>Cataplasme,</label>
         <item>A pultesse or grosse maner of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</item>
         <label>
            <hi>To</hi> Cauterize,</label>
         <item>To burne or seare with a red hot iron or other mettall.</item>
         <label>Cenotaph,</label>
         <item>An emptie Tombe or Sepulcher, wherein no corps is interred.</item>
         <label>Censours,</label>
         <item>Magistrates of State in <hi>Rome,</hi> whose charge was to valew and estimate mens goods, and enroll them accordingly in their seuerall ranges: Also to demise unto certaine farmers, called Publicanes, the publicke profits of the city for a rent, and to put foorth the city works unto them, to be undertaken at a price. Likewise their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice it was to oversee mens maners, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by oftentimes they woulde deprive Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of their dignitie: take from Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men their horses of service and rings: dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place commanders out of their owne tribe: disable them for giving voices; and make them AErarij.</item>
         <label>Centre,</label>
         <item>The middle pricke of a circle or globe, equally distant from the circumference thereof.</item>
         <label>Centumviri,</label>
         <item>A certeine Court of Judges in <hi>Rome,</hi> chosen three out of every tribe. And albeit there were 35. tribes, and the whole number by that account amounted to an hundred and five; yet in round reckoning, and by custome, they went under the name of an hundred, and therefore were called <hi>Centumviri.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Cercopes,</label>
         <item>Certaine ridiculous people inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Iland <hi>Pitherusa,</hi> having tailes like monkeys, good for nought but to make sport.</item>
         <label>
            <pb facs="691"/>
Chalons,</label>
         <item>A small piece of brasse money; the eighth part or (as some say) the sixth, of the Atticke <hi>Obolus:</hi> somewhat better than halfe a farthing or a cue.</item>
         <label>Chromaticke Musicke,</label>
         <item>Was soft, delicate and effeminate, ful of descant, fained voices and quavering, as some are of opinion.</item>
         <label>Cidaris,</label>
         <item>An ornament of the head, which in <hi>Persia, Media,</hi> and <hi>Armenia,</hi> the Kings and High priests wore, with a blew band or rib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band about it, beset with white spots.</item>
         <label>Cinaradae,</label>
         <item>A familie descended from <hi>Cinaras.</hi> Some read <hi>Cinyradae,</hi> and <hi>Cinyras.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Circumgyration,</label>
         <item>A turning or winding round.</item>
         <label>Cn.</label>
         <item>A forename to some houses in <hi>Rome.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Colian earth,</label>
         <item>So called of <hi>Colias</hi> a promontory or hill in the territorie of <hi>Attica.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Colleague,</label>
         <item>A fellow or companion in office.</item>
         <label>Colonies,</label>
         <item>Were townes wherein the Romanes placed citizens of their owne to inhabit, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as Free-holders, or tenants &amp; underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers; endowed with franchises and liberties diversly: Erected first by <hi>Romulus.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Comoedia vetus,</label>
         <item>Licentiously abused all maner of persons, not forbearing to name and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce upon the Stage even the best men, such as noble <hi>Pericles,</hi> wise <hi>Solon,</hi> and just <hi>Aristides:</hi> nay it spared not the very State it selfe and bodie of the Common-weale; whereupon at length it was condemned and put downe.</item>
         <label>Conctons,</label>
         <item>Orations or speeches made openly before the body of the people, such pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly as the Tribunes of the Commons u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed unto them.</item>
         <label>Congiarium,</label>
         <item>a dole or liberall gift of some Prince or Noble person bestowed upon the people. It tooke the name of that measure <hi>Congius,</hi> much about our gallon, which was given in oile or wine, by the poll: but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, any other such gift or distribution, whether it were in other victuals, or in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, went under that name.</item>
         <label>Consuls,</label>
         <item>two in number, Soveraigne Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates in <hi>Rome,</hi> succeeding in the place of Kings, with the same authoritie and roiall ensignes: onely they were chosen yeerely.</item>
         <label>Contignate,</label>
         <item>Close set together, so as they touch one another, as houses adjoining.</item>
         <label>Contusions,</label>
         <item>Bruises, dry-beatings, or crushes.</item>
         <label>Convulsions,</label>
         <item>Plucking or shooting paines: Cramps.</item>
         <label>Cordax,</label>
         <item>A lascivious and unseemly kinde of daunce, used in Comoedies at the first, but misliked afterwards and rejected.</item>
         <label>Criticks,</label>
         <item>Grammarians, who tooke upon them to censure and judge Poemes and other works of authors; such as <hi>Aristarchus</hi> was.</item>
         <label>Criticall daies,</label>
         <item>In Physicke be observed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the motion of the humour and the Moone; in which the disease sheweth some notable alteration, to life or death, as if the patient had then his dome. In which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard we say, that the seventh day is a king; but the sixth, a tyrant.</item>
         <label>Cube,</label>
         <item>A square figure: as in Geometrie, the Die; having sixe faces foure square and even: in Arithmeticke, a number multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it selfe; as nine arising of thrice three, and sixteene of foure times foure.</item>
         <label>Curvature,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Bending round, as in the felly of a wheele.</item>
         <label>Corollarie,</label>
         <item>An overdeale, or overmeasure, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven more than is due or was promised.</item>
         <label>Curule chaire,</label>
         <item>A seat of estate among the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans made of Ivorie; whereupon certaine Magistrates were called <hi>Curules,</hi> who were allowed to sit thereon: as also Triumphes were named <hi>Curules,</hi> when those that tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed were gloriously beseene in such a chaire, drawen with a chariot, for distincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Oration, wherein Captaines rode on horsebacke onely.</item>
         <label>Cyath,</label>
         <item>A small measure of liquid things: the twelfth part of <hi>Sextarius,</hi> which was much about our wine quart. So that a <hi>Cyath</hi> may go for three good spoonefuls, and answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in weight to an ounce and halfe, with the better.</item>
         <label>Cynicke Philosophers,</label>
         <item>Such as <hi>Antisthenes, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ogenes</hi> and their followers were: so named of <hi>Cynosarges,</hi> a grove or schoole without <hi>Athens,</hi> where they taught: or rather of their dogged and currish maner of biting; barking at men, in noting their lives over rudely.</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="d" type="part">
      <list>
         <head>D</head>
         <label>DEcius,</label>
         <item>A forename. For <hi>Decius,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <note place="margin">D.</note> it were the Gentile name of an house in <hi>Rome,</hi> yet grew afterwards to be a forename, as <hi>Paulus:</hi> and likewise fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>names at the first, in processe of time, came to name Families.</item>
         <label>D. Decimus,</label>
         <item>A forename to certeine Romans, as namely to <hi>Brutus</hi> surnamed <hi>Albinus,</hi> one of the conspiratours that killed <hi>Iul. Caesar.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Decade,</label>
         <item>That which conteineth tenne: as the Decades of <hi>Livie,</hi> which consist every one of tenne books.</item>
         <label>Democratie,</label>
         <item>A free State, or popular gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; wherein every citizen is capable of soveraigne Magistracy.</item>
         <label>
            <pb facs="691"/>
Desiccative,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Drying, or having the power to drie.</item>
         <label>Diatessaron,</label>
         <item>A consonance or concord in Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick, called a Fourth, where of there be foure in the Scale which compriseth fifteene strings: it answereth to the proportion, Epitritos; for it consisteth of three and one third part.</item>
         <label>Diapente,</label>
         <item>A consonance or concord in Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke, called a Five, it answereth to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion Hemiolios, or Sesquialtera: for three conteineth two and halfe; three and two make five.</item>
         <label>Diapason,</label>
         <item>a perfect consonance conteining two fourths; or made of <hi>Diatesseron</hi> and <hi>Diapente,</hi> As if it consisted of all: an Eight. It answereth to duple proportion, or <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plasion.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Disdia pason,</label>
         <item>A duple Eight; or quadruple Fourth; which was counted in old time the greatest Systema in the Musicke scale.</item>
         <label>Diastema,</label>
         <item>The intervall in the scale of Musick. Also the rest or Time, of which and of founds or notes consisteth Diatonicke Musicke.</item>
         <label>Diazeugmenon,</label>
         <item>Of disjuncts in Musicke.</item>
         <label>Diaphoretical, <hi>or</hi> Diphoretical,</label>
         <item>So is called in Physicke Excessive sweat, whereby the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits be spent, and the body much weakened and made faint, as in the disease Cardiaca.</item>
         <label>Diatonique Musicke,</label>
         <item>Keepeth a meane tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature betweene Chromaticke, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>harmoniacke: and may go for plaine song, or our Musicke.</item>
         <label>Diatonos,</label>
         <item>A note in Musicke. <hi>Diatonos Hypa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tōn,</hi> D, SOLRE. <hi>Diatonos Mesōn.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Dictatour,</label>
         <item>A soveraigne Magistrate above all others in <hi>Rome,</hi> from whom no appeale was granted, meere absolute and king-like; but that his time of rule was limited within sixe moneths ordinarily: so named, because he onely said the word and it was done; or for that he was <hi>Dictus,</hi> that is to say, nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by one of the Consuls, usually in fome time of great danger of the state, and not otherwise elected.</item>
         <label>Diesis,</label>
         <item>The quarter of a note in Musicke; or the least time or accent, G, SOL, RE, UT.</item>
         <label>Dionysius in Corinth,</label>
         <item>An usuall proverbe in <hi>Greece,</hi> against such as are upon their pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous estate, so proud and insolent, as they forget themselves and oppresse their inferiors; putting them in minde that they may have a fall as well as <hi>Dionysius,</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving beene a mighty and absolute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch of <hi>Sicily,</hi> was driven at last to teach a Grammar and Musicke schoole in <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Dithyrambs,</label>
         <item>Were songs or hymnes in the honour of <hi>Bacchus,</hi> who was surnamed <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyrambus,</hi> either because hee was borne twice, and came into this world at two dores; once out of his mother <hi>Senerleus</hi> wombe, and a second time out of his father <hi>Jupiters</hi> thigh: or else of <hi>Lythirambus,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as <hi>Pindarus</hi> writeth. For when <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> had sowed him within his thigh, at what time as he should come forth againe, he cried foorth, <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, that is, Undoe the seame, Undoe the seame. The Poets who composed such Hymnes were called Dithyrambicques, whose verses and words were darke and intricate.</item>
         <label>Divination,</label>
         <item>Soothsaying, or foretelling of future things.</item>
         <label>Dolichus,</label>
         <item>A long carriere or race, containing twelve, or (as some say) 24. Stadia.</item>
         <label>Dorian, <hi>or</hi> Doricke Musick,</label>
         <item>Was grave and so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: so called, for that the Dorians first de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised and most used it.</item>
         <label>Drachme <hi>or</hi> Dram,</label>
         <item>The eight part of an ounce. Also a peece of money valued at se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven pence halfe-penie in silver, and in gold much about a french crowne. The Romane <hi>denarius</hi> was aequivalent unto it.</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="e" type="part">
      <list>
         <head>E</head>
         <label>ECho,</label>
         <item>A resonance, or resounding of the last part of the voice or words delivered.</item>
         <label>Echo-pan,</label>
         <item>A song, of <hi>Echo</hi> supposed to be a Nymph not visible, but woonderfully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of <hi>Pan,</hi> the Heardmens god.</item>
         <label>Eclipticke,</label>
         <item>making or occasioning an eclipse.</item>
         <label>Elegi,</label>
         <item>Lamentable and dolefull ditties, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed of unequall verses, as the Hexame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Pentameter; and such be called <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiake.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Elenchs,</label>
         <item>subtile arguments devised to reproove or confute.</item>
         <label>Elotae,</label>
         <item>The common slaves that the Lacedae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monians used, and emploied in base mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries, as publicke executions, &amp;c.</item>
         <label>Elucidaries,</label>
         <item>Expositions or Declarations of things that be obscure and darke.</item>
         <label>Embrochalion,</label>
         <item>a devise that Physicians have to foment the head or any other part, with some liquor falling from aloft upon it, in maner of raine, whereupon it tooke the name.</item>
         <label>Emphaticall,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Expresse and verie significative.</item>
         <label>Empiricke Physicians,</label>
         <item>Who without regard ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="692"/>
of the cause in a disease, or the consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution and nature of the patient, goe bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to worke with those meanes and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines whereof they had experience in others, fall it out as it would.</item>
         <label>Empusa,</label>
         <item>A certeine vaine and fantasticall illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, sent by the divell, or as the Painims say, by <hi>Hecate,</hi> for to fright infortunate folke. Appeare it doth in divers formes, and seemeth to go with one legge (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it tooke the name, <hi>quasi</hi>
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>:) for one foote or legge it hath of brasse, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of an asse; and therefore it is named al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>.</item>
         <label>Encomiastical,</label>
         <item>Perteining to the praise of a thing or person.</item>
         <label>Endrome,</label>
         <item>A kinde of bickering or conflict.</item>
         <label>Endymatia,</label>
         <item>A kinde of daunce or Musicall Note.</item>
         <label>Enharmonion,</label>
         <item>one of the three generall sorts of Musicke: song of many parts, or a curious concent of sundry tunes.</item>
         <label>Enthymemes,</label>
         <item>Unperfect syllogismes, or short reasonings, when one of the premisses is not expressed, yet so understoode, as the conclusion neverthelesse is inferred.</item>
         <label>Epact,</label>
         <item>The day put to, or set in, to make the leape yeere.</item>
         <label>Ephori,</label>
         <item>Certeine Magistrates or Superinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents for the people in <hi>Sparta,</hi> in oppositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the kings, and to take downe their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall power: such as were the Tribunes of the Commons at <hi>Rome,</hi> ordeined for to abridge the Consuls absolute authoritie.</item>
         <label>Epiali,</label>
         <item>Be fevers of the Quotidian kind, that is continuall: they have an unequall distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature, both of colde and heat at once: but the heat seemeth to be milde and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle at the first: whereupon they tooke that name. These fevers also, for the same reason be called <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>.</item>
         <label>Epidemial diseases,</label>
         <item>Such as are occasioned by some common cause, and therefore spred, and take hold of all persons indifferently in a tract or city: as the pestilence.</item>
         <label>
            <hi>To</hi> Epitomize,</label>
         <item>To relate or pen a thing brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and by way of an abbreviarie.</item>
         <label>Epitritos,</label>
         <item>The proportion sesquitertion, whereby eight exceedeth sixe, namely by a third part.</item>
         <label>Etymologie,</label>
         <item>the knowledge of the origniall of words, and from whence they be derived.</item>
         <label>Eviration,</label>
         <item>Gelding, or disabling for the act of generation.</item>
         <label>Exharmonians,</label>
         <item>Discords or dissonances in Musicke.</item>
         <label>Exstasie, <hi>or</hi> Ecstasie,</label>
         <item>A traunce or transportati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the minde, occasioned by rage, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, feare, &amp;c.</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="f" type="part">
      <list>
         <head>F</head>
         <label>FLatulent,</label>
         <item>Windy, or engendring winde: as pease and beanes, be flatulent meat.</item>
         <label>Fomentations,</label>
         <item>in <hi>Physicke,</hi> be properly devises, for to be applied unto any greeved part: ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to comfort and cherish it; or to allay the paine; or else to open the pores of the skinne, and to make way for plasters and ointments to worke their effects the better. Laid to they are by the meanes of bladders, spunges, wollen clothes, or quilts and such like.</item>
         <label>Fungosity,</label>
         <item>A light and holow substance, such as wee may perceive, in spunges, mush<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romes, fusse bals, elder pith, &amp;c.</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="g" type="part">
      <list>
         <head>G</head>
         <label>GAlli,</label>
         <item>The furious priests of dame <hi>Cybele,</hi> the great mother of the gods, honored in <hi>Phrygia:</hi> It is supposed that they tooke that name of <hi>Gallus</hi> the river; the water whereof if they dranke liberally, they fell into a furious rage, and cut off their owne genetours.</item>
         <label>Graecostasis,</label>
         <item>A withdrawing gallerie or place in <hi>Rome,</hi> neere unto the Senate house <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Hostilia:</hi> where Greeks and other for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine Embassadors staide and gave atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance.</item>
         <label>Gymnastical,</label>
         <item>Belonging the publicke places of exercise, where youth was trained up to wrestling and other feates of activitie: the which places were called <hi>Gymnasia.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Gymnick games or plaies,</label>
         <item>performed or practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by those who were naked.</item>
         <label>Gymnopodia, <hi>or</hi> Gymnopaedia,</label>
         <item>a certaine daunce, that the Lacedaemonian children were trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in, barefoot; untill they proceeded to another more warlike, called <hi>Pyrrhica.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Gymnosophists,</label>
         <item>Philosophers of <hi>India,</hi> who went naked, and led beside a most austere and precise life.</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="h" type="part">
      <list>
         <head>H</head>
         <label>HAbite,</label>
         <item>In our bodies, is either the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiall constitution thereof; whereby we terme the evill habite (in Greeke) <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, whenas the bodie misliketh and thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not; and the good habite <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap> (in Greeke) when it prospereth: or els the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts; and so we say sweats, pocks, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zels,
<pb facs="692"/>
and scabs, are driven foorth to the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite of the body by strength of nature.</item>
         <label>Harmonicall Musicke,</label>
         <item>See <hi>Enharmonia.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Hemiolios,</label>
         <item>Proportion sesquialterall: contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the whole &amp; halfe; as twelve to eight.</item>
         <label>Hemisphaere,</label>
         <item>that is to say, The halfe sphaere or globe, used commonly for that part of the heaven which is in our sight.</item>
         <label>Hexameter,</label>
         <item>A verse consisting of six mesures, called feete.</item>
         <label>Hexatonos,</label>
         <item>Having six tones or six strings.</item>
         <label>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> ,</label>
         <item>The Aegyptians sacred Phi losophie, delivered not in characters and letters, but under the forme of living crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and other things engraven.</item>
         <label>Holocaust,</label>
         <item>A whole burnt sacrifice: whereas ordinarily they burnt upon the altar, onely the inwards of the beast.</item>
         <label>Homonymie,</label>
         <item>the double or manifold significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a word or sentence, which is the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of ambiguity and doubts.</item>
         <label>Horizon,</label>
         <item>That circle that determineth our sight, and divideth the one halfe of the sphaere of heaven above, from that which is under, out of our sight.</item>
         <label>Horoscope,</label>
         <item>the obseruation of the houre and time of ones nativitie, together with the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of the heavens at that very instant; and that forsooth in the East.</item>
         <label>Hypate, hypaton,</label>
         <item>Principall of principals. A base string in a Musicall instrument: or a note in the skale of Musicke, B, MI.</item>
         <label>Hypate Meson,</label>
         <item>A meane string or note in Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke: principall of meanes, E, LA, MI.</item>
         <label>Hypate,</label>
         <item>The base string in a lute or other strin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged instrument; so called, because it is sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted highest &amp; is principall. And yet it may seeme in vocall Musicke, as <hi>Lambinas</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it in <hi>Horace,</hi> to be the small treble, by that which he writeth of <hi>Tigellus,</hi> who song <hi>Iö Bacche, modò <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Voce, modò haec, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonat chordis quae quatuor ima:</hi> where by <hi>sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> he meaneth the treble, and <hi>ima</hi> the base. Also <hi>Boetius</hi> (as <hi>Erasmus</hi> upon the proverb <hi>Dis Diapason,</hi> observeth) writeth the cōtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, namely, that <hi>Hypate</hi> is the lowest or base; and <hi>Nete</hi> the highest or treble. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth <hi>Plutarch</hi> seeme to agree alwaies with himselfe in these termes.</item>
         <label>Hyperbolyaeum,</label>
         <item>A terme in Musick, belonging to their skale, &amp; appropriate to the trebles, that is to say, it signifieth Excellent or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding.</item>
         <label>Hyporchema,</label>
         <item>An hymne and dance unto <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo,</hi> performed by children with a noise of pipes before them, in the time of pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and thereupon it was also called <hi>Paean.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Hypotheticall proposuions,</label>
         <item>such as are pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with a supposition.</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="i" type="part">
      <list>
         <head>I</head>
         <label>IAmbus,</label>
         <item>A measure or foote in verse, consist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of two sillables, the former short, the other long: it is put also for the verse made thereof.</item>
         <label>Iambicke verses,</label>
         <item>be they which stand upon such feete. If of foure, they be called <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternarij:</hi> if of six, <hi>Senarij:</hi> if of eight, <hi>Octona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rij.</hi> Now for that this kinde of foote run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth very quicke, two of them together be reckoned but for one measure: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the said verses, be termed also <hi>Dime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri, Trimetri,</hi> and <hi>Tetrametri,</hi> as if they had but two, three, &amp; foure feete or measures.</item>
         <label>Icosaedron,</label>
         <item>A Geometricall solid body, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting twenty sides or faces, distinguished by their severall lines and angles.</item>
         <label>Idaeae,</label>
         <item>The formes of things setled in the divine intelligence or heavenly minde, according to which as paternes, by <hi>Platoes</hi> doctrine all things were made.</item>
         <label>Idaei Dactyli,</label>
         <item>were certaine servitours unto <hi>Cybele,</hi> bretheren all, called otherwise <hi>Cory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantes</hi> and <hi>Curetes.</hi> But whether they were Daemons, fanaticall men, or couse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning impostors, it is not agreed upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong writers: neither how many they were, or why so called. See <hi>Natalis Comes Mytholog.</hi>
         </item>
         <label/>
         <item>* But heere I must not forget to note, that in the Page 257 line 50, instead of <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>: some read <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, that is to say, of their owne fingers. <hi>Caelius Rhodig. Lect. Antiq. lib.</hi> 17. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.</item>
         <label>Identity,</label>
         <item>that is to say, The samenesse, or being the very same.</item>
         <label>Idus <hi>or</hi> Ides,</label>
         <item>Eight daies in every moneth, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived of an old word <hi>Iduo</hi> to divide, for that they commonly fall about the midst of the moneth, namely upon the thirteene or fifteene daies, according to <hi>Horace: Idus tibisunt agendae; Quidies mensem veneris marinae, findit Aprilem.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>
            <hi>To</hi> Incarnate,</label>
         <item>that is to say, to make flesh, or helpe that the flesh may grow: and so cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine salves or medicines be called incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natives.</item>
         <label>
            <hi>To</hi> Incrassate,</label>
         <item>that is to say, to make thicke and grose.</item>
         <label>Intercular daies,</label>
         <item>that is to say, set or put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene, as the odde daie in the leape yeare.</item>
         <label>
            <pb facs="693"/>
Interstice,</label>
         <item>that is to say, The space or distance betweene.</item>
         <label>Inumbration,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Shadowing.</item>
         <label>Ionicke Musicke,</label>
         <item>Gallant and galliardlike: plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant or delectable.</item>
         <label>Isonomie,</label>
         <item>An aequability of government under the same lawes, indifferently ministred to al persons: As also an aequality of right which all men doe enjoy in one state: And an ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall distribution unto all persons, not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Arithmeticall, but Geometri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call proportion.</item>
         <label>Isthmus,</label>
         <item>A narrow banke of lande lying be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene two seas, as namely, that of <hi>Corinth</hi> and <hi>Peloponnesus:</hi> and by analogie thereto, all such are so called. By a metaphor also, other things that serve as partitions, be so termed.</item>
         <label>Isthmick games,</label>
         <item>Were those which were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed neere <hi>Corinth</hi> upon the saide <hi>Isth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus:</hi> instituted as some thinke, by <hi>Theseus,</hi> to the honour of <hi>Melicerta,</hi> otherwise na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Palaemon</hi> and <hi>Portamnus.</hi>
         </item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="k" type="part">
      <list>
         <head>K</head>
         <label>KAlends,</label>
         <item>Was among the Romans the first day of the Moneth, or the very day of the new Moone, which commonly did concurre and fall out together: <hi>Neomenia</hi> in Greeke. But so called <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, that is to say, a <hi>Calando,</hi> because the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> then to call the people unto the court <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labra,</hi> and there to pronounce unto them how many daies there were to the <hi>Nones,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="l" type="part">
      <list>
         <head>L</head>
         <label>LUcius,</label>
         <item>A forename to divers families <note place="margin">L.</note> in <hi>Rome.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>
            <hi>To</hi> Laconize,</label>
         <item>that is to say, To imitate the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedaemonians, either in short and pithy speech, or in hard life.</item>
         <label>Lassitude,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Wearinesse.</item>
         <label>Later all motions,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Moovings to a side; for distinction of those that be circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, mounting upright or descending downward.</item>
         <label>Libations, <hi>or</hi> Libaments,</label>
         <item>Assaies of sacrifices, or offrings to the gods; especially of liquid things, as wine.</item>
         <label>Lichanos,</label>
         <item>A string of an instrument or note in Musicke: Index: In an instrument: the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finger string or third: in the GAM-UT, or skale, D, SOL, RE, and C, SOL, RE, UT, according to the addition of Hypatōn or Mesōn.</item>
         <label>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> ,</label>
         <item>Any publicke function: but more particularly for the ministerie in the church, about divine service and worship of God.</item>
         <label>Lydius Modus,</label>
         <item>
            <hi>Lydian</hi> Musicke, dolefull and lamentable.</item>
         <label>Lyceum, <hi>or</hi> Lycium,</label>
         <item>A famous place neere to <hi>Athens,</hi> wherein <hi>Aristotle</hi> taught Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophie. His followers, because they confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and disputed walking in this <hi>Lyceum,</hi> were called <hi>Peripatetici.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Lyrical poets,</label>
         <item>Such as composed ditties and songs to be sung unto the Lute or such like stringed instruments.</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="m" type="part">
      <list>
         <head>M</head>
         <label>MArcus,</label>
         <item>
            <hi>M'. Manius,</hi> with the note <note place="margin">M'.</note> of apostrophus, Forenames of sundry houses in <hi>Rome.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Medimnus,</label>
         <item>A measure conteining sixe <hi>Modij</hi> Romane; and may goe with us for a bushel and three pecks of London measure, or thereabout.</item>
         <label>Megarian questions,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Such as were propounded and debated among the Philosophers <hi>Megarenses:</hi> for there was a sect of them, taking name of the place; like as the Cyrenaiks: for <hi>Euclides</hi> and <hi>Stilpo</hi> were Megarians.</item>
         <label>Mercenarie,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Hirelings, or such as take wages.</item>
         <label>Mese,</label>
         <item>The middle string or meane: it endeth on Eight, and beginneth the other in the skale of Musicke. In the GAM- UT, A, LA, MI, RE.</item>
         <label>Metamorphosed,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Transmuted and changed.</item>
         <label>Metaphysicks,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Supernaturall. The first and principall part of Philosophy in the intention, although it be last attei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto, as unto which all other know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge serveth, and is to be referred. The Philosophers Theologie or Divinity, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of intelligible and visible things.</item>
         <label>Meteors,</label>
         <item>Be impressions gathered in the aire above; as thunder, lightning, blasing stars, and such like.</item>
         <label>Mimi,</label>
         <item>Were actours upon the stage, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting ridiculously the speech and gesture of others; jesters and vices in a play: Also certeine Poemes or plaies, more lascivious than Comoedies, and fuller of obscoene wantonnesse. The authors of such were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Minographi,</hi> as <hi>Laberius.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Mina, <hi>or</hi> Mna,</label>
         <item>A weight, answering to <hi>Libra,</hi> that is to say, a pound. Also coine valued at so much.</item>
         <label>
            <pb facs="693"/>
Minervall,</label>
         <item>The stipend or wages paid unto a Schoole-master for the institution and teaching of scholars; derived of <hi>Minerva,</hi> the president of learning and good arts.</item>
         <label>Mixolidian tune,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Lamentable and pitifull: meet for Tragoedies.</item>
         <label>Monarchie,</label>
         <item>The absolute government of a state, by one prince. Roialty.</item>
         <label>Mordicative,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Biting and sting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: as mustard seed, Pelletary of Spaine.</item>
         <label>Muscles,</label>
         <item>The brawny or fleshy parts of the bodie.</item>
         <label>Mythologie,</label>
         <item>A fabulous Narration: or the delivery of matters by way of fables and tales.</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="n" type="part">
      <list>
         <head>N</head>
         <label>NEmeia,</label>
         <item>Certaine solemne games institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the honour of <hi>Hercules</hi> for kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a lion in the forest <hi>Nemea;</hi> or as some thinke, in the remembrance of <hi>Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morus</hi> a yong babe killed by a serpent.</item>
         <label>Nete,</label>
         <item>The lowest or last string in an instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, answering to the treble, and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site to Hypate. Some take it cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, for the base. See Hypate: and <hi>Erasmus</hi> upon the Adage, Dis diapason.</item>
         <label>Nete Diezeugmenon,</label>
         <item>A treble string or note of musicke, last of disjuncts. E, LA, MI.</item>
         <label>Nete Hyperbolaean,</label>
         <item>the last of trebles: A, LA Mi, RE.</item>
         <label>Nete Synnemmenon <hi>or</hi> Syzeugmenon,</label>
         <item>The last of the conjuncts: a string or note in mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke, D, La, SOL.</item>
         <label>Niglary,</label>
         <item>Are thought to be notes or tunes in musicke, powerfull to encourage. See <hi>Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liast in Aristoph.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Nones,</label>
         <item>Were certaine daies in the moneth: so called, because they began evermore the ninth day before the Ides, honored by the Romans both for the birth day of king <hi>Servius,</hi> and also for the chasing out of the kings: for otherwise it was not festivall; according as <hi>Ovid</hi> writeth, <hi>Nonarum tute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la deo caret.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Novenary</label>
         <item>number, that is to say, Nine.</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="o" type="part">
      <list>
         <head>O</head>
         <label>OBolus,</label>
         <item>A certeine weight: halfe a scriptul or scrupul, the sixt part of a drachme or somewhat better in <hi>Greece:</hi> also a small coine, currant for eight chalci, which in silver is a peny and saithing.</item>
         <label>Octaedra,</label>
         <item>A Geometricall body of eight ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, sides or faces, distinct by their angles.</item>
         <label>Oeconomie,</label>
         <item>House-governement: or the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministration and dispose of houshold af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires.</item>
         <label>Oligarchi,</label>
         <item>A state of governement, wherein a few, and those properly of the welthier sort, rule the common wealth.</item>
         <label>Olympiades,</label>
         <item>were the space of those foure yeeres, according to which the Grecians reckoned the time: as the Romans did by their lustra; and Christians, by the yeere of our lord.</item>
         <label>Olympicke <hi>or</hi> Olympian</label>
         <item>games, were instituted first by <hi>Hercules</hi> in the honour of <hi>Jupiter Olymptus;</hi> or of <hi>Pelops,</hi> as some thinke: and celebrated with a solemne affluence and concourse from all parts of <hi>Greece</hi> every foure yeeres complet once, betweene <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sa</hi> and <hi>Elis,</hi> in a plaine called <hi>Olympta:</hi> where also stood the temple of <hi>Jupiter Olympius.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Oracle,</label>
         <item>An answere or sentence given by the devil, or the supposed gods of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> : also the place where such answeres were delivered.</item>
         <label>Organe,</label>
         <item>An Instrument. And our body is said to be Organicall, because the soule performeth her operations by the parts thereof as instruments.</item>
         <label>Orthios Nomos,</label>
         <item>In musicke a tune or song ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding high and incentive; which when <hi>Timotheus</hi> sung before king <hi>Alexander,</hi> he was so moved and incited, that presently he leapt foorth and tooke armes.</item>
         <label>Orthographi,</label>
         <item>That part of Grammar which teacheth the feat of writing truely: also, true writing it selfe.</item>
         <label>Ostracisme,</label>
         <item>In <hi>Athens</hi> A condemnation and confining for ten yeeres space of that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, who was thought to grow greater in wealth, reputation and opinion of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue or otherwise, than the democratic or free popular estate would well beare, ordained first by <hi>Clisthenes:</hi> who for his labour was himselfe first condemned. It tooke the name of <hi>Ostratos,</hi> a shell or little potsherd, wherein his name was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, whom any of the people was in that behalfe offended with; and meant to expell the city. And if the major part of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple noted one in this maner, he was sent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. It differed from banishment, because no person lost by Ostracisme goods or lands: againe the time was limited, and the certaine place set downe, where he should abide. In this sort <hi>Aristides</hi> the just, vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant <hi>Themistocles</hi> and other good men were driven out.</item>
         <label>
            <pb facs="694"/>
Oxyrynchos,</label>
         <item>A fish, so called, of a long sharpe beake or snout that it hath.</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="p" type="part">
      <list>
         <head>P</head>
         <label>PAean</label>
         <item>The name of <hi>Apollo.</hi> An hymne also to <hi>Apollo</hi> and <hi>Diana</hi> for to avert plague, warre, or any calamity: <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, which signifieth to strike or to heale, or of <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, to stay or make to cease.</item>
         <label>Paederastî,</label>
         <item>The loving of yong boies: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly taken in the ill part, as signifying the abuse of them against kinde.</item>
         <label>Paegnta,</label>
         <item>Pleasant poems or merry ditties for delight.</item>
         <label>Paeon, <hi>or</hi> Paeon,</label>
         <item>The name of <hi>Apollo;</hi> and of a metricall foot in verse, of which Paeans are composed: and it is duple, to wit of foure sillables, either the first long, and the other three short; or the first short and the other three long: it is named also Paean: also an epithet of <hi>Apollo.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>
            <hi>To</hi> Palliat,</label>
         <item>that is to say, To cover or hide: and so such cures be called Palliative, which search not to the roote or cause of the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease, but give a shew onely of a perfect cure; as when a sore is healed up aloft, and festereth underneath. And thus sweet pomanders doe palliat a stinking breath, occasioned by a corrupt stomacke or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eased lungs and such like.</item>
         <label>P. Publius,</label>
         <item>A forename to some Romane fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies.</item>
         <label>Panathenaea,</label>
         <item>A solemnity held at <hi>Athens:</hi> wherein the whole city men, women and children were assembled. And such games, dances and plaies as were then exhibited; or what orations were then and there made, they called <hi>Panathenaik.</hi> Of two sorts these solemnities were: once every yeere; and once every fifth yeere, which were called the greater.</item>
         <label>Pancratium,</label>
         <item>
            <hi>Plutarch</hi> taketh for an exercise of activity or mixt game of fist-fight and wrestling. Howbeit other writers will have it to be an exercise of wrestling, wherein one indevoureth with hand and foot, and by all parts of his body to foile his adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary: as also the practise of all the five feats of activity, which is called Pentathlon and Quinquertium: to wit, <note n="*">Or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the dart.</note> buffetting, wrest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, running leaping and coiting,</item>
         <label>Pancratiast,</label>
         <item>One that is skilfull and professed in the said Pancration.</item>
         <label>Paramese,</label>
         <item>Next the meane or middle string. A note in musicke: B, PA, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> , MI, in space.</item>
         <label>Paranete Hyperbolaean,</label>
         <item>A treble string or note in musicke: the last save one of trebles: G, SOL, RE, UT.</item>
         <label>Panegyricke,</label>
         <item>Feasts, games, faires, marts, pompes, shewes, or any such solemnities, performed or exhibited, before the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall assembly of a whole nation: such as were the <hi>Olympicke, Pythicke, Isthmicke,</hi> and <hi>Nemian</hi> games in <hi>Greece.</hi> Orations likewise to the praise of any person at such an as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly, be called <hi>Panegyricall.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Paradox,</label>
         <item>A strange or admirable opinion held against the common conceit of men: such as the Stoicks mainteined.</item>
         <label>Periode,</label>
         <item>A cercuit or compasse certeinly kept: as we may observe in the course of Sunne and Moone, and in the revolution of times and seasons: in some agues also and other sicknesses, that keepe a just time of their returne, called therefore Periodicall. Also the traine of a full sentence to the end, and the very end it selfe, is named a Periode.</item>
         <label>Paranete <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> ,</label>
         <item>A treble string or note in Musicke: the last save one of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncts: D, LA, SOL, RE.</item>
         <label>Paranete Synemmenon <hi>or</hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> :</label>
         <item>C, SOL, FA.</item>
         <label>Parhypate hypatōn,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Subprinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall of principals. A string or note in Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke: C, FA, UT.</item>
         <label>Parhypate Mesōn,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Subprincipall of meanes: a string or note in Musicke: F, FA, UT.</item>
         <label>Peripateticks,</label>
         <item>A sect of Philosophers, the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of <hi>Aristotle:</hi> See <hi>Liceum.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Phiditia,</label>
         <item>Were publicke hals in Lacedaemon, where all sorts of citizens, rich and poore, one with another met to eat and drinke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, at the publicke charges and had ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall parts allowed.</item>
         <label>Philippicks,</label>
         <item>Were invective orations made by <hi>Demosthenes</hi> the Oratour, against <hi>Philip</hi> king of <hi>Macedony,</hi> for the liberty of <hi>Greece.</hi> And heereupon all invectives may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Philippicke,</hi> as those were of <hi>M. Tullius Cicero</hi> against <hi>Antonie.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Phrygius Modus,</label>
         <item>Phrygian tune or musicke, otherwise called <hi>Barbarian;</hi> mooving to devotion, used in sacrifices and religious worship of the gods: for so some interpret <hi>Entheon</hi> in <hi>Lucianus:</hi> others take it for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>censing and stirring to furie.</item>
         <label>
            <hi>To</hi> Pinguifie,</label>
         <item>that is to say, To make fat.</item>
         <label>Plethoricall plight,</label>
         <item>that is to say, That state of the body, which being full of bloud and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther humours, needeth evacuation: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the said fulnesse be, <hi>ad vasa,</hi> as the
<pb facs="694"/>
Physicians say, when the said bloud and humours be otherwise commendable, but offending onely in quality: or, <hi>ad vires,</hi> when the same be distempered and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive to nature, and therefore would be ridde away; which state is also called <hi>Cacochy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Polemarchus,</label>
         <item>One of the nine Archontes or head magistrates in the popular state of <hi>Athens,</hi> chosen as the rest yeerely. Who notwithstanding that he reteined the name of <hi>Polemarchus,</hi> that is to say, a Captaine generall in the field, such as in the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne government of the kings, were em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied in warres and martiall service under them: yet it appeareth that they had civill jurisdiction, and ministred justice, between citizens &amp; aliens, of whō there were many in <hi>Athens;</hi> like as the Archon for the time being, was judge for the citizens onely. Assistants he had twaine, named <hi>Paredri,</hi> who sat in commission with him.</item>
         <label>Poliorceles,</label>
         <item>A surname of <hi>Demetrius,</hi> a valiant king of <hi>Macedonie,</hi> and sonne of king <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigonus:</hi> which addition was given unto him for beseeging of so many cities.</item>
         <label>Polypragmon,</label>
         <item>A curious busie body, who lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to meddle in many matters.</item>
         <label>Pores,</label>
         <item>The little holes of the skinne, through which sweat passeth, and fumes breath foorth.</item>
         <label>Positions,</label>
         <item>Such sentences or opinions as are held in disputation.</item>
         <label>Praetour,</label>
         <item>One of the superiour Magistrates of <hi>Rome.</hi> In the citie he ruled as L. chiefe Justice, and exercised civill jurisdiction: Abroad in the province, he commanded as L. Governour, Deputie, or Lieutenant Generall: In the field, he was L. General, as well as the Consull. At first, the name of Consul, Praetor, and Judge was all one.</item>
         <label>Primices,</label>
         <item>First fruits.</item>
         <label>Problemes,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Questions propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for to be discussed.</item>
         <label>Procatar cticke causes of sicknesse,</label>
         <item>Be such as are evident and comming from without, which yeeld occasion of disease, but do not main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine the same: as the heat of the Sunne, causing headach or the ague.</item>
         <label>Prognosticke,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Foreknowing and foreshewing: as the signes in a disease which foresignifie death or recovery.</item>
         <label>Proscription,</label>
         <item>an outlawing of persons in <hi>Rome,</hi> with confiscation of their goods, and sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the same in portsale: and depriving them of publicke protection.</item>
         <label>Prostambomene,</label>
         <item>A, RE, a terme in Musicke, signifying (a String or Note) taken in or to: for otherwise of two Heptachords, there would not arise 15. to admit a place in the middle for Mese, that is to say, the Meane, to take part of two Eights, or two Diapasons.</item>
         <label>Prosodia,</label>
         <item>A certeine hymne or tune thereto, in maner of supplication to the gods, and namely to <hi>Apollo</hi> and <hi>Diana,</hi> at what time as a sacrifice was to be brought and presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before the altar.</item>
         <label>Proteleia,</label>
         <item>The sacrifice before mariage: as also the gifts that ceremoniously went before.</item>
         <label>Prytaneum,</label>
         <item>A stately place within the castell of <hi>Athens,</hi> wherein was a court held for judgement in certeine causes: where also they who had done the Common-wealth singular service, were allowed their diet at the cities charges, which was accounted the greatest honour that could be.</item>
         <label>Parhypate Hypaton,</label>
         <item>A base string or note in musicke, Subprincipall of principals: C, FA, UT,</item>
         <label>Parhypate Meson,</label>
         <item>Subprincipall of meanes, a meane string or note, F, FA, UT,</item>
         <label>Pyladion,</label>
         <item>In musicke a kinde of note bearing the name of Pylades, a Poet comicall and skilfull master in musicke.</item>
         <label>Pyramidal,</label>
         <item>Formed like unto the Pyramis, which is a geometricall body, solid, broad beneath, and rising up one all sides which be flat and plaine, unto a sharpe point like a steeple. It taketh the name of <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, that is to say, Fire, which naturally hath that fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure.</item>
         <label>Pythia,</label>
         <item>or <hi>Phoebas,</hi> The priestresse or prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisse, who pronounced the answeres at the oracle of <hi>Apollo Pythius</hi> at <hi>Delphos:</hi> who tooke that name of <hi>Python</hi> there slaine by him and lying putrified: or of <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, that is to say, To aske and demand; for the resort of people thither to be resolved by him of their doubts.</item>
         <label>Pythick,</label>
         <item>or <hi>Pythian</hi> games, were celebrated to the honour of <hi>Apollo Pythius,</hi> neere the city <hi>Delphos,</hi> with greate solemnity: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted first by <hi>Diomedes</hi> and yeerely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed.</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="q" type="part">
      <list>
         <head>Q</head>
         <label>QUintus,</label>
         <item>A fore name to divers Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes. <note place="margin">Q.</note>
         </item>
         <label>Quaternary,</label>
         <item>the number of Foure: called like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, so highly celebrated
<pb facs="695"/>
by the Pythagoreans, comprising in it the proportion Epitritos, whereof ariseth the musicall harmonie <note n="*">
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap> .</note> Diatessaron; for it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth three and the third part of three: also Diplasion, because it comprehendeth two duple, whence ariseth the musicke dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pason: and Disdiapason, being dubled, which is an Eight &amp; the perfect harmony, according to the proverbe <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap> also in that, it containeth all numbers within it; for, one, two, three and foure arise to Ten, beyond which we cannot ascend but by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition of former numbers.</item>
         <label>Quaestors,</label>
         <item>inferior officers in <hi>Rome</hi> in maner of Treasurers: whose charge was to receive and lay out the cities mony and revenewes of state: of which sort, there were Urbani, for the city it selfe: Provinciales, for the provinces: and Castrenses, for the campe and their warres.</item>
         <label>Quinquertium,</label>
         <item>named in Greeke, Pentathlon. Five exercises or feats of activity among the greeks practised at their solemne games: namely <note n="*">Some put in stead hereof <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> .</note> launcing the dart, throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the coit, running a race, wrestling and leaping. See Pancratium.</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="r" type="part">
      <list>
         <head>R</head>
         <label>RAdicall moisture:</label>
         <item>Is the substantiall hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midity in living bodies; which is so u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited with naturall heat, that the one main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth the other, and both preserve life.</item>
         <label>
            <hi>To</hi> Rarifie,</label>
         <item>that is to say, To make more sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, light and thin.</item>
         <label>Rectdivation,</label>
         <item>Is a relapse or falling backe into a sicknesse, which was in the way of recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and commonly is more dangerous than the former: <hi>Recidiva pejor radice.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Regents,</label>
         <item>Professours in the liberall sciences and in Philosophi: a tearme usuall in the Universities.</item>
         <label>Reverberation,</label>
         <item>that is to say, A smiting or dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving backe.</item>
         <label>Rhapsodie,</label>
         <item>A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> together or conjoining of those Poems and verses especially hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icke or hexametre, which before were loose and scattered: such as were those of <hi>Homer,</hi> when they were reduced into one entier body of <hi>Ilias</hi> and <hi>Odyssca.</hi> Those Poets also, who recite or pronounce such verses, were tearmed <hi>Rhapsodi.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Rivals <hi>and</hi> Corrivals,</label>
         <item>Counter-suiters: or those who make love together, unto one and the same woman.</item>
         <label>
            <hi>To</hi> Ruminate,</label>
         <item>that is to say, To ponder and consider, or revolve a thing in the minde: a borrowed speech from beasts that chew the cudde.</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="s" type="part">
      <list>
         <head>S</head>
         <label>SAtyri,</label>
         <item>Woodwoses, or monstrous crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures with tailes, yet resembling in some sort, partly men &amp; women, &amp; in part goats; given much to venery and lasciviousnesse, whereupon they had that name: also to scurrill, frumping and jibing, for which they were also called <hi>Sileni,</hi> especially when they grew aged; supposed by the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall heardmen to be the fairies or gods (I would not else) of the woods.</item>
         <label>Satyrae <hi>or</hi> Satyrs</label>
         <item>were certaine Poems recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in place of <hi>Comoedia vetus,</hi> detesting and reprooving the misdemeanours of people and their vices: at first by way of myrth and jest, not sharpely and after a bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting maner, to the shame, disgrace or hurt of any person; such were they that <hi>Horace</hi> composed; howbeit they grew afterward to more diracity and licentiousnesse, noting in broad tearmes without respect all leaud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and sparing no degree; as those were of <hi>Juvenales</hi> and <hi>Persius</hi> penning. Latine poets onely, handled this argument, both in the one sort and the other.</item>
         <label>Scammonie,</label>
         <item>A medicinable plant, and the juice thereof issuing out of the roote when it is wounded or cut: it purgeth yellow choler strongly. The same juice or liquor being concrete or thickned and withall corrected is called <hi>Dacrydium;</hi> as one would say, the teares destilling from the roote: and is the same which the unlearned Apothecaries call <hi>Diagridium;</hi> as if forsooth it were some compound like their <hi>Diaphaenicon.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Scelet,</label>
         <item>The dead body of a man artificially dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or tanned, for to be kept and seene a long time. It is taken also for a dead car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casse of man or woman, represented with the bones onely, and ligaments.</item>
         <label>Scepticke philosophers,</label>
         <item>Who descended from <hi>Pyrrho;</hi> so called, for that they would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider of all matters in question, but deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of none: and in this respect they were more precise than the Academicks.</item>
         <label>Scolia,</label>
         <item>Were certeine songs and carols sung at feasts.</item>
         <label>Scrutinie,</label>
         <item>A search, and properly a perusing of suffrages or voices, at elections or judiciall courts, for the triallor passing of any cause.</item>
         <label>Secundine,</label>
         <item>The skinne that enwrappeth the childe or yoong thing in the wombe: in
<pb facs="695"/>
women the after-birth or later-birth; in beasts the heame.</item>
         <label>Senarie,</label>
         <item>The number of sixe, also a kinde of verse. See <hi>Iambus.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Septimane,</label>
         <item>A weeke or seven-night. Also what soever falleth out upon the seventh daie, moneth, yeere, &amp;c. as <hi>Septimanae foeturae,</hi> in <hi>Arnobius,</hi> for children borne at the seventh moneth after conception; and <hi>Septimanae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ,</hi> Agues returning with their fits every seventh day.
<table>
               <row>
                  <cell>Serg.</cell>
                  <cell>Sergius</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi>Forenames to certeine fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies in</hi> Rome.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Serv.</cell>
                  <cell>Servius</cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Sex.</cell>
                  <cell>Sextus.</cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
         </item>
         <label>Sesquialteral,</label>
         <item>A proportion, by which is ment that which conteineth the whole and halfe againe, as 6. to 4. 12. to 8. It is also named <hi>Hemiolios.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Sesqui-tertian,</label>
         <item>A proportion, whereby is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood as much as comprehendeth the whole, and one third part, as 12. to 9. and the same is called <hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> .</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Sesqui-octave,</label>
         <item>That which compriseth the whole and one 8 part; as 9 to 8, 18 to 16: in Greeke <hi>Eptogdoos,</hi> or <hi>Epogdoos.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Soloecisme,</label>
         <item>Incongruity of speech, or defect in the purity thereof. It arose of those who being Athenians borne, and dwelling in <hi>Soli,</hi> a city in <hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ,</hi> spake not pure Attick, but mixt with the Solians language.</item>
         <label>Solstice,</label>
         <item>The Sunne-steed, which is twice in the yeere, in Iune &amp; December, when the Sunne seemeth to stand for a while, at the very point of the Tropicks, either going from us, or comming toward us; as if hee returned from the end of his race, North and South.</item>
         <label>Sp. Spurius,</label>
         <item>A forename to some Romanes.</item>
         <label>Spasmes,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Crampes, or painfull pluckings of the muskles and sinewes. See <hi>Convulsions</hi> And Spasmaticke, full of such or given thereto.</item>
         <label>Sphaeres,</label>
         <item>The circles or globs, of the seven pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets: as also the compasse of the heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all.</item>
         <label>Spissitude,</label>
         <item>Thicknesse or dimnesse.</item>
         <label>Spondaeus,</label>
         <item>An hymne sung at sacrifices and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bations. Also a metricall foot in verse, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting of two long syllables: whereof prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally such hymnes or songs were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed.</item>
         <label>Stadium,</label>
         <item>A race or space of ground, contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning 625. foote, whereof eight make a mile, consisting of a thousand paces, which are five thousand foot, reckoning five foot for a pace; for so much commonly a man taketh at once in his pace, that is to say, in his stepping forward, and remooving one foot before another.</item>
         <label>Stoicks,</label>
         <item>Certeine Philosophers, whose first master was <hi>Zeno,</hi> who taught in a certeine spatious gallery at <hi>Athens,</hi> called Poecile, for the varietie of pictures wherewith <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignotus</hi> the excellent painter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> it: And for that a gallery in Greeke is called <hi>Stoa,</hi> therefore those Philosophers who taught and disputed therein, tooke that name of Stoicks.</item>
         <label>Strophes,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Conversions or tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings. In Comoedies and tragoedies, when the <hi>Chorus</hi> first speaketh unto the actours; and then turneth to the spectators, and pronounceth certeine Jambicks. In the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearsing of Lyricall verses, when the Poet one while turneth to the right hand, and another while to the left, and so reciteth certeine verses: which thereupon be called <hi>Strophae,</hi> and <hi>Antistrophae.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Stypticke,</label>
         <item>being such things, as by a certeine harsh taste, doe shew that they be astrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent: as the fruit called <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> , and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum especially, which thereupon is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <hi>Stypteria.</hi> And Stypticitie is such a qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</item>
         <label>Subitarie,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Of a sudden, without premeditation.</item>
         <label>Subterranean,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Under the earth.</item>
         <label>Superficies,</label>
         <item>The upper face or outside of any thing. In Geometrie it is that, which is made of lines set together, like as a line of prickes united.</item>
         <label>Superfoetation,</label>
         <item>Conception upon concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
         <label>Suppuration,</label>
         <item>A gathering to matter or attir: as in biles, impostumes, inflammations and such like.</item>
         <label>Sycophants,</label>
         <item>Tale-bearers, false promoters, or slanderous informers, and such as upon small occasions brought men into trouble. The name arose upon this occasion, that whereas in <hi>Athens</hi> there was an act, That none should transport figges out of the territory <hi>Attica;</hi> such as gave informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of those that contrarie to this law con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veied figges into other parts, were tearmed Sycophants: for that <hi>Sycon</hi> in Greeke, is a figge.</item>
         <label>Syllogismes,</label>
         <item>Be certeine formes of arguing: when upon two propositions graunted, which are called Premisses, there is infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a third, namely a Conclusion.</item>
         <label>
            <hi>To</hi> Symbolize,</label>
         <item>that is, By certeine outward
<pb facs="696"/>
signes, to signifie some hidden things: Thus an eie symbolizeth vigilancy.</item>
         <label>Sympathie,</label>
         <item>that is to say, A fellow feeling, as is betweene the head and stomacke in our bodies: also the agreement and naturall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie in divers senslesse things, as between iron and the load-stone.</item>
         <label>Symphonie,</label>
         <item>Concent and harmony, properly in vocall Musicke.</item>
         <label>Symposiarch,</label>
         <item>The master of a feast. The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes called him <hi>Rex,</hi> that is to saie, a king.</item>
         <label>Symptomes,</label>
         <item>Be accidents accompanying sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; as headach, the ague: stitch, short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of winde, spitting blood, cough and ague; the plurisie.</item>
         <label>Synemmenon, <hi>or</hi> Synezeugmenon,</label>
         <item>A tearme of art in musicke, signifying strings or notes conjunct.</item>
         <label>Syntaxis,</label>
         <item>The construction and coherence of words and parts of speech by concord and regiment.</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="t" type="part">
      <list>
         <head>T</head>
         <label>TItus,</label>
         <item>A forename to many houses of <note place="margin">T.</note> the Romans.</item>
         <label>Talent</label>
         <item>
            <hi>Atticke</hi> (as well ponderall which was weighed, as numerall or nummarie, counted in mony) was of two sortes: The lesse, of sixty pound <hi>Attick,</hi> and every one of them consisted of one hnndred <hi>Drach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae.</hi> If <hi>mina</hi> then, be three pound two shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings six pence starling in silver; this talent amounteth to one hundred eighty seven pound ten shillings of our english mony. The greater, or simply the great talent, is eighty <hi>minae</hi> and hath the proportion Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritos, or sesquitertian to the lesse: so that it commeth to two hundred and fifty pound starling.</item>
         <label>Tautologies,</label>
         <item>Vaine repetitions of the same things oftentimes.</item>
         <label>Ternarie,</label>
         <item>The number of three.</item>
         <label>Terpandrios,</label>
         <item>A severall tune in musicke, or a song that <hi>Terpander devised.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Tetrachord,</label>
         <item>An instrument in old time of foure strings: but now, it is taken for every fourth in the scale of Musicke or GAM, UT. whereof there be foure in fifteene strings: reckoning Mese, to end one octave and begin another.</item>
         <label>Tetrarch,</label>
         <item>A potentate or ruler over the fourth part of a country.</item>
         <label>Theatre,</label>
         <item>A shew place built with seates in maner of an halfe circle, for to behold games, plaies and pastimes; which if both ends meet round, is called an <hi>Amphitheatre.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Theorems,</label>
         <item>Principles or rules in any science.</item>
         <label>Theriacal Trochisks,</label>
         <item>Trosches made of vipers flesh, to enter into the composition <hi>Theri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aca,</hi> that is to say, <hi>Triacle.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Thesmothelae,</label>
         <item>Were six of the nine Archontes or chiefe rulers in <hi>Athens</hi> during their free popular estate. They had civill jurisdiction and sat as judges in certeine causes.</item>
         <label>Thesmothesium,</label>
         <item>seemeth to be the court or commission of the said <hi>Thesmothelae.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Topicks,</label>
         <item>That part of logicke which treateth of the invention of arguments, which are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Topi,</hi> as if they were places, out of which a man might redily have sufficient reasons to argue and dispute with <hi>Pro &amp; contra.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Tribunes of the Commons,</label>
         <item>Certeine officers or magistrates at <hi>Rome,</hi> as provosts and protectours of the cominaltie to restraine and keepe downe the excessive power of the consuls and nobility. Chosen they were and confirmed by the generall oth of the people, whereby they were <hi>Sacrosan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti,</hi> that is to say, Inviolable, &amp; no violence might be done to their persons. A nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive voice they had and power of inhibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on called <hi>Intercessio;</hi> whereby they might crosse and stop all proceedings of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate or any superiour magistrate (save on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Dictator) even of the very consuls, whom in some case they might command. They resembled much the Ephory in <hi>Sparta.</hi>
         </item>
         <label>Trite Diezeugmenon,</label>
         <item>The third of disjuncts a string or note in the scale of musicke C, SOL, FA, UT.</item>
         <label>Trite Hyperbolaean,</label>
         <item>A treble string; the third of Exceeding or treble; F, FA, UT.</item>
         <label>Trite Synnemmenon,</label>
         <item>or <hi>Syzeugmenon,</hi> The third of the Disjuncts, a string or note in musicke, B, FA, B, MI in rule.</item>
         <label>Trivtall,</label>
         <item>Common and ordinary as is the high way, stale and of no account.</item>
         <label>Trochaeans,</label>
         <item>A metricall foot in verse, consist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of two sillables; the former long, and the other short.</item>
         <label>Tropaees <hi>or</hi> Trophaees,</label>
         <item>Were monuments in memoriall of victory, erected in marble, brasse, or in default thereof with heaps of stone or piles of wood, in the very place where any Generall had vanquished his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimies and put them to flight; whereupon they tooke that name: for that <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap> in greeke signifieth, Turning back and flight.</item>
         <label>Tropes,</label>
         <item>In speech the using of wordes other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise than in their primitive and naturall
<pb facs="696"/>
signification; which many times giveth a grace to the sentence.</item>
         <label>Tutelar,</label>
         <item>Protectours and defenders. So were the gods or goddesses among the Painims called, whom they beleeved to have a spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall charge of any city or country.</item>
         <label>A Type,</label>
         <item>that is to say, A figure under which is signified some other thing.</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="v" type="part">
      <list>
         <head>V</head>
         <label>VEstall virgins,</label>
         <item>were certeine Nunnes or Votaries, instituted first by <hi>Numa Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilius</hi> king of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the honour of <hi>Vesta</hi> the goddesse: whose charge was to keepe the sacred fire that it went not foorth. Chosen they were betweene the yeeres of six and tenne of their age: and were enjoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned virginitie for thirtie yeeres: after which time it was lawfull for them to be married: But if in the meane while they committed fornication, buried they were quicke.</item>
         <label>Vnction,</label>
         <item>that is to say, Anointing.</item>
      </list>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>