<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115242_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19893</idno>
           <idno type="STC">632</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115242</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine deuout considerations of frequenting the blessed sacrament: written by the reuerent Father Fuluius Androtius of the Societie of Iesus. With sundrie other preceptes and rules of direction, composed for the benefit of such as seeke to attaine to the perfection of vertue. Firste written in Italian: after turned into Latine: and now translated into English</title>
                 <author>Androzzi, Fulvio</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Auroi (Ouroy), Pierre</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 296, 16 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="68"/>
   <pb n="121" facs="68"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou hast here curteous Reader diuers most profitable remedies, against sundrie temptations vvhere vvith our ghostly enimie doth daylie lye in vvaite to afflict, to tempt, and to ouercome vs: and especially those persons, vvho contemning the allurements of the vvorlde and the flesh, haue deuoted them selues to a spiritual life, placinge their chiefe endeauours, to subdue their appeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp; to conquer their ovvne passions. Read them therefore vvith great attention, &amp; no othervvise then if they vvere mest soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne remedies for such diseases, as afflict thy body both night and day. For if vve consider hovv much more pretious our sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les are then our bodies, vve shal see good reason, that vve ought most carefully to seeke out such preseruatiues, as may both cure our present infirmities, and also pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent such, as may in time befal vs. Wherein if thou finde any thinge profitable to thy soule, giue the only thankes and praise to almightie God, and pray for him, vvho for the loue of his diuine maiestie and good of
<pb n="122" facs="69"/> soules, bought vvith the pretious blood of our Sauiour Christ, hath collected this treatise. To vvhom vvith the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Holie Ghost be all honor and glorie, vvorlde vvithout end. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>