<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the high and mightie Prince CHARLES, Prince of Wales, Duke of Cornewall and Yorke, and Earle of Chester, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Powel, Daniel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115024_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09895</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20159</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115024</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the high and mightie Prince CHARLES, Prince of Wales, Duke of Cornewall and Yorke, and Earle of Chester, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Powel, Daniel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The loue of VVales to their soueraigne prince : expressed in a true relation of the solemnity held at Ludlow in the countie of Salop, vpon the fourth of Nouember last past. Anno Domini. 1616. Being the day of the creation of the high and mighty Charles, Prince of Wales, and Earle of Chester, in his Maiesties palace of White-Hall</title>
                 <author>Powel, Daniel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the high and mightie Prince <hi>CHARLES, Prince of</hi> Wales, Duke of <hi>Cornewall</hi> and <hi>Yorke,</hi> and Earle <hi>of</hi> Chester, &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most Illustrious and Peerelesse Prince,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which your <hi>Highnesse</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth in the Sunne rising, how in displaying his bright Beames, hee dispells all mistie vapours, and comforts, by the vigorous influence thereof, the feeble sences of inferior bodies: the same might easily haue bin discerned in the faces of all his Maiesties subiects (who formerly drouping through the Fates destinie) are at last cheered and reuiued by the happy <hi>Rise</hi> of your <hi>Highnes</hi> into the <hi>Princely</hi> throne of <hi>Wales,</hi> where you were no sooner enthronized by Gods graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous prouidence, by lawfull authoritie, and by the loue
<pb facs="3"/>of all his Maiesties liege people (who are the Princes principall Supporters) but it was a wonder to see of a sudden, what a sweet spring, what a happie change, what a powerfull renouation was wrought in the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall spirits of his Maiesties sayd subiects, who daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced for ioy, filled the Aire with shouts and acclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in all quarters, but specially in your proper Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian of <hi>Ludlow,</hi> the beautifull seate of his Maiesties chiefe Castle and Counsell of <hi>Wales,</hi> where my selfe (being not altogether an idle Actor, nor vnwilling Spectator) was so rauished with the fullnesse of ioy, which I saw in the hearts of the people, as I wished my selfe then to bee transformed into the shape of the sweete Nightingale, which was counted <hi>Vox prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereà nihil,</hi> that with Fames golden wings I might eccho out to the eares of all men, the loyall affection of the <hi>Brittish Nation</hi> to their royall <hi>Prince,</hi> and the <hi>royall fauours</hi> of their <hi>gracious Prince</hi> intended to them, whose very Name caused such a surplusage of mirth and admiration, as my Penne is not able to decipher the halfe of the reioycing which they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed, nor were they any way able with all their indeuors, to testifie the full measure of Gladnes which their hearts conceiued: If then in the divulging of this plaine Narration, I eclipse much of the glorious substance of the Shew, I hope your <hi>Highnesse</hi> in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding my loyall intention, will be induced to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don my daring presumption. And what is now the period of all our Petitions, but that Heauen may adde constancie to the felicitie of your <hi>Triumph,</hi> and then
<pb facs="3"/>we doubt not that our <hi>Ioyes</hi> shall euer waxe olde, but whiles your <hi>Highnesse</hi> continues to accept of the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Title of <hi>Prince of Wales,</hi> his Maiesties people will still haue new matter of reioycing in your graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Gouernment and powerfull protection: Thus in most lowly manner vpon my knee, crauing pardon for this my presumption, hoping your <hi>Excellencie</hi> will not discusse <hi>Nec quis, nec quid, sed quo animo,</hi> neyther the meanenesse of my selfe, nor the smallnesse of the matter, but onely the minde and heart of your poore <hi>Vassall,</hi> I rest praying for all blessings external, internall, and eternall to your <hi>Highnesse.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From <hi>Ludlow</hi>
         <date>this last of Nouember <hi>1616.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Highnesse deuoted in all obseruance</hi> Daniel Powel.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>