<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Author his Preface to the Lords and Mrs. of the Church of Rome.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115135_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07763</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18142</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115135</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Author his Preface to the Lords and Mrs. of the Church of Rome.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Fovvre bookes, of the institution, vse and doctrine of the holy sacrament of the Eucharist in the old Church : As likevvise, hovv, vvhen, and by what degrees the masse is brought in, in place thereof. By my Lord Philip of Mornai, Lord of Plessis-Marli; councellour to the King in his councell of estate, captaine of fiftie men at armes at the Kings paie, gouernour of his towne and castle of Samur, ouerseer of his house and crowne of Nauarre</title>
                 <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Bing, Isaac.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bing, Isaac.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Thomas 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ponsonby, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                            <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                            <distributor>Ponsonby, William</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>38, 484, 8 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Author his Preface to the Lords and <hi>M<seg rend="sup">rs.</seg> of the Church of Rome.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Apostle Saint Paul said to the Israelites his brethren according to the flesh,</hi> I speake the truth in Christ,
<note place="margin">Rom. 9</note> I lie not, my conscience beareth me witnesse by the holy Ghost, that I haue great heauines of hart, that I could wish my self accursed, &amp; to be separated from Christ for your sakes. <hi>This that great Apostle, notwithstanding who would not know any thing for all, but Christ, who desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to be separated from all the world, yea and separated in himselfe, to bee with Christ: and therefore verilie for some exceeding great and important cause: as, for to see them drawne out of the wayes of destruction, into the state of saluation: that is to say, coupled and vnited to Christ: And therefore it is most euident that hee iudged them lost, in that estate wherein they were, in asmuch as they coulde not bee founde in Christ, and so without saluation, for that they were without Christs. They neuerthelesse (sayth hee)</hi> to whome belonged the adoption, and the glorie, and the couenants, and the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the law, and the diuine seruice, and the promises: of whome came the fathers, and of whom according to the flesh came Christ? <hi>And yet notwithstanding all this, he letteth not to declare them</hi> to be of Israel, and yet not Israel: to be the seed of Abraham, yet notwithstanding not all children, because <hi>(saith he)</hi> the worde of God cannot fall away, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>May I here my masters be so bolde, as to say the like vnto you? In respect of my selfe verily I may not. I desire your saluation with a great affection: I wish it heartilie, with the hazard of this my life: yea I will say in a good conscience, as the saide Apostle saide vnto Agrippa:</hi> That it might please God to make you all such like as <hi>I</hi> my selfe, except these bondes: <hi>except those afflictions, whereunto this profession is subiect. For what is more, belongeth not to any man besides the Apostle, in whome the exceeding measure of knowledge begot an exceeding measure of loue towards God, and charitie towards his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, which as we cannot imitate in effect: so neither must we in worde: besides that this hyperbolicall kinde of speech, can hardly fit vs. But rather in respect of you, I dare be bold to say more: for the couenants and ordinances of the lawe, and the diuine seruice, and the promises, were giuen vnto you long ago: but not vnto you alone, but not to you more then others. And many fathers are sprung vp amongst you, and you it may be discended of them, according to the flesh: but yet for all this, the worde of God cannot fall away or perish, no not although Christ himselfe, who is God blessed aboue all things, should be descended of you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the flesh. That word verily which giueth vs to vnderstande, that there must fall out an apostacie in the Church, that the man of sinne, the sonne of perdition, should sit in the Temple of God, causing himselfe to be adored therein as God. And seeing you cleaue vnto him vnder the shadow of this See, of this pretended discent, I dare bee bolde to say vnto you freely with the Apostle: Deceiue not your selues with thinking your selues to be the children
<pb facs="4"/>of Abraham, for you are not children at all,</hi> such as are of the faith, <hi>and not of the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Galat. 3.7. Rom. 9.8.</note> are Abrahams children, for they are the children of the promise, they ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily are reputed for the seede.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>There is question then about this faith,
<note place="margin">In controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies we must haue recourse to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> and euerie man saith that he hath it. To know of what side Christ is, and euery man betaketh himselfe to him as his ayde, and thereupon all Christendome liueth in suspence and doubt, or in trouble. But, my brethren, let vs not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue men: Men, saith our Lord himselfe, who know not of their owne vnderstanding, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from whence he commeth, or whether he goeth: The spirits of men, saith the spirit of God, which are not able to comprehend his wayes. In a Sea so vnknowne to man, in these gulfes so perillous, we cannot attaine to the deliuering of any sure and certaine speech from other where then God himselfe: from the father, who hath spoken from heauen, shewed vs the sonne,
<note place="margin">Matth. 17.5. Iohn. 5.3 9. Psal. 19. 2. Tim. 3.</note> and said vnto vs,</hi> heare him: <hi>from the son, who crieth vnto vs in the midst of the Temple in the heate of the Pharisies, and all these great doctors their disputations,</hi> Search you the Scriptures diligently: <hi>and from the holie Ghost, who hath said to vs,</hi> They cause the eyes to see: they giue vnderstanding to children: <hi>by the Apostles,</hi> they are inspired of God, they make the man of God, <hi>euen the Euangelist and teacher himselfe,</hi> instructed vnto euerie good worke, and wise vnto saluation.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Our fathers (say some vnto you) beleeued as well, liued as well, whereto serue these alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations? Verily if you vnderstand this of your carnall fathers, then what other thing doe you say,
<note place="margin">S. Bern. Epi. 91</note> besides that which the Iewes said to our Lord? or which the Turkes or Iewes may not yet say vnto vs? How farre better, saith Saint Bernard, speaking of the reformation necessarie in the Church:</hi> Let them be cast behinde both me and you, which say, we will not liue better then our fathers. <hi>If of the spirituall, as of those that haue begotten vs to Christ: then who are they, but the Apostles, and the holie fathers that followed them? And what say we herein, but by their mouthes? And who is there to leade vs more from customes, to the lawe, from traditions to the holie Scriptures? Irenaeus saith,</hi> The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles preached the Gospel,
<note place="margin">Iren. l. 3. c. 1. &amp; 11. con. h. ret. Tradiderunt. Iust. Mart in Dialog. cum Tryphon. &amp; in exposit. fid.</note> and afterward by the will of God deliuered it vs in the Scriptures, that so it might be the foundation and pillar of our faith. <hi>Iustinus Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr;</hi> We must fixe our faith vpon God, and his onlie instructions: not vpon mans Traditions: we must haue recourse to the Scriptures, to the ende we may finde assurednesse in all things, &amp;c. That Dauid, that the Euangelists, that the Epistles of the Apostles doe teach vs,
<note place="margin">Tert. con. Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mog. Cum Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis senti.</note> &amp;c. <hi>Tertullian:</hi> I doe not receiue or admit of that which thou bringest of thine owne, without any Scripture. If thou bee an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolicall writer, be furnished with the doctrine of the Apostles, &amp;c. Bring backe the heretikes to the Scriptures, and so <hi>(saieth hee)</hi> they will not bee able to maintaine themselues. <hi>What would he haue said then at this day of our pretended Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, who abhorre nothing more, then to bee drawne backe to the Scriptures? Verilie and without all doubt, the same which he saith of these heretikes:</hi> Heretici sunt lucifugae Scripturarum, Like Owles they flie from the light of the Scriptures. Wherefore if that which thou speakest be not written, beware of that <hi>Vae,</hi> that curse, which is pronounced by the spirit of God, against them which adde vnto the Scriptures. <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cypr. de laps. &amp; in Epist. 74.</note> Doe the Martyrs commaund any thing to be done? But what if it bee not written in the law of the Lord. &amp;c? That <hi>(saith he)</hi> must bee done which is written, for so God appointed Iosua: wee must haue good regard to see if it bee written in the Gospel, in the Epistles of the Apostles, or their acts: for if it be, then such holy traditions must be obserued and kept. <hi>Traditions, as we see, contained in the Scriptures: for so did the fathers vse this worde, and not for all that which may be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined
<pb facs="4"/>in mans braine, prouided that it be of continuance and toleration. Origen,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Orig. in Ierem. &amp; in 25. in Matth.</note> Wee must call the holie Scriptures to witnesse: without these witnesses, the sence and expositions which we giue them, worke no beleefe. VVhatsoeuer the golde bee which is without the Temple, yet it is not sanctified, and as litle that sense which is besides the Scripture. <hi>Athanasius:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Athan. contr. Idol. ad Ioui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian. in 2. orat. contra Arrios. de interpret. Psalm in Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopsi. Theodor. l. 1. Socrat. l. 1. &amp; 5 Basi. de ver. fid. in Mora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. &amp; Regu. 26. &amp; 80</note> The holy Scriptures are sufficient of thēselues for the demonstrating of the truth. The stones wherewith the heretikes are to be stoned, are fetcht from hence: they are the Mistresses of the true faith, the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chors and props of our, &amp;c. <hi>And this is the cause why in the disputation against the Arrians, Constantine the Emperor breaking the array vnto the Councell of Nice, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not any other weapons.</hi> The Euangelicall bookes <hi>(saith he)</hi> as also those of the Apostles and Prophets, doe teach vs euidently, whatsoeuer wee must beleeue. Let vs gather from thence the deciding of our controuersies. <hi>Saint Basil,</hi> It is a most euident signe of infidelitie and pride, to go about to bring in any vnwritten thing: for the Lord hath said, My sheepe heare my voyce, and follow not the voice of any other, &amp;c. Whatsoeuer we doe or speake, must bee confirmed from thence, for the beleefe of the good, &amp; cōfusion of the wicked, Euery faithful man hath this proper to him, not to adde any thing thereto, neither yet to ordaine any new thing: for whatsoeuer it is, that is besides the Scripture, is not of faith,
<note place="margin">Ambros. de vocat. Gent. l. 2. c. 3. &amp; in lib de Parad. c. 12.</note> and therefore is sinne. <hi>Saint Ambrose:</hi> VVhere the Scriptures speake not, who shal speake? VVe must adde nothing to the commaundement, howe good soeuer it be: who so addeth thereto any thing of his owne, argueth it of imperfection, &amp;c. <hi>Saint Hierome,</hi> The Church of Christ, which dwelleth well,
<note place="margin">Hieronym. in Mich. l. 1. in ps. 98. in Ezeen. c. 3. in Agg. c. 1 in Mat. c. 23. in Esa. c. 8.</note> and all ouer the world, &amp;c, hath her townes, the law, the Prophets, the Gospel, the Apostles. It goeth not beyond her limits, that is to say, the holy Scriptures. VVhatsoeuer we say, must be auouched from thence. The Scriptures are our true meate, and our true drinke: of this wood is the house of wisdome built: whatsoeuer is not autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized by them, should be contemptible to vs, &amp; is likewise striken with the sword of God, who so is desirous to deliuer himself out of any doubt, let him go thither: but let him know that tendeth any other course, that he shall not attaine vnto the light of the truth, which he shal grope after in darknes. To be short <hi>(saith he)</hi> what soeuer is said since the apostles times, is cut off, it beareth no authority with it, &amp;c.
<note place="margin">Hieronym. in Psal. 87.</note> how holie &amp; prudent soeuer the Authors thereof might be. <hi>S. August.</hi> The Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall Scripture is set vpon a throne, and euerie faithfull vnderstanding must be subiect thereunto. If we, yea if an Angel from heauen,
<note place="margin">August. contr. Faust. l. 11. c. 5. &amp; cont. lit ras. Petil. 6 lib. 2. contr. Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist. c. 6. tract. 2 in Ep. S. Iohan</note> do teach any thing more then that which is contained in the Scriptures, the Law, or the Gospel, let him be accursed. In our cōtrouersies, let vs bring this ballance, these gold waights, as out of the closet of God, to iudge that of weight from that which is light. Let vs there iudge of errors, for God hath placed in the Scriptures a bright and cleare shining firmament, to discouer &amp; confute them. <hi>The Councels: for saith he vnto the Arrians.</hi> I alledge not vnto thee the Councell of Nice,
<note place="margin">Cont. Maxim. Episc. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian. l. 3. c. 14. De Ciuit. Dei. l. 11. c. 1. Epist. 166. De vnit. eccles. c. 1. 3. 4. 5. 6. 16.</note> neither therefore doe thou alledge vnto me the councel of Rimini, but let vs trie the maistry by the Scriptures, which both you and I my selfe doe well approue, &amp;c. <hi>The Church likewise: for,</hi> The citie of God doth beleeue in the Scriptures, and by them is faith conceiued. In the Scriptures <hi>(saith he)</hi> we haue learned Christ, therein also haue we learned to know the Church: we haue knowne the head, and therefore cannot misknow the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die thereof. VVhether we, or the Donatists be the Church, the Scriptures alone will teach and instruct vs. <hi>Saint Chrysostome,</hi> The ignoraunce of the Scriptures
<pb facs="5"/>hath begotten heresies, &amp;c. Though the dead should liue again, or an Angel des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend frō heauen,
<note place="margin">Chrysost. in hom. de Laza.</note> yet we must principally and before them beleeue the Scripture. The Angels are but seruants &amp; ministring spirits, but the Scripture is the Lord &amp; maister.
<note place="margin">In Epi. ad Gal. hom. 1. In 5. Mat. hom. 43. &amp; 49. In 1. ad Thess. homil. 7. In 2. ad Corin. homil. 33. In Psal. 5.95.142.147.</note> In at this gate doe both the sheepe and shepheard enter, they driue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way heretikes, who so entreth not by them is a theefe. The Scripture is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, it is inclosed therein, and fastned thereunto. The gate of this kingdome, is the vnderstanding of the Scriptures. Setting our course and sailing after them, wee haue the sonne of God, for our patron and protector: they are our rule and our squire. As the light is vnto the eies, so is the law of God vnto our spirits, without it all our senses halt. An heire doth willingly possesse himselfe of his fathers will and testament, and so should we no lesse of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the furniture and prouision for our warre against sinne and Sathan him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, &amp;c. In which <hi>saith he in another place,</hi> wee must either denie Christ, or blot out the Scriptures, or else become the obedient seruants of the Scriptures. <hi>And if he said this then against the heretikes of his time, then much more against Antichrist to come, and vpon farre more iust causes and considerations.</hi> For <hi>saith he,</hi> when this cursed heresie, the armie of Antichrist shall possesse the Churches, there will not bee found any proofe or maner of helpe to trie and know Christendome by, but the holy Scriptures. By them alone a man shall know where and who shall bee the true church. In this confusion and hurlie burlie, there will bee no want of bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and blasing abrode of miracles: for euen alreadie the counterfet Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans haue most: but and if a man looke any other way then to the Scriptures, hee cannot but bee offended, perish, and fall into the abhomination of desolation, which shall bee in the holie places of the Church. And therefore our sauiour Christ knowing afore hand, that such confusion should follow in the latter daies, will that we flie vnto the Scriptures. <hi>And now also this is the cause, why according to the aduertisement of Saint Chrysostome, we call you thereunto, we which thus alledge and contend, with the hazard of our liues, and for the working of your saluation and our owne, that that Antichrist is alreadie come, and seated in your Church: and all this according to the Scriptures, and by the Scriptures.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Hereto you replie, If his Scriptures alone take place in this controuersie, then what shall become of so many goodly traditions?
<note place="margin">What becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth them of the traditions 1. Cor. 11.</note> What shall become of our Church? Verely if you speake of diuine traditions such as whereof Saint Paule saith,</hi> I haue receiued of the Lord, Quod &amp; tradidi vobis, whatsoeuer I haue deliuered vnto you, <hi>of those which haue their foundation in the Scriptures, and whereof Irenaeus saith vnto vs;</hi> Looke what Gospel the Apostles preached, the same they deliuered vnto vs, tradiderunt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit, nobis, in the Scriptures. <hi>Of them saith Saint Cyprian,</hi> which descend from the authoritie of the Gospel,
<note place="margin">Cypri. in Epi. 74. ad Pomp.</note> and the writing of the Apostles. <hi>Verelie we will be readie to defend them, if you will beleeue vs, with common armour: we shall be both the one and the other, quit and freed from all our paines and trouble, for the Scriptures and they wil mutuallie acknowledge one another, as doe the little riuers, and their heads or springs: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing touched with the touchstone of the Scripture, they will hold their value. But if by Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions you meane mans inuentions, and doctrines that are without, and out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: then we tell you that Christ hath giuen definitiue sentence thereof:</hi> In vaine do you serue me,
<note place="margin">Matth. 15 9</note> teaching for doctrines the commaundements of men. <hi>And thus spake he to the Pharisies, who wholy rested themselues in the Church, &amp; in the Sorbone of that time, which said as you do of yours at Trent, that it was no lesse grieuous an offence to commit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst,
<pb facs="5"/>or omit any thing contained in their traditions,
<note place="margin">In Thal. ord 4. tract. 4. dist. 10 Esay. 29, 13.</note> then and if such commission or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission had beene in respect of any point of the law it selfe. And there is great like lihoode that it is come vpon you, which was forespoken by the Prophets:</hi> They haue serued mee according to the ordinances of men,
<note place="margin">Ierem. 8, 8.</note> and therefore wisedome shall perish from their wise men: They haue cast behind them the worde of the Lord, and there is no wisdome in them. <hi>But if you suspect the soundnesse of the Scripture,
<note place="margin">Iust. in Tryph</note> or rather the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightnesse of God in his owne cause, then let vs heare the fathers. Iustine:</hi> We must giue credite to God and his ordinances alone, and not vnto humane traditions. <hi>And that he ruleth them according to the Scriptures, appeareth by that which he said before;</hi> That Dauid, that the Euangelists, that the Apostles doe teach vs, &amp;c.
<note place="margin">Cyp. in Epi. 74</note>
      <hi>Saint Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian,</hi> If it be commaunded in the Gospel, if it be contained in the Epistles or acts of the Apostles, let vs obserue it as diuine and holie. <hi>But if it be not there, then what followeth but the contrarie? Saint Basil:</hi> VVe must learne the Scriptures,
<note place="margin">Basil. regul. 95</note> as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that which is to be practised in them, as well to replenish our spirit with pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as to leaue of to accustome humane constitutions. <hi>Saint Ierome:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hiero. in Esas</note> It is no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell <hi>(saith he speaking of the Iewes,)</hi> if you follow your traditions, seeing that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie country goeth to seeke counsaile at their Idols: but God verely hath giuen vs his scriptures, and darknesse shall ouerwhelme you if you follow them not. <hi>As also vnto Christians, for euen in his time, saith he, it was come to the lees.</hi>
      <note place="margin">In. Matth. 23.</note> VVo be vnto you wretched Christians, to whom the sinnes of the Pharisies are translated and come, euen that damnable tradition of theirs, &amp;c. wee swallow downe against the commaundement of God the things that are great, and hunt after the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of religion, in the small and little ones, &amp;c. <hi>And once for all:</hi> The sworde,
<note place="margin">Ad Laetam.</note>
      <hi>saith he,</hi> of the Lord striketh at all those doctrines, which are found bearing the shewe of Apostolicall traditions, without the authoritie and testimonie of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. <hi>And this is the verie thing whereof Saint Augustine so greatly complained him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe in his time, that in the Church euery thing was full of presumption,
<note place="margin">
            <hi>S.</hi> August. in Epi. ad Iouin. In S. Ioha. tract. 96.97.</note> and preiudicate opinion, that contrarie to the expresse worde of Christ, the yoke of Christians was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more heauie and greeuous, then that of the Iewes: That men made lesse conscience of the law of God, then of the least humane ordinances, or rather fansies. All this, or the most part thereof, comming from heretikes, and certaine Apocripha bookes,</hi> vnder the shadow, <hi>(saith he)</hi> of this worde, From the Lord, I haue yet many things to say, insomuch as that there is not the veriest foole that is, that dareth not to abuse the same: <hi>A place that some obiect against vs euen vnto this day about the same matter.</hi> But <hi>(saith he)</hi> when the Lord hath kept any thing hidden from vs, who is he that is so vaine, as to goe about to gesse at it, or so rash and foole-hardie as to take vpon him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueale it. <hi>And this is the cause why Saint Bernard, wearie of those insupportable traditions,
<note place="margin">Bern. Epist. 91 ad Abba. Suis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioni congreg.</note> said,</hi> I desire with all my hart to present my selfe as a partie in that Councel, wherin traditiōs are not obstinately defended, nor suspersticiously obserued: but rather the good and perfect will of God, with all humilitie and diligence searched after and sought for. <hi>And againe:</hi>
      <note place="margin">De precepto &amp; dispensat.</note> If there be any such as charitie hath beene the inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of, it is iust that by the same charitie they bee ceased and giuen ouer, if it bee so found expedient. <hi>Againe,</hi> The precepts which are of the ordinances of God, are necessarie, but those which are of humane constitution, arbitrarie, and at dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, &amp;c. <hi>And in deed the Ecclesiasticall historie doth witnesse vnto vs, that the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent fathers did leaue such things, as were meere obseruations, indifferent both vnto whole Churches, and particular persons, not inforcing any thing, but what was of the pure and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled
<pb facs="6"/>commaundement of God, as is to be read in Socrates, Nicephorus, &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Can not the Church then ordaine any thing?
<note place="margin">Socrates. Niceph. l. 12. c 14. Wherein, or how far the authority of the Church stretcheth.</note> And wherein shall the authoritie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of consist? Nay let vs not feare that it hath ouer little to doe. It is not a small thing, in the blindnesse wherewith man is blinded, and in the darknesse of this worlde, to keepe it selfe from straying and wandring out of the way of life, to keepe it selfe from loosing the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie light, through the sight of the eyes, and to guide it selfe and others by the same. And would to God it would haue contented it selfe to haue knowne this onely, and to haue beene ignorant in all the rest. Where as hauing toucht the forbidden tree, and hauing transgressed this worde,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Deute. 4. &amp; 12</note> Cursed be they which adde thereunto, <hi>shee hath opened her eyes to these false and deceyuing fiers, but shut them at the light, and so consequentlie lost her puritie, loyaltie, and innocencie; and leauing the truth of God, is further become left vnto her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The ancient fathers verily,
<note place="margin">The Fathers made faith the limits of the Church, and the Scriptures the bounds &amp; limits of faith. Colos. 2.8. 1. Cor. 4.6. Iohn 8.13. Not by succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion. Iren. l. 3. con:. heres. c. 11. &amp; l. 4. c. 43. &amp; 44. Tertul. de pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>script. &amp; de pudicit. Id verius, quod prius. Tertul. de virg. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>land. Con. Praxeam. Tertul. de pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>script. Cypr. Ep. 55. De lapsis. In tract de simplicit. pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tif. &amp; in ep. 74. Gregor. Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anz. in orat. habit ad lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem S. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanas. &amp; cont. Arrian. <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </note> haue not thought it any thing dishonoured, when they tyed it to the obedience of her Spouse, for they bounded it by faith, and faith by the Scriptures. And it would haue beene on the contrarie, a verie strange doctrine vnto them, that it shoulde haue spoken or heard any other language then her owne, seeing it is said vnto her by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle;</hi> See that none spoile you through Philosophie, or vaine deceitfulnesse, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the traditions of men. <hi>Againe,</hi> Learne of vs not to be wise aboue that which is written. <hi>And in vs, saith the Apostle, that is to say, by our example. And by her Spouse himselfe.</hi> If you abide in my worde, you shall be truly my disciples. <hi>Irenaeus saith;</hi> The Gospel is the pillar and foundation of the Church. It behoueth it to flie from all those, which flie from and forsake the principal succession, and cleaue vnto thē that keepe the doctrine of the Apostles. <hi>Tertul.</hi> The Church is knowne to be apostolical, not by nuber, not by succession of Bishops, but by the consan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinitie of doctrine. <hi>And this doctrine again.</hi> In this <hi>(saith he)</hi> in that the most anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entis most true, &amp; that is most ancient, which was from the beginning: and that which is from the beginning, is that which is frō the Apostles: from the Apostles <hi>(saith he)</hi> who left the Scriptures for vs, vpon whom are come the last ages: the Scriptures, by which the truth is defended, and not by tradition or custome. For how <hi>(saith he)</hi> could a man be able to speake of the things of faith, but by the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of faith? <hi>Saint Cyprian;</hi> Those are the Church <hi>(saith he)</hi> which dwell in the house of God. <hi>But how?</hi> Verily <hi>(saith he)</hi> who so is separated &amp; diuided from the Gospel, the same is not ioyned to the Church: for this is all one <hi>(saith he)</hi> after the maner, whereby Antichrist was brought in, vnder the name of Christ, by coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfetting things likely, thereby subtilly to frustrate the truth: where as it had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooued him to haue returned to the originall of truth, &amp; haue hasted back to the spring-head, to see at what place the pipes conueying the water vnto vs, were broken, &amp; by this meanes to haue lent his eare vnto the doctrine of the heauenly Master. For <hi>saith Nazianzene vnto the Arrians;</hi> The church is not defined by mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude; if they haue the people, we haue the faith; if they haue the golde and sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, we haue the true doctrine; succession must be valued by pietie, and not by Sea, or seate. Who so retaineth the same doctrine of faith, hee possesseth the same Sea: as he that retaineth the contrarie in the same Sea, is to be helde as an enemy. <hi>Because, saith Saint Chrysostome;</hi> The Church consisteth not in walles, but in faith: so that where faith is, there the Church is; where faith is not, there the Church is not. This is the true Ierusalem, whose foundations are placed vpon the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of the Scriptures. <hi>As also, (saith he)</hi> he goeth not out from the Church, that
<pb facs="6"/>goeth out from the bodie, but rather he that forsaketh the spirit, the foundation of the ecclesiasticall truth. We then <hi>(saith he)</hi> are gone out from them, in respect of the place, but they frō vs in respect of faith: we haue left with them the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the walles; but they haue left with vs the foundations of the Scriptures. <hi>Saint Ambrose;</hi> Christ alone is he whom no man ought to forsake, or change a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: to whom it is by good right said, Lord, to whom shall we go? thou hast the wordes of life. It is then giuen vs in charge aboue all things, to seeke out the faith of the Church, in which if Christ dwell, howe that then wee must make choise thereof, <hi>(namely for our habitation:)</hi> but if wee finde therein either an vnfaithfull people, or an hereticall teacher, that spoileth the dwelling, such Synagogue is to be auoided. And if, to be briefe, a Church forsake the faith, it behooueth vs to forsake and abandon it, &amp;c. <hi>And he yeeldeth a reason:</hi> Christ <hi>(saith he)</hi> is the rocke:
<note place="margin">Petra, non Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus. S. Ambr. l. 1 de paenit. c. 9.</note> the foundation of the Church, that is faith: if thou be in the rocke, thou art also in the church. <hi>But to the end we may not take one rocke for another,</hi> Know <hi>(saith he)</hi> that they which haue not Peters faith, can neither haue Peters portion and inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. <hi>Saint Ierome expounding the Creede,</hi> He hath not said, I beleeue in the holie catholike church; but I beleeue the holie church. The holie church is that which keepeth the faith of Christ, in the integritie and soundnesse thereof. It consisteth not of walles, but vpon the veritie of doctrine. VVhere faith is, there is it also, and there it was at such time as heretikes possessed all these churches.
<note place="margin">In Psal. 133.</note> VVouldst thou enter into this church, and that by the right way?
<note place="margin">In Psal. 5.</note> It is the reading of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Do thou, O Lord, so lay out and fit my way, as that I may not fall, or take offence in these Scriptures, seeing that by them I desire to enter into thy church. Yea <hi>(saith he)</hi> these Scriptures they are the kingdome of God himselfe.
<note place="margin">In <hi>S.</hi> Mat c. 21.</note> And when it is said, that the Lord hath translated the kingdom of heauen from the Iewes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, it is as much as to say, that he hath taken the Scriptures from them, to giue them vnto vs. In them <hi>(saith Saint Augustine)</hi> we finde Christ, in them wee are to seeke and search for the Church: in them, and by them, it is shewed vnto vs.
<note place="margin">Aug de vnit. Eccles.</note> And let vs not once imagine that we haue and hold the church, because we are in that wherein Ambrosius, or Optatus haue beene before vs: no nor yet because there are miracles wrought therein: for euen our Lord himselfe woulde that his disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples should be confirmed by the Scriptures, more then by any other meanes, and of that nature are the titles, precepts, and foundations of our cause.
<note place="margin">Cont. Petil. l. 3. c. 6. &amp; in Psalm. 69.</note> If then <hi>(saith he)</hi> there be any question, either of Christ, or of the church, or of any thing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer, that belongeth either to life, or faith, cursed bee hee that goeth out of the Scriptures. To the ende that thou maist not be deceiued, and that no man may cause thee to take him for Christ, that is not Christ, &amp; that for the church, which should not be the church, hearken vnto the voice of the shepheard; he hath she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed himselfe vnto thee, he hath shewed thee the church,
<note place="margin">In Ioh. ser. 131</note> My sheepe heare my voyce, &amp;c. The church is the house of God, but it is not God: wee beleeue the church, but we beleeue not in the church: It is the mother,
<note place="margin">In Epist. Ioh. tract. 3. In Psal. 103. Obpubilatur Epist. 48. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rm. 237. de Temp. ad Lucernam. Ber. in conuer. S. Paul. ser. 1.</note> but the two testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are her teates; from them we must sucke the milke of all the mysteries of our saluation. The Bishops may erre, there haue beene of them authours, both of schismes and heresies. The church in like maner is sometimes eclipsed, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with wet and tempestuous weather. The surest course is to make the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures our looking-glasse, as also for vs to walke in the torch-light of the scriptures. O Lord our good God <hi>(said Saint Bernard)</hi> such as seeme to holde the Primacie
<pb facs="7"/>in the church,
<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Cant. ser. 76</note> are the formost &amp; most forward to persecute thee. It is not inough for such as should be our guard and watchmen, to giue ouer their care of protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and vigilancie, except they further worke our spoile. At the least <hi>(saith he else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where)</hi> let him abound in his sense &amp; vnderstanding that will,
<note place="margin">Epist. 77.</note> but as for vs I could wish that they would let vs abound in the sense of the Scriptures.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>In the meane time,
<note place="margin">Durand. appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat mensuram fidei in prefat. Sentent. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas regulam intel ectus in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> ad Tim. cap. 6 lect. 1. Scot. mensur. Theol. in l. 1. Sent. q. 1 Gerson, regulā fid, de cōmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic. sub vtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que.</note> against these Scriptures, the law of the Church, the measure of faith; the rule and bridle of all maner of vnderstanding: I speake according to the Schoolemen themselues, Thomas, Durand, Scotus, Gerson, &amp;c. These miserable Doctors and teachers either of this world, or of the Prince of this world, enemies of the true light, children of darknesse, seeing they please themselues so greatly therein, doe not cease to furnish vs with ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peales, being imployed euer and anon, more in making of such, then of any other bookes. So that if we had nothing else against them, but that we might iustly suspect them of vnsounde dealing, seeing the auncient fathers of the Church did alwayes make their appeales vnto them, against the heretikes: and that in such sort, as that when they once perceiued them to come within the bounds of their iurisdiction, they held themselues victorers in their cause.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The holie Scripture, say they to vs, is not sufficient. And what other sufficiencie doe wee looke for therein,
<note place="margin">The scripture sufficient,</note> but to possesse God, who is sufficient of himself, euen for al maner of thinges? or what other, to be briefe, but to come to saluation? But and if thou wilt not beleeue the Apostle, who telleth thee, that</hi> the holy Scriptures are able to make thee wise vnto saluation, by faith which is in Christ, that is, the man of God: <hi>the Euangelist, the teacher of others:
<note place="margin">Iohn 5 39. Iohn 20.31.</note> at the least beleeue the sonne of God, who sendeth vs so expressely to the Scriptures:</hi> Because <hi>(saith he)</hi> that we haue life in them. <hi>And hast thou them to seeke and search for thine owne saluation? The Lord commaundeth thee to search them diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in them thou hast life. Dost thou labour and seeke how to teach it others? They are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to teach, conuince, correct and instruct. By them the sonne of God, the eternall word, did teach his disciples Hast thou to deale against heretikes? By the verie same hee stopte the mouthes of the Pharisies, and confounded the Sadduces, who did not admit of any mo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties then one. The heretikes cannot keepe their holde before them: yea they cannot possiblie defend themselues, otherwise then by refusing them:</hi> No sooner are they drawne there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>(saith Tertullian)</hi> but they are confounded, whether Ebionites, Hermogenists, or Marcionites, &amp;c. <hi>Yea, and if the controuersie should bee against the diuell himselfe, we know that from thence the Lord put him to silence; that he cōfuted him in all his schoole points,
<note place="margin">Apocal.</note> and sent him backe againe to the bottomlesse pit of hell: how much more the sonne perdition, for the ouercomming and discomfiting of whom, there are not any other armor or weapons spoken of? As he that must be ouerthrowne with the breath of his mouth, and beaten downe by the powerfulnesse of his Scriptures? wherefore the Scripture hauing beene of such sufficiencie in those dayes, both for the children of God, and against his aduersaries, where shall it sithence haue lost that his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>sufficiencie? Or who shall not rather suspect that we are become ouer sufficient, that is to say, spoyled with presumption? That we accuse it of insufficiencie, because our pretended and deuised sufficiencies are not found therein? And againe, if it were so much, at such times as the Church had no more but the olde Testament, both vnto saluation and condemnation: what shall we say of the times succeeding, and those of the present,
<note place="margin">According to the Fathers. Iren cont hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. l. 2 c. 47.</note> accompanied with the accomplishment of that in the person of Christ, and made more cleare by the new? And verilie the fathers also haue carefully kept themselues from this point, rather to be tearmed infidelitie, then errour or heresie. Irenaeus saith,</hi> We knowe verie well that the Scriptures are perfect: for they are appointed and spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="7"/>by the worde of God, and his spirit. <hi>Tertullian:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Tertul. contra Prax. &amp; Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>g Cypr. de Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism. Christi.</note> I adore and reuerence the fulnesse of the Scriptures: the scripture hath his reason, and is sufficient of it self. <hi>Saint Cyprian:</hi> Speake on Lord, thy seruant heareth. Christian religion shall finde that out of this Scripture doe spring the rules of all manner of doctrine, and that from thence riseth, as also that thither returneth, al whatsoeuer the discipline and gouernment of the Church doth containe. <hi>Antonius the Hermite;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Antonius in sui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Epistolis. Athanasius cont. Idola. Ad Serapion. In Ep. Senten. Dyonis. Hillar. l. 2. de Trinit.</note> The Scriptures are sufficient for all manner of knowledge of God, and all manner of discipline. <hi>Athanasius, who notwithstanding hath to deale against the Arrians,</hi> The holy scriptures are sufficient for the demonstration of the truth: learne onely the scriptures, for the lessons which thou findest there, will be sufficient for thee. Although <hi>(saith he in another place)</hi> I haue not found this word <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, cōsubstantiall, yet so it is as that I haue found the thing it selfe. <hi>Saint Hillarie vpon the same argument:</hi> The word of God, which by the testimonie of the Gospel hath beene transfused and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyed into our eares, is sufficient for the beleeuers: for what is there belonging vnto mans saluation, that is not to be found contained therein? Or what is there therein either lame or obscure? Verily euerie thing therein is full and perfect,
<note place="margin">Basil, de vera fide. Homil. 29. In oratione Ethica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> In Esai. c. 2. Chrys. hom. 9 in 2. ad Tim.</note> &amp;c. <hi>Saint Basill attributeth it to the same pride and infidelitie, to bring in any thing that is not written, or to reiect that which is written.</hi> The old and new Testament, <hi>(saith he)</hi> are the treasure of the church. All the commaundements of God are written, and must be obserued. All whatsoeuer is besides the straight and euen line of the Scripture, is a cursed abhomination before God. <hi>S. Chrysostome:</hi> The holie Scripture teacheth thee whatsoeuer thou shouldest know, or be ignorant of: Thou art a Gentile, and wouldest become a Christian: but our controuersies doe trouble thee. Thou knowest not to whom to goe, for euerie man pretendeth and alledgeth the Scriptures, &amp;c. Knowe that that which agreeth therewith is christian; but that which disagreeth with the same,
<note place="margin">In Acta. hom. 33. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Aug. de bono Viduit. De doct, christ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> l. 2. c. 9. serm. 88. ad fratres lib. de confes. 7 c. 7. In S. Ioh. tract. 49. vbi viamad vitam. De consensu Euan. l. 1. c. v. t.</note> is farre off from the rule of christianitie. Likewise, <hi>saith he in another place:</hi> It is the propertie of the diuell, to adde vnto the commaundements of God. <hi>Saint Augustine:</hi> The Scripture <hi>(saith he)</hi> doth prefixe and set before vs a law, teaching vs not to be more wise then we ought: looke not therefore that to teach thee, on my behalfe and part, is any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, but to expound vnto thee the wordes of my master: for euen <hi>(saith he)</hi> in the things that are openly taught in the Scriptures, is fully found al that which is to be done, or left vndone: all that which appertaineth vnto faith, or concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth maners. Some haue made choise to write of all that which may seeme to be sufficient for the saluation of the faithfull: In thy Christ, O Lord, and in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, I perswade my selfe, that thou hast placed the way of mans salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Whatsoeuer he would haue that we should reade of his deedes or wordes,
<note place="margin">Cyril. Alexan. In S. Iohan. l. 12 c. vlt.</note> that hath he commaunded his Apostles to write, as if it had beene done with his own hands, &amp;c. <hi>S. Cyprian Bishop of Alexandria;</hi> All that the Lord hath done is not written, but rather so much as the pen-men thought to be sufficient, both for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and doctrine of faith, to the end that shining through a right faith, manners, and the truth, we may come to the kingdom of Christ. <hi>Now those pen-men of whom he speaketh, were they not inspired of God? Is it not his holy spirit himselfe? Againe,
<note place="margin">Lib. 5. in. Leui.</note> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were he or Origen vpon Leuiticus.</hi> In the two Testaments, we may finde out and discusse, whatsoeuer matter concerning God, &amp; from the same gather, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer knowledge of things: in so much as that if any thing remaine not deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by these Scriptures, there is not any third, which we are to receiue and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb facs="8"/>of for the authorising of such knowledge. <hi>Cyrill Bishop of Ierusalem:</hi> Beleeue me not,
<note place="margin">Cyril. Hieroso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim. Catec. 4.</note> if I shew it thee not by the Scriptures: for the saluation of our faith is not bolted out by the meanes of any disputation, but plainly demonstrated by them.
<note place="margin">Thom. 1. part. Sum. q. 1. art. 3. Supra omne debitum crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae. Et q. 147, art. 4 p. 3. in add q. 6, art, 6.</note>
      <hi>And what will they say more, when as Thomas one of their side, saith;</hi> That the things that proceede of the onely will of God, besides whatsoeuer is due vnto the creature, cannot be made knowne vnto vs, otherwise then in that they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vnto vs in the Scripture: That the doctrine of faith and the Sacraments, cannot bee but of Christ: That the ordinances and statutes of the church are not of themselues of the necessitie of saluation? <hi>When also expounding the place in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie at this day, of the second to Timothie, chapter the third, he vseth these wordes:</hi> That the Scriptures teach the truth,
<note place="margin">In 2. ad Tim. c. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> reproue falshood, perswade vnto that which is good, and draw backe from that which is euill: Not <hi>(saith he)</hi> after any faint or feeble maner, but to the perfecting of the worke of saluation; yea <hi>(saith he)</hi> euen in the highest degree, &amp;c. <hi>And Scotus after him,</hi> That the holy scripture is sufficient for the Pilgrime, <hi>that is to say, for the Christian trauailing heere below,</hi> to come to the end of his purposed voiage, <hi>that is to say, vnto saluation:</hi> That this way is not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; but most certaine: that in the same likewise is founde sufficiently laid open, whatsoeuer is to be beleeued, hoped for, or done. <hi>And Cardinall Caietan vpon the place afore named;</hi> To the making <hi>(saith he)</hi> of the man wise vnto eternall salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and furnished with all those partes requisite for the making of the man of God perfect.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Admit (will some say vnto vs) that it is sufficient,
<note place="margin">The scripture is cleare and plaine vnto saluation. Lactan, l. 5. c. 1.</note> but yet notwithstanding obscure, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult, ambiguous, &amp; by consequent daungerous. This is all that which can be said against a wicked mā making his will, &amp; taking pleasure to set his heires togither by the eares, through sutes in the law. And what would they say then to the Gentiles, to Celsus, to Iulian, to all the Philosophers, who tooke occasion by reason of the facilitie and simplicitie of the same, to account thereof as base and contemptible. He that is the light of lights, and together there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with all goodnes it selfe, shall he delight himselfe in becomming obscure and darke vnto vs? This light that lightneth euerie man that commeth into the world; shall he be come downe here vpon earth to blind the world, euen them whom he hath chosen and set apart from the world? Shall not the essentiall &amp; almightie word of God haue power or knowledge, or will to expresse and make plaine his meaning in his worde; when as he is come from heauen vnto vs, from the bosome of the father amongst men, to expresse and manifest himselfe? The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost sent downe from the father, and the sonne, to teach the Apostles the things concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning saluation, and in them vs; comming downe vpon them in tongues of fire, to interpret himselfe in all maner of languages, shall he be no better then barbarisme and darknesse? shall he not be prouided of wordes cleare and plaine inough, to make himselfe to be vnderstood in the Scriptures? Verily we learne not this lesson in the Prophets, if they be not able to auouch vnto vs in that they speake their own cause.</hi> Thy word <hi>(saith Dauid)</hi> is a torch vnto my feete,
<note place="margin">Psal. 119. &amp; 19 &amp; 12.</note> that is to say, a light, causing our eies to see. They that speake not according to this word, <hi>(saith Esai)</hi> it is because they haue no light in them. <hi>Neither yet of S. Peter,
<note place="margin">Esai. 8.2. Pet. 1.19.</note> who in his iudgement hath thought it to be so far off from obscuritie, as that he hath commaunded vs to hearken to the Propheticall worde, as vnto a light that shineth in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. And what then shall be the brightnesse of the Gospel, which is the light of this light? the Sunne in respect of the lampe; and declared vnto vs by the Sonne, the brightnesse of the glorie of the father? Afterward the Apostle saith, that he hath spoken diuerse wayes to the Fathers, and to the Prophets, &amp;c. And to whom then shall he be obscure? to whom shall
<pb facs="8"/>he bee hidden, except as Saint Paule saith vnto vs,</hi> vnto them which perish,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 44.</note> to them whose vnderstāding the God of this world hath blinded, to the end that the light of the Gospel of the glorie of Christ might not shine vnto them.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Likewise the Fathers, they speake not according to our aduersaries:
<note place="margin">According to the fathers.</note> for when they aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere the Pagans, they go not about to excuse the simplicitie and clearnesse thereof, by deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them; but rather, say they, it behoued them to be such, to the ende that that which was for the saluation of euerie particular partie, might be vnderstoode of all. Irenaeus saith:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iren. cont. hae res. l. 2. c. 42, &amp; 67. Iust. in Tryph. Tertul. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrect.</note> All the Scripture, both Propheticall and Euangelicall, is manifest and without ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guitie, and may likewise be vnderstoode of all. <hi>Iustine;</hi> Let vs haue recourse vnto the Scripture, that therein we may find where to be safe and sure. <hi>Tertullian:</hi> The heretikes shun the light of the Scripture. <hi>So farre is it off that they should be able to shrowde themselues vnder the darknesse of the same. Athanasius:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Athan. in Epi. ad Iouinian.</note> True faith in Christ is cleare by the Scriptures. Let vs set <hi>(saith he against the Arrians)</hi> this candle vpon the Candlesticke, and it is sufficient. <hi>Saint Hillarie to the same purpose:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hillar. de vnit. patris &amp; fil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>i.</note> The Lord hath set forth the faith of the Gospel, in the greatest simplicitie that possibly can be, and hath fitted his wordes for our capacitie, so farre forth as our infirmitie is able to beare it. <hi>Constantine the Emperour likewise in the same cause:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Constant. in Concil Nicen. Socrat. l. 1. Chrysost. in 2. ad Thess. hom. 3. in Gen. hom 13. in <hi>S</hi> Iohn. hom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>6. in Esay. c. 1. in proaem. in Ep. ad Rom. in S. Mat. hom, 49. in S. Ioh. hom. 58. in S. Mat. hom. 22.</note> The Euangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, Apostolicall, and Propheticall bookes do plainly teach vs, what we are to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue concerning diuine things. <hi>Saint Chrysostome:</hi> All things are cleare in the scriptures; they declare themselues, not suffering any man to erre. The truth lieth not hidden, or obscure therein, except it be vnto such as will not search for it. As the light is to the eie, so is the law of God vnto our spirits: such as looke not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, doe walke in darknesse. Our whole mischiefe is for that we reade it not: that same, which is a doore, by which doe enter both the sheepe and the shepheard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> more necessarie for the simple &amp; idiot, then for the learned doctor. To be short, in that confusion which shall happen vnder Antichrist, we shall not be able to tell whither to haue recourse, but to the Scriptures: and there are none but those which are of a peruerse heart, that doe not vnderstand the mysteries, being such as in whom the spirit of truth resteth not. <hi>There might a whole volume be compiled of the like places. Epiphanius:</hi> All things are cleare and euident in the Scriptures, to such as with a holie discourse, according to reason, will heare the worde of God.
<note place="margin">Epipha. haeres. 69. &amp; 70. Hieronym in Matt c. 22. In Esay. c. 8.</note>
      <hi>Saint Ierome:</hi> They erre because they know not the Scriptures: and seeing they are ignorant in them, they know not the power of God, &amp;c. If we follow not the testimonies conteined in them: darknesse will oppresse vs, and ouerrun our doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, &amp;c. <hi>Saint Augustine against the Donatists:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Augu. de vnit. eccles. c. 5.</note> Let vs make choise of the plaine and manifest places: for if they should not be found such in the Scriptures, in vain should it be said, that wee shall finde in them to lay open the things shut vp, &amp; to make cleare such as are dark and obscure. <hi>Again;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Epist 3.</note> There is not any such great difficultie in the Scriptures, to come by the things necessarie vnto saluation: the making likewise whereby they are wouen &amp; set togither, is to be come by of all. There is matter fitting all sorts of spirits, as to correct the peruerse,
<note place="margin">Praua &amp; parua</note> to nourish the weake and yong nouices, and to delight such as are growne old and great. In the things that are manifestlie apparant in the Scriptures,
<note place="margin">De peccat me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litis. l. 2. c. vit.</note> are clearlie founde to be all those which concern faith &amp; maners. When we reason of any thing that is verie obscure, if wee bee not helped by the cleare testimonie of the Scriptures, man must be curbed and kept short for presuming too farre.
<note place="margin">De doct. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian. l. 2. c. 6.</note> The holie Ghost hath in such sort qualified them, as that in the cleare places they feede our hungrie appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite;
<pb facs="9"/>
and in the obscure they sharpen our dull taste: wee are refreshed with the things that are cleare, and set on worke by the obscure and darke. The profound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of this worde sharpneth,
<note place="margin">De verb. dom. serm. 11. &amp; de verb. Apost. serm. 13.</note> and setteth an edge vpon our indeuours, neither doth it for all that denie vs the vnderstanding thereof, &amp;c. <hi>Now if thou thinke to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre hereupon, then there is obscuritie therein: and of this obscuritie to conclude, either an impossibilitie of vnderstanding of them, or else a secking of something therein, that is not there to be found:
<note place="margin">De verb. Apo. Serm. 13.</note> To the one he answereth thee:</hi> The euill spirit hateth vnderstanding, for feare that by vnderstanding he should be forced to do and practise according thereunto:
<note place="margin">Planissime. De doct. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian. l. 2. c. 6.</note>
      <hi>And to the other;</hi> That out of all these obscurities there is not almost a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing gathered, that is not elsewhere deliuered in verie plaine and cleare sort. <hi>In briefe, to the ende thou maist not bring in any distinction betwixt the word written, and vnwritten, where as the Psalmist saith;</hi> Thy worde is a torch vnto my feete, &amp;c. This is <hi>(saith he)</hi> that worde which is contained in the holy Scriptures. <hi>And againe;</hi> The faithful that cleaueth to them, cannot be dazeled with the iniquitie of the world; no more then the starres fixed and set in the firmament, which cannot haue their light put out by the night. <hi>So farre is it from him, as our aduersaries doe, to terrifie the fathfull with going about to make them afraid of it, by reason of the obscuritie that is therein.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Yet so it is,
<note place="margin">But there are darke places. 2. Pet. 3.</note> will you say, as that there are difficult things in the Scripture; for S. Peter likewise saith, That in the Epistles of Saint Paule, there are, &amp;c. And what booke is there in any maner of facultie whatsoeuer, which hath not some, yea and many moe? But if thou hadst diligently read this text, and well weighed the Relatiue, it would haue appeared, that he saith not, that the Epistles of Saint Paul are difficult, but cortaine things in certaine points, which he handleth in them. And indeed what higher thing is there then the mysterie of our saluation, or more profoundly expounded? What thing more obscure, then that of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie; or more clearlie vttered? But thou shouldest therewithall haue added that which followeth;</hi> That the ignorant and vnstable doe wrest them, as they also doe other places of Scripture to their owne destruction <hi>Verilie for these obscurities, the Fathers did not driue Christians from the Scriptures; but rather encouraged them to labour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in so much the more.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iren. l. 3. c. 12. contr. haeres.</note> You haue <hi>(say they vnto vs)</hi> this furtherance, that there is not anie contrarietie therein; and further, that one place may expound, but not make more intricate an other. <hi>If we could but say as much of the Bookes of other sciences, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in so many contradictions, as also antinomies doe encounter and crosse one another, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie difficulties should we auoide? how much of our way and trauaile might we thinke our selues to haue gained?
<note place="margin">Lib. 2. c. 46. contr. h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>res.</note> Irenaeus saith;</hi> The whole Scripture, which God hath giuen vs, will be found to agree togither; the things spoken manifestly do expound the parables therein,
<note place="margin">Ambr. in psal. 119. serm. 8.</note> &amp;c. <hi>Saint Ambrose;</hi> There is much obscuritie in the Scriptures, but if thou knocke with the hande of thy Spirit at their gate, thou shalt begin to gather the reason of that which is there said; and it will be set open vnto thee, not by any other means then the word it selfe.
<note place="margin">Augu. de doct. Christian. l. 2. c. 25. Iren. l. 2. c. 46. contr. haeres. Basil in Asee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticis. 267. Aug Ep. 48 &amp; de doctrina Christiana. l 2. c. 6.</note>
      <hi>S. August.</hi> To illustrate the obscure ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of speaking, let vs take our paternes from the manifest ones; and so of plaine and euident sentences for the opening of the hidden &amp; couert ones. <hi>But otherwise, if vnder the colour of obscuritie, thou labor to gather any point of new doctrine, Irenaeus will say vnto thee;</hi> Thou must reason from the cleare places of the Scripture, and not from parables. <hi>Saint Basil:</hi> The things that may seeme darkly spoken in one place, are most cleare in another. <hi>Saint Augustine:</hi> Who is so impudent, as to expound a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie place of Scripture for himselfe by an Allegorie, if he haue not an other verie
<pb facs="9"/>cleare place in the Scripture, which may make it plaine? <hi>Seeing likewise saith he in another place,</hi> That of all that which is obscure therein,
<note place="margin">Lomb. l. 3. d. 5</note> there riseth not any thing almost, but that which is cleare elsewhere. <hi>Lombard:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Tho. in Sum. q. 147. art, 10. Pet. de Alliac</note> Where as the Scripture is si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, it will be good for vs not to affirme any thing. <hi>Thomas;</hi> Thou canst not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son from an Allegoricall sense, &amp;c. <hi>To be briefe, the Cardinall Alliaco,</hi> That the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is a lampe that giueth light; and that wee must haue recourse thither to haue saluation. <hi>Gerson;</hi> That an idiot, a woman, yea a childe,
<note place="margin">Gers. de Script &amp; de exa. doct. Pic. in Quest. an Papa sup. Concil.</note> are better to be beleeued alledging the Scripture, then the Pope and a whole Councell. <hi>And the Counte Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes Picus Mirandula, after the same manner. So farre off were these men, who yet were the lights of their time, from this darke opinion, sprung no doubt out of the pit of vtter darknesse;</hi> That the Scriptures were not any thing but darknesse. <hi>But in a word, the mischiefe is, for that we will finde it difficult, because that in the clearnesse thereof, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible for vs to finde out our inuentions; obscure because that our traditions cannot stand before this light; and imperfect, because that neither by it, nor before it, we are able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our imperfections.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Yet so it is, that our aduersaries replie, that there are controuersies amongst vs, that wee cannot agree of the expounding of the places which are alledged respectiuely;
<note place="margin">How they must be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</note> and therefore who shall expound them vnto vs? who shall cause vs to admit of one exposition, more then of another? Let vs striue thitherward, hauing Gods grace to assist vs; let vs come thereto with the Zeale of his glorie, the loue of the truth, and the desire of saluation; and then a meane knowledge ioyned with a good conscience, would speedily attaine the ende. And for some small taste thereof, may it please the reader to examine certaine rules that follow, being those which the auncient fathers doe teach vs.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The first is, That we be agreed vpon the Canonicall Scriptures, thereby to auoyde the confounding of them with the Apocrypha; that is,
<note place="margin">To agree of the bookes cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Canonical.</note> of the setting downe of the spirit of God for iudge, rightlie discerned and distinguished from euerie spirit of man: for humane scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, after the maner of monie, is so much the more hurtfull and damnable, by how much the coine that it hath counterfeited is the better: and hereof the olde Church hath had a speciall regard. I call this the first, because that by this doore, it did perceiue both vanities and heresies to enter into the Church, vnder a fained name of our Lord and his Apostles. They tell vs,</hi> that the Scripture is the ballance, the rule, and the squire, &amp;c.
<note place="margin">Hieronym. ad Laetam.</note>
      <hi>And therefore to render to things, their weight, measure, and streightnesse, it is necessarie that it should be iust. And this is that which S. Ierome telleth vs;</hi> Let vs looke vnto our selues to beware of the Apocrypha bookes: and if we will reade them, &amp;c. let vs know that they are not theirs, by whose names they are called, that many faultie things are mingled there amongst; that it craueth a singular prudencie in him, that loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to gather golde out of mud; and in a worde, that we must not reade them, ad dogmatum veritatem, for the confirming of doctrines. <hi>So farre off is he from beeing of iudgement, that wee shoulde rake togither the dregges of all manner of such Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours from all parts, therewith to defile the Church. And in another place;</hi>
      <note place="margin">In Symb. Ruf. in Praefat, in Prou. &amp; in Reg. in prolog. Galeato. Hibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras naemas.</note> Certaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse men, to strengthen their opinions, haue inserted vnder the name of holie personages, things that they neuer writ: and notwithstanding there are some which preferre these Hiberian fables, before the Authētike bookes. <hi>And this is the cause why S. August. doth presse the heretikes continually with the Canonicall Bookes, and refuseth the Apocrypha, wherin they did their whole indeuour to ground themselues.</hi> Let vs lay aside both on the one part &amp; the other, that which we produce frō elswhere then out of the Canonicall bookes: let vs shewe forth the holy Church, by the
<pb facs="10"/>holy Oracles; let vs search for it in the holie Canonicall Scriptures, &amp;c. To them I yeeld this honour, that their Authour could not erre any maner of way: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers I read in such sort, how holy or lerned soeuer they might be, as that I beleeue them not in that which they say, because they say it, but because they perswade me either by the Canonicall bookes, or else by probable reason, &amp;c. <hi>And therefore he saith further:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ep. 19. ad Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronym. l. 2. con. Dona. c. 3. con. Faust. l. 11. c. 5.</note> The aduised searcher of the holy Scriptures shall reade them first all ouer, but those onely which are called Canonicall; for then he shall be able to reade the others more safely, being alreadie instructed in the faith of the truth, for feare that otherwise they might forestall and get the aduantage of a weake spirit, abuse it with dangerous lies, &amp; infect it with some preiudicate opinion, cōtrarie to sound vnderstanding.
<note place="margin">Lib. de Ciuit. Dei. c. 15.23.</note>
      <hi>For</hi> although therin be found some truth, notwithstanding because of many vntruthes, they are vtterly without all Canonicall authoritie. <hi>And in the meane time what impudencie is it to go about to make him (to giue credit to the decree by committing the offence of a most notorious lie,
<note place="margin">D. 9. c. in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicis.</note> acknowledged also by Alphonsus of Castres) to haue said, That the Decretall Epistles of the Bishops of Rome, are of the same authoritie,
<note place="margin">Cyril Hierosol Catech. 4.</note> that the Canonicall Scriptures? Cyrill Patriarke of Ierusalem:</hi> Studie these Scriptures onely, which wee boldly and confidently reade in the Church, but haue not any thing to doe with the Apocrypha.
<note place="margin">Nazian. de ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris Scripturae libris.</note>
      <hi>Nazianzene:</hi> In them wee see the light, &amp;c. But to the ende that the bookes that are excluded from thence may not deceiue thee, learne to know the true and legitimate number, &amp;c. If you find any other then those, holde them for base and bastardlie ones. <hi>Yea, and this was one of the first workes of the Apostolike and Primitiue Church, to seale vp vnto vs the Canon of theese bookes, by the same spirit, which had inspired them, and so called them Canonicall, as if a man should say Reguler, because they are ordained the rule of Christian doctrines, and stand as a law to guide all our discourses. And to this first number it belongeth not, neither hath belonged since then, to any either man or Church, to chop in, or to adde other bookes, without the violating of the iudgement of the Apostolike Primitiue Church. For what other thing were it but to say, that it had excluded the bookes which it should haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted? Wherefore we may thinke that what they haue said of such as at this day leade vs to Iewish fables,
<note place="margin">Tit. 1.14.</note> and to the commaundements of men (which Saint Paule so earnestly war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vs of) to the pretended Gospels of Saint Iames, Saint Bartholmew, Nicodemus, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seph of Aremathia, &amp;c. yea and to the verie bookes, which the Church both Christian and Iewish haue pronounced Apocrypha, was not done to teach vs to draw from thence anie patternes of good manners, as sometimes the olde fathers do, but pretended articles of faith: not to strengthen any poynt of Canonicall doctrine, but to lay a foundation of a new inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted one, such as neuer came in the Canon. Euen as Saint Augustine after his modest maner would tell them the same that he said to the Donatists;</hi> These men wanting examples of their wickednesse, do boast themselues to haue found in the booke of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabees,
<note place="margin">August. cont. Gaudent l 2 c. 23.</note> one Razias to imitate, who slue himselfe: but the Iewes make no such account of these bookes, as they doe of the Law, the Prophets, and the Psalmes, to which God hath giuen testimonie, as to his witnesses. They haue beene recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not vnprofitablie of the Church, if so be they be soberly read, principallie in respect of these brethren the Machabees, who laboured and tooke paines for the law of God, &amp;c. <hi>Could he haue spoken thus of the diuine bookes inspired of God without blasphemie;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Caletan in 1. ad Cor. c. 12. v, 28.</note> Not vnprofitablie, if they be read soberlie? &amp;c. <hi>And this is the same that in our time Cardinall Caietan hath acknowledged, laying out the difference betwixt the Apostles, and all others in the Church.</hi> The vniuersall gouernment of the church,
<pb facs="10"/>
      <hi>(saith he)</hi> belongeth onely to the Apostles; not onely by worde and action, but also by writing: and therefore the onely writings of the Apostles, or those which haue beene approued by them, must haue the authoritie of holy writ.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>The second rule is; That for the vnderstanding of these Canonicall bookes,
<note place="margin">To haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course to the originals He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew and Greeke. Ambros. de S. Spir. l. 2. c. 6. &amp; de incarna. c. 8</note> or any place in them that is in controuersie, we haue recourse for the olde Testament, to the truth of the Hebrew; and for the New, to the Greeke: seeing there is neuer a translation, by whom soeuer it may haue beene performed, which can be called either Canonicall, or Authenticall: See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing also, that as from false premisses or propositions there cannot follow but a false conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion; so from false Grammar there cannot proceede true Diuinitie. And this is that which the Fathers say vnto vs:</hi> If any man striue about the diuersitie of Latin copies, that some vnfaithfull persons haue falsified them, let him in such case looke vpon the Greeke, &amp;c. <hi>Againe:</hi> We haue found it so in the Greeke copies,
<note place="margin">Hillar. in Psal. 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> the authoritie whereof is farre more to be preferred. <hi>Saint Hillarie:</hi> We haue oftentimes tolde you, that we cannot be satisfied in the vnderstanding of the Scriptures by the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine translation. <hi>And this Saint Ierome spoke to him that was ignoraunt in the Hebrew tongue. Saint Ierome also, whose translation some men doe so highly esteeme, howbeit that the best learned doe doubt if it be his, and all agree that all of it is not:</hi>
      <note place="margin">S. Hier. in Epi. ad Paulin. &amp; Marcel. &amp; ad Suniam, &amp; ad Damas &amp; in Prefat. in 4. Euang. &amp; in Zac. c. 4. &amp;. 8. &amp; ad Lucin. Augu. de doct. Christ. l. 2. c. 11 Epist. 59. &amp; 19 De doct. christ. l. 2. c. 10 &amp; 15 &amp; in Decret. D. 9 c. in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum. Genes. 3.</note> It behooueth vs to haue recourse to the originall of the Hebrew, for the Olde testament, and to the Greeke for the New: For <hi>(saith he)</hi> there are so manie diuerse Latine copies, as there are bookes; and by these originals wee must alter and correct that which hath beene ill translated by the Interpretors. <hi>Saint Augustine:</hi> The Latins to attain to the knowledge of the Scriptures, haue neede of two wings, of the Hebrew and Greeke tongues: let the Latines haue recourse vnto the Hebrew and Greeke co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, &amp;c. <hi>Againe:</hi> For to correct the Latins, let vs vse the Grecians, &amp;c. Let vs ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beleeue the tongue from whence the Expositors haue translated the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures into other tongues, &amp;c. <hi>Saint Augustine, I say who knew nothing in the Hebrew. And that they had iust cause to say so, may be made to appeare vnto vs by infinite examples. In Genesis it is said; That the seed shall breake the head of the Serpent: that is to say, Christ: The Vulgar translation saith,</hi> Ipsa, she<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>not</hi> Ipsum, <hi>that is to say,</hi> semen, <hi>and so by that means it is referred vnto the virgin Marie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> and so a Sauioresse set vp in stead of a Sauiour. At this stone good S. Barnard stūbled, as Burgensis, Caietanus, &amp; Canusius do acknowledge, &amp;c. And still they would that wee should leaue it in the way, to the ende that euerie man may stumble thereat. S. Paul in his Epistle to the Hebrewes, saith,
<note place="margin">Hebr. 13.</note> That God is well pleased with charitie and well doing. The Interpreter hath translated it, That by them men merit at Gods bands. See you not therefore, say some vnto vs, Merit proued in the Scripture? Yes, were it not that euerie man knoweth, what the worde <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> meaneth, nemely that God taketh pleasure, &amp;c. Melchisedech brought forth bread and wine to Abraham. In stead of</hi> Protulit, <hi>he hath translated it</hi> Obtulit:
<note place="margin">Genes. 18.</note>
      <hi>and see you not how thereupon also the sacrifice of the Masse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> But Vatablus, and Pagnine, and Caietan also, doe acknowledge the sooth: and therefore reforme the translation, and withall you wipe out the Masse. So vpon the Psal,</hi> 68. <hi>For,</hi> To sleepe amongst pots or Andirons; <hi>he translateth it,</hi> Inter Cleros, amongst the clergie; <hi>The lots or heritages: &amp;</hi> ex lapidibus sacculi, <hi>is made,</hi> lapides saeculi, stones of the ballance, that is, of weights, are made eternall stones: <hi>and fiue hundred such like. Where is the Doctor how holie or great soeuer he may be who resting and relying vpon any such translation, shall be able to gather any true sense? Who shall not be forced thereby to deceiue both himselfe and others? No lesse then Accursius in the law, when he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standeth not by reason of his time, either some exquisite Latin, or some Greeke word alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb facs="11"/>by the lawier. And yet the Councell of Trent (who set it downe for their position, to make errours authentike) will haue this translation to be authentike, and that in lectures, disputations, Sermons, and Expositions, it be vsed ordinarily; yea and that before that of Pagnines, or Arias Montanus, who haue kept themselues nearer vnto the Hebrew, And why? Not for any other cause then that ignorance may continue, so as that errour vnder the darknesse thereof may hide it selfe, seeing it cannot stand before the truth, true vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, or the light.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The third is,
<note place="margin">Scripture is expounded by Scripture.</note> That we expound Scripture by Scripture, one place by another, one by manie; obscure and darke ones, by cleare and plaine ones, or one darke one by many plaine ones: In which attempt we haue a farre greater facilitie, then they who should assay the like in prophane authours, because that we are assured that there is no contrarietie therein, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause also that there is a perpetuall correspondencie betwixt the new Testament and the old, and both in the one and the other, in it selfe: betwixt the new Sacraments and the old; and in the olde and new in themselues, &amp;c. And finally, because that in obscure places, wee are not to search for, or gesse out any thing that is new: yea on the contrarie, not any thing; said Saint Augustine, which is not clearely apparant in such places as are most cleare. This is the order,
<note place="margin">Nehem. 8.8.</note> which we reade to haue beene practised by Esdras, who, saith Nehemiah; read in the booke of the law of God, and therewith gaue the meaning, causing it to be vnderstood by the Scripture it selfe: The question at that time was about the purging and casting out of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine abuses,
<note place="margin">Actes 17.11</note> which were crept into the Church during the time of the captiuitie, by being mingled amongst the Gentiles. And hence are they of Berea commended, as conferring the Scriptures most diligently one with another, to see if it were so as Saint Paule preached vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. The question was of the resoluing of themselues by them, against the opinion of the Pharisies and Doctors of the Law, by the Scriptures, Whether Iesus crucified were that Christ or not. And this also is the precept which the Fathers teach vs. Iren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>us:</hi> The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrations which are in the Scriptures,
<note place="margin">Iren. cont. Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res▪ 1.2. c. 46. &amp; 67. Basil. in asceti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis. 267, Chrysost. hom. 13. in Gen. &amp; in Psalm. 147. Aug. de verb. dom. serm. 2. &amp; 11. Tho. 1. p. sum. q. 1. art. 9. Aegid. l. 2. Dist. 37.</note> cannot bee shewed but by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. <hi>Againe,</hi> The exposition which is according to the Scriptures, is that legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate and safe, &amp;c. <hi>Saint Basil:</hi> That which seemeth darke and ambiguous in one place of Scripture, is cleare and plaine in another. <hi>Chrysostome;</hi> The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is expounded by it selfe this is ourarmorie against the Diuell, &amp;c. <hi>Saint Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine,</hi> The wordes of the Gospel doe carrie their interpretation with them. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine:</hi> VVe vnderstand the darke places by the cleare what is darkly deliuered in one place, is clearly set downe in another, &amp;c. <hi>S. Thomas,</hi> That which is spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken metaphorically in one place, is spoken simplie in another. <hi>Aegidius Romanus;</hi> Of manie expositions we must take that which agreeth with the other scriptures, and not that which hurteth any part of them. <hi>Following also that which is said by the Canon</hi> Relatum,
<note place="margin">Can Relat.</note> That we must not seeke out a sense at our pleasure, from the purpose, to confirme it any maner of way by the authoritie of the Scriptures but take the meaning of the truth from the Scriptures themselues, if the place may be drawne into diuerse senses.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>The fourth is;
<note place="margin">In all exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie of faith must be kept.</note> That we see that the exposition which we giue or take, do alwaies retaine and keepe the analogie of faith, that it be proportionable and correspondent to the bodie of Christian doctrine, which some of the olde fathers haue called the rule of faith: I say, not to establish any new principles or articles of Christianitie, but to conforme and referre them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to those which haue beene receiued therein from all times. For the holy Scripture is the vniuersall principle of our faith, and it is well said, That there are as many articles of faith as sillables in it, because it is said of the least iota, that it shall not passe, and by conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent,
<pb facs="11"/>that we must most firmely beleeue it all. But notwithstanding, as this said Aegidius saith,</hi> All the Scripture is resolued into certaine articles of faith, to which all the doctrine therein is to be referred, and those as principles abide firme in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, and are not resolued into others. <hi>And from these principles we deduct our Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remes, and answere our Problemes, no lesse then the Mathematicians doe their Maxims,
<note place="margin">
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </note> Axiomes, and demaunds: but so much the more firmely, by howe much wee are the faster founded vpon the Creator, then vpon the creature: vpon the Law-giuer to the whole world, then vpon the law which he hath giuen it, which is Nature.
<note place="margin">Thom. in. Sum. q. 1. art. 5.6, 8.</note> And this is it which Thomas saith:</hi> That the holy doctrine taketh not his principles from any humane science, but from the wisdome of God, from which as from the most soueraigne wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, all our knowledge must take his direction and ordering: and that this skill commeth not vnto vs from naturall reason, but by reuelation: <hi>that is, from the Scripture diuinely inspired: and therefore,</hi> that it iudgeth of all. <hi>Verie farre differing from them who dispute of diuinitie according to the principles of Philosophie, or other sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences: against the law of Logicke, which saith,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. That we must not leape out of one science into another, but rather from a true vse of Logicke, &amp; discourse of reason from principles of one science, to draw the propositions and consequences that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the same. Our principles then are articles of faith, against which we must beware that our expositions doe not strike and dash themselues; but one the contrarie it is necessarie that they become conformable thereto. To strike thereupon, that is amongest the Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,</hi> Deduci <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, to be brought to an impossibilitie, that is to say, frō out of the bounds of reason, of Nature, &amp; of true diuinitie: <hi>this is according to the lawes of combate, to rub against the bands or ropes that pale in their ground, that is to bee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came, to be conuinced of falshood. Now the primitiue Church hath gathered them for vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a briefe collection, al those which the Councels put forth afterward, are nothing but Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries thereupon: and it is the same which Tertul. calleth</hi> Regulā fidei: <hi>Vnder which,
<note place="margin">Tertul. de vela vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>g de praes. &amp; aduers. Prax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eam. August. de Symbol. Beda in S. Ioh. l 1. c. 4. &amp; l. 3, c 5.</note> saith Saint Augustine,</hi> hath beene gathered togither whatsoeuer was dispersed throughout the diuine Scriptures: to the end that the memorie of the most dull and slow of conceipt, might not be ouerlaboured. <hi>And whereof Beda after him lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs this lesson: That we must beware that,</hi> Secundum fidem fit Sacramenti diuini expositio; That the exposition of the diuine mysteries be according to faith. <hi>In such sort as that we haue two Canons, but the one neuerthelesse an abridgement of the other, the Canonicall Scripture, and the Canon of faith, that is the Creede: that to stay our spirits, so that they may not search for in substance,</hi> any thing in faith,
<note place="margin">Tertul. de praescript.</note>
      <hi>(saith Tertullian)</hi> anie where else then in the doctrines of faith. <hi>This to direct them in the expounding of that, that is of the Scriptures and doctrines of faith; to the ende that they may not admit of any sense, how plausible soeuer it might be, which is gone, be it neuer so little, from the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of faith. For example <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> wee haue to deale with an Arrian, we shall say vnto him after the maner of Saint Augustine: let vs pitch our selues without any shifting vpon the Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall Scriptures: we haue no other titles whereby we may learne the right, but them. But if from these Scriptures he alledge vnto vs,</hi> The father is greater then I, &amp;c. <hi>we shall call to mind, that it is also written,</hi> I and the father are one: <hi>and the Scripture cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie. To the ende then, that the one and the other may proue true, we shall distinguish: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring the first vnto the humane nature, and the other vnto his diuine, that so we may not conclude against that which is said,</hi> I beleeue in Iesus Christ: <hi>for,</hi> Cursed be hee that putteth his cōfidence in any thing but God, &amp;c. <hi>And let vs further obserue here, that, as hath bin said, there is no societie since that of the Apostles, that can make that Canonicall
<pb facs="12"/>Scripture which is not: as in like maner there is not any that can make an article of the faith, of that which of it selfe is not one. This power saith the Cardinall Caietan himselfe, did ende there, and there is not any, either succession or discent, which can attribute it vnto it selfe, or which can pretend the same.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>What then?
<note place="margin">How we are to receiue and intertaine the Fathers.</note> And shall the Fathers that haue so highly deserued of the Church, that haue so much and so well trauelled in the Scriptures, serue vs for no vse? Yes, but marke the place due vnto them, and the which no other can bee attributed vnto them: they could not be called any sooner: It is for God in his word to giue vs his law:</hi> he is our onely Lawgiuer, to whom alone it appertaineth <hi>(saith the Apostle)</hi> to saue and to destroy.
<note place="margin">Iames. 4.12. Expounders not lawgiuers.</note>
      <hi>The greatest honour that man can haue giuen him in the Church, is to be an expounder. To take vpon him to make any lawes therein of himselfe, this is to coine money this is to incroch vpon the Prince, he cannot doe it without committing of treason, yea without the incurring of blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie. Here therefore we admit of the Fathers, as expounders of the law, word, and diuine Scriptures: we receiue their interpretations with reuerence admiring their pietie, doctrine and zeale, but alwayes with this exception most reasonable: That they be but expounders, not law-giuers: dispensers of the mysteries of godlinesse, and not authours. In whom we must consider what they haue said, not in that they haue said it, but in that they haue said it by the way of expounding of the Scripture; not speaking of their owne heades, but according to their capacitie of the sense and meaning thereof. As for example, we reason of purgatorie: The question here is not to know, if it be to be found in Origen, Augustine, or S. Gregorie: this rule abideth alwayes firme: That if there be one, it must needes bee that God hath made it, for there is not any Doctor that hath power &amp; abilitie to make it. If it belong to vs to know it, let God haue reuealed and disclosed it vnto vs, for it is not to be learned at the gesse of any of the Fathers: let vs then haue found it in the Church her treasurie, the Scripture. Now there will be some to shew vs some places out of it, from which they would collect and gather it: and accordingly they will, that they should be vnderstood on this sort, and we on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie. In this controuersie we shall reade ouer the Text verie carefully, as also that which goeth before, and that which followeth: we shall examine it to see if it be faithfully transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, we shall make comparison of the like places. All this hitherto is nothing else, but to call vpon the Spirit of God to be our aide, so much the more to inlarge and open our spirits, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that which the Apostle saith vnto vs.</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> Let the spirits of the Prophets, <hi>that is of such as haue the gift of interpretation,</hi> be subiect to the Prophets. <hi>We shall here consult with the olde Fathers, we shall compare their expositions, both with the Text, and amongst themselues, we shall marke if they haue vsed a good translation, whether they handle the place, by the way, or of set purpose, affirmatiuelie or doubtfully: and where they differ (as ordinarily it falleth out) we shall weigh them, both according to the age wherein they shal haue liued, (for it importeth infinitely,) and according to the testimonie that the Church shall haue giuen of their doctrine, for they are not all of one weight. And in the ende,</hi> caeteris paribus. <hi>We shall not despise the consent and agreement of many against a few. But God forbid, that we should receiue them for Law-giuers, or yet for Authours of opinions in the Church, either contrarie vnto, or without the scriptures. And as farre off must it be, that we should make them correctors or iudges ouer that ballance, which iudgeth them, and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in themselues will be weighed. For this should be blasphemie against God, treason against the Church, and an iniurie to themselues. We wholie yeeld vnto them in thus doing, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which they haue giuen to their predecessours, as whereby they haue set a law, and giuen an example for their successors, practised by them against those by these against themselues. If they had done otherwise, where had we beene long agoe? Seeing there is not so much as one
<pb facs="12"/>of them that hath not erred in some thing? many of them in the points of faith, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of them so farre as that they haue fallen into heresie? Verily wee had beene Chiliasts, with Irenaeus; Montanists, with Tertullian; Anabaptists, with Saint Cyprian; Arrians, with Theophilus; Pelagians, with Faustus; the originals of all errours, yea euen of Arrianisme with Origen, we should wound the bodie of Christ, not being subiect to paine:
<note place="margin">Zonar. de Ori. in Constant. S. Hie ad Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach. &amp; Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum de Origen.</note> we should like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise speake doubtfullie of the Deitie of the holie Ghost, with Saint Hillarie: we should con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne children dying without Baptisme, with Saint Augustine; we should giue them the Eucharist with Saint Cyprian, and the greatest part, vntill the time of Charles the great, euen vnto the mouthes of the dead, as certaine Councels doe beare vs witnesse. In a word, we should haue made with lesse then nothing, of the Church of Christ, Augeas his Oxehouse;
<note place="margin">Canus. l. 7. de locis. Theol. c. 3. Gen. Cent. 3. &amp; seq. ad finem. c. 4. Villavincē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius de ratione studi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap> Theolo. l. 4 c. 6, obseru. 1. &amp;. 2. Baron. annal. tom. 2.</note> of Noes Arke, a sinke of all superstitions and errours. Which thing our greatest aduersaries themselues at this time not being able to dissemble, doe say:</hi> All the Saints, such onely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted as haue written the Canonicall bookes haue spoken by the Spirit of man, and haue sometimes erred, euen in the matters of faith, both in worde and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, what profoundnesse of learning, or innocencie of life soeuer, that we can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue and marke in them. <hi>And they come so farre as to set downe their errors, and that both by their names, as also by their kinds: concluding that the Scriptures are onely without error, and exempted from lies.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>As therefore there are rules for the expounding of the Scripture, by the Scripture,
<note place="margin">The Fathers must be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, but not as law-giuers.</note> so there are also for the expounding of them by the Fathers, the first whereof is alwayes this; That they be receyued and read as expounders, not as law-giuers, and that they referre their expositions to the rule of faith, and the articles thereof, and not to make any new faith, any new articles: according to that which Saint Ierome saith vnto vs:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hieron. cont. Iouinian. August. de Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no viduitat.</note> As oft as I expound not the Scriptures, but speake freely of mine owne sense, reprooue me who will. <hi>And Saint Augustine:</hi> The holie Scripture hath set vs a rule, not to dare to knowe more then it behoueth: My teaching of thee then, may not be any other thing, then to expound vnto thee the words of the Teacher <hi>that is of the Lord.
<note place="margin">Vincentius c. 2 &amp;. 22, &amp; 41.</note> And this is the same that Vincentius Lyrinensis saith vnto vs:</hi> The Canon of the Scriptures <hi>(saith he)</hi> is perfect, and superaboundantly sufficient in it selfe for all things. <hi>Wee are not then to make any addition of the Fathers, to make by them any supplie vnto the doctrine of the Scriptures: but rather (saith he)</hi> seeing that they may bee interpreted in diuerse senses, it is meete to ioine therewithall the authoritie of the Ecclesiasticall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing: <hi>Not to adde vnto, or alter any thing that is written, but onely to make for the vnderstanding of it. For, saith he elswhere,</hi> It is written, Depositum serua: That which hath beene committed of trust vnto thee, not what thou shalt haue inuented: That which thou hast receiued, not what thou hast found out, wherein thou must not be an authour, but whereof thou art a gardiant: not an ordiner, but a disciple: not a guide, but a follower. What thou hast receiued in golde, redeliuer the same in golde, &amp;c. And in the person of Timothie, this is spoken vnto all Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, it is spoken to the whole Church, &amp;c. <hi>And what we say of one of the Fathers, we take it as spoken of all togither: for although all the men of the world could bee assembled and called togither, and that euerie one of them were worth an Augustine, they could not make, or cause to be made one article of faith, to binde the faith of a Christian to beleeue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other thing necessarie vnto saluation, then that which is in the holy Scripture:
<note place="margin">Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>.</note> following that which Saint Paule saith:</hi> Though I my selfe, or an Angel from heauen, should preach vnto you any other thing, then that which wee haue alreadie preached vnto you, let him be accursed. <hi>And a little after he setteth downe the reason:</hi> For I haue
<pb facs="13"/>not receiued or learned it of any man, but by the reuelation of Iesus Christ, &amp;c. <hi>And this hath beene renued by all the olde Fathers, though but ill fauouredly kept by them which were their successours, and whereupon notwithstanding our maister Gerson, and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall Caietan after him, haue framed this conclusion:</hi> That the Church of this time cannot any more, neither hath bin able besides that which the Primitiue Church could, to canonize any booke, establish any article of faith, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>The second is, That we discerne in the workes of the Fathers, the true and legitimate bookes, from the faigned ones, not to attribute them vnto them, and by consequent sucke out of them an other mans errors, in stead of their sound opinions, &amp; not to receiue any doctrine for old, when as the same shall be either new, or else verie sparingly commended vnto vs of the ancients. For it cannot be denied, but that there are many such, and those easily found out, either by the stile, being otherwise in one age, then it is in another, yea differing in some one time of some one father, from that of another, or by some apparance of contrarietie, and that either in doctrine, or exposition, a thing hardly befalling any one authour, or by the alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of Authours which are notoriously knowne, not to haue liued till after them, or by the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of some tearmes and speeches, not as yet practised in the Church in their time, &amp;c. Of all which sorts, the malice of men hath furnished vs with sufficient store of examples. For the stile of the Epistles attributed to the first Bishops of Rome, is meerely barbarous and Gottish, in the times of the greatest flourishing of the Latine tongue: and when there could not bee found in all Italie, nor in all the Romane Empire, either learned or idiot, that could speake this language: The stile of Denys the pretended Areoopagite, is nothing like to Saint Pauls, containing nothing of Apostolicall note or marke, nothing of the spoiling of Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, so oft repeated by the Apostle: The treatise of Sina and Sion against the Iewes, &amp;c. nothing of that vigor which was in Saint Cyprian his other writings against the very same, but farre lesse of his elegancie, zeale, and doctrine: The pretended Canons also of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, how should they proceed from them, when they forbid that which the others approue? and command that which they do openly disproue and disallow? And therefore by so much the more daungerous and poisonfull, for hauing purloined the name of so soueraigne a drug. And in such sort we are likewise to say of Saint Clement his reuises, and Saint Peter his peregri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
<note place="margin">Hieronym. in Apolog. cont. Ruff in. Epiph. haeres. 27.</note> which Saint Ierome and Epiphanius do witnesse vnto vs, wittingly to hold and take part with the heresie of Eunomius and Ebion, the most pernicious ones that haue been in the Church: Of the vnperfect worke vpon Saint Mathew, wherein Arianisme sheweth it selfe most euidently, howsoeuer notwithstanding condemned and conuinced by Chrysostome in all his bookes, &amp;c. The Liturgie how can it proceede from S. Iames, seeing it euery where spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of this worde Consubstantiall? a name in his time not heard of in the Church? The booke of the Hierarchie, how can that be made by S. Denys, at least the Areopagite, seeing it citeth Clement Alexandrinus? Or that of Christian questions, Iustine Martyrs; seeing it speaketh of the Manichies?
<note place="margin">De variis quaest. q. 23.</note> Or how can that of diuerse Questions bee made by Athenasius, seeing it alledgeth Athanasius the great? That of the calling of the Gentiles, by S. Ambrose, seeing it speaketh of the Pelagians? Those by Clement, Abdias, and Iulianus Africanus, which are full of Temples, of Altars, and of Porches, of Sextens chambers, seeing they were built in the honour of Saint Iohn at Ephesus? That of the Resurrection in Ethiopia, &amp; that by the commaundement of S. Mathew, in a time when al Christendome dreamed of nothing but Martyrdome? When as there was nothing more busily prouided then pyles of wood to burne the Apostles, and their disciples withall? And when they prepared nothing but Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, from whence the people might behold them deuoured of wilde beasts? And yet forsooth these are the goodlie bookes, whereto our aduersaries for the most part doe appeale, for ayde
<pb facs="13"/>and that oftentimes in those things, which haue beene the cause why they were condemned of falshood, and which haue caused the Church to account of them but as fables. But after all, who knoweth not how greatly the heretikes haue giuen themselues to falsifie thē, how greatly they haue bestirred themselues, to slip in either some of their heresies,
<note place="margin">S. Hieronym. in Symb. Ruff.</note> as Ruffinus witnesseth in the bookes of Clement, and S. Ierome in many others: or of their Traditions, as it is easie to be obserued in those of the Montanists? And if further, according to the measure of the growth and getting of foote of errours in Christendome, the Church of Rome haue beene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so carefull, (as we haue seene at Trent) to cut off or alter in the bookes of the Fathers, what soeuer might be founde to impugne their superstitions: (and who can doubt of this practise to haue beene followed for the space of many ages, hauing beene guided by one and the same spirit) who shall be able to assure himselfe of the truth, sinceritie, and naturalnesse, euen of the most legitimate? Seeing in Gratian his Decretall, wee may marke so manie places of the Fathers and Councels notoriouslie corrupted, according as the authoritie of the Pope, or powerfulnesse of deceipt did growe in the Church, and tempered</hi> ad sensum currentem, <hi>as they call it, according to the disease of the time, and course of the Market? Seeing by name in the Copies of Beda and Theophylact, (who are of the time when the doctrine of the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charist began to varie,) we perceiue by the comparing of them with old bookes found in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasteries, places concerning this matter, either gelded or cut out or added and augmented? And thus also it is euen at this day, wherein great personages haue complained themselues, how they haue beene driuen to labour to discerne and finde out for vs, the stiles and spirits of writers: from whose paines taken herein, wee may ease our selues in the practising of this rule. And let this bee saide for no other ende, then of manie to giue an example in some few particulars of the cursed practises that Sathan hath continued in the Church, for the bringing in of his errours, vnder the name of the most approoued Teachers. And this veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie not newe or straunge, seeing that euen presently after the life time of the Apostles, if Saint Iohn, who ouerliued them, had not prouided against it, he had fathered some vpon Saint Paule, Saint Peter, and certaine others, and those also of the peregrination of Saint Paul and Thecla; which our aduersaries at this day labour to raise againe out of the graue, and to set in their former liuelihood and credite.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The third is; That we marke diligently if the father or ancient Doctor which we handle,
<note place="margin">To consider well if such father haue v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed a good translation.</note> haue followed a sound translation, haue well vnderstood the words and phrase of the Text in controuersie or not: for, for example, what apparance is there, that the Commentaries of S. Hillarie, or of S. Gregorie vpon Iob: of S. Ambrose, S. Augustine, or S. Bernard vpon the Psalmes, can alwaies reach vnto the sense and meaning, when they haue vsed a translation, wherein there are almost as many faults as words? That S. Anselme, or S.
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> Bernard should be able to gather good doctrine from that place, in the translation of Genesis;</hi> Ipsa conteret ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put Serpentis, the woman, <hi>and not Christ</hi> shall breake the Serpents head▪
<note place="margin">Gen. 4</note>
      <hi>Or out of that other, Gen.</hi> 4. Quam vt veniam merear: <hi>from whence our aduersaries gather the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of merit? There where it is:</hi> My punishment is greater then that I can beare. <hi>Whereas then we shall find that a Father shall haue followed a false translation, we shall not possiblie be able to come by a true exposition: so that in such case, we are to preferre and make more account of the least, that shall haue had it right, then him who shall haue followed the false, following the precept which they themselues did giue vs here tofore:</hi> That we are not to rest vpon the Latine translation, but to haue recourse vnto the originall and fountaine, whether Hebrew or Greeke.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>And now behold the fourth, which is, that when we are once agreed of the literall sense, we should weigh the expositions of the Fathers the Interpreters, both in the ballance of the
<pb facs="14"/>Scripture, and in the analogie of faith: respect their pietie, doctrine, and time wherein they liue, and receiue their opinions with reuerence: whether they shall be differing, or agreeing in one, or arising from diuerse and sundrie persons; let vs preferre that which is spoken in handling the place of purpose, before that which is spoken in touching of it by the waye: that which is saide in teaching familiarly, before that which may bee spoken rhetoricallie, as it somtimes falleth out in preaching: that which is spoken affirmatiuely, before that which is spoken doubtfully: that which is spoken from the proper sense of the Authour, before that which is spoken by imitating of another: that which is gathered from the literall sense, before that which is drawne from some allegoricall sense, which proueth not: and aboue all, that which is spoken of some place in cōtrouersie, before the controuersie rise, at such time as there is nothing sought after therein but the simple truth, yea or otherwise after it hath beene ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued, when as we shall haue searched out thereof, for the fortifying of our opinion. Here also will occasion be administred, to put difference betwixt the Fathers, according to the degree and qualitie that their doctrine and pure life hath aduaunced them vnto in the Church: for there is some such a one that is worth manie, according to their times; according, I say, as they haue beene nearer, or further off from the true light, seeing that Saint Ierome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth himselfe,
<note place="margin">S. August. ad Ianuarium. Bed. l. 4. in Sam. c. 2.</note> that he was in his time come vnto the lees. Saint Augustine;</hi> That all was now become full of presumptions, preiudicate opinions, and more then Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daicall Ceremonies. <hi>Beda likewise:</hi> That it was a lamentable thing, and not to bee vttered without teares, how that in his time the Church grewe worse and worse euery day. <hi>And this will proue true in counting cleane contrarie to our Iesuites: for they to cast dust in the eyes of the world doe tell vs: Such a one who liued</hi> 800. <hi>or</hi> 1000. <hi>yeares since, hath said this or that: whereas they should say, such a one who liued</hi> 200. 300. <hi>or</hi> 400. <hi>yeares next after the Apostles, hath spoken thus, &amp;c. For our question is not how long time a lie hath indured.</hi> The diuell <hi>(saith the Lord,)</hi> is a liar from the beginning: <hi>but what manner of doctrine that was which was first, that is according to Tertullian the truth, then, when, how, &amp; by what degrees, falsehood and lying sprung vp, increased and grew great, &amp; aduaunced it selfe against,
<note place="margin">Vincent. Lyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nens. c. 39.</note> and aboue this truth, &amp;c. And this is that which Lyrinensis saith:</hi> For the expounding of the Canonicall Scripture, we must summon and call togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the aduises of the fathers, but preferre that euermore which they haue spoken, either all or the greatest part of them, and that verie manifestly, often, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly, assuredly, &amp;c. what hath beene otherwise deliuered, what Saint, Martyr, or Teacher soeuer he hath beene, let vs hold it, inter proprias &amp; occultas, &amp; priuatas opiniunculas, for Apocrypha and priuate opinions.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Furthermore we are euer to proceed forward to the fifth: that they are to be read as great personages,
<note place="margin">That we must reade them in such sort as they will be read.</note> but neuerthelesse as men, whose writings cannot be equall with the Scripture, as little as their spirits can match the holy Ghost, yea such on the contrarie, as must be iudged by the scripture, examined one by another, euen the old with those which in regard of them are new, as they haue sufficiently learned in some places to reproue them, of whom they had beene instructed in many things,
<note place="margin">Cyr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>l in Leuit. l, 5.</note> according to the rule which S. Cyril giueth vs.</hi> If there be any thing in the scripture to be decided, besides the two Testaments, let vs know that we haue not any third, the authoritie whereof we are bound to receiue. <hi>This also is the same that the Fathers say vnto vs. S. Ierome,</hi> Let euery thing that shall haue bin spoken after the Apostles time be cut off,
<note place="margin">Hieronym. in Psal. 86.</note> let it not carrie any authoritie with it, how holy or eloquent soeuer the Author may bee.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Saint Augustine:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Augu. de vnit eccles. c. 6.</note> Reade to me of the Law, Prophets, Psalms, Gospel, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistles: reade &amp; we wil beleeue, &amp;c. <hi>Al others</hi> saith he, how holy or learned soeuer
<pb facs="14"/>they be; I read them, not to belieue that which they affirme to bee true, because they say it, but in as much as they proue it vnto me by these canonical Authors,
<note place="margin">Ep. 19. ad S. Hieronym. Ep. 111. &amp; 112</note> &amp;c. For how Catholike so euer they may be, there is alwaies something in their writings, which (their honour reserued) it is lawfull for vs to reproue, if it doe not agree with the truth. Thus am I affected in other mens writings, and such wish I them to be in mine, &amp;c. <hi>And if you would know of what manner of men hee pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poseth to speake, he speaketh of his owne bookes:</hi> Rest not thy selfe <hi>(saith he)</hi> in my books,
<note place="margin">Lib. 3. de Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. contr Cres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. l. 2. c, 21 Ep. 112.</note> but correct them by the reading of the Scriptures. <hi>Of those of Saint Cyprian:</hi> I doe not hold them for Canonicall; but I examine them by the Canonicall: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I find them conformable I praise him, where otherwise, there (with his good leaue) I reiect and forsake him. <hi>Of these, namely Saint Ambrose, and Saint Ierome,
<note place="margin">Contr. Faust. l. 11. c. 5. &amp; l. 2. Contr. Donat.</note> &amp;c.</hi> I purposed not <hi>(saith he)</hi> to intermingle their opinions, that so thou maiest not thinke that wee should follow the sence of any man, as the authoritie of the Scripture. <hi>Of all them in generall, that haue written since the time of the Apostles.</hi> In them all <hi>(saith be)</hi> the reader or hearer hath free iudgement, to approue or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouethem, not being bound of necessitie to belieue them, but with libertie of iudging, &amp;c. <hi>Yea, saith he elswhere:</hi> All the letters of Bishops, <hi>(without any excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to those of the Bishops of Rome)</hi> which haue beene written, or are written after the Canon of the Scriptures, may be reprehended by the Councels; and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinciall Councels giue place to the generall; and the first generall are oftentimes amended by the latter; Sine vllo typo sacrilegae superbiae, without any swelling of wicked pride. <hi>In like manner saith hee to Maximinus Bishop of the Arrians:</hi>
      <note place="margin">August. contr. Maxim. l. 3, c. 14.</note> I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge not vnto thee the Councell of Nice, <hi>(though the worthiest that euer was)</hi> by way of preiudice, neither alleadge thou against me that of Rimini: For as I hold not my selfe bound to the authoritie of the one, so neither doe I take thee to be bound to the authoritie of the other; wherefore let vs reason the matter toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the authoritie of the Scriptures, &amp;c. Of which onely <hi>(saith hee against the Donatists)</hi> by a speciall priuiledge, denied to all others that come after, it is not lawfull to doubt. <hi>And in the meane time Peter Abbot of Clugnt,
<note place="margin">Petr. Cluniac. l, 2.</note> amongst the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded errours, for which Peter Bruits, who read the Diuinitie Lecture at Tholosa, was bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, about the yeare 1200. obserued this:</hi> That hee belieued in the Canonicall Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture only, and would not consent that the Fathers had the same authoritie with it. <hi>And that this was the errour of that time, appeareth in Gratian; who liuing at this time, maketh the Decretall Epistles of the Popes, equall with the Epistles of Saint Paul; and falsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth Saint Augustine to fortifie his owne saying. How farre better dealt Gerson and the Count Picus of Mirandula, who doe more accompt of a lay man, an idiot, an olde man, a child, with a place of Scripture, then a Pope or vniuersall Councell without Scripture?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Now, who so shall read the Scriptures, and the Fathers vpon the Scriptures, furnished with these rules, calling vpon the name of God, and bringing a right zeale to the searching out of the truth: let vs not doubt but that hee may easily discerne of the controuersies of this time, as to know on which side truth or falshood is; as also the right and naturall interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of such places, as are in controuersie, as well as the peruerted and bastardly. Yea</hi> the Gentile himselfe <hi>(said Chrysostome)</hi> will learne by our controuersies,
<note place="margin">Chrysost hom. 33. in Acta.</note> to what Church he ought to cleaue; howbeit that both the one and the other do pretend Scriptures: seeing we say not that we belieue in humane reasons, that might be
<pb facs="15"/>able to trouble him; but in the Scriptures that are simple and true. <hi>And how much the rather then the Christian, who, as one would say, should be borne, fed and made, by the language of the Scriptures? And in deed I hope that in this discourse which wee haue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken of the historie and doctrine of the Masse; it will appeare from place to place, that it is altogether in vaine for the most part, that our aduersaries fortifie them selues with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; who verily if they were to come amongst <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> againe, would neuer acknowledge for their children, the deceits and abuses, that are authorised vnder their names.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>But as S. Augustine said;</hi>
      <note place="margin">August. Epist. 166.</note> We haue learned Christ in the Scriptures, as also wee haue there learned the Church: <hi>I dare also here say vnto you my masters; therein wee shall take knowledge of Antichrist; therein shall we obserue the corruption that hee hath brought into the Church: The corruption: for it serueth not any more either for seed graine, or grasse, as sometimes: The darnell &amp; good Corne alike perhaps, vntil the time of earing, would be able to deceiue vs a little; but growne into flower, and being come to their perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that filleth with the stench of the smell, and poysoneth with his vapour, all such as should stand a farre off: And euen so Antichrist; for there is no more any question of a starre, to conduct and guide vs to him; of seeking of him in a Manger, in his swathing band, or in his first infancie:</hi> As at such rime <hi>(saith S. Paul)</hi> as iniquitie began but to worke. <hi>For to make vs all inexcusable, the day of the Lord is come to his full height: He is seated vpon seuen mountaines; incamped in the Temple of God, extolling himselfe aboue God, extolling himselfe against God; working with all the efficacie of Sathan, in all powerfulnesse and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of lying; making drunke with his Cup, the Kings and Princes of the earth; opening his mouth in blasphemies against the highest, against his Christ, and vnder the name of Christ. All his properties, all his circumstances are therein so liuely painted out vnto vs; as that there is nothing wanting, but the putting to of his name: and yet that is also therein giuen vs in Cyphers in a mysterie; which succession of time, and the euident plainnesse of his effectes hath sith then deciphered. To you then my Masters vpon whome the last times are come, it belongeth to take knowledge of him; either by the pourtraiture which yee haue of him in the Scripture, or by his working which you see in the Church; or by his words, or by his workes. For then you shall not haue to say vnto vs any more: Who are you that declare him vnto vs? Where are your Commissions? Where are your Bulles? These are the petti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foggeries of the Court of Rome. It is said: that the Sonne of perdition shall cause a great Apostasie: Either we must turne with those of the Apostasie, or protest against it. But you should giue him thankes, that shall haue counsailed you to flie from the plague into your towne; from the Wolfe into your sheepefold; and from fire, into your barne. You should ring the alarum Bell your selues; to the end that men might runne thereto, that men might seeke to succour you.
<note place="margin">Apoc. 18.4.</note> You should come forth: for it is said;</hi> Come out of Babilon my people, <hi>with great haste, and without looking backe; for this is the spirituall Sodome: And it is said;</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 5. Apoc. 18. &amp; 19</note> My little children flie from Idols. <hi>And we all together will goe crying:</hi> Shee is fallen, shee is fallen: <hi>Yea we shall goe singing;</hi> Saluation, and glorie, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and power be giuen to our Lord God: His iudgements are true and iust: He hath reuenged the bloud of his seruants: He hath executed iustice vpon her which hath cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted the whole earth: The smoake thereof shall ascend for euer. AMEN.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>