<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NORABLE
Syr ARTHVR CHYCHESTER,
Knight, Lord Deputy of Ireland: And to the right
Honorable Sir GEORGE CARIE Knight, Barron
of Clopton, together with the Honorable Syr
THOMAS RIDGEVVAY, Knight Barrone
Viz-treasurer, and Treasurer at Wars in
his Maisties Realme of Irelande,
and one of his Maiesties pruie
Councell in that Realme.</title>
           <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115925_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10723</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21003</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115925</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NORABLE
Syr ARTHVR CHYCHESTER,
Knight, Lord Deputy of Ireland: And to the right
Honorable Sir GEORGE CARIE Knight, Barron
of Clopton, together with the Honorable Syr
THOMAS RIDGEVVAY, Knight Barrone
Viz-treasurer, and Treasurer at Wars in
his Maisties Realme of Irelande,
and one of his Maiesties pruie
Councell in that Realme.</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true and a kinde excuse vvritten in defence of that booke, intituled A newe description of Irelande : Wherein is freely confessed 1 The cause of the writing of that booke. 2 How that booke was brought into obloquy and slander 3 A reuocation of all ouersightes that through ignorance were published in that booke. 4 A bulwarke or defence of all truthes contayned in that booke. Pleasant and pleasing both to English, and Irish. By Barnabe Rych, Gent. Seruant to the Kinges most excellent Maiestie</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Adams, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>3, 25 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE
Syr ARTHVR CHYCHESTER,
Knight, Lord Deputy of Ireland: And to the right
Honorable Sir GEORGE CARIE Knight, Barron
of Clopton, together with the Honorable Syr
THOMAS RIDGEVVAY, Knight Barrone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
Viz-treasurer, and Treasurer at Wars in
his Maisties Realme of Irelande,
and one of his Maiesties pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uie
Councell in that Realme.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost Honorable Lords, and most Worthy
to be honored Knight. Let it not seeme
strang (with all humblenes I beseech it)
that I haue thus presumed to couple you
together in the patronizing of these lines
that are neyther vnbeseeming your great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes,
nor vnbefitting your worthines. For to whom doth
more properly belong the patronage of those things, that
(after a certaine manner) doe appertaine to the seruice
of his Maiestie then to those that are well knowne to bee
godly, wise, religious, and that are best affected to the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice
of his Maiestie?</p>
   <p>The matter that I haue taken in hand, (as time and
occasion serueth) requireth to be graced and countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced,
not onely by those that are great, but likewise by
those that are good, aswell by those that bee godly as by
those that bee in greatest Authority, and howe soeuer it
may bee sayd, it hath past the hands of a silly workman,
yet I am sure the stuffe is good: the which although I haue
not graced and garnished with that gorgious imbrodery,
that is looked after by curious eyes, yet I haue clothed
it with truth and plainenes. I would be glad to arme these
mine indeuours, with better deserts then to present them
<pb facs="3"/>
vnder the presidents of the widowes mite, or the smal pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
of water that was offered to <hi>Alexander:</hi> the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
are stale, &amp; too threedbare to bee presented to your
viewe, ouer worne indeede by euery bastard Poet: Let
mee then humbly offer them with a Souldiers faithfull
heart, that is still armed to the proofe to indeuour any
thing that may tend to the glory of God, to the seruice of
my Soueraigne or to the good of this distressed Country
of <hi>Irelande,</hi> wherein I liue and drawe my breath.</p>
   <p>Might it please you nowe but to vouchsafe mee a
fauourable acceptance, I shall number it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
your many fauours towardes
mee: And I will still rest my
selfe at your comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>In all humble and duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<hi>affection</hi>
BARNABE RICH</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>