<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST HONORABLE AND Reuerend Prelate Peter Aldo∣brandine, Cardinall of the holy Roman Church, Robert Bellarmine Cardinall sendeth greeting.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115760_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08035</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1840</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115760</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST HONORABLE AND Reuerend Prelate Peter Aldo∣brandine, Cardinall of the holy Roman Church, Robert Bellarmine Cardinall sendeth greeting.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A most learned and pious treatise : full of diuine and humane philosophy, framing a ladder, wherby our mindes may ascend to God, by the steps of his creatures. Written in Latine by the illustrous and learned Cardinall Bellarmine, of the society of Iesus. 1615. Translated into English, by T.B. gent</title>
                 <author>Bellarmino, Roberto Francesco Romolo, saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>—Recusant</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 575, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST HONORABLE AND <hi>Reuerend Prelate</hi> Peter Aldo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brandine, <hi>Cardinall of the holy Roman Church,</hi> Robert Bellarmine <hi>Cardinall sendeth greeting.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>IN September last by Gods assistance, I fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed as I was able, a Booke <hi>Of the ascention of the minde vnto God by the stepps of his Creatures.</hi> For hauing abandoned all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cares, I made choise to spend that Month by Licence of his <hi>Holinesse,</hi> in diuine contemplation.
<pb facs="5"/>And albeit I writt it one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for my priuate vse: yet through the perswasions and aduise of friends; I haue published it, and made it appeare vnder the protection of your name. For no sort of men may take more profitt thereby (if it shall profit any) then those which are most occupied in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique affaires, especially Prelats of the Church: Among whom you are not inferior vnto any; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Cardinal, an Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop, and Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine of the holy <hi>Roman
<pb facs="5"/>Church,</hi> and a <hi>Protector</hi> and <hi>President</hi> of the <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Inquisition.</hi> An other cause also why I Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate this booke vnto you, is to leaue vnto the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of posteritie some Monument of your great benefits vnto me, and of my thankfulnes vnto you therefore. Neither doe I doubt that the small<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse thereof will make it lesse grateful vnto you: for bookes are not to be esteemed by the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of their leaues: but by the fruitefulnesse of the matter whereof they
<pb facs="6"/>treate. As for this book how others will censure it I knowe not: but to me it hath prooued more profitable then my other workes: For which cause I vse not to reade my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bookes but vpon ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie: but this booke I haue willingly read o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer three or foure times, and purpose hereafter to read it often. Although perhapps not the desert thereof, but affection maketh it dearer vnto me; because I haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten it like an other <hi>Beniamin</hi> in my last olde
<pb facs="6"/>age. Receaue therefore most <hi>Worthy Cardinal</hi> this small present from me as a testimonie of my due obseruancie toward you: And as a Monitor execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Charge; that when the troubles of businesse ouermuch op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse you, and seeke to hinder you from your accustomed houres of prayer vnto God: it may modestly remember you to lay aside for a while all such affaires, and to withdrawe your minde vnto those inward and vsuall ioyes, that by
<pb facs="7"/>reading and meditating you may see <hi>That our Lord is God,</hi> to wit, the onely true, highest, and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting happinesse, in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining or loosing wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, mans greatest fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie or misery doth consist.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>