<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Maurus, Terentianus</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115974_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10801</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21074</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115974</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Maurus, Terentianus</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sacred septenarie, or The seuen last wordes of our Sauiour Christ vttered vpon the crosse, (with the necessary circumstances of the same:) : expounded by a commentary, gathered out of the holy Scriptures, the writings of the ancient fathers, and later diuines. By Alexander Roberts, Bachelour in Diuinity; and preacher of Gods word at Kings Linne, in Norfolke</title>
                 <author>Roberts, Alexander</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Samuel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 58, 2, 59-105, 3, 107-163, 3, 165-200, 2, 201-247, 1 page, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may iustly (Christiā Reader) be lyable to the censure, eyther of indiscretion, or presumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that I, who might haue lien hid in obscurity, should offer my selfe to the view, and sight of the world; &amp; so consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the sondry iudgements of the refined wits of this learned age. But yet herein I haue some refuge and excuse left; for I take not vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me <note n="a" place="margin">Scribo relato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris potius fide, quam Authoris praesumptione. Vincentius Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ensis aduere sus Haereses.</note> the stile, to be titled an absolute Author, but accounted a faithfull relator of that, which in former times holy Fathers, &amp; reuerēd Diuines of succeeding ages, haue committed to writing; and so shrowde my selfe vnder the wings of their authority. Yet if any shall conceiue, that euen in this I might haue made better choice of their sentences, and more artificial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly disposed the same, I will not stand to make any A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology for my selfe: for howsoeuer, it shall not bee vnprofitable, that I haue giuen the attempt, to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle an argument of so eminent quality, as is these <hi>heauenly and last speeches of our blessed Sauiour,</hi> because <note n="b" place="margin">Mens boni studij, &amp; pij rot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, si effectum non inuenerit caepti operis, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet tamen prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. Salulanus in praefatione ad libros suos de Gubernatione Dei.</note> where there is a good purpose, and a religious end propounded, though the effect bee not answerable,
<pb facs="4"/> yet euen those are not to be vnrespected. And it may be, that some hereby will be stirred vp hereafter (to whom God hath vouchsased more happy wittes, and greater lysure) to supply my wants, and amend my faults. In the meane while, happily time shall not be altogether euill spent, in reading this so inartifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally &amp; rudely penned Treatise. For oftentimes those who are fed with delicates, doe finde better <note n="c" place="margin">Saepenum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ro inter quatidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap> sapiunt, &amp;c. Gregorius Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ues in praef ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> suas in Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>phe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> taste, &amp; receiue greater contentment in homely and country fare then in their owne meates so exquisitely dres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed; or else haue their stomackes whetted, more desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously to eate of their owne former diet. And wee know that for the furniture of the Tabernacle, not onely golde, siluer, purple and precious stones were offered and accepted; but also goates haire, and bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers skinnes,
<hi>Exod.</hi> 25. 45. Neither am I ignorant, that Schoole diuinity, &amp; handling of controuersies, is now more in request then positiue; yet I thought it not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>sse, in this, rather then the other to bestow my paines. For <note n="d" place="margin">L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>icus
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> lib. 3.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap> discordia,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Carolum Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> it falleth out most vsuallie, that in the heate of contention, some men wrest the holy scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and stifly maintaine their owne conceits; onely that they might not seeme to consent in <hi>opinion</hi> with them, from whom they dissent in <hi>affection:</hi> whereby the truth of Religion is eftsoones
<note n="e" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>gn
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ibus
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>ribus,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>obscured,</hi> and our holy profession wounded, and such points of faith cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into question, (through importunity) which should haue continued vntouched, and vnmoued. For hereby weake consciences are vnsetled, all reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is made questionable, and holy discipline of life and conuersation vtterly neglected. And so thou hast (Christian Reader) the reason of my labour thus
<pb facs="4"/> imployed in this Treatise (first penned in Latine for my owne priuate vse, in the intermission dayes of a lingring Quartane, and then also Englished at the request of some friends;) which I submit to thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. He therefore who suffered those things for vs all, which euery one <hi>should</hi> haue done for himself, but none <hi>could;</hi> open the eyes, not of our bodies, as he did those of <hi>Thomas,</hi> but our soules, that wee may behold his side, and wounds, and bee rauished with the loue of that glory he hath prepared; vntill he shal shew (comming in power) that his face in the clouds which the wicked spitted on vpon earth, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the irreuocable definitiue sentence vpon all flesh, and take vs (whom he reconciled to the Father, for whom he died and suffered) vnto himselfe; that wee might be one with him, as he is one with God, who is with the Father and the holy Ghost, God e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, blessed for euer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>Forsitan, hunc aliquis verbosum dicere librum Non dubitet; forsan, multo praestantior alter Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>perta pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>et, quum plura inuenerit ipse; Deses, &amp; impatiens, nimis hac obscura putabit: Pro captu lectoris habent sua fata libelli, &amp;c.
<signed>TERENTIANVS MAVRVS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>