<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE EMPERIALL MAIESTIE OF GREAT BRITTAINE, FRANCE, AND IRELAND, KING CHARLES.</title>
           <author>Norton, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115254_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08347</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18673</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115254</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE EMPERIALL MAIESTIE OF GREAT BRITTAINE, FRANCE, AND IRELAND, KING CHARLES.</title>
                 <author>Norton, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The gunner : shevving the vvhole practise of artillerie: vvith all the appurtenances therevnto belonging. Together with the making of extra-ordinary artificiall fireworkes, as well for pleasure and triumphes, as for warre and seruice. VVritten by Robert Norton, one of his Maiesties gunners and enginiers</title>
                 <author>Norton, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Robinson, Humphrey</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 100, 99-158, 4 pages, 27, 2 leaves of plates (25 folded), illustrations (woodcuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                    <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_king">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE EMPERIALL MAIESTIE OF GREAT BRITTAINE, FRANCE, AND IRELAND, KING CHARLES.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lmighty GOD hauing made your <hi>Maiesty</hi> Soueraigne ouer many strong Nations, naturally Martiall, and Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially exercised in Armes: Yet if they want Discipline (though many) they are but few; and though else strong, yet therefore weake. Your mighty Kingdomes also being strongly situated by Nature, Intrenched about with a broade Dike the Seas, Pallisadoed with Rockes and Sands, Sentinelled with strange setting Tydes of Ebbes and Floods, Defended by frequent Stormes and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pests, highly Inritched with Fertillity of Nature, Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished plentiously with all manner of Matterialls fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the felicity of Mans life vpon Earth, both for time of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Warre;</hi> So that nothing can seeme to bee more wished for, if Industery bee vsed; but es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, if Correspondency bee found in a good and due temper betweene the Head and the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, as perfect Obedience and Seruice from the Members to the Head, and entire loue and care from the Head to the Members, for their good and safety. <hi>Gunnes</hi> your Maiesty hath, but want <hi>Gunners,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they want Respect and Encouragement: let
<pb facs="3"/>Occasions be ruled with Reason, VVarrs managed with Discipline, Iudgement, and Pollicie: Let stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne Offendors be punished, Deseruing Men pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, Eminent Places not granted for Fauour to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sufficient Men or Strangers, hauing honest Subiects farre more able to performe the Seruice: So we shall all make Holiday to serue our <hi>God,</hi> obey our <hi>King,</hi> and enioy Gods blessings bestowed vpon vs, <hi>euery Man Eating his Grapes vnder his owne Vine,</hi> without feare of forraigne Enemies: To conclude then, nothing can be wanting, Men, Money, Meanes nor Prosperity; when the God of Order hath setled such a congruity. Now that your Maiesty may the better be prouided hereafter of vnderstanding <hi>Gunners</hi> to manage your Artillery, the powerfull Regent of moderne VVarre: I haue endeuored in this <hi>Practice of Artillery,</hi> to supply their wants the best I can, not doubting but in short time it may worke good effect therein: If your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty will be gratiously pleased to countenance these few Lines vnder your Royall Patronage. My wrongs and discouragements hath hitherto hindred the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication hereof: VVhich, if your Maiestie would be pleased to referre to be examined and relieued accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly; It will then appeare I had cause to speake; And I should be againe encouraged for greater and further Seruices hereafter: So most humbly crauing pardon for my boldnesse, prostrating my selfe at your Sacred Feete, as by Oath and Duty bound, will euer remaine,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your most Faithfull and Loyall Subiect and Seruant, <hi>ROBERT NORTON.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>