<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most worthie, the most vertuous and godly Prince, Henrie, by the grace of God, Prince of Wales, Duke of Cornwall, Earle of Chester, and Heire Apparant of the Realme of great Britaine, France, and Ireland.</title>
           <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115897_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10701</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20983</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115897</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most worthie, the most vertuous and godly Prince, Henrie, by the grace of God, Prince of Wales, Duke of Cornwall, Earle of Chester, and Heire Apparant of the Realme of great Britaine, France, and Ireland.</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Faultes faults, and nothing else but faultes</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Chorlton (Charlton), Jeffrey (Geoffrey)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>3, 63, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the most worthie, the most vertuous and godly Prince, <hi>Henrie,</hi> by the grace of God, Prince of Wales, Duke of Cornwall, Earle of Chester, and Heire Apparant of the Realme of great Britaine, France, and Ireland.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Souldier (most gracious and worthie Prince) hath once againe betaken him to his Penne; he hath, to auoyd idlenesse, endeuored with <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitian</hi> to catch flies, he grasped at greater matters, then his abilitie was able to reach vnto. He meant to haue mounted the <hi>Alpes,</hi> that stumbled by the way at a sorie Mole-hill. But I see it is Souldiers lucke, for when they hope to effect wonders, they conclude with iust nothing. I dare not therefore present these trifles as worthie your gracious view, I know they are too slight for your greatnesse, and too meane a present for so high re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne: Shall I offer them yet vnder the examples of the <hi>Widowes mite,</hi> or, <hi>the handfull of water</hi> that was offered to <hi>Alexander.</hi> Me thinkes the conceit
<pb facs="3"/>is growne too stale, when euerie bastard Poet hath alreadie worne it threed-bare: no, I present them with a Souldiers faithfull heart, that is still armed to the proofe, to doe your Grace all humble and dutifull seruice. If my lines bee of little worth, your Graces name is of great worth, and inough to shrowde both them and me from the prowdest contemner. The rude Poet <hi>Cherilus,</hi> had nothing worthie to be noted in his verses, but onely the name of <hi>Alexander</hi>: And I confesse my fruites are too vntimely to be gathered in the age of this ripe and plentifull haruest. I haue therefore with <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilus</hi> the better to adorne them, humblie presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of that gracious fauour, that hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie tied me with all dutie and zeale, to lay my hands vnder your Highnesse feete.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces most humble and dutifull souldier: Barnabie Rich. </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>