<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A protestation of the Authour.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115299_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09002</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19294</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115299</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A protestation of the Authour.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A scholasticall discourse against symbolizing with Antichrist in ceremonies: especially in the signe of the crosse</title>
                 <author>Parker, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schilders (Grapheus, Painter), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Middelburg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 196, 18, 144, 8 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>X to the Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="note_from_the_author">
   <head>A protestation of the Authour.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S <hi>Augustine</hi> once thought it fitt, vpon occasion to make knowne, both <hi>whereof</hi> he stood in doubt, and also <hi>wherefore:</hi> so iudged I it my parte of late (touching the <hi>Cōtrouersies</hi> about the <hi>Ceremonies</hi>) to shewe in writing, both what the poyntes be I stood vpon,
<note place="margin">Augustin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Genefi. ad liter. lib. 10. c. 26</note> and what are my grounds and reasons. To this purpose I addressed a certayne Treatise (such as it was) against the <hi>Crosse:</hi> which I imparted to some of my friends: either to haue their censure of it, or to approoue my selfe vnto them in my forbearance to conforme. This being copied out by some (who I know not) was made more cōmon then I would: and that vnliked, &amp; more vnfashioned, then might be for my credit. By this meanes I was inforced to take penne in hande againe, &amp; to frame this sorie <hi>Treatise:</hi> as to set right what before was out of square, so to polish (as I was able) what was vnfyled, and to take in (by some additions) some things that wanted. Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I doe not know, into whose handes this poore labour of myne may come: therefore I begge of the indifferent Reader, to take knowledge before hande from me of these fewe things. First, let none thinke me to be one that standeth vpon termes of learning: I am too much priuie to ouermuch ignorance: I know well (although not so well as I should) <hi>quàm mihi sit curta supellex:</hi> besides I want bookes and conference, and my Schoole studies haue ben long discontinued. In regard hereof I am to craue common humanitie at the least, which is to read my abortiue ouersightes with due compassion: some of which I haue my selfe alreadie found: as Malta mistaken out of <hi>Surius</hi> for Nilenus: <hi>Nazianzen</hi> forgotten in Germanes allusion, and the time of the German triple Crowne, not so distinctly set down as it should. Secondly, as I doe not stande vpon any chalenge to learning at all, so neither doe I stande peremptorilie, vpon the assertions of this Treatise (not as if I doubted of what I haue written, whether it be true or not) but because my determination is no more, then to suppone and propound the reasons which I haue against the Ceremonies, and that <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis causae</hi> onlie, by way of disputation. To haue set downe euery thing with a <hi>Quaere,</hi> had bene for a Discourse vnfitt, to haue annexed to euerie period and proposition <hi>As it seemeth to vs,</hi> or <hi>As we thinke,</hi> absurd and tedious: I expect it shall suffice, that <hi>I protest</hi> here once for all, that these Clauses be vnderstood throughout this whole Discourse. What then? I
<pb facs="3"/>write here,
<note place="margin">in Psal. 85:</note> as <hi>Augustine</hi> elswhere, <hi>non tanquam affirmator, sed tanquam scrutator,</hi> which can any mislike? For a very <hi>Papist</hi> him selfe will haue leaue to dispute against a <hi>Synode,</hi> so he do it <hi>inquirendo non astruendo:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Nicol. Clau. disputat. de Concil. Melchior Canus. Amos 7.10</note> yea more, an <hi>Inquisitor</hi> him selfe giueth leaue to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect the corruptions of a church Leiturgie, so it be <hi>dolenter</hi> done, not <hi>calumniosè.</hi> Thirdly, because our Aduersaries racke our speeches, and oftentimes without all colour make them speake against the state (after the example of <hi>Amaziah</hi> against <hi>Amos, The lande is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to beare his wordes,</hi> and of <hi>Eusebius,</hi> the Court is against <hi>Laserius, Facis Imperatorem nostrum Nabuchodonosorem?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Theodorit. histor. eccles. lib. 2. ca. 16.</note> when he had pleaded in simplicitie, <hi>Non diminuitur solitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine mea verbum fidei, sic enim est olim tres tantum inuenti sunt qui edicto Regis non resiste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent</hi>): Therefore I protest, that whatsoeuer shalbe founde within this Treatise <hi>Reprehenso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riè,</hi> is intended of the Prelates and those Opposites of ours, that be Schollers and Diuines: it is not written of any Ciuill Magistrate, much lesse is it meant of <hi>his sacred Maiestie,</hi> (whom the Lord blesse, long to raigne ouer vs): so that I clayme here that common <hi>Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> of all ages, <hi>The King, and a mans owne Mother must be alwayes excepted when they be not expreslie named.</hi> Fourthlie, let no man say, I haue an ambition and vaynglorie, stuffed the margent with <hi>quotations.</hi> Being charged with <hi>Noueltie</hi> and <hi>Singularitie,</hi> I was in all wisedome to dye my selfe in a tincture <hi>concolor mortuis,</hi> as neare as I could. Being a <hi>dwarfe</hi> in stature likewise, I was to creepe vpon the shoulders of some tall men, and with <hi>Zacheus</hi> to clime some trees to see the better. Further, who knoweth not how much it auayleth with what arme a Dart is throwen, in which respect who can mislike, if wanting sides of myne owne, I haue vsed the strength of theirs who first or last haue fought the battayles of the Lord? Last of all, shall it be lawfull for our <hi>Opposites</hi> to rake out of the graue against vs, the <hi>rotten reasons of Papistes, Lutherans, Adiaphorithes:</hi> but vnlawfull for me to sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon auncient and reverend Protestantes, to beare witnes to the Trueth? This I speake, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause (pull the vizard away) and the souldiers with their muster against vs, will be found no other,
<note place="margin">Polycen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s de stratage.</note> then such as the soldiers of <hi>Gastro</hi> were, to wit, <hi>Aegyptians</hi> in <hi>Graecian</hi> harnesse: whereas on the other side none can iustlie censure me, who before condemneth not <hi>Enni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> and <hi>Naeius,</hi> I meane our auncient standerd bearers and forerunners in the faith. Fiftly, let no man put me to busines about the length of this Discourse, to which my earnest de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire carried me, which was to search euery corner of the controuersie which I handle with the lantorne of the <hi>Word,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pro. 20.27.</note> and by the light thereof, to scatter (as much as laye in me) the <hi>grosse corruptions</hi> that infecte the bowelles of our Churches. What that I may pleade ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample? For <hi>Clodis Tarcinensis</hi> wrote a verie great volume of the verie same argument,
<note place="margin">Ionas Anie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianens. de cultu Imag. lib. 1. Bonauentu. Vulcanius in epist. ad Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din. Belgic.</note> I meane against the verie hauing of Crosses and Images in the Church: and <hi>Nilus Suzice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> no lesse then 120. chapters in an argument of the same kinde, to wit, about the leauen. Hauing thus aduertised touching the purpose of my writing: I come to satisfie some of them who thinke I should not haue written at all: And of these Censors I obserue foure sortes. The first sorte doe iudge all contending about Ceremonies, to bee no better then vayne disputing, such as the Apostle doeth forbid. I aske: <hi>Are not Ceremonies matters of faith? Yea certainly.</hi> They are indeed <hi>matters of faith,</hi> and therefore not vaine, but neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie to be knowne and discerned by vs.
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.5▪</note> That we may not guesse, but clearely vnderstande how they are all <hi>established,</hi> or <hi>condemned</hi> by Gods word. Howbeit were they but thinges indifferent, as indeed they are not in Gods worshipp; yet must they not (specially in this vse) be done in <hi>faith?</hi> or can there any faith be of them that is not grounded on the word, which is the only word of faith? It is sufficient if the scripture be not against them. True: but (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> of olde) <hi>If the scripture doeth not permit them, it doeth forbid them,</hi> and <hi>sine lege &amp; contralegem</hi> (<hi>as in Policie,</hi>
      <note place="margin">lib. de Cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. milit. Thom. Mor ton. Apolog pa. 2. lib. 1. cap. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Idem p. 420 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eza Annot. in 1. Cor. 11 10. 1 Cor. 11.7.14.16.34</note>
      <hi>so in Diuinitie</hi>) <hi>are both one.</hi> In deed if not <hi>viua ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio</hi> out of the word, yet <hi>manifesta aequitas</hi> alwayes is euer needfull to the very circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Gods seruice: as for lawfulnes so for expedience: expedience I say, and the same, not onely generall according to the perpetuall circumstances which cleaue to their kinde: but also speciall, according to the occasionall circumstances that occurre in their particular practise. So much is manifest by Paule who proueth the Expedience of the vayle (a ciuill custome in the Church of Corinth) by reasons drawen from the lawe of God and Nature, before he forbiddeth <hi>cōtending</hi> against it: and putteth ouer the ordering of other circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of celebrating Gods publique worship in that Church, till by <hi>oculata experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> he had seene their estate, and weighed what was most conuenient. What whē this course is not obserued? Why men are set to eate their meate without salt (saieth <hi>Hierome</hi>) when they are commaunded any thing that hath no relishe from the worde: and to builde without haye and stubble, like Israel in Egypt, when they bee not allowed some warrant out of the Scripture, which only can combine the matter of the worke, &amp; make the frame
<pb facs="3"/>of the building sure. But <hi>Augustine</hi> will haue vs followe a Synode of a Church <hi>etiam latente veritate.</hi> What and will he haue vs followe it too, without vsing the meanes that may bring the trueth to light? No, but here he requireth euen <hi>certa documenta,</hi>
      <note place="margin">lib. de pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. merit &amp; remiss ca 36 Fasc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>cul. rer. expetend. ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic. 18. folio 129. in 1 Cor. Homil. 13. Rom. 14.5.</note> out of the worde to the commaundements of the Church: euen as <hi>Iohn Wiclephe</hi> taught since his time. We must take nothing from the Prelates which is not <hi>clarè,</hi> euen <hi>clarè</hi> demonstrated by the scriptures. <hi>Chrysostome</hi> giueth a reason hereof: Our cogitation halteth, when the worde wanteth, which halting is sinne, because we are bounde to the <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> of a full perswasion euen in indifferent things and all. And in this Controuersie of the Ceremonies the trueth is not <hi>latens.</hi> I trust this verie Discourse will shewe there is not onely no reason to conforme, but also reason strong and euident against <hi>Conformitie:</hi> at the least I doubt not, but it wil cleare vs from that <hi>stomacke</hi> and <hi>stubburnes</hi> wherewith we are vniustly bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened, as bearing vs witnes we are the men that keepe the olde rule, <hi>Non est a consue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine recedendum facile, nisirationi aduersetur.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Augusti. de Mufic. lib. 2. cap. 8. Tertull. de veland virg. Digest. lib. 1 Ticul. 3. cap. 39. Tho. Aqui. sum. p. 2. q. 92. art. 3.</note> for which wee protest according to the auncient tenor, <hi>Nullam respicimmus consuetudinem quam damnare non possu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus:</hi> and therevpon call at the Tribunall for that olde sentence, <hi>Quod non ratione in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troductum est, sed ex errore primum, deinde consuetudine obtectum est, in alijs simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus non obtincat:</hi> in the Schooles, for that Decision Theologicall, For asmuch as the law Diume proceedeth from the will of God, the Humane onely from the wil of man, <hi>vsus authoritati cedat, prauum vsum lex &amp; ratio vincat.</hi> The second sorte of our Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors, though they mislike not all sticking at Ceremonies, yet all standing they condemne against an Order once established in a Church. What, and haue we then liued to the time to heare <hi>Sion</hi> speake in <hi>Sorbons</hi> language: No further reason must be sought, then a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodes owne authoritie, that which the wiser sort of Papistes them selues condemne?
<note place="margin">nicol Clau. collat. de Concil. Cyril Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rosol ca. 4. Mat. 23.8.</note> Sure to beleeue any, or each <hi>simpliciter dicent,</hi> vpon his bare worde: is to sett vp a Maister on earth, to no small preiudice of our Maister in heauen, whom we are onely in this maner to beleeue. It is also to inthrall the Church to a seruitude Babylomeall, if not worser, for so much as some childrè of Babell her self, refuse to bowe downe their neckes to this yoake, as we see by <hi>Alphonsui,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Alphons. de Cast. cont. haeres. lib. 1. cap. 7. Martin Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther li. cont. papat. Nicol. Clau. disputat. de Concil.</note>
      <hi>Miserrima seruitus est</hi> (saith he) <hi>iurare in alicuius verba Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistri.</hi> I omitt to obiect here, yea so much to inquire, whether the Synode that made this order, sate as Iudges in their owne case, which is against the lawe of <hi>Nature:</hi> whether they assumed an Immunitie to them selues, to haue al accusing of them reputed schisme, which is our exception against the Concill of <hi>Trident.</hi> whether they came resolute against Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and fully bent to make such Decrees as best might strengthen their owne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states, whereby the Concill of <hi>Pisa</hi> once barred and shut out the Holy Ghost from their assemblie: whether the name of the house it self knew not of many Canons made, as at the second Councell of <hi>Ephesus</hi> many subscribed to what they knew not. Last of all, whether some Canons were only read, as at the Diet. of <hi>Augusta</hi> the <hi>Jnterim</hi> was proposed only by the Chaūcelour of <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, &amp; so thought sufficiently ratified, although the States and Peeres there present, neuer gaue their voyce to it. The Inquisition of these things and other the like, I say, I omitt. This is the answere I rely on: the Reformation we seeke,
<note place="margin">Zepper de polit, eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siast. in epist. dedicator.</note> is in substance the same, which not one, but many: Why speake I of many? which euen all the godly Synodes haue agreed on, that haue bene gathered from time to time, since the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storing of the Gospell, in all the Churches best reformed beyond the Seas. The third sort of our Censors will giue vs leaue, to gainsaye a <hi>Peter,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Nilus Thes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salonicens. de precat. Papae.</note> when in Ceremonies hee walketh awry: howbeit in conference to his face onely and not in writing. <hi>Nilus</hi> supposed it was in vayne to debate with the Pope, alwhile he looked to bee iudge him selfe, and doe the Prelates looke for lesse? The Bishop <hi>Argensius</hi> found by experience in the Councill of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sile,</hi> that there is no dealing with Superiours who expect the inferiour must <hi>succumbere:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aeneas Sylu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> in gest. Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cil. Basiliens. lib. 1. Polydor. Virgil. de Inuentor. rer. li. 8. ca. 4 Augustin. epist 174. Carol. Sigō. de regn. Ital. lib. 9.</note> and doe not the Prelates expect asmuch? <hi>Luther</hi> stept away from <hi>Caietan,</hi> euen after the listes were entred, because he saw he would <hi>magis imperio rem definire, quam disreptatione:</hi> and haue we not cause to suspect them &amp; feare the same of the Prelates? <hi>Augustine</hi> when he conferred with a great man, he was ouercome, though not <hi>veritate,</hi> yet <hi>clamore:</hi> and it was giuen foorth against him, that he was foyled when he was not: and haue former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences with the Prelates sorted to any better euent? For my owne parte I had a priuate defence for my selfe. <hi>Albericus</hi> was better at writing, then at disputing: so is it with me, by reason of the dulnes of my witt, I must plodd on what I doe, and when I haue aduised my selfe all that I can, yet all cometh short of that which should be. The fourth and last sorte of our Censors, mislike not writing, saue at this time, when wee should busie out selues (they thinke) about more needfull matters. Certaine it is that we their mistake. For it is an <hi>Hercules</hi> that is fitt to throw out the <hi>dounge</hi> it selfe of Poperie: such as I am, serue best,
<pb facs="4"/>to sweepe downe (as they are taken) the <hi>Cobwebbes</hi> of it which yet remayne in the house of the Lord. When the Cobwebbes fell downe all on a suddayne at the Councell in <hi>Trul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,</hi> the Fathers there present tooke it as ominous:
<note place="margin">Concil. Tom. 2 p. 895. Caro. Sigon. vbi. supra. p. 49</note> so may we nowe our selues learne from it how cleane the house of the Lord must be kept from al coinquination with hereticques. Suppose the Ceremonies were no more then that they are taken, the <hi>cobwebbes of poperie?</hi> Doe not euen cobwebbes foster poysonful spiders? sure these cobwebbes of ours doe. And see ye not how they haue gotten euen to the verie toppe of the Pallace, as Salomon spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth? Shall we suffer them there with silence?
<note place="margin">Pro. 30.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> must we not write to sweepe them downe at the least from thence? And let others looke to those matters, which some repute only able to shake the mountaynes of our religion, whom the Lord (as a Father speaketh) hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp into the mount: my standing is at the foote of the hill, therefore it shalbe inough for me to acquite the place I stande in, from those corruptions, Which howsoeuer counted <hi>molehilles,</hi> yet much molest the holy vineyard of the Lord. Euen this also must needes be done by some or other. For though the people were foolish, whom <hi>Gerebrard</hi> mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, who thought the moūtaines were endangered as often as the Moales did wagg: yet I remember I haue read that euen Moles in <hi>Thessalie</hi> once ouerthrewe a whole Towne:
<note place="margin">Plin. histor. lib. 8. c. 29.</note> sure I am (I see it with my eyes and am sorie) that these <hi>Moles</hi> against which I write, haue euen alreadie annoyed, if not vctie neare decayed diuerse goodly Cōgreganous. And as for the time,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 16.9</note> where is assistance to the trueth most necessarie, but where it hath most aduersaries? It is time for the asse him selfe (saieth one) to open his mouth,
<note place="margin">Gildas de excid Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. in proaem. Inc. 19.40.</note> when things runne to ruine. And our Sauiour, where other witnesses doe fayle, let the stone him selfe crie. These pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises considered, I am not deterred from proceeding to the Search following, into which I now enter in the name of the Lord: premising that common and beaten rule, <hi>non est obstinatus qui paratus est corrigi:</hi> for which I finally protest with <hi>Iob:</hi> Teach m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> and I will holde my tongue,
<note place="margin">Iob. 6.24.2.26.</note> and cause me to vnderstande wherein I haue erred? How stedfast are the wordes of righteousnes, and what can any of you iustly reproone? Doe ye imagine to reproous words that the talke of the afflicted should be as winde? Now therfore be content to looke vpon me, for I will not lye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your faces.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>