<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right honorable Sir Tho. Egerton knight, L. Keeper of the great Seale of England, one of her Maiesties most honorable priuie Councell.</title>
           <author>Powel, Gabriel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115017_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09887</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20150</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115017</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right honorable Sir Tho. Egerton knight, L. Keeper of the great Seale of England, one of her Maiesties most honorable priuie Councell.</title>
                 <author>Powel, Gabriel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The resolued Christian, exhorting to resolution : Written, to recall the worldling, to comfort the faint-harted, to strengthen the faithfull, and to perswade all men, so to runne, that they may obtaine. By Gabriel Powel</title>
                 <author>Powel, Gabriel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Bushell, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 302, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right honorable <hi>Sir Tho. Egerton knight,</hi> L. Keeper of the great Seale of England, one of her Maiesties most honorable priuie <hi>Councell.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable, I make bolde to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent vnto your Lo. patronage this smal Trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tise: the Subiect whereof, affoording store of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, to fight against the allurements of the world,
<pb facs="3"/>the frailty of the flesh, and the feare of death, is ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther triuiall nor vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table: the maner of hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, furnished with sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of holy Scripture, fraught with exampls, &amp; garnished with variety of familiar similitudes, not affected nor vnpleasaunt: the Vse, to recall the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly worldling, to comfort our distressed frend, &amp; to
<pb facs="3"/>solace our owne soules, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fruitfull &amp; necessary: &amp; the End, to strengthen the faithful, to arme them with Faith &amp; Patience, against the serpentine as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saultes of the Children of Babylon (who long since haue heated their furnace hoter than that of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchad-nezzars, wherin they are ready to throwe all those that will not fall
<pb facs="4"/>downe and worship their golden Image) a strong &amp; necessary prouision. Thus not doubting of your Lo. good liking, &amp; acceptance hereof, such is your zeale to Vertue and Piety: and humblie entreating that your L. good fauor which hath bene so much enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged towardes Doctor <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel</hi> my Father (who now with the Lorde hath rest
<pb facs="4"/>from his labors) wil not be straightned vnto vs, his poore Children: I beseech the Lord Iesus blesse your Honour, and make you zealous more and more, for the Gospel: giue you a swift foote to hunt out the Bulles of Basan, and the wily Fox-cubbes that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy the yoong Ʋines: heape vppon you his bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings spirituall and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall,
<pb facs="5"/>that in a good hope you may runne your race, and in the end, obtaine the high price of your calling.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships to commaund, <hi>Gabriel Powel.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>