<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>G., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115990_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68659</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21055.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115990</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>G., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A vievv of the civile and ecclesiasticall law : and wherein the practice of them is streitned, and may be releeved within this land. VVritten by Sr Thomas Ridley Knight, and Doctor of the Civile Law</title>
                 <author>Ridley, Thomas, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Turner, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 277, 25 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Learned and usefull View of both the Lawes, once more adventureth it selfe upon the Opinion of Men, and it may now hope to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a more indifferent cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure then before, as being committed to a season more mature, and more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly dispos'd; for howsoever the Time that first brought this forth, could not be charged with any notable distemper; yet the Common-wealth wee live in is of that thriving nature, that however the present time may still bee good, yet it alwayes makes the succeeding Age better then it selfe. This argues the State not neare her ruine, though some unruly Spirits, led by an irregular Motion, have beene bold to anticipate; as if every one that bad so much pitty as to feare, had also judgement
<pb facs="3"/>
enough to foresee the ruine of a Kingdome. 'Twas more then enough for such Men to set downe the Fate of a single-soule, without resolving upon the doome of a whole Nation. But these that would seeme to know such high things, are most properly punished by being neglected: for to a Man that would bee thought to know, and knoweth not, no greater miserie can happen, then that hee should faile of his Expectation. If I were to serve or follow any time, I would propose the Present, which as it hath lesse of the pretences of former Ages, so it hath much more of the Moderation: and if it needs must be suspected that the State is not farre from her fall, let this be the onely rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, because she draweth so neere to her perfection. That which heretofore most of all incumbred these Dominions, was the disproportion of the Civill Power to the Ecclesiasticall. This a Great Prince abated, and the Act was truly masculine, yet like those of the strongest importance, would not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by the same hand; therefore it was by him so fully done, on the one side, that it might be feared lest it should runne over on the other. To prevent this, the discretion of these late discerning times hath warily provided; the wisedome of the Prince
<pb facs="3"/>
having so well tempered both the Powers, that it may now be hoped, they shall agree one with an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as both doe in him, by a glorious correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. The State thus bending towards the best, and thé most perfect mediocrity, this Author whose hope that alwayes was, couldnot but revive again; therefore it is, that though hee be dead, hee yet speaketh. If still there be that will reprehend these our paines, as if they were cast upon a man too much sought after, be it so; but these men have least cause to complaine, for if the matter of this Booke be, as they suppose, then the onely way to suppresse it will be to make it common, for things of that nature are least of all enquired for, when they are most easily to be found; but if they rarely appeare, they are more eagerly sought after, and the more obstinately esteem'd.</p>
   <p>VVhen first I would see this Treatise, I beheld it at a distance, and not without some prejudice; for so I was prompted by the insinuations of a fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Report; but finding it under the Protection of the High and Mighty Prince <hi>Iames,</hi> I tooke libertie to resolve against all popular contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And now, to seeke any other Patron for this new Edition, I have thought it altogether inglori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>For what can the man doe that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth after the King?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For a Note or two, which I have here and there timerously let fall, If the Reader expect that I should aske his pardon; there may bee cause, but there is no convenience: for this kinde of Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is now adayes indifferently set before those things that are well, and those that are ill done. Besides, it would argue Certaine follie, to be enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged there for pardon, where our choyce is to offend. VVhat I have here done amisse, I shall hereafter hope to rectifie, either by doing something that shall be better (if that may be) or (which is the safest way) by doing so no more.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>I. G.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>