<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>In honour of the Translator.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115671_Fr1_7_17</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17832</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4510.8</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115671</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>In honour of the Translator.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Britain, or A chorographicall description of the most flourishing kingdomes, England, Scotland, and Ireland, and the islands adjoyning, out of the depth of antiquitie : beautified vvith mappes of the severall shires of England: vvritten first in Latine by William Camden Clarenceux K. of A. Translated newly into English by Philémon Holland Doctour in Physick: finally, revised, amended, and enlarged with sundry additions by the said author</title>
                 <author>Camden, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Latham (Lathum, Lautham), George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, Elizabeth.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Young (Junius), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 822, 233, 59 pages, 50 plates, mostly folded, illustrations, maps, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>In honour of the Translator.</head>
   <l>THe <hi>PEN</hi> unspoild, though worne beyond a Pen,</l>
   <l>The <hi>HAND</hi> unwearied, though with toile opprest:</l>
   <l>The <hi>HEAD</hi> diseas'd for ease of Englishmen,</l>
   <l>(Yet still hold out) in motion heere doe rest.</l>
   <l>They rest in motion; restlesse nest is that;</l>
   <l>Yet that's the rest thy Pen, thy Hand, thy Head</l>
   <l>Deere <hi>HOLLAND</hi> hath; which all (untir'd) translate</l>
   <l>The greatest Volumes, greatest Braines have bred.</l>
   <l>Life being so short as from the Birth to Beere</l>
   <l>Is but a span; all times may well admire</l>
   <l>How so much may be onely written here,</l>
   <l>Where toile makes that short life more soone expire.</l>
   <l>Had I an Angels tongue, or else a Pen</l>
   <l>Made of his Pinion (might I judge of thee)</l>
   <l>I should so speake and write that Gods and Men</l>
   <l>Should see a Miracle of thee through me.</l>
   <l>For, <hi>NATVRE</hi> workes but still to hold her state;</l>
   <l>And for that worke alone neglecteth all:</l>
   <l>But thy workes doe her power in thee abate,</l>
   <l>For others good; that's supernaturall.</l>
   <l>So th'art a Miracle of Men, for Men;</l>
   <l>Yet if this Miracle be thought untrue</l>
   <l>To thy good <hi>HEART,</hi> from thy Head, Hand, and Pen</l>
   <l>Give what is right, and then all is but due.</l>
   <l>To count the Volumes most voluminous,</l>
   <l>Which thou translated hast with care (past care)</l>
   <l>And Art (past Art) were but superfluous:</l>
   <l>For, all doe know them, sith they famous are.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>NATVRES</hi> great Secretarie thou didst teach</l>
   <l>To speake such English, as (though he be high</l>
   <l>In cloudy-matter) English eies may reach,</l>
   <l>His highest Pitch: that tries the Eagles eie.</l>
   <l>The <hi>Roman</hi> most renown'd <hi>Historian</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <hi>Trajans</hi> great <hi>MASTER<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> Moralls (boundlesse bookes)</l>
   <l>Smooth <hi>Tranquill,</hi> and the rugged <hi>Ammian,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Thou mad'st as smooth to speake, as <hi>Venus</hi> lookes.</l>
   <l>And, for thy last, (but so it cannot be</l>
   <l>If life doe last, for still thou wilt be doing)</l>
   <l>Here is a <hi>WORKE</hi> translated now by thee,</l>
   <l>For which we long the Learned have beene wooing.</l>
   <l>In this, through thee, wee see (as in a Glasse)</l>
   <l>The wrinckled Face of grave <hi>ANTIQVITIE:</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Thy passing Autor here himselfe doth passe</l>
   <l>Or'e whom thou raign'st while he doth subject lie.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Camden,</hi> whose Fame nor Seas, nor Lands can bound</l>
   <l>(Yet they best know him farthest from our ken;</l>
   <l>For, English least doe know his voices sound)</l>
   <l>Is made more famous by thy famous Pen</l>
   <l>For, now the English knowes his worthinesse:</l>
   <l>His Countrimen now see him as he is:</l>
   <l>Before, they at his vertue could but guesse;</l>
   <l>And guesse by Artlesse Aimes, that often misse.</l>
   <l>Yet, Man of Art, behold! for all this All</l>
   <l>How thou art subject (that deseru'st to raigne</l>
   <l>In all mens loves) to hate of great and small,</l>
   <l>That to be learn'd alone, take envious paine;</l>
   <l>Who seeke, for Knowledge onely to be knowne:</l>
   <l>("For, who know most, are knowne still most of all)</l>
   <l>They deeme Wit, Folly; that to all is showne;</l>
   <l>And Goodnesse, Badnesse hold, if generall.</l>
   <l>Who knows the voice of Envy, theirs doe know;</l>
   <l>For, Envy speakes but onely by their tongues,</l>
   <l>Who being a devill speakes (she cares not how)</l>
   <l>By borrow'd Organs which to them belongs.</l>
   <l>Alas poore Snakes! (base Envies Instruments)</l>
   <l>Poore in your Wit, and way-ward in your Will)</l>
   <l>Yee little learne, so, hate the Ornaments</l>
   <l>Of Arte in greater Wits of lesser skill.</l>
   <l>Did ye not doubt your owne defect of Wit</l>
   <l>You would all Artes should still be showne to all▪</l>
   <l>And let the best Wit make best use of it,</l>
   <l>For Wits renowne, and letters liberall.</l>
   <l>Yea, you would wish the Babylonian towre</l>
   <l>Were yet to build, while all one tongue impart▪</l>
   <l>That so, sole Wit might be Arts Governour,</l>
   <l>Not tongues, that are the Essence of no Art.</l>
   <l>But were yee good, and would all <hi>Good</hi> should know.</l>
   <l>Who Envy this more learn'd, lesse-envious man,</l>
   <l>You would the frankest praise on him bestow</l>
   <l>That makes th'unlearn'd a learn'd Historian.</l>
   <l>Shall English be so poore, and rudely-base</l>
   <l>As not be able (through meere penury)</l>
   <l>To tell what French hath said with gallant grace,</l>
   <l>And most tongues else of lesse facunditie?</l>
   <l>God shield it should; and Heav'n foresend that we</l>
   <l>Should so debase our owne deere mother-tongue▪</l>
   <l>That shewes our thoughts (how ever high they be)</l>
   <l>With higher tearmes, and el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>quence among,</l>
   <l>Then, let me muzzle those so d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>gged mouthes</l>
   <l>That byte and barke at what they should defend:</l>
   <l>They lies doe love, that hidden would have Truthes:</l>
   <l>And he is Vertues foe that's Errors friend.</l>
   <l>But, kind <hi>Philêmon,</hi> let thine active Muse</l>
   <l>Still mount above these base detracting spirits:</l>
   <l>Looke not so low as Snakes that men abuse,</l>
   <l>And highest Fame shall crowne thy lowest merits.</l>
   <l>Goe forward (maugre backward Envies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rabs,</l>
   <l>That still goe backe) thy paines give others pleasure:</l>
   <l>They play proud <hi>Miriams</hi> part, thou <hi>Ionada<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s</hi>▪</l>
   <l>They skant our learnings lists, thou giv'st us measure.</l>
   <l>This <hi>Camdens-Britaine,</hi> that on wings of Art</l>
   <l>Flies or'e the World, knowne least where most it ough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>,</l>
   <l>There thy free Pen to all doth it impart,</l>
   <l>And mak'st them learn'd that almost are untaugh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>.</l>
   <l>For, <hi>Camden</hi> (whose all time out-wearing fame,</l>
   <l>Sith he the learned hath so often gladded)</l>
   <l>Hath, by thy Pen, now multipli'd his Name:</l>
   <l>For, now to <hi>Camdens Britaine, Holland's</hi> added</l>
   <l>Then, pregnant <hi>HOLLAND, Britaine</hi> fertile mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>▪</l>
   <l>With learnings compost; till the croppe of Art</l>
   <l>Be ready for our neighbours Sithe, and Rake,</l>
   <l>That have lesse skill, than will to take our part▪</l>
   <l>So shall this soile (when thou art soile or sand)</l>
   <l>Call <hi>Camdens-Britaine, Hollands</hi> richest land▪</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>The unfaired honourer of thee and thine indeavours. JOHN DAVI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>S of Hereford.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>