<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Randall, Joshua</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115645_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10398</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20682a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115645</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Randall, Joshua</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Three and tvventie sermons, or, Catechisticall lectures upon the sacrament of the Lords Supper : preached monthly before the Communion. By that late able, and painfull preacher, Master Iohn Randall Bachelour of Divinitie, pastor of Saint Andrewes Hubbart in little Eastcheap London, sometimes fellow of Lincolne Colledge in Oxford. Published by his executor Iosh. Randall, as he found it corrected by the authors one hand, in his study, since his death</title>
                 <author>Randall, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Clifton, Fulke</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 235, 1, 317, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, here is (by a divine hand and providence) through many difficulties presented to thy view, and committed to thy considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the faithfull labours and painfull endeavors of that late painfull Preacher, and faithfull Minister of Christ <hi>Iohn Randall,</hi> Bachelor in Divinity, sometime Fellow of <hi>Lincolne</hi> Coledge in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and late Rector of Saint <hi>Andrew Hubbart</hi> in little <hi>East<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheape London;</hi> whose learning and Religion is sufficiently declared in these sermons concerning the Sacrament of the Lords Supper: a worke perfected in his life time, found in his study under his owne hand, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>all but two sermons, which in his life time were lent (as is seemes) but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver returned, which with much paines at the length by the love of some unexpected friends are obtained. Other of this Authors workes are extant, published by that late Minister of Christ <hi>William Holbrooke:</hi> Compare these and them together, and I hope thou shalt finde in them a parity and lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nesse, so that they will appeare children of the same fath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ey have beene viewed and approved, and are now pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>or the common good: If thou read with that affection <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> was caried in delivering, I doubt not but thou sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> much sweetnesse in the increase of grace, and strength <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> with Christ for the fitting thee for glory, which is the thing in truth of affection I wish to thee for thy endlesse and eternall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. Thus intreating thee to beare with my rudenesse, and to afford thy earnest prayers to God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> his blessing upon the work, that it may profit in the thing intended. I take my leave.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Resting thine in any thing in the Lord for the furtherance of thy Faith, <hi>IOSHVA RANDALL.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>