<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Ridley, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115990_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68659</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21055.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115990</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Ridley, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A vievv of the civile and ecclesiasticall law : and wherein the practice of them is streitned, and may be releeved within this land. VVritten by Sr Thomas Ridley Knight, and Doctor of the Civile Law</title>
                 <author>Ridley, Thomas, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Turner, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 277, 25 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, I confesse, as I meditated this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise upon mine owne motion (as I doe somtimes matters of other argument, when my leasure serves mee thereto) so also I doe not set it out to the view of the world upon mine owne motion, but was desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous it should have beene kept in, saving that I must obey where I am bound. The thing that gave mee cause to this meditation, was, that I saw many times how meanly men e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steemed of the Civile and Ecclesiasticall Law of this Land, valuing them by the practice of so much of them, as we have among us. And therefore I thought good, although not wholly to unfold the riches of them, yet to make shew of them folded up, in such sort as Mercers make shew of their silkes and velvets, laid up in whole peeces in their shops; whereby it may bee seene, what great variety they have of all these kinde of wares, although the goodnesse of the ware it selfe cannot be discerned, because it is foulded up: Besides, seeing how frequent prohibitions are in these dayes in causes of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cognisance more than have beene in former time, I thought it not unworthy my labour to inquire and see upon what just grounds they are raised up in this multitude; not of any humour I have, to gainesay the lawfull proceedings of any Court (which I reverence and most readily acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge their authoritie in all things belonging to their place) but to know and search out the truth of those suggestions that give cause unto these prohibitions. For whenas such Lawes as are written of these businesses, are written indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, as well for the one Iurisdiction as the other, no man is to be offended if the one Iurisdiction, finding it selfe pres
<pb facs="7"/>
sed by the partiall interpretation (as it supposeth) of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, inquire the ground of such interpretation, and labour to redresse it if it may be, by the right interpretation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: To the end, that either Iurisdiction may retaine their owne right, and not the one bee overtopt by the other, as it seemeth to be at this day: And that in such matters (as they concerne) of their owne right, as depend of no other autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie but of the Prince alone: which is the thing onely that is sought in this little Treatise. And therefore the Reverend Iudges of this Land are to be intreated, that they will vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe an equall interpretation of these matters, as well to the one Iurisdiction as the other, for so it is comely for them to doe; and if they doe it not, the other are not so dull-senced, but they can perceive it, nor so daunted, but that they can flie for succour unto him, to whose high place and wisdome, the deciding of these differences doth of right appertaine. <hi>PENELOPE</hi> is said to have had many wooers comely in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and eloquent in speech, but shee respected none but her owne <hi>ULYSSES:</hi> Such should be the minde of a Iudge, that whatsoever other appearance or shew of truth be offered, one saying, This is the true sence of the Law, and an other that; yet the Iudge should respect none but the very true germane and genuine sence thereof indeed. Which if it were religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously or indifferently observed in every Court, then needed not this complaint that now is, but every Iurisdiction should peaceably hold his owne right, such as the Prince, Law, or Custome hath afforded unto it.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>THOMAS RIDLEY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>