<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONO∣RABLE, CHARLES LORD HOWARD, BARON OF EFFING∣HAM, LORD HIGH ADMI∣rall of England, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Hood, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115226_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03580</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13701</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115226</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONO∣RABLE, CHARLES LORD HOWARD, BARON OF EFFING∣HAM, LORD HIGH ADMI∣rall of England, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Hood, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vse of the two mathematicall instruments : the crosse staffe, (differing from that in common vse with the mariners:) and the Iacobs staffe: set foorth dialogue wise in two briefe and plaine treatises: the one most commodious for the mariner, and all such as are to deale in astronomicall matters: the other, profitable for the surueyor, to take the length, height, depth, or breadth, of any thing measurable. Set forth by Th. Hood. mathematicall lecturer in the citie of London. Newly reviewed, and the second time imprinted. The staues are to be sold in Marke lane, at the house of Francis Cooke</title>
                 <author>Hood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Dexter, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE, CHARLES LORD HOWARD, BARON OF EFFING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HAM, <hi>LORD HIGH ADMI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of England, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I presented this little booke in writing vnto you (right Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) I did little thinke that it should haue come vnto the Printers hand: but the Staffe being shewed vnto diuerse men that were desirous to know the vse thereof, I thought the labour would be too long to teach euerie one, and to write it out continually, the pains would haue bin much more. Therefore to saue both my paines in writing, and my labour in teaching, I could finde no better meanes, then to commit it vnto the presse. Considering then that it must abrode, I beseech your Honour, that it may appeare vnder your name, that as it pleased you at the first to giue it a friendly entertainment, so now you would also be Patron vnto the same, that your authority protecting, and your wisdome allowing it, you may stay the vnaduised censure of some rash conceipted men. Wherby I shalbe both encoraged to a further study, and bound to pray for your Honours increase in all good things.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors most humble, <hi>Thomas Hood.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>