<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the valiant Captaynes and renow∣med Souldiours of Englande, Barnabe Riche wisheth for their better encouragement, en∣crease of credit, estimation and necessarie maintenance, according to their due desertes.</title>
           <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115900_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68649</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20979</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115900</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the valiant Captaynes and renow∣med Souldiours of Englande, Barnabe Riche wisheth for their better encouragement, en∣crease of credit, estimation and necessarie maintenance, according to their due desertes.</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Allarme to England : foreshewing what perilles are procured, where the people liue without regarde of martiall lawe. With a short discourse conteyning the decay of warlike discipline, conuenient to be perused by gentlemen, such as are desirous by seruice, to seeke their own deserued prayse, and the preseruation of their countrey. Newly deuised and written by Barnabe Riche Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Middleton, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Barker, Christopher</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>102 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the valiant Captaynes and renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Souldiours of Englande, Barnabe Riche wisheth for their better encouragement, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of credit, estimation and necessarie maintenance, according to their due desertes.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough (right noble Captaynes and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Souldiours) I may seeme too rashe and bolde to enter into those discourses so farre surpassing my capacitie, the which I knowe I haue finished not according as the argument hath required, but according as the slendernes of my skyll would permit me: yet I protest, I haue not taken in hand to write, for any vayne glory or presumption in my selfe, but rather to incite some one amongst you, that is more able &amp; sufficient, to performe a greater enterprise, to a much better perfection: and for my parte, I haue but vsed the office of the meanest labouring man, &amp; (as it were) haue but brought lyme and stone together, wherewith the master worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man maye erecte his building in braue and sumptuous sorte.</p>
   <p>Thus crauing pardon for this my bolde attempt, I sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit altogether what I haue done to your noble iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, to correcte and amende what you shall see needfull and requisite. And thus I rest, yours to dispose</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Barnabe Riche.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>