<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, IAMES BY THE GRACE OF GOD KING of great Brittaine, France, and Ireland, Defender of the faith.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115095_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07799</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18176</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115095</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, IAMES BY THE GRACE OF GOD KING of great Brittaine, France, and Ireland, Defender of the faith.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A catholike appeale for Protestants, out of the confessions of the Romane doctors : particularly answering the mis-named Catholike apologie for the Romane faith, out of the Protestants: manifesting the antiquitie of our religion, and satisfying all scrupulous obiections which haue bene vrged against it. Written by Th. Morton Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Morton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 680, 20 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, IAMES BY THE GRACE OF GOD KING of great Brittaine, France, and Ireland, Defender of the faith.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongst all the bookes, which of long time haue bene published by the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane presse (most renowned and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soueraigne) the late <hi>Apologie of the Romane church</hi> may seeme both in the Prefaces, and progresse thereof to haue deserued your Maiesties most fauorable acceptance. In the diuerse Prefaces whereof your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie is saluted in those due, and almost proper attributes of <note n="a" place="margin">In the Epistle dedicatory to the Parliament.</note>
      <hi>Princely and Christian wisedome, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing fountaine of Grace;</hi> your Nobles and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators of State in the Epithets of <hi>Honorable Peeres, and graue Sages;</hi> your Diuines and other Protestant-Doctors with at least the adiunct of <hi>Learned.</hi> Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise than the Romish Jnquisitors haue done, who, lest that a Protestant King might obtaine in the world the cōmendation of <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Edouardus se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>tus Angliae Rex, admirand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> indolis adoles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens. Haec po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strema verb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> deleantur.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>x Hisp. fol. <hi>148.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Admirable towardnesse;</hi> or a Duke the title of <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>Natus est Christopherso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus praeclarue Dux Wittéber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gensis. Deleatut verbum, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarus.</hi> Ibid.</note>
      <hi>Excellent;</hi> or lest our publike writers (espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb facs="3"/>
Caluine) might be named <note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ceru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>logus Deleat it ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>bum, Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logus.</hi> Ibidem. <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
               <desc>•••</desc>
            </gap>ldenco Zum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>o Theologo. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>atur. Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logo.</hi> Index ib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d</note>
      <hi>Diuines,</hi> yea or else so much as <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>upprimatur nomen Caluini, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>onatur, studio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus quidam.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> 2 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>at one of their Prosel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap> ran from Men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>z to R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>me to change <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> name of <hi>Calumus</hi> into the a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> of <hi>Baromu.: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> illo Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>o longè re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legato, me tuo proprio (Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, cognomine omāsti, &amp; locu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletash, &amp;c.</hi> Iustu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Calu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nus alias <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Veteracastrensi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. sacr. l. <hi>1.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>p. <hi>1 Melancthonis &amp; ahorum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num omittan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> Index Belg. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ud Iunium. pag. <hi>164.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>named</hi> at all; have commanded all such like Ascriptions to be <hi>blotted out.</hi> Which publike perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinesse these <hi>Apologists</hi> may seeme by this their more ingenuous dealing to checke and controll, except that they will be thought to haue vttered the voices <hi>Temporum potiùs quàm hominum.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Concerning their progresse. Although the <hi>Apologie</hi> be farre from that absolutenesse, which the publisher thereof pretendeth, who iudgeth it to be in some things <hi>demonstratiuely vnanswerable,</hi> as other Romanists do likewise conceiue: yet notwithstanding whatsoeuer Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of singular moment is vsed in the volumes of the Romish Doctours, or what colourable accordance soe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hath proceeded from the pen of any learned Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant, which appeared in anie degree aduantagious vnto their Roman cause; that seemeth herein to haue bene col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, vrged, and reinforced against vs with as singular choise of matter, with as ponderous weight of cōsequence, with an as exact and exquisite a method and style, together with as sober a temper of speech, as they by their diligence, iudgement, wit, Art, and moderation could easily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme.</p>
   <p>This seene, forthwith our most reuerend, carefull, and religious Metropolitane commanded a certaine num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Diuines, then at hand, to employ their studies for the perfecting of a satisfiable Reply: which had accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly bene sufficiently accomplished, had not the heate of the common sicknesse, and other their importunate oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences hindered their indeuours. At what time the
<pb facs="3"/>
burthen (my occasions then better sorting) did (yet not by choise but by chance) fall vpon me, the weakest and vnworthiest of those parties assigned: which, notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, after a due perusall of the <hi>Apologie,</hi> I did at length vndergo, not vpon presumption of any singular dexterity in my selfe, but as in confidence that God would enable me hereunto, he being <hi>In minimis maximus,</hi> and often choosing the <hi>weake things to confound the strong:</hi> so also vpon an experience that diuerse Romish Doctors would be at hand ready to lend me herein their best support.</p>
   <p>Which kind of assistance of <hi>learned Aduersaries</hi> the Apologists themselues <note n="f" place="margin">In the Epistle dedicatory to your Maiestie.</note> haue layd downe for the <hi>grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test reason of satisfaction,</hi> and we do accordingly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. For if it be held an excellent point of physicke, <hi>Ex Vipera theriacum,</hi> to turne poison into an Antidote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst poison; and in God accounted an high degree of vengeance, to <hi>turne the Aegyptians against the Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Esay. 19. 1.</note> and in Dauid celebrated as a principall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of triumph, to <hi>cut</hi> off <hi>Goliah</hi> his head with his <hi>own sword;</hi> and in Christ obserued as an vnanswerable ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of conuiction to iudge the euil seruant from his <hi>owne</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luc. 19. 22.</note>
      <hi>mouth;</hi> and acknowledged in S. Paul as the most expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite means of confutation of the men of <hi>Crete,</hi> to oppose <note place="margin">Tit 1. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> against them their <hi>owne</hi> Poet, whom he calleth their Prophet: thē may we iustly presume better of our cause, wherein our Romish Aduersaris will proue our rightfull Aduocates.</p>
   <p>For which cause I doubted not to answer that, which they haue vniustly intituled, <hi>A Catholike Apologie out</hi>
      <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
         <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
      </gap>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>