<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the High and Mightie Prince IAMES, by the grace of God, King of great Britaine, Fraunce and Ireland, De∣fender of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Ridley, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115989_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10783</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21054</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115989</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the High and Mightie Prince IAMES, by the grace of God, King of great Britaine, Fraunce and Ireland, De∣fender of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Ridley, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A vievv of the ciuile and ecclesiastical lavv : and wherein the practise of them is streitned, and may be relieued within this land. VVritten by Thomas Ridley Doctor of the Ciuile Law</title>
                 <author>Ridley, Thomas, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>—English Stock</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Islip, Adam.</publisher>
                            <publisher>—English Stock</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 230, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the High and Mightie Prince IAMES, by the grace of God, King of great Britaine, Fraunce and Ireland, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the Faith, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST gratious Soueraigne, since it hath pleased your Maiestie of your Princely care towards the Church, and your common wealth, to take knowledge of some differences that are in Iudicature betweene your Ecclesiasticall and Ciuile Law, and the Temporall Law of this Land (by which ioynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly your Maiesties State is managed next after your owne most rare prouidence, and the wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of such, whom it hath pleased your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to associat vnto your selfe in the great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of your Kingdome) I haue bin bold to offer vnto your Maiestie this simple Treatise, as
<pb facs="3"/>
that which doth lay out the cause of those Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences more particulerly than any man hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto hath expressed the same. In comming to which (because I doe speake for those parts of your Maiesties Laws, which are lesse knowen vnto your people, and esteemed no otherwise of them than they see the practise thereof to be here within your Land) I haue thought good, as it were in a briefe, to set out the whole sum of both the Lawes to the view of the people, that they may see there is more worth in those for whom I speake, than was by many concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to be: so that the profession of the Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticall and Ciuile Law may appeare to the world, neither to be ilde nor vnfit for the State; so far as it hath pleased the Royall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessors of your Highnesse to giue entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnto it, and your Maiestie your selfe to admit of it. In al which there is no other thing sought, than that such grieuances as haue bin of late offered by one Iurisdiction vnto the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and in consequence, to all your subiects, who follow any suits in the Ciuile or Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall Courts, may by your Princely wisdome be considered, and by your authoritie be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dressed, if they be found to be grieuances in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed:
<pb facs="3"/>
for now as things are, neither Iurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on knowes their owne bounds, but one snat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth from the other, in maner, as in a batable ground lying betweene two Kingdomes; but so that the weaker euer goeth to the worse, and that which is mightier preuailes against the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: the professors thereof being rather wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to giue Lawes and interpretations to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, than to take or admit of any against them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues. For which, the weaker appeales vnto your Highnesse, humbly desiring your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties vpright and sincere Iudgement to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne where the wrong is, and to redresse it accordingly, which is a worke worthy your Maiesties high consideration. For as the Land is yours, so also the Sea is yours, &amp; the Church is vnder your Highnesse protection, as a child is vnder his Tutor; so that all the Lawes therof appertaine vnto your Maiesties care and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort alike: For which, not onely the whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of your Ecclesiasticall and Ciuile Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers that now are, but those which shall suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in those places for euer hereafter vnto the worlds end, will praise and magnifie your Maiesties gratious fauour towards them, and wee that now are will pray to God for the
<pb facs="4"/>
long and happie prosperitie of your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and your posteritie ouer vs, during the continuance of this Heauen and this Earth, and after the passing away therof, a perpetual fruition of the new Heauen and the new Earth, wherein righteousnesse onely shall dwell for euer.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties most humble and dutifull Subiect, Thomas Ridley.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>