<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115632_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69038</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4284</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115632</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The theatre of Catolique and Protestant religion : diuided into twelue bookes. Wherein the zealous Catholike may plainelie see, the manifest truth, perspicuitie, euident foundations and demonstrations of the Catholique religion; together with the motiues and causes, why h should perseuer therin. ... Written by I.C. student in diuinitie</title>
                 <author>I. C., student in divinity</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Boscard, Charles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>632 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="9" facs="5"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Certaine Protestant (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) quassinge, and caurroussinge in a place, cried out against the Pope, which is a custome nowe a dayes, aswell with the meanfest, as with the greatest, &amp; cheefest personages, hauing their ministers at their elbowe when they are at meate, to sclander the Pope, Priestes and Catholikes. I woulde they had read and obserued the verse of S. Augustine.</p>
   <q>
      <l>
         <hi>Quisquis amat dictis absentum rodere vitam,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Hanc mensam vetitam nouerit esse sibi.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Who soe speakes ill of those that absent be,</l>
      <l>Forbidden is this tables companie.</l>
   </q>
   <p>But these men when they are in their greatest dissolution, then they raile against religion, which should bridle, and restraine them from their rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, and wanton excesse. This partie being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by a certaine Catholike gentleman, that was at the boorde, began presently to defend his liberty, and licentiousnes by holy scripture, and by the wordes of our Sauiour mistaken &amp; ill applied, answered, that whatsoeuer enteretd into the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, doth no harme to the soule, but that which co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from the harte. This is noe newe practise in
<pb n="10" facs="6"/>
the malignant Church, as Eusebius saith of the Heretike Cerinthus, who because he was giuen to the bellye and beastly pleasures, framed holy scripture accordinge to his sensualitie, as this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant alleadged Scripture against fastinge, and began to prouoke the Gentleman to dispute with him; who answered him, that it was not his part to reason or iudge of holy Scripture, being soe mysticall, and so far exceedinge his capacity, es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in such disordered places amoungest the cuppes; the fruite whereof would rather tende to confusiō, then to edificatiō or deuotiō. The Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stante replyed, that if any man could answeare to his demaundes or questions at the full, and satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him truly and effectually, he would become Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike: the Gentleman said he would doe his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to propounde such demaundes to others; and soe he went vnto the cheefest protestants of that place, who haue sett downe these challenges &amp; deliuered thē vnto the said gent. who deliuered them vnto me; beinge in one house with him.</p>
   <p n="2">2 These propositions were nothinge else, but the old heresies of auncient hereticks, and were long since condemned, and anathematized by the auctority of the Catholike Churche in all ages, wherein those heretikes did springe vp. As by S. Peter against Simon Magus. By Liberius the Pope, S. Athanasius and S. Hillary, against Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius. By S. Damasus, S. Gregory Nazianzen &amp; S. Basil against Macedonius. By S. Celestinus Pope and S. Cyrill of Alexandria, against Nesto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius. By S. Leo against Eutiches. By Irenus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<pb n="11" facs="6"/>
Valentine. By Tertulian against Marcion. By Origine against Celsus. By S. Cyprian against Nouatus. By S. Hierom against Heluidius; Ioui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian, Vigilantius, Luciferans. By S. Augustine against Donatists &amp; Pelagians. By Agath against Montolistes. By Tarasius against Imadge break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. By Lanfrancus, Guitmundus and Algerius, against Beringarius. By Petrus Cluniacensis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Henricians and Petrobrusians, and against Adelhard. By S. Bernard against Thomas Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>densis, and Witcleefe. By the Bushoppe of Roche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, as well by his bookes as by his blood, against Luther and Zuinglius. By Kinge Henry the 8. himselfe, against the said Luther, whose booke I haue. Finally by soe many generall Councells of the world in all ages, and by the most famous &amp; generall Councell of Trente, which sate vpon this matter the space of 16. yeares.</p>
   <p n="3">3. Touching the aforesaid propositions, truly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> was loath (though earneastly entreated by the Gentleman) to trouble myselfe to answere them, and that for many causes. First for that Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantes are voide of all humility, whose religion is nothing elce thē a peruerse and self-wild denial of religiō, neuer learning the trueth simply but op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugning it wilfully. The second, because whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Protestants write, they doe it not nether for gods sake, or for their owne edification, but for the destruction and confusion of others, as Luther himselfe their Author did confesse disputinge with Eckius, who said, that it was not for godes sake, he tooke that matter in hande: and therfore none
<pb n="12" facs="7"/>
more maleparte or sawcie then they be,<note place="margin">
         <p>Osuis. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de here. Sur. hist. Anno. <hi>1519.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Beza in pref. noui testam. An <hi>1565.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Tom. <hi>2.</hi> Lib. <hi>3.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae to. <hi>5</hi> ad Galat. c. <hi>3.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Beza act. c. <hi>10.</hi> in pref. noui test.</p>
         <p>Mus. in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis cōmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nib. c. <hi>10.</hi> Bren. in Apolo. conf. wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenb. c. de cōcil Calu. de vera eccl. refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat.</p>
         <p>Musc. de comm. loc. c. de mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strat, inter. prep locor. commu. Martyr de votis.</p>
         <p>Illir. pref. noui testa. Pet. in pref. <hi>1.</hi> cor. Humfred. in vit. Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elli par. <hi>212.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Calu. in pref. instit. ad Regem Galli.</p>
         <p>Martyr de votis pag. <hi>566. 10.</hi> res. Camp. <hi>5.</hi> ratio.</p>
         <p>Beza ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empla Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca.</p>
      </note> for they denie all groundes of disputation; all traditions of the Apostles, Doctors, Councells, and testimonie of holy Martyres. For as when S. Augustine, and the holy Doctors of the Church, reasoned with the Donatists, Arrians, Maniches, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and vrged them with the aucthoritie of godes Church, with the iudgmente of the sea A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolique, with the succession of Bishoppes in the same, with the Councells, and finallie with the name Catholike, those heretikes quite reiected all those groundes and meanes of tryall: euen so Luther the captaine and ringleader of these late heretiques said. I set not by a thousande Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stines, and a thousand Cyprians alleadged against me alone: calling S. Augustine, S. Hierom and S. Gregorie, the Iustices af the Papisticall king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Thus also did that proud Beza, charge O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigines with blasphemie, adding that neither S. Chrysostome, nor any of the Greeke fathers, did euer declare the trueth simply: &amp; charged Saint Hierom with shamles errors, as inuocation of Saincts, and the practise of chastitie or virginitie in the Church. Musculus also said, that S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom did deserue rather hell then heauen. Brentius did charge the first Councell of Nice with foule er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors. Caluine called the fathers thereof Lunatick and francticke people. Musculus saith, they were instigated and led by the diuill, and that all Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uncells were pernitiouslie fallen into errors. Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banus Regius said, that in the best tymes of the Church, Sathan ouerruled all Bushoppes. Peter
<pb n="13" facs="7"/>
Martyr called the aunciente Fathers, pratlers, but no diuines. Illiricus reiected the said Fathers. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Martyr also said, that as longe as men relie v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Fathers, they must be deluded with er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors. Doctour Humfrie at Oxford said, that Iuell gaue a great scope vnto the Papists, and did him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe greate wronge, in alleadginge the Fathers for himselfe: for what haue we to doe with fleash &amp; and bloud? The same also Caluine and Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr wrote. Whitakers also vnto Doctour Sanders answered sayinge. We care not for your histories. Doctour Toby Mathewe said to Father Campion. If he should beleue the Fathers, he could not be a protestante. Beza cried out against Athanasius, and the Fathers of the Councell of Nice, for that (saith the) Athanasius found out this Tripartite god (he meant the blessed Trinte.) He said also that he Fathers of that Councell were blinde so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phists, the ministers of the the beast, &amp; the bond-slaues of Antechrist.</p>
   <p n="4">4. The third cause of this mine auersion was, because protestantes are hard to be reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: for that amoūgest all the sects that euer were none were more inconstant, or variable in their Doctrine then the Protestants. For neither birdes, or beastes (as Plinie saith) doe watche to breake other birdes egges, or destroie others of-springe,<note place="margin">Plin. na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural. hist. lib. <hi>10.</hi> c. <hi>74</hi>
      </note> as these Protestantes watche to destroye and abrogat the Doctrine which was hatched before them: so as whatsoeuer the first gospeller doth settle, the whelpe that comes from him doth destroye it: as in steede of many examples the confession of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gusta
<pb n="14" facs="8"/>
may serue for one, so called for that in that citty,<note place="margin">
         <p>Colloq. al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenbar. f. <hi>4 39.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Colloq. al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenb. fol. <hi>464.</hi>
         </p>
      </note> the Lutheranes did exhibit to Charles the 5. a booke wherein were written all the articles of their Doctrine, which was 50. times chaunged and mangled, as they themselues affirme, in all which, the last is nothinge like the first, and soe, they call it. <hi>Cothurnum &amp;c.</hi> A dislikinge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the rest, notwithstandinge Luther said it to be. <hi>Fundamentum quod hactenus papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stis opposuimus.</hi> The fundation which hitherto we opposed against the Papists, the grounde of our religion according to the word of god, and the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie rule of the peace and establishinge of trāquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie in Germany (saith he) but in very trueth was the cause of all the warres, and troubles thereof: and which was abolished out of Germany, yea out of Augusta it selfe, and within fewe yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came zuinglians &amp; Zuingfeldians, and is in noe place accepte in Saxonie: For other sectes (with which that miserable Country doe abounde, being in nūber 20. as Stanislaus Rescius describeth) carrienge with thē all the sway, did steppe in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moungest them, and so at the last Luthers Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine was vtterly reiected. Count Palatines Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untry can beare witnes of this mutabilitie, which from Zuinglianisme, turned to Lutheranisme, &amp; againe from Lutheranisme to zuinglianisme.<note place="margin">Smidlerus in vita Bullen. f. <hi>15.</hi>
      </note> As also vpper Germany when one Prince, or great su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendent dies, the people after their death doe change their religion.</p>
   <p n="5">5. England alsoe cannot denye this to be true, which a certaine Pope many hundred yeares
<pb n="15" facs="8"/>
prophesied of them, saying. English men, of all nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ons are most inconstant and waueringe in their faith, the time shall come (saith he) that when Christendom shall haue most neede of them, they shall suarwe from their faith, and fall into sectes, and heresies. For in our daies it changed her religion 4. times within 30. yeares: vnder kinge Henry the 8. kinge Edward his sonne▪ Queene Marie; and Elizabeth; And as Fox saith, kinge Edward beinge a childe after his fathers funerall, by the instigation and settinge on of his Vncle the Duke of Somersett, did abolish the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which his Father had by lawe ordained viz. The six articles, containing. 1. The trueth of the Reale presence. 2. That both kindes for all persons, are not necessarie. 3. That marriage of Priests is prohibited by the lawe of God. 4. That Vowes and votaries are confirmed by the lawe of God. 5. That the Masse is agreable to Christes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tution. 6. That Auricular confession, is war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by the word of God. This kinge sett foorth two bookes of reformation &amp; afterwards a third. These articles of our faith were made at one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemente by the said kinge Henry the 8. and were abrogated as superstitious inuentions by another Parleamēt. <hi>Anunas &amp; menstruas fides,</hi> as Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larie and S. Basil say of the Arrians, euery newe yeare and moneth a newe faith. And what I pray you can be amoungst Christians, more dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracefull then this? For ought not our Religiō, &amp; euery article thereof, to be as the same S. Basil saith; <hi>eadem heri, hodie &amp; in saecula?</hi> to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt
<pb n="16" facs="9"/>
noe change, but to continewe his vigor, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well yesterdaye, to daye, as alsoe for euer? Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording whereunto our Sauiour alsoe saith, that heauen and earthe shal passe, but my wordes shal not passe, nor any iott, nor sillable thereof till al be fulfilled. Is there any Christian to be found, who dares be so bould to say that our Parlament exceedeth the power of God? But god by his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute power (as Aristotle and all diuines, and Philosophers affirme) cannot make two contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories or contraries to be trewe, because of the implication therein (for if the one be trewe, the other must be false) and truly noe more can these opposite and contradictorie Parleaments, be pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siblie true.</p>
   <p n="6">6. The 4. cause was, that Protestantes make but a mockery of all religion, for that they follow Nicholas Machauailes precepts, holding that the Catholike religion is a hinderance to state, and that Princes shoulde followe that religion (though the groundes thereof be neuer soe false) which doth aduance their present estate: but contrarie to this S. Thomas saith, that wisdome and power are companions of trewe religion, which when it fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, the power of state alsoe faileth: <hi>non veniat anima mea,</hi> saith S. Bernard, <hi>in Concilium e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum qui dicunt &amp;c.</hi> my soule shall not follow their Councells who say, that the exaltation and and peace of the Empire, will hunder the peace of the Church. If Iustice be a vertue to giue euerie man his owne, to giue to Cesar his owne, and to God his owne, how doth the Prince keepe Iustice
<pb n="17" facs="9"/>
with god, that takes from God his righte, which is religion, &amp; depriues his diuine maiestie of that worshipp &amp; reuerēce which is due vnto him? This is proued, for that Princes followinge this false reason of state, haue beene put by God frō their state, as Ieroboam the seruant of Salamon, to cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinewe himselfe in the kingdome which he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from Roboam, did alter the Religion &amp; made a false religion. For he made two golden calues, one at Dan, and the other at Bethell: and also al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the order of priestoode, by ordaininge others that were not of the order of Leuie. For which both he and his yssue were depriued of their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and destroied of their liues. The Princes of the Iewes, by reason of their state, put Christ to death, least the Romaines shoulde come vpon thē, neuerthelesse the Romaines came vpon them, and destroyed them.</p>
   <p n="7">7. Vetiza a kinge of Spaine and his succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor Rodorigus, fearinge the rebellion of their sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, for their owne wicked actes, destroied and rased downe all the stronge holdes of Spaine: which was the cause that, that Country was broughte in one quarter of a yeare in subiection by the Moores, which were not expelled Spaine in 700. yeares after. The kinges of Fraunce, Francis the first, and his sonne Henry the second, the one brought in the Turcke, thinckinge to bringe him in to Spaine against Charles the fift Emperour &amp; kinge of Spaine, to destroy Spaine. But whether did the tempest driue the Turcke, but to Tolouse within France, which afterwards with great a
<pb n="18" facs="10"/>
doe, makinge many spoiles of that Countrie; were driuen out, after burninge the Cittie of Nicea &amp; other citties out of which they brought with them 5200. Christians as slaues, amongest which num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber were 200. consecrated virgins; the other did ioyne with the rebellious protestāt Princes against the said Charles, by whom they were ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen and brought to subiection. Kinge Henry the third of Fraunce, beinge perswaded, that he should neuer be obeyed of his subiectes, vnles he should make away the Catholique Princes, as Henry of Loren Duke of Guise and Luyes of Iorē, the Cardinall his brother: murthered them in the assembly of Bloys 1588. but for that he was led rather by the wicked Councell of Macheuillians, and not by the lawe of God, he was punished himselfe by a poore sillye friar without the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curment of any, but of his owne head, who thrust him thorough with a knife beinge in the middest of his army, purposing to besidge Paris. Iohn Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericke Duke of Saxonie, intendinge to take the Empire from the house of Austria, followed Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Luthers Councell, that he should change his religion, soe that by the procurment of Luther he rebelled against his soueraigne. But the frute that he reaped by this false reason, was to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, put in to prison, depriued of his estate, Dukedome and dignity of elector shipp: was not Absolon destroyed by the false Councell of Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofell? And Aman by his wicked plottes, by which he tought to destroie Mardocheus and the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren of Israell? For there is noe wisdome or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell
<pb n="19" facs="10"/>
of Macheuillians against God &amp; his Church. Thomas Cromwel was put to death (as Fox saith) by the cruell lawe he made himselfe, as by a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine fatall destinie (these be Foxes wordes) that whosoeuer should be cast into the Tower, he should be put to death without examination; the said Fox calleth this Cromwell the wall and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fense of protestant religion. But, <hi>qui hominibus placent confusi sunt, quoniam Deus spreuit nos,</hi> those which doe please men are confounded, for God despiseth them.</p>
   <p n="8">8. The principal and last reason or cause is, for that these articles are already condemned by the generall Iudgement and verdit in soe many generall Councells as haue beene in the world, &amp; specially by the last generall Councell of Trent, therfore nowe they ought not to be called in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion. Whereupon Gelasius the Pope saith. <hi>Maio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res nostri diuina inspiratione cernentes, &amp;c.</hi> Our Ancestours foreseinge by diuine inspiration, did most earnestly pray the faithfull, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer was decreed by any Councell against anny heresie, for the faith of the Catholiks and the Catholike trueth, it should neuer be broughte in question againe. Also Leo the Pope did desire the Emperour Marcianus, that there should be noe retractation in any thinge defined by the holy Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uncell, and soe the said Marcianus established by lawe accordinge to his request, that none should dispute of the definition of the Councell. The said Leo also taught the same in his Epistle to the Councel of Chalcedon, &amp; to Maximus the Bus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hopp
<pb n="20" facs="11"/>
of Antioch. The same is also decreede in the Councell of Ephesus, and in the Councell of Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon, S. Augustine also said, that it is an inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solent madnes to disputed against any thinge, that the Catholike church had defined. For our Sauior saith, whosoeuer heareth your, heareth me, and whatsoeuer they will you to doe, that doe yee.</p>
   <p n="5">5. For as much therfore, as these heresies were condemned (as I haue said) by the generall Councell of Trent, vnto whom protestantes refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to come to trye their doctrine (for none euer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuseth the triall of generall Councells, but here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes) therfore we ought not to dispute with them any more. Which also rightly agreeth with the coūcell of S. Paul vnto Titus saying. A man that is an hereticke after the first and second admonitiō, shunne, knowinge that such a one is peruerted. And to Tomothy he saith, these be they that craftilie enter into houses, and leade captiue silly women, alwaies learninge and neuer attaininge vnto the knowledge of the trueth, but as Iames and Mambris resisted Moyses, soe these also resist the trueth, men corrupted in minde, reprobate cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerninge the faith. All the while that S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine was an Heretick S. Ambrose would neuer dispute with him; And the Empresse Placilla, wife vnto the great Theodosius, vnderstanding that Eunomius the Hereticke would faine reason with her husband, for eschewinge danger of being cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by him, did with great wisdome hinder the conference. And Nazianzenus saith, we ought to abhor Heretikes as the destructiō of the church, and the poyson of trueth, not carienge any hatred
<pb n="21" facs="11"/>
vnto their persons, but hauing pitty of their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors. Ignatius likewise saith, <hi>vt siilij <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>cis fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gite diuisionem vnitatis, &amp; malam haeretico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum doctrinam.</hi> As the children of light, shunne diuision of vnitie, and the wicked doctrine of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, by whom the whole world is defiled, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sraine from those euill hearbes, which Christ did neuer plant, for they be not the seede of God, but of the deuill. Be not deceaued brethren, saith he, whosoeuer shall followe a seducer, shall neuer possesse the kingdome of heauen: and whosoeuer departes not from a false preacher, shall purchase euerlastinge damnation.</p>
   <p n="10">10. Thus he admonished, that we should be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of wicked Heresies, the reason of his caueat is, for that Heresie (as the holy Doctors saye) is a certaine mischeefe of the diuill and a firebrande, that cometh from hell, a pestilente, corrupt, and poysoned aier, a cancker that consumeth the body in which it is norished, a certaine disease, that doth penetrate the intralles, and doth corrupt and infest the soules of Christians: and not only doth kill with her touche as the Viper doth, or with her sighte as the Basilike, or with her belching as the dragon, but after all these fashions and many more, doth destroy, confounde, and cast away all that approache it, neither is there any other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie but to flie, nor any other refuge then to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte from such a one, as is intangled with it; no other security, then to be far from such an infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and contagious mischeefe, which with the name of Christe, destroieth Christ in our hartes,
<pb n="22" facs="12"/>
and vnder the pretence of faith, destroyeth faith. And S. Augustine saith; let euery Catholike flie and abhor them, with whom the Church commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicateth not: for we ought not, saieth he, to haue parte with them, that haue no participation with themselues, and which are not vnited to the body of the whole Church; and to conclude with our Sauiour, one should neuer otherwise accompte of them, then as of heathens and publicans, and his holy Euangelist S. Iohn forbiddeth vs to salute them.</p>
   <p n="11">11. Therfore (gentle Reader) these be sufficiēt reasons wherfore we should be loath to dispute with Protestantes, which through their fall from godes Church are voide of all humility, intoxica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with pride, and are so blinded with malice, that they cannot learne or imbrace the trueth, or haue any trewe wisdome. For as the holly scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture saith, into a malicious soule, wisdome shall not enter: For in all ciuill conuersation or dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, especially in matters of religion, we should intend nothinge els but the consolation of our sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and the edification of our neighbours, and as the Apostle saith, <hi>Non nosmetipsos, sed Iesum Christum praedicamus,</hi> not our selues or our owne glory should we ayme at, but that of Christ Iesu, whose cote without seame is rente in peeces by so many wilfull inuēted opinions of protestāts: whose mysticall body (I meane his Church) is des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pised, forsaken, &amp; persecuted: the fruite of whose doctrine, and the proiect of their strange deuises, tendes to nothinge els, then to shake the very pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars,
<pb n="23" facs="12"/>
stroungest foundations, and fortresses of all Christianity: and at lenght to bringe in all cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and doubtfulnesse in our beleefe, and misbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe in the principaleste misteries in our Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like religion, plaine Athesime and confusion of all Christian piety, a gate for all disorders, and disso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of life and manners, a shipwreacke of Conscience, and other marckable and sutable ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes to their doctrine and behauiour, which are practised by them daily in all places where they beare sway. And although euery man (as S. Naz. saith) may thinke of God, but not euery man dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute of him, so euery man ought not to dispute or doubte of the cheefest misteries of Catholike reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but beleeue them simply with the vniuersall Church, which is (accordinge the Apostle) the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mamente and foundation of trueth: and therfore can not in any sorte deceaue vs.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>