<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115299_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09002</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19294</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115299</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A scholasticall discourse against symbolizing with Antichrist in ceremonies: especially in the signe of the crosse</title>
                 <author>Parker, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schilders (Grapheus, Painter), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Middelburg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 196, 18, 144, 8 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>GEntle Reader, thou mayest perceiue by the following Protestation, how the Author was forced to compile this Treatise, to preuent the discredit he might reape by some scattered notes. The like necessitie doth compell, the present publishing hereof, to avoyde the scandall which may arise, by a large answere, penned to the first papers, which were scribled out by the Author in few dayes, and are not the true copie to which he doth slande: In which respect I hope the Author will not be offended hereat, when it shall come to his knowledge, though he were altogether vnwilling it should passe into the handes of his frindes for so publick a purpose. And to thee good Reader I doubt not but it shall bee very acceptable, for the great learning, acutenes, modestie, fidelitie and sufficiencie thou shalt finde therein: It containing a full answere to whatsoeuer hath bene materially obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Prelates, or any of their Champions in d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>fence of the Ceremonies, and in special, to the <hi>Sophistications</hi> of such, as haue written for the Crosse in Baptisme. Thus forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to commende the worke which will much better commende it selfe, I commende both thee and it, to the rich blessing of God in Christ Iesus. Farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>