<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE REVEREND and Right VVorshipfull Doctor KINGS LEY, Archdeacon of CANTERBVRY my louing friend; ROBERT ABBOTT wisheth all increases of faith∣fulnesse in Gods Church heere, and glory hereafter through Iesus CHRIST.</title>
           <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115232_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19290</idno>
           <idno type="STC">57</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115232</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE REVEREND and Right VVorshipfull Doctor KINGS LEY, Archdeacon of CANTERBVRY my louing friend; ROBERT ABBOTT wisheth all increases of faith∣fulnesse in Gods Church heere, and glory hereafter through Iesus CHRIST.</title>
                 <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The danger of popery: or, A sermon preached at a visitation at Ashford in Kent : vpon 2. Thess. 2.12. Wherein the marks of antichristianisme and signes of truth are opened and applied, and the question of the sauing and damning of those that follow Antichrist is explaned by the Scriptures. By Robert Abbott, preacher of the Word of God at Cranebrooke in Kent</title>
                 <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <distributor>Meredith, Christopher</distributor>
                            <distributor>Stephens, Philemon</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 42 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE REVEREND and Right VVorshipfull Doctor KINGS LEY, <hi>Archdeacon of</hi> CANTERBVRY my louing friend; ROBERT ABBOTT wisheth all increases of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse in Gods Church heere, and glory hereafter through Iesus CHRIST.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Worshipfull and Reuerend,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat you thankfully and louing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accepted when it was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, commeth, you see, in another forme; crauing a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond veiw. Though what I intended could not all be spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the allotted time, yet may it all be seene. If you thinke it may be vsefull in this secure age for any of the Cleargy vnder you, your countenancing of it may incourage others to reade it. I doubt nothing of your loue either to mee, or mine, much lesse to the common good. This poore Sermon will (I hope) be found to ayme at good, because at God, and against Antichrist. It is
<pb facs="3"/> true, it might haue beene the worke of farre more able, but not more willing. Therefore as such a worke it is tendred vnto you, from him who desires to continue to God a faithfull souldier against the Pope of Rome, and to your worship</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>A poore friend and fellow-helper in the worke of Christ Iesus, ROBERT ABBOT.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>