<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115279_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17298</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4140.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115279</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A divine tragedie lately acted, or A collection of sundry memorable examples of Gods judgements upon Sabbath-breakers, and other like libertines, in their unlawfull sports, happening within the realme of England, in the compass only of two yeares last past, since the booke was published : worthy to be knowne and considered of all men, especially such, who are guilty of the sinne or arch-patrons thereof</title>
                 <author>Burton, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stam, Jan Fredericksz</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 46, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, it is a true saying of that royal King Salomon Prov. 19. 29. <hi>Iudgments are prepared for Scorners:</hi> that is, for such who contemne the precepts and admonitions of God, and his faithfull Ministers. And as they are thus <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared,</hi> so are they oft times executed upon such, even in this present life: that Gods power, truth, and justice might be manifested, and wicked men frighted from their evill courses: So the Psalmist: Psalm. 9. 16. <hi>The Lord is knowne by the judgment that he executeth; the wicked is snared in the worke of his owne hands:</hi> the reason is thus rendered by the Prophet Isay. c. 26. 9. <hi>For when thy judgements are in the earth, the inhabitants of the world will learne righteousnesse;</hi> though never so indo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible and refractory before. Neither doth God so inflict his judgements, <note n="*" place="margin">As he hath done on the 4. Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, and on these Infrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of it.</note> as to have them presently forgotten; but he stampes a <hi>Memento</hi> on them; <hi>having so done his marvelous works</hi> (as wel of justice, as of mercy) <hi>that they ought to be had in remembrance.</hi> Psalm. 111. 4. Himselfe therefore hath vouchsafed to record (even in sacred writ) many notable examples of his avenging justice, both ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, Nationall, and personall, for al posteritie to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template;


<pb facs="3"/>
prefacing some of them with a special <hi>Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum</hi> for our more serious consideration of them; with Luk. 17. 32. <hi>Remember Lots wife:</hi> which judgments though executed many thousand yeares past, <hi>yet they remaine still fresh upon record,</hi> as done but yesterday, even <hi>for this very end, that they might be examples unto us, not to last after evil things as they lusted,</hi> nor to trace the footsteps of their sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wayes, lest we should incurre the selfe same <hi>exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plarie punishments</hi> as they susteined. <hi>1. Cor. 10. 5. to 12.</hi> And as God himselfe, so holy men of God in all ages, following his example, have carefully observed, and registred to posteritie the speciall most remarkable judgments of God upon obstinate sinnes and sinners of all sorts, (with which not only ecclesiasticall, but even profane Stories, are fully fraught) happened in the ages, and the places wherein they lived: Many whereof <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r.</seg> Iohn Fox in his Acts and monuments,</hi> neere the end, <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r,</seg> Raynolds</hi> in his <hi>Treatise concerning the miraculous discovery and punishments of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Murtherers.</hi> D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>Thomas Peard in his Theatre of Gods judgments,</hi> with sundry others, have collected and dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted into intire Tractates, the very reading &amp; serious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>usall whereof, would no doubt daunt the most professed Atheist, &amp; reclaime the most incorrigible sinner. I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore desiring to tread in their pious footsteps, having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from good intelligence many memorable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidents of Gods avenging Iustice upon Sabbath-breakers; &amp; the profaners of Sacred times devouted to his service, happening within the compasse of our little Iland within two yeares space, (since the publication of the <hi>Declaration for Sports and Pastimes after evening Prayer on the Lords day, in Parish Churches by divers</hi>(<note n="a" place="margin">Nullam habet spem salutis ager quem ad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperantiā Medicus hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur: Sence.</note>
      <hi>Ministers</hi>) hath sett open the floudgates to this presumptuous Sinne of Sabbath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breaking; thought it a part of my bounden duty to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve


<pb facs="3"/>
and propagate their memorie both for the honour of Gods truth and justice; the vindication of the intire sanctifycation of his sacred day, (which he hath visiblie pleaded for from heaven, since men have been auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciously profane, as to pleade, and I would I could not say to <note n="b" place="margin">See the doctrine of the Sabbath; The History of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath; the tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atise of the Sabbath-day and discourse of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath lately printed: whichthough they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the very name of Sabbath, as Iewish yet they are all characterised with that name and title.</note>
      <hi>write</hi> and preach against it upon earth) the clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of those Ministers innocency, who now unjustly suffer thorough the malice of ungodly persecutors, and raging Prelates, for refusing to joine with others in spur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring on the people to the greedy pursuite of this crying dangerous Syn, to the ruine of their Soules, their bodies, and shame of our religion, and the monition of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, and all future ages, to beware of this so dangerous a transgression. How God hath punished this very Syn in former ages, in such who have either by dancing, Sports, Pastimes, orunnecessary Labors and travels profaned his Sacred day, I meane not to record: he that listeth may read store of such examples registred to his hands in the <hi>Counsell of Paris, under Lewis and Lotharius anno</hi> 829. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c. 50.</hi> (which relates in generall; <hi>That many present in this Councell were eye-witnesses, and others of them had it by relation, that some men upon the Lords day being aboute their husbandry, have bene slaine with thunder, some puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed with the contraction of their joynts and sinnes, some even with visible fire have had their bodyes and bones burnt up in a moment, and sodainly resolved into ashes, and that many other terrible examples of like nature hath hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened and did fall out dayly: By</hi> WHICH IT WAS DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CLARED, THAT GOD IS MVCH OF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FENDED WITH THE DISHONOVR OF SO GKEAT A DAI;) Petrus Plessensis in Litania major Sermo 20. <hi>In Mathew Paris,</hi> Historia Major Anno 1200. p. 194. in <hi>Roger Houenden</hi> Anno 1200. p. 822.


<pb facs="4"/>
In <hi>Mathew Westminster.</hi> Flores Historiarum: Anno 1200. In <hi>Vincentius Beluacensis,</hi> Speculum Morale l. 3. pr. 9. Distinctio 9. ofdances, In the <hi>flower of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements,</hi> printed in the beginning of K. Hen. 8. fol. 159. to 163. In <hi>Henricus Gran.</hi> Distinct. 9. Exemp. 51. in the Magdeburge <hi>Centuries Centurie.</hi> 12. c. 6. In D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Bownde</hi> his doctrine of the Sabbath Edition. 2. p. 252. to 263. the first booke: in <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Iohn Feild</hi> his declaration of Gods judgments at Paris garden: in M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>Philip Stubs</hi> his Anatomie of abuses. p. 185. in the <hi>Practice of Piety:</hi> 429. to 434. and D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Beard</hi> his Theatre of Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. All which have registred sundrie notable Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God upon sundry Sabbath-breakers (which have presumed to daunce, worke, or travell, on the Lords holy day) of purpose to shew the danger of profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning holy times, and to deterre men from this common sinne, for which so many have smarted from heaven in an exemplarie manner. I shall therefore confine my selfe only to such domesticke examples, as have fallen out in sundry corners of this our Realme within these two yeares, of purpose to refute the <note n="*" place="margin">2. Pet. 2. v. 16.</note>
      <hi>madnesse of those Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> who in the Presse and Pulpit; and the profanes of those people, who in their dauncing-greenes, and may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pole arbors, have bene so audacious, as to affirme, <hi>the Profanation of the Lords day by Maygames, Daunces, May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poles, Wakes, and common Labour out of time of divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> (<hi>especially after evening Prayer</hi>) to be no sin at all against the 4. <hi>Commandement, or any other Law of God or man; but</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">See the History, Treatise, Discourse, &amp; Doctrine of the Sabbath accordingly, and sunday no Sabbath.</note>
      <hi>necessary and commendable point of true Christian Liberty</hi> (they should have sayd of carnall and heathenish licentiousnesse rather) <hi>from which the people must not be debarred;</hi> But let these blinde guides, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines learne from these examples, to correct this


<pb facs="4"/>
their erronious judgment, and practise; <hi>for feare the Lord make them the next examples in this kinde, to teach others to keepe his Sabbaths better,</hi> and more intirely for the future. And if these tragical spectacles of divine ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice will not perswade them, that such profaning of the Lords most Sacred day, is a Syn, yea and a crying Syn too, as all our writers, (yea and our Prelates gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, till now of late have unanimously defined, and the whole <hi>State in Parliament in</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">1. Car. c. 1. 3. Car. c. 1</note>
      <hi>two late famous Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes</hi> and <note n="e" place="margin">1. 27. H. 6. 5. 5. &amp; 6. E. 6. c. 3.</note>
      <hi>two more ancient Acts,</hi> to omit our <note n="f" place="margin">Of the Time and Place of Prayer. part. 1. Of Diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and unlawfull Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. part, 3. p. 293. 293.</note>
      <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milyes</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">The Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer after the 4. and 10. Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
      <hi>Common Praier booke,</hi>
      <note n="h" place="margin">Canon. 13. 163.</note>
      <hi>Canons,</hi>
      <note n="i" place="margin">
         <hi>Article</hi> 35 <hi>of Ireland.</hi> 56</note>
      <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, and</hi>
      <note n="k" place="margin">Queene Elis▪ Injunct: 20.</note>
      <hi>Injunctions,</hi> which conclude the same) I say have adjudged such a presumptuous trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression, as will draw downe Gods vengeance on mens heads; Our late Soveraigne <hi>K. Iames</hi> of happy memory and our present gracious Soveraigne Lord <hi>R. Charles</hi> with all the <hi>Prelates, Cleargy and people of the Realme in the first yeares of both their Raignes,</hi> in the severall Bookes of <hi>Common Praier, and order for the publike fasts set out by their royall authorityes, and the Bishops advice, with the Consent and harty desire of the whole Realme for the abating aversion, and ceasing of those dreadfull eating Plagues which then</hi> swallowed up many thousands <hi>of people every weeke</hi> will informe them; That amonge other Syns, <hi>The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faning</hi> OF THE SABBATH (So <hi>King Iames his Booke</hi> styles the sunday) and <hi>not keeping holy the Lords day, was one cheife cause why those two great terrible Plagues</hi> (and why not also this great Plague which is now begun and spread much abroade) <hi>brake in upon us;</hi> to the destruction not of some few Particular persons, but of many thousands, and the punishment of the whole Realme, and Nation in generall. And because some of these men plead most falsly, <hi>that the chiefest</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>writers of the reformed Churches are of their opinion,</hi>
      <note n="l" place="margin">Homil. 162. in Matth. fol. 308. Hom. 28. in Mar. f. 35. Hom. 56. in Lu. f. 141. Hom. 36. in Ioan. f. 77. Hom. 88. in Act.</note>
      <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Rodolphus Gualter, and</hi>
      <note n="m" place="margin">Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in Matth. 12. &amp; 14. p. 376. 423. in Ioan. 7. f. 293.</note>
      <hi>Wolfgangus Musculus</hi> (men of principall note and learning amonge them) will both assure them, <hi>that the Lords day is not onely</hi> WHOLLY, ONLY, AND INTIRELY TO BE SPENT IN RELIGIOVS PVBLIKE AND PRIVATE DVTIES OF GODS WORSHIP, AND THAT DAVNCING, SPORTES, AND PASTIMES, ON IT, ARE SINFVLL, AND EXE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CRABLE; (the constant judgment of all forraigne Protestant divines whatsoever, as I am able to prove; what ever <note n="n" place="margin">History of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath. part. 2. c. 6. Inst. 9. 10.</note>
      <hi>D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Helyn</hi> or <note n="o" place="margin">D. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linghton Sunday no Sabbath p. 8.</note> others have rashly averred to the contrary; But likewise further informe them; <hi>That God may justly revenge the great contempt of his Deity in profaning his Sacred day with daunces and such like Revells and discorders,</hi> WITH HORRIBLE PVNISH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTS, NEITHER IS IT TO BE DOVBTED (<hi>saith M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Gualther</hi>) THAT THE PROFANATION OF THE LORDS DAY, IS NOT THE LEAST CAVSE OF THE EVILS AND CALAMITIES OF OVR AGE, Yea their owne most illustrious Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>Robert Bellarmine</hi> (whom they allmost deify when they doe but name him:) is so farre a Puritan in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, that he not only spends <note n="p" place="margin">Concio 6. 9. 19. 20. 21.</note> 4. or 5. <hi>whole Sermones against dauncing, mummeries, maskes, and such like Bacchanals,</hi> (which he simply condemnes at all times, <hi>but especially on sacred festivals</hi> and <hi>Lords dayes as most detestable profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of them;</hi>) but likewise professeth; <hi>that the practise of them upon sacred times,</hi> was the occasion of all the <hi>publike calamities</hi> and judgments which they suffered. But by these <hi>Daunces, Mummeries, Bacchanels, and discor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> (saith he) <hi>we polute the holy dayes of the Lord: and yet neverthelesse do we inquire the reasons why God doth punish us? why we are slaine in our very houses? doe not</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>the Scriptures cry aloude, Sinne maketh a people miserable:</hi> And there is no evill in the Citie, which the Lord hath not done. <hi>Therefore these our sinnes of profaning the holy dayes of the Lord with daunces, revels and bacchanals, have procured us famine, and poverty, and pestilence, and sedition, and</hi> ALL PLAGVES AND SCOVRGES. <hi>And verily</hi> (saith he) in another Sermon. <hi>I vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feare, that if we proceed to celebrate the Bacchanals with mummeries, and maskes, and daunces, as we doe at other times, and to provoke God to wrath, with so many wicked Pastimes, our sinne will be growen to the full at last, and the anger of the Lord be so farre incensed, that he will utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy us, as we see he hath destroyed many nations, for what I pray hath destroyed Grecia? But even that very thing which we doe? They were men exceedingly given to drunkenesses, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting and</hi> DAVNCING, (<hi>and that upon sacred times</hi>) <hi>as may be knowne, by the Orations of Basill, and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sostome. But what hath God done? because they were addicted to these things, and especially to</hi> DAVNCING, <hi>he hath imposed such a severe tyrant</hi> (<hi>to wit the Turke</hi>) <hi>upon their necks, that they now groane under the yoke, and are pressed with so heavy a burthen,</hi> THAT THEY HAVE NEITHER TIME, NOR WILL TO DAVNCE OR CAPER. Thus <hi>Bellarmine</hi> to his greate admirers shame and refutation. If then this sinne of profaning the Lords day, by dauncing, Maygames, Ales, Pastimes, or unnecessary travel and labour, drawe downe Gods Plagues and vengeance upon whole Kingdomes and Churches, as these authors, (together with <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Iohn Feild, in his declaration of the judgement of God, at Paris Garden;</hi> and <hi>Humphry Robarts in his complaint for the Reformation of divers vaine, and wicked abused exercises, practised on the Sabbath day, which tend to the</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>hinderance of the Gospell, and increase of many abominable vices: printed by Richard Iones, London 1580. together with M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Philip Stubs, in his Anatomic of abuses, and M<seg rend="sub">r</seg>. Iohn Nortbrooke in his Treatise where in dicing</hi> DAVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CING, <hi>vaine playes and Enterludes, with other idle Pastimes and exercises commonly used on the</hi> SABBATH DAY, <hi>are by the Word of God, and ancient writers reprooved, printed for George Bishop▪ London: 1579.</hi>) most punctually testifie: and the <hi>Practise of Piety dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to his Majesty, and 39. times printed by publike au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority resolves:</hi> no wonder if it hath lately caused God to unsheath his sword of exemplarie justice upon these particular persons, (that I speake not of the whole Kingdome in generall now scourged with a fresh plague and lately a drought) whose tragicall examples I here present unto your view, to deterre all others from this Sinne. It is a true saying of <hi>Cyprian, Praebentur cunctis Exempla, cum fuerint quibusdam irrogata Supplicia. The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Punishments of a few are warnings to all:</hi> God grant that these may be so to us. <hi>Hee</hi> (saith the same Father) is <hi>over audacious, who strives to passe over there, where he hath seene another to have fallen; hee is outragiously bead-stronge, who is not strucke with feare, when he beholds another perish in that course; which he is running; he onely is a lover of his owne safety, who takes warning by the Deathes of others: and he alone is a prudent man, who is made wise by the Ruines of other men.</hi> God of his mercie vouchsafe that the exemplarie deathes of these few here specified (and of thousands more in this time of mortality, occasioned by this Sinne of Sabbath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breaking were as the former pests; <hi>Together with a Plague in Pope Pelagius the second his time An. Domin.</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>591.</hi> as <hi>Petrus Blessensis in his 20. Sermon de Litania majori, records:</hi>) may prove life to many; and the judgements on some, become remedies to cure all, who are sicke of the selfesame Sinne.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>