<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Maior, Aldermen, and Inhabitants of N.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115732_Fr1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03231</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1335.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115732</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Maior, Aldermen, and Inhabitants of N.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>To the maior, aldermen, and inhabitants of N. That whiche heretofore I haue propounded to you (right worshipfull and beloued) in teaching, I do now publish to all men by printing, to wit, mine opinion of the vnlawfulnesse of games consisting in chance</title>
                 <author>Balmford, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harrison, John 3</publisher>
                    <distributor>Boyle, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>1 sheet (1 page), 1/2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <head>To the Maior, Aldermen, and Inhabitants of N.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which heretofore I haue propounded to you (right Worshipfull and beloued) in teaching, I do now publish to all men by printing, to wit,
mine opinion of the vnlawfulnesse of games consisting in chance. My desire is either information, if I erre in iudgement, or reformation of so
leud a practise. But whether I erre or no (which yet I would gladly vndestand,<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 3. 7.</note> for I ought not to teach an vntruth, though to Gods glorie) yet
there is none, zealous indeed against sinne, desirous from the heart to reclaime sinners, and who deepely considereth the grieuous abuses, which
accompanie dicing and carding (as horrible swearing, dangerous quarelling, losse (I say not of good houres, but) of nights and dayes, and the
pittifull vndoing of too too manie) but will remembe that<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 12.</note> all things are not expedient, which are lawfull, and therefore abstaine from such
Heathenish passe-times, that, if by their example they cannot reforme, they may be sure<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 8. 9.</note> they do not confirme gamesters in their inordinate walking. Which
respect, the 7. Iniunction forbidding Ministers to vse these vnlawfull games, may be supposed to haue. Now that which authoritie exacteth of Ministers, doth Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
require of all true Professours. For as the one are to be<note n="*" place="margin">1. Tit. 5. 3.</note> ensamples to the flocke, so the other are to be<note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 2. 15.</note> lights in the world. And therefore as PAVL saith.
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 8. 10. 13</note> If meat offend my brother, I will eate no flesh while the world standeth. So euerie true Chistian should say, and that with more resolution (for Play is not so ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie
as meat.) If play offend my brother, who seeing me hauing knowledge, play, is boldned to follow gaming, I will not play while the world standeth. Which
care vnto edification if all, who haue the<note n="*" place="margin">Psal. 50. 1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 17.</note> word in their mouthes, and would not be thought to hate to be reformed, would manifest in their sincere conuersation
and if Magistrates, who should not<note n="*" place="margin">Rom 13. 4.</note> carie the sword in vaine would do what they may by<note n="*" place="margin">33 H. 8. c. 9 5. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> 25.</note> law, to banish these forbidden past-times, or rather lost-times, I doubt
not, but that preaching and writing against them would more mightily preuaile, and this good would come of it, manie would applie themselues to better ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercises,
there would be lesse time mispent in Alehouses, and God lesse prouoked to displeasure against vs. But these things I referre to the consideration of the wise
and this my Dialogue to the iudgement of the Godly, chiefly to you, whose good I wish especially. Farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>