<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all those Readers that
are well disposed.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115916_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10703</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20986</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115916</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all those Readers that
are well disposed.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The honestie of this age· : Proouing by good circumstance that the world was neuer honest till now. By Barnabee Rych Gentleman, seruant to the Kings most excellent Maiestie</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 <publisher>Adams, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 49, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To all those Readers that
are well disposed.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLEMEN, there are but fewe in
these dayes, that are willing to heare
their faultes: but they are fewer by a
great number that are willing to amend
them, Find faults, could neuer yet get
grace, for <hi>Adulation</hi> is crept so closely
into our bosomes, that smoothing <hi>Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie</hi>
is more dearely esteemed, then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending
<hi>Veritie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I confesse my selfe to be ill beholding
to mine owne tongue, that could neuer flatter, lispe, nor lye: Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
hath made the carriage of my words to bee something harsh
and dull, yet when they seeme to be most slow, perhaps sometimes
they be most sure: I speake plainely, &amp; I meane honestly: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
my wordes bee not imbroydered with high morality, I care
not: for I leaue that to <hi>Schollers, Maisters</hi> of <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Methode.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If my lynes be plaine and true, they so much the more resemble
their <hi>Sier,</hi> and for children to bee like their <hi>Parentes,</hi> besides the
<hi>Midwife</hi> will giue it a blessing, so it is a signe they be <hi>Legitimate:</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes
I know they cannot want, that in their procreation were bred
and borne before their time, for as I conueyued of them in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant,
so I was deliuered againe in a moment: and these abortiue
brates that are thus hastely brought into the world, though they
seldome prooue to haue any great vigor or strength, yet I hope
these will proue to be of as honest and plaine dealing as their father.
I make no doubt but they will please as many as I desire to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,
and those are Good men, and Vertuous women: for the rest
that are gauled, if I rubbe them vnawares, it is but <hi>Chance-medly,</hi>
and then I hope I shall obtaine a pardon of Course, prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting
aforehand that I haue not aymed at any one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
that hath not a guiltie conscience to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse
himselfe: if any man will thinke them
to be too bitter, let him vse it as an
<hi>Apothecaries</hi> pill, that the more
bitter, the better
purging.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>