<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>R., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115540_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10318</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20602</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115540</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>R., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A directorie teaching the way to the truth in a briefe and plaine discourse against the heresies of this time : Whereunto is added, a short treatise against adiaphorists, neuters, and such as say they may be saued in any sect or religion, and would make of many diuers sects one Church</title>
                 <author>Radford, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>—Recusant</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 608 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nderstādinge by a freinde of myne, not longe agoe, that one of fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar, and olde acquaintance of his, was desirous to knowe the trueth in matters of religion; and to haue the trueth set downe in writing, for his better memorie, &amp; stay in this greate diuersity of mens mindes, and sundry opinions at this day: I was loath at first to enterprise the matter, for that I knewe, that there be written books most ample, and learned of all matters of controuersie at this present farre beyonde my learning, and skyll; wherin the Heretiks of our tyme, be moste eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently confuted: and the trueth moste plainly open, sett downe, and declared; able to satisfie any man in consciēce whosoeuer, that with lowly spirit, and desire of trueth, will consideratly and throughly read them. Yet considering many men in this troublesome tyme there be (that be desirōs to knowe the trueth) either cannot attayne those books, or be not of ability to buy them: or if they be, yet not at leasure to read them: or not of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and capacity sufficient well to conceauē of them; fearing likewise lest if any at my handes shoulde desire to knowe GODS trueth, and I
<pb facs="11"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="11"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="12"/>
hiding it from them, for want of discharge of my duety, might highly displease GOD, (to whom I am to make an account,) &amp; that I might iustly be reckoned amongst those, whom God by his holie Prophet complaineth of, Paruuli petierunt panem. My little ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s that is poore simple soules, desirons of the trueth, &amp; their sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation haue desired bread, the foode of GODS worde, and the Sacraments, &amp; there was not that woulde breake it vnto them; Though there be many others of my Brethren, that doe, and can doe it farre better, I being the least, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyest of all: Yet for these and diuerse other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations, &amp; especially for discharge of my duty, at this present, I haue breiflie, and plai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly for the simple sorte, set downe my mynde, touching the cheifest matters, of controuersies in religion in this tyme, wherby an vnlearned man, may easilie by him self, or another, finde out sufficient autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to satisfie his minde, touching the trueth of the most matters of religion in question at this day: wherein be not afraide (good countryman) but be bolde I warrant thee, by such authority as I haue set downe to presse, and charge the greatest Heretike in the worlde. For he may wrangle &amp; wrest, and seeke many narrow shifts: but in the ende, he will bewraye his owne wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knes; For this vndoubted, and infallible Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church and trueth, may for a tyme in some sorte be oppressed: but neuer suppressed nor hidde it may be gainsaid, but in the ende cānot be with stoode, no more then that Idoll Dagon could stand, but in presence of the Arke of the liuing
<pb facs="12"/>
GOD, was throwne downe &amp; burst a sunder: not for that in me any such exquisite matter may be founde; but because I leane of such sure grownds, &amp; authority, that possiblie cannot faile. For euē as at the noone day the light of the sunne cannot be denyed; so there is a certaine truth so plaine, that by no guylefull falsehoode in wordes, nor deceitefull coloured speeches, can in any wise be darkned, or ouerthrowne; which trueth to speake and teach, if man shoulde cease; the very rockes, and stones might crie out. But for that I write this little treatise, to informe espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, an ignorant, and vnlearned man: therefore I haue acco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>modated my selfe as much as I could, to his vnderstanding, vsing plaine wordes, and now &amp; then ofte repetition of things that to the learned be not needfull, and may seeme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>edyous. Wherefore if this writing chaunce to fal into the handes of the learned, they may looke for no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yne phrases, or rhetoricall termes, at my handes; neither in writing hastely haue I obserued that order, and methode, which otherwise were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite. Only, let him remember to whom I write▪ &amp; for whose sake especially, I haue written this; which if not so sufficiently as I would wish, yet at least wise, it may be an occasion to some other, that cā doe it better, to make a more large, and profitable discourse. In the meane tyme if this my poore labour, and indeauoures, may doe any good; be an instrument, or meane, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>erte to GOD, or strengthen, Yea but the leaste, or weakest soule in the worlde: I thinke my paines well bestowed, and attribute thou no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="13"/>
to me, but giue the praise, &amp; thanks wholly to GOD. But if (vppon iust occasion) in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting so in haste and that I aslure you with out any help of bookes, <note n="*" place="margin">Excepte that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telic in 2. or 3. cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pters onlie of the B. Sacramit of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare, I hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> not onlie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged, some au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorityes, of the holy Fathers, gathered by a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and late wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but al so therin, nov a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d then haue vsed some oshisowne speeches whose name though ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, yet for the present vpon inst reasons, I doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale.</note> trusting only to my slender, &amp; weake memorye of that I haue heretofore reade or in schooles heard of my masters: if I say in tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of so high misteries so many, and waighty matters, I in any sorte haue fayled, or gone one iotte astray from the common receaued faith, of the true Catholike, and Apostolike Romane Churche (as by GODS gratious assistance I trust I haue not) yet if there be any of my learned Catholike Brethren, that can synde any iust faulte, or error herein: I will not obstinatly defende yet, (as Heret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ks doe) but humbly thanke him, that will friendlie, &amp; charitable, either correct it him selfe, or warne me of it, that I may correct it my s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lfe, &amp; amend it. For I as a fra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>le mā may easily e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>; Yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>l I boldlie say, with that learned * Father, I w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>euer be an heretike: by GODS grace, as alwaies submitting my lelfe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd all my sayings, and doings, to the censure, judgment, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the holy Catholike Churche, that I knowe cannot erre. Neither haue I heare written any large discourse of any thing: but only touched as it weare the toppes of things with what bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie l mighte, makinge the vnlearned to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand. But this I beseech you, if at any tyme you perce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e me to enueigh sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rply against heretiks or their falie d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>alings, &amp; abuses; that you woulde not take yt, that I doe it for any wante of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, towards them, or for hatred against their persons: but only in respect of their vices, and
<pb facs="13"/>
damnable sects, &amp; heresies, wherby they hurt thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, and others, and slaunder the trueth. For it is the zeale of GODS cause, and the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like trueth, that some tyme more vehemently, causeth me to speake; for it is not the most ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious heretike in this lande; nor all the heretiks (though neuer so malitiouslie they seeke our bloude) but GOD is my witnes; I am so farre from wishing them harme (though olde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festred diseases must be cured with sharpe medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines sometymes for the patients good) that I woulde lay my hands vnder their feete and kisse the very grounde they tread one, to doe them good; and winne their soules to GOD: which though with the losle of my lise it were donne: yet I trust in GOD; I shoulde thinke it well<note place="margin">* <hi>Aug.</hi>
      </note> bestowed. But if my laboures can doe such no good: yet I hope GOD will accept my good will; and desire. And if that I may herewith doe any well disposed person good: Then I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech him whosoeuer that I, a sinnful wretch; may be pertaker of his good prayers; which is all I desire for these smal paines. Fare you well.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>10. Aprilis. Anno 1594.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Written by him who desireth the good of his Countrye, and saluation of all. I. R.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>