<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE TRANSLA∣TORS PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>A., C.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115932_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10745</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21022</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115932</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE TRANSLA∣TORS PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>A., C.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Holy pictures of the mysticall figures of the most holy sacrifice and sacrament of the Eucharist: set forth in French by Lewis Richome, prouinciall of the Societie of Iesus; and translated into English for the benefit of those of that nation, aswell protestants as Catholikes. By C.A</title>
                 <author>Richeome, Louis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Birchley Hall Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Lancashire</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 300, 12 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE TRANSLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TORS PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OOD Reader, I present vnto thy view the Embleame of thy temporall life, Translati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>(nihil enim noui sub sole)</hi> &amp; a soueraigne preseruatiue of thy spirituall life, which is holy meditation, the indigested crudities of these times, occasioned by rawe study and superficiall prayer, send vp such grosse fumes into the head, and breede such wayward spirits in the heart, as in matters of Religion, doe make the greater sort, euen at mans estate, to <hi>thinke as a childe,</hi> to <hi>speake as a childe,</hi> with no lesse ignorance then contention. A strange preuarica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the childrens game in jest, should prooue good earnest amongst men. <hi>Cock sodden halfe eaten:</hi> surely the most, that know any thing, doe liue vpon the swimme, and thinke the first seething of the pot to be sufficient, wanting the maturity of deeper meditation. Sweet Iesu, how is thy net rent, and great fishes slip out, for want of due conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration? How many diuisions, and subdiuisions doth thy seamelesse coate endure? Indeed, in earthly things, variety is cause of pleasure, but in case of Religion, variety is the mother of nullity, a position no whit paradoxall, being grounded vpon a principle of secular policie it selfe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed euen by the God of wisdome, saying, That <hi>a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome diuided against it selfe</hi> (there is variety) <hi>cannot stand,</hi> there is the nullity. The <hi>Lutheran,</hi> the <hi>Caluinist,</hi> the <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane,</hi> the <hi>Brownist,</hi> and <hi>Anabaptist,</hi> make the Diuels <hi>Sett of fine Parts,</hi> consisting of discords; who alwayes running Diuision in a wrong key vpon the plain song of Scripture, doe marre the soule, which God made a harmony; yea, and all the musick too in the Church of God; and which is the
<pb facs="3"/>worst of all, neuer rest so little as a briefe, no nor yet are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> haste, for any order I see taken, to coniure downe these spirits, which make the Church become monstrous, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> monstrously predicated of, that it should be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poted of incompatible contradictions. These are much like so many race-Poasts, that steppe before each other a mile in madnesse (for that is distraction) and he that runs the course ouer, is sure to ouer-runne the Constable; and is sure to runne his sight out, though not out of sight; which euery pious minde, and studious of the Churches weale, cannot but hartily wish might soone betide them.</p>
   <p>But now behold again; although in respect of the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and disasterous issue of these wicked designes, Ipitie these men more, then they doe themselues: yet I shame to see the ground, and first originall of this intoxication. And what? haue they neither hearts, nor fore-heads for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues? not a <hi>Ianus</hi> amongst them to looke behinde, and before, whence and whither? good God, that neither pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, nor shame, is able to strike one notch into their whir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling heads, to stop those exentrick motions of a brain-sick giddinesse, whose punishment condigne, and sutable to the sinne, must be a whirle-pit. But I haue almost forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten my selfe, being rapt beyond measure, when I seriously meditate vpon those woful aberrations. The thing, I would vtter, is this. Aske a Sectary (Puritane, Brownist, or other) the ground of his opinion, and he laies you downe a Bible, and many words makes he of the Word, which he will be tryed by, though for the sense therof, in conclusion, it must be tried by him, and he vntutored, slaue to his owne shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low weenings, will bee hammering out some improper word, of his owne proper forge, and appropriate it to that most sacred Word it selfe; and then presently preuent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention, by cursing his Aduersary, that shall adde, or dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish from it. This, oh this is it, that makes me blush, for their impudencie, laugh at their folly, and grieue at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, done to those heauen-inspired Oracles, yea that bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb facs="3"/>Spirit of God himselfe, by those fanaticall enthusiasme.</p>
   <p>I could speake vpon mine owne experience very much in discouery of this folly and impiety, (and to discouer it, is to refute it): but I may not exceed the limits of an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, and future occasion may offer it selfe for more ample discourse herein. For the present, I hartily desire thee (good courteous and Christian Reader) to learne truely, and exactly, what that Scripture meaneth, by testifying of it selfe, That <hi>no scripture is of any priuate interpretation.</hi> Next, to that rule put this example, set before the eyes of thine imagination, the sects aboue mentioned, with all the petty rioters, calued out of them; and (if thou canst haue patience to endure the while) suppose also the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures laid in common before them, then let them demand each of other, from the first to the last, and reciprocally, what infallible assurance and warrant they haue, to builde their particular opinions, different amongst themselues, &amp; impugned by the demander, vpon such and such places of sacred Writ, as they pretend; and it is not to bee vttered, what a spirit of contradiction thou shalt soone discerne in them vpon strict examination, and yet what a spirit of flumber too, that all this while they cānot see it thēselues.</p>
   <p>But to leaue those out-flying hunters, which the Church (if it were so well manned, as to top them) should whip in at the first breaking our, or whippe out at last for euer comming in againe. It is now high time to turne my speech to thee, good Christian, that with true humility, &amp; vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned sincerity seekest the plain way to heauen, &amp; thy soules happinesse. To render thee a general account of this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular designe; vnderstād, that this Treatise is chosen by me, amongst many other, for that it something concernes that point of the warrant of holy Scripture, before touched, as being founded thereupon, and seconded also by the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the Doctors in the firster age of the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stamēts Church. Besides, the most of those places alledged (and there be 14. of them in all) are so profound in search,
<pb facs="4"/>so pleasant in the finding, so correspondent in the Type, so reuerend in the Mystery, so euery way absolute, as (setting all controuersies aside, with the which I will not medle) I professe I could not hold off my hands from translating, though it were for my owne priuate vse, onely to keepe me both from idlenesse, and from employments of inferiour condition. And after peceiuing that, whereas I intended to make the Translation onely lesse priuate, some were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly endeauouring to make it altogether publike; for the worthy respect I must euer beare to the first moouer hereunto, and the generall good of my owne Countrey, in the encrease of piety and true deuotion; I was sooner yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hereunto, as being not a little glad, that my poore la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours should euer prooue to be accounted worthy of the Churches acceptance. Now my greatest feare is, lest I haue done the Author himselfe some wrong through the tenuity of my skill. I must confesse, I haue not been apprentise to this trade of translating, nor did I euer breath that stranger ayre of <hi>France;</hi> what I haue got herein, is by my trauailes at home. Besides, those that are wel practised in this course, wil yeeld me that the elegancy of speech, vsed by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poser, is by diffrence of language much abated in the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation, be in neuer so exact; yet my hope is, I haue giuen you the same man still, though in an English habite; and though the manner of the stile be changed yet the matter of the book is the same it was. Thou hast heere my feares, and my hopes, take my prayers also with thee (good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) in stead of a blessing vpon thy perusall hereof, and if it like thee, giue me thine againe in change, for further illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination: it is all I craue of thee for my paines; thou shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest not deny these prayers to thine enemy, though hee skorne them, sure thou canst not, but giue them thy friend, that begs them, and desires to rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy seruant in Iesus Christ, C. A.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>