<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL and reuerend in Christ, the heads of Colleges, and com∣panie of students, of the Vniuersitie of Oxford, Iohn Rai∣noldes wisheth grace and peace from God the fa∣ther, and from our Lord Iesus Christ.</title>
           <author>Reynolds, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115546_Bo1_25</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10345</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20626</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115546</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL and reuerend in Christ, the heads of Colleges, and com∣panie of students, of the Vniuersitie of Oxford, Iohn Rai∣noldes wisheth grace and peace from God the fa∣ther, and from our Lord Iesus Christ.</title>
                 <author>Reynolds, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The summe of the conference betwene Iohn Rainoldes and Iohn Hart : touching the head and the faith of the Church. Wherein by the way are handled sundrie points, of the sufficiencie and right expounding of the Scriptures, the ministerie of the Church, the function of priesthood, the sacrifice of the masse, with other controuerises of religion: but chiefly and purposely the point of Church-gouernment ... Penned by Iohn Rainoldes, according to the notes set downe in writing by them both: perused by Iohn Hart, and (after things supplied, &amp; altered, as he thought good) allowed for the faithfull report of that which past in conference betwene them. Whereto is annexed a treatise intitled, Six conclusions touching the Holie Scripture and the Church, writen by Iohn Rainoldes. With a defence of such thinges as Thomas Stapleton and Gregorie Martin haue carped at therein</title>
                 <author>Rainolds, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>475, 1, 479-674, 659-750 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="337"/>
   <pb n="661" facs="337"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL and reuerend in Christ, the heads of Colleges, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of students, of the Vniuersitie of Oxford, Iohn Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noldes wisheth grace and peace from God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and from our Lord Iesus Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Anna</hi> the mother of <hi>Samuel</hi> had brought vp her child, whom she had obtained of God with earnest prayers to put from her selfe the reproch of barennesse: she consecrated him to God before <hi>Eli</hi> the Priest, <note n="a" place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.28. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.18.</note>that he might <hi>liue and serue in the temple of the Lord.</hi> In like maner I desiring to consecrate to <hi>the temple of the Lord</hi> my <hi>Samuel,</hi> as it were, &amp; the first child of trauaile that God hath ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to my barrennes, haue thought good to present him to God before you, fathers, and brethren, welbeloued in Christ, who ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are already or shall be put in trust with the charge of <hi>the temple,</hi> to <hi>serue</hi> (if it may any way) <note n="b" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16.</note>
      <hi>the temple of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God.</hi> Perhaps a rash enterprise, &amp; vndertaken somewhat more boldly, then aduisedly: chiefly séeing that it is so far inferior to the ripenes of <hi>Samuel.</hi> And truely I haue hetherto béene stil of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> minde, that I had leiffer the things which I had brought foorth (rather as vntimely fruites, then perfit children) should be kept within, then come abroad into the light; &amp; stay in the court of <hi>the temple,</hi> then presse into <hi>the temple.</hi> For I haue béen dealt with both oft, and earnestly, by my very frends, that I would suffer to be printed and published, as other sclender exercises made ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the fence-schoole (as you would say) then for the field: so chiefly my <hi>Orations,</hi> which, when I read the Gréeke lecture in our College. I made to mine audience <hi>cōcerning the studies of humanitie and philosophie.</hi> Which yet I haue refrained to doo, not of enuie, for I haue addicted my selfe to wish well vnto the Church &amp; common wealth; neither of vnkindnes, as though I were not willing to gratif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e them whom I was greatly bound too: but partly through bashfulnes, least any man should thinke me to hunt after glory, which young men are too gréedie of; partly through the knowledge of mine owne weaknes, who neither in respect of wit, nor age, nor learning, was ripe inough to bring foorth fruites which might be set before all men to be
<pb n="662" facs="338"/>
tasted off. For though I desire to benefitte all whom I may, hauing learned of <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>Epist.</hi> 9. <hi>ad Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyt. Tarent.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Plato</hi> that <hi>I am not borne for my selfe alone, but for my countrey; neither can I benefitte my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey more by any meanes, then by teaching the waies how to attaine to good artes,</hi> as <note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>De diuinat. lib.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>Tully</hi> thought well: yet I fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red least I should offend in a common faute, <hi>an itching lust to write,</hi> which <note n="e" place="margin">
         <hi>Epist. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>p.</hi> 1. <hi>ad August.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Horace</hi> did terme <hi>madnes</hi> in his daies, what would he haue done if he had liued in ours? in which there is such plenty both of passing wits, and of works excellent, that wise men may iustly thinke it vnmeete to publish any thing, that is not wrought with cunning, filed with iudgement, pooli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed with labour, fruitfull for commoditie, and for vse necessary. Howbeit, after that I was discharged of that profession of artes of humanitie, that I might the better applie the studie of diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie: what before of bashfulnes and iudgement I had still re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frained to doo in things of lesse importance, least I should doo it more rawly then I thought méete; the duetie which I owe to God and his Church hath mooued me now to do that in a weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie matter, though not so ripely as I would. Which thing, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken both by the aduise and the request of the godly, I was occasioned to thinke off by one <hi>Richard Bristow,</hi> an English<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man borne, abiding at <hi>Doway,</hi> professing the <hi>Romish</hi> faith: who hath set foorth a poisoned worke against the faith and Church of Iesus Christ, the faith which we professe, the Church of which we be. That worke, entitled <hi>Motiues to the catholike faith,</hi> when first he set it foorth, he hath abridged since into a pamphlet of <hi>Demaundes to be proponed of catholikes to heretikes,</hi> and printed it againe: setting before vs the same vnsauory Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worts, twise sodden by himselfe, a thousand times by Popish cookes, to the great anoyance of guestes, if they féede on it; great loathing, if they féede not. What a gréeuous iniury therein be hath doon to the Church of England, nor only to the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die thereof, but to the seuerall partes also, by raysing vp vntrue and wicked surmises, by casting out reprochfull spéeches, by lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heresies to our charge: it shalbe declared (as I heare) shortly; in the meane season let the godly iudge: whiles, to beginne with our most gratious <hi>Queene,</hi> the daughter of godlinesse, the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the faith▪ the mainteiner of peace, the nurse of the Church, the preseruer of the weale publik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, the mother of our countrey▪
<pb n="663" facs="338"/>
he doth not onely <note n="f" place="margin">
         <hi>Motiu.</hi> 47.</note> note her by the name of <hi>Pharao,</hi> but also <note n="g" place="margin">
         <hi>Mot.</hi> 15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 40.</note> putteth secretely into mens heads that she is not a lawfull, but a <hi>pretensed Queene,</hi> (as <note n="h" place="margin">
         <hi>Bulla Pij quinti contr. Regin. Angl. Nicol. Sander. de visib. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch. eccles. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Laurent. Sur. in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>er. ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note> the Papistes terms her:) of her Maiesties faithfull and obedient <hi>subiectes</hi> he saith that they <note n="i" place="margin">
         <hi>Motiu.</hi> 40.</note>
      <hi>obey her for common humanitie,</hi> not of duetie: to traitors, who suffred for taking armes against her, he geueth the title of <note n="k" place="margin">
         <hi>Motiu.</hi> 15</note>
      <hi>holy and most glorious Martyrs</hi>: he sclaunderously repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that <note n="l" place="margin">
         <hi>Demaund.</hi> 48.</note>
      <hi>the wiser sort and principall of the Realme haue prooued by experience of our dooings that our religion is no religion at all</hi>: that our <note n="m" place="margin">
         <hi>Motiu.</hi> 39.</note>
      <hi>Bishops and Ministers are most ill and wicked,</hi> and <note n="n" place="margin">
         <hi>Motiu.</hi> 31.</note>
      <hi>very fewe who preach, and they scarce euer preach vpon the mysteries of faith</hi>: that our people <note n="o" place="margin">
         <hi>Demaund.</hi> 41.</note>
      <hi>the neerer they come to the preachers doctrine, the more they fall away from order and godlines,</hi> assuring yet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to be <hi>saued by faith only be they neuer so wicked</hi>: that in our <note n="p" place="margin">
         <hi>Motiu.</hi> 31.</note>
      <hi>Vniuersities,</hi> either <hi>nothing is studied</hi>; or <hi>the arte of speaking only, not Diuinitie</hi>; or if <hi>Diuinitie,</hi> not all, but <hi>a fewe points of it</hi>: that <note n="q" place="margin">
         <hi>Demaund.</hi> 41. <hi>&amp; Motiu.</hi> 31.</note>
      <hi>our countrey is full</hi> not of men, but of monsters, of <hi>Atheistes,</hi> of <hi>Achrists,</hi> of them who beléeue not that a mans <hi>soule</hi> dooth liue more then a beasts when it is gone out of the body: finally, (not to rake out of those caues of brimstone the rest of the <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Psalm.</hi> 120.4..</note>
      <hi>coales of iuniper</hi> which he dooth throw both generally vpon whole estates, and vpon many lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and godly men particularly,) that <hi>our Church,</hi> the very body of <hi>our Church,</hi> dooth not foster an heresie or two, but <note n="r" place="margin">
         <hi>Demaund.</hi> 38.</note>
      <hi>hath reuiued many old heresies,</hi>
      <note n="s" place="margin">
         <hi>Demaund.</hi> 51.</note>
      <hi>besides at least a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand more of their owne inuention</hi>; that it committeth not a sinne or two, but <note n="t" place="margin">
         <hi>Motiu.</hi> 39.</note>
      <hi>holdeth a common schoole of sinne,</hi> wherein the <hi>scholers</hi> be most lewde, and the <hi>masters</hi> lewder; that it <note n="u" place="margin">
         <hi>Demaund.</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>thinketh verely there is no saluation at all, no reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> a thing which I tremble to mention, but this cockatrice with venemous mouth hath said, hath said? nay he hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten it, and he hath writen it with a penne of iron, he hath wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten it to last as a monument of his sclaunder, that we <hi>thinke ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily there is no saluation at all, none at all,</hi> and that <hi>our reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion indeede is no religion.</hi> Now, these false and sclaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous spéeches against our Church, wherewith he hath besette his worke in sundry places as with precious stones, are vnderlaide with reasons against our Churches faith, begotten of the same
<pb n="664" facs="339"/>
father, and sisters germaine to the sclaunders: loose, and dull, in truth; yet in apparance sharpe, and sound: which although the skilfull might crush in péeces without harme, yet might they doo harme by stinging the vnskilfull: euen as a scorpion if he sting a man, dooth hurt him with his sting; but if you bruse him straight and with his body brused anoint the part stoong, he dooth you no hurt. Wherefore to the intent that this scorpion of <hi>Bristow,</hi> pricking with two stings, (as the worst kind of scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions is wont,) the one of sclaunders, the other of cauilles, might doo no hurt to our men, whom in the vniuersities or other parts of the realme he is thought to haue stoong: many godly men haue wished him to be brused, that, if not all the parts, yet at least so many as the grace of God (which only healeth) would recure, might therewith be anointed. And this doo they séeme to haue wished so much the more, because some men hauing litle skill in physiche doo thinke that this scorpions stingings are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable. For both <hi>Bristow</hi> himselfe, as <hi>Thraso <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Terence,</hi> praising his owne spéeches, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Terent in Eunucho.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>And now they were all afraide of me,</hi> doth proudly aske <note n="y" place="margin">
         <hi>Demaund.</hi> 34.</note>
      <hi>whether any of our great Masters will answere his Demaundes</hi>; as though we had neither shield in the Church to quench the fierie dartes of Satan, nor physician in Israel to heale such as are wounded: and I know not what <hi>Gnatho,</hi> which hath cast abroad of late infamous verses in our vniuersitie, hath insolently boasted that <note n="z" place="margin">A <hi>sclaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous libell,</hi> sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi> 1577.</note>
      <hi>the Captaines trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble amazed with Bristowes lightning,</hi> as though he had astoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Coronells of our army, &amp; not the souldiers onely. But let <hi>Bristow</hi> know that nether all doo feare him, howsoeuer <hi>he hath touched the youthes in his Pasquines</hi>: nor poore men haue cause to stand in doute of him, though he threaten <hi>(being armed with a leauer and a dish-clout) that a wil quel all who stand in his way, &amp; crush thē in peeces.</hi> And if the Parasites of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Pope think that to be <hi>lightning,</hi> which he hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>asht to burn England: sure it is such <hi>lightning</hi> as was (after the <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Virgil. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>id. lib.</hi> 6.</note> Poet) the <hi>lightning</hi> of <hi>Salmoneus, who shaking oft a torch, did counterfeit the thundring soundes and lightning flames of heauen.</hi> But such kindes of <hi>lightning,</hi> although they daunt the wauering Gréekes and <hi>towne of Elis,</hi> whose king is <hi>Salmoneus</hi>: yet they daunt not the vnuincible Christians and citie of the liuing God, whose king is the Lord. And let him who flasht it take héed, if he bee
<pb n="665" facs="339"/>
wise, least his foolish <hi>lightning</hi> (as <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Apoll odor. de orig. Deor. lib.</hi> 1.</note> they say it happened to <hi>the lightner Salmoneus</hi>) be reuenged with true <hi>lightning</hi> of almightie God, to the vtter ruine of him selfe, his towne, and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens. For the Church which is <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.13.</note> lead by <hi>the holy Ghost into all truth,</hi> hath béene alreadie taught by him out of the scriptures, and shall be taught farther (through the grace of God,) what dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference there is betweene the <hi>lightning</hi> of <hi>Bristow,</hi> and the light of Iesus Christ: the <hi>lightning</hi> of <hi>Bristow,</hi> the heate whereof doth hurt the bodies which it striketh; the light of Iesus Christ, the beames whereof delite the men to whom it shineth: the <hi>light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> euill and pestilent, which blindeth them who sée, and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them who liue; the light, good and healthfull, which giueth sight vnto the blinde, and life vnto the dead. Neither are wee without many godly men of excellent autoritie, learning, and iudgement, euen amongst them whom <note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>maund.</hi> 34.</note> this <hi>Tertullus</hi> nameth reprochef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lly <note n="e" place="margin">
         <hi>M. Nowel</hi> in his <hi>confut.</hi> of <hi>Dormans dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe chapt.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>▪</note>
      <hi>great Mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ters,</hi> who could haue shewed this long ago. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>wbeit they haue stayed hetherto from dooing it, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther because they thought his folies were refuted before they were writen, for that (after the maner of the Popish writers) he bringeth no new matter, but scowreth vp old rustie stuffe, as <note n="e" place="margin">
         <hi>M. Nowel</hi> in his <hi>confut.</hi> of <hi>Dormans dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe chapt.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>▪</note> one of them did note long since: or because they purposed first to encounter with such as had writen before, and more pithily, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to deale after with the rest in due time, as <note n="f" place="margin">
         <hi>D. Fulke</hi> in the <hi>preface</hi> of his answere to <hi>Heskins, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> &amp; <hi>Rastell.</hi>
      </note> an other sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified of late that he meant: or because, the controuersies being sufficiently traueled in by many, they thought that they might well cease from this labour, though the Papistes ceased not from their impudencie; as <note n="g" place="margin">
         <hi>Ier.</hi> 28.11.</note>
      <hi>Ieremie</hi> hauing answered <hi>Hananiah</hi> once, gaue him no answere whē he repeated his error: or because perhaps some had no leasure from their weightier charge of fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Church; some listed not to striue with such a railing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son; some, while they thinke that others haue taken it in hand, do let it alone; al, either remember the counsell of the wise man, that <note n="h" place="margin">
         <hi>Prou.</hi> 26. <hi>ver.</hi> 4.</note>
      <hi>thou must not</hi> alwayes <hi>answere a foole, least thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like him,</hi> or if it were requisite to <note n="î" place="margin">
         <hi>vers.</hi> 5.</note>
      <hi>answere</hi> him now <hi>least he seeme wise in his owne conceit,</hi> they straine curtesie who should doo it. For my part, least the <hi>Philistines</hi> should vaunt any longer, as if their were no man amongst the <hi>Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> that durst fight with <hi>Goliath,</hi> or <note n="k" place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.10.</note> the <hi>Israelites</hi> be grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with hearing the host of the liuing God to be so <hi>defyed of</hi> an
<pb n="666" facs="340"/>
      <hi>vncircumcised Philistin</hi>: I purposed through gods grace, though perhaps <hi>Goliath</hi> would haue disdained me as a childe, yet I purposed to set vpon him in the name of the Lord of hostes, the God of the host of <hi>Israel.</hi> But when I had prepared my selfe to the battaile, and chosen <hi>smooth stones out of the brooke</hi> of Gods worde, <note n="l" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4.</note> which are <hi>mightie through God to cast downe holdes, &amp; euery high thing that is exalted against the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God:</hi> I heard that the matter was dispatched alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die by <note n="m" place="margin">
         <hi>D. Fulkes Retentiue</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowes Motiues</hi>
      </note> a stoute and faithful souldiour of Christ, by whom many <hi>Philistines</hi> had before beene conquered. Whose worke (as I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood since) is at the presse too, and shall be shortly published. Wherefore laying now aside my former purpose, I thought on that <hi>demaund</hi> and promise of <hi>Bristow</hi> touching <hi>the scripture</hi> and <hi>the Church,</hi> wherein he doth challenge and offer vs the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat. For whereas a countrie man of ours, vnder the title of <hi>an vnlearned Christian,</hi> (concealing his own name,) had set foorth <hi>a booke</hi> touching <hi>the autoritie of Gods word &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Church:</hi>
      <note n="n" place="margin">
         <hi>Demaund.</hi> 34.</note>
      <hi>Bristow</hi> willeth him to <hi>set out his booke, and put his name to it, with approbation of our Rabbines, and with priuilege,</hi> and promiseth that <hi>he shal quickly see it answered.</hi> This <hi>booke</hi> haue I sought for, but could not fall vpon it, all the copies of it (as I ghesse) being sold. Neither knew I how to speake with the autor, who had cōcealed his name, I dout not but for good cause. But to satisfie, (if not wholy, yet as farre as I might) the chalēge of <hi>Bristow</hi>: I haue set out this litle treatise of the same point, with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> autours <hi>name</hi> thereto, &amp; <hi>approbation,</hi> not of <hi>Rabbines,</hi> (whom we leaue to that Synagogue whose <note place="margin">
         <hi>Matt.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.7.</note> rulers <hi>loue to be called Rabbi, Rabbi,</hi> Maisters, &amp; Doctours,) but of graue and learned men whom it concerneth. Which thing I hope will like him so much the better, because it compriseth not onely that question touching <hi>the scripture</hi> and <hi>the Church</hi> that he desireth to be set out, but certaine other also of the same kinde, chiefly touching <hi>the Church,</hi> whereof he hath onely the bare name to boast of. And I looke for an answere so much the sooner, because there are now fower yeares past, since <note n="p" place="margin">In <hi>the title</hi> of his booke of <hi>Demaundes.</hi>
      </note> he promised a Latin booke: to which whether it be come abroad already, or to come shortly, he may ioine (if it please him) an answere to these <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusions.</hi> Wherein if he thinke it méete for him to deale, there are thrée things both easy to be doon, and reasonable (in my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment)
<pb n="667" facs="340"/>
which I will request him. One is, that he will set downe the text of my <hi>Conclusions</hi> wholy with his answere, (as I had determined to doo with his <hi>Demaundes,</hi>) that the readers may sée, what he confuteth, and how. An other, that he will not kicke against the prickes: that he will yéelde to the truth and not go about to darken the cléere light of the sunne of righteousnes with cauils and sclanders. The thirde, that if he be ashamed to say, <hi>the truth preuails against me</hi>: yet in reprouing such things as he assayeth to reproue, he will deale more soundly and sincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then <hi>D. Stapleton</hi> hath doon in his <hi>Doctrinall Principles of faith,</hi> a worke more full of wordes then truth. For to confute our doctrine, <note n="q" place="margin">
         <hi>Princ. fid. doctr. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</note> that <hi>the Church is the company of Gods elect and chosen,</hi> which we teach of <hi>the Catholike Church,</hi> and it is true: he teacheth <note n="r" place="margin">
         <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> that <hi>euill men are mingled in the Church with good, the reprobate with the elect,</hi> which thing is also true in <hi>the militant Church.</hi> But true thinges agrée with true thinges; ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>her doth one truth ouerthrow an other. We hold▪ that <hi>the Catholike Church, which is commended to vs in the Creede, is the whole company of Gods elect and chosen.</hi> He answereth, that <hi>the militant Church, which is mentioned in the scriptures too, containeth neither all the elect, nor them onely.</hi> And by this answere he saith he hath confuted the errour and heresie of the <note n="*" place="margin">So he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs of <hi>Iohn Husse,</hi> a godly man, and holy martyr, who taught as we do concerning <hi>the Church.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Hussites.</hi> But therein he dealeth like them of whom the prouerbe is, <hi>I asked for hookes, &amp; they say they haue no mattokes.</hi> But (to returne to my purpose) I haue thought good to publish my <hi>Conclusions,</hi> euen in the same sort as they were set downe in verses, and opened with supposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, according to the order of publike disputations of our Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersitie; the rather for this cause, that straungers might perceiue the kinde of our disputations; which and all things els of our U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuersitie are so debased by <note n="s" place="margin">
         <hi>Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>iu.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>Bristow,</hi> as if wisedom had béene borne with them alone, and should dye with them. Now these six <hi>Conclusions</hi> containe the chiefe fountaines,<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> and argument of the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions.</note> and as it were the very foundations of the controuersies, which we haue with the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> That the light thereof will be some helpe, I trust, to such as are not wilfully blinde, to scatter <hi>Bristowes</hi> mistes,<note place="margin">
         <hi>The first conclusion</hi>
      </note> and all the mistie cauils of <hi>Bristowes</hi> mates and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices.</p>
   <p>For where it is certaine by manifest proofe, as <note n="t" place="margin">
         <hi>In catechis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Concil. Trid.</hi>
      </note> the Church
<pb facs="341"/>
of <hi>Rome</hi> it selfe doth acknowledge, that <hi>the whole doctrine of religion and faith</hi> (which leadeth the faithfull to <hi>saluation</hi> and <hi>life</hi> by the true and right worship of God) <hi>is contained in Gods word</hi>: the Papists, to establish their superstitions and errours that are against the scripture, <note n="u" place="margin">
         <hi>Ibid. in exord. catechism.</hi>
      </note> diuide <hi>the worde of God</hi> into <hi>scripture</hi> and <hi>traditions</hi>; that what they can not finde in <hi>Gods writen worde,</hi> they may cauill that is was ordered by <hi>Gods traditionarie word,</hi> so to terme it. An old sleight and policie of the ympes of Satan, wherewith first the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pharises</hi> of the Iewes did craftily assay to beguyle our Sauiour Christ, as the <note n="x" place="margin">
         <hi>Matt.</hi> 15.2. <hi>Mark.</hi> 7.5.</note>
      <hi>Euangelistes</hi> haue writen: afterwarde the heretikes <note n="y" place="margin">
         <hi>Hieron. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in Aggae. cap.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian,</hi>
      <note n="z" place="margin">
         <hi>Iren. cont. haeres. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>Valentinus, Marcion,</hi> and their felowes assayed in like sort to beguyle Christians, as <hi>Ierom</hi> and <hi>Irenaeus</hi> shew. And these are the parents of that corrupt opinion concerning <hi>tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> which are called <hi>Apostolike</hi> as by <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Maximé de Tatiani radice crescentibus. Hieron. in Agg. cap.</hi> 1.</note> olde heretikes, so by <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Brist. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund.</hi> 29. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiu.</hi> 9.</note> new. The <hi>Roman</hi> Church embraceth the opinion as her owne childe: litle considering that it is a bastard, not conceyued by Christ, but got by theft from old heretikes. Unlesse perhaps she had it rather by adoption from <hi>Marcus Antonius</hi>: who <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>Cic. in Anton. Philip.</hi> 2.</note> when the <hi>Senate</hi> had ratified the actes of <hi>Caesar,</hi> he added to <hi>Caesars</hi> acts what he listed, and would haue it to stand as sure as if <hi>Caesar</hi> him selfe had enacted it. But that the opinion it selfe is a bastard (whosoeuer begot it, an heretike or an Heathen) and therefore to be shut out of <note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>Deu.</hi> 23.2.</note>
      <hi>the Lordes assemblie,</hi> which <hi>bastardes</hi> are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to <hi>enter into,</hi> my first <hi>Conclusion</hi> sheweth: wherein I haue declared that <hi>the holy scripture teacheth the Church all thinges necessarie to saluation.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now, the Papists, being cast downe from this bulwarke, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre vnto <hi>the Church,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>The se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion.</hi>
      </note> and say thereof <note n="e" place="margin">24. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>c. a recta. in glossa Catechis. Trid. in expos. Symb.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>it can not erre</hi>: that although their <hi>traditions,</hi> that is, their errours, did not spring from Christ, yet can they haue no faute, because <hi>the Church</hi> doth hold them. <note n="f" place="margin">
         <hi>In Thalia.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Herodotus</hi> reporteth, that <hi>Cambyses</hi> king of <hi>Persia,</hi> burning with wicked loue of his owne sister, asked the <hi>Persian</hi> iudges whether hee might mary her by the law of the realme. Whereto they made answere after consultation, that <hi>they found no law which permitteth a brother to mary his sister: but an other law they had found yet, which permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the king of Persians to do what he list.</hi> The <hi>Persian</hi> iudges offended, if they fained this law: the <hi>Persians,</hi> if they made it.
<pb n="669" facs="341"/>
But vpon that answere <hi>Cambyses</hi> did ioyne him self inces<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in mariage with his sister. The Heathens haue reproued this fact of his, as wicked: and is not the Papists <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>act most like vnto it? The <hi>Roman</hi> Church, the Quéene of <hi>Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ylon,</hi> hath burned with a cursed desire, not of her brother, as <hi>Cambyses</hi> of his sister, but of i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols &amp; superstitions. The aduise of Bishops, the <hi>Roman</hi> iudges, hath béene asked, whether she might mary superstitions and i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols by the law of Christ. The Bishops haue caused the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to be serched, and they finde no law whereby the worship of idols and superstitions is permitted: but an other law they haue found yet which prouideth that the Church can not erre in decreeing any thing. The <hi>Roman</hi> iudges offended who fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this law: the <hi>Romanists,</hi> who allow it. But vpon this sentence their Church pretendeth mariage, committeth adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, with superstitions and idols in most abominable sort. Yet <note n="g" place="margin">
         <hi>Demaund.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 34.</note>
      <hi>Bristow</hi> layeth it in the foundation of his house, and maketh mention of it as if it were the law of <hi>Austin,</hi> yea of <hi>Christ</hi>: but impudently, and fasly; that it may well appéere he neither knew what <hi>Christ</hi> said, nor what <hi>Austin</hi> meant. Wherefore to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the ruinous walles both of the house, and the foundation, I haue set the second <hi>Conclusion</hi> against it: which proueth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestly that <hi>the militant Church may erre not in maners on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but in doctrine too.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And that being settled doth séeme withall to settle &amp; strengthen the third: wherein it is auouched,<note place="margin">
         <hi>The third conclusiō.</hi>
      </note> that <hi>the holy scripture is of greater credit and autoritie then the Church.</hi> Truly, I should maruaile, that it could euer come into the minde of any man to thinke otherwise: had not <hi>S.</hi>
      <note n="h" place="margin">2. <hi>Thess.</hi> 2.4.</note>
      <hi>Paul</hi> foretold that <hi>the man of sinne, the sonne of perdition, should sit in the temple of God, &amp; exalt him self aboue God.</hi> Which prophecie hath béene fulfilled in their eyes, who haue séene Antichrist preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Christ: &amp; they haue séene Antichrist preferred before Christ, who haue séene the <hi>Church</hi> aduanced aboue the <hi>scripture.</hi> For what is detracted from the <hi>scripture,</hi> the worde of Christ; that is in déede detracted from Christ, the autour of the word. And that, which in shew is yéelded to the <hi>Church</hi>; is attributed in truth to the Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi> Both these thinges are euident by <note n="i" place="margin">
         <hi>Ecclesia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>. hierar. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4▪</note>
      <hi>Albertus Pighius</hi>: whose sayinges, concerning the <hi>scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> and the <hi>Church,</hi> although they bee very insolent and
<pb n="670" facs="342"/>
vngodly: yet there were amongst them who liued before <hi>Pighius</hi> euen of the chiefetaines of the Romish Church, as namely <note n="k" place="margin">
         <hi>Concil. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant. Sess.</hi> 13. <hi>Hoc non ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance.</hi>
      </note> the <hi>Fathers</hi> of the <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Constance,</hi> and Cardinall <note n="l" place="margin">
         <hi>Epist.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>ad Bohemos.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Cusanus,</hi> who spake more insolently. They who liued since, haue kept the sense and substance of <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sanus,</hi> and <hi>Pighius,</hi> in that they geue a Princely or rather a ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall <hi>autoritie to the Church</hi> for <hi>expounding the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> as Cardinall <note n="m" place="margin">
         <hi>Lib. de ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press. Dei verbo</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Hosius</hi> dooth. But they haue put fresh colours on it, and qualified as it were the rigour of the spéeches: in so much that <note n="n" place="margin">
         <hi>Demaund.</hi> 24.</note>
      <hi>Bristow</hi> (treading the steppes of <note n="o" place="margin">
         <hi>In confess. Petricou. cap.</hi> 15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.</note>
      <hi>Hosius,</hi>) requyreth not greater <hi>autoritie</hi> for the <hi>Church,</hi> but séemeth wel content to make it <hi>equall with the scripture.</hi> Howbeit, hee speaketh so, I know not how, that I dare not auouch he is of that mind. For though he doo chalenge like obedience to them both, like truth, like priuilege to be frée from errour: yet in that hée addeth, that <hi>we beleeue the scripture because of the Church,</hi> if he come as néere to the meaning of <note n="p" place="margin">
         <hi>Epist.</hi> 3. <hi>ad Bohemos.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Cusanus</hi> as he dooth to his wordes, that he thinke the <hi>scriptures</hi> credit and autoritie dependeth of the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>the Church imparteth autoritie canonicall</hi> (as <note n="q" place="margin">
         <hi>Ecclesiast. hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>rarch. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>Pighius</hi> expresly saith) <hi>vnto the scripture</hi>: he hath a harder forhead then I thought he had. Yet <note n="r" place="margin">
         <hi>Defens. fid. Trident. lib.</hi> 3.</note>
      <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dradius,</hi> the expounder and patrone of the faith of <hi>Trent,</hi> spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth much more modestly and religiously (to geue him his due praise) of the <hi>autoritie</hi> of the <hi>scriptures.</hi> Which first he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth that <hi>they haue not from men, but from God; not from the Church, but from the holy Ghost</hi>: and then he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth thereof, that <hi>it is detestable to teach that either pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane bookes may be made canonicall by the Church &amp; Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, or such as are certainly canonicall may be refused. Of the which things to affirme the one</hi> (he saith) <hi>it is a point of notorious impudencie: the other, of madnesse and impietie not to be suffered.</hi> O that <hi>Andradius</hi> had likewise detested the <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Reu.</hi> 17.4.</note>
      <hi>cuppe</hi> of <hi>the whoores abominations</hi> in other things? Or, (sith he is dead,) I would to God that all Christians, who of godly mind mislike somewhat in her, (and who dooth not mislike somewhat?) would mislike the rest of all her filthinesse too: nor onely be <hi>Christians almost,</hi> as <hi>Agrippa,</hi> but <hi>like both almost and altogether to Paul,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>The fourth conclusion</hi>
      </note> as <note n="s" place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 26.29.</note>
      <hi>Paul</hi> did wish to him.</p>
   <p>To the which end that I might help them forward, as much
<pb n="671" facs="342"/>
as lay in me: I haue doone the best I can to heale the dangerous humors of opinions, which do so anoy the tast of séely soules, that they thinke the heauenly bread to be poyson, and abhorre the swéetest foode of life as woormwood. These humours, that I speake off, are peruerse errours, which seduce them from the truth in that article of our Créede, <hi>I beleeue the holy catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church.</hi> For some are perswaded, that the name of <hi>holy Church</hi> belongeth not to the whole company of the Christian people, but to the Ministers onely and Bishops of the Church: no not to the Ministers of euery Church neither, but of the Church of Rome, euen the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Cardinals.</hi> Whom <hi>to haue gotten by a certaine custome to be called the church, and that the church had doon, receiued, and ordeined, that which was do on, receiued, and ordeined by them:</hi>
      <note n="t" place="margin">
         <hi>In defensore pacis. part.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>Marsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Patauinus</hi> did note in <note n="*" place="margin">Aboue two hundred yeres agoe.</note> his age, and it is too well knowen vnto men of yéeres. Other some, and they of the lernedder sort, acknowledge that the <hi>Church</hi> doth signifie the company of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men, and beléeuers, but they wil haue that company to bée <note n="u" place="margin">
         <hi>Francise. Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian. de eccles. &amp; ord. min. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>a people assembled by their own Bishop, and cleauing to the head,</hi> that is, <hi>to the Pope,</hi> least the Papall State be any way impaired. They comprehende therefore all such within that company as doo professe the faith, both the good and badde, holy and profane, godly and hypocrites. There are some also who thinke that <hi>by this point [to beleeue the holy church] the churches authoritie is commended to vs</hi>: that we should <hi>trust, credite, and obey the church,</hi> which <note n="x" place="margin">
         <hi>Catechism. Conc. Trident. in exposit. Symb.</hi>
      </note> the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> (it séemeth) would insinuate, though somewhat darkely and distrustfully. But <note n="y" place="margin">
         <hi>Demaund.</hi> 44.</note>
      <hi>Bristow</hi> therein dooth beare the bell away. For he (the more easily to deceiue <hi>English</hi> men, at least the simpler, if not all) worketh treacherie with the dooble signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of wordes; expounding this article, <note n="1" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>Credo eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siam.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>I beleeue the Church,</hi> as if the meaning of it were, <note n="2" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>Credo ecclesiae▪</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>I trust the Church:</hi> betwéene the which things there is great difference, and that very manifest, in the Gréeke and Latin, though in our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tounge not so. Yet this man was created <hi>Doctor</hi> at <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>way</hi>: and some doo account him a man of much value. O wretched professors of the <hi>Doway-schoole,</hi> that created such a <hi>Doctour</hi>: but more wretched Papistes, if they geue credit to such a <hi>Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour:</hi> who whether he be sophister or sclaunderer more notable,
<pb n="672" facs="343"/>
it is harde to say. A learned man among the Heathens (if I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member well) said, that <hi>physicians can not finde a medicine against the byting of a sclaunderer.</hi> But, because <note n="z" place="margin">
         <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.27.</note>
      <hi>the things are possible with God which are impossible with men</hi>: therefore vpon confidence of his gracious goodnes I haue assayed to make one against the biting of this sclaunderer, and of the like, in the fourth <hi>Conclusion</hi>: wherein I haue declared, (setting apart the Prelates of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and goates mingled with shéepe) that <hi>the holy Catholike Church which we beleeue, is the whole companie of Gods elect and chosen.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>The fifth conclusion</hi>
      </note>Moreouer, least the painting of the <hi>Romish Church</hi> should make vnskilfull young men to be enamored of her, when they should heare many commend her as <hi>Catholike, Apostolike, and sound in faith</hi>: to take this visard also away from her face, &amp; wash away her painting with water of the holy Ghost, I haue added y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fifth <hi>Conclusion,</hi> that <hi>the Church of Rome is not the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, nor a sound member of the Catholike church.</hi> A matter, cléere in truth, but hard to be perswaded: specially to louers: for <hi>Cupide</hi> is blinde. And as he saith in <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>In Bucolia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>t.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Theocritus,</hi>
      <q>The things that are not faire, seeme faire to him that is in loue.</q>
      <hi>Daphnis</hi> in the Poet saith so to <hi>Polyphemus:</hi> we by experience haue found it true in <hi>Bristow.</hi> For he, being besotted with the loue of the <hi>whoore,</hi> is not content to say that she alone is <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike</hi>: that errour were more tolerable; at least it were an error common to him with many. But <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Demaund.</hi> 44.</note> he affirmeth farther, that <hi>the Church might be &amp; was called Apostolike, for this cause one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that we might be directed thereby as by a marke to the Church of Rome, founded by the Apostles Peter and Paul, the onely Church now left of all the Churches Apostolike.</hi> Which flattering spéech of this louer <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>atechism. Concil. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. in expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sit. Symb.</hi>
      </note> the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, the bridegroome of his <hi>Church,</hi> though doating on his bride too, yet refuseth: acknowledging that <hi>the Church was called Apostolike (by</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>In Symbolo Concil. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinopolit.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>the Fathers in the Creede) to note the beginning of the Church which it hath from the Apostles, because they deliuered once the Churches doctrine, and spread it abroad through all the world.</hi> As for them <note n="e" place="margin">
         <hi>Bristow Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiu.</hi> 12.</note> that geue the title of <hi>Catholike</hi> to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi>: they must take aduisement how to cléere their boldnesse from attaint of
<pb n="673" facs="343"/>
sacriledge, who decke an adulteresse with the spoiles of the spouse of Christ; or, (to thinke the best of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi>) who spoile the mother to decke the daughter, and her not the best, with great wrong and iniurie to the rest of the sisters. For the name of <hi>Catholike</hi> dooth not appertaine to this or that <hi>Church,</hi> but to <hi>the Church vniuersall, continued through all nations, ages, and prouinces, from Adam vnto vs and to our poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie</hi>: as the <note n="f" place="margin">
         <hi>Catechism. Trid. in expo. Symb.</hi>
      </note> Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> and the <note n="g" place="margin">
         <hi>Andrad. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fens. fid. Trid, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Petr. a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to▪ contr. confes. Wirtenb. cap. de ecclesia.</hi>
      </note> expounders of the Councell (such is the force of truth) doo confesse plainly. But the chiefest errour that is to be abated, is theirs, who are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is of <hi>right opinion</hi> and <hi>sound in points of faith</hi>: yea, so <hi>sound</hi> and <hi>right,</hi> that they think <hi>no pestilent disease may attache her, no contagion infect her, no spot of vnfaithfulnes any way defile her.</hi> Of the which asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they alleage the Fathers, (to omitte the residue, men of ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser credit,) for principall patrones. And therein <note n="h" place="margin">
         <hi>Defens. fid. Trident. lib.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>Andradius</hi> dealeth somewhat wisely. For he dooth heape together witnesses without testimonies, the geuers of euidence without euidence, <hi>Austins, Ieroms, Basils, Athanases,</hi> and <hi>Chrysostoms.</hi> But <note n="i" place="margin">
         <hi>De vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ib. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nar. eccle. lib.</hi> 7.</note>
      <hi>Sanders</hi> much more gloriously. For he hath laide on such a l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ade of testimonies, that, if the sayings should be numbred and not weighed, we must léese our suite, no remedy. But all the Fathers (whom this pety-lawier produceth as speakers for the <hi>Popes monarchie,</hi>) doo either deny that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> did erre, or that it may erre: did erre, as <note n="k" place="margin">
         <hi>Aduers. hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Sander argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento</hi> 20,</note>
      <hi>Irenaeus, In the Church of Rome that doctrine hath beene kept still which was deliuered by the Apostles:</hi> may erre, as <note n="l." place="margin">
         <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>epist</hi> 3. <hi>aut epist.</hi> 55▪ <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. Pam. San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. argum.</hi> 42.</note>
      <hi>Cyprian,</hi> that <hi>the Romanes are they whose faith is commended and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by the Apostle, vnto whom vnfaithfulnes can not haue accesse.</hi> The former, who deny that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> did erre, speake not against vs. For we doo not say that it did erre in <hi>Irenaeus</hi> time, but that it dooth erre now. He denyeth that it did erre: we say that it dooth erre: doo we gainesay one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? <hi>Ierusalem</hi> is called <note n="m" place="margin">
         <hi>Ps.</hi> 48. <hi>ver.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>the citie of God</hi> by the <hi>Psalmist,</hi> and <note n="n" place="margin">
         <hi>ver.</hi> 9.</note> he is said there to be serued: <note n="o" place="margin">
         <hi>Esay.</hi> 1, 21.</note>
      <hi>Esay</hi> termeth it an <hi>har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot.</hi> The temple of the Lord is named <note n="p" place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 8.20.</note>
      <hi>the house of God,</hi> the house of prayer, by <hi>Salomon:</hi> by <hi>Christ</hi> it is reported to be <note n="q" place="margin">
         <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.13.</note>
      <hi>a denne of theeues.</hi> Dooth <hi>Esay</hi> speake against the <hi>Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mist,</hi> or <hi>Christ</hi> against <hi>Salomon</hi>? No, but the <hi>Psalmist</hi> sheweth
<pb n="674" facs="344"/>
what <hi>Ierusalem</hi> was, in his time: <hi>Esay,</hi> what in his. <note n="r" place="margin">
         <hi>Esai.</hi> 1.21.</note>
      <hi>The faithfull citie is become an harlot</hi>: it was a <hi>faithfull citie,</hi> but it <hi>is become an harlot. Salomon</hi> teacheth what <hi>the house of God</hi> ought to be: <hi>Christ,</hi> what it is made. <note n="s" place="margin">
         <hi>Matt.</hi> 21.13.</note>
      <hi>You haue made it a denne of theues:</hi> it was not to <hi>Salomon,</hi> but <hi>you haue made it.</hi> So <hi>Rome</hi> was likewise sound in the time of the Fathers, but the faithfull citie is become an harlot: the soundnes it hath lost, it hath got a leprousie: it was the house of God, it is a denne of théeues: it held <note n="t" place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.8.</note>
      <hi>the faith of Christ,</hi> but it is fallen from it. It <hi>had kept the doctrine still which was deliuered by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles,</hi> vntill the time of <hi>Irenaeus</hi>: but that it <hi>hath kept still</hi> vntil our time <hi>the doctrin which was deliuered by the Apostles,</hi> doth it thereof folow? Unlesse perhaps the Popes Courtiers will proue, that the whoores, the Courtisans which keepe their stewes, are virgins, because they were virgins when they were litle babes. The former Fathers then, who deny that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
      <hi>church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> did erre, doo not gainsay vs. The later, who deny that it may erre, gainsay vs in deed: but they gainesay y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> holy Ghost too. By whose inspiration the blessed Apostle exhorting the <hi>Roman church</hi> not to lift vp it selfe against the <hi>Iewes:</hi>
      <note n="m" place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20.</note>
      <hi>Be not high minded</hi> (saith he) <hi>but feare. For if God spared not the natural branches, take heed least he also spare not thee. Behold there fore the bountifulnes and seueritie of God: seueritie toward thē which haue fallen; but toward thee, bountifulnes, if thou continue in his bountifulnes: or els thou shalt also be cut off.</hi> The <hi>church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> therefore may be <hi>cut of</hi>: if <hi>cut of,</hi> then erre: if erre, then <hi>vnfaithfulnes may haue accesse vnto it.</hi> What? and was <hi>Cyprian</hi> of an other minde? Pardon me <hi>O Cyprian</hi>: I would beléeue thée gladly, but that beléeuing thee I should not beléeue the word of God. But whether we should rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue, God, or man: let the Papists iudge. At least, if they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue rather man then God: let them beléeue the reason and iudgement of their owne men. For <note n="n" place="margin">
         <hi>Pet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. a Soto contr. confess. Wirtenb. cap. de concilijs.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Sotus,</hi>
      <note n="o" place="margin">
         <hi>Alfons. a Castr. aduers. haeres. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.</note>
      <hi>Alfonsus,</hi>
      <note n="p" place="margin">
         <hi>Confess. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tric. cap.</hi> 24. <hi>&amp; contr. Brent. lib.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>Hosius,</hi>
      <note n="q" place="margin">
         <hi>Disputatio num aduersus Lutheranos Tom.</hi> 6. <hi>de au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorit. &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test. vniuer. ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. cap.</hi> 5.</note>
      <hi>Verratus,</hi> the lightes of the Papists, doo witnesse that <hi>any particular church may erre.</hi> But that <hi>the church of Rome is a particular church,</hi> the same <note n="r" place="margin">
         <hi>Ibid. cap.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>Verratus</hi> affirmeth, nor can the rest deny it. Wherefore if <hi>Cyprian</hi> did thinke that the <hi>church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> can not erre: in that he must him selfe be condemned of errour by the Papists iudgement. And so, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb n="675" facs="344"/>
all the testimonies of the Fathers are of two sortes, the one of them true, but cleane beside the purpose; the other to the purpose enough, but vntrue: it foloweth that the sicknes of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> can finde no helpe in any medicines of the Fathers. What haue we then to doo with them by whom olde <hi>Rome</hi> is praysed and reported <note n="s" place="margin">
         <hi>Iren. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Sander. argument.</hi> 4.</note>
      <hi>to gather together Christians to peace, and repaire their faith,</hi>
      <note n="t" place="margin">
         <hi>Dionys. epist. ad Soter. apud. Euseb. l.</hi> 4 <hi>c.</hi> 22. <hi>Sander. arg.</hi> 15.</note>
      <hi>to minister reliefe vnto the brethren &amp; the Churches,</hi>
      <note n="u" place="margin">
         <hi>Episcop. Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. in ep. ad Iul. apud Sozo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>Sander. arg.</hi> 109.</note> to be <hi>a schoole of the Apostles, a mother-citie of godlinesse,</hi>
      <note n="x" place="margin">
         <hi>Ignat. in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scri. ep. ad Rom. Sander. arg.</hi> 5.</note>
      <hi>a sanctified Church,</hi> and such like things a number? We haue to doo with new <hi>Rome,</hi> whom <note n="y" place="margin">
         <hi>Platin. Onu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phr. Sabellic. Guicciardin. Theodoric. a Niem. Abbas Vrsperg. &amp;c.</hi>
      </note> her owne stories, actes, and monuments doo conuince to be a nurse of wars, a parent of vnfaithfulnesse, a spoyler of the brethren, a worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of idols, a seate of couetousnesse, a ladie of pride, a cherisher &amp; inflamer of lustes, of outrages, of abominations: whose most louing <note n="z" place="margin">A famous Fryer ad Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, <hi>Baptista Mantuanus.</hi>
      </note> sonne complaineth of his mother, that <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Ecloga.</hi> 9.</note>
      <hi>her old fame continueth, but her goodnesse is gone;</hi> that <hi>her Pastours are turned into the shape of woolues, the neerer you come the filthier all thinges be;</hi> that <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Ecloga.</hi> 5.</note>
      <hi>trifles are giuen, gold is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, and onely money raigneth there;</hi> that <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>De calamitat. tempor. lib.</hi> 3.</note>
      <hi>the Church-goods are made to serue for scoffers, the altars for wantons, the temples for boyes abused by vnnaturall monsters;</hi> that <note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>Syluar. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Ode. vl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>the lawes diuine and humane are denyed, men and God deceiued, holinesse put to flight, godlinesse despised, renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and afflicted:</hi>
      <q>
         <l>Yet that a holy life would leade, from <hi>Rome</hi> see that ye flee:</l>
         <l>Though al things els be lawful there, yet good ye may not be.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>And these may séeme (I hope) both weightie causes, and iust,<note place="margin">
         <hi>The sixth conclusiō.</hi>
      </note> why <hi>the reformed Churches</hi> (to come to the last <hi>Conclusion</hi>) <hi>in England, Scotland, Fraunce, Germany, &amp; other kingdomes &amp; commō wealthes, haue seuered them selues from</hi> the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Rome.</hi> Though if this were al, that it were <hi>not lawful to lead a holy life at Rome,</hi> y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we <hi>might not be good,</hi> as <hi>Mantuan</hi> affirmeth: we would haue departed from y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> citie of <hi>Rome</hi> as <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuan</hi> aduiseth vs, but we would not haue gone frō the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> If onely smal infirmities had cra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed the health of <hi>Rome</hi> in pointes of faith, such as certaine did in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> time of the Fathers: we would haue lamented▪ but tolerated it; &amp;, taking compassion of <note n="e" place="margin">
         <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.2.</note>
      <hi>men being vnwarily fallen into a faute, we would haue born their burdens.</hi> But sith in the felowship of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
      <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> it was not lawful for vs, either to serue God with a holy worship,
<pb n="179" facs="345"/>
or to beléeue God with a holy faith, as God hath commanded; sith the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> being taken with contagious diseases &amp; a frensy, did put her counsellers to the fyer, frends to the sword, brethren to cruell death, and stained the faith of Christ with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proches, creatures with the Lordes honour, Gods seruice with idolatrie: we went away from Papists, not willingly, as from men; not vnwillingly, as from heretikes; and <hi>reforming</hi> our <hi>Churches</hi> by the rule of Gods worde, we seuered them from the contagion of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> Wherin because nothing was doon by our brethren, but that which the Apostle <hi>S. Paul,</hi> a cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen instrument of the holy Ghost, both <note n="f" place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 19.9.</note> did, and <note n="g" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.5. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17.</note> taught to be doon, as I haue proued in the Conclusion: the Lord shal iudge beweene our <hi>Churches</hi> and <note n="h" place="margin">
         <hi>Demaund.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>Bristow,</hi> who condemneth them of the same <hi>schisme,</hi> of which the <hi>Donatists</hi> were guiltie; and he will giue sentence in the last day that <hi>we haue beene seuered from the Church of Rome by the prescript of his word,</hi> that is, <hi>lawfully.</hi> But, some man will say, you ought not to leaue the felowship of the <hi>Romans,</hi> of <note n="i" place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.7.</note>
      <hi>them which are at Rome, belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of God, Saints by calling, whose faith is spoken of throughout the whole world.</hi> But, I answere, that the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> which now are there, be not <hi>Romans</hi>: they be carkases of <hi>Romans.</hi> It is an other <hi>Milo: his lustie armes are dead.</hi> It is an other <hi>Hector: how greatly chaunged from him?</hi> But you ought to obey and not resist the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi>
      <note n="1" place="margin">
         <hi>Optimus</hi>
      </note> most good in grace, <note n="2" place="margin">
         <hi>Maximus</hi> as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Papists call him.</note> most great in power, the vicar of Christ, <note n="k" place="margin">1. <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi> 5.3.</note>
      <hi>the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessour of Peter.</hi> But, that <note n="l" place="margin">
         <hi>Andrad. defen. fid. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>rid. lib.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>we must resist him, if he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand thinges vniust and pernicious</hi> yea, that <note n="m" place="margin">
         <hi>Gent. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>eruet. de reparand. eccles. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>sciplin.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>it is the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Princes to resist him in vnlawfull thinges</hi>: the Papists them selues teach. But Christians ought to <note n="n" place="margin">
         <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4.3.</note>
      <hi>keepe vnitie of spirit in the bond of peace</hi>: and <note n="o" place="margin">
         <hi>Cicer. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip.</hi> 13.</note>
      <hi>the name of peace is sweeete, the thing it selfe both pleasant and healthfull.</hi> But through vnitie of spirit we ought to grow together <note n="p" place="margin">
         <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4.13.</note>
      <hi>into the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of of faith</hi>: and to <note n="q" place="margin">
         <hi>Philip.</hi> 4.2.</note>
      <hi>be all of one minde,</hi> but <hi>in the Lord.</hi> If <hi>peace</hi> should be <hi>made</hi> with the Pope and Papists, it would be like <note n="r" place="margin">
         <hi>Cicer. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipp.</hi> 12.</note> the <hi>peace</hi> with <hi>Antonie</hi> and his adherents; that is, not <hi>a peace,</hi>
      <note n="s" place="margin">
         <hi>Eurip. Iphig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. in Aul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>d.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>but an agreement</hi> of <hi>slauery to them,</hi> nay, of impietie. Wherefore, as <hi>Agamemnon</hi> (in a Gréeke Poet) did answere his brother <hi>Menelaus</hi> of whom he was requested to shew him selfe a brother by giuing his consent to a wicked act: so doo I answere
<pb n="170" facs="345"/>
my brother requesting me to ioyne with him in felowship of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> whose faith is vnholy, whose seruice is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly;
<q>
         <l>
            <note n="*" place="margin">
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</note>My wittes I would enioy with thee:</l>
         <l>But madde with thee I would not bee.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>And here an ende of my preface. Onely this remaineth, that I desire hartily and beséech all Christians, who shall take paines in reading hereof, that they will reade, weigh, and interpret all thinges with a Christian minde; lay aside the preiudice of their owne opinions; <note n="t" place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.1.</note>
      <hi>examin the spirits, whether they be of God or no</hi>; séeke to finde the truth, and loue it being found; aduertise me if they thinke I haue missed in any thing; beare with my briefenes, because I was constrained to shut vp much in few wordes: looke how faithfull and diligent I haue béene in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and prouing the <hi>Conclusions,</hi> whereof God is my witnes who will reu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ale the secretes of thoughtes; so moderate and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different let them shew them selues in censuring and iudging of that which they shall reade, as before the Lord who shal be iudge of iudges. Finally, let them folow the godly people of <hi>Beroea,</hi> who (when <hi>Paul</hi>
      <note n="u" place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 17.11.</note>
      <hi>preached</hi>) <hi>receiued the word with al readines of mind, and dayly serched the scriptures whether those things were so</hi>: &amp; not the froward <hi>Luciferians,</hi>
      <note n="x" place="margin">
         <hi>Hieron. in dialog. aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Lucif. c.</hi> 9.</note>
      <hi>of whom he confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth who best knew the maners of his owne companions, that they might be conuinced more easily then perswaded.</hi> As for you, my fathers and brethren welbeloued, with remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of whom I haue consecrated my labour (such as it is) to the Church of God: I pray you and beséech you by our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, who hath redéemed vs with his pretious blood and sanctified vs to him selfe, that you will striue by all meanes to aduance the glory of God, to cherish the séedes of godlinesse, to helpe forward the Churches safetie, to nourish fruitfull plantes, to make the Uniuersities praise to be encreased, I meane <note n="y" place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.29.</note>
      <hi>the prayse which is, not of men, but of God.</hi> Confute you the ill spéeches of <hi>Bristow,</hi> by your deedes: and shew, by your workes, that the crimes wherewith hee chargeth vs are sclanders. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow ye well the good oportunitie of time in studie of good artes, by hearing, reading, disputing, meditating, speaking, and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Doo ye the worke of the Lord with ioynt desire, and will, and trauaile: <note n="z" place="margin">
         <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.4.</note>
      <hi>one body, one spirit,</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Ier.</hi> 32.39.</note>
      <hi>one hart, one way.</hi>
      <pb n="678" facs="346"/>
Stirre vp exercise of learning, decayed (I had almost said,) but I hope better. Destroy those wanton lusts that draw men from studie; idlenes, a swéete euill; delicacie, the baite of <hi>Venus</hi>; the ryote of feasts, the vanitie of apparell, vnhonest pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimes, vnseasonable drinkinges, the plagues of stageplay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the sights and shewes of <hi>Theaters.</hi> Last of all, to conclude with the Apostles wordes, <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8.</note>
      <hi>whatsoeuer things are true, what soeuer things are honest, whatsoeuer things are iust, whatsoeuer things are pure, whatsoeuer things are woorthie loue, whatsoeuer things are of good report, if there be anie vertue, and if there be any praise, thinke ye on these things. If there be any vertue, and if there be any praise,</hi> brethren, <hi>thinke ye on these things.</hi> The God of might and mercie lighten vs all with the grace of his holy spirit: that the heads of Colleges may be <hi>present to gouerne,</hi> and gouerne to benefit the companie committed to them, <note n="c" place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 19. <hi>ver.</hi> 20.</note> as <hi>Samuel</hi> was wont: that the members of Colleges may lerne vnder <hi>Samuel</hi> to <hi>prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi> by speaking of, and setting foorth the praise of God, as the <hi>prophets</hi> did: that young men, who studie the artes of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie, may in other things be vnlike to <hi>Saul,</hi> yet like to <note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>ver.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>Saul among the prophets</hi>: that Colleges themselues and all our companies may be assemblies, not of prophets onely, but of such as prophecie and folow the les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of the prophets, to the honor of God, the comfort of the godly, and our owne salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, through Iesu Christ our Lord. Fare ye well. From <hi>Corpus Christi</hi> College. The 2. of <hi>February.</hi> 1580.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in Christ Iesus, Iohn Rainoldes.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>