<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[To The Reader]</title>
           <author>B., E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115852_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00200</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1025</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115852</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[To The Reader]</title>
                 <author>B., E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The curse of sacriledge : Preached in a priuate parish church, the Sunday before Michaelmas last. To which are annexed some certaine quære's, which are pertinent to the vnmasking of our homebred church-robbers. D.E.B</title>
                 <author>Brouncker, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lichfield, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 38, 6 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <opener>
      <salute>READER,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> CALL heaven to witnesse, the prime marke I ayme at by this my declamation against Sacriledge, is the flourishing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state of this Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and that by diversion of those Iudgments which by the perspectiue of the word, I des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry approaching towards vs, vnlesse a <hi>non plus vltra</hi> bee set to this still spreading Leaprosie. Meruaile not how I dare <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> thus freely speake in a poynt that tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches so farre on the <hi>vtile</hi> and <hi>iucundum</hi> of thousands, and some of those too <hi>Grandies,</hi> For I am confident hee is no Legitimate Priest, who is afraid to thwart any sinne, though neuer so much backt and vpheld by an arme of flesh; If sinners haue browes of brasse, Gods Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadors must not haue hearts captiuated with feare &amp; bashfullnes. If the Laities hands be fraudulently busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in snatching and filching, our tongues must not bee lockt vp from sharp and zealous reprouing. It is the Character of a wise man to bee free in Rebukes, when vice is bold and daring. For myne owne part I desire no longer to liue then I dare resolutly say with <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the great, <hi>In causa in qua Deo placere cupio, homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes non formido,</hi> As I acknowledge myne owne ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, so withall I remember that one of the <hi>Infantery</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/> may doe acceptable seruice in the field, as well as one of the <hi>Cauagliery.</hi> An ordinary Pursiuāt deliuer the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of a King, as well as a Herald at Armes; That a musket may set a Cannon a roaring. That their paines was as requisite for the Temple who brought but stones and Cement, as theirs Who brought Gold and rich orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments It is the Lords method to bring great things to passe by small beginnings, to ordaine strength out of the mouthes of babes and sucklings. And if like little despi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed <hi>Dauid</hi> I shall not conquer this vast <hi>Goliah,</hi> yet if I shall put the worthies of <hi>Israell</hi> into Armes who are likely to winne the day, I shall deeme my selfe so happy, as to cry out with him, <hi>ite triumphales circum mea tempora lauri.</hi> Nor mayest thou deeme this ouermuch presumption, when as victory is neuer wholly ascribed to him who strikes the last stroke, but they who gaue the first or second onset, may clayme a leafe or two in the triumphant Laurell, And all bee it I subscribe to him who sayes hee sees no reason that soe high a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as Diuinity should bee presented to the people in the sordid ragges of the tongue; Nor that hee who speakes from the father of languages should deliuer his Embas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage in an ill one, Yet haue I in this my Sermon followed both the counsaile of blessed <hi>Austine</hi> when hee sayes, <note place="margin">Lib. 4. de do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrina Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sti cap. 10.</note>
      <hi>qui docet, vitabit omnia verba quae non docent,</hi> Hee who teacheth must bauke all those words which teach not. His reason is, <hi>quid enim prodest locutionis inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritas, quam non sequitur intellectus audientis.</hi> As also that of learned <hi>Tostatus, tenetur Doctor illo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do docere, quo sentiat discipulis vtile esse,</hi> A Teacher must vse that method by which hee may most profit
<pb facs="3"/> those who are learners And that because (saith hee) <hi>docere non est propter docentem, sed propter eos qui</hi>
      <note place="margin">Comment: in 3. prolog. Hieron: Qu. 17. tom. 1 in Mattheum.</note>
      <hi>docentur.</hi> Teaching hath for its obiect the hearers and not the speaker himselfe. If thou aske mee why I craue not the protection of some powerfull <hi>Moecenas,</hi> know first, that as it is held a folly to haue recourse by our praiers to the Saincts in heauen when the way lyes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to Christ himselfe, so I take it to bee needlesse to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition for mans countenancing of that which I am well assured the Allmighty God accepts of as a sweet-smelling Sacrifice offered vp from the Altar of a wel-disposed heart. As also I am of opinion, I may, as fitly as euer <hi>Diogenes,</hi> light a Candle at noone day, and goe vp and downe with a <hi>hominem quaero</hi> as being ignorant where to meet with a man, which some way or other falls not vnder the curse of my text, who either by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying impropriated tithes, or by pleading vniust Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes, makes not a sheepe of this or that shepheard by withdrawing from him part of his annuall accrewing fleece. Now for a farewell, let mee entreat thee to weigh and examine these ensuing lines without preiudice, so shall I hope at length to reap some part of the large crop of my desire.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the rough and craggy way to blisse E. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>