<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VERTVOVS, Renowned, High, and mightie Monarch, JAMES, our dread Soveraigne, by the grace of God King of great Britaine, France, and Ireland, Defen∣der of the saith, &amp;c. All grace, true honour, continuall health, ioyfull prosperitie, with all other princely vertues in this life, and the crowne of glory, through the mercy of Ie∣sus Christ, in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Andrewes, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115373_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19511</idno>
           <idno type="STC">594</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115373</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VERTVOVS, Renowned, High, and mightie Monarch, JAMES, our dread Soveraigne, by the grace of God King of great Britaine, France, and Ireland, Defen∣der of the saith, &amp;c. All grace, true honour, continuall health, ioyfull prosperitie, with all other princely vertues in this life, and the crowne of glory, through the mercy of Ie∣sus Christ, in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Andrewes, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Christ his crosse or The most comfortable doctrine of Christ crucified : and ioyfull tidings of his passion, teaching vs to loue, and imbrace his crosse, as the most sweete and celestiall doctrine vnto the soule, and how we should behaue our selues therein according to the word of God. Newly published by Iohn Andrewes minister and preacher of the word of God at Barricke Basset in the country of Wiltes. Wherein is contained, first the chiefe and principall motiues and causes, that should moue and stirre vs vp to the earnest meditation of his passion. Secondly, with what minde we should come to his meditation. Thirdly, how divers and manifold is the meditation of the passion. The fourth part intreateth of the types, and figures contained in the old Testament, touching the passion of Christ</title>
                 <author>Andrewes, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 <publisher>Andrewes, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Barnes, Joseph</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 72, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT VERTVOVS, Renowned, High, and mightie Monarch, JAMES,</hi> our dread Soveraigne, by the grace of God King of great Britaine, France, and Ireland, Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the saith, &amp;c. All grace, true honour, continuall health, ioyfull prosperitie, with all other princely vertues in this life, and the crowne of glory, through the mercy of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, in the life to come.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST Gracious &amp; Dread Soveraigne, vnworthy (I know) are these my endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, either to bee shrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the prejudice of contempt, vnder your Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Majesties protection, (a Prince of so great magnanimitie and iudgement) or offered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your learned view; yet your continuall bountifulnes and dayly favours towardes good learning (especially ifit savour of divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity) as it doth exceed your Roialty or great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, so will it also (I trust) excuse my boldnes in this my humble entreating your gracious
<pb facs="3"/>
Patronage of this my first &amp; vnlearned Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atise, the which being rawly comprised in a few scattered leaues, and as rudely composed in a sort of scribled &amp; vnlettered lines, the out ward haske whereof, although it be farre vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the lordly gift that <hi>Aconitanus</hi> offered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Alphonsus</hi> king of <hi>Aragon,</hi> being vnpolished, may seeme vnpleasant, yet (no doubt) the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward kernell once tasted, and well digested, may proue cordiall, and right fruitfull. And although I cannot with ramping Lyons run in with mightie prayes; yet with the little Ant by hawling in my wheaten graine, I am ready prest to signifie the force of my loue, &amp; loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty towards your most excellent Maiestie. And thus in al humility, I beseech your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to accept this mite of my poore la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours: so shall I (if God spare me life) be cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted &amp; encouraged, vnder so mightie a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourer, to proceed in the like studies; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my boundē dutie, incessantly with all humilitie pray vnto almightie God (by whom both Kings and Princes raigne) to his glory not onely to preserue your Grace, in
<pb facs="3"/>
Royall throne of Monarchie vpon earth, but also to be farre more adorned, to raigne with a celestiall crowne of glorie in the kingdome ofheauen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Royall Maiesties faithfull and ever loyally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted subiect, Io. ANDREWES.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>