<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE GODLY AND Well-affected Reader whosoever.</title>
           <author>Otes, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115186_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08578</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18896</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115186</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE GODLY AND Well-affected Reader whosoever.</title>
                 <author>Otes, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An explanation of the generall Epistle of Saint Iude. Delivered in one and forty sermons, by that learned, reverend, and faithfull servant of Christ, Master Samuel Otes, parson of Sowthreps in Norfolke. Preached in the parish church of Northwalsham, in the same county, in a publike lecture. And now published for the benefit of Gods church, by Samuel Otes, his sonne, minister of the Word of God at Marsham</title>
                 <author>Otes, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, Elizabeth</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 58, 61-400, 403-424, 405-472, 475-525, 19 pages, folded table, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE GODLY AND <hi>Well-affected Reader whosoever.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, I am bold at the length to present to thy view these Sermons of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers upon the Epistle of Saint <hi>Iude,</hi> which though in this Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned age, among so many excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and accurate Sermons and Treatises, it may seeme pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption to publish, yet in this sinfull age, I thought they might proove most usefull for the beating downe of sinne, and convincing the consciences, and converting the soules of sinners, there being not many of this kinde: for though knowledge abound, and learning florish, and most desire to have their understanding informed, and affections pleased, yet true godlines and righteousnes is dayly decaying, and few desire to have their lives re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; though they have the <hi>forme of godlines,</hi> yet they have denied the <hi>power</hi> thereof; and though they professe they <hi>know God,</hi> yet in their <hi>works they deny him.</hi> Which this man of God considering, did bend all his labour and learning to the beating downe of sinne, and building up in vertue and saving knowledge: wherein how powerfull and prevalent hee was, thou mayst ghesse by these Sermons <hi>tanquam ex ungue leonem.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning himselfe, his learning, life, &amp;c. It is not meete I should say much, seeing I may seeme to speake
<pb facs="5"/>
partially out of affection, yet I hope I may without blame give testimony to that truth which all that knew him will acknowledge; namely, that hee was a faithfull labourer in the worke of the Lord, a worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that needed not to bee ashamed, a burning and a shining light, burning with zeale, shining both by divine Doctrine and godly conversation. Burning so, as he consumed himselfe, to give light to others; and shining, not onely before his Parochiall charge, where hee lived and exercised his Ministery; being as an <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi>
      <note place="margin">Sowthreps in Norfolke.</note> to that <hi>Hyppo,</hi> a <hi>Polycarpe</hi> to that <hi>Smyrna,</hi> but the whole Country; so as they all knew him a faithfull <hi>Samuel,</hi> a learned, laborious, and godly Preacher, who did empty himselfe, to fill others, and did waste and consume his strength, to instruct the flocke commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his charge. Neither was the lustre of his light confined in that Parish or Country wherein hee lived, but shined further into other parts of this Kingdome, so as three very Godly and Eminent Persons in this State; worthy instruments of Gods glory, florishing in their time with many excellent graces and vertues on earth, and now all shining glorious Saints in Heaven, did take notice of him, and did successively entertaine him Chaplaine (namely, Sir <hi>Francis Walshingham,</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary to the State, Sir <hi>Iohn Popham,</hi> Lord-Chiefe-Iustice of England, and Sir <hi>Henry Hobart,</hi> Knight and Baronet, Lord Chiefe-Iustice of the Common Pleas;) all which notwithstanding, hee continued so lowly in his owne eyes, and so zealous in his Function, as hee neither carelesly, nor ambitiously, left his Cure to seeke other preferment: But having at any time performed his due observance to those Honorable Persons, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as hee was engaged, hee presently returned to his accustomed weekely, and almost daily taske of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching: for his heart was so inflamed with the zeale of Gods glory, and yet so ballanced with the feare of God, and true humility, that neither the learning nor graces that were in his owne heart, nor the lustre and
<pb facs="5"/>
grace he had with other, did puffe him up with price: and this humility and lowlines in his owne eyes <hi>(Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na &amp; rara virtus,</hi> as S. <hi>Bernard</hi> tearmes it) made him thinke neither these nor any of his Sermons or writings worthy of publike view, so as though hee were much importuned by offers and earnest entreaties, yet would not be drawne to publish any of them. But for as much as it is not meete, those learned labours should dye with him, whereby, hee being dead, may (with <hi>Abel)</hi> yet speake, and the living bee furthered in the way of life, I resolved to publish these Sermons upon S. <hi>Iude,</hi> Preached in a weekly Lecture to a publike audience on the market day at <hi>Northwalsham</hi> in <hi>Norfolke;</hi> Intending (God assisting) if I may understand these to become ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable &amp; profitable to the people of God, to publish more. In the meane time I shall send these forth, with <hi>Iacobs</hi> blessing and prayer for his Sonnes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 43. 14. <hi>God Almighty send thee mercy in the sight of the man, &amp;c.</hi> In the sight of the proud man, that he be no more high-minded, as <hi>Herod;</hi> In the sight of the poore man, that hee may bee content with the things hee hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as <hi>Paul;</hi> In the sight of the stubborne man, that he may yeeld with <hi>Saul,</hi> and say, <hi>Lord, what wilt thou have mee to doe?</hi> In the sight of the penitent man, that his wounds may be bound up, and Wine and Oyle pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into them; In the sight of the barren man, that he may live and bring forth much fruit; In the sight of every man, that they may draw neere to God with a pure heart in assurance of faith, sprinkled in their hearts from an evill conscience, and washed in their body with pure water. But especially in the sight of our <hi>Ioseph,</hi> our <hi>Iesus,</hi> who blesse thee and these to thee, and all other meanes of furthering thy salvation; to whose grace I commend thee, this tenth of <hi>April,</hi> 1633.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in Christ Jesus,</hi> Samuel Otes.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>