<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epilogue and Conclusion of the Booke.</title>
           <author>Brathwait, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115197_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08534</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18853</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115197</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epilogue and Conclusion of the Booke.</title>
                 <author>Brathwait, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Andreas Ornithoparcvs his Micrologvs, or Introduction: containing the art of singing : Digested into foure bookes. Not onely profitable, bvt also necessary for all that are studious of musicke. Also the dimension and perfect vse of the monochord, according to Guido Aretinus By Iohn Dovland lvtenist, lute-player, and Bachelor of Musicke in both the Vniuersities. 1609</title>
                 <author>Ornithoparchus, Andreas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Adams, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 80, that is 90, 2 pages, music, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="epilogue">
   <pb facs="50"/>
   <head>The Epilogue and Conclusion of the Booke.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am to intreat the curteous Reader fauourably to view this Worke of Musical</hi> Theorems, <hi>which I haue before this some yeres past searched out, &amp; now at last put into the forme of a booke and printed, not out of any arrogant humour, as some enuious persons wil report, but out of a desire to profit the Youth of Germany, whilst others are drousie. If the basenes of the stile, or simplenes of the words offend any man, I intreat him to attribute that to the matter which we handle, and the persons for whom it is written, namely, Children. I doubt not but there will be some, that will be soone ready to snarle at it, and to backbite it, contemning it before they read it, and disgracing it before they vnderstand it. Who had rather seeme than be Musitians, not obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Authors, or Precepts, or Reasons: but whatsoeuer comes into their haire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braind Cockscombe, accounting that onely lawful, artificiall, and Musicall. To whom I intreat you (gentle Readers) to lend no eare. For it is a thing praise-worthy to displease the euill. Yea, (to vse the sentence of</hi> Antisthenes <hi>the Philosopher) to be backbited is a signe of greatnesse; to backebite, a token of meanesse. And because the praise of one wise man is better than the commendation of Ten fooles; I pray consider not the number, but the quality of those detractors: and thinke what an easie matter it is to silence those Pyes, and to crush such Fleas euen betwixt two nayles. Neither hearken ye to those that hate the Art: for they dissuade o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from that which their dulnesse will not suffer them to attaine to, for in vaine it is to harpe before an Asse. But account that this I speake to you as a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, because I haue passed the Ferrular. For the cunning men in each Art must be beleeued, as the Emperours Maiestie saith. Wherefore let those courteous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders (that be delighted with</hi> Ornithoparchus <hi>his paines taken) be contented with these few things, for as soone as I can but take breath, they shall see matters of greater worth.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>