<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>S. Stronge, in the behalf of the Authour.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115900_Fr1_8</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68649</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20979</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115900</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>S. Stronge, in the behalf of the Authour.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Allarme to England : foreshewing what perilles are procured, where the people liue without regarde of martiall lawe. With a short discourse conteyning the decay of warlike discipline, conuenient to be perused by gentlemen, such as are desirous by seruice, to seeke their own deserued prayse, and the preseruation of their countrey. Newly deuised and written by Barnabe Riche Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Middleton, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Barker, Christopher</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>102 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <head>S. Stronge, in the behalf of the Authour.</head>
   <l>IF painfull pilgryme for his toyle, deserues a guerdon due</l>
   <l>In seeking of the sacred sorte, which vertue doth pursue:</l>
   <l>Or if the wakeful watche in warre, do merit like reward,</l>
   <l>Or cunning pylot that with skill, doth take his due regard,</l>
   <l>To cut in twayne the billowes huge, that swell in Occean sea,</l>
   <l>And keepes the keele aright his course, tyll wished port he wray:</l>
   <l>Then (Ritche) that rings this larum bell, to warne his countreyes thrall,</l>
   <l>And sortes (much like the busie bee) the hunny from the gall,</l>
   <l>Deserues no lesse, in lieu thereof: such fruite I reape thereby,</l>
   <l>As for my parte, a double prayse, I may him not deny.</l>
   <l>The toyle to him no profit yeelds, he bites on bitter paine:</l>
   <l>He hales home haruest for the chaffe, the reader reapes the graine.</l>
   <l>He giues the sworde and shield in hande, to shroud thee from annoy,</l>
   <l>He wisely warnes thee of the worse, lest foes might thee destroy:</l>
   <l>He treades thee out a perfect path, oh England loude I crye,</l>
   <l>Refuse therefore thy follies past, he sees thee goe awrye:</l>
   <l>And leaue of al thy lustfull lyfe, and eke thy great excesse,</l>
   <l>Thy dainty fare, thy fine array, and eke thy wantonnesse.</l>
   <l>Leaue of likewise thy vsance great, and leaue thy lawing vaine,</l>
   <l>Lest for the present guyle thereof, there happe some future paine.</l>
   <l>Yet God forbid but iustice should in eche thing beare the sway,</l>
   <l>And lawe is good where lawe is vsde, I cannot this denay.</l>
   <l>But so your Common lawes are courst, at will of euery pelth,</l>
   <l>That common is the woe (God knowes) but priuate is the wealth.</l>
   <l>Do sorte thy selfe from Comedies, and foolish playes of loue,</l>
   <l>Lest tragicall and worse perhaps in fine thee chaunce to proue.</l>
   <l>Take sword in hand, and leaue of ease, for nowe the tyme is comme,</l>
   <l>The bell is rong, the trumpettes sound, all arme doth strike the dromme.</l>
   <l>And thanke good (Ritch) that rings the same, to wake thee out of sleepe,</l>
   <l>That thou thy selfe, that liuest at peace, in safetie still mightst keepe.</l>
   <l>A iewel ritche and gemme of price, the same no doubt doth seeme,</l>
   <l>A ritcher gifte for thy behoofe, he could not geue, I deeme.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>