<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE INTRODVCTION.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115479_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10262</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20546</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115479</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE INTRODVCTION.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Hadassa: or The history of Queene Ester : with meditations thereupon, diuine and morall. By Fra. Quarles</title>
                 <author>Quarles, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Moore (More), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>100 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE INTRODVCTION.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>WHen <hi>Zedechia</hi> (He whose haplesse hand</l>
      <l>Once swaid the Scepter of Great Iudah's Land)</l>
      <l>Went vp the Palace of proud Babylon,</l>
      <l>(The Prince <hi>Seraiah</hi> him attending on,)</l>
      <l>A dreadfull Prophet, (from whose blasting breath<note place="margin">Ierem. 52.</note>
      </l>
      <l>Came sudden death, and nothing else but death)</l>
      <l>Into <hi>Seraiah's</hi> peacefull hand betooke</l>
      <l>The sad Contents of a more dismall Booke:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Breake epe the leaues, those leaues so full of dread,</l>
      <l>Reade (sonne of thunder) said the Prophet, reade,</l>
      <l>Say thus, say freely thus, The Lord hath spoke it,</l>
      <l>'Tis done, the world's vnable to reuoke it;</l>
      <l>Woe, woe, and heauy woes ten thousand more</l>
      <l>Betide great Babylon, that painted whore;</l>
      <l>Thy buildings, and thy fensiue Towers shall</l>
      <l>Flame on a sudden, and to cinders fall;</l>
      <l>None shall be left, to waile thy griefe with Howles:</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Thy streets shall peopl'd be with Bats, and</hi>
         <note n="*" place="margin">Isay 13. 21.</note>
         <hi>Owles:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>None shall remaine, to call thy places voyd,</l>
      <l>None to possesse, nor ought to be enioy'd;</l>
      <l>Nought shall be left for thee to terme thine owne,</l>
      <l>But helplesse ruines of a haplesse towne:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Said then the Prophet, When performance hath</l>
      <l>Empty'd thy Cheekes of this thy borrow'd Breath,<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
            <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="6"/>Euen so the Persian Host it selfe bestur'd,</l>
      <l>So fell great Babel by the Persian sword,</l>
      <l>Which warme with slaughter, and with blood imbru'd,</l>
      <l>Ne'r sheath'd, till wounded Babel fell, subdu'd.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But see! These braue Ioynt-tenants that suruiu'd</l>
      <l>To see a little world of men vnliu'd,</l>
      <l>Must now be parted: Great <hi>Darius</hi> dyes,<note place="margin">Darius dyes.</note>
      </l>
      <l>And <hi>Cyrus</hi> shares alone, the new-got prize;<note place="margin">Cyrus, King alone.</note>
      </l>
      <l>
         <note n="*" place="margin">Carionis Chro. lib. 2. p. 81. <hi>2. Chro. 36. 23.</hi>
         </note> He fights for Heauen, Heauens foemen he subdues:</l>
      <l>
         <note n="*" place="margin">Carionis Chro. lib. 2. p. 81. <hi>2. Chro. 36. 23.</hi>
         </note> He builds the Temple, he restores the Iewes,</l>
      <l>By him was <hi>Zedechias</hi> force disioynted,</l>
      <l>Vnknown to God he was, yet Gods Anoynted;<note place="margin">Isay 4. 45. </note>
      </l>
      <l>But marke the malice of a wayward Fate;</l>
      <l>He whom successe crown'd alwaies fortunate,</l>
      <l>He that was strong t'atchieue, bold to attempt,</l>
      <l>Wise to foresee, and wary to preuent,</l>
      <l>Valiant in Warre, successefull to obtaine,</l>
      <l>Mustnow be slaine, and by a <note n="*" place="margin">Tomyris. Cyrus dyes.</note> Woman slaine.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Accursed be thy sacrelegious hand,</l>
      <l>That of her Patrone rob'd the holy Land;</l>
      <l>Curs'd be thy dying life, thy liuing death,</l>
      <l>And curs'd be all things, that proud <hi>Tomyris</hi> hath.<note place="margin">Tomyris Queen of the Massage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans.</note>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>O worst that Death can doe, to take a life,</l>
      <l>Which (lost) leaues kingdom's to a Tyrants knife:</l>
      <l>For now, alas! degenerate <hi>Cambyses</hi> (vices)<note place="margin">Cambyses King succeeded Cyrus</note>
      </l>
      <l>(Whose hand was fill'd with blood, whose heart with</l>
      <l>Sits crowned King, to vexe the Persian state,</l>
      <l>With heauy burthens, and with sore regrate.</l>
      <l>O <hi>Cyrus,</hi> more vnhappy in thy Son,</l>
      <l>Then in that stroke wherewith thy life was don!</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Cambyses</hi> now sits King, now Tyrant (rather:)</l>
      <l>(Vnlucky Sonne of a renowmed Father.)</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="6"/>Blood cries for Blood: Himselfe reuenged hath</l>
      <l>His bloody Tyranny, with his owne death;<note place="margin">Cambyses dyes.</note>
      </l>
      <l>That cruell <note n="*" place="margin">Chro. Carionis. lib. 2. p. 89.</note> sword on his owne flesh doth feed,</l>
      <l>Which made so many loyall Persians bleed,</l>
      <l>Whose wofull choyce made an indiff'rent thing,</l>
      <l>To leaue their liues, or lose their Tyran' King:</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Cambyses</hi> dead, with him the latest drop▪</l>
      <l>Of <hi>Cyrus</hi> blood was spilt, his death did stop</l>
      <l>The infant source of his braue Syers worth,</l>
      <l>Ere after-times could spend his riuers forth.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Tyrant <hi>Cambyses</hi> being dead, and gone,</l>
      <l>On the reuersion of his empty Throne,<note place="margin">A Magus suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds Cambyses.</note>
      </l>
      <l>Mounts vp a <hi>Magus,</hi> which dissembled right,</l>
      <l>Forging the name of him, whose greedy night<note place="margin">Smerdis.</note>
      </l>
      <l>Too early did perpetuate her owne,</l>
      <l>And silent Death did snatch away vnknowne.</l>
      <l>But when the tidings of this Royall cheat,</l>
      <l>Tymes loyall Trumpe had fam'd, th'vsurped seat</l>
      <l>Grew too too hot, and longer could not beare</l>
      <l>So proud a burthen on so proud a Chayre:</l>
      <l>The Nobles sought their freedome to regaine,</l>
      <l>Not resting, till the <hi>Magi</hi> all-vvere slaine;<note place="margin">The Magi slaine by the Persians.</note>
      </l>
      <l>And so renovvned vvas that happy slaughter,</l>
      <l>That it solemniz'd was for euer after;</l>
      <l>So that what pen shall write the Persian story,</l>
      <l>Shall treat that Triumph, and write that dayes glory;</l>
      <l>For to this time the Persians (as they say)<note place="margin">
            <hi>The feast is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is the slaughter of the Magi.</hi>
         </note>
      </l>
      <l>Obserue a Feast, and keepe it holy-day;</l>
      <l>Now Persia lacks a King, and now the State</l>
      <l>Labours as much in want, as it of late</l>
      <l>Did in abundance; Too great calms doe harme</l>
      <l>Sometimes as much the Sea-man, as a storme;</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="7"/>One while they thinke t'erect a Monarchy;</l>
      <l>But that (corrupted) breeds a Tyranny,</l>
      <l>And dead <hi>Cambyses</hi> fresh before their eyes,</l>
      <l>Afrights them with their new-scap'd miseries;</l>
      <l>Some to the Nobles would commit the State,<note place="margin">Otanes.</note>
      </l>
      <l>In change of Rule, expecting change of fate;</l>
      <l>Others cri'd no, more Kings then one incumber;<note place="margin">Darius, Gobrias, Asphatines, Hidarnes.</note>
      </l>
      <l>Better admit one Tyrant, than a number:</l>
      <l>The rule of many doth disquiet bring;</l>
      <l>One Monarch is enough, one Lord, one King:</l>
      <l>One saies, Let's rule our selues, let's all be kings;</l>
      <l>No, saies another, that confusion brings;</l>
      <l>Thus moderne danger bred a carefull trouble,</l>
      <l>Double their care is, as their feare is double;</l>
      <l>And doubtfull to resolue of what conclusion,</l>
      <l>To barre confusion, thus they bred confusion;</l>
      <l>At last (and well aduis'd) they put their choyce<note place="margin">They put the choyce of their King to seuen Electors.</note>
      </l>
      <l>Vpon the verdit of a Iuries voyce;</l>
      <l>Seuen is a perfect number; then by seuen,</l>
      <l>Be Persia's royall Crowne, and Scepter giuen;</l>
      <l>Now Persia, doe thy plagues, or ioyes commence;</l>
      <l>God giue thy Iury sacred euidence:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Fearefull to chuse, and faithlesse in their choyce,</l>
      <l>(Since weale, or woe depended on their voyce,)</l>
      <l>A few from many they extracted forth,</l>
      <l>Whose euen poys'd valour, and like equall worth</l>
      <l>Had set a <hi>Non plus</hi> on their doubtfull tongues,</l>
      <l>Vnweeting where the most reward belongs,</l>
      <l>They this agreed, and thus (aduis'd) bespake;</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Since bleare-eyd mortals, of themselues, can make<note place="margin">The speech of the Electors.</note>
      </l>
      <l>No difference 'twixt good, and euill, nor know</l>
      <l>A good from what is only good, in show,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="7"/>But, with vnconstant frailty, doth vary</l>
      <l>From what is good, to what is cleane contrary;</l>
      <l>And since it lies not in the braine of man,</l>
      <l>To make his drooping state more happy, than</l>
      <l>His vnprospitious stars allot, much lesse</l>
      <l>To lend another, or a state successe,</l>
      <l>In vaine you therefore shall expect this thing,</l>
      <l>That we should giue you fortune, with a King:</l>
      <l>Since you haue made vs meanes to propagate</l>
      <l>The ioyfull welfare of our headlesse State,</l>
      <l>(Bound by the tender seruice that we beare</l>
      <l>Our natiue soyle, far then our liues more deare)</l>
      <l>We sifted haue, and boulted from the Rest,</l>
      <l>Whose worst admits no badnes, and whose best</l>
      <l>Cannot be bettered:</l>
      <l>When Chaunticleere, (the Belman of the morne)</l>
      <l>Shall summon twilight, with his bugle horne,</l>
      <l>Let these braue <hi>Hero's,</hi> drest in warlike wise,</l>
      <l>And richly mounted on their Palferies,</l>
      <l>Attend our rising Sun-gods ruddy face,</l>
      <l>Within the limits of our Royall place.</l>
      <l>And he whose lusty <note n="*" place="margin">The Persians did dedicate Horses to their God, which was the Sunne.</note> Stallion first shall neigh,</l>
      <l>To him be giuen the doubtfull Monarchy;</l>
      <l>The choyce of Kings lies not in mortals brest,</l>
      <l>This we; the Gods, and fortune doe the rest.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>So said, the people, tickl'd with the motion,</l>
      <l>Some tost their caps, some fell to their deuotion,</l>
      <l>Some clapt their ioyfull hands, some shout, some sing,</l>
      <l>And all at once cri'd out, A King, A King.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>When <hi>Phoebus</hi> Harbinger had chac'd the night,</l>
      <l>And tedious <hi>Phospher</hi> brought the breaking light,</l>
      <l>Complete in armes, and glorious in their trayne,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="8"/>Came these braue <hi>Heroes,</hi> prauncing o're the playne,</l>
      <l>With mighty streamers came these blazing starres,</l>
      <l>Portending Warres, (and nothing else but Warres;)</l>
      <l>Into the royall Palace now they come:</l>
      <l>There sounds the martiall Trump, here beats the Drum,</l>
      <l>There stands a Steede, and champes his frothy steele,</l>
      <l>This stroaks the ground, that skorn's it with his heele,</l>
      <l>One snorts, another pufs out angry wind,</l>
      <l>This mounts before, and that curuets behind;</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>By this, the fomy Steeds of <hi>Phaëton</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Puffe too, and spurne the Easterne Horizon:</l>
      <l>Whereat the Nobles, prostrate to the ground,</l>
      <l>Ador'd their <note n="*" place="margin">The Persian worshipped the Sunne.</note> God, (Their God was early found.)</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <note n="*" place="margin">Heroditus in medio Tholiae Iustin.</note> Forthwith, from out the thickest of the crowd,</l>
      <l>In depth of silence, there was heard the loud,</l>
      <l>And lustfull language of <note n="*" place="margin">Stiled Assue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, whom Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tactines calls Artaxerxes.</note>
         <hi>Darius</hi> Horse,</l>
      <l>Who in the dialect of his discourse,</l>
      <l>Proclaim'd his rider, King; whereat the rest</l>
      <l>(Patient to beare what cannot be redrest)</l>
      <l>Dismount their lofty Steeds, and prostrate bring</l>
      <l>Their humbled bodies to their happy King;</l>
      <l>
         <hi>God saue the King,</hi> they ioyntly say, God blesse</l>
      <l>Thy prosprous actions with a due successe;</l>
      <l>The people clap their sweatty palmes, and shout,</l>
      <l>The bonfires smoke, the bels ring round about,</l>
      <l>The minstrels play, the Parrats learne to sing,</l>
      <l>(Perchaunce as well as they,) <hi>God saue the King.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Assuerus</hi> now's inuested in the throne,<note place="margin">Ester▪ 1. 1.</note>
      </l>
      <l>And <hi>Persia's</hi> rul'd by him, and him alone;</l>
      <l>Prooue, happy <hi>Persia's</hi> Great <hi>Assuerus,</hi> prooue</l>
      <l>As equall happy in thy peoples loue.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Enough; And let this broken breuiate</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="8"/>Suffice to shadow forth the downefall state</l>
      <l>Of mighty Babel, and the conquest made</l>
      <l>By the fierce Medes, and Persians conqu'ring blade;</l>
      <l>Whose iust succession we haue traced downe,</l>
      <l>Till great <hi>Assuerus</hi> weare the Persian Crowne;</l>
      <l>Him haue we sought, and hauing found him, rest:</l>
      <l>To morrow goe we to his royall Feast.</l>
   </lg>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>