<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE HENRY WRIO∣THESLEY, EARLE OF SOVTHAMP∣ton, and Baron of Titchfield, W. B. wi∣sheth continuance of health, with prosperous estate and felicitie.</title>
           <author>B., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115403_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A22560</idno>
           <idno type="STC">90</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115403</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE HENRY WRIO∣THESLEY, EARLE OF SOVTHAMP∣ton, and Baron of Titchfield, W. B. wi∣sheth continuance of health, with prosperous estate and felicitie.</title>
                 <author>B., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The most delectable and pleasaunt history of Clitiphon and Leucippe: written first in Greeke, by Achilles Statius, an Alexandrian: and now newly translated into English, by VV.B. Whereunto is also annexed the argument of euery booke, in the beginning of the same, for the better vnderstanding of the historie</title>
                 <author>Achilles Tatius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Mattes, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 152 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE HENRY WRIO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THESLEY, EARLE OF SOVTHAMP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and Baron of <hi>Titchfield,</hi> W. B. wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth continuance of health, with prosperous estate and felicitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T what time (Right Honourable) the renowned Prince <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon,</hi> was about to lay siege vnto the famous Cittie of <hi>Corinth,</hi> the Corinthians appalled with the fear of this sodaine newes, euery man fell to prepare himselfe readie to the defence of the Citie: here one scoured vp old ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, another carried morter and stones, to fill vp the breaches of the wall: others went to make a trench, others to the casting vp of a bulwarke: to conclude, euery man applied himselfe about some things, as need &amp; time did require. Which diligence of the people, <hi>Diogenes</hi> marking well, hauing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wheron he might bestow his labour, girding his clothes to him, began to rowle his Tub, wherin he dwelt, vp and downe the Market place: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing asked of one of his acquaintance why he did so:
<pb facs="3"/>
And I also (said he) do rowle my Tub, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t amongst so many workmen I alone might not be id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>. In like maner (right noble Lord) since the same hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to me now, as it was in <hi>Diogines</hi> age, that amo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>gst so many multitudes of writers, which eueryday doo publish and set foorth new workes, I alone might not be idle, I haue thought good with <hi>Dioge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> to rowle my small Tub also: and because that, <hi>non omnibus contingit adire Corinthum,</hi> Of euery course wood <hi>Mercury</hi> is not made, neither is euerie mans Muse alike, to flie aloft: I haue bestowed my labor on the translatiō of this pleasant History, first writtē in Greek by <hi>Achilles Statius,</hi> which now I haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed to dedicate to your honor, being a delightful poeme, although in prose: which doth consist in the fiction, not in the meeter; although seeming full of prolixitie, yet with delight auoyding satietie, being a meane to beguile the time, and other exercises be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing past, to serue for recreation: wherefore I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit this to your honourable protection: beseeching your honour fauourably to accept of this my small trauell in translating of this Author, whom if I haue worthily translated as he requires, I am assured your honour will well like of: knowing that if the grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous beames of your fauour shine therin, no carping <hi>Momus</hi> can shadow it. Resting thus in hope of your Honours curtesie, I cease: wishing you a happie life, with increase of all honour and felicitie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours in all dutie: <hi>W. B.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>