<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface of the Translator, To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115223_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10094</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20348</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115223</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface of the Translator, To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The doctrine of the Sabbath· : Delivered in the Act at Oxon. anno, 1622. By Dr. Prideaux his Majesties professour for divinity in that Vniversity. And now translated into English for the benefit of the common people</title>
                 <author>Prideaux, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, Elizabeth</publisher>
                    <distributor>Seile (Seale, Seely, Seyle), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 41, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface of the Translator, To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F all the controversies which have exercised the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> there is none more ancient than that of the <hi>Sabbath:</hi> So ancient, that it tooke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning even in the infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the <hi>Church,</hi> and grew up with it. For as we read in the <hi>Acts,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cap. <hi>15.5.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>There rose up certain of the sect of the Pharises, which beleeved, saying, that it was needfull to circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise the people, and to command them to keepe the law of Moses</hi>; whereof the <hi>Sabbath</hi> was a part: Which in the generall, as the Apostles laboured to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse, in the first <hi>Generall Councell</hi> holden in <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem:</hi> So did <hi>S. Paul,</hi> upon occasion of whose ministry this controversie first began, endeavour what he could a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this particular. Sharply reproving those which hallowed yet the <hi>Iewish Sabbath,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gal. <hi>4.10.11.</hi>
      </note> and <hi>observed dayes, and moneths, and times, as if he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed his labour in vaine upon them.</hi> But more
<pb facs="3"/>
particularly in his Epistle to the <hi>Colossians, Let no man judge you in respect of an holy day,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cap. <hi>2.16.17.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>or of the new Moone, or of the Sabbath dayes; which were a shadow of things to come, but the body is of Christ.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>4.</hi>
      </note> Both which expressions of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> are in this following discourse produced to this very purpose. Yet notwithstanding all this care, both generally of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> and more especially of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> to suppresse this errour; it grew up still, and had it's patrons and abettours. <hi>Ebion</hi> and <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> two of the wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedst hereticks of the <hi>primitiue times,</hi> and after them <hi>Apollinaris,</hi>
      <note place="margin">See Austin de h<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>b. &amp; Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius.</note> are said to countenance and defend it; which, doubtlesse made the ancient fathers declare themselves more fully in it, as a dangerous point; which seemed to confirme the <hi>Iewes</hi> in their incredulity, and might occasion others to make question of our <hi>Saviours</hi> comming in the flesh. Hence was it, that <hi>Irenaeus, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin Martyr, Tertullian</hi> and <hi>Eusebius,</hi> men of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne for learning in the <hi>primitive times</hi> (three of the which are cited in the Text of this following dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, and the fourth quoted in the margin) affirme for certaine,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>2.</hi>
      </note> That never any of the <hi>Patriarks</hi> before <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses Law,</hi> did observe the <hi>Sabbath:</hi> which question<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse they must have done, had that Law beene <hi>morall,</hi> and dictated by <hi>nature,</hi> as now some teach us. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by the opposition made by <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> in his confutation of the heresies of the <hi>Ebionites</hi>; and by the resolutions of <hi>Theodoret,</hi> on the <hi>20.</hi> of <hi>Ezekiel, Procopius Gazeus,</hi> on the second of <hi>Genesis,</hi> by <hi>Damascen,</hi> and our <hi>venerable Bede</hi> (which two last are here also cited, Sect. the <hi>2.</hi>) concurring with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer fathers; all talke and observation of the <hi>Iewish
<pb facs="3"/>
Sabbath</hi> vanished utterly; and the <hi>Lords day,</hi> which had from the <hi>Apostles</hi> times beene instituted by the <hi>Church,</hi> in the place thereof, was <hi>hallowed,</hi> without any rivall. Nor doe I finde, but that all superstitious fancies about that day, were as wholly abrogated, as the day it selfe.<note place="margin">Epist. <hi>3.</hi> l. <hi>21.</hi>
      </note> Save that <hi>Saint Gregory</hi> tells us, how some in <hi>Rome</hi> were so superstitious in this kinde, that they would neither worke upon the <hi>Saturday,</hi> no, nor so much as <hi>wash upon the Sunday,</hi> But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in the darker times, as it is thought by some, <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter de Bruis</hi> the founder of the <hi>Petrobusians</hi> (he was burnt for heresie Anno <hi>1126.</hi>) began to draw too deepe on these lees of <hi>Iudaisme</hi>; which here our <hi>Doctor</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timates in the <hi>7.</hi> Sect. where he joynes the <hi>Petrobusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> with the <hi>Ebionites,</hi> who indeed were <hi>Iewish</hi> in this point. And possibly, from the remainders of this Doctrine, <hi>Fulco</hi> a <hi>French Priest,</hi> and a notable hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, as our King <hi>Richard</hi> counted him,<note place="margin">In Rog. Hoveden</note> lighted upon a new <hi>Sabbatarian</hi> speculation, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Eustachius</hi> one of his associates dispersed in <hi>England</hi>: I call it new, as well I may. For whereas <hi>Moses</hi> gave commandement to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that they should sanctifie one day onely of the weeke, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth</hi> whereon God rested: They taught the people that the <hi>Christian Sabbath</hi> was to begin on <hi>Saturday</hi> at three of the clock, and to continue till Sun-rising on the <hi>Munday morning</hi>: During which latitude of time, it was not lawfull to doe any kinde of worke what ever, no not so much as to <hi>bake bread on Saturday for the Sundayes eating; to wash or dry linnen for the morrowes wearing.</hi> Yea, they had <hi>miracles</hi> in store▪ pretended to be wrought on such as had not yeelded to
<pb facs="4"/>
their doctrine; thereby to countenance the <hi>Supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious,</hi> and confound the <hi>weake.</hi> And which was more than this, for the authoritie of their device, they had to shew a letter sent from God himselfe, and left pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digiously over the Altar in <hi>Saint Simeons Church</hi> in <hi>Golgatha</hi>: wherein this <hi>Sabbatarian</hi> dreame was imposed forsooth upon all the world, on paine of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse plagues and terrible comminations, if it were not punctually observed. The letter is at large re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated by <hi>Roger de Hoveden</hi>;<note place="margin">Anno. <hi>1201.</hi>
      </note> and out of him, as I suppose,<note place="margin">Anno. <hi>1200.</hi>
      </note> by <hi>Matth. Paris:</hi> who doe withall repeat the miracles, whereby this doctrine was confirmed. I adde no more but this, that could I either beleeve those miracles, which are there related: or saw I any now, like those, to countenance the reviving of this strange opinion (for now it is revived and published:) I might perhaps perswade my selfe to entertaine it.</p>
   <p>But to proceed. Immediately upon the <hi>reformation</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> in these Westerne parts, the <hi>Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie</hi> brake out afresh; though in another manner than before it did.<note place="margin">Institut. l. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi> Sect. <hi>33.</hi>
      </note> For there were some of whom <hi>Calvin</hi> speakes, who would have had all daies alike, all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually to bee regarded; (hee meanes the <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists,</hi> as I take it) and reckoned that the <hi>Lords day</hi> as the <hi>Church</hi> continued it, was a <hi>Iewish</hi> ceremonie. Affirming it to crosse the doctrine of <hi>Saint Paul,</hi> who in the Texts before remembred, and in the <hi>14.</hi> to the <hi>Rom.</hi> did seeme to them, to crie downe all such diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of dayes and times, as the <hi>Church</hi> retained. To meete which vaine and peccant humor, <hi>Calvin</hi> was faine to bend his forces; declaring how the <hi>Church</hi> might lawfully retaine set times for Gods solemne ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,
<pb facs="4"/>
without infringing any of S. <hi>Pauls</hi> commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But on the other side, as commonly the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse is more exorbitant than the defect, there wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not some others, who thought they could not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the <hi>Lords day</hi> sufficiently, unlesse they did affixe <hi>as great a sanctitie unto it,</hi> as the <hi>Iewes</hi> did unto their <hi>Sabbath.</hi> So that the change seemed to be onely of the day; the superstition still remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning no lesse <hi>Iewish,</hi> than before it was. These taught, as now some doe, <hi>Moralem esse unius diei observationem in hebdomada,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ib. Sect. <hi>34.</hi>
      </note> the keeping holy to the Lord one day in seven, to be the <hi>morall</hi> part of the fourth Commandement: which <hi>doctrine, what else is it,</hi> (so hee proceedes, and here the <hi>Doctor</hi> so repeates it in his third Section) <hi>than in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Iewes to change the day, and to affixe a greater sanctitie unto the day, than those ever did?</hi> As for himselfe, so farre was hee from favouring any such wayward fancie, that as <hi>John Barclay</hi> makes report,<note place="margin">Paraen, lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. vlt.</note> hee had a consultation once, <hi>de transferenda solennitate Dominica in feriam quintam,</hi> to alter the <hi>Lords day</hi> from <hi>Sunday</hi> unto <hi>Thursday.</hi> How true this is I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not say. But sure it is, that <hi>Calvin</hi> tooke the <hi>Lords day</hi> to be an <hi>ecclesiasticall</hi> and <hi>humane consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi> onely, <hi>Quem veteres in locum Sabbati subrogarunt,</hi> appointed by our <hi>Ancestors</hi> to supply the place of the <hi>Iewish Sabbath:</hi> and (as our <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> tells us from him in his seventh Section) <hi>as alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable by the Church at this present time,</hi> as first it was,<note place="margin">Institut. l. <hi>3.</hi> Cap. <hi>8.</hi> Sect. <hi>34.</hi>
      </note> when from the <hi>Saturday</hi> they translated it unto the <hi>Sunday.</hi> So that we see, that <hi>Calvin</hi> here
<pb facs="5"/>
resolves upon three <hi>Conclusions:</hi> first, that the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping holy of <hi>one day in seven,</hi> is not the <hi>morall</hi> part of the fourth Commandement: secondly, that the day was changed from the last day of the weeke unto the first, <hi>by the authoritie of the Church,</hi> and not by any divine Ordinance: and thirdly, that the day <hi>is yet alterable by the Church,</hi> as at first it was.</p>
   <p>Neither was hee the onely one that hath so deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined. For, for the first, <hi>that to keepe holy one day of seven,</hi> is not the <hi>morall part of the fourth Commandement,</hi> our <hi>Doctor</hi> hath delivered in the third Section, that not <hi>Tostatus</hi> onely, but even <hi>Aquinas,</hi> and with him <hi>all the Schoolemen,</hi> have agreed upon it. Nor was there any that opposed it in the <hi>Schooles of Rome,</hi> that I have met with, till <hi>Catharinus</hi> tooke up armes against <hi>Tostatus:</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, but with ill successe, that the Commandement of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> was imposed on <hi>Adam</hi> in the first Cradle of the world; there where the Lord is said <hi>to blesse the seventh day and sanctifie it.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gen. <hi>3.</hi>
      </note> Which fancie, by our <hi>Author</hi> is rejected, and the opinion of <hi>Tostatus</hi> justified against him, though he name him not. As for the <hi>Protestant Schooles,</hi> besides what is affirmed by <hi>Calvin,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>3.</hi> &amp; <hi>7.</hi>
      </note> and seconded by the <hi>Doctor</hi> in this following Discourse; this seemes to be the judgement of the Divines of the <hi>Low-Countries. Francisc. Gomarus,</hi> one knowne sufficiently for his undertakings against <hi>Arminius,</hi> published <hi>Anno 1628.</hi> a little Treatise about the <hi>Originall of the Sabbath,</hi> and therein principally canvassed these two Questions: first, whether the <hi>Sabbath were ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="5"/>
by God, immediately on the Creation of the World:</hi> the second, <hi>Whether all Christians are obliged by the fourth Commandement, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to set apart one day in seven, to Gods holy worship:</hi> both which hee determines nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively. And <hi>Doctor Ryvet,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Goma<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. desensio sentent. c. <hi>10.</hi>
      </note> one of the foure <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors</hi> in <hi>Leiden,</hi> although he differs in the first, yet in the second, which doth most concerne us <hi>Christians,</hi> they agree together: affirming also jointly, that <hi>the appointing of the Lords day for Gods publike service, was neither done by God himselfe, nor by his Apostles, but by authoritie of the Church.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Investig. Sabb. cap. <hi>4.</hi>
      </note> For Seconds, <hi>Gomarus</hi> brings in <hi>Vata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blus,</hi> and <hi>Wolfgangus Musculus</hi>; and <hi>Ryvet</hi> voucheth the authoritie of our <hi>Doctor</hi> here. For so <hi>Gomarus,</hi> in the <hi>assertion</hi> and <hi>defence</hi> of the first opinion against this <hi>Ryvet;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cap. <hi>10.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>De quibus etiam Cl. &amp; Doct. D. Prideaux in Oratione de Sabbato consensionem extare, eodem judicio</hi> [by <hi>Ryvets</hi> information] <hi>libenter intelleximus.</hi> I will adde one thing onely, which is briefely this. The <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> when they discovered <hi>Fretum le Maire, Anno 1615.</hi> though they observed a most exact account of their time at <hi>Sea</hi>; yet at their comming home, they found, comparing their account with theirs in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that they had lost a day; that which was <hi>Sunday</hi> to the one, being <hi>Munday</hi> to the other. Which of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie must happen, as it is calculated by <hi>Geogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,</hi> to those that compasse the World from West to East: as contrarie, they had got a day, had they sayled in Eastward. And now what should these people doe when they were return'd? If they must sanctifie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisely
<pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>one day in seven,</hi> they must have sanctified a day apart from their other countrymen, and had a <hi>Sabbath</hi> by themselves; or to comply with others, must have broken the <hi>Morall Law,</hi> which must for no respects be violated. See more hereof at large in <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penters Geogr. p. 237. &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Next, for the second <hi>Thesis,</hi> that the <hi>alteration of the day is onely an humane and Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Constitution,</hi> the <hi>Doctor</hi> sheweth in the fifth Section, the generall consent of all sorts of <hi>Papists, Iesuits, Canonists,</hi> and <hi>Schoolemen;</hi> of some great <hi>Lutherans</hi> by name; and generally, of the <hi>Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strant</hi> or <hi>Arminian Divines</hi> in their <hi>Confession:</hi> whose tendries in this point, wee may conceive with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son not to be different from the doctrine of the <hi>Belgick Churches</hi>; in that the foure <hi>Professors</hi> of <hi>Leiden,</hi> in their <hi>Examination</hi> or <hi>Review</hi> of that <hi>Confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,</hi> have passed them over without note or opposition. To these besides, are added diverse of our owne; <hi>&amp; e nostris non pauci,</hi> as hee speakes it in the generall; <hi>i. e.</hi> as I conceive his meaning, such as are neither of the <hi>Lutheran</hi> nor <hi>Arminian</hi> partie. Of which, since hee hath instanced in none particularly, I will make bold to borrow two or three Testimonies out of the Tractate of <hi>Gomarus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cap. <hi>3..</hi>
      </note> before remembred. And first he brings in <hi>Bullinger,</hi> who in his Comment on the first of the <hi>Revelation</hi> calls it <hi>Ecclesiae consue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem,</hi> an Ecclesiasticall Ordinance; and after addes, <hi>Sponte Ecclesiae receperunt illam diem, &amp;c. The Church did of its owne accord agree upon that day, for wee reade not any where that it was commanded.</hi> Next <hi>Vrsinus,</hi> telling us that
<pb facs="6"/>
God had abrogated the <hi>Iewish Sabbath</hi>; addes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently, that <hi>he left it free unto the Church,</hi> alios dies eligere, <hi>to make choice of any other day to be selected for his service; and that the Church made choice of this, in honour of our Saviours resurrection. Zanchius</hi> affirmes the same. <hi>Nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libi legimus Apostolos,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>We reade not any where</hi> (saith he) <hi>that the Apostles did command this day to be observed in the Church of God; onely we finde what the Apostles and others of the faithfull used to doe upon it,</hi> liberum ergo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquerunt: <hi>which is an argument, that they left it wholly unto the disposition of the Church. Aretius, Simler, Dav. Paraeus,</hi> and <hi>Bucerus,</hi> which are all there alledged, might bee here produced, were not these sufficient; Adde hereunto the generall consent of our <hi>English Prelates,</hi> the <hi>Architects</hi> of our <hi>reformation</hi> in the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the sixth;<note place="margin">Anno <hi>5.</hi> and <hi>6.</hi> of Edward <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
      </note> who in the <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> about keeping <hi>holy dayes,</hi> have determined thus, together with the rest of that grand assembly; <hi>viz. Neither is it to be thought that there is any certaine time, or defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite number of dayes, prescribed in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but that the appointment both of the time and also of the number of the dayes, is left by the authority of Gods Word, to the authority of Christs Church, to bee determined and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed orderly in every Country by the discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Rulers and Ministers thereof, as they shall judge most expedient to the true setting forth of Gods glory, and edification of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> Which <hi>preamble</hi> is not to bee understood of <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="7"/>
dayes,</hi> or of <hi>Saints dayes</hi> onely (whose being left the authority of the <hi>Church</hi> was never questioned) but of the <hi>Lords day</hi> also: as by the <hi>body of the Act</hi> doth at full appeare.</p>
   <p>Last of all for the third and last conclusion, <hi>that still the Church hath power to change the day,</hi> our <hi>Doctor,</hi> in the seventh Section, brings in <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linger, Bucer, Brentius, Vrsinus,</hi> and <hi>Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitius, aliisque nostris,</hi> with diverse others not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med particularly, as they are; which thinke no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise thereof than <hi>Calvin</hi> did, and shewes by what di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction <hi>Suarez,</hi> though otherwise no friend unto the men, doth defend their doctrine: now as the doctrine was, such also is the practise of those men and Churches, devoyd of any the least superstitious rigour; esteeming it to be as a day left arbitrary, and therefore open to all honest exercises and lawfull recreations; by which the minde may be refreshed, and the spirits quickned. Even in <hi>Geneva</hi> it selfe, according as it is related in the inlargement of <hi>Boterus</hi> by <hi>Robert Iohnson, All honest exercises, shooting in Peeces, Long-Bowes, Crosse-Bowes, &amp;c. are used on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day, and that both in the morning, before and after the Sermon; neither doe the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters finde fault therewith, so that they hinder not from hearing of the Word at the time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. Dancing</hi> indeed they doe not suffer; but this not in relation to the <hi>Sunday,</hi> but the <hi>Sport it selfe,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Heylius Geogr. <hi>in</hi> France.</note> which is held unlawfull, and generally forbidden in the <hi>French Churches.</hi> Which strict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, as some note, considering how the <hi>French</hi> doe delight in <hi>dancing,</hi> hath beene a great hinderance
<pb facs="7"/>
to the growth of the <hi>reformed</hi> Religion in that Kingdome.</p>
   <p>Which being so, the <hi>judgement</hi> and the <hi>practise</hi> of so <hi>many men,</hi> and of such <hi>severall perswasions</hi> in the controverted points of the <hi>Christian faith,</hi> concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring so unanimously together: the miracle is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that wee in <hi>England</hi> should take up a contrary o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, and thereby separate our selves from all that are called <hi>christian.</hi> Yet so it is, I skill not how it comes to passe, but so it is, that some amongst us have revivd againe the <hi>Iewish Sabbath,</hi> though not the <hi>day</hi> it selfe,<note place="margin">Roger<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>on the Article<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. Art. 7.</hi>
      </note> yet the <hi>name</hi> and <hi>thing.</hi> Teaching <hi>that the Commandement of sanctifying every seventh day, as in the Mosaicall Decalogue, is naturall, morall, and perpetuall;</hi> that <hi>whereas all things else in the Iewish Church were so changed that they were cleane taken away; this day (meaning the Sabbath) was so changed, that it still remaineth:</hi> and lastly, <hi>that the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath was not any of those ceremonies which were justly abrogated at Christs comming.</hi> All which <hi>positions</hi> are condemned for contrary to the <hi>Articles of the Church of England</hi>: as in a <hi>Comment</hi> on those <hi>Articles, perused and by the lawfull authority of the Church allowed to bee publike,</hi> is most cleere and manifest. Which <hi>Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals</hi> though dangerous in themselves, and different from the <hi>judgement</hi> of the <hi>ancient Fathers,</hi> and of the greatest <hi>Clerks</hi> of the <hi>latter times,</hi> are not yet halfe so desperate, as that which followeth thereupon, in point of <hi>practise.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Id. <hi>in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles.</hi>
      </note> For these <hi>positions</hi> granted, and entertained as <hi>orthodox,</hi> what can we else expect; but
<pb facs="8"/>
such strange <hi>paradoxes,</hi> as in consideration of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises, have beene delivered from some <hi>Pulpits</hi> in this <hi>Kingdome;</hi> As <hi>viz. That to doe any servile worke or businesse on the Lords day, is as great a sinne, as to kill a man, or commit adultery;</hi> that <hi>to throw a Bowle, to make a Feast, or dresse a wedding dinner on the Lords day, is as great a sinne, as for a man to take a knife and cuts his childes throat;</hi> that <hi>to ring more Bells than one on the Lords day, is as great a sinne as to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit murder.</hi> The Author which reports them all, was present when the broacher of <hi>the last position</hi> was <hi>convented</hi> for it. And I beleeve him in the rest. The rather, since I have heard it preached in <hi>London,</hi> that the <hi>Law of Moses,</hi> whereby <hi>death temporall</hi> was appointed for the <hi>Sabbath-breaker,</hi> was yet in <hi>force;</hi> and that who ever did the <hi>workes</hi> of his <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary calling</hi> on the <hi>Sabbath day,</hi> was to <hi>dye</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. And I know also, that in a Towne of my acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, the <hi>Preachers</hi> there had brought the people to that passe, that neither <hi>baked</hi> nor <hi>rost-meat,</hi> was to bee found in all the <hi>Parish</hi> for a <hi>Sundayes</hi> dinner throughout the yeere. These are the ordinary fruits of such <hi>dangerous Doctrines;</hi> and against these and such as these, our <hi>Author</hi> in this following Treatise doth addresse himselfe, accusing them that entertaine the former <hi>Doctrinalls,</hi> everywhere, of no lesse than <hi>Iudaisme,</hi> and pressing them with that of <hi>Austin,</hi> that <hi>they who literally understand the fourth Commandement, doe not yet savour of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> Section the third.</p>
   <p>This when I had considered, when I had seriously
<pb facs="8"/>
observed how much these fancies were repugnant both to the tendries of this Church, and judgements of all kinde of Writers, and how unsafe to be admitted; I thought I could not goe about a better worke, than to exhibite to the view of my deare <hi>Countrymen</hi> this following Treatise; delivered first, and after pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished by the <hi>Author</hi> in another Language. The ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, since of late the clamour is encreased, and that <hi>there is not any thing now more frequent in some</hi> Zelots <hi>mouthes,</hi> (to use the <hi>Doctors</hi> words) <hi>than that the Lords day is with us licentiously, yea sacrilegiously prophaned,</hi> Section the first. To satisfie whose scruples, and give content unto their mindes, I doubt not but this following Discourse will be sufficient: which for that cause I have translated faithfully, and with as good proprietie as I could: not swerving any where from the sence; and as little as I could, from the phrase and letter. <hi>Gratum opus Agricolis:</hi> a Worke, as I conceive it, not unsutable to the <hi>present times:</hi> wherein, besides those <hi>pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant fancies</hi> before remembred, some have so farre proceeded, as not alone to make the <hi>Lords day</hi> sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the <hi>Iewish rigours</hi>; but to bring in againe the <hi>Iewish Sabbath,</hi> and abrogate the <hi>Lords day</hi> altogether. I will no longer detaine the <hi>Reader</hi> from the benefit hee shall reape hereby: Onely I will crave leave, for his greater benefit, to repeat the summe thereof; which is briefely this: First, that the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> was not instituted in the <hi>first Creation of the World,</hi> nor ever kept by any of the <hi>Ancient Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarkes,</hi> who lived before the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Moses:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no <hi>Morall</hi> and perpetuall <hi>Precept,</hi> as the others
<pb facs="9"/>
are, <hi>Sect. 2.</hi> Secondly, that the <hi>sanctifying</hi> of <hi>one day</hi> in <hi>seven,</hi> is <hi>Ceremoniall</hi> onely, and obliged the <hi>Iewes;</hi> not <hi>Morall,</hi> to oblige us <hi>Christians</hi> to the like observance, <hi>Sect. 3. &amp; 4.</hi> Thirdly, that the <hi>Lords day</hi> is founded onely on the <hi>authoritie</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> guided therein by the <hi>practice</hi> of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles;</hi> not on the <hi>fourth Commandement,</hi> (which he calls a <hi>scandalous Doctrine,</hi> Sect. <hi>7.</hi>) nor any other <hi>expresse authoritie</hi> in <hi>holy Scripture,</hi> Sect. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; <hi>7.</hi> Then fourthly, that the <hi>Church</hi> hath still <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie</hi> to change the day, though such <hi>authoritie</hi> be not fit to be put in practise, <hi>Sect. 7.</hi> Fifthly, that in the <hi>celebration</hi> of it, there is no such <hi>cessation</hi> from the <hi>workes of labour</hi> required from us, as was exacted of the <hi>Iewes;</hi> but that we lawfully may dresse Meat, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable unto every mans estate, and doe such other things as be no hinderance to the <hi>publike Service</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the day, <hi>Sect. 8.</hi> Sixtly, that on the <hi>Lords day</hi> all <hi>Recreations</hi> whatsoever are to be allowed, which honestly may <hi>refresh</hi> the <hi>spirits,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease <hi>mutuall love</hi> and <hi>neighbourhood</hi> amongst us; and that the <hi>names</hi> whereby the <hi>Iewes</hi> did use to call their <hi>Festivals</hi> (whereof the <hi>Sabbath</hi> was the chiefe) were borrowed from an <hi>Hebrew word,</hi> which signifieth <hi>to dance,</hi> and to <hi>be merry,</hi> or <hi>make glad the countenance.</hi> If so: if all such <hi>Recreations</hi> as encrease <hi>good neighbourhood;</hi> then <hi>Wakes,</hi> and <hi>Feasts,</hi> and other <hi>Meetings</hi> of that nature. If such as honestly may <hi>refresh</hi> the <hi>spirits;</hi> then <hi>Dancing, Shooting, Wrastling,</hi> and all other Pastimes, not by <hi>Law prohibited,</hi> which either exercise the <hi>body,</hi> or revive the <hi>minds.</hi> And lastly, that it appertaines to
<pb facs="9"/>
the <hi>Christian Magistrate</hi> to order and appoint, what Pastimes are to be permitted, and what are not, (obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience unto whose commands, is better farre than sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to any of the Idols of our owne inventions:) not unto every private person, (or as the <hi>Doctors</hi> owne words are) <hi>not unto every mans rash zeale, who out of a Schismaticall Stoicisme</hi> (debarring men from lawfull Pastimes) <hi>doth incline to Iudaisme,</hi> Sect. <hi>8.</hi> Adde, for the close of all, how doubtingly our <hi>Author</hi> speakes of the name of <hi>Sabbath,</hi> which now is growne so rife amongst us, <hi>Sect. 8.</hi> Concerning which, take here that notable <hi>Dilemma</hi> of <hi>Iohn Barklay,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Paraen. l. <hi>1.</hi> cap. vlt.</note> the better to incounter those who stil retaine the <hi>name,</hi> and impose the <hi>rigour:</hi> Cur perro illum diem plerique Sectariorum Sabbatum appellaetis, &amp;c. <hi>What is the cause</hi> (saith hee) <hi>that many of our Sectaries call this day the Sabbath? If they observe it as a Sabbath, they must observe it, because God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted on that day: and then they ought to keepe that day whereon God rested; and not the first, as now they doe, whereon the Lord began his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. If they observe it as the day of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours resurrection, why doe they call it still the Sabbath; seeing especially that Christ did not altogether rest that day, but valiantly overcame the powers of death?</hi> This is the summe of all: and this is all I have to say unto thee <hi>(Good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader)</hi> in this present businesse. <hi>God</hi> give thee a <hi>right understanding</hi> in all things, and a <hi>good will</hi> to doe thereafter.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>