<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1571</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115669_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02008</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12153</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115669</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A litle treatise, conteyning many proper tables and rules : very necessary for the vse of al men, the contentes wherof appere in the next page folowing. Collected and set forthe by Richard Grafton. 1571</title>
                 <author>Grafton, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Tottell (Tathyll, Tothill, Tottyl), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1571</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>108 pages, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Calendars, almanacs and prognostications</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE order of</hi> this small Booke, &amp; the matters ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in conteyned are as foloweth.</p>
   <p>¶ <hi>FIRST</hi> I haue placed herein a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lender, wherein I haue obserued the olde Saynctes dayes, not of supersticion, as thoughe I thought euery of them mencioned in the saide Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lender to be a saincte (for of some I know the contrarye: Neyther if they were all saynctes, do I therfore place them in my Calender) But because it hath bene a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome of aūcient time to vse their names in signifiynge and makinge certayne the dayes, tymes, and termes of the yere, as by the dating of diuerse olde Deedes, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidences, and Recordes it wil apere. And because the same custome is yet retayned in the retorning of writtes and processes, and also is commonly vsed in the notinge and settyng forth of the principall Faires and Markettes &amp; other seasons of the yere those names serue well for my purpose, &amp; therfore I mighte not conueniently haue
<pb facs="3"/>
left them out. And vnto the said Calender I haue added the Calendes, Nonas, and Ides, because diuerse euidences are dated on those daies and by those wordes. And therunto also I haue added the vigiles and festiuall daies, with the trewe time of the Termes and their returnes, because that hauyng this booke, there shalbe no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to call for any other Calender.</p>
   <p>And finally in the ende of the saide Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lender, I haue set forth an Almanacke for lx. yeeres yet to come, wherein is shewed the first Sonday in Lent, Caster day, Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gacion weke, &amp; Whitsonday, and by them you may finde al other moueable feastes.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>NEXT AFTER</hi> the Almanacke is a Table or Rondell that teacheth for euer readely to finde the yeres of our Lord, the Epact, the Pryme, the Dominicall letter and the Leape yere, with a declaracion of the vse of the same Table.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>AND</hi> also a rule to knowe the age of the Moone, her Chaunge, and Full for euer. Then foloweth a Table to finde the feastes of Easter, and so all other the moueable feastes that haue bene in tyme past, or shall be hereafter for euer, with a
<pb facs="3"/>
playne instruction of the vse and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standinge thereof.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>THEN</hi> begynneth my Computacion of yeres, wherin is to be noted, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry page therof is deuyded into eyghte se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall partes or places, as may appere by the tytles ouer euery of their heades. In the fyrste place are the yeres of our lorde. In the second the Pryme: In the thyrde, the Epact: In the fourth, the Dominicall letter: In the fifthe, the leape yere, when so euer it happeneth: In the sixte, are the names of the kinges as they reigned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning with Williā the Conquerour. &amp;c. And in the same place also are the Mone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes that euery of them entred into theyr reignes. And in the seuenth, are the daies of the Monthes that euery of them began to reigne in. And in the .viij. and last, are the yeres that euery of them reigned.</p>
   <p>Also in the ende of the reigne of euerye kynge I haue shewed the day of his death if he died beinge kyng, or the daye of his deposicion if he were deposed, with a true accompte howe many yeres, Monethes, weekes or dayes he reigned.</p>
   <p>¶ <hi>AND HERE</hi> I thincke it mete to
<pb facs="4"/>
declare somewhat of the commoditie and necessarye vse of the Computacion afore mencioned. And for the better instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and vnderstandynge thereof I wyll moue certayne questions, and geue aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sweres to the same, in suche sorte as shall so vtter the order and maner therof (as it were by examples) that I doubt not, but the trewe and necessary vse of the same, shall playnely appere to all men.</p>
   <div n="1" type="question">
      <head>1. Question.</head>
      <p>I wold know by this Computacion in the fourth yere of king Edward the first, what was then the yere of our Lorde, the Prime, the Epact, Dominicall letter, and the Monthe and daye that he beganne his reigne in, and what day in the weeke the same was?</p>
      <div type="answer">
         <head>Aunswere.</head>
         <p>Amonge the kinges, seke out for kynge Edwarde the first, and then looke for the fourth yere of his reigne, and there it appe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth to be the yere of our Lord. 1275. The
<pb facs="4"/>
Prime. 3. The Epact. 18. The Dominical letter F. The Monethe that he began his reigne in, Nouember &amp; the. 16. day, which day that yere was Saterday, as is easy to be knowen if you looke in the Calēder for the .xvj. daye of Nouember, accomptyuge F. for Sonday, then that day must nedes be Saterday, and so of all other the lyke.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="2" type="question">
      <head>2. Question.</head>
      <p>An Euidence dated the. 15. Calendes of December in the .iij. yere of kinge Iohn, I wolde knowe what daye of the Monthe the same was, and howe long it is sithen?</p>
      <div type="answer">
         <head>Aunswere.</head>
         <p>First loke in the Calender in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Month of Nouember for the Calendes of Decēber, and there you shall finde, that the .xv. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendes of December is on the .xvij. day of Nouember. Then seeke in the Computa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion for kinge Iohn, and you shall fynde that the thirde yeere of his reigne was in the yere of our Lorde. 1201. And then sette downe this yere of our lorde wherein the
<pb facs="5"/>
question is asked, whiche is. 1571. and take out therof. 1201. and there resteth. 370. And so it must followe that vpon the .xvij. day of Nouember next, it shalbe sithen the .iij. yere of kynge Iohn. 370. yeres, and thus of the lyke.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="3" type="question">
      <head>3. Question.</head>
      <p>An Euidence dated the second Sonday in Lent in the .iiii. yere of kinge Stephin. I would know in what yere of our Lord the same was, and also in what Monthe, and on what daye the seconde Sonday in Lent was then?</p>
      <div type="answer">
         <head>Aunswere.</head>
         <p>First looke among the kinges for king Stephyn. And when you haue found him then looke for the .iiij. yere of his reigne, and there you shall finde the yeere of our lorde to be. 1138. and the Prime. 18. and B. the Sondaies letter. Then go to the table that teacheth to knowe Easter day and al the moueable feastes, whiche is the nexte Table before the Computacion.</p>
         <p>
            <pb facs="5"/>
And there vnder the title of Prime, seeke among those nombers for. 18. And when you haue founde it, loke downward from the lyne where the Prime standeth, and seeke for the next B. whiche that yere was the Sondaies letter. And when you haue founde B. go forwarde in that lyne, and there you shall finde the .xx. daye of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary to be that yere the first Sonday in Lent, and thervnto put .vij. dayes for one weeke more, and that sheweth that the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde Sonday in Lent that yere was the 27. day of February. Then set down this present yere of our Lord. 1571. and take out therof the yere of our Lord that was then, whiche was. 1138. and there resteth. 433. And so it doth plainely appere that the. 27. day of February next comming, it shalbe 433. yeres-sithen the .iiii. yere of the reigne of kinge Stephyn. And thus you may do with the lyke.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="4" type="question">
      <head>4. Question.</head>
      <p>I haue a lease for .lxxx. yeeres, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan at Mighelmas in the. 17. yere of king Henry the .vij. My desire is to knowe this
<pb facs="6"/>
present yere. 1571. whether my lease be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired, or how many yeres I haue to com?</p>
      <div type="answer">
         <head>Aunswere.</head>
         <p>First in the Computacion loke among the kinges for king Henry the .vij. &amp; then for the. 17. yere of his reigne, whiche you shall finde to be in the yeere of our Lorde 1501. The whiche nomber take out of this present yere of our Lord. 1571. and then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth. 70. &amp; so many yeres of the said lease shall be expyred at Mighelmas nexte, and then shall remayne. 10. yeres to come, and so of the lyke.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="5" type="question">
      <head>5 ¶ An other Question and playne example meete for suche as can not extracte one nomber out of an other.</head>
      <p>A Lease dated the vj. of Iulij, in the. 31. yere of the reigne of kyng Henry the .viij. for the terme of xl yeres that began at our Lady daye in Lent then next folowinge: I woulde now knowe whether the sayde lease be expyred, or how many yeres there are to come?</p>
      <div type="answer">
         <pb facs="6"/>
         <head>Aunswere.</head>
         <p>Fyrst loke in the Computacion among the kynges for kinge Henry the .viij. and for the. 31. yere of his reigne, whiche you shall fynde to be in the yere of our Lorde. 1539. Then at the next yere folowinge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to recon, and call that one, and so tel downe in order all the yeeres folowinge, and ende with this present yere. 1571, And in the whole, you shall finde the nomber of 32. And so many yeres of the sayde lease shalbe expired at our lady day in lent next comming. And at that time there shal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine to come of the saide lease .viij. yeres and thus you may accompte the yeres of any lease.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="6" type="question">
      <head>6 An other very plaine question or example, easye for all men to conceaue, and in this time is commonly vsed,</head>
      <p>A lease dated the 17. daye of August, in the v. yere of the reigne of kyng Edward the .vj. for the terme of xxj. yeres, whiche began at Mighelmas then next folowing. I aske the question this xij. day of August
<pb facs="7"/>
1571. whether the saide lease be expired, or howe many yeres are yet to come?</p>
      <div type="answer">
         <head>Aunswere.</head>
         <p>Fyrst in the Computacion, amonge the kinges, seke for king Edward the vj. and for the v. yere of his reigne, and there you shall finde the yere of our lorde to be. 1550. Then begyn at the next yere after, which is 1551. and call that one, and so tel down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde all the yeres to this presente yeere 1571. And in the whole you shall finde. 21. whiche plainely declareth that at Mighel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas next, the aforesaid terme of. 21. yeres shall be fully expired. And this you maye do in the accompt of all termes of yeres.</p>
         <p>Note also that in the said Computacion diuerse of the kings haue in the first yere of their reigne no yere of our Lorde: The cause is, that they began in the same yere that the former kinge dyed in. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when you tell the yeeres, do not rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them that haue no yere of our Lorde,</p>
         <p>Note also that the yere of our lord after the Computacion of the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, beginneth euer the. 25. day of March
<pb facs="7"/>
which is the daye of the Annunciacion of our Lady. And the nomber of the Epacte beginneth euer the firste daye of Marche, and the Prime the fyrst daye of Ianuary.</p>
         <p>Note also, that when thou accompteste any terme of yeeres, that the same terme that thy lease first beganne in, must ende &amp; fynishe in the last yere of thy reconynge at the selfe same terme. As if thy lease be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan at Myghelmas for .xxj. yeres, then it muste ende at Mighelmas the same yeere that the whole .xxj. yeres are expired in, &amp; if at Midsomer, then it must ende at Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somer the same yere, as the last question and example dothe playnely shewe.</p>
         <p>And this I trust may suffyce for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of the vse, order, and commody<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the saide Computacion.</p>
         <p>Then foloweth .iiij. Tables that teache for euer to know in most Portes and Ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uens of this Realme: when it is ful Sea, with a plaine declaraciō of the said tables.</p>
         <p>And fynally one other Table, shewing for euer what signe the Mone is and shall be in euery daye, and declareth also what dayes are good to let Blood, Pourge, or Bathe. &amp;c.</p>
         <p>
            <pb facs="8"/>
And hereunto I haue added the Month, daye, and place, of all the Faires kept in England, set forth in a more orderly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then heretofore hath ben.</p>
         <p>And fynally, in the later ende hereof is set out the waies (in a larger maner then before they haue ben) as well how a man maye trauell from any notable towne in England, to the Citie of Lōdon, as from London to any notable towne, or from one notable town to an other in the most partes of this Realme: So that herein are conteyned the chiefe and moste necessary things that pertaine to any mans trauel.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>