<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Corderoy, Jeremy</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115604_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19331</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5756</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115604</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Corderoy, Jeremy</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A short dialogue, wherein is proved, that no man can be saved without good vvorkes</title>
                 <author>Corderoy, Jeremy</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <publisher>Barnes, Joseph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waterson, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 2, 110, 2 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S to the body of man (Curteous Reader) all kinds of diseases, to all kinds of ages are not incident, but some disea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses are more peculiar to vs whē wee are children, some proper vnto vs when we are yoūg mē, some more incident when wee are olde: so in the Church of God, al kind of evils breake not forth in one age, but some are more peculiar to some age, thē vnto others; as both histories of former times, and daily experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doe manifest vnto vs; the disposition whereof come not
<pb facs="6"/> by chance, but by the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate coūsaile of the Lord, who in his iust iudgmēt disposeth of these things, as it shal make for his glorie, and the good of his church. That these things come to passe by the appointment of God, it is manifest by many pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of the Scripture, wherein god sheweth that he doth send these calamities for the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of his church, &amp; also fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telleth the time when they shal come; in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>3. of <hi>Deuterono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie,</hi> verse, 3. the Lord saith that <hi>he vvill sende false Prophets a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst vs, to trie vs, vvhether we loue him with al our harts &amp; with al our souls.</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y this means mens harts shal be manifested, whether they loue God or no;
<pb facs="6"/> they that belong vnto God, wil not giue eare vnto these false Prophets, but vvil bee directed by the word of God; according to that saying of our Saviour, <hi>my sheepe heare my voice, &amp; fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ioh. 10.</note>
      <hi>they vvill not follovve a straunger, but flee from him, for they knovve not the voice of a stranger.</hi> He foresheweth whē such &amp; such evils shal come, as it appeareth in divers places of the Prophets in the olde Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament; and in the new, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of Iohn aboundeth in predictions of things to come. Now as God in his goodnes &amp; mercy towards vs vouchsafeth to forewarne vs of these temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations that shal come on vs, &amp; when, that therefore vvee may
<pb facs="7"/> bee the better armed against such events; so it is our duty, to take notice hereof, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly to addresse our selues to withstand such temptations as shal come on vs; but especiallie to obserue what evils are more proper to the time wherein we our selues liue, as most pertinēt vnto vs; not to speake of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of olde time, but of latter times, as most concerning vs. The Apostles, inspired by the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Ghost, haue intimated vnto vs of this age, what temptatiōs shal assault vs, vvho haue divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the time from the incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Christ, vntil his second cōming to iudgment, into two several times; in which, two se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral temptations shal assaulte
<pb facs="7"/> the church of God: the former of these two times, they terme, the latter daies; the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ther, the last daies. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n the former, that is the latter daies, shal come er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours in doctrine: in the last times shal come corruption of māners: not that the later daies shal be free from corruption of life and vngodly behaviour, or the last daies shal bee free from errour of doctrine: but in the latter daies errour of doctrine, in the last daies lewdnes of life, as two predominant ill humors shal abound, &amp; therfore accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the diuersitye of these two times, it is our duty to bend our selues more against the one then the other. In the time of errour, wee must most of al en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour
<pb facs="8"/> to confute error; in the times of vngodlines in life, wee must contend against vngodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in conversation. Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause this time present wherin we liue is the last time, wherein corruptiō of māners shal most aboūd, according to the predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Apostle, the which wee see with our eies to be too true: I haue chosen rather to speake of the necessitie of good works to saluatiō, as most befit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this time, then against er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in doctrine (though I haue not altogither omitted to speak some thing against it) seeing that now most men offende in lewdnesse of life, more then in errour of doctrine. If any doubt whether this time wherein we
<pb facs="8"/> liue, be the latter or last times or no, let him but conferre the prophecie of these tvvo times, with the euent which hath fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len out, &amp; he may easily be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved. The Apostle Paul spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the latter daies, wherin error in doctrine should aboūd saith:<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.1</note>
      <hi>now the spirite speaketh e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently, that in the latter daies some shal depart from the faith, and shall giue heede to spirite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> of errour, and doctrines of divels, which speake lies through hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crisie, and haue their conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces burned with an hot yrō.</hi> That this latter time began in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles time, and holdeth vntil the revealing of Antichrist, the same Apostle sheweth in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, vvhere he saith, <hi>the
<pb facs="9"/> mysterie of iniquitie doth alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die worke,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Thess 2.</note>
      <note place="margin">Chrysost. <hi>2.</hi> The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>2.</hi> hom <hi>4.</hi> Ambros <hi>2.</hi> Thes. <hi>2.</hi> Hierom in Dan. <hi>7</hi> &amp; quest <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>1</hi> ad Algas. Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tull de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrec. car. Lactan l <hi>7</hi> Aug. lib <hi>20</hi> cap <hi>19</hi> Zancheus in <hi>2,</hi> Thes <hi>2</hi> Osiander in <hi>2</hi> Thess <hi>2</hi> &amp; epit hist eccl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s. cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur <hi>7.</hi> lib. <hi>1</hi> &amp; lequent. Plat. de Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>if <hi>3.</hi> Func Cron. de Phoca &amp; Bon. <hi>3.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>onely hee which nowe with-holdeth shal let, vntil he be taken away.</hi> He which hindred Antichrists authority then, was the greate power of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of Rome, who would hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power of the man of sinne, vntill he, that is, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour should be taken avvaie; as histories, the event, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positours doe testifie vnto vs; when the power of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour should bee Eclipsed, then the man of sinne should exalte himselfe aboue all that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led God, or is worshipped; that hee shoulde sit in the temple of God, shewing himselfe that he is God, which in the Popes of Rome hath already beene veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,
<pb facs="9"/> exalting themselues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue God, taking vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues the authoritie of God, making lavves to be observed vpon no lesse daunger of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal damnation; then the laws of God: dispensing against the plaine worde of God, abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the commaundemente of God, to establish their owne. This the mā of sinne hath fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, according as it hath been foretolde of him. But his pride shal bee abated, and hee shal come to an ebb, as the same A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle foretelleth;<note place="margin">2. Thess 2.8 Esay 11.4.</note> saving <hi>that the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d will consume him with the spirit of his mouth,</hi> that is, by the preaching of his gospel. By this means we see the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Antichrist now brought
<pb facs="10"/> to a very lowe ebbe, and his madnesse made manifest to al men,<note place="margin">2 Thess. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>i. 12.</note> saving in some fewe, to whom God hath <hi>sent strong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lusions,</hi> that they may bee dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, because they loued not the trueth. Antichrist being reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and made manifest, nowe follovveth the last time, this time present wherein we nowe liue; of which the Apostle Paul speaketh. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. Saying, <hi>this know also, that in the last daies shall come perilous times, for men shall bee lovers of their owne selues, covetous, boasters, prowd, cursed speakers, disobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to parents, vnthankefull, vnholy, vvithout naturall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, truce-breakers, false ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusers, intemperate, fier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e, des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pisers
<pb facs="10"/> of thē that are good, trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, heady, high-minded, lovers of pleasure more then God, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a shewe of godlynesse, but haue denyed the force of it.</hi> The Epist. of Iude consisteth,<note place="margin">2. Pet.,</note> almost whollie, of the description of these ill men, of whom also Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter forewarneth vs; the which if you reade, you shal haue the manners and behauiour of the men of this age presented as liuely vnto you, as if you shuld see them al in a glasse at one vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>w. Now (as I haue saide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) corruption in manners being the proper disease to this age, in reason we should bende our chiefest strength against this disease, especiallye since the reason whye the Apostles
<pb facs="11"/> foreshevve these thinges is,<note place="margin">Iude 3.</note> that wee should earnestly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende against it, and that in this miserable and perilous time, we should haue compassion on some, pulling them out of the fire,<note place="margin">vers. 22.</note> in <hi>putting a difference,</hi> as the Apostle Iude saith. He cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares this time, to a citie set on fire, which when it happeneth, vvee catch at that vvhich is dearest in our sighte, and saue it from burning. We must put a difference according to the differēce of mē: for, some there are, who sinne of infirmitie and weaknes, &amp; are, as the Apostle saith <hi>overtakē w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>th sinne;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gal. 6 1.</note> these we ought, to reclaime with the spirit of mildnes &amp; gentlenes. Others there are who are more
<pb facs="11"/> stubborne and wilful; these wee must rebuke more sharpely. A third kinde there is, vvho,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.2</note> so they may enioy their pleasurs, care neither for God nor man; who say vnto vs, <hi>depart frō vs,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iob. 21.14.15.</note>
      <hi>vve desire not the knowledge of the Lorde; vvho is the Almighty that wee shoulde serue him, and what profite shoulde wee haue if vvee should pray vnto him?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psalm. 50.17. Ier. 2.24.</note> these kinde of men hate to bee refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, these are like those wilde Asses vsed to the vvildernesse, that wil not be turned, and who so seeketh to turne them, shal but vvearie himselfe,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.6. Exod. 10.29. 2. King. 3.14.</note> but not prevaile: let these pleasantlie descende to hell, for who can turne them; wee may not <hi>giue that which is holie to dogges, nor
<pb facs="12"/> cast pearles to swine,</hi> if wee doe they wil treade thē vnder their feete, &amp; returne and al to rent vs. Wherefore if I may bee so boulde to advise those, to whō the care of soules is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, I would advise them to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the steppes of our ancient Fathers, who alwaies bent their studies against that of their time, wherin they lived, which was most hurtful, and the abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses which then most aboūded. Since the time of the Apostles, vntil within these fewe yeares, errour in doctrine most aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, therefore we see the godly men of that age bent their whole studies to confute er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours but nowe (God be than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked) this disease beeing almost
<pb facs="12"/> cured, and as greate a disease, as the former, affecting the Church of God, in my opinion, if wee devide the worde aright and minister a word in due sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, we ought especially to vse our endevour to reclaime men from vngodly behaviour, and not wholy, in these daies, spend our studies and labours against errour in doctrine; notwithstā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding (gentle Reader) I speake not definitiuely herein, but my slender opinion; if I speake vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on weake groundes, I will not be stubborne, but am content to yeelde to men more iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the Lord, <hi>JEREMY CORDEROY.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>