<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Minsheu, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115752_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09312</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19622</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115752</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Minsheu, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A Spanish grammar, first collected and published by Richard Perciuale Gent : Now augmented and increased with the declining of all the irregular and hard verbes in that toong, with diuers other especiall rules and necessarie notes for all such as shall be desirous to attaine the perfection of the Spanish tongue. Done by Iohn Minsheu professor of languages in London. Hereunto for the yoong beginners learning and ease, are annexed speeches, phrases, and prouerbes, expounded out of diuers authors, setting downe the line and the leafe where in the same bookes they shall finde them, whereby they may not onely vnderstand them, but by them vnderstand others, and the rest as they shall meete with them</title>
                 <author>Perceval, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bollifant, alias Carpenter, Edmund</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 84, 4, 68 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F it be vanitie and vexation of minde, for a man to toile in this life to gather riches togither, when he knowes not whether he be wise or foolish that shall enioy it: we may thinke the sweate of our spirits and the toile of our bodies, to be altogither vaine, which write or print, when we cannot tell whether they will prooue sober or franticke, to whom we leaue the possession of our tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels. But the Spaniard saith, <hi>Quien de miédo se murió de cagaxónes le hizié<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron la sepoltura;</hi> and because as the Italian saying is, <hi>A molti puzza l'ambro,</hi> Amber is accounted stinking by many: and <hi>Dal asino non ne hai che calzi &amp; petti:</hi> I am resolued for this once to put on merchants eares, to heare with patience euerie mans speech and dispraisings of his wares, because <hi>Quot homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, tot sententiae,</hi> So many men, so many mindes. Therefore he that should leaue off any good worke for any mans ill speech, may well be likened to that poore seely fellow, which on a time went with one of his sonnes with his Asse before him to the wood, to fetch him a loade thereof for his wife and children, and meeting trauellers by the way; some misliking with him that he should goe on foote, and let his Asse goe leere; others, that he roade himselfe, and suffered his childe to goe a foote; others, that he loaded the poore Asse with two persons, being scarce able to carrie himselfe; others, when he left his sonne alone riding and himselfe go on foote; in such sort that the countrey fellow could not tel what to do, seeing do what he could, still he found repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henders: whereupon he would goe no further forward, but returned sad home to his house without wood, where he remained for feare of fault finders, till he and his houshold were neere starued with colde, till at last finding his owne simplicitie, he returned to the wood, and to as many as he met by the way, he said; <hi>Hee that passeth for other mens speeches and repreefes, endureth colde and a thousand greefes;</hi> and he that will throw a stone at euerie dog, shall haue a wearie arme: but I hope, <hi>Qui bien ferá, bien aurá,</hi> And for all the dogs bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, the moone will stand where it did. And I say to the malitious, <hi>Mets ta main sovent en ton sein, et tu ne mesdirás de ton prochain.</hi> And let them remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that <hi>Chifa quello che non deve, gliavien quel che non crede,</hi> According to a Historie I haue read of an Emperour, who had his brothers sonne for his cupbearer: The Emperours steward and vncle, for enuie perswaded the cupbearer that his breath did stinke, and wished therefore to turne his face from the Emperour when he deliuered the cup till remedie were found: forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he told the Emperour, that his cupbearer had defamed him to all his court, by saying his breath did stinke; and to know it for a certaintie, he like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise told him how he should see the cupbearer turne away his face from him when he came neere him; whereupon the Emperour conceiued such wrath against him, (as the saying is, the anger of a Prince the messenger of death)
<pb facs="4"/> that he sent expresse commaund to his burners of bricke, that they should burne that man that came vnto them first the next morrow; and likewise commaunded his cupbearer to be there so earely that none might be before him: on the morrow morning verie earely the cupbearer going, and passing by a church in the way went in and fell into such a sound sleepe, that it was the afternoone before he could awake. The steward in the meane time to see the euent of the cupbearer, went and was burned himselfe aliue. The cupbearer at his returne signified to the Emperour what had happened, and also was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous to knowe of the Emperour why he should send him thither, &amp;c. If nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Histories nor reason perswade them, they must needs be answered with silence, and so gentle Reader I rest silent from troubling thee or them herewith any longer, more grieued at my mishap and disabilitie, then wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting good will or liking to doe thee seruice. <hi>Haec raptim. Vale.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Iohn Minsheu.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>