<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, IAMES Earle of Carlile, &amp;c. Count Palatine of the Prouince of CARLILE, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Featly, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115123_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00608</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10743</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115123</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, IAMES Earle of Carlile, &amp;c. Count Palatine of the Prouince of CARLILE, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Featly, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon preached to the nobely-deseruing gentleman, Sir Thomas Warner : And the rest of his companie: bound to the West-Indies. For their farevvell: At St. Buttolphs, Aldersgate, London. Septemb. 6. 1629. By Iohn Featly, Preacher of the Word of God</title>
                 <author>Featley, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 34 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, IAMES Earle of <hi>Carlile, &amp;c. Count Palatine</hi> of the Prouince of CARLILE, &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Vtie</hi> becomes disguised, where it wants the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of <hi>Integrity:</hi> and this loses it selfe, when ignorant of <hi>expression. Great Personages</hi> are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten cloyed (as with the <hi>verball expressions,</hi> so) with the hypocrisie of those that tender them. But my <hi>selfe</hi> am become the <hi>exception</hi> against that common rule; and I dare with as bold a Confidence convict, as slight the
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Opposer.</hi> My bowing-heart hath bin alwaies steep'd in desire to present the <hi>Pledge</hi> of an humble <hi>obseruance</hi> to your <hi>Lordship:</hi> But remaining guilty of my <hi>weaknesse,</hi> here I sue for <hi>assistance</hi> by a Noble <hi>Protection.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The <hi>Sermon</hi> it selfe is the <hi>Defenders</hi> of the <hi>faith;</hi> and though briefe, yet <hi>orthodox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</hi> If any carpe at it, peraduenture it may proue a <hi>Mansenile-apple,</hi> (whereof I haue seene diuers in the <hi>Indies</hi>) that blisters the <hi>Tongues</hi> of them that taste.</p>
   <p>The Noble worth of my deseruing <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, Sir Thomas Warner,</hi> made me a <hi>Traueller</hi> into the <hi>Indies,</hi> being thereby the first <hi>Preacher</hi> vpon <hi>Saint Christo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers Ilands.</hi> And your <hi>Lordships</hi> vnualu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Goodnesse and <hi>Patronage</hi> of those <hi>Parts,</hi> hath now commanded this <hi>Sermon</hi> to trauell into the <hi>Censure</hi> of each <hi>Peruser:</hi> If it suffer by a Martyrdome, yet the <hi>Author</hi> shall euer appeare</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships humbly and faithfully-deuoted, IO. FEATLY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>