<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right honorable Thomas Lord Garrarde, Bar∣ron of Garrardes Bromley: and to the right worshipfull his brother in law, Sir Peter Leigh of Lime, I. C wish∣eth health, honor, &amp; happinesse in this life, and in the life to come.</title>
           <author>C., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115877_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01475</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11600</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115877</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right honorable Thomas Lord Garrarde, Bar∣ron of Garrardes Bromley: and to the right worshipfull his brother in law, Sir Peter Leigh of Lime, I. C wish∣eth health, honor, &amp; happinesse in this life, and in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>C., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Two treatises : the first, entituled, The foode of the faithfull. The second Deaths welcome</title>
                 <author>Garey, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                    <distributor>Chorlton (Charlton), Jeffrey (Geoffrey)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 29, 3, 80 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right honorable <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Garrarde,</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of <hi>Garrardes Bromley:</hi> and to the right worshipfull his brother in law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, Sir <hi>Peter Leigh</hi> of Lime, <hi>I. C</hi> wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth health, honor, &amp; happinesse in this life, and in the life to come.</head>
   <p>I <hi>Socrates</hi> the Athenians Orator (right honorable) calleth Nobilitie the pillar of learning, and <hi>Plato</hi> saith, that a true noble man is a faithfull fauorite of the learned. And for this reason the Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, Orators, Poets, Diuines, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther writers, consecrate their labors to the Patronage of such worthymen, who are placed in the high sobeare of greatnesse, and seated in the Throne of Nobilitie, who can with power, and may with au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie defend them vnder the fauorable winges of their safe protection. In like
<pb facs="3"/>manner, I who am neither sound Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sopher, nor eloquent Orator, nor good Poet, nor profound Diuine, haue presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to dedicate to your gracious viewes, these two Treatises (whose rudenesse are far vnsutable to weare the Liueries of your names) for two especiall considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. The first is, because you two be the great fauorits of learning, and in you liue the sparkes of <hi>Augustus</hi> liberallitie, to cherrish the Muses, who now for want of succor are almost famished. The second is, which mooueth me most of all, to giue you a liuing memoriall of the louing duty I bare to your honored deceased mother, vnto whom for many singular good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors, I will euer recognise my selfe infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitly bounden, for whose sake I suppose I haue passed the bonds of modesty in this presumptious attempt. Yet notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding perswaded by my friends earnest in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties, and mooued by that priuate du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie which I owe, to that vertuous Lady your mother (who is now a cohabitor with God) I haue emboldened my bashfull nature, and as he saith, <hi>Commas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culaui frontem pudoris limites transilire.</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb facs="3"/>therefore (most renowned Patrons) this gratefull testimonie of my dutie, and thankfulnesse, which I tender for mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold benefits vnto you both, whom I make as honorable twinns vnited in the vnion of my zealous, and duteous affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: I confesse it is a trifle, nor a fit ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to be bee viewed by your seuere eies, yet I hope you will receiue it as a token, and earnest pennie of my long concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led loue, and dutie, according to your accustomed, and incomparable gentel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: <hi>Phillip</hi> of Maccedon did accept a bunch of grapes giuen by a Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaine; and <hi>Apollo</hi> did vouchsafe to take a wodden dish as a great gift. So I trust that you (sithence my abilitie serueth to no better purpose, nor you expect a kind of remuneration) will receiue it in curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous manner, and grant this abortiue brat (which should haue wanted a Godfather, had I not chosen you) to shelter vnder the defensiue shadowes of your patronage, giuing it the Almes of your approouiug commendation, to cloath the naked beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garie of his threed-bare inuention: which if it shall please your good honors to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="4"/>like <hi>Minerua,</hi> this forsaken deformed Owle, vnder the sure target of your tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it shall be as secure from Critickes, as <hi>Ʋlis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>es</hi> was free from the Greekes, being defended with <hi>Aiax</hi> buckler. So hoping of your wished defence, I commit it with all submission to your protection, saying, that which <hi>Gratian</hi> sayd to his Patron, <hi>Ʋobis soluo quod debebam, et ad huc debeo quod soluam.</hi> So duly, and daily praying for you, and yours, I humbly take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your honors in all duty to commaunde. I. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>