<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHOR TO The Reader.</title>
           <author>Maurus, Terentianus</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115671_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17832</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4510.8</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115671</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHOR TO The Reader.</title>
                 <author>Maurus, Terentianus</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Britain, or A chorographicall description of the most flourishing kingdomes, England, Scotland, and Ireland, and the islands adjoyning, out of the depth of antiquitie : beautified vvith mappes of the severall shires of England: vvritten first in Latine by William Camden Clarenceux K. of A. Translated newly into English by Philémon Holland Doctour in Physick: finally, revised, amended, and enlarged with sundry additions by the said author</title>
                 <author>Camden, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Latham (Lathum, Lautham), George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, Elizabeth.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Young (Junius), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 822, 233, 59 pages, 50 plates, mostly folded, illustrations, maps, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE AVTHOR TO The Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Hope it shall be to no discredite, if I now use againe by way of Preface, the same words with a few more, that I used twentie foure yeares since, in the first edition of this worke. <hi>Abraham Ortelius</hi> the worthy restorer of Ancient Geographic arriving heere in England, about thirtie foure yeares past, dealt earnestly with mee that I would illustrate this Isle of <hi>BRITAINE,</hi> or (as he said) that I would restore antiquitie to Britaine, and Britaine to his antiquitie; which was, as I understood, that I would renew ancientrie, enlighten obscuritie, cleare doubts, and recall home Veritie by way of reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, which the negligence of writers and credulity of the common sort had in a manner pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed and utterly banished from amongst us. A painfull matter I assure you, and more than difficult; wherein what toyle is to be taken, as no man thinketh, so no man believeth but hee that hath made the triall. Neverthelesse how much the difficultie discouraged mee from it, so much the glory of my country encouraged me to undertake it. So while at one and the same time I was fearefull to undergoe the burthen, and yet desirous to doe some service to my Country, I found two different affections, Feare, and Boldnesse; I know not how, conjoyned in me. Notwithstanding by the most gracious direction of the <hi>ALMIGHTY,</hi> taking <hi>INDVSTRY</hi> for my consort, I adventured upon it, and with all my studie, care, cogitation, continuall medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, paine, and travaile I imploied my selfe thereunto when I had any spare time. I made search after the Etymologie of Britain &amp; the first Inhabitants timorously, neither in so doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a matter have I affirmed ought confidently. For I am not ignorant that the first originals of nations are obscure by reason of their profound antiquitie, as things which are seene very deepe and far remote: like as the courses, the reaches, the confluencies, &amp; the out-lets of great rivers are wel knowne, yet their first fountaines and heads lie commonly unknown. I have suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinctly run over the Romans government in Britain, and the inundation of forraigne people thereinto, what they were, and from whence they came: I have traced out the ancient divisions of these Kingdomes, I have summarily specified the states, and judiciall Courts of the same.</p>
   <p>In the severall Counties I have compendiously set downe the limits (and yet not exactly by pearch and pole to breed questions) what is the nature of the soile, which were places of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test antiquitie, who have beene the Dukes, Marquesses, Earles, Vicounts, Barons, and some of the most signall, and ancient families therein (for who can particulate all?) What I have performed, I leave to men of judgement. But time the most sound and sincere witnes will give the truest information, when envy which persecuteth the living, shall have her mouth stopped. Thus much give me leave to say, that I have in no wise neglected such things as are most ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall to search, and sift out the Truth. I have attained to some skill of the most ancient Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish and English-Saxon tongues: I have travailed over all England for the most part, I have conferred with most skilfull observers in each country, I have studiously read over our owne country writers, old and new, all Greeke and Latine authors which have once made mention of Britaine. I have had conference with learned men in other parts of Christendome: I have been diligent in the Records of this Realme. I have looked into most Libraries, Registers, and memorials of Churches, Cities, and Corporations, I have pored upon many an old Rowle, and Evidence: and produced their testimonie (as beyond all exception) when the cause required, in
<pb facs="6"/>
their very own words (although barbarous they be) that the honour of veritie might in no wise be impeached,</p>
   <p>For all this I may be censured unadvised, and scant modest who being but of the lowest fourme in the schoole of Antiquitie, where I might well have lurked in obscuritie, have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured as a scribler upon the stage in this learned age amidst the diversities of relishes both in wit and judgement. But to tell the truth unfainedly, the love of my Country which compris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth all love in it, and hath endeared me unto it, the glory of the British name, the advise of some judicious friends hath overmastred my modestie, and (wild I, nild I,) hath enforced me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst mine own judgment to undergo this burden too heavy for me, &amp; so thrust me forth into the worlds view. For I see judgements, prejudices, censures, reprehensions, obtrectations, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions, affronts, and confronts, as it were, in battaile array to environ me on every side: some there are which wholly contemne and avile this study of Antiquitie as a back-looking cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riositie; whose authority as I do not utterly vilefie, so I do not overprize or admire their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Neither am I destitute of reasons whereby I might approve this my purpose to well bred and well meaning men which tender the glory of their native Country: and moreover could give them to understand that in the studie of Antiquity, (which is alwaies accompanied with dignity, and hath a certaine resemblance with eternity) there is a sweet food of the mind well befitting such as are of honest and noble disposition. If any there be which are desirous to be strangers in their owne soile, and forrainers in their owne City, they may so continue and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in flatter themselves. For such like I have not written these lines, nor taken these paines. Some there be who may object the silly web of my stile, and rough hewed forme of my writing. Verily I acknowledge it, neither have I waied every word in Goldsmiths scales, as <hi>Vario</hi> commanded, neither purposed I to picke flowers out of the gardens of Eloquence. But why should they object this, when as <hi>Cicero</hi> the father of Eloquence denieth that this kind of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument can <hi>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> that is, be flourished out, and as <hi>Pomponius Mela</hi> said, <hi>is incapable of all Eloquent speech.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Many happily will insult over me for that I have adventured to hunt after the originals of names by conjectures, who if they proceed on to reject all conjectures, I feare me a great part of liberall learning and humane knowledge will be utterly out-cast into banishment. For the edge of our understanding is so blunt that we are of necessitie enforced to prosecute many matters in all professions conjecturally. In Physick <hi>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> which are nothing else but conjectures, have their place, and stand in good steed, likewise in Rhetoricke, Civil Law, and other arts they are admitted and allowed. And whereas conjectures are certaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tections of things unknown, and as <hi>Fabius</hi> termeth them, directions of reason to verity, I have alwaies thought that they were to be accounted among the skuppers wherewith <hi>TIME</hi> worketh and draweth <hi>VERITIE</hi> out of <hi>Democritus</hi> his deepe dungeon. But if these men may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to attribute ought to conjectures, I doubt not but my modesty and moderation in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecturing may withall purchase my pardon; <hi>Plato</hi> in his <hi>Cratilus</hi> commandeth that we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal the originals of names to the barbarous tongues (for so he called al but Greek) as being most ancient. I thereupon in Etymologies and my conjectures have made recourse to the British, or Welsh tongue (so they now call it) as being the same which the Primitive and most ancient In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of this land used, and to the English-Saxons tongue which our Progenitors the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish spake. He commandeth that the name be consonant to the nature of the thing, &amp; the nature thereof to the name, if they be herein dissonant, I admit them not. In things, saith he, there is <hi>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi>: that is, but I cannot aptly expresse them, <hi>A sound, a forme, and colour,</hi> if these discover not themselves in the name I reject the conjecture. As for obscure Etymologies, far fetched hardly wrested, and which may be drawne diversly; I have vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safed them no place it this worke, finally I have beene so sparing and cautelously forecasting in my conjectures that if I be not thought <hi>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> that is, <hi>Happily adventurous,</hi> I shall not seeme <hi>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> that is, <hi>Presumptuously audacious.</hi> And albeit I have once or twice framed two conjectures in one and the same name, yet I forget not in the meane time that <hi>VNITIE</hi> is consecrated unto <hi>VERITIE.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>There are some peradventure which apprehend it disdainfully and offensively that I have not remembred this or that family, when as it was not my purpose to mention any but such as were more notable, nor all them truely (for their names would fill whole volumes) but such as hapned in my way according to the method I proposed to my selfe; And with Gods grace I
<pb facs="6"/>
may have a more convenient occasion to deserve well of the Nobilitie and Gentry. But happily they will be most offended herein who have least deserved of their conutry, or overvallew themselves most, or whose Gentry may be but newly blossomed. Of whom yet I protest I would not offend any, and therefore desire and hope their noble natures will not take it offensively upon such causelesse apprehensions.</p>
   <p>Others will call me in question for that I have commended some persons now living; yet I have done it sparingly, and that out of an assurance of verity, out of the common consent and voice of such as can well judge of worth, &amp; from no base flattery. By these sparing commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions such as are commended may be lessoned that their deportments may be answerable, and that they preserve and daily increase the same. Succeeding ages, which I respect more than the present, will render to every man his right whatsoever is now scribled in papers. In the meane time I wish them to remember, that to praise good men is but to shew a light of direction as out of a watch towre to posteritie. True is that saying of <hi>Symmachus. Imitation is encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged with the seemely praises of the good, and imitating vertue is cherished by the example of others honour.</hi> If any say that I have sought occasion to commend some one or other, I confesse it. Neither is well-meaning without leasing to be blamed among the good, and well deserving, friends are not to be forgotten. Howsoever <hi>Virtue</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> hath alwaies op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posites, and men usually envie the present, and reverence what is past; yet God forbid that we should be so partially injurious as to thinke our times under most worthy Princes to be barrein of praiseworthy persons. As for such as maligne the praise of the good, I feare me least in their owne guiltinesse they may apply the dispraise of the bad to themselves. As for my selfe I sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly understand that which <hi>Plinie</hi> intimated to <hi>Tacitus</hi> in like case. <hi>There will bee great offence, and slender thankes, for albeit in the loosenesse of the world, there is much more to be discommended than commended; yet if you commend you shall be taxed as oversparing; if you discommend you shall be censured as overlavish, although you doe the one most compleatly, and the other most moderatly.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Some will blame me for that I have omitted this and that towne and Castle, as though I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to mention any but such as were most notorious, and mentioned by ancient authours. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther verily were it worth the labour once to name them, when as beside the naked name there is nothing memorable. Truly it was my project and purpose to seeke, rake out, and free from darkenesse such places as <hi>Caesar, Tacitus, Ptolomy, Antonine</hi> the Emperor, <hi>Notitia Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciarum,</hi> and other antique writers have specified and <hi>TIME</hi> hath overcast with mist and darknes by extinguishing, altering, and corrupting their old true names. In searching &amp; seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after these, as I will not avouch uncertainties so I doe not conceale probabilities. That I have not found out every one although I have sought after them with painfull &amp; chargeable inquiery let it bee no imputation to mee, as it is not to a Spadiard that worketh in Mines, who while he findeth &amp; followeth the maine vaines, seeth not the hidden small fillets; or that I may use that which <hi>Columella</hi> did. As it is the commendation of a good Huntsman to find game in a wide wood so it is no imputation if he hath not caught all, and likewise to me, Some things are to be left to the inquisitive diligence of others, Neither, as a learned man said, he teacheth well which teacheth all. An other age, and other men may daily find out more. It is enough for me to have begun, and I have gained as much as I looke for, if I shall draw others into this argument, whether they undertake a new worke or amend this.</p>
   <p>There are certain, as I heare who take it impatiently that I have mentioned some of the most famous Monasteries and their founders. I am sory to heare it, and with their good favour will say thus much, They may take it as impatiently, and peradventure would have us forget that our ancestours were, and we are of the Christian profession when as there are not extant any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more conspicuous, and certaine Monuments, of their piety, and zealous devotion toward God. Neither were there any other seed-gardens from whence Christian Religion, and good learning were propagated over this Isle, howbeit in corrupt ages some weeds grew out over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranckly.</p>
   <p>Mathematicians wil accuse me as though I had wholy missed the mark in the Cosmographi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal dimentions of longitude, &amp; latitude. Yet heare me I pray you. I have carefully cōferred the Locall tables new &amp; old, Manuscript, and printed, of Oxford &amp; Cambridge, and King Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Fifth. In the latitude they doe not vary much from <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> but agree wel together, neither do I thereupon imagine with <hi>Stadius,</hi> that the globe of the earth is removed from his
<pb facs="7"/>
centre, therefore I have relied upon them. But in the Longitude there is no accord, no consent at all. What should I then doe? When as therefore the moderne navigators have observed that there is no variation of the Compasse at the Isles of <hi>Asores,</hi> I have thence begun with them, the account of Longitude as from the first Meridian, which yet I have not precisely measured.</p>
   <p>As for obscuritie, fables, extravagant digressions I trust there is no cause to sue out my par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. There will be no obscuritie but to them which have not sipped the first elements of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and our histories: upon fables I have no waies relied, and that I might not digresse extravagantly. I have had often recourse to the title of my booke (as Pliny adviseth) and eft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soones demanded of my selfe why I tooke penne in hand. Many have found a defect in this worke that Mappes were not adjoyned, which doe allure the eies by pleasant portr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iture, and are the best directions in Geographicall studies, especially when the light of learning is adjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the speechlesse delineations. Yet my abilitie could not compasse it, which by the meanes and cost of <hi>George Bishop,</hi> and <hi>John Norton</hi> is now performed out of the labours of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stopher Saxton,</hi> and <hi>John Norden,</hi> most skilfull Chorographers.</p>
   <p>But least I should run at randome in my Preface. To accomplish this worke the whole maine of my Industrie hath been imploied for many yeares with a firme setled study of the truth, and sincere antique faithfulnesse to the glory of God and my country. I have done dishonour to no nation, have descanted upon no mans name, I have impaired no mans reputation, I have impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched no mans credit, no not Geffrey of Monmouth whose historie (which I would gladly sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port) is held suspected amongst the judicious. Neither have I assumed upon my self any perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of knowledge, but only that I have been desirous to know much. And so I right willingly acknowledge that I may erre much, neither will I sooth and smoth my errors. Who shooting all day long doth alwaies hit the mark? Many matters in these studies are raked under deceitfull ashes. There may be some escapes from memory, for who doth so comprehend particularities, in the treasury of his memory, that he can utter them at his pleasure? There may be mistakings in regard of my unskilfulnes, for who is so skilfull that strugling with <hi>TIME</hi> in the foggie darke sea of Antiquity, may not run upon rocks? It may be that I have been misled by the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of authors and others whom I tooke to be most true, and worthy of credit. <hi>Neither is there verily</hi> (as Pliny saith) <hi>any easier slipping from truth, then when a grave Authour war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranteth an untruth.</hi> Others may be more skilfull and more exactly observe the particularities of the places where they are conversant, If they, or any other whosoever, will advertise mee wherein I am mistaken, I will amend it with manifold thankes, if I have unwitting omitted ought, I will supply it, if I have not fully explicated any point, upon their better information I will more cleere it, if it proceed from good meaning, and not from a spirit of contradiction and quarelling, which doe not befit such as are well bred, and affect the truth. Meane while let your kind courtesie, my industry, the common love of our common mother our native Country, the ancient honour of the British name obtaine so much upon their entreaty, that I may utter my judgement without prejudice to others, that I may proceed in that course that others have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly done in the like argument, and that you would pardon my errors upon my acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which may be as well hoped as requested, from good indifferent and reasonable men; so I passe not for the unreasonable, and worser sort which gnaw upon all at tables, carp in conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, envy, back-bite, slander, and detract. For I have learned of the Comicall Poet, that slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is the treasure of fooles which they carry in their tongues, and I know for certainty that <hi>Envy</hi> is seated (I will say it although <hi>Envy</hi> stood at my elbow) in none but in degenerous, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble, and base minds. The honest good and noble natures as they detest envy, so they cannot envy. As for my selfe, and this worke, I doe most humbly submit it to the censure of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honest and learned with all respective reverence of whom if it be not approved, I hope in regard of my professed love to our native Country, that it may be excused. <hi>Farwell.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>TERENTIANVS MAVRVS.</signed>
   </closer>
   <postscript>
      <p>
         <hi>Bookes receive their doome according to the Readers capacitie.</hi>
      </p>
   </postscript>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>