<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Postscript]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115274_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08522</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1884</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115274</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Postscript]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The hope of peace : By laying open such doubts and manifest vntruthes as are divulged by the Arch-priest in his letter or answere to the bookes which were published by the priestes</title>
                 <author>Bennett, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Turke, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 45, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="postscript">
   <pb facs="25"/>
   <p>After that this answere to M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> his Letter was printed, an other copie of the same letter came to our sight, which hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed vs to amend the first copie by way of <hi>Errata,</hi> although it contain nothing of moment more then the first, except that in the <hi>6.</hi> Page in the end of the first clause in answere to the first point these words are wanting. <hi>It toucheth the greater part and better part of that cōpany there.</hi> To which if we would imitate others in their insolent comparisons, we might say (and perchance with more truth) that the lesser part was the better, and answer to that of the greater part, <hi>Stultorum infinitus est numerus.</hi> The world is full of Fooles. But remembring that saying of the Apostle, Rom. <hi>14. What are you who iudge an others seruant?</hi> We can conclude no otherwise then the same Apostle concluded, <hi>2.</hi> Cor. <hi>10. He is approued, whom God commendeth.</hi> In the same <hi>6.</hi> Page lin. <hi>23.</hi> where <hi>(greatest)</hi> must be put in place of <hi>(most grieuously)</hi> (a word not likely to be so much mistake) the sence might giue that the Pope is contemned by the complaint of the vsage of the Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, if F. <hi>Parsons</hi> (as at other times) in his Letters to F. <hi>Holt,</hi> dated <hi>15.</hi> May, <hi>1597.</hi> did not confesse that he found errors in the Iesuites their carriage toward the Schollers, and such, as if many of those things had happened in their quietest Colledge in <hi>Spaine</hi> or <hi>Flaunders,</hi> they would haue put the peace out of ioynt.</p>
   <p>Also page <hi>8.</hi> in the margent <hi>Zecchius de rep eccle.</hi> is left out, who in his Treatise <hi>de statu Ill. D. Card.</hi> Num <hi>9.</hi> handling the office of a Protector, saith not one word concerning his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>