<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE DE∣DICATORY. To the right honorable and most noble Lady, the Lady B. A.</title>
           <author>M., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115340_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21061</idno>
           <idno type="STC">743</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115340</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE DE∣DICATORY. To the right honorable and most noble Lady, the Lady B. A.</title>
                 <author>M., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of patience. Written by Father Francis Arias, of the Society of Iesus, in his second parte of the Imitatio [n] of Christ our Lord. Translated into English</title>
                 <author>Arias, Francisco</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Boscard (Buree), Jeanne</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 225, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DICATORY. <hi>To the right honorable and most noble Lady, the Lady B. A.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAM</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>In the transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of this <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise of Patience,</hi> I haue had no cause to exercise <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> for I dispatched it
<pb facs="3"/>with a great deale of gust, in regard that I was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded therein by your Ladyship; the expression of whose will giues euer occasion of much ioy to mee. Now therefore, since, vpon the matter, it came from your Ladyship, it is but reason that it returne againe; though it must not be without the interest of my humblest thankes for your ministring mee so faire an occasion, whereby I may haue seen more<pb facs="3"/>clearly what in my selfe I ought to be; and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently what I am not: To the end that hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if I growe not more patient, yet at least I may grow more hūble, through the too certaine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of my great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects.</p>
   <p>Your Ladyship, I assure my selfe, will be pleased to looke vpon it with at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention; especially in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of what it is in it selfe; though partly also, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause<pb facs="4"/>it is a poore presēt of mine And I shall pray our good God, with whole my heart, that you also may be much the better by it, in thanking his diuine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty, for that which you shall perceiue him to haue giuen you, and in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him hard, to enrich you, with whatsoeuer you may yet finde your selfe in this vertue to want. And if his holy name may be glorified hereby, and your soule and mine as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted
<pb facs="4"/>to doe him the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter seruice, it is that very reward, which most wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly I would bestowe vpon my selfe for this little labour, though I had all power in mine owne hāds: yours Ladyships, I most humblie kisse, and doe you reuerence, with the hart of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>A most obliged and most humble seruant euer. T. M.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>