<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>H., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115004_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02442</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12574</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115004</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>H., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The spiritual pilgrimage of Hierusalem, contayninge three hundred sixtie fiue dayes iorney : wherin the deuoute person may meditate on sondrie pointes of his redemption. With particular declaration of diuers Saints bodies and holy places which are to be seene in the said-voyage: As also sundrie deuout praiers and meditations verie healpful to the pilgrimes: With licence</title>
                 <author>Paeschen, Jan van</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Boscard, Charles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 173, that is 174 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Calendars, almanacs and prognostications</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eing it is so my (Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike brother) that this presente life is no other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge but a continuall▪ Pilgrimage vvhich vve are to make vpon the earth: and that al the time of our life is a terme prefixed of God the Creator, during vvhich space vve ought to accōplish this
<pb facs="3"/>voiage, vvhich vvhen vve haue faithfully vvalked, vve may come to the Citie of heauenly Heirusalem, vvhich is our king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and most proper contrie: vvere it not great follie &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligence in vs, if vve should forget, or to say more trulie, des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pise, and not accompte, of the principal place of our repose, but like vnvvise men rather to sit dovvne and rest our selues in the midle of our iorney, to vvit in the fillbie and durtie vvayes of this vvretched and vvicked vvorde? The trauailer or
<pb facs="3"/>fote Post, vvhich is ordinarily hiered to goe some Iorney; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his iorney be longe, the the vveather fovvle, and the vvayes very vncleane, yet hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth not his voiage for the difi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie he conceiues of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, but knovvinge that he get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his liunige by meanes of the gaines, and that he shal vvel che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishe, and refreshe him self, vvhen he is arriued at his Inne, vvith great facilitie supporteth the asperitie of the trauaile, vpon hope of the recompence vvhich he aftervvards expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth.
<pb facs="4"/>VVe then (deare brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren expecting the (rovvne of) euerlastinge glorie, vvhich our lord hath promised to such as loue him, shal vve appeare more vnvvillinge, or vvearie for the obtayninge hereof, then vve vvould be for the gayninge only of some temporall commoditie? Let vs behould therfore vvhat care &amp; paines our louing lord hath taken of our saluation; let vs learne to trauaille couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously &amp; like deuout &amp; holy pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimes to follovve his steppes, vvho hath left vs an exsam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="4"/>of his blessed life &amp; passion, and ruminate in our hartes eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day aparte, some seuerall poinct therof, and after vvel to practise the same in our selues (for such ought to be the end of al our spiritual exercises) by vvhich meanes vve may attaine to the happie end that vve desier vvherof hauing found this litle Treatise of <hi>A Spiritual Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,</hi> assuringe my selfe that it vvould be a thinge very agreable to al maner of deuout and pious persons, I thought good to bring the same to light. Beseechinge
<pb facs="5"/>the gentle Reader to accept of this litle guift, and to respect more my hartie affection, then the littlenes of the thinge. The rest I remitt to the disposition of Almightie god the Creator of al thinges, vvhose only honnor and gloire I desier herein, Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy hartie vvel-vviller in Christ Iesus R. H.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>