<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull M. ROBERT MORDAVNT of Massingham Hall, in the County of Norsolke, Esquire, and Mistris AMY MORDAVNT, his mostlouing Bedfellow: All increase of Grace in this life, and of glory in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Greenwood, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115797_Fr4_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02186</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12329</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115797</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull M. ROBERT MORDAVNT of Massingham Hall, in the County of Norsolke, Esquire, and Mistris AMY MORDAVNT, his mostlouing Bedfellow: All increase of Grace in this life, and of glory in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Greenwood, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Greenvvoods vvorkes : contayned in fiue seueral tractates. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. of the Day of iudgement. Lords Prayer. Race to saluation. Torment of Tophet. Baptisme of Christ</title>
                 <author>Greenwood, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bell, Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Clarke, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 117, 1, 6, 92, 12, 8, 82, 6, 10, 43, 11 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="181"/>
   <pb facs="181"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull M. ROBERT MORDAVNT of <hi>Massingham</hi> Hall, <hi>in the County of</hi> Norsolke, <hi>Esquire, and</hi> Mistris AMY MORDAVNT, his mostlouing Bedfellow: <hi>All increase of Grace in this life, and of glory in the life to come.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eldome or neuer (Right Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) doe we finde Tractates, either Humane, or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, passe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their particular Dedications, that being shrowded vnder the safe-garding gourds of honorable and right godly dispositions, they might the better bee preserued
<pb facs="182"/>
from the parching detractions of malignant <hi>Cynicks:</hi> I make bolde therefore (discarding all selfe-hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and irregular singularity) to commend this poore <hi>Present, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strum ad patrocinium,</hi> to the worthy patronage of your well-affected Worships, two especiall reasons mouing me hereunto. First, that mine vnfained gratitude, entire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and most humble duty for all your fauors inexpressible, might heereby bee made apparent: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it being deliuered at that solemne baptisme of <hi>Charles</hi> your first born and hopefull heyre, none I know more worthy of this <hi>Dica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> than your worthy and right Christian persons.</p>
   <p>I present it to your religious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations, as a louing and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>New-yeeres gift:</hi> for it aymes at that blessed <hi>New birth,</hi> and happy
<pb facs="182"/>
      <hi>New life,</hi> liuely in baptisme repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented, without which it is not pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible for either of you to possesse the Kingdome of God.</p>
   <p>Accept therefore (I humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech you) and take in good worth this short Treatise; short both in line and learning: respect not (as is that <hi>Prouerbe</hi>) the measure of the gift, but the minde of the giuer, what is wanting in the one (I dare boldly promise) is made vp in the other.</p>
   <p>At your best leisures vouchsafe, I pray, now and then to peruse it, and I trust that your Christian paines herein shall bee well reguer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den'd with heauenly pleasures here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from.</p>
   <p>The Lord God make this (with all other like Christian helps) much profitable to your soules, and as he hath abundantly blessed you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>outward
<pb facs="183"/>
honors and dignities ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, he would also euen fill your heares and spirits with the inesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable riches of his al-sufficient grace: that hauing granted this two-fold blessing to you in this life, you may haue the more assured hope of a third in the life to come, which is his blessing of glory: for all which forenamed blessings, your Worships shall haue my best and most deuout prayers, continued to the Lord; to whose sweetest prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction I betake you both with your hopefull sonne this present day and euermore:</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From Hempsted in Essex, <date>Ianuary, 10. 1620.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Worships alwaies ready<lb/>
to be commanded in the LORD.<lb/>
         <hi>Henry Greenwood.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>