<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>R., E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115794_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10650</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20927</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115794</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>R., E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An explication of the hundreth and tenth Psalme : wherein the severall heads of Christian religion therein contained; touching the exaltation of Christ, the scepter of his kingdome, the character of his subjects, his priesthood, victories, sufferings, and resurrection, ar largely explained and applied. Being the substance of severall sermons preached at Lincolns Inne; by Edward Reynoldes sometimes fellow of Merton Colledge in Oxford, late preacher to the foresaid honorable society, and rector of the church of Braunston in Northhampton-shire</title>
                 <author>Reynolds, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bostock, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 301, 304-525, 5 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, when I was first perswaded to communicate some of my poore labours to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, my purpose was to have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded unto those Treatises which were extant before so much of these which I now present unto thy view, as concerneth the Elogies of the Gospell of Christ, the instrument of begetting the <hi>life of Christ in us:</hi> for little reason had I considering mine owne weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, the frequent returnes of that service wherein these pieces were delivered, and the groning of the presse of late under writings of this nature, to trouble the world a second time with any more of my slender provisions towards the worke of the Sanctuary, in this abundance which is on every side brought in. But finding that worke grow up under mine hand into a just volume, and conceiving that it might bee both more acceptable and usefull to handle a whole Scripture together (especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally being both of so noble a nature, and at first view of so difficult a sense, as this Psalme is) than to single out some verse and fragment by it selfe; I therefore resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved once more to put in my Mite into the Treasurie of the Temple, which (though for no other reason) may yet I hope be for this cause accepted, because it beareth the Image and Inscription of <hi>Christ</hi> upon it. Some passa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges therein are inserted which were delivered in another
<pb facs="4"/>
order, and on other Scriptures, and some likewise which were delivered in other places, and on other occasions; which yet being pertinent to the series of the discourse, I thought might justly seeme as naturall parts, and not as <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>▪ incoherent and unsuteable pieces. Such er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors as have escaped in the presse, and the unfitnesse of some of the <hi>Titles</hi> of the <hi>Pages</hi> (which in my farre ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence from the presse, while most of the booke was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, were ordered by others who attended upon it) I shall desire thee courteously to passe by: those greater slips which may haply perturbe the sense, I have noted together. So submitting my poore labours to thy favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Censure, and commending thee to the Blessing of God. I rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>E. R.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>