<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Courteous Reader, I pray correct with thy pen these mistakes and omissions of the Printers, ere thou read the Books, Errata and Omissions.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115279_Ba1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17298</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4140.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115279</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Courteous Reader, I pray correct with thy pen these mistakes and omissions of the Printers, ere thou read the Books, Errata and Omissions.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A divine tragedie lately acted, or A collection of sundry memorable examples of Gods judgements upon Sabbath-breakers, and other like libertines, in their unlawfull sports, happening within the realme of England, in the compass only of two yeares last past, since the booke was published : worthy to be knowne and considered of all men, especially such, who are guilty of the sinne or arch-patrons thereof</title>
                 <author>Burton, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stam, Jan Fredericksz</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 46, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <head>Courteous Reader, I pray correct with thy pen these mistakes and omissions of the Printers, ere thou read the Books, Errata and Omissions.</head>
   <p>In the Title page, l. 17. r. <hi>inchoat.</hi> l 18. r. <hi>cansummat</hi> In the Epistle, p. 2. l. 3. for with. r. <hi>as</hi> l. 15. r. <hi>hapning.</hi> p. 3. l. 4. r. <hi>so</hi> audaciously. l. 24. f. sins, r. <hi>sinewes.</hi> l. 27. f. hath, r. <hi>have.</hi> l. 31 r. <hi>In</hi> Petrus <hi>Blesensis.</hi> p 4. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. 29. r. <hi>pointes.</hi> p 5. l. 13. r. <hi>and</hi> such p. 8. l. 31. f. were as, r. <hi>as were</hi> In the examples, p. 11. Exam. 5. l. 8 were all drowned: adde this omission: <hi>as some letters report: Others say they were onely in great danger of drowning, a spring tide breaking the Ice, but with much labourwer at last saved after</hi> 2. <hi>or</hi> 3. <hi>houres space by the helpe of hotes.</hi> p. 15 l. 13. f. reare, r <hi>reare</hi> p. 28. l. 1. f. 1634 r. 1636 l. 2. r. Parish <hi>of S. Giles</hi> p. 32. l. 1. f. now, r. <hi>enough.</hi> l 6. r. Dr. <hi>H.</hi> l. 11. f. invention, r. <hi>inundation.</hi> l. 23. f. to, r. <hi>of.</hi> p. 33. l. 19. f. defining, r. <hi>defying.</hi> p. 38. l. 31. prophanesse, r. <hi>prophaners.</hi> p. 39. l 1. had, r. <hi>hath.</hi> l. 18. come, r. <hi>rowe.</hi> p. 40 l. 30. this, r. <hi>his.</hi> l. 32. none. r. <hi>any.</hi> p. 41. l. 20. r. <hi>Bochellum.</hi> p. 36, in the marg. r. <hi>Beluacensis.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>