<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, Mr. William Bull, MAYOR of the Citie of WELS, I. B. Wisheth all prospe∣ritie in this life, and eternall happinesse in the life to come.</title>
           <author>B., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115252_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00337</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1046</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115252</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, Mr. William Bull, MAYOR of the Citie of WELS, I. B. Wisheth all prospe∣ritie in this life, and eternall happinesse in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>B., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The seauen spirituall exercises of a deuout soule : Containing the life and death of our sauiour Christ: compiled in seauen meditations, replenished with most godly, and deuout motions, and seruing for the seauen dayes in the weeke</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Budge, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 114 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT <hi>WORSHIPFVLL,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>William Bull,</hi> MAYOR of the Citie of WELS, I. B. <hi>Wisheth all prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie</hi> in this life, and <hi>eternall happinesse</hi> in the life to come.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F all men are by nature and duty bound to gratifie their
<pb facs="3"/>wel-deseruing Friends, (most deare, and much respected VNCLE) then must I not ouerslip time to make requitall of your manifold kindnesses, by some slender gift, such as the zeale of my dutie, and the abilitie of my minde is able to performe. And now to make it appeare, not so much in comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as in action, I haue sent you a small Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, which (in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of some Diuines, whom I reuerence in my heart) is, for matter, of worthy respect; for me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, plaine; for practise,
<pb facs="3"/>godly; and (I hope) for the fruits of it, profitable: for what of higher re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, of more facilitie, of deeper deuotion, and of greater comfort, then the meditation of the Historie of our Sauiour CHRIST, which you see here parted into seauen dayes practise, and may be the Christians daily taske. I will say no more of it, onely vse it, peruse it, practise it: and after your charitable censure, if it may seeme worthy your patronage, claime it as your owne; your owne you may then call
<pb facs="4"/>it, for without you, it had neuer seene the Sunne, nor the Sunne it. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexe of your fauours to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me, and the vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued kindnesse of <hi>Some</hi> that are neare allyed to you (whom I onely point at,
<note place="margin">R. B. &amp;c.</note> I neede no more, as also the godly disposition of you all in matters of pietie and deuotion) haue called this light out of darknesse, and made it (that long hath wandred from the Author) like a wearyed Pilgrime to flye to you for prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
   <p>As you loue Christ,
<pb facs="4"/>so fauour it, and as you fauour godlinesse, so loue <hi>It.</hi> Make it your daily,
<note place="margin">Viz. <hi>This Booke.</hi>
      </note> though not your whole, taske: and resolue of this, that Christ cals men, as well to Mount Tabor by diuine Meditation, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire his goodnesse and glory; as <hi>Caesar</hi> cals them to beare the Sword, for the defence and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of authoritie.</p>
   <p>Thus crauing your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable acceptance of this poore mite, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking the patronage of the same, I wish you all health and happinesse. Leauing this to you, with
<pb facs="5"/>the remembrance of my humble dutie.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>London,</hi> this 3. of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> 1612.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Cosen in all seruice to be commanded. <hi>I. B.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>