<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER. Wherein certaine malicious cauills, &amp; opprobrious reproaches obiected a∣against the Author by M. Collins in his Preface, are fully answered; and his notable fraud, folly, and grosse i∣gnorance, euen in Grammer is dis∣couered.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115111_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00914</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11020</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115111</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER. Wherein certaine malicious cauills, &amp; opprobrious reproaches obiected a∣against the Author by M. Collins in his Preface, are fully answered; and his notable fraud, folly, and grosse i∣gnorance, euen in Grammer is dis∣couered.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The obmutesce of F.T. to the Epphata of D. Collins. Or The reply of F.T. to D. Collins his defence of my Lord of VVinchesters answere to Cardinall Bellarmines Apology : In which reply M. Collins is conuinced of most manifest frauds, falsityes, fooleryes, &amp; lyes. Written b Thomas Fitzherbert Priest of the Society of Iesus, in defence of his adioynder impugned by M. Collins: wherein the authors name was cyphred with the two letters F.T</title>
                 <author>Fitzherbert, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>lxxx, 548, 4, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="XXIIj" facs="12"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER. Wherein certaine malicious cauills, &amp; opprobrious reproaches obiected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>against the Author by <hi>M. Collins</hi> in his Preface, are fully answered; and his notable fraud, folly, and grosse i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnorance, euen in Grammer is dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>ORASMVCH as I haue already declared in my Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle Dedicatory, the groundes and causes of this Controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sy betwixt <hi>M. Collins</hi> &amp; me, and his fraudulent man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in answering my <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynder,</hi> togeather with my whole drift, and scope
<pb n="XXIIIj" facs="13"/> in the ensuing reply, I will now gentle Readers) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to giue you satisfaction in this Preface con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning some ignominious aspersions, which he labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in his Preface to c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st vpon my reputation, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I hope to make it appeare vnto you, that <hi>Verba oris eius iniquitas &amp; dolus.</hi> Psal. <hi>35. The words of his mouth, are nothing els but i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquity and deceit:</hi> and that therefore, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>etur dolor eius in caput eius, &amp; in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticem ipsius iniquitas eius descendet.</hi> Psal. <hi>7.</hi> His sorrow shalbe turned vpon his head, and his i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquity shall descend vpon his owne crowne. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse my meaning is not to trouble you, or my selfe with the answer of many trifling obiectiōs, maleuolous cauils or s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>urrilous scoffs which occur euery where in him in such abound<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nce, that if I should but take knowledge of them this Preface would grow to a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume) but my intention is to say somewhat briefl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to those points only, which may seeme most to import, and being most vrged &amp; ampl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>fied by him, may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d some scruple, or doubt in the Reader.</p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1.</hi> Therefore wheras he insinuateth, that he could touch me if he list, with personall vices, I will let it passe as an idle vaunt of an idle brayne, seeing that I fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d in diuers parts of his worthles worke, that he knoweth not as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>et the condition, and quality of my person. For albeit he sayth truly of me, that I am a <hi>Iesuite</hi> (as I am indeed, I humbly prayse God for it) yet he holdeth me for a <hi>lay,</hi> and a <hi>marryed</hi>
      <pb n="XXV" facs="13"/> Iesuit, shewing his ignorance as well of my present <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>state (who haue beene vnmaryed, and a Priest these <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>wenty yeares) as also of the custome of the Catholik <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hurch, which doth not admit to Priesthood any that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re marryed, and liue with their wiues: so as I see <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ot what he can truly vnderstand of my more priuate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd secret demeanour, when he so much mistaketh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y publique profession and quality, wherof no man is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>gnorant that knoweth me. Therefore for as much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s he promiseth his Reader to giue him a tast of my <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>onditions,</hi> and <hi>spirit,</hi> out of myne owne wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ngs, and especially out of my <hi>Adioynder,</hi> by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iscouery of foure speciall thinges, which he sayth he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ath obserued therein, (to wit, my <hi>vanity,</hi> my <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ulency,</hi> my <hi>ignorance,</hi> &amp; my <hi>circumstance</hi>) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> will examine how well he hath performed his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ise; and I doubt not but you will find, that he hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ot only fayled in all, but also foyled himselfe nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly, discouering in himselfe both great fraud, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rosse folly.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2.</hi> First then for my <hi>Vanity,</hi> he sayth in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>urth page of his Preface thus: <hi>It is worth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>onsidering how euery where he coupleth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>imselfe with the Cardinall, and somety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>es iets before him, sometymes behind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>im, like the fantasticke wooer that</hi> Ouid <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>escribes,</hi> &amp; modò praecedit, sequitur modò. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hus sayth <hi>M. Collins.</hi> And why forsooth? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ary because I say in my Adioynder pag. <hi>68. Places
<pb n="XXVj" facs="14"/> alleadged by the Cardinall, and my selfe.</hi> And againe, pag. <hi>38. The law</hi> Inter Clara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>alleadged both by the Cardinall, and me.</hi> And againe pag. <hi>356. Twelue Fathers allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the Cardinall and me, and the like in diuers other places:</hi> but most ridiculous sayth M. <hi>Collins,</hi> where I go before the Cardinall, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> when I say: <hi>Obiected as wel by me, as by the Cardinall.</hi> And againe in another place, <hi>The Bishops answere to</hi> S. Cyprian, <hi>makes as much against me, as against the Cardinall.</hi> All which M. Collins taketh to be <hi>feathers of my frantique ambition, scattered euery where throughout my worke.</hi> VVherto he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so addeth the frequent mention, which I make of my <hi>Supplement,</hi> because I say many tymes, <hi>As I haue noted, &amp; shewed in my Supplement: A quality,</hi> sayth M. Collins, <hi>somewhat vnu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suall amongst Writers that are not starcke madd, to beate vpon their owne, especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly so often.</hi> So he, with a great deale of other idle stuffe, and bitter taunts touching both these points, which I omit as well for breuityes sake, as because his booke, I am sure, is so common amongst you, that I need not to be ouer tedious in laying downe his text.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3.</hi> Now then heere you see, what he sayth of my <hi>Vanity,</hi> and how well he proueth his imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof; wherein he beginneth to play his prize,
<pb n="XXVIj" facs="14"/> that is to say, to practise that kind of fraud, which he continueth for the most part throughout his whole worke, I meane his dissimulation of my text, and of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he circumstances of the matter in question betwixt vs, by which meanes he doth charge me with what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he list, without feare to be controuled by any that hath not my <hi>Adioynder,</hi> to confront with his answere, as you shall now euidently see in this, whereby you may the better iudge of the rest.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <hi>4.</hi> Therefore to discouer his cozenage in this point, you are to vnderstand the cause, why I do so of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten speake as well of the Cardinall, and my selfe, as also of my Supplement. This doth appeare sufficiently in the very title of my booke, which is this: <hi>An Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynder to the Supplement of F. Rob. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons his discussion of M. D. Barlowes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere &amp;c. conteyning a discouery, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of very many foule absurdityes, falsityes, and lyes in M. D. Andrewes his latin booke intituled: Responsio ad Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiam Cardinalis Bellarmini &amp;c.</hi> Thus did the Printer set downe my tytle, and added further that the sayd <hi>Adioynder</hi> was <hi>written by F.T. author of the Supplēent, to iustify certaine places, and authorityes alleadged as wel by him, as by the Cardinall in his Apology, and pretended to be answered by M. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="5">
      <hi>5.</hi> VVho now is he, that seeth this, and doth
<pb n="XXVIIj" facs="15"/> not euidently see withall, what reason I had to make mention of my selfe many tymes togeather with the Cardinall, seeing that the speciall scope of my adioyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der was to confute the Answeres of my Lord of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chester</hi> to certain places, first alleadged by the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall, and cyted after by me, in my <hi>Supplement,</hi> so as my intention was to answere for vs both, for so much as concerneth those authorityes or arguments, which were common to vs both. And this I say was euident inough by the very title of my <hi>Adioynder.</hi> Besides that, I also declared the same expresly &amp; am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply in the very first chapter thereof, wherin I signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, that when I had well neer ended my <hi>Supple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt,</hi> I chaunced to haue a sight of my Lord of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chesters</hi> answere to Cardinall <hi>Bellarmines A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> and found therein that his Lordship pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended now and then to answere some places, autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rityes, and arguments which had been obiected by me to <hi>M. Barlow</hi> in my <hi>Supplement,</hi> and that therefore fearing, that if I did not confute the sayd answeres of my Lord of <hi>Winchester, M. Barlow</hi> might either blame me for not taking notice thereof or perhaps make vse thereof himself, I resolued to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine and confute them.</p>
   <p n="6">
      <hi>6.</hi> As for as much as my meaning was not to answere my Lords whole worke, or any part thereof further then those places, authorityes, or arguments should giue iust occasion; I signifyed diuers tymes, that the place which I handled was cyted, not only by
<pb n="XXIX" facs="15"/> me, but also by the Cardinall, to the end it might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eare, that I kept my selfe still within my compasse, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd did not extend further then to those authorityes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r arguments, which as I haue sayd were common to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s both, or had dependance thereon, and contayned withall some notable fraud, or falsity. This then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ng my only drift, and intention in my <hi>Adioynder,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>an any man with reason blame me, or ascribe it to <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>anity,</hi> that I mentioned my selfe now and then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ogeather with the Cardinall, hauing vndertaken to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nswere for vs both.</p>
   <p n="7">
      <hi>7.</hi> The like I say also for the mention I make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>therwhiles of my <hi>Supplement,</hi> as that hauing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eated therein diuers thinges at large, which occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed afterwards to be touched in my <hi>Adioynder,</hi> and might haue requyred some large discourse, if I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ad not handled it before) I referred the Reader of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y <hi>Adioynder</hi> to my <hi>Supplement</hi> for those <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>atters already handled therin, to auoyd the need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>sse repetition thereof; besides that it appeareth eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ently by the Printers Epistle, to the Reader, that my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>tention was to haue had the <hi>Supplement,</hi> &amp; the <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>dioynder</hi> bound both in one volume, albeit the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rinter altered my designe because it seemed to him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>at the volume would be ouer great: so as my inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>n being considered, it may easily be conceaued how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>perfluous, and ridiculous it would haue beene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> haue repeated in my <hi>Adioynder</hi> those thinges, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hich I made account might be easily seene in my
<pb n="XXX" facs="16"/>
      <hi>Supplement,</hi> euen in the same Volume.</p>
   <p n="8">
      <hi>8.</hi> Now therefore iudge, good Reader, what <hi>Vanity</hi> it was in me to me make mention of my <hi>Supplement,</hi> as often as I had iust occasion to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my Reader thereto for his better satisfaction, concerning those points, which I had already treated more amply therein. And consider I pray you withal both <hi>M. Collins</hi> his folly, and his fraud: his folly in that he picketh such an impertinēt, &amp; foolish quarrel against me without any ground, or cause giuen o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> my part, his fraud in that he abuseth both me, and his Reader, in dissembling all that in my <hi>Adioyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> which sufficeth to cleare me of the imputation, wherewith he chargeth me. Thus much for the first point.</p>
   <p n="9">
      <hi>9.</hi> The second is my <hi>Virulency,</hi> as he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it, because I speake sometymes sharply to my Lord of <hi>Winchester,</hi> retorting vpon him many cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelious speaches, which he vsed not only against Catholiques in generall, but also particulerly against Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> calling him <hi>lyar,</hi> and <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tard,</hi> and against all Popes (tearming them <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christs</hi>) yea against <hi>S. Peter</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>imselfe, whome he blasphemously called <hi>caput morbidum,</hi> and <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>cem ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>è sanum</hi>) besides the notorious calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es and vntruths which he inuented, and vttered a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainst t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e <hi>Iesuit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>;</hi> all which I must needes confesse moued me other whyles to some asperity of speach, to make him see how true it is which the Comicall Poet
<pb n="XXXj" facs="16"/> sayth, <hi>Qui dicit quod volt, audiet quod non volt.</hi> But whatsoeuer passed in that kind in my <hi>Adioynder,</hi> I hope his Lorship cannot take any iust offēce at my manner of treating him in this my reply, wherein you shall find, that I beare all due respect to his Lordship otherwise thē I did in my <hi>Adioynder,</hi> the reason whereof I thinke good to yeild you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I make no doubt, but that you of your selues, will note the difference, and perhaps desire to know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he cause.</p>
   <p n="10">
      <hi>10.</hi> The truth is, that when I wrote my <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>oynder,</hi> I did not know in his Lorship any true title <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f Honour, or Dignity, Ecclesiasticall or Temporall, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hich might mooue me to esteeme or respect him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>herwayes then as a priuate person; for albeit he was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hen called Bishop of <hi>Ely,</hi> yet I could not (according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o our Catholike doctrine) acknowledge either that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>itle, or any Episcopall authority in him, being no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>her, but a meere lay man, and consequently voyd of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ll Ecclesiasticall function, and dignity, in which res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ect I gaue him no better title thē of <hi>M. Andrews:</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ut seeing he is now aduanced to the state of a priuy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ounsellour to his Maiesty, I do most willingly yeild <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>im the respect, and honour due to his place and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ty; and therefore do not only forbeare all vnreue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ent manner of speach, but also treate him with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>onourable stile of Lordship, as one of the Lords of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>as Maiesty most Honourable priuy Counsell. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hereas I call him also my Lord of <hi>Winchester,</hi> I
<pb n="XXXIj" facs="17"/> wish it to be vnderstood, that I do not acknowledg hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> therby to be a Bishop (for the reason before declared but that I do it, because I will not deny to any Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellour of his Maiesty any Honorable stile, or ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> which is commonly giuen him, so as it may be vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stood to be abstracted from all spirituall power an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> authority, as I conceaue this may be, and therefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> I do so intend it: And this I say, notwithstandin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>M. Masons</hi> pretended Register, whereby he labou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth to iustify the consecration of the first pretende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Bishops in Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> tyme; which hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> been so fully answered by our learned countryman <hi>M. D. Champney,</hi> that there remayneth no furthe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> doubt, or scruple concerning that matter.</p>
   <p n="11">
      <hi>11.</hi> And now to returne to <hi>M. Collins,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> doubt not but that considering how much he mistike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th and how seuerely he reprehendeth the <hi>vitulency</hi> which he would haue you conceaue in me, you cann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> but imagine, that he is eyther a very mirrour of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty, or at least void of all malice, and virulency, or els you must needes hould him for a very soole, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> blame that in other men, wherein he is faulty him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe; for <hi>turpe est doctori</hi> &amp;c. But truly he is so far from moderation in that kind, that he surpasseth all that euer I haue read, for rayling, and scoulding more like a curst Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eane, then a graue Doctor wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the chie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e chaire in the Noble Vniuersity of <hi>Cambridge.</hi> This may appeare by the most viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent &amp; exorbitant inuectiues which he maketh euery
<pb n="XXXIIj" facs="17"/> where against the <hi>Iesuits,</hi> &amp; by the names which he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uenteth for me, not contenting himselfe to call me <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sse, gull, foole, noddy, wretch,</hi> and such like, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ut also <hi>false Theefe, Rustique, arrant Clowne, Dogge, Mastiue, Curr, Lither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ellow, Hobby-horse, Rakeshame,</hi> &amp; <hi>Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>erly fellow,</hi> without any other occasion, then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ause he cannot tell how to answere me otherwise, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ut only by bragging, boasting, and rayling vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e, as if I had committed some not able errour, or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>urdity, when he either dissembleth, or els corrupteth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>y text in such sort, that he maketh me say what he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>st, and then triumpheth vpon his owne fraud, as if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he sault were myne; wherof you shall see many most <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uident examples in this my Reply. But as for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>roachfull, and reuyling speaches, I little regard thē, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nowing from what spirit they proceed, I meane a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>irit that rather deserueth to be coniured with an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>xorcisme (such as our Sauiour vsed to the tatling Diuell, when he sayd, <hi>Obmutesce, &amp; exi de ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ine,</hi> Marc. <hi>1.</hi>) then to be answered in writing; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd therfore it is no more wonder to heare him raile, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd rage, then to heare a goose hisse, or a dogge barke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r to see a serpent spit his poyson, or any other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ure to do according to his kind. And thus much for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he second poynt.</p>
   <p n="12">
      <hi>12.</hi> The third is my <hi>Ignorance</hi> (forsooth) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n the latin tongue, for he is <hi>loath,</hi> as he sayth, <hi>to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>earch my more hidden schollership,</hi> and yet
<pb n="XXXIIIj" facs="18"/> there was no remedy but that he must needs first h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> a fling at my greeke (though by the way of a Paren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thesis only) taxing me for the word <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, as a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> for <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>accepit genua,</hi> and for <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>qualis;</hi> but as for the first, to wit, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> I cyted out of <hi>Homer,</hi> it was an euident errour i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the print, easily committed in the change of the ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> letters ς and φ, into ι and ψ, so as the word should b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. And I doubt not but that the indiffere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> Reader will easily conceaue, that this may well ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> happened without any fault of myne, if he conside<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> that my <hi>Adioynder</hi> was printed many hundred of miles from me; whereas <hi>M. Collins</hi> his booke, being printed vnder his owne nose, is so full of faulte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> escaped in the print, that he hath corrected in a table for that purpose very neere <hi>60.</hi> besides many more, which may be noted, and are not corrected. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> whereas some of those which are there set downe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> in Latin, some in Greeke, and some in English. I thinke he would hold me to be very impertinent, if I should taxe him with ignorance in any of the three tongues for any of those errours, though they were not corrected. But as for <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, sure I am that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> wordes are so in <hi>Homer, Iliad. 1.</hi> and therefore I cannot ghesse what he blameth therein, except per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps he be himself so ignorant, as to say, that is should be <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, not knowing that the Poets doe cast away the augment, when occasion requires. And if the Latin translation doth displease him, and that
<pb n="XXXV" facs="18"/> perhaps he would say, <hi>praehendit genua,</hi> and not <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ccepit genua,</hi> I graunt indeed that it might be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ayd so more elegantly, but seeing that <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ommonly signify <hi>accipere,</hi> it seemed to me sufficient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o giue the more litterall, and common signification <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f the greeke word, and not to hunt after elegancy. Lastly whereas he carpeth at <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, or <hi>aequalis,</hi> say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ng also that Father <hi>Eudaemon Ioannes</hi> tript at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he same stone, I know not what fault he findeth ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>her in the greek or in the Latin; for if he should deny <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hat <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, or yet <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>; doth signify <hi>aequalis,</hi> he should <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e too to ignorant, and absurd; and sure I am, that he will not deny it, but will haue it to signisy so; &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ore I wonder why he sayth, that it is the stone wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at we tripped, seeing that neither of vs deny it, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit we do indeed both say that it doth signify also <hi>si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milis,</hi> like. And if that be the <hi>petra scandali</hi> wherat we stumbled, why doth he not confute it, or at least make some mention of it? For all that he sayth concerning my ignorance in this point, is this: <hi>Also,</hi> sayth he, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> for <hi>aequalis</hi> pag. <hi>44. the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry same stone that his reuerent Father tript at before.</hi> So he, wherin you see, he speaketh not a word of <hi>similis.</hi> but only of <hi>aequalis,</hi> which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthelesse both my Lord of <hi>Winchester,</hi> and he himself do take to be the true signification of <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, and therefore they vrge against vs the wordes <hi>aequalia priuilegia,</hi> in the latin translation of the Councell of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> where the Greeke is <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>,
<pb n="XXVj" facs="19"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="XXVIj" facs="19"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="XXVIIj" facs="20"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="XXIX" facs="20"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="XXX" facs="21"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="XXXj" facs="21"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="XXXIj" facs="22"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="XXXIIj" facs="22"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="XXXIIIj" facs="23"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="XXXV" facs="23"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="XXXVj" facs="24"/> so as you way marueile with me, what the man mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth heere; and note also how substantially he proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth my ignorance in the Greeke: therefore now l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> vs see what he sayth to my Latin.</p>
   <p n="13">
      <hi>13.</hi>
      <q>First, sayth he <hi>pag. 40. cap. 2. num. 3.</hi> because the Bishop had sayd, <hi>legat canone mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stum, ne maiora sed aequalia sint priuilegia, &amp;c.</hi> He thus: <hi>whereas he sayes that the Coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of</hi> Chalcedon <hi>did by that Canō giue to the Bi hop of Constantinople</hi> ne maiora sed aequ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alia priuilegia <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which though it be the reseruing of the word <hi>ne</hi> in both places, yet euery meane Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nist easily sees that <hi>ne</hi> should haue beene turned into <hi>non</hi> in the later place, if he meane any <hi>sense</hi> should be in his sentence, as he began it, and therefore I ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> impute it to nothing but to his lacke of skill in the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments.</q> Thus sayth <hi>M. Collins,</hi> wherin I beseech you to note, that he himselfe acknowledgeth that in my allegation of my Lords words, I preserue the word <hi>ne,</hi> euen as my Lord hath it, thogh he sayth it should haue beene turned into <hi>non</hi> to make it good Latin is the later place where I repeate it; which obiection of his would haue beene of little force if he had not frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulently ended his allegation of my text with an <hi>&amp;c.</hi> insteed of setting downe my translation of my Lords words which immediatly followed. For hauing sayd (as you haue seene heere alleadged by him) <hi>That the Councell of</hi> Chalcedon <hi>did giue to the Bishop of</hi> Constantinople, <hi>ne maiora sed aequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia
<pb n="XXXVIj" facs="24"/> per omnia priuilegia,</hi> I translated those la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>n words thus, <hi>not greater but equall priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>dges in all thinges,</hi> wherby you may euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> see, that I tooke <hi>ne</hi> for <hi>non,</hi> translating <hi>ne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ra,</hi> not grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er though I was scrupulous to repeat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>y Lords words otherwayes then I found thē in him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd therefore I preserued the word <hi>ne</hi> in both places, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ecause my Lord hath <hi>ne</hi> &amp; not <hi>non;</hi> for I know not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ny such r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>le of construction, or congruity to be obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed, betwixt Latin, and English, as might bind me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> alter his Latin word, when I meant to giue the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ue sense of it, as you see I did in translating it, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> I haue sayd <hi>M. Collins</hi> dissembled, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ealed, least it might help to discouer the vanity of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>euill; and therefore wheras he sayth, that <hi>ne</hi> should <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aue beene turned into <hi>non</hi> in the Latin to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ue sense in my sentence, I remit it to thy iudgment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ood Reader whether taking the Latin togeat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ith my translation (which he concealed) the sense be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ot both true, and cleare in my sentence, and his solly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd fraud notorious in this his first instance; so as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ow I may passe to the second, which you shall see to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e more friuolous, and foolish then the former.</p>
   <p n="14">
      <hi>14.</hi> He alleadgeth the words of my <hi>Adioyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>er</hi> out of my second Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ter nu. <hi>6.</hi> pag. <hi>42.</hi> where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> say thus: <hi>It is sayd expresly of the Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>f</hi> Constantinople <hi>that it should be magnifyed &amp; extolled as old</hi> Rome <hi>was, secundam post <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>llam existentem.</hi> Thus sayd I, which he lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="XXXVIIj" facs="25"/> downe, and then proceedeeh in these wordes: <q>This is the letter I graunt, in the Councel of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> but almost killing Priscian, as he sets it downe, for <hi>secunda post illam existens,</hi> the Church of <hi>Constantinople</hi> (to which that refers) being <hi>Ecclesia,</hi> and not <hi>Ecclesiam,</hi> in his period, &amp; so to be translated if it were to be put in Latin.</q> So he. Graunting as you see, that I lay downe truly the Latin words (to wit <hi>secundā post illam existentem</hi>) as they are in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> albeit being referred to the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish which goeth before, they do not, as he supposeth, make good construction with it, and so do almost kill <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>scian.</hi> But this is much like vnto the former, for wheras I had a little before alleadged the whole Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of the Councell in English &amp; concluded the same with those wordes in Latin (which were the very words of the Councell, and most to be noted for the matter then in controuersy) I had occasion a little after to vrge the same words, and repeated them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in such sort, as <hi>M. Collins</hi> hath noted, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slating them immediatly thus, <hi>being the second after her,</hi> which translation being also concealed by <hi>M. Collins,</hi> as the former was, agreeth both with the Latin, which I alleadged, and with the English which went before, and made the sense perfect; so as all the incongruity which <hi>M. Collins</hi> doth ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine in my wordes, is betwixt the Latin and the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish; and therefore to make good this his conceit of
<pb n="XXXIX" facs="25"/> errour and ignorance in me, he must frame some new Grammer with rules, and precepts ordayning a new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> nd of cōstruction (neuer yet heard of) to be obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>d betwixt two diuers languages, whereof indeed I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cknowledge my selfe to be ignorant.</p>
   <p n="15">
      <hi>15.</hi> But what will you say, if he himselfe do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ustify me in this, and eyther defend me against him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>elfe, or els condemne himselfe of ignorance aswell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s me? will you not take him for a very wise, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>onsider at doctor? In the <hi>4.</hi> chapter of my Adionder, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> alleadged a place of <hi>Optatus,</hi> beginning thus; <hi>Legimus principem nostrum &amp;c. we read <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hat Peter our Prynce receaued the whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ome keys against the gates of hell</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>M. Collins</hi> comming to answer this place in his <hi>4.</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hapter. nu. <hi>27.</hi> saith thus. Yet in the same booke <hi>Optatus calles Siricius in playne tearmes not</hi> princeps noster, but socius noster, our fryend, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd fellow. Thus sayth <hi>M. Collins,</hi> and now I may say to him, as you heard him say to me a little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>efore, <hi>(mutatis mutandis) this is the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>er I grant in Optatus, but almost killing Priscian, as he sets it downe;</hi> for as <hi>M. Collins</hi> exacteth of me a Grāmaticall constructiō betwixt the latyn and the English in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e former sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, so may I also, <hi>eodem iure,</hi> exact the same of him here betwixt the verbe <hi>call,</hi> and the nownes <hi>princeps,</hi> and <hi>socius,</hi> which should therefore be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n the accusatiue case; but if he say, that <hi>princeps,</hi>
      <pb n="XL" facs="26"/> and <hi>socius,</hi> in him, must be the nominatiue case <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> agree with <hi>Siricius</hi> (because he saith, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> calls <hi>Siricius</hi> not <hi>princeps,</hi> but <hi>socius noster</hi> &amp;c.) I say that <hi>Siricius</hi> being a proper name, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> English aswell as latyn, and therfore may passe s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in all cases, without variation, what English wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> soeuer doth gouerne it: but <hi>Princeps,</hi> and <hi>socius,</hi> being pure latin wordes must according to <hi>M. Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins</hi> his new grammar haue a latyn construction, &amp; therefore being gouerned by the verbe <hi>call,</hi> they must be in the accusatiue case. And if he wil haue <hi>Sirici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> in that sentence to be a pure latyn word, and not english, then he should haue said by his own rule, that <hi>Optatus called Siricium,</hi> and not <hi>Syrici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> so as let <hi>Syricius</hi> be what language he will (I meane English or latin) he should haue sayd of him, that <hi>Optatus</hi> called him, not <hi>principem nostrum,</hi> but <hi>socium nostrum.</hi> Doe you see now how the poore man is ouer taken here? for eyther he must cleare me of the ignorance, which he impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to me, or els he must condemne himself as much as me, in so much that the wordes of the Apostle, Rom. <hi>2.</hi> may be iustly applyed vnto him, <hi>in quo iudicas alterum, te ipsum condemnas; eadē enim agis quae iudicas.</hi> Thou cōdemnest thy self in that wherein thou iudgest another, for thou doest the same thinges which thou iudgest; thus much for the second poynt.</p>
   <p n="16">
      <hi>16. Thirdly he obiecteth my translation of these
<pb n="XLj" facs="26"/> words of</hi> S. Aug. pag. 149. componit salutem mem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rorum in capite, <hi>which I englished thus;</hi> he compounded the health of the members in the head, <hi>and in this translation, he taketh exception to the word</hi> compounded, <hi>because</hi>
      <q>compounding of health, <hi>saith he,</hi> is a phrase scarse fit to be vsed by Apothecaryes, or theyr boyes, much lesse by Phisitians, but least of all by him that would seeme to know the latyn, and to english S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin.</q> So he. VVhereto I answere, that whereas he vndertooke to shew my ignorance in the latyn tongue, the fault which he findeth here is only in my English, so as the question is, whether <hi>to compound health,</hi> be a good english phrase? the truth is, that I vsed the word <hi>compound,</hi> because it is a true english word (though deriued of the latin) and doth signify the same that <hi>compono</hi> doth in latyn; and forasmuch as the very latyn phrase of <hi>componere salutem,</hi> is somewhat strange, and that there did not occurre vnto me any other proper english word to explicate the same, I thought it better to translate it so, according to the very letter (which I alwayes do as neere as I can) then to vse circumlocutions, and multiplicity of wordes, when it may be auoided; and truly it were no great maruell, nor would giue (as I hope) any great scandall to my reader, if hauing been out of my country aboue <hi>40.</hi> yeares, I should ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther want now and then a proper english word, or
<pb n="XLIj" facs="27"/> erre in some English phrase, considering the grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> mutation, and change of the English tongue synce I came thence, which in deed I haue noted to be such in those few English bookes which I haue seen, that I do not sometymes well vnderstand them; and none that I haue read do seeme to me so extrauagant for strange, and new fangled wordes and phrases as <hi>M. Col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ins;</hi> as for example, when he sayth heer a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle after, that the translatours Latin is not afrayd of a <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ar nycer teste;</hi> also pag. <hi>260. thats the blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</hi> Likewise pag. <hi>307, reliquations,</hi> pag. <hi>365. circumgestation,</hi> pag. <hi>395. inerrable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> pag. <hi>273. to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>renlace,</hi> pag. <hi>156. Cicero Rhetoricates of Pompey,</hi> pag. <hi>266. hypercri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall:</hi> and in his epistle to his Maiesty, <hi>intimity, and personating another,</hi> in the abstracts of his second part num. <hi>4. mistakes of memory not sonticall.</hi> And finally to omit many other, whereas I do once in my <hi>Adioynder</hi> vse the word <hi>cult</hi> pag. <hi>388.</hi> (saying that <hi>Vigilantius tooke adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for a diuine cult, and worship</hi>) he sayth pag. <hi>371.</hi> that I am so <hi>cult, and so quilted in my tearmes &amp;c.</hi> where you see, that <hi>cult,</hi> as I vse it, is so fully explicated, with the word <hi>worship</hi> and the circumstances, that no man can doubt of the sense therof; wheras his <hi>cult,</hi> and his <hi>quilted</hi> are so obscure, that for my part, I know not what he mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth thereby: and sure I am, that the other wordes also aboue mentioned, would not haue passed for
<pb n="XLIIj" facs="27"/> good English in my tyme, howsoeuer they do now, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hich I leaue, <hi>good Reader,</hi> to thy iudgment. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>is shall suffice for his third instance.</p>
   <p n="17">
      <hi>17.</hi> His fourth is, that I haue marred my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>rd of <hi>Winchesters latin with my addle cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uptions,</hi> because I alleadged my Lords wordes: <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>oncludit testes suos Augustino,</hi> with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of <hi>cum,</hi> which my Lord hath not; &amp; againe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hat I alleadge <hi>scrutabitur Hierusalem cum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ucernis.</hi> Sophon. <hi>1.</hi> for <hi>in lucernis, either ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the scripture,</hi> sayth he, <hi>or correcting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>he ould translators latin, or both,</hi> wherof he counteth the one <hi>impious,</hi> and the other <hi>ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous;</hi> of all which he hath no other ground, but his owne malice. For although I alleadged my Lords words, and the text of Scripture, so as he sayth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I trusted to my memory, yet it is euident, that there is no corruption, nor any kind of fraud therein, nor change of the sense, or meaning, seeing that in any allegation of my Lords wordes, <hi>cum</hi> is but onely superfluous, and altereth nothing of the sense; neither doth it marre my Lords latin in such sort, as to make it either false, or barbarous; for albeit I graunt, that it may well be sayd, as my Lord hath it, <hi>concludit testes suos Augustino,</hi> yet <hi>cum Augustino,</hi> is much more common, and no way to be reprehended: and whereas I haue <hi>cum lucernis,</hi> in the other text, for <hi>in lucernis,</hi> it is euident, that I keep the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> sense, as it may appeare by the Greeke text of the
<pb n="XLIIIj" facs="28"/>
      <hi>Septuaginta,</hi> which hath <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>cum lucer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi> Therefore this would not haue seemed to <hi>M. Collins</hi> any great matter, if he were not toot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> malicious, or were but halfe as sauourable to me, as he would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eeme to be to S. <hi>Augustine,</hi> whome be excuseth in like case, <hi>pag. 133.</hi> for altering certaine words of <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi> saying: <hi>That though he altered the wordes (as is soone done</hi> (sayth he) <hi>in allegations of memory) yet he keep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> the sense:</hi> so as to alter wordes in allegations of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory when the sense is kept entyre seemed to him no greater matter in <hi>S. Augustine,</hi> though he houl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the like in me, to be a heynous crime, no lesse then <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mpious,</hi> and a notable argument of my igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e: but how much he abuseth <hi>S. Augustine</hi> with what needles excuse of him, you shall see in my fifth Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pter <hi>nu. 11 12.13. &amp; 14.</hi> where I haue occasion to speake of that point.</p>
   <p n="18">
      <hi>18.</hi> But what need I alleadge his fauorable excuse of <hi>S. Augustine</hi> in this, when he is fayne to make a serious Apology for my Lord of <hi>Winchester</hi> in like manner, saying thus. <hi>pag. 266. num. 17.</hi>
      <q>The most reuerend Bishop neuer sayd of himselfe that he could not slip in matter of memory. <hi>Si sciens fallo,</hi> is his impreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>So</hi> Hieremy <hi>for</hi> Zachary <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.9. so diuers like. For what should I say of the Fathers quoting Scripture, as they often do, rather as it was in their memoryes, thē
<pb n="XLV" facs="28"/> as we read it in the text? And yet no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>est learned man, but would hould such <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>apes for very veniall I imagine.</q>
      <hi>So he, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ith more to the same purpose concerning the forsayd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>istake of</hi> S. Augustine, <hi>and</hi> Ciceros <hi>short me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ory touching quotations.</hi> But that which I wish to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e specially noted heere, that he condemneth himselfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> be no <hi>honest learned man,</hi> seeing he doth not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ould a scape of memory in me to be <hi>very veniall</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>or as he tearmeth it more finely in his table <hi>not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>onticall</hi>) but vrgeth it potently for impiety, and a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>idiculous absurdity. And yet truly he had as much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eed as any other, for ought I see, to plead for pardon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n this behalfe, for a notable mistake, and scape of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>wne memory in the very same page of his Preface within <hi>8</hi> or <hi>9.</hi> lynes after this, which he layeth to my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>harge, as it shall appeare now presently in this next <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nstance.</p>
   <p n="19">
      <hi>19.</hi> Thus then he proceedeth: <q>Repraesenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e <hi>Theodosium</hi> in liberis, is to giue the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren grace to be like their Father, but <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>raesentare defunctum,</hi> is to supply the losse of the dead, by yealding another in his roome, which S. Augustine wishes may be of the posterity.</q> So he. VVherein first I wish <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o be noted, that I do alleadge this place in my <hi>Adioynder</hi> out of S. <hi>Ambrose</hi> his funerall oratiō made at the exequyes of <hi>Theodosius</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>our, which you see <hi>M. Collins</hi> attributeth to <hi>S.
<pb n="XLVj" facs="29"/> Augustine.</hi> Now then is this <hi>sonticall,</hi> or <hi>no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> sonticall?</hi> veniall, or mortall? if it be <hi>veniall</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> him, why is the like <hi>mortall</hi> in me? if <hi>sontical<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> in me, why not <hi>sonticall</hi> in him? so as you s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> his memory is no better then other mens. Secondly t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> answer also to his obiection in this instance, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> wordes of <hi>S. Ambrose,</hi> which I alleadged are these <hi>Tu so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>us Domine inuocandus es, tu rogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, vt eum in filijs repraesentes,</hi> which I tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slated thus: <hi>Thou O Lord alone art to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocated, thou to be prayed, that thou mayst represent him in his children;</hi> and afterward in the number following, viz <hi>33.</hi> (which <hi>M. Collins</hi> quoteth) I do explicate the same, saying that <hi>S. Ambrose</hi> in those wordes, <hi>speaketh of prayer to a particuler purpose, to wit, to obtayn grace of God for the Emperours children, to make them like their father.</hi> And how doth <hi>M. Collins</hi> confute this? Marry for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sooth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he saith, that <hi>repraesentare defunctum, is to supply the losse of the dead Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius, by yealding another in his roome.</hi> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> will you see his egregious foolery? for what reason or need had <hi>S. Ambrose</hi> to pray, that the children of <hi>Theodosius</hi> might succeed him, and be in his roome, when his two sonnes <hi>Arcadius,</hi> and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norius,</hi> were already in possession of the Empyre, not only then when <hi>S. Ambrose</hi> made that oration, but also before <hi>Theodosius</hi> dyed; for <hi>Arcadius</hi>
      <pb n="XLVIj" facs="29"/> had reigned togeather with him ten yeares, and <hi>Honorius</hi> two yeares; who also (I meane <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norius</hi>) was present at this funerall oration (as it appeareth therin,) <hi>Arcadius</hi> being gone, presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly vpon his fathers death, into the east partes, which were assigned, and allotted to him for his gouerment; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ow then is it likely that <hi>S. Ambrose</hi> would pray <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o God for that which was already performed long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>efore, and then in vre? I meane that his roome might be supplyed by some of his posterity? what the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ould he meane by praying God to represent <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>osius</hi> in his children, but only to make then like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>im in wisdome, and valour, for so indeed the losse <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f him would be as fully supplyed by theyr vertue, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>is roome was already possessed by theyr personall suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ession. And yet forsooth <hi>M. Collius</hi> concludeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ainst me thus: <hi>Does not this,</hi> saith he, <hi>also <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rgue him a solid Latinist?</hi> But I may say of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>im with more reason, Doth not this argue him a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>olemne foole?</p>
   <p n="20">
      <hi>20.</hi> But what will you say if his next instance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e as wise as this? Marke well what he sayth, &amp; he will tell you so himsel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e. Semblable, <hi>saith he, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hat cap.</hi> 1. <hi>nu.</hi> 11. <hi>where thus be construes the Bishops words,</hi>
      <q>Clariùs id loquuntur Ambro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius, &amp; Augustinus, quàm vt obstrepere possint nouitij nostri: they speak it lowder or clearer, then that our nouices can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>radict it, <hi>whereas it should be,</hi> then that our
<pb n="XLVIIj" facs="30"/> nouices can drown it, <hi>for a man may contr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dict that which is neuer so clearely spoken; drown <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> or suppresse it he cannot, but because he knew not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> other sense of the word</hi> obstrepo (<hi>as in</hi> Tully <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> Marc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>llo, obstrepi videntur milirū clam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re &amp; tubarum sono) <hi>therefore he commits th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> soloecisme <hi>in translating.</hi>
      </q> Thus sayth this accur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> Grammaticall, and <hi>hipercriticall</hi> Doctour, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> you see telleth you, that this is <hi>semblable</hi> to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: &amp; truly you may wel belieue him; for he playet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the foole no lesse in this thē he did in the other. He tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth you of a great <hi>soloecisme,</hi> which he sayth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> haue committed in translating <hi>obstrepere,</hi> to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict;</hi> because I knew not of another sense it hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in <hi>Tully p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o Marcello,</hi> where it signifyeth to <hi>drowne,</hi> as a greater sound drowneth a lesse; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to make this deuise of his the more probable, he vset<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> a pretty sleight to corrupt the text of my translation; for whereas I translate my Lords wordes thus: <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brose,</hi> and <hi>Augustine do speake (or affirme) it more plainely then that ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Nouices can contradict it.</hi> He hath it in a different letter (a laying downe my wordes) <hi>that they speake it lowder or clearer thē that our Nouices ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> contradict it;</hi> Changing the word <hi>plainly</hi> into <hi>lowder</hi> &amp; <hi>clearer,</hi> to draw the matter to a soun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> that his inuention of drowning it, may seeme to hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the more ground in the sentence now in question; b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> to decyde this Grammaticall Controuersy I remit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="LIX" facs="30"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o all Dictionaryes, and to the vse of that word in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ll Authours; for although it doth most properly sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ify to make a kind of noyse or rustling; yet it inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eth an opposition, or contradiction, as when a noyse <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> made to hinder, interrupt, or contradict some bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y.</p>
   <p n="21">
      <hi>21.</hi> Therfore <hi>Calepine</hi> doth explicate it in his manner, <hi>contra aliquem strepitum facio, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>bloquor, contradico.</hi> The like we read also in <hi>Thesauro Linguae latinae.</hi> Also <hi>Nizolius,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ho professeth to giue the sense of Ciceronian words, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd to shew how <hi>Cicero</hi> vseth them, giueth no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>her <hi>Sinonymum</hi> of <hi>obstrepo,</hi> but <hi>obloquor,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hich is to speake against, or contradict; &amp; to these <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> may add our English Dictionaryes, wherof I haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>wo heere; the one set forth in <hi>Oxford</hi> by <hi>Ryder,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd the other in <hi>Cambridge</hi> by <hi>Thomas Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>masius</hi> (for I haue not <hi>Cooper</hi>) but these being la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er then he, doe by all likelyhood, either agree with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>im, or correct him, if he haue erred) and these two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re very consorme to the latin Dictionaryes before al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eadged. <hi>Ryder</hi> hath for <hi>obstiepo, to make a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>oyse, or otherwise to stir against, to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>le, interrupt, or be against.</hi> And <hi>Thomas Thomasius,</hi> hath also the very same: so as all these <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o iustify my transl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tion of <hi>obstrepere,</hi> to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ict. And as for the reasons which <hi>M. Collins</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ringeth to the contrary, they are indeed worthy of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>is profound wit, and skill in Grammer. The first is,
<pb n="L" facs="31"/>
      <hi>That a man may contradict that which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> neuer so clearely spoken; drown it, or sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse it he cannot.</hi> So he. But by his leaue when any thing is so cleare, that it cannot be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned, or gainesayd with any shew of reason, it ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> well be sayd, and is sayd commonly, that it cannot b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> contradicted, supposing that it cannot be done with reason. For as the Lawyers say, <hi>hoc possumus, quod iure possumus,</hi> we may do that, which w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> may do by right, and reason.</p>
   <p n="22">
      <hi>22.</hi> Moreouer wheras he confirmeth his idle conceit with an example out of <hi>Tully</hi> pro <hi>Marcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo</hi> (wherin <hi>obstrepi militum clamore,</hi> doth signify, as he sayth, to be drowned) he sheweth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to be a silly Grammarian; for put the case, that it should signify so there, will be therfore restrayne it alwayes to that sense: and by that example, reduce all the seuerall significations of <hi>obstrepere,</hi> to drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as if it did or could signify nothing els? Then le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> him tell me, whether it shall signify to <hi>drowne</hi> also in <hi>Cicero,</hi> when he sayth in his Epistle to <hi>Metellus vt tibi literis ostrepere non auderem,</hi> which <hi>Thomas Thomasius</hi> expoundeth <hi>to trouble with letters;</hi> but according to <hi>M. Collins, Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> durst not drowne <hi>Metellus</hi> with his Letters. Also in his third booke <hi>de Oratore,</hi> speaking of some O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratours that were so obscure by the multitude, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion of strange wordes, that they hindred and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded themselues, he sayth, <hi>ipsi sibi quodāmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do
<pb n="Lj" facs="31"/> obstrepere videntur.</hi> Shall we then say that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hose Oratours did drowne themselues? Yea, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hat will you say, if <hi>obstrepi clamore militum</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e expounded by an approued Author, to be cryed out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>gainst which is in effect to be contradicted? VVill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ot that, trow you, suffice to make good my translati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n? So doth <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>homas Thomasius</hi> expound it in his Dictionary, printed the fourth tyme in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> and therefore belike approued by the whole Vniuersity; &amp; if I should graunt him, that <hi>ostrepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e</hi> in my Lords sentēce may be translated to <hi>drown,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hat should he gayne thereby? Is it not cleare, that the same also must needs include a gaine saying, or a contradiction, as to say, that <hi>S. Ambrose,</hi> or <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> do speake it lowder then any contradiction shalbe able to drown it? Or that it cannot be drowned by any contradiction? Or by any man that shall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict, or impugne it? But now take away his forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the word <hi>lowder,</hi> which he hath foisted into my translation, insteed of <hi>more plainly,</hi> there is no appearance in the world why <hi>obstrepere</hi> should signify there to <hi>drown.</hi> And how ridiculous is he to translate <hi>clariùs, lowder?</hi> For who would say of those Fathers, that they speake or say any thing <hi>low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> when the same may be more properly expressed after the ordinary manner, by <hi>more clearely, more plainly, or more manifestly,</hi> as the word <hi>clariùs</hi> doth indeed import? So as his folly is no lesse manifest in this then his fraud. Finally if we
<pb n="LIj" facs="32"/> consider aswell the nature of the word <hi>obstrepere,</hi> as also my Lords scope, and drift in that sentence, it will<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e euident, that it is so farre from signifying to drowne by any lowd kind of contradiction, that it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther signifyeth the quite contrary, to wit, to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict by way of muttering, as to say, in effect thus: Those fathers do speake or affirme it so manifestly, that none can so much as whisper, mutter, or open his mouth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it; for no doubt my Lordes meaning was that the matter was so cleare, and manifest in <hi>S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brose,</hi> and <hi>S. Augustine,</hi> that it could not admit the least contradiction in the world: and to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose it is to be noted, that he who added the English to the other languages in <hi>Calepine,</hi> did very well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse the nature of the word <hi>obstrepere,</hi> expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it in English to <hi>hisse,</hi> or <hi>mutter against,</hi> which is farre from crying out so lowd, as to drowne any thing by force of voyce. Thus much to his sixt instance, wherby you see how good a Grammarian he is.</p>
   <p n="23">
      <hi>23.</hi> His seauenth and last, is sutable to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer for fraud, foolery, and ignorance. But to the end you may the better vnderstand the whole matter, I must first acquainte you with the occasion thereof which was this. Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> for the proofe of <hi>S. Peters</hi> supremacy ouer the Apostles, and the whole Church, alleadged a place of <hi>S. Augusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi> out of his sermons <hi>de tempore, serm. 124.</hi> in these wordes: <hi>Totius corporis morbum in ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
<pb n="LIIj" facs="32"/> capite curat Ecclesiae</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He (to wit, Christ) cureth the disease of the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in the very head of the Church, and cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>oundeth the health of all the members,</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pso vertice, <hi>that is to say, in the very crowne, or top of the head.</hi> Thus sayth <hi>S. Augustine,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lleadged by the Cardinall. To this my Lord of <hi>Winchester</hi> answered two wayes; the one reiecting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he sermon whence the place was taken, as not S. <hi>S. Augustins, because,</hi> sayth he <hi>there were no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ermons</hi> de tempore <hi>in S. Augustines tyme,</hi> whereof I proued the contrary at large in my <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynder cap. 4. num. 21. 22. &amp; 23.</hi> His other answere was, that the Cardinall had produced that testimony of <hi>S. Augustine</hi> very <hi>vnluckily,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it giueth vs notice, sayth he, of no other head but of a <hi>sickly head, nor of any other crowne of a head, but of a crazed, or crakt crowne.</hi> Thus sayd my Lord of <hi>S. Peter,</hi> &amp; then addeth fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thus: <hi>Praesertim cùm eumdem morbum in capite vestro notarint diu iam medico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum filij, etsi omnes non ego, id est, plus ego quàm omnes,</hi> that is to say, especially seeing that the Phisitians children haue now a long tyme noted the same disease in your head, althogh all not I that is to say, I more then all. Thus sayd my Lord, which seemed to me very mysticall, and so like a riddle, that I was fayne to ghesse at his meaning, and to make di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers constructions of it, touching aswell the Phisitians,
<pb n="LIIIj" facs="33"/> as their children, and specially concerning the wordes <hi>etsi omnes non ego, id est, plus ego quàm omnes,</hi> of which I sayd thus in my <hi>Adioynder pag. 153. num. 33.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="24">
      <hi>24.</hi>
      <q>But although we may ghesse, who were the Physitians, and their children, yet it will not be so easy to coniecture what he meaneth by <hi>etsi omnes non ego, id est, plus ego quàm omnes,</hi> although all not I, that is to say, I more then all for truly I haue shewed it to diuers, and haue not found two that agree in the interpretation of it; but the most probable seemeth to be the one of two; one is, that he alludeth to the wordes of <hi>S. Peter,</hi> when he sayd, <hi>etsi om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes scandalizati fuerint, sed non ego,</hi> althogh all shalbe scandalized, yet not I, who neuertheles was scandalized more then they all, because he alone deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Maister; which sense hath great difficulty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it neither hath connexion with that which go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth immediatly before, nor is truely applyable to the Pope (of whome <hi>M. Andrewes</hi> seemeth there to treate) but is only contumelions to <hi>S. Peter</hi> (being a taunting kind of exprobation of his fall) and therefore me thinkes <hi>M. Andrewes</hi> should not admit it to be his meaning, as sauouring to much of impiety. The other sense is, that it should be referred to <hi>M. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewes</hi> himselfe, and that there is some little fault in the print, I meane in the points, though not in the words, which therefore should be pointed thus, <hi>etsi omnes, non ego?</hi> And if all, not I? that is to say,
<pb n="LV" facs="33"/> of all haue noted this disease in your head, why should not I note it? Giuing to vnderstand, that he will not yeald to any of his brethren for zeale, and skill in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the faults of Popes, but rather <hi>plus ego quàm omnes,</hi> that is to say, therein will I go beyond them all; which sense hath at least some good coherence with the precedent clause, and well befitteth, <hi>M. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewes</hi> his zeale to the Ghospell, and hatred to the Pope, and so may passe for his meaning.</q>
   </p>
   <p n="25">
      <hi>25.</hi> Thus sayd I in my Adioynder, making two expositions of my Lords words: the former, as you may well perceaue, more serious then the later: neuertheles <hi>M. Collins</hi> maketh no mention of the former, but taketh hould of the later, because I deuided <hi>etsi,</hi> into <hi>et</hi> and <hi>si,</hi> and make an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue at <hi>ego?</hi> VVhereupon he sayth thus: <hi>These are the fopperyes of this great gul, &amp; you see how profound an vnderstander of the Latin he is, that he is fayn to point the Bishops wordes a new, with his senseles interrogatiues, before he can construe them or miscōster them rather, as likewise to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide them, and clip them by turning</hi> etsi <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> et, <hi>and</hi> si, <hi>but lastly to deuise a difference betweene,</hi> medici <hi>and</hi> medicorum filij, <hi>a most palpable demonstration of his vnmatcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dunsery, &amp; like the boy in the Grammer schoole, that construed</hi> pullus equinus, <hi>a horse chicken.</hi> Thus raueth <hi>M. Collins,</hi> carping at this
<pb n="LVj" facs="34"/> my construction, which any man may see I made <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronicè,</hi> and by the way of iest, to play a little vpon my Lords obscure manner of writing, wherein no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was so cleare as his blasphemy against <hi>S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> which indeed moued me to treate his Lordship with lesse respect then otherwayes I would haue don, though at that tyme I esteemed him for no better thē <hi>D. Andrewes.</hi> But <hi>M. Collins</hi> (to the end he might the better charge me not only with ignorance in vnderstanding the Latin, but also with falsity in changing the points, and in clipping, and deuiding the wordes) wholy dissembleth aswell my whole text, as my other more serious interpretation, wherof he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no mention at all, but layeth load vpon this, as if I had giuen it alone, and in good earnest: which putteth me in mind of what he sayd of me in his third Chapter pag. <hi>146.</hi> because I reproued my Lord of <hi>Winchester</hi> for saying that Card. <hi>Bellarmin</hi> did imitate or follow <hi>Iouinian,</hi> which <hi>M. Collins</hi> sayth, my Lord sayd in iest, and therefore he calleth me a <hi>Rustique,</hi> and <hi>an arrant Clowne, not discerning,</hi> sayth he, <hi>what is iest, and what is earnest.</hi> But if that be a true property of <hi>an arrant Clowne,</hi> then truly <hi>M. Collins</hi> may passe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly for one, and a kindly one, who will needes take such an euident iest (as that of myne was) for earnest and deny that of my Lordes to be earnest, which no man that reades it can take for a iest, but for a meer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aunder, as may be seene in my <hi>Adioynder cap.
<pb n="LVIj" facs="34"/> 3. num. 22. 28. &amp; sequent.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="26">
      <hi>26.</hi> Moreouer I cannot but wonder why he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>counteth it an <hi>vnmatchable Dunsery</hi> in me, to make a difference betwixt <hi>medici,</hi> and <hi>medico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum filij</hi> (because I did descant a little vpon it, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining who might be the Fathers, &amp; who the sonns) for I cannot conceaue, that either there can be a son without a Father, or an <hi>identity</hi> betwixt any Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; his sonne except in the Blessed Trinity, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in neuerthelesse there is a reall, and true distinction of persons, and much more in all creatures; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore except he can tell me of some mens sonnes (be they Phisitians or others) that are all one with their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, he may go for an <hi>vnmatchable dunse</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, to hould it for an <hi>vnmatchable dunsery</hi> in me to make a difference betwixt <hi>medici,</hi> and <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicorum filij,</hi> shewing himselfe to be as wise, as the Grammar schoole-boy, of whome he speaketh; for as the foolish boy tooke a horse colt for a horse chickē, so this silly Doctor taketh a horse and a colt for all one, and therefore if the boy had beene demaunded, what is <hi>pullus asininu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> he might haue sayd very truly, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> signifyeth <hi>M. D. Collins.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="27">
      <hi>27.</hi> But to proceed to the conclusion of this point, be censureth the relation which I make of <hi>plus ego quàm omnes,</hi> to <hi>S. Peter,</hi> as a token of my bad latin, because I do thereby vnderstand that S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> was more scandalized then all the rest of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, and consequently, that I would say in Latin,
<pb n="LVIIj" facs="35"/>
      <q>
         <hi>plus scandalizatus, which cannot passe for currant</hi> (sayth he) <hi>by the touch-stone of the more accurate Grammarians, who happily would no more say,</hi> plus scandalizatus, <hi>for more scandalized, thē</hi> plus illiteratus, <hi>for more vnlearned.</hi>
      </q> So he; not wholy condemning me (as it seemeth) of false latin, but of barbarisme at least: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles he might haue considered, if it had pleased him, that I did not vse that phrase as my owne, but ascribed it only to my Lord; and for as much as his Lordship was so mysticall, and obscure in that senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, that he was scant intelligible, I had no reason t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> thinke that he did speake so accurately then, as at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tymes, but that it might suffice, if it were true latin though perhaps none of the best. But will <hi>M. Collins</hi> maintayne it, out of his great skill in Grā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, that <hi>plus scandalizatus</hi> may not passe for currant amongst the accurate Grammarians? By whome trow you, will he be content that the matter betryed? By <hi>Poets?</hi> By <hi>Oratours?</hi> Or by both? For my part I am cōtent to remit it to either of both. For who knoweth not that <hi>plus</hi> is vsed aswell by O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratours as by Poets for <hi>magis,</hi> &amp; ioyned with verbs and participles both actiue, and passiue? <hi>Nullum adolescentem plus amo,</hi> sayth <hi>Plautus.</hi> Mer. <hi>Diligo illum plus in dies,</hi> sayth <hi>Cicero ad Atticum</hi> lib. <hi>6. Calesces plus satis,</hi> sayth <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</hi> And that it is vsed with verbes passiue, it is cleare in <hi>Cicero ad Atticum,</hi> who sayth, <hi>caue
<pb n="LIX" facs="35"/> putes plus me quemquam o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uciari.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="28">
      <hi>28.</hi> Now then I would gladly know of the <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>curate grāmarian M. Collins</hi> what difference <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he findeth for the construction, or propriety, yea or elegancy of the phrase betwixt <hi>plus cruciari,</hi> and <hi>plus scādalizari:</hi> &amp; if we may say <hi>plus cruciari,</hi> and <hi>plus scandalizari,</hi> why not <hi>plus crucia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> and <hi>plus scandalizarus.</hi> And therefore <hi>Plautus</hi> in <hi>True.</hi> made no doubt to say, <hi>plus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tromissus,</hi> for <hi>magis intromissus.</hi> D. <hi>Non ego</hi> saith he, <hi>nunc intro ad vos, mittor? A. qui dum? quam miles magis D. quia enim plus dedi.</hi> A. <hi>plus enim es intromissus cùm dabas.</hi> So he. And I doubt not but that both <hi>Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro,</hi> and <hi>Plautus,</hi> were as <hi>accurate Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> as <hi>M. Collins,</hi> and that they had <hi>the tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chstone</hi> as well as he. This then being so, I hope I may also goe for a Grammarian, notwithstanding these exceptions which <hi>M. Collins</hi> hath taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst my skill in grammar, whereby also it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, what a good grammarian, and latinist he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s, who can so litle iudge of latyn as heer you haue seene. And to the end that the same may be yet more eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, I will acquaynt you with some of his transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whereof I haue not had occasion to speake in my reply. I omit as a trifle (thought I am sure he would not let it escape in me, without an ample, &amp; a seuere censure) that he translateth <hi>sedula</hi> for <hi>dutifull.</hi> pag. <hi>111.</hi> in Pope <hi>Leo</hi>'s epistle to the
<pb n="LX" facs="36"/> Emperour <hi>Martian</hi> in these words, <hi>Et precor, &amp; sedula suggestione vos obsecro. I pray, and beseech you</hi> (sayth he) <hi>dutifully, aduising or informing,</hi> and this he translateth in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, to proue that Pope <hi>Leo</hi> did make suite to the Emperour with acknowledgment of duty; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he translated it truly before, saying, <hi>sedula suggestione,</hi> by diligent suggestion, <hi>I</hi> will not insist vpon it, but will let you see how wel he vnderstandeth a place of <hi>S. Augustine de ciuitate dei.</hi> lib. <hi>10.</hi> cap. <hi>1. S. Augustins</hi> wordes are these. <hi>Quia latinè loquendi consuetudine non solùm imperitorum, verum etiam doctissimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, &amp; cognationibus humanis, at{que} affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatibus, &amp; quibuscun{que} necessitudinibus dicitur exhibēda religio, non eo vocabulo vitatur ambiguum, cùm de cultu Deitatis vertitur quaestio.</hi> &amp;c. For asmuch as by the custome of speaking latyn, not only of the ignoranct but also of the best learned, religion is to be exhibited both to humane kindreds, and affinityes, and also to all kynd of alliance, and association (by friendship, or otherwayes) the ambiguity is not auoyded by that word when question is made of the worship of the Deity &amp;c. Thus sayth <hi>S. Augustine,</hi> giuing to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand that the latin word <hi>Religio</hi> is equiuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and ambiguous, signifying not only the worship of God, but also the obseruance, or reuerent respect due to all kind of kindreds, and alliances, and to
<pb n="LXI" facs="36"/> proue this, he alleadgeth the common vse, and custome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> speach aswell of the ignorant, and vnlearned, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the best learned, who vse the word in both senses: so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> it is to be obserued heere that <hi>S. Augustine</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>eaketh of the custome of the learned, and vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed.</p>
   <p n="29">
      <hi>29.</hi> But how doth <hi>M. Collins</hi> vnderstand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>? Forsooth the ioyneth the wordes <hi>imperitorum</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd <hi>doctissimorum</hi> (not to <hi>consuetudine,</hi> as <hi>S. Augustine</hi> doth, but) to <hi>affinitatibus,</hi> and <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ecessitudinibus,</hi> and saith thus pag. <hi>369.</hi> lin. <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>2. Exhibemus religionem</hi> (sayth <hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tine) quibuscum{que}, necessitudinibus,</hi> not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nly <hi>doctissimorum,</hi> but also <hi>imperitorū. To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ll these we performe a reuerence of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi> So he; as if <hi>S. Augustine</hi> had said, or meant, that a kind of religious respect is to be had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o the kindred, and alliances aswell of the vnlearned, as of the learned, which no grammar boy that could but construe latyn, would haue so much mistaken, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e hath done. Besides that it is to be noted, that be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hangeth the order of <hi>S. Augustine</hi> his wordes to make good his errour; for whereas <hi>S. Augustine</hi> saith <hi>non solùm imperitorum, sed etiā do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctissimorum,</hi> he hath it, <hi>non solùm doctissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morum, sed etiam imperitorum;</hi> wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>his difference is to be obserued, that <hi>S. Augustine</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>peaking of custome or manner of speach, had reason <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o make more account of the custome of the best lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="LXIj" facs="37"/> then of the ignorant; and therefore to pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> that the word <hi>Religion</hi> is ambiguous, he said that not only the ignorant, but also the best learned vsed i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> ābiguously; But as <hi>M. Collins</hi> hath placed the wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>S. Augustine</hi> should seem to make the <hi>emphasis</hi> vpon the <hi>ignorant,</hi> as to say, that the word <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> was vsed ambiguously by the custome not only of the best learned, but also of the ignorant, as if the vse of word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s receaued more authority from the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome of the ignorant then of the best learned, so as by this transposition of the words, <hi>M. Collins</hi> hath m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e <hi>S. Augustine</hi> speake absurdly. Agayn if we take the wordes <hi>impe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>itorum,</hi> and <hi>doctissimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> as they lye in <hi>S. Augustine,</hi> and apply them to <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>itatibus</hi> as <hi>M. Collyns</hi> doth, no lesse ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surdity will follow; for so <hi>S. Austine</hi> shall seeme to haue conceaued that his reader might doubt whether the affinity of the best learned were to be respected, aswell as the affinity of the ignorant, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to res lue that doubt <hi>S. Augustine</hi> said that a reuerend respect was to be had to the affinity not only of the ignorant, but also of the best learned; which would haue been a very idle speach, and most vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of <hi>S. Augustine;</hi> for no man that reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth affinity in the ignorant, would doubt whether it were to be respected also in the most learned; so as the very absurdity in the sense might haue moued M. <hi>Collins</hi> to suspect his construction of the wordes, if he had not been as witles in vnderstanding <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustines</hi>
      <pb n="LXIIj" facs="37"/> meaning, as ignorant in construing his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>atyn.</p>
   <p n="30">
      <hi>30.</hi> The like ignorance, but with more fraud, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e sheweth in correcting a translation of myne in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. chapter. nu. <hi>33.</hi> The place which I translated was of <hi>S. Augustine</hi> in his Booke <hi>de cura pro mortuis cap. 4.</hi> (concerning the good which the dead may receaue by the care of their friends to bury their bodyes neer to the monuments of Saints) which I layd downe in my <hi>Adioynder</hi> pag. <hi>301.</hi> in these wordes. <hi>Sed cùm talia viuorum solatia re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiruntur</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but when such comforts of the liuing are sought, whereby they may shew theyr pyous mynd or affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes theyr friendes, I do not see what help the dead may receiue therby, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this, that whiles the liuing do remember where the bodyes of theyr frynds are layd,</hi> eisdem illis tamquam patronis susceptos apud Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum adiuuandos commendent, <hi>they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend them to the same</hi> (Saynts) <hi>as to their patrons, who haue receaued them into theyr protection, to be helped with God, which truly they might doe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they could not bury them in such places.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="31">
      <hi>31. Thus farre I translated, and cited</hi> S. Augustines <hi>words: which</hi> M. Collins <hi>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sureth thus. pag. 283.</hi> By the way, <hi>saith he,
<pb n="LXIIIj" facs="38"/> you construe</hi> apud dominum adiuuandos co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mendent, <hi>they may commend them to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> holpen with almighty God, as if,</hi> apud do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minum <hi>depended of</hi> adiuuandos, <hi>and not o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> commendent; <hi>with such pretty bosles of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisit learning it your worke embellishe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> that write against bishops.</hi> So he, shewing the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein his own grosse ignorance, and notorious wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> of wit, which will be most euident, if we consider the latyn words layd down by me in my translation, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ereof he doth fraudulently dissemble some part. The words are these: <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sdem illis aquam pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronis susceptos apud dominum adiuuan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos commendent;</hi> in which words I desyre to be noted, <hi>eisdem illis,</hi> as being in true grāmaticall construction the datiue case, and necessarily to be gouerned by <hi>commendent;</hi> so as the sense must needs be, that they <hi>may recommend them to the same saynts, as to theyr Patrons</hi> &amp;c. which being so, I would gladly know of this <hi>accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Grammarian M. Collins,</hi> how <hi>apud dominum</hi> can depend on <hi>cōmendent,</hi> to make good sense and construction? will he say, that <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendent</hi> shall gouern both <hi>apud dominum,</hi> and <hi>eisdem sanctis</hi> how then shall we construe it? must we say, that they <hi>may commend them to God to the same saynts?</hi> or <hi>to the same Saynts to God?</hi> then what construction or sense is there in the <hi>sentence?</hi> but perhaps he will say, that it must be
<pb n="LXV" facs="38"/> construed, that they <hi>may commend them to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>he same Saints with God;</hi> if he say so, then <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>pud Dominū</hi> doth depend rather vpon <hi>eisdem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>anctis,</hi> then vpon <hi>commendent,</hi> or rather it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ependeth vpon some wordes to be vnderstood, as <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ui sunt,</hi> or the like, As to say, that <hi>they may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ommend them to the same Saints,</hi> qui sunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pud Dominum, which are with God: whereby it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ppeareth that <hi>apud Dominum,</hi> can no way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>end vpon <hi>commendent,</hi> as <hi>M. Collins</hi> would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aue it to do; whereas making it to depend on <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uuandos,</hi> and that <hi>eisdem Sanctis</hi> be gouerned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y <hi>commendent,</hi> the sense is cleare, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>truction very good; for so it will be (as I translated it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>efore) <hi>that they may commend them to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ame Saints, as to their patrons, into whose protection they were receaued;</hi> adiuuandos a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ud Dominum, <hi>to be helped with God.</hi> Can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y thing be more cleare then this? And yet you see <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he silly fellow triūpheth, as if he had vtterly confoū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed me with this instance; and therfore as he sayth of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, that <hi>with such bosses of exquisite lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning my wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>k is embellished that write a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Bishops,</hi> so I may say more truly of him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hat <hi>with such botches of gross ignorāce his worke it patched that writes against Iesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ts.</hi> And yet forsooth this is the man who as <hi>M. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eph Hall</hi> his fellow Doctour affirmeth <hi>(Mulus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ulum) is one of the prime ornaments of</hi>
      <pb n="LXVj" facs="39"/> Cambridge, <hi>whose learning,</hi> sayth he, <hi>wit, ind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement, eloquence the world knoweth, whose workes doe prayse him inough in the gate, from whose learned hand there neuer fell any thing without applause:</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> finally he appealeth <hi>to al the Tribunals of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, whether all Doway haue yeilded ought comparable to this mans pen;</hi> but how little honour, or rather how great iniury he doth to the Vniuersity of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> in making such a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> ignorant fellow the prime Ornament therof, I lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> it to the iudgement of the discreet Reader.</p>
   <p n="32">
      <hi>32</hi> VVell then, you haue now seene how wel he hath proued his imputation of my ignorance, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> rather how ignorant &amp; childish he hath shewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe euen in the latin tongue, albeit there is nothing more frequent in him, then to call in question my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinity as if he were Lord of the Latin language, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t I could haue no greater part therof then it should please him to affoard me: when neuerthelesse I may boldly say, that although I do not take vpon me more skill in the latin then ordinary, yet I could both speak and write true Latin before he was borne, and do n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> yet need, as I hope, to begge, or borrow any of him, for ought I see either heere or in his latin booke writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten against Father <hi>Eudaemon Ioannes,</hi> which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> nothing el, but a very <hi>rapsody,</hi> as I may say, of oul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> rusty, and barbarous words, and vncouth phrases, whereby his stile is so obscure, and harsh that no man
<pb n="LXVIj" facs="39"/> can read it with patience, much lesse with pleasure, and delight: in so much that it may iustly be sayd of him, at <hi>S. Hierome</hi> sayd of <hi>Iouinian</hi> the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ike, <hi>Non est contentus nostro, id est huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o, more loqui: altiùs quidam aggreditur, parturiunt montes, nascelur ridiculus mus, quod ipse non sani esse hominis, non sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ius iuret Orestes.</hi> Thus much concerning his third obiection.</p>
   <p n="33">
      <hi>33.</hi> There resteth now the fourth, and last of his obiections, to wit <hi>my circūstance</hi> (as he termeth it) which if he did not himselfe explicate, it would I thinke pose the Reader to ghesse what he meant by it. Thus then he sayth: <hi>Come we now to the fourth, which is his tediousnes, and his tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ketiuenes, in very truth insupportable, I meane his lazy, heauy, and dull repetitions of the selfe same thing often.</hi> So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e. And what repetitions thinke you are these, which are so odious, and insup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ortable? Marry forsooth, they are the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capitulatiōs of my Lord of <hi>Winchesters</hi> errours, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersights, falsityes, and absurdityes, which I do some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes vpon occasion repeate, remitting the Reader to the places where I had before treated thereof: &amp; the like I do with <hi>M. Collins</hi> in this my Reply, which as it seemeth will displease him highly, and put him into a pelting chafe, for he doth no more loue to heare of his faults, then the dogge to see the whip, or the scolding queane the cucking-stole, or the Thiefe
<pb n="LXVIIj" facs="40"/> the gallowes, but he must haue patience; for I must by his leaue, be so bould, as to put the Reader in mynd of them now and then, to the end he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them the better, and know <hi>M. Collins</hi> for a most fraudulent, and cogging companion. And this I hope may suffice for answere to his foure obiections against my selfe.</p>
   <p n="34">
      <hi>34.</hi> Heere then, thou hast seene, <hi>good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> that the calumnious cauills of my Aduersary (which haue obliged me to the iust defence of my self) haue already drawne me almost beyond the bounds of a Preface; and if I should proceed to discouer the rest of his impertinent fooleryes, this would become a tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atise, rather then a Preface; and therfore I will now draw to an end, and will only say somewhat briefly to a friuolous imputation of corrupting the Fathers, wherewith he chargeth me, giuing two examples thereof: the one concerning a place of <hi>S. Augustin,</hi> which I haue answered fully in the second Chapter of my Reply, <hi>num. 37.</hi> (&amp; therfore I omit to speak of it heere) the other is touching a place of <hi>S. Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an de vnitate Ecclesiae,</hi> out of whōe I alleaged in my <hi>Adioynder pag. 101.</hi> these wordes: <hi>To shew a vnity, he ordained one chaire:</hi> and a litle after, <hi>the Primacy is giuen to Peter, that one Church of Christ, and one chaire may be shewed.</hi> Now <hi>M. Collins</hi> sayth of this my allegation thus: <hi>In Cyprians wordes there is no mention of chayre, one, or more. The
<pb n="LXIX" facs="40"/> wordes are only these,</hi> vt vnitatem manifesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>et, vnitatis eiusdem originem ab vno incipientem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ua authoritate disposuit, <hi>and yet professing to English them, he couches very handsomly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n the very hart of them, I know not what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>bout the appointing of one chayre.</hi> Thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ayth <hi>M. Collins,</hi> accusing me as you see, to haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dded those wordes to the text of <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>et after a few lines, the silly fellow sayth inough to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eare me of this accusation, confessing that I follow <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>amelius</hi> in his edition of <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi> according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o a coppy which he found in <hi>Cambron,</hi> wherof he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aith thus. <hi>As for the</hi> Cābron <hi>coppy, &amp;</hi> Pamelius <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>he finder, they are to light of credit to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ace so many, so ancient, and so vncontro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>able. Shal the Bishop be censured for allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ing that which all haue saue one (and yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o iustly suspected as sauouring of</hi> Sixtus Quintus <hi>poysoned sallet) &amp; shall not this be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>alled forgery, to cleaue to one so abortiue, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nd new fangled, and forsake the rest?</hi> So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e. VVherin you see he confesseth that I haue the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>on of <hi>Pamelius</hi> for me, and that <hi>Pamelius</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>wed a coppy which he found in the Abbey of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ron;</hi> so as if there were no more to be sayd in my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>fence but this, it might suffice to cleare me from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rruption, and forgery, seeing that I follow an editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> receaued, and publiquely bought and sould throgh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>t Christendome.</p>
   <gap reason="missing" extent="10 pages">
      <desc>〈10 pages missing〉</desc>
   </gap>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>