<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS RENOWMED excellency, Henry Prince of Wales, Sonne and Heire apparant to our most gracious Soueraigne, increase of all Royall giftes and graces.</title>
           <author>Arthington, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115869_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21664</idno>
           <idno type="STC">797</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115869</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS RENOWMED excellency, Henry Prince of Wales, Sonne and Heire apparant to our most gracious Soueraigne, increase of all Royall giftes and graces.</title>
                 <author>Arthington, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Principall points of holy profession : touching these three estates of mankind. 1. Their creation. 2. Their subuertion. 3. Their restoration. Wherein 1. Gods mercifulnesse. 2. Satans maliciousnesse. 3. And mans weakenesse is made manifest. Composed in verse by H.A.G</title>
                 <author>H. A. (Henry Arthington)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Pavier, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HIS RENOWMED excellency, <hi>Henry</hi> Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> Sonne and Heire apparant to our most gracious Soueraigne, increase of all Royall giftes and graces.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F my meanes come in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion, with the greatnes of your Person, (O most No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble young Prince) it may be denied intollerable boldnes, for me to present unto your highnes so simple a Booke in so plaine a verse but, if the matter and manner be equally ballanced: The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, intreating of three most excellent fundamentall points of sacred profession, Viz:) first the creation, <hi>2.</hi> the Subversion &amp; restoration of mankind. I hope no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian will take exception, but the patronage thereof, may wel become your person.</p>
   <p>As for the maner, composed in verse, If that seeme too base for so graue points of skill (which ought rather to be handled in prose,) I say with all humilitie, that GOD is Authour of both aswell verse as prose) and that in the chiefest secrets of Diuinty, for (next the holy Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) what pointes can be named of greater importance, then mercy and Iudgement:) And yet the most prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> saide: <hi>His Song should be of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
<pb facs="3"/>
and Iudgement)</hi> If his example will not stande my warrant: yet, all his Psalmes with <hi>Athanasius</hi> Creed of the highest Misteries published in verse, (with our Soueraigns priuiledge) will approue the maner (against all detractors. But some may yet replye; The stile of my verse is to lowe and simple to preasse into a Princes presence, vnlesse it were of an higher pitch, &amp;c. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse no lesse, and yet auouch thus much, that the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pler my skill is, the more it shall commend your Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an disposition (most Noble Prince) to accept of the same. In assurance whereof, I haue thus far presumed to publish these verses so familiarly (after <hi>Dauids</hi> psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes) for the more easie apprehention &amp; remembrance of the meaner sort of people, to vse at al times for their edification, that God may be gloryfied in their saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is the end of my poore indeuors, committing the successe vnto his good blessing, with your most No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble person, long to prolong many good yeares in health, with much increase of honor: Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your high excellencyes</hi> Deuoted Suppliant. <hi>Henry Arthington.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>