<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGH∣TY MONARCH CHARLES King of Great Brittaine, France and Ireland, De∣fender of the Faith.</title>
           <author>Bernard, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115391_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68550</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1926</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115391</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGH∣TY MONARCH CHARLES King of Great Brittaine, France and Ireland, De∣fender of the Faith.</title>
                 <author>Bernard, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Bible-battells. Or The sacred art military : For the rightly wageing of warre according to Holy Writ. Compiled for the vse of all such valiant worthies, and vertuously valerous souldiers, as vpon all iust occasions be ready to affront the enemies of God, our king, and country. By Ric. Bernard rector of Batcombe Somersetshire</title>
                 <author>Bernard, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Blackmore (Blackamore), Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 <publisher>Boler (Bowler), James 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 273, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TY MONARCH CHARLES King of <hi>Great Brittaine, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the Faith.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Puissant-Prince.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>TRONG be Your <hi>Armes,</hi> and victorious Your <hi>Armies,</hi> the <hi>Lord of Hosts</hi> be with You, and the mighty God of <hi>Iacob▪</hi> Your <hi>Refuge.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>That foretolde by <hi>Christ</hi> is now verified: a noise there is of warres, and a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of warres: <hi>Nation</hi> ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth against <hi>Nation,</hi> and <hi>Kingdome</hi> against <hi>Kingdome:</hi> and now, as <hi>John</hi> saw in the vision, is the <hi>Holy Citty</hi> trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vnder foote. It must be so for a time. On they goe &amp; haue prevailed: but yet there is hope, if we warre aright. The great <hi>Man of warre</hi> (as <hi>Moses</hi> calleth him) hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected vs in the <hi>Bible bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tells;</hi> vsefull I hope, for these times: but yet I leaue this to Your Majesties Heroicall wisdome to iudge. Into me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod
<pb facs="3"/> and order I haue col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected them: and am bolde in all humility of heart to present them to Your <hi>Sacred Person.</hi> Your <hi>Highnesse</hi> the <hi>Saints</hi> looke vnto for safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard The poore distressed <hi>Churches</hi> cry aloud for help. Is not their habitation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Aceldama, the field of blood?</hi> Many <hi>Valorous Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages</hi> doe attend the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of time; many valiant <hi>Martialists</hi> expect direction, and all hearken after but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a word of command. Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>consolate <hi>Princes</hi> craue aide: Religion it selfe saith to her <hi>Defender,</hi> set forward. The
<pb facs="4"/> hearts of the people, readie with purse, I hope, will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, as now they pray, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally for the <hi>Churches</hi> safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
   <p>Stand therefore (ô King) in the <hi>Forefront</hi> of the <hi>Lords Battailes;</hi> though not in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, yet in the power of Your Might, to suppresse the inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of high hearted <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi> And the strong arme of the <hi>Subduer of Hosts</hi> be with you, that this great name of <hi>Charles the First,</hi> amongst our famous <hi>Kings,</hi> may become renowned by wisdome and piety, Prowesse and Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, throughout the <hi>Christian
<pb facs="4"/> world.</hi> This be the prayer of all faithfull Subiects, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver mine.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties humble and and most loyally devoted Subiect and Servant: RICHARD BERNARD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>