<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Worshipfull, and my very good Maister, M. IOHN DARCIE, Esquier, grace, mercie, and peace from God the father through our Lord Iesus Christ be multiplied.</title>
           <author>Allin, Raphe</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115873_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68991</idno>
           <idno type="STC">376.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115873</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Worshipfull, and my very good Maister, M. IOHN DARCIE, Esquier, grace, mercie, and peace from God the father through our Lord Iesus Christ be multiplied.</title>
                 <author>Allin, Raphe</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The hauen of hope : containing godlie praiers and meditations for diuers purposes. Gathered by R.A</title>
                 <author>Allin, Ralph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 <publisher>Hatfield, Arnold.</publisher>
                            <publisher>James, Yareth.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newton, Ninian</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 195, 9 pages, 16°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Worshipfull, and my very good Maister, M. IOHN DARCIE, Esquier, grace, mercie, and peace from God the father through our Lord Iesus Christ be multiplied.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Alling vnto my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brāce (wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull Sir) the streight accoūt that our Sauior Christ shal take of his seruants, on whom he hath bestowed his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, and seing the reward
<pb facs="3"/>that the good and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble seruant shall haue for wel bestowing &amp; imploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng the same. And also set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting before mine eies, the punishment prepared for the wicked and vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble seruant, I (waieng the reward of the one, and the punishment of the other) thoght it to be very neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary &amp; my bounden dutie, (according to the talent, which almightie GOD in mercie hath bestowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="3"/>me) to write this little booke, two especial causes moouing me thereunto: the first &amp; principall cause is, to discharge my dutie towards almightie GOD (of whom I haue receiued and do receiue euery good gift whatsoeuer it be) as neere as he will giue mee grace: for as the Scripture saith; <hi>Euerie good gift, and euerie perfect gift commeth from aboue,</hi> (the Lord make vs thankfull for them) for
<pb facs="4"/>when we haue done what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer we can of our selues (which is nothing) yea, when we thinke that we haue done the best seruice that can be done, yet must we vnderstand and knowe that we are but vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble seruants, and haue not done so much as is our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to do. This is the first and principall cause that mooued me to the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of this little Treatise. Then when I had finish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="4"/>this small peece of worke, being vndetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned whom I might make my patrone, at length it came into my mind to present the same vnto your worships view, as to one, of whome (among men) I haue receiued the greatest benefits. Therfore the second cause that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me to the writing of this little volume, was, som<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>what to gratifie your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships goodwil, which hath
<pb facs="5"/>at all times been so great towards me. But perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture your worship may thinke it a great presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in me, to present such a rude peece of worke to you, but I craue pardon for my boldnes, and I trust that your Worship will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it according to my good meaning, and I hope in the almightie Lord, (that although it be not furnished with Ciceronical eloquence) you shall find
<pb facs="5"/>in it such matter, as shall tend both to the glorie of GOD, and the health of your soule, and that is my greatest desire. Thus being loth to vse superfluitie of words, I end, desiring al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God to prosper your Worship in all your affaires, that you may so walke before him in this vale of miserie, that when this our sinful course is ended; you and we may all reigne togither with
<pb facs="6"/>him in that place, which he (in mercie) hath prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for all his elect chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: to the which place, bring vs the Father, the Sonne, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghost, <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Worships most humble to command:</hi> Raphe ALLIN.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>