<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Authour to the reader, why he tooke in hand to write this booke.</title>
           <author>Saker, Austin</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115900_Fr1_10</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68649</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20979</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115900</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Authour to the reader, why he tooke in hand to write this booke.</title>
                 <author>Saker, Austin</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Allarme to England : foreshewing what perilles are procured, where the people liue without regarde of martiall lawe. With a short discourse conteyning the decay of warlike discipline, conuenient to be perused by gentlemen, such as are desirous by seruice, to seeke their own deserued prayse, and the preseruation of their countrey. Newly deuised and written by Barnabe Riche Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Middleton, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Barker, Christopher</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>102 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>The Authour to the reader, why he tooke in hand to write this booke.</head>
   <l>IN dolful dumpes of deepe despayre, and vnacquainted fyt,</l>
   <l>with troubled head but here of late, I chaunced for to syt,</l>
   <l>reuoluing what reuenge the goddes doe yeld to those of right,</l>
   <l>that haue their godheds in disdaine, or yet contemnes their might:</l>
   <l>What iustice Ioue did rightly vse, and Iuno also showe</l>
   <l>on Priams race for Paris fact, the Troyans all did knowe.</l>
   <l>Acteon felt Dianas force, shee yelded him for hyre:</l>
   <l>and what it is for mortall men, to moue the gods to yre</l>
   <l>Narcissus may a mirrour be, of Venus scourge to such</l>
   <l>as haue her darlings in disdaine, or at her lawes will grutch.</l>
   <l>The Spider shewes how vaine it is, to such as will contemne,</l>
   <l>and Piers daughters for like fact, the Muses did condemne.</l>
   <l>And Bacchus byrdes had dewe reward, for that they would despise,</l>
   <l>and what reuengement hath bene vsde by Ceres may suffise.</l>
   <l>Though I omit a numbre mo, that here I could recite,</l>
   <l>who for contemning of the gods, haue felt their force and might:</l>
   <l>But here my muse is in a maze, my senses all do shake,</l>
   <l>my fainting wits do faile for feare, my quiuering quil doth quake,</l>
   <l>To blaze the bloody broyles of Mars, the mightie god of warre,</l>
   <l>wherewith he plagues such rebels stout, as at his lawes will snarre.</l>
   <l>How he doth scourge the carelesse crewe, that liues deuoide of awe,</l>
   <l>in secure sort without regard of Mars or martiall lawe.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="8"/>No stories strange I need recite a hundred yeres forepast,</l>
   <l>but such as chaunst in these our dayes, and at this houre doth last.</l>
   <l>Let Holland make discourse at large, if I haue said amisse,</l>
   <l>whose state sometime in all respectes, surmounted most in blisse.</l>
   <l>Whose townes were seated in such sort, by nature framed so strong,</l>
   <l>as no assault of forraine foe, might do them sodaine wrong.</l>
   <l>No want of welth might work their wo, no coine with thē was scāt,</l>
   <l>of shippes great store in euery port, no pleasure they did want.</l>
   <l>
      <note place="margin">Lecker cost is good chere.</note>They livd at case in vyle excesse, they sought for (Lecker cost)</l>
   <l>their paunches stuft with double beere, was that they carde for most.</l>
   <l>They honourd Bacchus as their god, and Venus had her dewe,</l>
   <l>but as for Mars they knew not him, they were not of his crewe.</l>
   <l>they scornd to learne the lawes of armes, their countrey to defend,</l>
   <l>they livd in peace, which as they thought, should neuer haue an end.</l>
   <l>But mighty Mars, who long had winkte, &amp; borne with their contēpt</l>
   <l>perceiuing that from him and his, them selues would stil exempt,</l>
   <l>To teach such rebels to resist, his godhed did deuise</l>
   <l>a straūge reuenge, yf wisely waid: for whom they did despise,</l>
   <l>And whom they held in most contempt, euen they did rule the rost,</l>
   <l>and such had them at their command, as they despised most.</l>
   <l>Loe here of Mars the iudgement iust, prepared but of right,</l>
   <l>that those which had both him and his, but late in such despight,</l>
   <l>Those that disdaind all martiall wightes, &amp; scornd to learne their law</l>
   <l>by martiall might were soone supprest, and brought to liue in awe.</l>
   <l>Of men of warre by vowe profest, a troupe of Mars his traine,</l>
   <l>though numbre small more haughtie heartes, came neuer out of spaine</l>
   <l>And these were planted in their townes, throughout in euery place,</l>
   <l>and souldiers now prescrybd them lawes, a wofull altered case.</l>
   <l>They swaid the sword where they became, for who durst them resist?</l>
   <l>they tooke their liues as they thought good, &amp; pardond whom they list</l>
   <l>Their liues &amp; goodes were at command, their coyne at spaniards call,</l>
   <l>their virgins faire, their married wiues, the spaniardes held as thrall.</l>
   <l>their scutes must scoure with fristers fraught whō spaniards must cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoy</l>
   <l>their waggans trould with lusty frowes, that neuer made it coy.</l>
   <l>Their husbands they must be content, they durst not seeke redresse:</l>
   <l>the spaniardes held them in good awe, their deedes did shew no lesse.</l>
   <l>A hundreth Spanyardes in a towne would gouerne thousands fiue,</l>
   <l>the Hollanders were men of peace, they lovd not they to striue.</l>
   <l>Good men they tooke all in good part, but if they hapt to quarrell,</l>
   <l>their strife at first was stird about, that (Shellam) in the barrell.</l>
   <l>But though of Holland all this while, my tale hath bene pretended,</l>
   <l>yet other places in like case, with Holland haue offended,</l>
   <l>And haue with Holland felt the scourge, of Mars his force and might</l>
   <l>wherewith he dauntes the rebel route, that hath him in despight.</l>
   <l>Hath Seland thinke you scaped free, let Flanders make report.</l>
   <l>let Brabant bragge what gaines they get, that liues in secure sort.</l>
   <l>But Antwerpe thou thy woful wracke, thy spoyle hath proued plain</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="8"/>where martiall mindes do want, no state in safety may remaine.</l>
   <l>For thou that sometime didst excel, whose wealth did so abound,</l>
   <l>whose daily traffyque did surmount, whose like might not be found,</l>
   <l>Whose streets with marchāts so did swarm, who by their painful toil</l>
   <l>did bring their goodes by sea and land, from euery forraine soyle.</l>
   <l>Of Europe thou the storehouse rich, wert sometime cald by name,</l>
   <l>in wealth I say a perelesse piece, so passing was thy fame.</l>
   <l>Thy houses built in brauest sort, with walles enuirond round,</l>
   <l>a platforme of a greater force, might not in haste be found.</l>
   <l>Artillery both great and small, abundant was thy store,</l>
   <l>for armour, weapon, powlder, shot, what should I speake of more?</l>
   <l>For all prouisions for the warre, great store thou didst possesse,</l>
   <l>thou nought didst want but martial mindes, the sequel shewd no lesse</l>
   <l>For thou ne durst at all contend, what Spaniardes would gainesay</l>
   <l>thou paydst for building of a slot, that wrought thy owne decay.<note place="margin">A slot is a castel.</note>
   </l>
   <l>In bondage thus at Spaniardes call, thy selfe thou didst bequest,</l>
   <l>by meanes whereof thy store became, a scourge to all the rest.</l>
   <l>What did insue is to well knowen, I need not here expresse,</l>
   <l>I rewe thy wracke, but yet I say, thou didst deserue no lesse.</l>
   <l>For hadst thou traind but halfe the troupe, to bin of Mars his traine,</l>
   <l>that practisd dayly to be drunke, in Bacchus beastly vaine:</l>
   <l>Or hadst thou spent but halfe the pelfe, to maintaine martiall wightes</l>
   <l>that was consumde in vile excesse, by Bacchus drunken knightes,</l>
   <l>What keyser could haue wroght thy woe, what prince haue done thee wrōg</l>
   <l>what forraine foe haue thee anoid, thy force had bene so strong?</l>
   <l>But Mars might be of no accompt, thou knewest no such a god,</l>
   <l>his lawes were neuer cald to mind, before thou felt his rod.</l>
   <l>Who will not here confesse a trueth, that all thy spoyle and wracke,</l>
   <l>was but for want of martiall mindes? thou hadst no other lacke.</l>
   <l>For better proofe this may suffice, to such as will confesse</l>
   <l>a trothe apparant to be true, what should I more expresse</l>
   <l>Then this, the spoyle the Spaniardes gaue to Antwerpe in such sort,</l>
   <l>that all the world doth wonder yet to heare the true report?</l>
   <l>Fiue thousand Spaniardes at the most, by force in bloody broyle,</l>
   <l>should so subdue a famous towne, and beare away the spoyle.</l>
   <l>Where such prouision of defence, in store did so abound,</l>
   <l>where hundred thousands able men were dayly to be found.</l>
   <l>Ynough to eate the Spanyardes vp, had they bene bakte in pyes,</l>
   <l>or had bene brued in double beere, because the Flemings gyes</l>
   <l>Do better serue to drinke then eate, the Spaniardes had bene dead,</l>
   <l>they would haue drunke them all vp quite, without a byt of bread.</l>
   <l>But here ynough to make my proofe, and stil of this be sure:</l>
   <l>where Mars is had in no accompt, no state may long endure.</l>
   <l>May rebels (thinke you) scape his scourge, may such cōtempt go quite</l>
   <l>will Mars the mightie god of warre be had in such despight?</l>
   <l>No no, he may deferre a time, ere he reuengement take:</l>
   <l>but in the end he payes them home, the stoutest then doth quake.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="9"/>O England would thou didst regard, what plagues in time do hap</l>
   <l>to such as so without respect are luld in pleasures lap,</l>
   <l>And feares no force of future fits, that after may ensue,</l>
   <l>till dangers doe beset them round, and then to late to rue.</l>
   <l>And would to God by others harmes, thou mightst so warned be,</l>
   <l>that thou into thine owne estate, wouldest vouchsafe to see.</l>
   <l>And tel me then yf Mars be had in honour like a god,</l>
   <l>yf not, how thinkest thou to escape the rigour of his rod?</l>
   <l>May peace procure so great contempt, and alter kind so farre,</l>
   <l>that yr should make thee quite forget there is a god of warre?</l>
   <l>Shal martiall feates be stil neclect, as though we were so sure,</l>
   <l>that this our time of pleasant peace, should euermore endure?</l>
   <l>Would God it might, but so to wish, I know is but in vaine,</l>
   <l>our foes are ready prest no doubt, they seeke but time to gaine.</l>
   <l>What though in secret yet they lie, who knowes not why they stay?</l>
   <l>their quarrell is not now to seeke, they hope but for a day.</l>
   <l>Loe here the cause that vrged me first, to take in hand to wright</l>
   <l>this blunt discourse, good reader, here presented to thy sight.</l>
   <l>Which yf thou wilt vouchsafe to read, do iudge as thou shalt finde:</l>
   <l>giue sentence then, and I wil mend, yf ought mislike thy minde.</l>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   <epigraph>
      <q>Felix quem faciunt aliena pericula cautum.</q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>