<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHOR TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115242_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19893</idno>
           <idno type="STC">632</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115242</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHOR TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine deuout considerations of frequenting the blessed sacrament: written by the reuerent Father Fuluius Androtius of the Societie of Iesus. With sundrie other preceptes and rules of direction, composed for the benefit of such as seeke to attaine to the perfection of vertue. Firste written in Italian: after turned into Latine: and now translated into English</title>
                 <author>Androzzi, Fulvio</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Auroi (Ouroy), Pierre</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 296, 16 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>THE AVTHOR TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsideringe how litle it profiteth or auaileth a man, to be possessed of a ritch and a most rare Iewell, if being igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant or carelesse of the worth therof, he suffer it to be obscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or kept secreat in his chest: I thought good by pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishinge and printing this booke, to bringe forth into the
<pb facs="10"/> world a certaine most pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Iewel, I meane to shewe how greate a treasure he is possessed of that hath obteyned from God the grace of fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent communicatinge and receiuinge the B. Sacrament: which worke I haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken principally for that end, that when a man shall knowe with how ritch a Iewell he is endowed by the diuine bounty of God, he may the more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely loue it, esteeme the more royally of it, be more thankfull to God for it, and more carefull and prouident
<pb facs="10"/> neuer to loose it. And euen as the pleasinge sweete tast of the most dainty &amp; rarest mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes is neuer perfectly knowen if it be but presented before our eyes, and not tasted in the mouth and chewed with the teeth: (for the more it is bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, the better it is tasted, so that they which swallow it downe whole vnchewed, doe neuer perfectly finde the true tast therof:) Euen so curteous Reader it is not sufficient for thee, to haue knowen the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of this most B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and the manifould
<pb facs="11"/> benefitts sett forth in this booke, neyther is it enough to reade that which is conteyned in the meditations and rules prescribed heerin: but far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thow must exercise and put in practise the same, and chew and grinde them vvith the teethe of consideration and spirituall contemplation, demanding hartely of God that it may please him so to illuminate thy minde vvith the light of his Grace, that thovv maiest perfectly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destand vvhat thou readest heerin.<note place="margin">Luc. 11.</note> It pleased God in the
<pb facs="11"/> ould lavv to accompte those beastes for cleane that chevved their cudd, therby to shevv, that he vvhich vvilbe the seruant of God or one of his foulde, ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolue and ruminate in minde his diuine misteris. Conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe therfore that of all the meates vvhich God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for the vse of man, this of the most B. Sacrament to be the most delicate and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent aboue all others, he hath especially appointed it, most diligently to be chevved in the mouth of our minde.
<pb facs="12"/> VVhen our Lord God gaue the Manna to his people in the vvildernesse, vvith great admiration they said Manhu, that is vvhat is this?<note place="margin">Exod. 16.</note> therby to shevv, that this sacred miste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie prefigurated by Manna ought not to be svvallovved dovvne hastely, but to be vvel considered; discussinge in the minde vvho he is vvhom vve receiue th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rin. VVhich thinge this little booke vvill instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cte and teach thee, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore read it ouer often, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiuely, prayinge for the Author therof and giueing
<pb facs="12"/> praise and glory to God, vvho is not only the Author of all goodnes, but hath euer, and euer vvill remaine in this B. Sacrament: therby to make vs partakers of euerlastinge happines.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>