<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣SHIPFVLL SIR GEORGE MANVVARING of EITHFIELD in the County of SALOP Knight, and to the vertu∣ous Lady Madame ANNE his beloued wife: As also to the right worshipfull and well qualified Gentleman Sir ARTHVR MANWARING Kinght, their sonne and Heire, Car∣uer to Prince HENRY his Grace, Prince of Wales, All happinesse Internall, Externall, Eter∣nall, heartily wished.</title>
           <author>B., F.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115859_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19616</idno>
           <idno type="STC">605</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115859</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣SHIPFVLL SIR GEORGE MANVVARING of EITHFIELD in the County of SALOP Knight, and to the vertu∣ous Lady Madame ANNE his beloued wife: As also to the right worshipfull and well qualified Gentleman Sir ARTHVR MANWARING Kinght, their sonne and Heire, Car∣uer to Prince HENRY his Grace, Prince of Wales, All happinesse Internall, Externall, Eter∣nall, heartily wished.</title>
                 <author>B., F.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Scala cœli : Nineteene sermons concerning prayer. The first sixe guiding to the true doore: the residue teaching how so to knocke thereat that wee may enter. The former part containing a preparation to prayer, the latter an exposition vpon the seuerall petitions of the Lor prayer</title>
                 <author>Andrewes, Lancelot</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Burton, Francis</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 248, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL SIR GEORGE MANVVARING of EITHFIELD in the County of SALOP Knight, and to the vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lady Madame ANNE his beloued wife: As also to the right worshipfull and well qualified Gentleman Sir ARTHVR MANWARING Kinght, their sonne and Heire, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to Prince HENRY his Grace, Prince of Wales, All happinesse Internall, Externall, Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, heartily wished.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worshipfull, if Christs owne Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, though feruent in Spirit, yet in acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their ignorance, were
<pb facs="3"/>
desirous that he should teach them (as <hi>Iohn</hi> also had taught his Disciples) how to pray. How much more neede then haue we, in these our daies of frozen zeale, to desire instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this duty. If much bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, &amp; blind deuotion were acceptable before God, the Papist would get the Goale: If turning vp the eyes to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uē, with bended knees to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke view, but hallow hearts (deceiuing men) were accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God, the Hypocrite would out-strip al: If not pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at all, were acceptable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, the Atheist would attaine heauen before all. But if all of these be so farre wide
<pb facs="3"/>
thereof as that the one's <hi>not praying at all,</hi> and the others, <hi>praying amisse,</hi> bee both turned into sinne; then well may wee say, <hi>Lord teach vs how to pray,</hi> that our prayers, or not pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at all, bee not turned into sinne also.</p>
   <p>Many of vs, though liuing in the bright sun-shine of the Gospell, yet know not <hi>How, For what,</hi> or <hi>To whom,</hi> to pray. <hi>How</hi> our hearts are vtterly vnprepared, our thoughts wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, our cogitations musing vpon vanities: <hi>For what,</hi> when wee should pray for Spirituall things, wee craue earthly and carnall things, when afflictions are needfull to bee heaped vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="4"/>
vs, wee are impatient vnder the least burthen, desiring all things that may keepe downe our proud flesh, and prepare vs better to Godward, to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued: <hi>To whom,</hi> Some pray to <hi>Mary,</hi> some to <hi>Peter,</hi> some to <hi>Paul,</hi> creatures of God; Some to Crucifixes, stocks, &amp; stones, the works of mens hāds, forsaking the true God, and blaspheming his holy name by idolatry and Paganisme. These Sermōs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing (right Worshipfull) in my weake <unclear>vnderstanding</unclear>, giue great light (in this kind) vnto the simple, profitable &amp; sound directions to the learned, wholesome instructions vnto all: The Title of the Booke ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presseth
<pb facs="4"/>
sufficiently the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect therof; The Sermons them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, the Authours exact skill and acute iudgement in han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dling thereof; whose name, though concealed, yet skilleth it not much, for not the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man the worke, but the worke must approue the workeman. Thus much for them both: now for my self; I haue alwaies adiudged a principall part of true honour to consist, as in being vertuous ones selfe, so al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so in protecting and defending vertue and vertuous actions in others; To the honour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of your names, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in also to expresse my owne loue and duty to your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,
<pb facs="5"/>
I haue made bold to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title you Patrons and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors hereof, that as the worke it selfe is vertuous, so also your names may heerein remaine vpon record vnto po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity, <hi>The Honourable Protectors of vertue.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships much deuoted, <hi>F. B.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>