<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the worshipfull Maister Richard Euerard: Thomas Pritchard wisheth continuance of health, wealth, and prosperitie.</title>
           <author>Pritchard, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115267_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10138</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20397</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115267</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the worshipfull Maister Richard Euerard: Thomas Pritchard wisheth continuance of health, wealth, and prosperitie.</title>
                 <author>Pritchard, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The schoole of honest and vertuous lyfe : profitable and necessary for all estates and degrees, to be trayned in: but (cheefely) for the pettie schollers, the yonger sorte, of both kindes; bee they men or women. by T.P. Also, a laudable and learned discourse, of the worthynesse of honorable wedlocke, written in the behalfe of all (aswell) maydes as wydowes, (generally) for their singuler instruction, to choose them vertuous and honest husbandes: but (most specially) sent writte [n] as a iewell vnto a worthy gentlewoman, in the time of her widowhood, to direct guide her in the new election of her seconde husband. By her approoued freend and kinseman. I.R</title>
                 <author>Pritchard, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>How (Howe, Haw), William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>To the worshipfull Maister <hi>Richard Euerard:</hi> Thomas Pritchard <hi>wisheth</hi> continuance of health, wealth, and prosperitie.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F benefites bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye</hi> beestowed, may whet dulled senses, or taste of receaued curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, spurre the cowarde Knight to hazard him selfe: I haue good cause &amp; occasion to venture the reproch of people, rather than to suffer so lyberall a <hi>Micenas</hi> to lose deserued fame, or my selfe to bee spotted with ingratitude, the Mother of vices: which the <hi>Romanes</hi> so spited and enuied at, that they atta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched therwith, were as fellones fully exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted to death. Supposinge therfore, it to bee least approchfull, to set foorth to the gaze of people my ignorance, and to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate with the world my silly sentences: than that, my ingratefull acceptions of your liberalitie, should either impaire so
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>laudable a qualitie, grafted in your mind, or stop the same to my Successors. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though that your Worships children bee so vertuously trayned vp, that they neede not the instructions of so base a Booke: yet J hope it may reclayme the rude rablement of people, to lead a better &amp; more lawdable lot of life. Whose re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliacion to Vertue, can not bee, with out your condigne praise, that disdayned not to patronise my trauell, tendring the same. Which though grosely fumbled vp, yet your curtesie is such: that you wil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider of my meaninge, and weye good will more than this papers Pamphlet, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe the same. <hi>Alexander</hi> Kinge of <hi>Macedonia</hi> did not weye the cup of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which <hi>Synaetes</hi> imparted vpon him, but his good wil, so J trust my pretence wil bee accepted more than the thing J greete you with all. And therupon I commit you to Gods good gouernment.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours to commaund. <hi>Tho. Pritchard.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>