<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115696_Bo1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10499</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20775</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115696</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The romish Iudas : A sermon preached at Saint Maries in Oxford the fifth of Nouember, 1610. By Iohn Ravvlinson Doctour of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Rawlinson, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Hall, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hodgets, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or euery purpose vnder Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen there is both <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, (so the <hi>Septuagint</hi> read it<note n="a" place="margin">Eccles. 3.</note>
      <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastes</hi> 3.) <hi>Tempus</hi> and <hi>Tempesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitas,</hi> a Time and a Season: and the Season is (as I may call it) <hi>Salactionum,</hi> the salt that so seasoneth al our actions, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer is vnseasonable is euer vnpleasing.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Musica in luctu importuna narratio,</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Ecclus. 22.6.</note> saith the <hi>Sonne of Sirac. c.</hi> 22. A tale out of time is as musicke in mourning: or (in<note n="c" place="margin">Suidas.</note>
      <hi>Suidas</hi> his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe) <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, as the wearing of a hot
<pb n="2" facs="6"/>and heauy winter-cloake at Midsommer-Yea, that <hi>Panis Angelorum, Angelicall Manna</hi> that came downe from Heauen, though when it was gathered in due time, it had in it <hi>Omne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectamentum,</hi> the delight and delicacie of all sweets,<note n="d" place="margin">Sap. 16.20.</note>
      <hi>Sap.</hi> 16. yet being gathered out of sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, <hi>tempore non suo,</hi> as vpon the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day, <hi>it putrified and was full of wormes,</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">Exo. 16.20</note>
      <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.</p>
   <p>As in other works, so especially in this great and notable worke of the Lord <hi>(the Worke of Workes)</hi> the dispensation of his holy word, there is a tempestiuitie or season to bee obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. <hi>Text</hi> and <hi>Time</hi> must haue congruitie each with other.</p>
   <p>As at other times, so especially at such a time as this, which for the noble and excellent worke of our deliuery wrought therein by the high and mighty hand of God, from the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable designes of that cursed crew, those <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuli Catilmarij,</hi> whelpes of <hi>Catilines</hi> breed, <hi>&amp; Iudae plusquàm Iudaici,</hi> more than <hi>Iewish Iudasses,</hi> who as <hi>this day fiue yeeres</hi> had banded them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues together for the extirpation both of Prince and people, may bee called <hi>a Time of Times,</hi> (for, but for it, to vs time had beene no
<pb n="3" facs="6"/>more) and doth therfore rightfully challenge at our hands <hi>a Song of Songs,</hi> euen a song of thankesgiuing, which is the best and sweetest melodie in the eares of God.</p>
   <p>While I speake of suting this time with a Text, I presume your conceits doe already an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate, and runne before mee in my choice; which indeede shall bee <hi>a choice without choice,</hi> none other than that of <hi>Iudas</hi> his treason, the hideous crie and dinne whereof so latelie sounded, and shall now againe bee reuiued in your eares.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>