<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NOVRABLE, AND TRV∣ly Noble Lord, WILLIAM, Earle of PEMBROKE.</title>
           <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S115603_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01379</idno>
           <idno type="STC">115</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S115603</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NOVRABLE, AND TRV∣ly Noble Lord, WILLIAM, Earle of PEMBROKE.</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Fiue sermons preached vpon sundry especiall occasions : Viz. 1 The sinners mourning habit: in Whitehall, March 29. being the first Tuesday after the departure of King Iames into blessednesse. 2 A visitation sermon: in Christs Church, at the trienniall visitation of the righ reuerend father in God the lord bishop of London. 3 The holy choice: in the chappell by Guildhall, at the solemne election of the right honorable the lord maior of London. 4 The barren tree: at Pauls-Crosse, Octob. 26. 5 The temple: at Pauls-Crosse. August 5. By Tho: Adams</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, John 2</publisher>
                            <distributor>Grismand (Grismond), John</distributor>
                            <distributor>Grismand (Grismond), John</distributor>
                            <distributor>Grismand (Grismond), John</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 79, 1, 6, 56, 4, 68 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE, AND TRV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Noble Lord, WILLIAM, Earle of PEMBROKE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y your Honours fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, I had a place in the sad Court of <hi>Whitehall</hi> this last Lent: and it was so disposed by our blessed Maker, that I know not whether, my Text was a Comment vpon the Occasion, or the Occasion vpon my Text: they met together with such vnhappy happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. As this Sermon tooke Birth in the highest Sphere of our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, so there learning to presume on the helpe of your Noble wing, it
<pb facs="3"/>
hath aduentured to flie abroad. And whither, iustly, should it take the first flight, but to your Honours Protection, from whom it receiued Breath and Motion? I haue beene bold also to send a paire of Seruants to wayt vpon it, which were produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by other solemne occasions. I humbly beseech your Lordsh. to giue them all your Passe: and then I feare not, but that for your Noble Names sake, (not their owne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite) wheresoeuer they light, they shall find kind entertainment; and doe yet some more good to the Church of God. Which successe, together with your Honours happinesse, is still prayed for, by</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships humbly deuoted and ready to bee commanded, THO: ADAMS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>