<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116162_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11050</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21315.2</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116162</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Roome, for a messe of knaues : Or, a selection, or a detection, or, a demonstration, or a manifestation. of foure slaues. Or, a conuiction, or a comiction, or, a combination, or a copulation of foure varlets. Or, a reperition, or a repetition. Or, a replication, or a recapitulation. of foure harlets. With a narration or a declaration, a relation or an explication, of a strange (but true) battell, fought in the little Isle (or worlde) of Man</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Fosbrooke, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>38 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing written this course dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course
or rather discouery, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought
my selfe that it would
not be amisse, according to the
lawdable custome of pamphlet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
to Dedicate the same (how vnpolished
soeuer) vnto some good patron or other, for
shelter: when straict it came to my minde that
this fashoning of dedicating bookes, and so to
place the name of some <hi>Grand Signeor,</hi> in the
forefront of an Epistle, was for all the world,
like a Vintner: who at the first setting vp of his
Trade, yea and all his life after, hangs vp the
glorious spangled Iuey-bush to draw good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes
to the tasting of his Outlandish Liquors
which made me to dislike this fashion of To
the Right Honorable, or so, &amp; determined To
leaue it to the Printer without ane badge at all;
When sodainly it came againe to my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance
how difficult a matter it was now
in these duble dealing daies to seeme singuler or
selfe conceipted in any course, the whold mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liking
such fellowes no lesse then your Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polyters,
being men almost of the same kinde
and condition: and therefore I must needs
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>insanire cum alijs,</hi> and dedicated it must be, But
to whome? marry (quoth I to my selfe) to some
great man at least, (for its in vse now to haue
great <hi>Godfathers▪</hi> though we be neuer so meane)
&amp;c.</p>
   <p>I but (quoth my selfe) it may be he will hould
it too base S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>biac for his <hi>Honor</hi> to patronize,
and vnhappily one or other of his followers
neare to him may finde himselfe agreeued &amp;c.</p>
   <p>Then (quoth I Ile to some Doctor? surely no
(quoth my selfe) for he in his great wisdome
&amp; great learning, may ouer shoote the marke,
or thinking it not fitting his grauely or so: may</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Why then</hi> may it not be, then to some Knight?
oh by no meanes (quoth I for he peraduenture
would take the matter in dudgion to haue a
discouery of Knaues offered vnto him, were it
but for the Affinity of the names, &amp; peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
(if he were one of those trauailing Ks.
that knows more Languages then one) standing
vpon the <hi>Etimology</hi> of the word, being deriued
from the Dutch<note n="*" place="margin">Knact in Duch is a Knaue.</note> Knact would conceiue Iay
med at the Knight also, (whereunto before
God and the Country I plead not guilty) and in
a fume (especially if he were at his <hi>Tabac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o</hi>)
would bid me be packing and take my knaues
with me, or else (and then sweares heele) &amp;c.
Put case I offer it to some great Lawyer (quoth
I) in no case (quoth my selfe) for if he should
alter the case by misprision, and with a writ of
<pb facs="3"/>
the Case, case or cage you vp in the Counter
then you were in a wise Case, were you not?
How lik'st a Phisition then? (quoth I) mary I
pray God I may neuer haue neede of them
(quoth my selfe) Now by <hi>Mars</hi> ile to some
Mounser Capetaino.</p>
   <p>Then by <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nus</hi> thou art madd (quoth my selfe)
for the peace being now concluded in the
Lowe Countries, he in a malcontent humor
(mistaking thy meaning) may peanter plaine
stabbe thee, or so.</p>
   <p>Why then (quoth I) what woodst haue me
doe? for sooth gud sir quoth my selfe get you to
some rich Cittezen that hath broke off his
Trade and so.</p>
   <p>Now I see th'art shallow (quoth I) for think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
thou that he which breakes with h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
and creditors, and so will not breake with
thee?</p>
   <p>No, I know a bette way then that: Ile alter
the case and Gender too, and take a Lady, or
some great Gentlewoman that hath a heart as
bigg as a Ladyes: Nay that's as worse (quoth
my selfe) for ten to one she would rather enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
one or all thy Knaues, then thy booke of
their discouery, and so reward thee with one
of their cast liueryes and so.</p>
   <p>Now would I were a Saint, if I know to
whome then: I am in doubt (quoth my selfe)
that some one of these 4. Knaues thou writst of,
<pb facs="4"/>
came behinde thee in thy dreaming sleepe and
hath clapt thee on the coxcombe and cract thy
brainpan: but now I thinke ont, Ile helpe thee
to 4 C. for thy 4 K. to whome thou maist com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
them: viz the Court, the Campe, the Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
and the Country: You shot well at Rouers
quoth I, but I know an other C worth all your
C. Ile stand too't, such a C. she is, that she may
be wife to the greatest <hi>Earle in Europe:</hi> a C, of
all C. a tresnoble, command<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ng conquering C
a couragious kinde C. And where she affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
not, a full fell furious and fiery foe is shee.
God send me from her frowne then quoth my
selfe: what <hi>Angell deuill?</hi> what <hi>Ianus</hi> I pray thee
mought she be? mary quoth I the <hi>Epitome</hi> of hir
great name is <hi>Signiora Madonna Cogitatione Reina del
Microsmo:</hi> O quoth my selfe <hi>my aude metris,
A ken hur so weele sir, A shus a blithe Lasse a gud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth
Sir if she be plezd, And a o fell feend a she
froune: a foule eele au hur wezan shas oft gard me
to grit Sir.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Well (quoth I) if I finde her no worse then I
left her I care not: I pray thee Sira where lefst
her (quoth my selfe) forsooth I left her where
they shall finde her that reads on my Booke,
except in her Husbands absence she be gon to
visit her Neece <hi>Venus</hi> or stepdame <hi>Luna:</hi> which
I know his <hi>Honor</hi> will not be well pleasd with
when he coms home, but be it as it may, if she
be gon abroad I wil stay til her returne, or leaue
it intrust with some frtend neere about her.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>