<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his especiall and kind Friend M. John Land, Merchant, and true favour of Art.</title>
           <author>Wovtneel, Hans</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116476_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16239</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3163</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116476</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his especiall and kind Friend M. John Land, Merchant, and true favour of Art.</title>
                 <author>Wovtneel, Hans</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The booke of fiue collumnes of architecture : called Tusca, Dorica, Ionica, Corinthia &amp; Composita: drawne and counterfeited after the right symmetry and cunning measurs of free-masons. Gathered with great diligence by Hans Bloome, out of antiquities, for the benefit of free-masons, carpenters, goldsmithes, painters, carvers, in-layers, anticke-cutters, and all other that delight to practise with the compass and squire. Translated out of Latine into English by I. T</title>
                 <author>Blum, Hans</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Peake, Sir Robert 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Peake, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10 leaves, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To his especiall and kind Friend M. <hi>John Land,</hi> Merchant, and true favour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> of Art.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, I have made bold to choose you for the Patron of this Translation, wherein though I want ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ce, I have kept some forme, aswell as I could apparell a stranger in English ornaments. Not that he had need of us, but that we all need him, especially all such as affect the excellent Art of Architecture, that giveth beauty to Palaces, decency to Temples, and maketh Cities opulent, by drawing multitudes of strangers to wonder at their buildings. Pardon me, I pray you, that I take in hand to stand under s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>h huge Colossus and so strong Columnes. I grant (considering my little skill) you would rather thinke, I should speake somewhat in his praise that makes Flies so subtill, that the breath of any would move: or in his commendation that made a Coach and Horses so small, that a Bees wing could cover. I deny not such labours to be curious, but they are not commedious; they are even as fit to beautifie a C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>y i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> a time of peace, as the fellowes chaine a Flea would leape in, was to barricado, or crosse a streete in the time of warre. I have beene bold to make choise of you for my Patron, as well for your far travaile and speculation, as for that I have heard you have beene ever carefull and studious in bookes of Lymning, Painting, Graving, Building, and such like. I beseech you accept my labour, in removing these Pillars, Squares and Formes Geometricall into English, and assure your selfe if you take it acceptably, I shall thinke my selfe, as greatly pleased, as was <hi>Sixtus</hi> the last, who had all the peoples praise and acclamation in <hi>Rome</hi> for removing <hi>Cae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>rs</hi> Pyramis, from the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of the old City to the new.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your affected friend HANS WOVTNEEL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>