<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Willyam Painter.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1560</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116544_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01297</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11420</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116544</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Willyam Painter.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Antiprognosticon that is to saye, an inuectiue agaynst the vayne and vnprofitable predictions of the astrologians as Nostrodame, [et] c. Translated out of Latine into Englishe. Whervnto is added by the author a shorte treatise in Englyshe, as well for the vtter subuersion of that fained arte, as also for the better vnderstandynge of the common people, vnto whom the fyrst labour seemeth not sufficient</title>
                 <author>Fulke, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Sutton, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1560</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Willyam Painter.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>A Foule fall dontles <hi>Fulce</hi> doth geue thastrologers eche one:</l>
      <l>Bycause no firme foundation they buylde their arte vpon.</l>
      <l>Who doo surmyse and fondly fayne, mens fortunes to foreshewe.</l>
      <l>And make the symple forte beleue, that they their fates can knowe.</l>
      <l>But al thos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> bragges this boke doth breake and make them seeme full colde,</l>
      <l>With argumentes atchieued by arte with reasons manyfolde.</l>
      <l>Though Cunyngham the same doo carpe or Uaghan vayne it iudge,</l>
      <l>Or other suche, with scornefull scoffe thereat doo beare some grudge:</l>
      <l>Sith Grindall graue the grist hath ground and Molens molendine,</l>
      <l>The meale hath made, whence bulted was and brought this flower fyne,</l>
      <l>The lesse we nede theyr force to feare, we haue suche stuffe in store,</l>
      <l>Comparisons are odyous, therefore I adde no more.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>Comparatio omnis odiosa.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>