<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ADVERTISMENT TO THE READER, translated out of the French.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116663_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19951</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6384</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116663</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ADVERTISMENT TO THE READER, translated out of the French.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An oration made on the part of the Lordes spirituall : in the chamber of the Third Estate (or communalty) of France, vpon the oath (pretended of allegiance) exhibited in the late Generall Assembly of the three Estates of that kingdome: by the Lord Cardinall of Peron, arch-bishop of Sens, primate of Gaule and Germany, Great Almenour of France &amp;c. Translated into English, according to the French copy, lately printed at Paris, by Antoine Estiene. Whereunto is adioyned a preface, by the translatour</title>
                 <author>Du Perron, Jacques Davy</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 128 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="13"/>
   <pb n="1" facs="13"/>
   <head>AN ADVERTISMENT TO THE READER, translated out of the French.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Author of this Discourse vnderstanding that some had put in print two seuerall Speaches in his name, far different both in sense and wordes, from that which he by word of mouth deliuered, he was constrayned to bring this to light as an Antidot or Countermaund to those other. Neither did he much wonder to see such peeces of changeable colours clapt togeather, some true, some false, according vnto euery ones passion, without resemblance to the originall: for he doth thinke that no pen could fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, nor memory retayne two Speaches wherof the shortest lasted three houres, although swiftly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced. But he was much astonished at the liberty of this tyme, that within <hi>Paris</hi> (himselfe being present) any should publish two Speaches in his name without acquainting him with it, therby to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand whither he would acknowledge them for his owne. It is true indeed, that he was not the only
<pb n="2" facs="14"/>man, who had byn so dealt withall: for some other Prelates had lyn handled after the same manner, and found as litle of theirs in those remnantes besto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed on them, as <hi>Euphorbus</hi> in <hi>Pithagoras.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now therefore it doth suffice him to present thee with that he pronounced in the Chamber of the Third Estate. For that it was in a manner all one with that he made in the Chamber of the Nobility, the reasens being the same, and no difference at all, but in the beginning, conclusion, and ornuments: By reason wherof the publishing of the one might serue for a generall remedy of the suppositions of the other two.</p>
   <p>As soone as he had therefore signified to the Gentlemen of the Third Order, that being to speake in their presence, he thought himself obliged to make the same prayer to God, which <hi>Pericles</hi> was accusto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to do, being to speake to the <hi>Athenians,</hi> that nothing might passe from him vnbeseeming those that had imployed him, neyther of those that were to heare him,
<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 50.</note> he directed his words to God, saying with the <hi>Psalmist: Domine labia men aperies,</hi> and then began as followeth.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>