<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           <author>Hopkins, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116954_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03641</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13770</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116954</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 <author>Hopkins, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Two sermons vpon the XII. chapter of the Epistle to the Hebrewes, the sixteenth and seuenteenth verses : Preached in the citie of London the twelfth day of Iune, 1608. By Thomas Hopkins minister at Yeardley in the countie of Worcester</title>
                 <author>Hopkins, Thomas, minister at Yeardley</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Welby, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, the searcher of all hearts doth know, that at the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of these Sermons it was farre frō any thought of mine they should euer haue been committed to the Presse to bee set out in print, confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing my great inabilitie that way. But forasmuch as some of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers tooke the paines to gather the notes thereof, without either my knowledge or consent; and thereupon seeming to haue some liking thereof, were earnest with me for my consent to commit them to the print: whose godly desire I perceiuing to proceed from a speciall willingnesse to make others partakers of that profit they seemed to haue receiued themselues, gaue them my promise, if they would copie them faire out, and send them downe into the countrie to me, I would take some paines in the viewing them ouer, and setting them in order, and so would send them vp to them againe to vse at their pleasure: which they so did; and accordingly (by the Lords helpe) I haue performed to them, as my leasure in my charge would permit me. Now then, if these my simple labours shall bee thought worthie the view of the world, I doe humblie entreate thee (Christian Reader) to beare with me; which I know thou wouldest willinglie doe, if either thou didst know my weakenes
<pb facs="5"/>in gifts, my small leasure for vndertaking any such worke, or speciallie the marke and end I aime at. I pray thee construe all in good part; and what is amisse for want of skill, correct it; and if any thing haue ouershot me in ouerzealous carriage, impute it to my infirmitie. But if there happen any thing that shall worke to humbling for sinne, either generall or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, for the land, or for thy owne self, giue all the praise to God: and as I haue endeuoured to benefit thee and others, which is the maine end of my labours, so doe I entreate thee to assist me with thy prayers vnto God, that hee will assist me with his blessed spirit in the worke of my Ministerie. And thus hoping I may entreate for a friendlie acceptance at thy hands, and to affoord me thy good word for my good will, and a fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable construction for my paines, I doe commend it to the blessing of the Almightie, and thee to his gratious protection, wishing to thee as to myselfe, viz. the mercie of God in Iesus Christ. December <hi>20. 1608.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord Iesus, <hi>Thomas Hopkins.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>