<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116579_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20187</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6619</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116579</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The opening of heauen gates, or The ready way to euerlasting life : Deliuered in a most familier dialogue, betweene reason and religion, touching predestination, Gods word, and mans free-will, to the vnderstanding of the weakest capacitie, and the confirming of the more strong. By Arthur Dent, preacher of the word of God, at South-Shoobery in Essex</title>
                 <author>Dent, Arthur</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wright, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 126 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Epistle to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Diuine worke (gentle Reader) though the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor left vnprinted, yet comming to his hands that wisht a continuance to the memory of the famous Writer, and a comfort to the soule of the desirous Reader, hee thought good to bring it to the presse: and the rather seeing that the points herein handled (beeing in them-selues very difficult, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore
<pb facs="3"/>
not so plainly expressed) are here laid down that the meaner capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city may be instructed, &amp; the skilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler more confirmed. Heere thou maist see <hi>Reason</hi> contending with <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> resoluing those doubts which to <hi>Reason</hi> seeme dissol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable. Here thou shalt know, though <hi>Reason</hi> tel thee, if God haue praede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinated his elect, yet, <hi>Religion</hi> will tel thee, except thou worke out thy sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation with feare and trembling, thou art none of Gods fore-chosen: If from hence <hi>Reason</hi> say vnto thee thou hast absolute free-will, yet <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> will tell thee that thy willing comes from God. In a word; heere Ignorance shall be taught by Truth, and <hi>Atheisme</hi> confuted by <hi>Religion.</hi> Then (courteous Reader) peruse this worthie Worke (of the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Preacher Maister ARTHVR DENT) wherein thou shalt finde the ready Pathway to eternall life;
<pb facs="3"/>
through which if thou wilt soiourne, at the end thereof thou shalt finde Heauen-gates set wide open to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue thee, and troopes of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels ready to carry thee into <hi>Abraham</hi> his bosom, where thou shalt rest from thy labor, and haue all teares wiped from thy eyes.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>