<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Of the choise of History, by way of Preface, dedica∣ted to the Courteous Reader, vpon occasion of the frequent Translations of these latter times.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116620_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11366</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21625</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116620</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Of the choise of History, by way of Preface, dedica∣ted to the Courteous Reader, vpon occasion of the frequent Translations of these latter times.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The tvvo most vvorthy and notable histories which remaine vnmained to posterity (viz:) the conspiracie of Cateline, vndertaken against the gouernment of the Senate of Rome, and the vvarre which Iugurth for many yeares maintained against the same state. Both written by C.C. Salustius</title>
                 <author>Sallust</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Jaggard (Jagger), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Jaggard (Jagger), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jaggard, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 60, 6, 8, 7-110, 2 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>Of the choise of History, by way of Preface, dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Courteous Reader, vpon occasion of the frequent Translations of these latter times.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He chiefest occasion that moued the <hi>Scythians</hi> so peremptorily to distast <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Antiquities,</hi> was for that they saw the <hi>wals</hi> painted, and the <hi>Libraries</hi> of the <hi>Greekes</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> stuffed,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Bodin.</hi>
      </note> with the records of their owne Atchieuements, but the memorable astions of other Nations, either ouer-slipped, or satyrically disgraced. For all other Nations (the <hi>Haebrewes</hi> excepted) committed nothing to writing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their Fortunes. And surely (I know not vpon what grounds.) It is a generall fault amongst al <hi>Martiall men;</hi> to pen nothing of their owne exploites: And those who haue somewhat inv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed their minds to learning, for their excessiue delight therein, can hardly be drawn at any time to alter their stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. By which peruersenesse of eithers error, those Nations which haue bin famous for their <hi>Military valour,</hi> haue vtterly lost their ancient reputation, after their imbracement of Letters and learning.</p>
   <p>The best reasons that I can giue, are either to be grounded vpon desire of case, or else vpon their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency in the precepts of Nature and Diuinity; which not only abhorre the effusion of blood, but withal depose their former infusion of <hi>Barbarisme</hi> and cruelty; as in experience wee haue seene it come to passe, first by the <hi>Greekes</hi> and <hi>Latines,</hi> and afterwards by succeeding Nations. The people of <hi>Asia,</hi> were euer accounted good Orators and pen-men, but the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> rude and rough fellowes, vtterly vnlearned: and yet by war and Conquest, at home and abroad, acquired worthy purchases, and had their fortunes eternized to the world; not by themselues, but by strangers: Whereas the memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Actions, wars and Conquests of the <hi>Celts,</hi> the <hi>Germans,</hi> the <hi>Arabians</hi> and <hi>Turks,</hi> are either buried in obliuion, or at least Ballated in one sheet of paper, and that (for the most part) by their enemies. Better fortune had the <hi>Graecians</hi> in setting forth the battell of <hi>Salamme</hi> or <hi>Marathon.</hi> For by the ample discourses thereof, a man would imagine that a more honourable piece of seruice was neuer atchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in any age. But as <hi>Alexander</hi> sitting in <hi>Darius</hi> his chaire of Estate, pleasantly told the Ambas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sadors of <hi>Greece,</hi> aggrauating the danger of the present rebellion of all the <hi>Greeke</hi> Citties, that <hi>those wars seemed vnto him but as conflicts of Mice and Rats.</hi> In like sort those easie warres that <hi>Alexander</hi> managed against the effeminate <hi>Asians</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d <hi>Persians</hi> (to which <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>to</hi> spared not to giue the epithites of <hi>Woomanish,</hi> and <hi>Caesar, Contemptible</hi>) hold no comparis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> with the bloudie in counters of the <hi>Celts,</hi> the <hi>Germans,</hi> the <hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Tartars,</hi> as may easilie be gathered by those who are disposed to call to mind their ouerthrowe giuen and taken, and finally written by each others enemies.</p>
   <p>Wherefore to make a iudicious coniecture of the goodnesse of Histories, wee ought to remember the wise counsell of <hi>Aristotle,</hi> not onely in our choose, but also in our reading, <hi>That an Author ought not to be accepted with an ouer-weening credulity, nor reiected with peremptorie incredulity.</hi> For if we credit al, in all writers, we cannot choose but oftentimes swallow things false, for true, and so commit grosse errors in dispatches of importance: So againe, if we should presentli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> condemne an Historie, as of no credit, we should reape no profit, in counteruaile of time therein consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Yet let euery <hi>Author</hi> beare his owne blame, whereof if they that haue stuffed their m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>numents of memory with fabulous impostures, be guiltie in one s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rt, in no lesse fault are the <hi>Turkes,</hi> who can say nothing of their discent or Originall, neither will suffer any writing thereof to be commended to posterity; beleeuing, that no Historiographer can write truely vpon report, much lesse will they, who were either in action, or in place ouer the action; euery man being bewitched to tell a smooth tale <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o his owne credit: Or suppose, he be of an vnpartial spirit, yet either the feare of great p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rsonages, or passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or mony, will preuaricate his integrity. But what should discourage succeeding Ages, that they should feare to write freely of their Equals? Surely in these times, it is not probable that amongst such variety of Authors, no one should be found, whose workes were not void of affection, of corruption, of enuy, of passion. Let the iudicious Reader therefore, between these extreames (of lightnesse and Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique
<pb facs="4"/>
rashnesse) take the middle course, so shal he cul out of euerie good <hi>Author</hi> singuler purity. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let him censure the worke, before he fully vnderstand the depth and sufficiencie of the Author. But indeede this should be the care of the state, to looke into the argument and method of Books before they come to the Presse, least by the vulgar censuring of some deficient labours, others of more suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency be dishartned from publishing their writings. For in this choise of Authors, which euery student ought to propose vnto himselfe, I would not haue euery one to be his own iudge (for censure is a gifte of art and experience) but to moderate his opinion by coherence, comparisons, &amp; infallible reasons, which if they be not allowed by the maior partie, let him neuer be ashamed to change his determination. For as those which will spend their verdicts vpon Pictures, their dimensions, lineaments &amp; colours (wherin the skilfullest eie is often cozened and deceiued) ought not to bee ignoraunt of Symmetry, to giue true iudgement: So is it necessarie for him that will distinguish betweene the sufficiency and insufficiencie of Historie, not onelie to bee well read in the Arts, but also much conuersant in humaine occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances.</p>
   <p>Of Writers in this kind there are three sorts, the first whereof being wel qualified by nature, but bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by learning, haue bin called vnto Magistracie. The second sort haue wanted learning, and yet proued verie sufficient by the adiuncts of Nature and experience: and the letter being somewhat hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped by Nature, and wanting experimentall imploiment, haue notwithstanding by their industrie and integritie in their collection of Historie, euen equalled those who haue spent the greatest portions of their daies in the Counsell-house of Princes. Of euery one of these you shall find infinite variety, &amp; so much the greater, by how much euerie one sauoureth of more or lesse integrity, learning and experience. The best are those which are best seene in all these, and free from passion. I adde passion, because it is harde for an vpright conscience discoursing of an euill subiect, to abstaine from hard language; or on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther side, to attribute vnto good actions a moderate commendation. For the inserting medestly in praise of the good, and dispraise of the wicked, hath giuen no smal ocasion for the amplifying of Historie. Whereof <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f good Authors ought to be noted, what shall we say of Euill?</p>
   <p>No slight consideration must therefore be taken, whether our Historiographer hath written of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, or of others; of Fellow-Citizens or Strangers; of Friends or Enemies; of Militarie discipline or Ciuill Gouernement; of his Equals or Inferiours; and lastly, of his owne time, or of sore-passed ages. For iudgement in this imployment, Secretaries, Priuy-Counsellors, and Presidents in Courtes of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice are verie sufficient: (for by these three the state is ballanced) but more sufficient is he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> who alone sitteth at the Helm; but most of al he, that adioyneth much reading of Law and Historie to dailie expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience. To the perfection whereof two things are most requisite; <hi>Bookes</hi> and <hi>Trauaile;</hi> without the former, whereof, the difficile management of imployment (in any kind) is hardly attained to, and the date of mans life is ouer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>short to compasse it by trauaile and wandering obseruation, as of olde time did <hi>Licurgus, Solon</hi> and <hi>Vlisses.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The last of whom <hi>Homer</hi> pronounced wise, <hi>For that he had seene the maners of many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the customes of diuers Citties.</hi> In these daies many dote vpon sight of strange countries, the Natures of liuing Creatures and plants, the Fabrickes of Palaces and <hi>Pyramides,</hi> with the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worne sculptures of Ancient coines, but the misteries of publicke Gouernment, and their alterations, they neuer regard.</p>
   <p>Next vnto Bookes of humanitie, and experiments of Trauaile, I commend insight in Lawe. <hi>For those that are to determine suits and contentions</hi> (saith <hi>Arcadius</hi>) <hi>knowe all sortes of misdemeanors;</hi> and not misdemeanors onely, but their contraries, without the indifferent apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion whereof, the one and the other cannot be pried into and preuented. For in discerning between good and euil, consisteth the fulnesse of human wisedome.</p>
   <p>Whereuppon wee are to gather, that of all sorts of Historiographers those are worst to bee liked of, which with impure handes (as the Prouerbe is) presume to write of History, being both vnexperienced in affaires of importance, and veterly vnlearned. Of these is my chiefest Caue at in choise of Historie.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>The next to beware of, is a rayling or a passionate Writer (for you shall not find all Authors free from this humor) and him suspect of flattery, by praising himselfe, his fauourites and Country men, and bitterly taunting his opposites, or enemies. But when you meet with an Authour, who giueth his enemy his due commendation, read him with trust and beleefe; and the rather, if he bee a stranger to both parties: esteeme him as litigious persons do of Vmpiers in Abitrementes, voyd of partiality. For it is aparant that <hi>Dionisius Hallicarnasseus</hi> (a man of no eminent place in Gouernment) wrote the History of the <hi>Romans</hi> with better faith and more vprightnesse, then <hi>Fabius, Salust,</hi> or <hi>Cato,</hi> men aduanced to wealth and honour in their Common-weales. For <hi>Polibius</hi> a <hi>Graecian</hi> in many places doth tax <hi>Fabius</hi> &amp; <hi>Philenus</hi> of falshood, the one a <hi>Roman</hi> the other a <hi>Carthaginian,</hi> and both writing vpon the <hi>Punicke</hi> warres; the one giuing all the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the <hi>Romans,</hi> the other to the <hi>Carthaginians.</hi> These are the words of <hi>Polibius. Phile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> avoucheth that the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> behaued themselues valiantly, and the <hi>Romans</hi> baselie and cowardly. But <hi>Fabius</hi> by the censure of <hi>Polibius</hi> was a man of approued honesty, &amp; wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to whom the proiects of the <hi>Romans,</hi> nor the counterplots of the enemy were hidden, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuealed Yet both Orator like were very wary to say or do any thing to their own irreputations. But let not any thinke, that in an History he can discharge both the part of an Orator &amp; Historiogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher. For I cannot allow of those writings which in praises and flattery are copious, in reprehension of vices, briefe and penurious; this maxime being most iustifiable, that euen the man of best dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion and vprightnesse, committeth manifold errors. Wherein <hi>Equinard</hi> and <hi>Acciolus</hi> haue so magnified <hi>Carolus Magnus, Eusebius</hi> Constancie, <hi>Nebrensis</hi> Ferdinand, <hi>Iouius</hi> Cos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Medices, <hi>Phillostratus</hi> Apollonius, <hi>Procopius</hi> Bellisarius, <hi>Staphilus,</hi> and <hi>Leua,</hi> Charles the fift, that heerein they haue rather merited the sirnames of <hi>Orators,</hi> then of <hi>Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riographers.</hi> And therefore let the iudicious Censurer suspend his iudgement not by the scale of Friends and Countreymen, but by the verdict of enemies also. Against <hi>Phillip Comines,</hi> in praising of <hi>Lewes</hi> the <hi>XI.</hi> let him oppose <hi>Meir;</hi> and not <hi>Meir</hi> onely, but <hi>Paulus Aemilius;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the one is excessiue in commending, the other as farre gone in discommending; the third in a meane. <hi>Meir</hi> tearmeth him <hi>periurious and fratricide, whose desire was aboue al things, without regard of the Lawes of God or man, to become sole Tyrant of the state.</hi> The same Author calleth <hi>Comines</hi> himselfe, <hi>Traitor</hi> and <hi>Fugitiue.</hi> And therefore in these altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I wish neither of them to be belieued, because the one was highly aduanced and inriched, by the King, the other a professed enemy, and had his p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n deeplier dipped in gall, then was seeming for an Historiographer. <hi>Aemilius</hi> was neither friende nor foe (for he was of <hi>Verona</hi>) and wrote grauely and modestly in these words. <hi>The Duke</hi> (saith he) <hi>did enuy the King, accusing him with the death of his Brother, to haue corrupted his Brothers children, and to work them to poison their Father.</hi> Hee affirmes nothing rashly, he omitted not repugnant reports. They wrote in the life of <hi>Lewes;</hi> this man an hundred yeares after, impossible at that tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to bee possessed with expectancy of grace, feare, or enuy. So <hi>Tacitus</hi> did avowe the actions of <hi>Tiberius, Claudius, Caius,</hi> and <hi>Nero,</hi> reported in their life times to be full of flattery through feare, and after they were dead, as full of despight, and both false. And therefore it was his first prot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that he would write them without Enuie or Flattery, as in a time of more securitie. For hee wrote an hundred yeares after their deaths, and peraduenture had read the saying of <hi>Aristotle,</hi> that <hi>New Histories were as fabulous and distatiue as those of deepest Antiquity.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Surely those tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> will write of the present, can hardlie write truly, but they must touch the credi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and reputation of some men. And therefore <hi>Cicero</hi> in his Catalogue of all the best Orators, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred not one liuing, least they which by chance or negligence were forgotten or omitted (as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe speaketh) should conceiue displeasure. Who would then seeke for truth amongst Authors conuersing with such times, <hi>Wherein to write what a man would not, was accounted dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honest: to write what he would, dangerous.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The best course is therefore without all fear to dedicate our Papers to posterity, or if any think so well of his workes, that he will publish them in his life time, let his History consist of times past,
<pb facs="5"/>
collected out of the best Cōmentaries publicke, priuate, and Ancient; As did <hi>Lyuy, Tranquillus, Tacitus, Arrian,</hi> and <hi>Dionisius Hallicarnasseus,</hi> all, most approued Authors: and the last of most credite, because he wrote of another state, not of his owne, and sawe all mens Commentaries, and secrets of state by publique permission.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Polibius.</note>In this ranke also, are <hi>Polibius, Plutarch, Metasthenes, Ammianus, Polidor, Ctesias, Aemilius, Aluaresius,</hi> and <hi>Lodowick Roman.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But of those which haue nothing in thē but reports, <hi>ek toon aloon akroamatoon</hi> as <hi>Polibius</hi> spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, and haue not seene publicke Registers, let them be of no Authority. For the better Authors to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce better beleefe, avouched their authorities from publique remembrances, as <hi>Ammianus,</hi> vvho brought to light the Originall of the <hi>Galles</hi> from their <hi>Publicke Monuments.</hi> So likewise <hi>Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> writeth in his preface, That he read the Commentaries of King <hi>Ptholomy,</hi> an eiewitnesse of the Acts of <hi>Alexander,</hi> neuer before set forth. <hi>Appian</hi> had the like Fortune with the papers of <hi>Augustus. Metasthenes</hi> and <hi>Ctesias</hi> with the Libraries of the <hi>Persians. Diodorus</hi> with the <hi>Arcana</hi> of the <hi>Egiptians. Onasicratus</hi> and <hi>Aristobulus</hi> the Lieutenant of <hi>Alexander</hi> avow those things which they sawe with their eyes in <hi>Egipt</hi> and <hi>India.</hi> Not that I dare avouch that the truth of History is to be sought for in the Commentaries of Kinges, for they are giuen to speake largely of their owne praises, but to make vse of those Obseruations which are little or nothing interessed in their praise or disgrace; as the <hi>Computations of times, the largenesse and scituation of Prouinces, the Gouernment of Citties, the ages of Princes, their raignes and succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions,</hi> and in especial, their <hi>Policies;</hi> wherein the end of reading all in all consisteth. For as <hi>Metas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenes</hi> affirmeth, <hi>All men that writ of Princes are not to be beleeued, but especially the Priests, to whose fidelity and custody the publicke Annals were incredited.</hi> Such a one was <hi>Berosus,</hi> who collected the raignes of the <hi>Assyrians</hi> out of the Annals of his predecessors. This <hi>Metasthenes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Secondly, if a History haue such and so many witnesses as cannot be contested, it hath the greater ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parancie of truth, yea in seeming incredulities, especiallie if it suffer examination and triall. For vvho would beleeue that the <hi>Roman</hi> Senate at the motion of a Clowne, who dreamed that <hi>Iupiter</hi> called vnto him in his sleepe, and willed him to admonish the Senate that they should renew the plaies, because he that lead the dance in the former shawes had daunced falsie. The Senate assented. One man perchance in relating this triuiall accident would not be beleeued, but heerein <hi>Plutarch, Lyuy, Dionisius, Valerius</hi> and <hi>Pliny,</hi> do all agree; who in so vniforme a consent of the Senate and people could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late a falshood.</p>
   <p>But methinkes I heare one say, the latter was deceiued by the error of the former; and so each after other. Surely and so it may be, not onely in the Historie of humanitie, but also of Nature: For the olde world reported, that Swan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> approching their ends, would sweetlie sing their Funerall farewels; a tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition not onely receiued from the times of <hi>Eschilus</hi> by Poets and Painters, but likewise by the chiefest of the Phylosophers, <hi>Plato, Aristotle, Chrisippus, Philostratus, Cicero</hi> and <hi>Seneca.</hi> And yet <hi>Pliny,</hi> and after him <hi>Athenaeus</hi> report vppon proofe, that it is but a Fable, and so to this day it yet remaineth.</p>
   <p>But as for naturall Historie the validitie thereof, whereof we meane not to discourse, it soone experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, which in humaine (for their infinite confusions) can neuer be examined. As for example; Many good Writers, and not one, or two, but almost twentie wrote that the Duke of <hi>Orliance</hi> was beheaded for Treason, and that at <hi>Paris</hi>: and yet it was apparant, that XXX. yeares after his imprisonment in <hi>England,</hi> he returned into <hi>France,</hi> and there peaceably died. For which rashnesse my Countrey-man <hi>G. Bellay</hi> doth sharpely reprehend those Historiographers, who will audaci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uslie commit to publique beliefe the flying reports of fame and the vulgar. Of this fault <hi>Strabo</hi> taxed <hi>Possidonius, Erastos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenes</hi> &amp; <hi>Metrodorus. They deliuered for true history</hi> (saith he) <hi>the reports of the most inconstant people.</hi> But <hi>Possidonius</hi> vsed the Authoritie of <hi>C. Pompey,</hi> so that I thinke hee could write nothing vnaduisedly.</p>
   <p>Therefore when Authors disagree amongst themselues, I take it the safest course to beleeue the latest,
<pb facs="5"/>
at leastwise if their reasons co-here necessarily, and their Arguments are strong <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o proue what they say. For such is the Nature and obscurity of truth, that vnlesse it be raked from auncient and fundamentall Originals, it will hardly appeare like it selfe, but best then, when the reports, the flatteries and passions of the vulgar are buried with their bodies.</p>
   <p>As to Religion, because the Controuersies betweene the professions and professors thereof, are so ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconciable, I woulde not aduise a man to seeke out the Opinions of the Heathen among the <hi>Iewish</hi> Writers, nor of the <hi>Iewes</hi> amongst the <hi>Christians,</hi> nor that of the <hi>Christians</hi> amongst the <hi>Moores</hi> or <hi>Mahumetans,</hi> but to read the Authors of euerie sect and Religion by themselues, to weigh the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of the writer, and the validitie of the thing written, and how they agree or disagree amongest them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues. So much (concerning this Argument) as hath beene set foorth by diuers Authors, I will rather blanch with the imputation of mistaking and ignorance in Antiquities, then with the foul Title of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth; euen as the old <hi>Graecians</hi> dealt with the <hi>Romans</hi> and the <hi>Celts,</hi> and the <hi>Romaines</hi> with the <hi>Caldeans</hi> and <hi>Iewes,</hi> ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h one being ignorant in the Antiquities of either Nation.</p>
   <p>In reading the disgraces of an enemy, let our assertion bee suspended vntill we haue examined the worth of the writer; for an aduersaries report is not rashly to bee reiected, nor at first sight imbraced; but heerein let vs imitate <hi>Caligula,</hi> who commanded the History of <hi>Caesar</hi> written by <hi>Cassius</hi> and <hi>Labienus,</hi> and condemned by the Senate, to be published; saying, <hi>That it was profitable for the state, to haue the Actions of euery man, vnderstood by all men.</hi> Yet for my part, if the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony of the one or the other concerning <hi>Caesar,</hi> were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ow extant, I would not altogether admit them to beliefe; no nor build confidence on <hi>Caesar</hi> himselfe, when he writeth, that the <hi>Pompeyans</hi> made no conscience of Diuine and humaine thinges, and le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t no Sacriligious violence vnattempted, whereas he himselfe without any feare of Religion or deity, sacked all the Temples of the <hi>Gaules,</hi> and broake vp the Treasurie of the Holy Sanctuary, which <hi>Pompey</hi> and his faction feared and refused to violate. But the reason that moued <hi>Caesar</hi> to disperse these scandals on <hi>Pompey,</hi> was to make his enemy odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that so he might pretend a iust cause of war, when to a good man no excuse can seem reasonable to wage warre against his Countrey.</p>
   <p>As concerning his Commentaries, most men receiue them with approoued allowance, and no maruel, when a Generall was forbidden by the Law <hi>Porcia</hi> to giue in to the <hi>Tribunes</hi> of the Treasury, a false report what number of enemies he had slaine. Wherein if he failed, he was to be depriued of his General<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, and denied his triumphall Ceremony; which rather then <hi>Caesar</hi> would giue ouer, hee would not sticke to account that lawfull which made best for his purpose, how vnlawfull soeuer. Which law, though he had not kept inviolably, yet the feare of infamy so awed his ambition, that hauing many enemies, hee knew they would not haue failed to indict him of falshood, especially being resolued to publish his books in his own life time. An instance whereof is to be seene in <hi>Cicero</hi> his <hi>Anti-Cato,</hi> though he wrote saith <hi>Tacitus</hi>) as persons accused are accustomed to behaue themselues before Iudges.</p>
   <p>This therefore that we haue spoken touching the writings of Enemies, is to be receiued, except in cases of corruption and transfugation. Such a one was <hi>Froysard,</hi> who whether he sto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re beholding to the <hi>English,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Note the Author <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> was a Frenchman.</note> or the <hi>English</hi> to him, many make question, he himselfe publickly acknoledging their bounty and munificence. Such another was <hi>Aretine,</hi> who would glorie that hee was well rewarded by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se whom he praised; yea, though he did it against his conscience: Yet thus much wil I say for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, that it is not to be doubted, but that hee wrote truly, being either in action, or at least s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ending the best part of his life amongst militarie men: the fault that I finde is, for that he altogether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t the due de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serts of his owne Nation, which I thinke no vncorrupted passion can do. For <hi>Polibius</hi> (accounted a most true Author) when he came to discourse of his Countreymen, could not so moderate his p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t needes it must breake out into most bitter invectiues against <hi>Philarchus,</hi> for extenuating the valour and forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the <hi>Megalopolitans</hi> in their warre against <hi>Aristomachus.</hi> The same humour (if I bee not deceiued) prouoked <hi>Plutarch</hi> to write against <hi>Herodatus</hi> wherein he inu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yeth at nothing s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> sharpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as at those things which hee wrote concerning the <hi>Boetians</hi> and <hi>Che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ronesians.</hi> But who can refraine laughter that readeth <hi>Sabellicus</hi> his comparisons of the <hi>Venetians</hi> wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>res with those of the <hi>Romans</hi>? Euen <hi>Donatus Gianotus,</hi> his Fellow-Cittizen could not indure them.
<pb facs="6"/>
With this disease (if it may be tearmed a disease, with an honest fallacy to maintaine the reputation of our Countrymen) almost all Historiographers are troubled. And therefore had I rather read <hi>Caesar</hi> discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of the manners of the <hi>Galles, Tacitus</hi> of the <hi>Germans, Polibius</hi> of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mianus</hi> of the <hi>Frankes,</hi> for that they were strangers, vnaduanced, vncorrupted, &amp; were wel acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Originals of those things, whereof they presumed to write.</p>
   <p>The next doubt that troubleth my mind, is whether an Historiographer, ought to praise, dispraise, shew his opinion; Or leaue all to the iudgement of his Reader. For either partie I will lay downe the best alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ons I can, and so leaue it to discretion.</p>
   <p>Historie ought to be nothing but a representation of truth, and as it were a Map of mens actions, sette forth in the publicke view of all commers to bee examined; And therefore the predesca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ting opinion of the writer cannot but bring much discredite to the Action, in that hee presumeth to prepossesse the minds of Artists with imaginarie assertions, seeming to teach those, who knew better then himse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>fe what belongeth to such affaires, to the wiser sort, who will not he deceiued (for that he cometh to Counsel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he be called) he seemeth verie suspitious.</p>
   <p>No lesse guiltie of another sault are many Historiographers, who in the midst of their discourses, fall off from their entended Narrations, to play the Orators or Rethoritians, so deluding the expectations, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding the memories of their readers. Such a one was <hi>Timaeus,</hi> condemned for both; and for his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gradation from <hi>History</hi> to <hi>Satyrisme,</hi> vulgarly termed <hi>Istitimaios</hi> and slanderer. For sithence there is nothing more difficile, then to Iudge truely, who would not be aggreeued to heare an Historiographer, hauing nothing to do in Counsell or matter of state, to breath out his assertion of the chiefest commanders in the <hi>Republicke</hi>? Or what can be more foolish then to listen to a fellow who neuer saw f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ld, reasoning of the victories and ouersights of Generals and their Armies. Such a malepart part plaid he (I silence his name) that wrote the wars betweene <hi>Henry</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> the Emperour, by playing the iudge on both sides. He loded the King (or rather ouer-loded with such grosse flatterie and praises, that his Maiestie could not endure to heare them but with loathing; <hi>Charles</hi> hee condemned as a most wicked and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlie Captaine, omitting no words of reproach which his wit could imagine. Alas good man! lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle considered he, that his reproaches redounded to the discredit of his owne partaking, to whome it could not be imputed a dishonour to contend with such a Prince; more dishonourable to bee by him ouerthrowne: but most dishonourable to contract affinity. Well, by this his ouersight he lost the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite of an Historiographer, and was by the consent of all good men condemned for an vniust iudge. No l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sse onerseene was <hi>Iouius</hi> in his rash and odious comparisons of the liues of <hi>Selimus</hi> and <hi>Isma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> the <hi>Sophi;</hi> of <hi>Charles the fift,</hi> Pope <hi>Paule,</hi> and diuers other great Princes.</p>
   <p>Against these I oppose <hi>Xenophon, Thucidides, Tranquillus, Caesar, Guicciardin,</hi> and <hi>Sleydan,</hi> who seldome, and that wisely, and vpon occasions intermix their Opinions. Truly <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sar</hi> for military discipline, being all praise-woorthie, and a profound Artist in state-gouernement, though without reprehension he might speake his mind in warlike Controuersies, and that withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> imputation of ignorance, yet when hee did it, it was done with discretion and modestie. For when some about him affirmed, that <hi>P. Scilla</hi> might haue perfected his victory, if hee had pursued the troopes of <hi>Pompey, Caesar</hi> made answere, <hi>That he allowed of his proceedings: For</hi> (saith he) <hi>the Office of a Generall and Lieutenant are different; the one is to manage accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Commission, the other as occasions shall importune.</hi> Again, in the battel of <hi>Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salia</hi> when <hi>Pompey</hi> commanded his souldiers to standfast, and not to remoue; to receiue the enemy, &amp; not to charge: <hi>To do the like</hi> (saith <hi>Caesar</hi>) <hi>I see not by any reason how it should stand to our aduantage, because Nature hath infused into euery man a certaine alacrity &amp; cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of minde ready to quarrell: Thus a good General ought to cherrish, not to pull backward.</hi> Heere <hi>Caesar</hi> contended with <hi>Pompey</hi> not in armes onely, but in counsell also.</p>
   <p>Many are the examples which may iustifie this policy of <hi>Caesars,</hi> as the victory of <hi>Epaminon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> against the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> and therefore what can bee more distastiue then to heare another <hi>Phormio,</hi> who neuer saw field, to giue a peremptorie censure of such Personages, and their Fortunes; or a Schoole-man to talke of the amendment of the Lawes of <hi>Lycurgus</hi> and <hi>Solon,</hi> being the wisest ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrats
<pb facs="6"/>
that euer bore office; which when <hi>Aristotle</hi> had done, he ran into the dislike of many men for it; of <hi>Polibius</hi> sparingly, of <hi>Plutarch</hi> more f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eely; how iudiciously I say not; but generally affirme, that to speak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of things we assuredly know not, is an argument of Leuity; Peremptori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y to iudge, app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rantly dangerou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. <hi>Viues</hi> the Schoolemaister of <hi>Charles</hi> blameth <hi>Comines</hi> for the same fault of leui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y, because he often digresseth from his History; then from the liues and fortunes of Princes, and lastly f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lleth into discourse of an happy life, after, the fashion of Phylosophers.</p>
   <p>This notwithstanding; <hi>Comines</hi> was a man that spent his whole time eith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r in place of gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> wars, or in famous Embassies, and so did not <hi>Viues.</hi> So that in my fancy, if any mā might censure, su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ely he might. But admit his reprehension iustifiable, then would I aduise an Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storiograph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r to resolue either to determine modestly, or for altogether to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lde his peace, but that the authority of <hi>Polibius</hi> doth draw me to a contrary opinion For, the reason wherfore he blameth <hi>Philarchus,</hi> was for that he <hi>Silenced due desarts:</hi> yea, and affirmeth the chiefest vse of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals to be, to inflame the good to progression by the example of their likes, and to de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>r the wicked by d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>slike of former courses. Which reason both <hi>Tacitus</hi> and <hi>Procopius</hi> allow of, besides that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny graue Authors at end of their discourses haue vsed the president; &amp; amongst the number, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gathias</hi> (a wonder to me) doth <hi>compare a bare Relation, to an old-wiues tale;</hi> but his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority doth not so weigh with me, that therby I can be induced to cōsent; especially, since by the most graue censis of <hi>Cicero Caesar</hi> who went beyond al other Historiographers in this kind of cōmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, That <hi>his history was naked, simple, &amp; true, &amp; without all Ornament of Art laid open to euery mans censure.</hi> Of like nature is the history of <hi>Xenophon,</hi> which he annexed to <hi>Thucidides,</hi> wherein he interlaceth no Opinion of his owne maketh no digression, neither vseth any Ornaments of Oration. And to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ir opinions, that suppose the praises of ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tue, &amp; the display of vices to be the fruit of History, I answere, that it may more truely and properly bee handled by Philosophers (to whose element it pertaineth) then by Historiographers. He disgraced <hi>Nero</hi> suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently, that penned his butchering of most honest persons, <hi>His schoolemaister, his two wiues, his Brother</hi> Britannicus, <hi>&amp; finally his mother.</hi> Al these, without further addit on of words, <hi>Tranquillius</hi> writeth purely and plainly: But <hi>Appian</hi> after he hath shewed howe <hi>Methridates</hi> slew his Mother, his brother, his three young sons, and so many daughters; addeth, <hi>A man bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and mercilesse against al sorts of people.</hi> He rein he no lesse detracted from the credite of his former discourse, then <hi>Iouius,</hi> who for his long Oration, bitter and full of despight, against the Tyranies of <hi>Selimus</hi> Prince of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> seem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th vnto me to haue laid vpon his credit a pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall disg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ace, for that it had b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n sufficient to haue simply related the murder of three <hi>Bassaes,</hi> of great integri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y and neare alliance, two Brethren, fiue Nephewes, and his aged Father; &amp; not aft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r the maner of Orators (verie imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oper for an Historiographer) to run out into impertinent discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, which peraduenture the Reader may conster to be false or suspicious. And this vnder correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of those, who think nothing more vnprofitable, then a bare R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lation: for my part I dislike not cē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures vpon great Potentates and thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> fortunes, so the censur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rs be men of iudgment &amp; sufficiency. For discoursing of City gouernment <hi>Dionisius Halicarnasseus, Plutarch, Liuy, Zonaras, Dio</hi> and <hi>Appian</hi> are commended. For the Art mil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tary, <hi>Caesar, Paterculus, Ammianus, Frossard, Hiricius, Bellay:</hi> For both, <hi>Xenophon, Polibius, Thucidides, Tacitus, Comines,</hi> &amp; <hi>Guic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciardin</hi>: For policies and Cour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ship, <hi>Tranquillus, Lampridius, Spartianus, Sleydan</hi> &amp; <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiauel.</hi> For maners of people &amp; description of Countries, <hi>Diodorus, Mela, Strabo, Leo Afer, Boemus Aluaresius</hi>: For religion, <hi>Philo, Iosippus, Eusebius, Theodoret, Socrates, Sozo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Nicephorus, Calistus, Orosius, Sidonius, Gregorius Turonensis, Abasurspergensis, Gulielmus</hi> Bish. of <hi>Turi, Antonius Florentinus,</hi> and the writers of the <hi>Magdeburg</hi> Historie.</p>
   <p>But wisely spake the <hi>Ancients, Ne sutor vltra crepidam,</hi> in which sence I would not haue a <hi>Polibius</hi> to discourse of Religion, Nor a <hi>Eusebius</hi> of the Art military. Thus much in general of the duty of Historiographers, now of the choise of the best of these: for to hope for better were mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; to wish it, vanity. And as for those who Poetize vnto themselues the Idea of an absolute Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storiograph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r: such a one as neuer hath bin, nor euer wil be, I say they might haue spent their times
<pb facs="7"/>
and studies to better purpose. For who maketh question, but that an Historiographer ought to bee a man of grauity, integritie, seuerity, of good intelligence, eloquent, and fully insighted into the offices of publique and priuat Gouernment; I thinke none but fooles will fall in love with an Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ory, which hath nothing in it saue eloquent words, fained Orations, &amp; merry digres<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ions; verily supposing, that he that writeth but to please the care, cannot but neglect the truth, wherof <hi>Thucidides, Plutarch</hi> and <hi>Diodorus</hi> accuse <hi>Herodotus;</hi> and yet <hi>Cicero</hi> (to me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> wonder) tearmeth him the <hi>Parent</hi> of History, whō all Antiquity accuseth of falsity. And therefore let him be as we find him, whom al Authors so vniuersally condemne, but not vtterly reiect. For besides his eloquent sale, and the sweet dialect of the <hi>Ionique</hi> phrase, we shall find in him many remembrances of Antiquity: and to speake freelie, in his latter bookes diuers things most truly reported.</p>
   <p>Therefore wit to be deceiued in our choise, let those be imbraced, who are by all allowed, especially in those times wherein they liued, and were Actors in the affaires. Of which ranke in my iudgement, are <hi>Thucidides,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Thucidides</note>
      <hi>Salust, Xenophon, Comines, Guicciardin, Caesar,</hi> and <hi>Sleydan.</hi> Neither is it materiall that the <hi>Athenians</hi> accused <hi>Thucidides,</hi> of affectionate partiality towards the <hi>Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonians</hi>: for heereby being an <hi>Athenian</hi> and not a <hi>Lacedemonian,</hi> they added to his credit. And besides, the man had bin imployed in diuers Imbassies &amp; commands in the <hi>Peloponesian</hi> war; was rich, nobly discended, had to do in all affaires of state, maintained Intelligenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rs, and lastly wrote of their actions, who then liued, and that in n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> free state: who would call such an Author, or such an, Historie, into suspition. Neither did his fauour towards the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> so drowne the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his owne Countreymen, but that he gaue them their due praises. And although he were by thē cast into banishment, when he wrote his History, yet he not onely cleared his onely aduersarie and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ile worker <hi>Pericles</hi> from publicke obloquy, but being dead thought him so praise-worthy for his poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, gouernment, that he doubted not to prophesie, but that with his death the state would fall into a present declination: yet <hi>Diodorus</hi> sticketh not secretly to carpe at the method of his Orations, as doth <hi>Trogus Pompeius</hi> (witnes <hi>Iustine</hi>) against <hi>Lyuy</hi> &amp; <hi>Salust</hi>: saying, <hi>That they exceeded the bounds of History, by inserting their direct and indirect Orations.</hi> For (as <hi>Cicero</hi> saith) <hi>nothing can be more pleasing in History then simple and significant breuity.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But if we should go about to extract from <hi>Liuy</hi> al his Orations, we should leaue him but smal frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; which reason, <hi>Caligula</hi> pretended for defacing his portraiture, and remouing his writings out of all Libraries; which in truth to me seemeth in some sort tollerable, for that he himselfe protesteth in his o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e and fortifieth booke, that hee determined <hi>to write nothing but the Romaine Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Salust.</note>Of <hi>Salust</hi> we can define nothing, because all his workes are almsot lost: by those which remaine, wee cann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t denie, but that he was a most sincere Author, and deepe Statist. For he tooke paines to trauaile into <hi>Affricke</hi> to be truelie informed of his <hi>Bellum Iugurthinum.</hi> And surelie he wrote freelie: for what could be more freche spoken, then to c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rsine the man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>fold sufficiencie of the whole <hi>Roman</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple then liuing, to consist in one onely <hi>Caesar</hi> and <hi>Cato</hi>? So <hi>Thucidides</hi> attributed to <hi>Pericles</hi> his true and most deserued commendations: So did <hi>Sleydan</hi> his, to King <hi>Francis;</hi> to the <hi>Duke of Saxony,</hi> his; to <hi>Belay,</hi> and <hi>Alasco,</hi> theirs, reiecting all odious comparisons. But if an Authour will needs discend into a bitter straine, then let him proue his assertions with pertinent Argumentes; for otherwise the world will grow into suspition that he hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> written but vpon heare-say. Which course <hi>Guicciardin, Plutarch, Machiauel, and Tacitus,</hi> haue followed, whereby they haue most clearelie laid open the secre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>est proiects and policies of diuers Princes. As for <hi>Sleydan</hi> hee vvas King <hi>Francis</hi> his interpreter,<note place="margin">Sleydan</note> and often imployed in Embassies by his Commonwealth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and being a D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uine his chiefe scope was to write of Religion, the controuersies wherof as likewise the Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (direct and indirect) hee included in as briefe a method as possi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>y he coul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>: which to manie men seeme tedious; but to a spirit desirous to read antiquities, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> of importance, nothing should be so taken. For in our Authors <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>sard,</hi> &amp; <hi>Carter</hi> you shal find a masse of leuitie, but withall many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="7"/>
case to be reiected; which you shall not find in <hi>Emilius,</hi> who freely confesseth that he hath witting he ouerpassed those things, which other men haue written. Of the same mold are the histories of <hi>Leo Afer, Aluarasius. M. Gazus,</hi> which speake to all accidents, weighty, indifferent, triuiall; therewith to satiate the itching eares of the curious. But this shall you seldome finde amongst the <hi>Greeke</hi> or <hi>Latine</hi> writers, who onely proposed to discourse of the actions of warre or peace, vnlesse some memorable accident intervened; as with <hi>Liuie,</hi> The burning of the Capitoll in the sociall warre; with <hi>Tacitus,</hi> That furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fire which consumed twelue wards of the Citty.</p>
   <p>As for <hi>Prodegies,</hi> not the basest, but euen the most famous writers haue noted them, though flatlie incredible; as <hi>Caesar</hi> himselfe; That in the ciuill warre, the statue did sweat at <hi>Traley:</hi> a man other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise neither fearing God, nor much regarding honesty. Herein <hi>Liuie</hi> most religiously (I had rather say superstitiouslie) exceeded all others. For ye shal read of nothing so frequēt, as how Oxen spoke, Vines burnt, Statues sweated, Stars fell from heauen; how God appeared to <hi>Hanniball:</hi> that a childe of six moneths olde, proclaimed a Triumph, and such like. These writers, <hi>Polibius</hi> tearmed <hi>Tragoedos,</hi> &amp; not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly: because they could not fetch <hi>Anniball</hi> out of Purgatory, they woulde bring downe the Gods on the stage by deuises. But <hi>Polibius</hi> was an Atheist, and wrote verie vnreuerently of religion; the others are more charitably to be censured. For it were better to be superstitious, then irreligious, and more tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to adore some God, then to acknowledge no deitie.</p>
   <p>In other mens praises <hi>Liuie</hi> is also somewhat too prolix; for when he preferreth <hi>P. Sempronius</hi> before all others his Fellow-Citizens (wherein he offreth an apparant wrong to the residue) he reporteth him <hi>To haue all the perfections that Nature or Fortune could possibly bestow vpon Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> Nor heere ending, he proceedeth to amplifie particulers, as his discent, his wealth, his eloquence, his complexion, his age, his Noble spirite, and militarie knowledge. Next him, hee eleuateth <hi>Furius Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>millus</hi> to the Heauens; <hi>Africanus</hi> higher; so that I see no man hath cause to wonder, why <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus</hi> gaue him the Epethi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e of <hi>Pompeianus,</hi> seeing he was excessiue euen aboue exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sse in the praises of that Man. But in reprehension he was modest and graue; as in the contention between <hi>Marcus Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius</hi> and <hi>C. Claudius</hi> for the censorship, wherein the one most spightfully inveied against the other; <hi>It is an vnseemely contention</hi> (saith he) <hi>where both parties depart the place with equal shipwracke of reputation.</hi> And in another place speaking of the ancient reuerence of the <hi>Plebei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> towards the <hi>Patricij: That modesty and carriage</hi> (saith he) <hi>which you shall now see in one, was in those times common to the Vniuersall multitude.</hi> The like modesty he vseth of <hi>Caluinus Companus: What! shall I tearme him wicked? No, but a Reprobate in the highest degree, who maketh choise to Tyranize, rather by his owne fall, then to behold the prosperity of his country.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This Author is not onely of one vaine through his whole worke, but euer like himselfe, of an vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing capacity, graue, spare in commending, bitter in reprehension, and like a politicke Law-maker and good Commander wrote worthily of Military and ciuill gouernment, with the Office of an Historio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grapher. His histories intreat almost of al Nations which were of any reputation in his time, or somwhat before, (viz) from the CXXIIII. <hi>Olimpiad</hi>: that is, from the worlds Creation <hi>3680.</hi> to the year three thousand seauen hundred, sixtie six, but of fortie Bookes which he wrote, foure and thirtie are lost. And as he was an excellent Historiographer, so was hee a verie good Phylosopher: for in the treatie of peace with the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> he forewarneth the Princes and Gouernors of the state, to enter into speciall considerations, whether those with whom they were to confederate, <hi>were compelled thereto by necessity, or with desire of alliance.</hi> His sixt Booke a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oundeth with the like obseruations, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he discourseth at large of the ciuill and militarie policie of the <hi>Romans.</hi> For the Topography of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and places none of the Auncients came neere him. The blind ignorance of times and former Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riographers, who put many fabulous Narrations vpon the <hi>Romans,</hi> he often reprehendeth: as this one most shamefull out of <hi>T: Liuius</hi> and <hi>Appian,</hi> who report, <hi>That</hi> Camillu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>defeated the Legions of the</hi> Galles, <hi>with such an Vniuersall slaughter, that no one was left aliue, to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the taking of the Citty.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Of the like error laboured <hi>Iustine, Callimachus,</hi> and his Scholiasts, in their vntrue suggestion,
<pb facs="8"/>
That <hi>Brennus hauing wasted</hi> Italy, <hi>led his Army into</hi> Greece, <hi>where it vtterly perished by lightning from Heauen, for sacking the Temple of</hi> Apollo <hi>at</hi> Delphi, whereas <hi>Polibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> proueth by forceable arguments, and conclusions of necessity, <hi>That after the foresaid army had burned the Citty, they trauelled as farre as</hi> Hellespont, <hi>where being allured by the sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation of the Countrey, they seated themselues about</hi> Bizantium, <hi>and ouerthrowing the</hi> Thracians, <hi>possessed the Monarchy vntill the times of</hi> Clayaru. Which can be no strange matter, considering that not long ago they tooke <hi>Bizantium</hi> with their Captaine <hi>Baldwin,</hi> and for a long time gouerned the Empire of the <hi>Graecians.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In our daies <hi>Iouius</hi> imitated <hi>Polibius</hi> as concerning the Generall Historie of his time, saue heerein is the difference, that <hi>Polibius</hi> was either an Actor or Commander, or had the pervsall of the publicke records: <hi>Iouius</hi> reported many things vpon heare-say, and at aduenture. <hi>Polibius</hi> was trained in the military discipline and offices of state, <hi>Iouius</hi> in neither. <hi>Polibius</hi> was a Noble man in his Countrey, <hi>Iouius</hi> a <hi>Plebeian: Polibius</hi> a Generall, <hi>Iouius</hi> a Physition. The one reporteth, that hee had trauailed thorough the greatest part of <hi>Europe,</hi> the Coast of <hi>Affricke,</hi> and <hi>Asia</hi> the lesse, to learne the customes of those different people. And to his own glorie: <hi>That he sate in the</hi> Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tican <hi>seauen and thirty yeares, was of Counsell to</hi> Scipio African, <hi>and his continuall as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sociate in warre:</hi> Whereas the other, altogether kept company with Bishops: And beeing asked why <hi>he coyned false reports, and smothered true?</hi> he answered, <hi>For my friends sakes:</hi> saying, <hi>That if those that be now aliue will not beleeue me, I am sure, those that come after, will affoord mee, and my fauourites, expected commendations.</hi> Gorraeus <hi>of</hi> Paris <hi>hath dedicated this censure to Eternity: That the rales of</hi> Amadis <hi>are as true and probable, as the writings of</hi> Iouius: Had he fabled for the good of the state (which <hi>Xenophon</hi> and <hi>Plato</hi> do tollerate in Magistrates) it had bin passable: but by lying to slatter, is vnseemely for all sorts, but most vile in an Historiographer. For as <hi>Bessarius</hi> the Cardinall when hee saw verie many whose liues were questionable, canonized at <hi>Rome</hi> through blind deuotion, saide; hee doubted whether all were true which was related of the ancient Saints: so fabulous Historiographers are often an occasion, that those of desart are called into suspition.</p>
   <p>If he would haue imitated <hi>Polibius,</hi> he should haue bin mindfull of his owne position set down in the Preface of his Histories: That <hi>he that swarueth from the truth of his proiect, pulleth out the eye of a most beautifull creature.</hi> How well he obserued this admonition, we wil not make tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, by him, who tearmed him an <hi>Author of Tales,</hi> neither by <hi>Sleydan,</hi> nor <hi>Brutus Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> (who often blame him for vntruths) because the one was of a contrarie religion, the other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture excepted vnto for imputation of <hi>Tirrany,</hi> but by <hi>Guicciardine</hi> the Parent of History and an Author without all exception. Whose relations if you please to compare with those of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius,</hi> you shall find them to agree as square proportions do with round, especial<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y in their Orations, Epistles, Treaties, and Compositions: all which <hi>Iouius</hi> mouldeth out of his owne braine, but with such confusio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of method, that euen by the censure of <hi>Alciat</hi> (his only <hi>Trumpet</hi>) the vnskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullest souldiers haue turned their tongues to Scholasticall declamations against him. I w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ll ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe the fond adhortation of <hi>Charles</hi> the Emperour vnto him, <hi>Expedire te, inquit</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ui. <hi>cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes oportet &amp;c.</hi> As also <hi>His conference and Complaints</hi> with <hi>Iouius,</hi> which vnto my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension seeme as true, as that <hi>Mulcasses should slay aboue two hundred Lyons; six hundred thousand of small Cattle to be pillaged out of the Territory of</hi> Brixium<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>and two hundred thousand of the greater sort to be driuen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ut of</hi> France, according to his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port. The like he setteth downe concerning the Empires of the <hi>Persians,</hi> the <hi>Abessines,</hi> and the <hi>Turkes,</hi> which whither they were true or false he could neuer vnderstand vpon rumors &amp; reports; and as for the Counsels of Princes, their speeches, their Letters, their instructions, or publick mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents, he neue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> saw them, and yet notwithstanding he presumeth to write as con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>idently, as if he had bin interessed in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>usinesse.</p>
   <p>Whereupon it is not to be doubted, but what hee might haue written truely, hee would not; <hi>as the affaires of Italy;</hi> what he would, he could not, <hi>as the estates of forraine Princes.</hi> Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse hee protesteth that if he were compared with any of the Writers of his owne time, hee could<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="8"/>
not but take it vnkindly. Which rash protestation (in my fancie) he broched by the president of <hi>Arria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> who thought himselfe by so much superiour to any Historiographer whatsoeuer, that writ the life of <hi>Alexander,</hi> by how much <hi>Alexander</hi> excelled all other Emperours.<note place="margin">Arrianus</note> Surely this <hi>Arrianus</hi> was a man learned &amp; wise, as apeareth by his Cōmentaries vpon <hi>Epictetus;</hi> and moreouer ioyned experience to his reading, insomuch that <hi>Adrian Augustus</hi> for his singuler sufficiency, preferred him to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulship, hauing run through all other inferiour offices, yea euen in the integritie of the state. I will silence his eloquence and Attique phrase, which was so pure, that he was called a second <hi>Xenophon.</hi> Indeed if <hi>Iouius</hi> were in any tittle to be compared to <hi>Arrian,</hi> then had hee cause to take it in euill part to bee matched with others; which by his fauour I meane to do it, not for that I will affirme that those thinges which he wrote were vntrue and barren, but that for euer he shall carrie this eare-marke of falshoode, that where euer he writeth truely, he shall be accounted but a <hi>suspected Author;</hi> yea, with this one note, more satyricall, and of far greater indignity, <hi>That by prostituting his Labors to sale, his lies yeilded him better profit, then other men could gaine by speaking of the trueth.</hi> And so I will leaue him, and returne to the <hi>Ancients,</hi> whom I will compare with our <hi>Moderne,</hi> and betweene <hi>Themselues,</hi> as the lot falleth.</p>
   <p>The first man I meet withall is <hi>Dionisius Halicarnasseus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Dionisius</note> who besides his modest method of speech and his Attique dialect; wrote the Antiquities of the <hi>Romans</hi> from the Original of their Cities foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation with such integrity, as no <hi>Graecian</hi> or <hi>Latine</hi> hath at any time done the like. For whereas the <hi>Latines</hi> neglected things triuiall, as Sacrifices, Playes, Triumphs, Ensignes of Magistracies, the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall gouernment of the state, Subsidies, Auguries, Parliaments, and the difficile diuision of the people into wards and Tribes; Lastly, the potencie of the Senat, the priuiledges of the Commons, the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Magistrates, and the power of the people, be in my iudgement hath best performed them of anie man liuing. And to make them the more easie to bee vnderstood, hee hath compared the customes of the <hi>Greeks</hi> with the Lawes of the <hi>Latines,</hi> deriuing the priuiledges of Clyents which <hi>Romulus</hi> institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (and which <hi>Caesar</hi> noteth to be common amongst the <hi>Gals</hi>) from the <hi>Athenians</hi> and <hi>Thessali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> The <hi>Roman Dictator</hi> to be of equall power to the <hi>Haumoste</hi> of the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> to the <hi>Archon</hi> of the <hi>Thessalians</hi> and the <hi>Aesynmet</hi> of the <hi>Mytilens:</hi> yea, had it not hin for this mans labours, the Lawes of <hi>Romulus, Numa</hi> and <hi>Seruius,</hi> together with the Original discent of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> had bin long since buried in forgetfulnesse, through the pride of the <hi>Romans,</hi> who accounted &amp; omitted these remembrances as base &amp; vulgar (A fault almost common with al Authors) as if they were as well knowne to strangers, as to Natiues.</p>
   <p>The like diligence almost vsed <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his <hi>Roman</hi> Antiquities;<note place="margin">Plutarch</note> what censure is to be giuen of him, I thinke euerie man knoweth. For seeing he was the Schoole-maister of that excellent Prince <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ian,</hi> an ancient Courtier, and at last Gouernour of <hi>Istria,</hi> there is no question to be made, but he ioyned practise and experience to his great wisedome. Hee wrote the Historie of the two most famous people of the world, not methodically and in order, but abruptly, and by way of Comparison. All that I admire in him is his so free opinion in al matters, that to me he seemeth rather a censurer of Princes, then an Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storiographer; yet with this submission to his worth, that if any man may be thought a fit Vmpire in bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesse of such weight, I hold him to be <hi>Plutarch,</hi> or no man. For vvhat could be vnknovvne to a man of so high a reach, so deepe a iudgement? Which are verie remarqueable in his most graue disputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a Republicke, and his profound Philosophie. The Originall occasions of wars, their openings, their progressions, ouerthrowes, and victories, he handleth like an excellent Commander. And sometimes he discendeth to matters of meanest moment, euen of houshold affaires; as is that remembraunce of <hi>Cato</hi> the Censor, who of purpose set enmitie betweene his seruants, <hi>Least by their ouermuch licentious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, they should busie their braines about proiects of farre worse consequence.</hi> The like he remēbreth of <hi>Pericles,</hi> who accustomed to <hi>sell to the vtmost aduantage the reuenues of his domaines, and to buy by the penny his daily prouision.</hi> Oftentimes hee relateth thinges incredible and meerely fabulous, but he vseth the worde <hi>Phasi,</hi> to forewarne rash beleefe. As in the life of <hi>Licurgus,</hi> he writeth, <hi>That a</hi> Lacedemonian <hi>Lad suffered the Rack euen to death, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then he would reueale the theft of a Fox:</hi> And that <hi>Agesilaus was amerced by the</hi> Ephori <hi>for populer dependancy.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="9"/>That he sometimes committed an ouer-sight in the Antiquity of the <hi>Romans,</hi> for that, being a <hi>Graecian,</hi> and not perfectly vnderstanding the <hi>Latine</hi> tongue, (as himselfe confesseth in the life of <hi>Demosthenes</hi>) he is to be borne withall. As where he writeth, that in Iudgements <hi>Gracchus</hi> by the Law <hi>Sempronia</hi> equalled the Gentlemen with the Senators, when as by the same Law that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue was taken from the Senate, and absolutely transferred to the Gentlemen; as <hi>Velleius, Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian, Asconius, Tacitus</hi> and <hi>Florus</hi> testifie: It is apparant that he mistook <hi>Legem liuiam pro Sempronia,</hi> and <hi>Gracchus</hi> for <hi>Drusus.</hi> The like fault he committed in valewing the <hi>Drach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> with the <hi>Roman Denarius,</hi> and the <hi>Mina</hi> with <hi>Libra</hi> in the liues of <hi>Fabius</hi> and <hi>Anthony,</hi> which <hi>Budeus</hi> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>llowing, soone slipped into error; As hee could not choose, the quoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent being false. &amp;c.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Dio</note>For <hi>Dio</hi> who can make question of his excellency and sufficiency, beeing a man that spent his whole time in affaires of the state, and running through all the degrees of Office, was twice chosen <hi>Consull,</hi> and after that <hi>Proconsull;</hi> wherein he gouerned the Prouinces worthily, &amp; no doubt ioyned experience to his great learning. He it was, that collected the order of their Dyets, their Magistracies, the course of their proceeding<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in law, the inauguration of their Princes, and the policies of their state. Yet seemeth he to striue of purpose, to maintaine the factions of <hi>Caesar</hi> and <hi>Anthony,</hi> against <hi>Pompey</hi> and <hi>Cicero.</hi> And those prodegies which hapned in the borders of the <hi>Marconra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni</hi> he attributeth to <hi>Arnulphus</hi> the <hi>Egiptian,</hi> &amp; not to the Christians, whereat <hi>Turtullian, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sebius, Orosius, Iustine, Paulus Diaconus,</hi> and <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> himselfe contested, in his letters to the Senat. Many are of opinion that <hi>Diodorus</hi> was matcheable vnto him;<note place="margin">Diodorus</note> many, that he deserueth precedencie; for my part I see no such reason, either for phrase (thē which, nothing could be penned more vulgar) or for method of History. That whereof he meaneth to relate, he disposeth of truely, orderly and bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>fely, in the beginning of euery booke: The proofe whereof you may find in his first booke, wherein he diuideth his whole worke into fortie Bookes, and in six, includeth all the former time before the <hi>Troian</hi> war; The eleuen following beginning at the <hi>Troian</hi> warre, end with the death of <hi>Alexander;</hi> the last four and twenty, discend to the wars of the <hi>Gals.</hi> The which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation amounteth to about one thousand one hundred and thirty yeares, besides the reports before the <hi>Troian</hi> war, which the <hi>Ancients</hi> deemed fabulous. From whence, to the return of the <hi>Heracli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dae</hi> (according to the account of <hi>Apollodorus</hi>) he numbreth XC. yeares: from thence to the first <hi>Olimpiad CCCXXVIII.</hi> from the first Olimpiad, to the war of the <hi>Gals DCCXXX.</hi> Likewise, he only of al the Ancient, adi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ynd vnto his history the times wherin the most eminent Philosophers, Poets, and Historiographers flourished. As in his fourteenth Book, he witness<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th, that <hi>Ctesias</hi> began his history at <hi>Ninus, Lysiades</hi> being <hi>Archon.</hi> He also collected together six bookes of this Author concerning the Empire of the <hi>Assyrians,</hi> and as many of the <hi>Persians,</hi> for the most part generallie discenting from <hi>Herodotus.</hi> Whose Authorities <hi>Plutarch, Pausanias, Athenaeus,</hi> and almost all the <hi>Greeke</hi> Authors do also follow. To vs is nothing remaining but an Epitome.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Thucidides</note>
      <hi>Thucidides</hi> (he saith) began his history (<hi>Charites</hi> being <hi>Archon, Q. Furius,</hi> and <hi>M. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pirius</hi> Consuls, (viz.) from the restoring of the <hi>Heraclidae</hi> to the taking of <hi>Perinthus.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Theopōpus</note>
      <hi>Theopompus</hi> began at the first year of <hi>Phillip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon, Calimedes</hi> being <hi>Archō,</hi> in the hundred &amp; fiue Olimpiad (<hi>C. Genutius</hi> &amp; <hi>L. Aemilius</hi> being Consuls. And for that which <hi>Diodorus</hi> reprehendeth in <hi>Theopomp,</hi> for the same may another reprehend <hi>Diodore.</hi> Of eight and fiftie Bookes (saith he) since are suspitious; So saith <hi>Viues,</hi> of sorty of <hi>Diodors,</hi> we haue scarse twelue remaining, fiue whereof are stuffed with such idle matter, <hi>That nothing was euer writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten more fabulous.</hi> And whereas he protesteth, to write an vniuersall Historie, he onely discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth of the <hi>Greekes;</hi> and that with such prolixity (that both forgetting his <hi>Laconique</hi> breuitie, and his obiection of tediousnesse against <hi>Thucidides</hi>) he spendeth more Paper in reciting the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of one <hi>Gilippus</hi> a <hi>Lacedemonian,</hi> than in the whole history of the warres managed through <hi>Italy</hi> in three hundred yeares. His long digression vpon the Pestilence at <hi>Athens,</hi> and the coniec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures thereof, who can indure? His exposition vpon the <hi>Lunary</hi> yeare is as absurd, whereby men were accounted to haue liued one thousand and two hundred yeares, as though euen in those Ages many of the Patriarchs did not exceed that limitation.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="9"/>He avoweth, that he spent thirty yeares in trauell, and writing his Historie: which if it bee true, then can I not but maruell why he wrote the affaires of <hi>Italy,</hi> the next, adioyning Countrey so slenderly, considering be liued in the times of the <hi>Romans</hi> highest prosperity (viz:) in <hi>Caesars</hi> Dictator-ship. For if you compare him to <hi>Lyuy</hi> or <hi>Dionisius,</hi> you shall find them varying almost in all places, but especially in their computation of their <hi>Fasti</hi> and <hi>Olimpiads,</hi> wherein hee is most incertaine. Which peraduenture might be occasioned through his defect in the <hi>Latine</hi> tongue, apparantly manifest in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting euery where <hi>Phouriō</hi> for <hi>Furius,</hi> as if the Orthography had bin alone. And as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> writing <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Horatius</hi> for <hi>Marcus, Sp. Manius</hi> for <hi>Melius, Lactuca</hi> for <hi>Luctatius, Trigemmus,</hi> for <hi>Tricostus,</hi> I could haue imputed the error to the mistaking of the Printer, were not they Persons of Consular rank, <hi>Decemvirs</hi> and <hi>Tribunes,</hi> in the Catalogue of whom he somtimes ouer-leapeth three, sometimes foure, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>But these mistakings are easily holpen by the studious labours of <hi>Charles Sigonius,</hi> and <hi>Onu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrius Panuinius,</hi> both worthily deseruing the Epithites of learning for their exquities searches of the <hi>Roman</hi> Antiquities.</p>
   <p>Wherein <hi>Cornelius Tacitus</hi> hath likewise plaid the part of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o lesse commendable an Author.<note place="margin">Tacitus</note> For although he wrote the gests but of one Age, (viz:) from <hi>Tiberius</hi> to <hi>Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ua,</hi> yet omitted he neyther things of weightiest, indifferent, or of meanest consequence. In his fourth booke, though he protested to write neither of battailes, nor of taking of Citties, nor ouerthrowes of A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mies, nor the contentions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the people and the Nobility; concluding it to be a worke thought inglorious, yet profitable. And by and by after (saith) we will annex cruell edicts, daily arraignments, hippocriticall friendships, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of Innocents, and the causes of these misfortunes. Yet describeth hee most fully, all the warres which happened in those times, wherein he was either a Commander or Actor. After the battaile of <hi>Actium</hi> no man penned the Art of Warre and pleading, in a larger method then he. For he spent the greatest part of his time in military seruices, and imployments of the Cittie, and being chosen Procon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sull, he obtained the lower <hi>Germany</hi>: at which time he so perfectly and truely set downe the manners, Lawes and Customes of that Nation, that at this day the <hi>Germans</hi> do attribute their Antiquities to one onely <hi>Tacitus.</hi> And to his greater glory, that <hi>Tacitus Augustus,</hi> who f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r his excellent wisedome was created Emperour by the Vniuersal consent of the Lords and the Legions, deriued his discent from this our Author, and fill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d all Libraries with as manie of his workes as were remaining vnperished. In method of discourse he is maruellous short, sententious, and full of wisedome: as appeareth for a tast by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se few insuing sentences.</p>
   <p>What could be pronounced with more breuity and more bitternesse, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> to say of <hi>Sei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nus? That no man could stand in his good grace<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> vnlesse <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ee made his way thereto by villanie.</hi> What of <hi>Poppea? That shee put no difference betweene married men and Adulterers, but there setled her fancy, where she saw most profit arising.</hi> The Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>shnesse, the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinenci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> &amp; drunk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nnes of <hi>Vitellius,</hi> he inueyeth against most bitterly; but indeed nothing could be spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kē bitter inough against such a person; who besides the manifold imperfections of his nature perswaded the Lords to establish the Lawe of incest, and <hi>Married the Vncle to his Sisters daughter.</hi> One day walking amongst the dead bodies of slaughtered Cittizens, when he saw euerie man to loath that intollerable st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nch: Ob! saith he, <hi>The dead enemy sauoureth sweete, but the Cittizen swee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If you will haue his opinion of Lawes and Gouernment, what could bee more grauely spoken, them to say<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>That euery great Magistrate ought to be acquainted with somewhat that was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, thereof to make vse to the common good. Plato</hi> differed not much from this asserti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; They <hi>may as well go about to cut off all Hydrates heads</hi> (saith he) <hi>as to take away al Imperfections from Lawes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If you desire to looke into the method of pleading, the Office of a Senator, or the Antiquities, not of the <hi>Romans</hi> onely, but of many other Nations, you shall no where find so plentifull a Haruest. What should I say? Onely this, that for men of eminency, Magistrates and Iudges, no Historiographer, can be read with like profit.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="10"/>And therefore it grieueth me, that some sew haue censured him with reprehension, whome I would not stand to refute, were not their Authorities of good credit. As <hi>Alciat,</hi> who was so vnad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uised as to call his truely praise-worthy History, Thorny, or ouer-growne with Briars, in that Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle which he wrote to <hi>Iouius.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The next are those, who cannot relish him for his hard phrase, but they are such, who had rather be alwaies plodding vpon easie and trifling studies, then erect their spirits to be perfect in those graue relations, which states-men and Princes haue ante-acted, to future profit and example. As for <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat,</hi> I see not, why he should contemne an Author so generally allowed, and himselfe notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding boast of his owne eloquence, vnlesse for that <hi>Decius</hi> blotting his name out of the Roll of the Lawyers, notwithstanding called him <hi>Ceceronian;</hi> as <hi>Ierom</hi> writeth, that he was scourged before the Tribunall of Christ, for that he wrote like a <hi>Ciceronian,</hi> not like a Christian. Howeuer <hi>Ierom</hi> did suffer, su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e I am <hi>Tacitus</hi> doth suffer his hard censure without desert. But let this passe for a iest, <hi>Budaeus</hi> with no lesse bitternesse, tearmeth him of all writers the wickedest, because be wrote opro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briously against the Christians, which was the reason indeed (as I think) that moued <hi>Turtullian</hi> to call him Lier; <hi>Orosius</hi> Flatterer.</p>
   <p>But as <hi>Marcellus</hi> answered the younger <hi>Cato,</hi> that a light woman did euer euill in doing light, but not euill in taking her hire being once light: So <hi>Tacitus,</hi> in that he was not a Christian, did euilly; but wrote not euilly against Christians, being (as he was) an Heathen. I for my part shoulde haue censured him wicked, if whatsoeuer Religion he adored, he had not laboured to maintaine it with the ouerthrow of the opposite; especially when he saw the Christians and <hi>Iewes,</hi> as Sorcerers and men defamed f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r Adulteries and other heynous crimes daily drawne to execution; what Histori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>grapher could haue moderated his pen?</p>
   <p>For ignorance, if any Author may be excused, then surely may <hi>Tacitus,</hi> for fetching <hi>Iudaeos,</hi> from <hi>Ida</hi> a Mountaine in <hi>Creet, Quasi</hi> Idaeos; As well as <hi>Nicholaus Damascenus</hi> for dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>Hierosolyna quasi Ierosoula, pera</hi> for <hi>Iera sulein.</hi> Well, if he des<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rue so heauie a cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure for this fault, what shall we determine of <hi>Vlpian,</hi> who wrote seauen Bookes <hi>De torquendis Christianis,</hi> and those not to teach knowledge, but to deuise exquisite torments.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Trāquillus</note>
      <hi>Tranquillus</hi> must likewise vndergo the very same censure, where he discourseth of the Christians, and yet hath it bin his good hap for the residue of his Historie to carrie this report amongst the iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, <hi>That neuer was any thing better written by any Historiographer.</hi> Some men are dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleased for his recitall of hase and triuiall matters; but such should remember, that amongst the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and speeches of Princes, nothing ought to seeme light, nothing vnworthie obseruation, beecause they liue in the eye of the multitude, and according to their presidents the world will be conformable. That he tooke too much paines in perticuler penning the incontinencies of Princes, which <hi>Tacitus</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ted, I will not excuse him.</p>
   <p>But in this ouer-sight <hi>Lampridius</hi> did excell him. For he relateth so many bes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iall sorts of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures deuised by <hi>Heliogabalus,</hi> and those in such open tearmes, that he seemeth to haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>enned thē rather for Imitation, then Narration. Both of them serued in the priuy Counsels of Princes, but espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>Tranquillus,</hi> who was Secretarie to <hi>Adrian,</hi> and depriued thereof, for being more familiar with the Emperors wife, then the custome of Court-like modestie could endure. The residue that wrote the liues of the succeeding Emperors, as <hi>Dio, Spartianus, Capitolinus, Herodianus, Trebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius, Vopiscus, Entropius, Lampridius, Volcatius, Ammianus, Pomponius Laetus, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rosius</hi> and <hi>Sextus Aurelius,</hi> were not so highlie imployed in the state, as was <hi>Lampridius,</hi> which <hi>Vopiscus</hi> doth freely confesse, calling him a most refined Author, and truly. For these are his words: <hi>Hee was a man neither proude of his place, nor giuen to vice, nor swayed by passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>He writeth, that <hi>Caligula</hi> in the beginning of his raigne was as compleat a Prince, both for giftes of minde and bodie, as none more compleat, but afterward proued so vnsatiate a licentia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in all sortes of vices, that no monster in Nature could be comparable vnto him, So likewise he relateth the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb facs="10"/>
first fiue yeares of <hi>Nero;</hi> and then discourseth, how <hi>Claudius</hi> was of so blockish a spirit, that euen the basest at the Barre would call him <hi>Foole,</hi> sitting vpon the seat of iudgement: and lastlie, amplyfieth that notable Iudgement of the Emperour, before whom a woman being brought, which would not acknowledge her owne childe, with Arguments inforced on both sides so strong and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that hardly any man could tell what to determine; by commanding the woman to marrie the young man, she confessed the truth. What could haue bin more wisely decided by <hi>Salomon</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, the Maister of wisedome?</p>
   <p>The like industry for truth was not in <hi>Herodian,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Herodian</note> though he had the meanes, but for that which he wrote, he is often noted of error by <hi>Spartianus</hi> and <hi>Capitolinus.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Moreouer, in <hi>Tranquillus</hi> you shall find many good instructions of the <hi>Roman</hi> Antiquities, their ancient customes, their lawes, their statutes, and such Edicts of the Senate, as no where shal you meet with the like. The royali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es and prerogatiues of their Princes onely he and <hi>Tacitus</hi> recorded.</p>
   <p>The man whom we may match with <hi>Tranquillus,</hi> in my opinion is <hi>Velleius Paterculus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Velleius Paterculus</note> who besid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s his great learning, bore Offices of Honour both in the field &amp; Citty. His sweet and elegant phrase I will not speake to, but avow his method of breuity and perspicuity (if wee had his whole workes) in relating the <hi>Roman</hi> Antiquities from vtmost memory to be such, as therein second to no man he ought to be iudged. His Orations in the praises of Men of Marke, are excellent and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy himselfe, as you may read in his Encomions of <hi>Pompey, Caesar, Cicero,</hi> which were not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as pertinent to the scope of his history, but by way of preface to the vnderstanding of his history.</p>
   <p>Wherein <hi>G. Bellay</hi> vic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>roy of <hi>Naples,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Bellay</note> in a litle Booke of his, concerning the antiquities of the <hi>Galles</hi> hath imitated his method, and hath left an excellent president for future Historiographers to behold and follow. He wrote likewise in <hi>Latine</hi> and <hi>French</hi> the exped<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tion of <hi>Charles</hi> the fifte into <hi>Prouince;</hi> a workful of wit and wisedome: as he could not otherwise do, being quicke of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ll learned, and fully experimented in affaires of state: wherin he spent his whole time, either imployed in Counsell, in Ambassies, or in command of Armies: his vacant houres he dedicated to the Muses. Insomuch, that amongst the French Nobility, this glorie ought onely to be his; That he was the first man <hi>which gaue weapons to Learning, and Learning to weapons.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause no man shal accuse one being his Countrymā (for he was of <hi>Anioy</hi>) of flattery<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> let him belieue that <hi>Sleydan</hi> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h spent much more paper in his commendation; vpon whom, when he had said al he could to his highest praise, he giue this testimony; That he was not only worthy to be called, <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licae nobilitatis Decus.</hi> Wherefore let him march in ranke with <hi>Polibus, Thucidides, Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon, Caesar,</hi> &amp; <hi>Tacitus,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>or that he examined with an vnstaind pen the reasons of accidēts, their beginnings, their ripen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ngs, their ends; and with them their policies, their actions, their Orations. For the Obi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ō that he wrote but litle, that is not material in choise of history, since euery man may iudge a Lyon by his claw. Next copious <hi>Guicciardin</hi> presenteth himself,<note place="margin">Guicciar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din</note> whom I would haue said, had wrote in Imvation of the former, had they not bin liuing at one time. And although he neuer trauelled fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then <hi>Italy,</hi> neither was matchable to <hi>Bellay</hi> in militarie imployments, yet notwithstanding by the generall verdict of many grauemen, he is adiudged to ante-cede all modern Historiographers, if not the Ancient. For whatsoeuer falleth within compasse of question, he it neuer so intricate, there sheweth he an admirable finenesse of wit in discoursing vpon accidents, euery where interlacnig graue sentences to good purpose: As in one place, he couertly taxeth the French of improuidence, for inuading Prouinces like tempests, but keeping and maintaining them like faint-harted Cowardes: giuing them to vnderstand, that militarie acquisitions were not onelie vnprofitable vnto them, but likewise burdensome and full of losse. A saying worthie so graue an Author, and fit to be thought vpon by all intruding Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. In another place he glanceth at the ouer-weening conceits of the <hi>Venetians</hi> in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se words. <hi>The Venetians (saith he) all Italy being in a flaming fire, sat still, and without mouing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected the issue of the warre, and their portion of prey, as if no man durst to haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended their Wisedomes. But a temporizer ought to be superior in force, or els to run the same course that the strongest doth.</hi> The which reprehensions haue in them no gall, no ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquy; neither vsed hee to praise or dispraise any man before hee were deade, and that
<pb facs="11"/>
without affection or flattery. As was manifest in Pope <hi>Leo,</hi> by whose fauours he parchased great wealth, Honour, and aduancement. For he elected him Generall of the Ecclesiasticall forces, &amp; chief Commander through his whole Territories: And yet he giueth him this censure, <hi>That hee was a Prince indowed with many Vertues, and as many vices.</hi> And of all writers he alone rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his incons<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ancie, in confederating first against King <hi>Francis,</hi> and after playing the Foxe with <hi>Charles</hi> the Emperour; That when by his helpe he had throwne the <hi>French</hi> out of <hi>Italy,</hi> he mought the easiler haue dealt with the <hi>Spanish.</hi> Againe, what could be more truely spoken of <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> That <hi>coloured all his vnsatiable desires, with pretences of Religion, and the common good.</hi> Another argument of his integrity and vnpassionate disposition, was his refutation of <hi>Paulus Iouius</hi> his Oration <hi>de morbo gallico,</hi> in fauour of the <hi>French:</hi> with whom hee had good cause to haue bin offended, for the hard siege they gaue him at <hi>Placentia,</hi> wherein himselfe and his whole for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes were ingaged, had he not valiantly defended the place. <hi>Reason it is</hi> (saith he) <hi>to disburden the</hi> French <hi>of the infamy of this disease, when as the</hi> Spanish <hi>broug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t it into</hi> Italy <hi>frō the westerne Islands.</hi> Such was his loue, such his care, to write nothing but truth! and therefore he either setteth downe nothing at aduenture, or what he setteth downe, hee proueth with reasons of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity. For it is reported that he had the transcripts of all Letters, Decrees, Confederacies, Treaties, and Orations; and therefore boldly vsed these words. <hi>Such a one spake in this manner:</hi> or where he was doubtfull, <hi>Such a one spake to this or like purpose;</hi> wherein hee is altogether different from <hi>Iouius,</hi> who as he deuised a great part of his History, so coined he out of his owne braine (as schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers vse to do their Schoolasticall declamations) all his Orations. A presumption most mani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring by the Oration of <hi>Baylon,</hi> which <hi>Guicciardine</hi> extracted out of the Originall copie, and rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth cleane contrary to <hi>Iouius.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Besides, be was so diligent a searcher of Actions, persons, places, and counsels, that he seemed to haue trauelled, through all the Citties, Borrough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, Castles, and riuers of <hi>Italy,</hi> and (which is most effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to haue perused their publique Records.</p>
   <p>What euer was reported by the vulgar, bee neuer omitted; but noted it as he found it; As in the battle of <hi>Maurit</hi> where the <hi>French</hi> defeated the <hi>Swizzers;</hi> wherein he could not auouch certainely what numbers were slaine, <hi>Because</hi> (saith he) <hi>some spake vpon enuy, some vpon sauour, and others vpon heare-say: many reported XIIII. thousand, as many ten thousand: Some eight thousand, and others but three thousand.</hi> His historie of <hi>Italy</hi> containeth the tearme of for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie yeare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>; what was without the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>unds thereof, he toucheth sparingly and in measure. The wars of the <hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Persians,</hi> though his intelligence was much better then <hi>Iouius,</hi> hee wittingly le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> passe, least by affirming things of doubtfull certaintie, he should incurre suspition; yet, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y should not altogether he in ignorance, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>in inhreth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>m lightlie, in this maner: <hi>It was reported that</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limus <hi>inuaded</hi> Syria <hi>and</hi> Egipt.</p>
   <p>Some men note him of prolixity: but those, who either vpon loue or occasion, are desirous to read affaires of state, and the vicissitude of wordlie occurrants, let them neuer grow w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie of that faul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>; because no part of the vniuersall earth, presented more nouelties, more alterarations, then <hi>Italy</hi> alone did in those times. And how easie a matter it was for him to write truelie, who by the generall suffragies of the <hi>Italian</hi> Nation, was indowed with singuler wisedome, learning, integritie, and experience, who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not? For without doubt, sithence some men wrote one thing, some another, and euerie one after his owne fancie, we cannot but make reckoning, that it proceeded from diuine prouidence, amongest such a rapsodie of pen-men, to find one whose credite soared so high, as vtterlie to ecclipse, if not to extinguish, not onelie the blind lights of vulgar fellowes, but also the impostures of <hi>Iouius</hi> and <hi>Bembus.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Bonibus</note>For although <hi>Benibus</hi> were a man of good place, eloquent, and long imployed in the Generall affairs of <hi>Italy,</hi> yet surelie wee must say, that he wrote manie things in fauour of his Cittizens otherwise then truth, or else suffer <hi>Guicciardine</hi> to be conuinced of manie an vntruth. Of which disputable imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, let this one president sway for either. After the <hi>French</hi> had vtterly broken the <hi>Venetians</hi> at <hi>Fornoue,</hi> and as the report went, had purchased their way by the sword, <hi>Bembus</hi> concludeth, that they neither ouerthr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>vv, nor were ouerthrown, but disgraceth their returne into <hi>Fraunce,</hi> by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull
<pb facs="11"/>
name of a flight. Which <hi>Guicciardine</hi> more Soldier-like relateth in this manner: <hi>If it may be accounted victory, to bring our desires to their wished ends, then surely the</hi> French <hi>were victors, because they vndertooke the battell to no other end, but to bring the King in safety into</hi> France, which they performed. And therefore, sithence <hi>they rowted their enemies, whereof some fell by the sword, and others were drowned in the riuer</hi> Tarus, <hi>who would demand other tokens of victory?</hi> In the battell of <hi>Rauenna, Bembus</hi> likewise dissembleth the truth; the honour of which dai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s iourney no man hetherto denyed the <hi>French. For</hi> (saith he) <hi>of common souldiers and Horsemen, there were on both sides aboue eighteene thousand slaine; each party suffered like losse, but each party inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not like fortune.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Wherefore in that he tearmeth the <hi>Venetians</hi> the <hi>Bulwarke</hi> of <hi>Italy,</hi> &amp; the Ornament of the Christian, Common-wealth, magnifying their Iustice, their faith, their greatnesse and power; yea, and the incredible pompe and strength of euery <hi>Venetian</hi> gally against the <hi>Turke,</hi> together with the Religion, modesty, and piety of euery priuate Cittizen, I say, I can affirme nothing more true, then that hee plaide the part of a good Cittizen, and not of a good Historiographer. That euerie where he tannteth the <hi>French,</hi> for their inconstancie and breach of oath with the <hi>Venetians</hi> and <hi>Alfonsus Auila,</hi> that humour more discommendeth himselfe, then his enemy. For, if it be infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous by the Lawe of armes, for a souldier to reuile an aduerse Nation, how much more disgrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is this humour in an Historiographer, especially if in that, wherof he accuseth another, he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selse be guiltie. As without doubt, they were of that accusation, which <hi>Guicciardin</hi> layeth vppon the <hi>Venetians</hi> for breach of the league. Whom he accuseth not with suspitions of double dealing, but flatly affirmeth, <hi>That they receiued into their Cittie</hi> Avila, <hi>euen then Triumphing ouer the</hi> French, <hi>and their sworne enemie.</hi> And that more is, did what they could to <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude him in the league, the King of</hi> France <hi>being most vnwilling thereto.</hi> That there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which hee writeth Oratour-like of the vnfaithfulnesse of the <hi>French,</hi> may goe as currant as his relation, <hi>That during the</hi> Venetian <hi>warre in</hi> Apulia, <hi>such Armies of Crowes and Vultures combated in the Aire, that twelue Carts were numbred to bee loden vvith their dead bodies.</hi> Of which report <hi>Bembus</hi> speaketh not doubtfully, but with much confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
   <p>By his owne Testimony<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> he was threescore yeares old, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n he b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>gan to writ his Historie, at which age, hee cou'd hard'y endure to take that pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, which we do exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ct man Historiographer. His owne words are: <hi>I am weary to set downe the matters of smallest moment in that warre.</hi> And againe, <hi>Who can endure to read all without tediousnesse?</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se are meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the phrases of Ora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ors, as was also the Oration of <hi>Lauredan</hi> against <hi>Mimus</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>uouring of the same affectation; wherein hee stood so precisely vpon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> purity of a wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d, that fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> were not true Grammer, he would refuse it, were it neuer so significant. The Emperour of <hi>Turkes</hi> he woulde stile <hi>King of Thrace,</hi> being scarcely the twentieth part of his Kingdome: and the Duke of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine,</hi> King: If he did it for phrase sake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in my Opinion he did worse for se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> sake.</p>
   <p>But <hi>Procopius</hi> was farre vnlike <hi>Bembus</hi>:<note place="margin">Procopius</note> for it should seeme, that he neither neglected, or vnderstood not the method of History, nor the elegancie of the <hi>Greek</hi> tongue, but related the bare accident with diligent obseruation of thinges of small moment. And for that he alwaies accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied <hi>Bellisarius</hi> in Action, was of his Counsell, imployed in diuers Embassies, and indifferent wel learned, I make no doubt to ranke him with the best. And againe, I could not but allow him the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of a most true Authour, because he setteth downe the Letters, the Counsels, the leagues, and Orations in diuers and different stile of speeches (infallable arguments of true relations) but that he remembreth his <hi>Bellisarius</hi> somewhat more often, then modesty may warrant, and that manie times very foolishly.</p>
   <p>And yet no where so foolish, as where he excuseth the murder of <hi>Constantianus,</hi> maister of the Horse to <hi>Iustinian</hi> the Emperour, procured by <hi>Bellisarius,</hi> and would haue the worlde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, <hi>That the destinies and not his Maister had decreed, that</hi> Constantianus <hi>should die
<pb facs="12"/>
in that manner,</hi> His coniectures of the thirty Hogges and the Statue of <hi>Theodorus,</hi> I reckon as childish; As also his dimension of <hi>Thule</hi> to be twice as great as <hi>Brittaine,</hi> being indeed not so, by halfe. But his report, that <hi>Vesuvius,</hi> scituated on this side <hi>Naples,</hi> should disgorge ashes, which with the wind were carried as farre as <hi>Bizantium,</hi> passeth all beliefe, being prodigies altogether sauouring of <hi>Graecian</hi> leuity, wherein the <hi>Heathen</hi> Historiographers, are not onely to be taxed, but likewise, the Ecclesiasticall.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Nicephorus</note>
      <hi>Nicephorus Calistus</hi> is stuffed with like Fables, and <hi>Zonoras,</hi> otherwise an allowable Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, with <hi>Nicephorus Gregoras,</hi> are of the same straine, and now and then <hi>Eusebus Caesarien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis:</hi> As where with eagernesse of protestation, he affirmeth that he saw, a plant grow of his owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord at the base of a piller. Whereupon a brazen Statue of Christmas erected, and by the woman cured of her issue of blood dedicated to our <hi>SAVIOVR</hi> three hundred yeares before. Which as soone as by growth it had touched the extreamest hem of the Statues ingrauen garment, it proued to cure al ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of diseases.</p>
   <p>The like estimate ought to be had of the workes of <hi>Antoninus, Adonis, Saxo Grāmaticus, Sigis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert, Phriculphus, Nauclerus, Marianus, Merlin, Vrspergensis, Annonius, Turpin, Guaguin, and such like old Annales;</hi> which notwithstanding we cannot vtterly want, &amp; of these too, some are better then other. For although <hi>Gregory Turenensis, Antonius Florentine, Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lielmus Bishop of Tire, and Abbas Vrspengēsis,</hi> relate many prodigious miracles, yet amongst them shall you find verie profitable and good obseruations, especially for those times, which as a man may say, were ouer whelmed with <hi>Barbarisme.</hi> For they were men long and much imployed in affaires of state and publicke Counsels; And therefore it may wel beseeme vs amongst their Garbish, to cut out their best annotations, as men doe Golde out of Rockes and Rubbish; especially where better are not to bee had.</p>
   <p>As, for the Historie of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> if you wil not credit <hi>Paulus Venetus</hi> and <hi>Hayton,</hi> then must you al most beleeue no man.<note place="margin">P. Venetus Haiton</note> And that which they wrote, is but little, and full of Fables; but of the two, <hi>Hayton</hi> is the truer. <hi>P. Venetus</hi> writeth, that the <hi>Caspian</hi> Sea is alwaies without Fish, except on fasting daies: that <hi>Quinzay</hi> containeth in circuit seauenty miles, and hath twelue thousand bridges, vnder which, For their concauitie, Ships vnder saile may passe, and repasse. The Acts, Customes, Lawes, and Religion of the <hi>Tartars</hi> you must vnderstand where you can.</p>
   <p>The state of <hi>Aethiopia F. Aluarus</hi> hath written with better integritie and more warinesse, being since confirmed by Straungers,<note place="margin">F: Aluarus</note> good Authors, and late Trauellers, and with great delight to bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vsed.</p>
   <p>The late Histories of the <hi>Gothes, Saxons, Neruians, Sarmatians</hi> or <hi>Polonians</hi> and <hi>Danes, Zēglerus, Cromerus, Crantzius</hi> &amp; <hi>Olaus</hi> haue published; al except <hi>Olaus</hi> very probable Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, who now and then telleth wouders: whereof manie, by the Testimony of Authors and good wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses may induce perswasion; as the metamorphosing of men into Wolues, once set downe by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of <hi>Herodotus, Pomponius Mela,</hi> and the <hi>Ancients,</hi> and nowe againe verified by the <hi>Moderne.</hi> Which <hi>Gaspar Pencer,</hi> a man of great Learning, well aduised, and one that had tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelled through most partes of <hi>Europe,</hi> did signifie vnto me, that hee heard it crediblie reported by the Inhabitantes to bee true. Which whether it bee a secret of Nature, as is storied of <hi>Parrhasius,</hi> or an influence of Diuine punnishment, as it is recorded of <hi>Nabuchadnezar,</hi> I cannot yet resolue.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Leo Afer</note>After <hi>Aluaresius</hi> followeth <hi>Leo Afer,</hi> and for similitude of subiect, I will compare him to <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponius, Strabo,</hi> and <hi>Pausanias,</hi> whome I will hence-forward tearme <hi>Geographistorici,</hi> for their <hi>Geographicall</hi> method of Historie. <hi>Strabo</hi> lightly toucheth the kingdomes and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weales of the whole world, <hi>Pausanias</hi> onely the Prouinces of <hi>Greece,</hi> but so exactly describeth their greatnesse, their declinings, the inhabitants, the Citties, Castles, Riuers, Hilles, Springs, Temples, and statues, that by al mens opinions in that kind, be challengeth precedency. So <hi>Leo Afer,</hi> by birth a <hi>Moor,</hi> by habitation a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> first a <hi>Mahumetan</hi> and afterward a Christian, after he had Trauailed
<pb facs="12"/>
almost the better part of <hi>Affricke, Asia</hi> the lesse, and a good portion of <hi>Europe,</hi> was taken Prisoner by Pirats, and presented to Pope <hi>Leo.</hi> During the tearme of which captiuity, be translated into the <hi>Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> tongue these remembrances, which with infinite toile, hee had gathered in the <hi>Arabian</hi> language concerning <hi>Affrica,</hi> the customes, lawes, and diuers people thereof, with the scituation and description of the whole Region. The art military he seldome toucheth, but the ouerthrowes of their Kings, giuen and taken, he briesely relateth, without Orations or ornament of stile, Geographically, not Historically, and yet with pleasing delight of noueltie, he cōfineth his vnwilling Reader to studious perseuerance. He thrusteth vpon vs no great impossibilities, vnlesse it be the admirable docility of the <hi>Egiptian</hi> Asse, of which himselfe was an eye-witnesse. Likewise, that the tailes of certaine Sheepe of <hi>Egipt,</hi> shoulde weigh some fiftie pound, some one hundred and twe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tie pound: It is the report also of <hi>Bellonius, Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronimus,</hi> and <hi>Cardanus.</hi> At a word, bee onely of all men hath discouered that Nation, which lay buried in ignorance and Barbarisme a thousand yeares before his time.</p>
   <p>Next after him approcheth <hi>F. Leandrus</hi> and <hi>S. Munster</hi>; the former described <hi>Italy,</hi> the other all <hi>Germany</hi> as liuely to viewe, as if it were in Maps or Tables, adioyning thereto the History of the various fashions and maners of the people. But <hi>Munster</hi> had done well, if he had turned his <hi>Cosmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphiam</hi> into <hi>Germanographiam,</hi> being indeed nothing else to speak on, saue a particuler descrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Heluetia,</hi> their scituations, people, and discent.</p>
   <p>But as our <hi>Geographistorici</hi> mingled <hi>Topography</hi> with story:<note place="margin">Xenophon</note> so our <hi>Philosophistorici</hi> beu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified their Narrations of Action with precepts of wisedome. In which kind, great is the praise of <hi>Xe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nophon,</hi> yea, the greater, in that he had no president to imitate (as <hi>Velleius</hi> witnesseth of <hi>Homer</hi>) nor none that shall be able to imitate him. Nearest approacheth <hi>Plutarch,</hi> then <hi>Laertius,</hi> and thirdly <hi>Philo Iudaeus,</hi> betweene whom and <hi>Plato</hi> the Ancients in my iudgement gaue a most true censure.</p>
   <p>Equall vnto these is <hi>Iosippus;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iosippus</note> or if inferior in secrets of Philosophy, farre superiour in the sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Antiquitie. At which <hi>Ierom</hi> doth wonder, that such exquisit knowledge of the <hi>Graecian</hi> dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents, should be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ound in a man of the <hi>Irish</hi> Nation. But the reason thereof is apparant in his Bookes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Appion</hi> the <hi>Grammarian,</hi> wherin he so verisieth the writings of <hi>Moses</hi> (though sufficient-full of credit themselues) by the authorities of the <hi>Graecians,</hi> the <hi>Persians,</hi> the <hi>Egiptians</hi> &amp; <hi>Caldae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that nothing can be read with more profit, by those who are desirous to studio Antiquities. The Ages of the old world related by <hi>Moses,</hi> he confirmed by the Testimonies of twelue Historiographers, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> take away all scandall of incredulity. The Auncestry, saith, Religion, learning and integritie of his Countrey-men, He not onely preferreth before all Nations, thereby to reuiue the ecclipsed honor there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but also doth his vtmost to redeeme from obliuion and opposition, things of vndoubted veritie. For by his writings, the Fables of <hi>Herodotus, Diodorus,</hi> and <hi>Iustine,</hi> are easily to be refuted.</p>
   <p>After him, <hi>Hegesippus</hi> a <hi>Iew,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hegesippus</note> wrote fine Bookes of the <hi>Iewish</hi> wars, which <hi>Ambrose</hi> by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port turned into <hi>Latine.</hi> But <hi>Iosippus</hi> wrote better and truer, because hee was both in Action and command, and being prisoner to <hi>Vespahtian</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi>: Notwithstanding by their fauours purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the freedome of the Cit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie, and the Honour of a Statue. For in him were inuested these good parts of an Historiographer, which we haue mentioned before, (viz:) great learning, vnpassionate integrity, &amp; experience of affaires. His integritie is apparant in this; That being a <hi>Iew,</hi> he gaue notwithstanding a graue, ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ent, and La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dible Testimonie of Christ; whereas our Ecclesiasticall writers discoursing vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the aduersaries of our Religion, are so farre transported with Enuie, that they not onelie conceal their deserued commendations, but also disgrace them with most opprobrius and vndecent railings. Wherof, let <hi>Iulian</hi> the <hi>Apostata</hi> be the plaintife, who though he were worthie both of blame &amp; punishment, yet for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se things which be performed with good commendation and honour, he ought not to be silenced by an Historiographer:<note place="margin">Ammianus</note> wherein our writers haue generally faulted: And certes, should rather haue imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus</hi> his method and ardent desire of deliuering in <hi>Vtramque partem.</hi> nothing but truth: who after he had committed the neuer-dying vertues of Princes to memory, then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to display their vices, as euerie good Author ought to do. And the accusations which he laid vpon <hi>Iulian,</hi> were, that <hi>he mingled old Heathnish superstitions with the vnspotted &amp; simple</hi> (for those be his words) <hi>religion of the Christians: that he bereft them of all helps of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, &amp; cruely commanded the</hi> Countes Palatines <hi>of</hi> Constantius <hi>to be murdred.</hi>
      <pb facs="13"/>
These were his vices; His excellent vertues, as his temperance, his fortitude, his continency, his fauour to wisedome, and his Iustice aboue opinion, he proueth by action and witnesse. As in this one example for many. When <hi>Delphidius Gallus</hi> (a most sharpe Orator) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ad accused <hi>Numeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> President of <hi>Narbon</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> then lying at <hi>Paris,</hi> and was vrged to bring forth his proofes and witnesses: <hi>Most mighty</hi> Caesar <hi>(saith he) what man will euer be found guilty, if his bare deniall be sufficient to cleare him?</hi> To whom <hi>Caesar</hi> answered, <hi>And what man shall euer depart innocent, if one mans accusation should suffice to condemne him?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This <hi>Ammianus</hi> was a <hi>Graecian,</hi> a Knight, and a follower of <hi>Vrsicinus,</hi> maister of the horse in all the warres almost, which in those times were managed by the <hi>Romans</hi> in <hi>Europ,</hi> or <hi>Asia.</hi> His workes remaine whole, and digested into eighteen Bookes, beginning at the thirtieth yeare of the Emperor <hi>Constantius,</hi> and ending with <hi>Valeus.</hi> The o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>her thirteene are easie to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded out of other mens writings. He had begun at <hi>Nerua</hi> where <hi>Tacitus</hi> ended, and whom of all men he resolued to obserue and imitate. Onely heerein is the difference, that <hi>Tacitus</hi> (according to the times) had a speciall regard of the <hi>Roman</hi> el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>gance, but <hi>Ammianus</hi> vsed <hi>Italian</hi> phrases and som<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>imes neither <hi>Latine</hi> nor <hi>Romaine,</hi> but plaine <hi>Greeke.</hi> He much and often digresseth from the maine history, a disease whereunto euen the greatest Authors are much inclined; and whereof <hi>Possidonius</hi> doth grieuously complaine against <hi>Cicero.</hi> But <hi>Ammianus</hi> regarding the matter more then the phrase, salueth that Octiection against himselfe in this manner. <hi>In that</hi> (saith he) <hi>the text seemeth tedious, it profiteth our vnderstanding to the ful: for who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer affecteth ouermuch breuity, where things of doubtfull knowledge are related, seeketh after ease, but ripeneth not his iudgement.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Wherefore amongst such diuers and different variety of Authors, it is most necessarie, for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man to make a true and aduised choise of that learning whereunto his study standeth most adic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, least in this small and short leisure of life, he seeme not to haue read much, and y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t in points of amb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>guity cannot determine with himsel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e vpon what to resolue.</p>
   <p>As if he be throughly perswaded of <hi>Polidor</hi> for the affaires of England, (although he be suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to the <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>French</hi>) of <hi>Rhenanus</hi> for the Historie of <hi>Germany,</hi> and <hi>Aemilius</hi> for the state of <hi>France,</hi> then shall he need to take no great paines in <hi>Beda, Guagun, Gacus, Saxo,</hi> and such l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ke, who handled the said Histories without method or order: and no maruel; for as those Times afforded great plenty of writers, so their credits and reputations quickly vanished. <hi>Plutarch</hi> reckoneth vp three hundred that wrote the battaile of <hi>Marathon</hi>: And of thirty that committed to print the affaires of <hi>Italy,</hi> one onely mans credit and good method, haue quite put the residue to the horne.</p>
   <p>In these times the world swarmeth with such as commit to writing things of base and vulgar Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, whereas in times of greatest antiquity wee had almost none. And therefore because it were a labour infinite, to peruse euery mans papers, let the Iudicious Reader, out of manie, make choise of the better, by the assistance of these directions, (or by better of his owne, if he can) which we haue heere before described.</p>
   <p>Thus much for choise of History, which I avow not so positiuely to haue published, but that therin I am content to leaue euery man to his free election.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   <pb facs="13"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>