<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE GROVNDS AND CONTENTS OF THESE HISTORIES.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116165_Fr5_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10668</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20944</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116165</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE GROVNDS AND CONTENTS OF THESE HISTORIES.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The triumphs of Gods revenge against the crying and execrable sinne of (willfull and premeditated) murther : VVith his miraculous discoveries, and severe punishments thereof. In thirtie severall tragicall histories (digested into sixe bookes) committed in divers countries beyond the seas, never published, or imprinted in any other language. Histories which containe great varietie of mournfull and memorable accidents ... With a table of all the severall letters and challenges, contained in the whole sixe bookes. Written by Iohn Reynolds</title>
                 <author>Reynolds, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lee, William 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lee, William 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 75, 3, 81-181, 7, 187-260, 259-294, that is 293, 7, 303-414, 10, 425-527, 9, 337-404, 409-464 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summaries">
   <pb facs="233"/>
   <pb facs="233"/>
   <head>THE GROVNDS AND CONTENTS OF THESE HISTORIES.</head>
   <list>
      <item>
         <hi>HISTORIE. XXI. Babtistyna</hi> and <hi>Amarantha</hi> poyson their Eldest Sister <hi>Iaquinta,</hi> after which <hi>Amarantha</hi> causeth her servants, <hi>Bernardo</hi> and <hi>Pierya</hi> to stiffle her elder Sister <hi>Babtistyna</hi> in her Bed. <hi>Bernardo</hi> flying away, breakes his necke with the fall off his Horse, <hi>Pierya</hi> is hanged for the same, so likewise is <hi>Amarantha,</hi> and her body after burnt; <hi>Bernardo</hi> being buried, his body is againe taken up, and hanged to the Gallowes by his feete, then burnt and his ashes throwen into the River.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>HISTORIE. XXII. Martino</hi> poysoneth his Brother <hi>Pedro,</hi> and murthereth <hi>Monfredo</hi> in the streete; He after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards growes mad, and in confession reveales both these his murthers to Father <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> his Ghostly Father, who afterwards dying, reveales it by his Letter to <hi>Cecilliana,</hi> who was Widdow to <hi>Monfredo,</hi> and Sister to <hi>Pedro</hi> and <hi>Martino. Martino</hi> hath first his right hand cut off, and then is hanged for the same.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>HISTORIE. XXIII. Alphonso</hi> poysoneth his owne Mother <hi>Sophia,</hi> and after shoots and kils <hi>Cassino</hi> (as he was walking in his Garden) with a short Musket (or Carabyne) from a Window. Hee is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed for those two murthers, then burnt, and his ashes throwne into the River.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>HISTORIE XXIV. Pont Chausey</hi> kils <hi>La Roche</hi> in a Duell. <hi>Quatbrisson</hi> causeth <hi>Moncallier</hi> (an Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary) to poyson his owne Brother <hi>Valfontaine, Moncallier</hi> after fals, and breakes his necke from a paire of staires. <hi>Quatbrisson</hi> likewise causeth his Fathers Miller to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="234"/>
and strangle <hi>Marieta</hi> in her Bed, and to throw her body into his Mill-Pond, <hi>Pierot</hi> the Miller is broken alive on a wheele, and <hi>Quatbrisson</hi> first beheaded, then burnt for the same.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>HISTORIE. XXV. Vasti</hi> first murthereth his Sonne <hi>George,</hi> and next poysoneth his owne Wife <hi>Hester,</hi> and being afterwards almost killed by a mad Bull in the Fields, hee revealeth these his two murthers, for the which he is first hanged, and then burnt.</item>
   </list>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>