<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE GROVNDS, AND CONTENTS OF these HISTORIES.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116165_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10668</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20944</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116165</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE GROVNDS, AND CONTENTS OF these HISTORIES.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The triumphs of Gods revenge against the crying and execrable sinne of (willfull and premeditated) murther : VVith his miraculous discoveries, and severe punishments thereof. In thirtie severall tragicall histories (digested into sixe bookes) committed in divers countries beyond the seas, never published, or imprinted in any other language. Histories which containe great varietie of mournfull and memorable accidents ... With a table of all the severall letters and challenges, contained in the whole sixe bookes. Written by Iohn Reynolds</title>
                 <author>Reynolds, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lee, William 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lee, William 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 75, 3, 81-181, 7, 187-260, 259-294, that is 293, 7, 303-414, 10, 425-527, 9, 337-404, 409-464 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summaries">
   <pb facs="58"/>
   <pb n="85" facs="58"/>
   <head>THE GROVNDS, AND CONTENTS OF these HISTORIES.</head>
   <list>
      <item>
         <hi>HISTORIE VI. Victorina</hi> causeth <hi>Sypontus</hi> to stabbe and murther her first Husband <hi>Souranza,</hi> and shee her selfe poysoneth <hi>Fassino</hi> her second: so they both being miraculously detected and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed of these their cruell Murthers, hee is beheaded, and shee hang'd and burnt for the same.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>HISTORIE VII. Catalina</hi> causeth her Wayting Mayd <hi>Ausilva</hi> two severall times attempt to poyson her owne Sister <hi>Berinthia;</hi> wherein fayling, shee afterwards makes an Empericke, termed <hi>Sarmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ata,</hi> poyson her said Mayd <hi>Ansilva: Catalina</hi> is killed with a Thunder bolt, and <hi>Sarmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ata</hi> hang'd for poysoning <hi>Ansilva. Antonio</hi> steales <hi>Berinthia</hi> away by her owne consent; whereupon her Brother <hi>Sebastiano</hi> fights with <hi>Antonio,</hi> and kills him in a Duell: <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthia</hi> in revenge hereof, afterwards murthereth her Brother <hi>Sebastiano;</hi> she is adjudged to be immured betwixt two Walls, and there languisheth and dyes.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>HISTORIE VIII. Belluile</hi> treacherously murthereth <hi>Poligny</hi> in the street. <hi>Laurieta, Poligny's</hi> Mistris, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayeth <hi>Belluile</hi> to her Chamber, and there in revenge shoots him thorow the body with ae Pistoll, when assisted by her Wayting-Mayd <hi>Lucilla,</hi> they likewise give him many wounds with a Ponyard, and so murther him▪ <hi>Lucilla</hi> flying for this fact, is drowned in a Lake, and <hi>Laurieta</hi> is taken and hang'd and burnt for the same.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>HISTORIE IX. Iacomo de Castelnovo</hi> lustfully falls in love with his daughter in law <hi>Perina,</hi> his owne sonne <hi>Francisco de Castelnovo's</hi> Wife; whom to injoy, he causeth <hi>Ierantha</hi> first to poyson his owne Lady <hi>Fidelia,</hi> and then his said sonne <hi>Francisco de Castelnovo:</hi> in revenge where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>Perina</hi> treacherously murthereth him in his bed. <hi>Ierantha,</hi> ready to dye in travell of child, confesseth her two Murthers; for the which she is hang'd and burnt▪ <hi>Perina</hi> hath her right hand cut off, and is condemned to perpetuall imprisonment, where she sorrowfully dyes.</item>
      <item>
         <pb n="86" facs="59"/>
         <hi>HISTORIE X. Bertolini</hi> seekes <hi>Paulina</hi> in marriage, but she loves <hi>Sturio,</hi> and not himselfe: hee prayes her Brother <hi>Brellati,</hi> his deare friend, to sollicite her for him, which he doth, but cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile; whereupon <hi>Bertolini</hi> lets fall some disgracefull speeches, both against her honour, and his reputation: for which <hi>Brellati</hi> challengeth the Field of him, where <hi>Bertolini</hi> kills him, and hee flies for the same. <hi>Sturio</hi> seekes to marry her, but his father will not consent there. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>nto, and conveyes him away secretly: for which two disasters, <hi>Paulina</hi> dyes for sorrow. <hi>Sturio</hi> findes out <hi>Bertolini,</hi> and sends him a Challenge, and having him at his mercie, gives him his life at his request: hee afterwards very treacherously kills <hi>Sturio</hi> with a Petrone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> in the Street from a Window: he is taken for this second Murther, his two hands cut off, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> beheaded, and his body throwne into the River.</item>
   </list>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>