<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116646_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69163</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6043</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116646</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Paradise within us: or, The happie mind. By Robert Crofts</title>
                 <author>R. C. (Robert Crofts)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 89, 100-198 pages, 1 leaf of plates, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ormerly having studied out of many good Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors divers notes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Subject of <hi>Mans Happinesse;</hi> And since (for private use) written the same together in a Booke Entituled VIA FOELIX, <hi>The hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Way▪</hi> in three generall Partitions, The first of <hi>Terrestriall,</hi> The second of <hi>Morall,</hi> And the third of <hi>Divine</hi> happinesse on Earth. And further, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the same in divers particular Sections: I have new lately for some Reasons abstracted and new studied out of the same, (but in a different manner and method, and with divers alterations and additions,) Three little Generall Treatises, The first of Earthly happinesse Entituled, <hi>The
<pb facs="3"/>
Terrestriall Paradice.</hi> The second this of Morall happinesse, Entituled, <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice within vs.</hi> And the third of Divine happinesse on Earth, Entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Heaven within vs.</hi> The first and the third I have lately publish't, This having Relation to both the other, I thought not amisse to be impressed last of the three. Having beene en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged in the former, I doe intend hereafter to Review, new study, and publish the Rest; Being a farre more particular and large discourse of this Subject Happinesse on Earth, and Physically, Philosophically, Histori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally and Divinely digested. But, not entertaine you with a Prolix Pream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Forasmuch as the Preface to the Readers In the Terrestriall Paradice may in divers respects bee applyed to this Booke also, without any further Introduction, I proceed.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>