<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>L., S.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116488_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18501</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5051</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116488</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>L., S.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of wisdome : three bookes written in French by Peter Charro [n] Doctr of Lawe in Paris. Translated by Samson Lennard</title>
                 <author>Charron, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 <distributor>Aspley, William</distributor>
                            <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>38, 550, that is 554, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doubt not (gentle Reader) but some there are that will not gently censure these my labours; for I am not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant how hard a thing it is to please all. Some are curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, whom if I should endeuour to please, I should displease my selfe: Some are enuious, and those I care not whether I please or no. As for the iudicious Reader, I confesse I would willingly content him, because if he be truly iudicious he will iudge of my faults as if they were his own, and rather commend my good endeuors, than condemne my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities. This is the man whom I desire to satisfie, and must giue to vnderstand that I haue vsed a plaine English phrase, because the grauitie of the matter required it; and I loue not to smell of the inkhorne: and of all others I haue auoided the French, wherein it
<pb facs="6"/>
was written, because I would not haue it seeme to be a translation. The Latine I haue left vntoucht; and if that be a fault, I disbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den it vpon the Author: He did it; and why not I? And if hee thought all French men vnderstood it; why should not I haue as good a conceit of my Countreymen? If he thought none fit to reade his booke, but such as vnderstood it, it is no fault in me if I thinke so too. Howsoeuer, or whatsoeuer my ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sights may be (which I doubt not but a curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous eie may make too many) let it suffice that I acknowledge mine owne weaknesse, and both in respect of the tongue and weight of the matter if selfe, should not haue presumed to haue vndergone so heauy a burden, had I not been encouraged by my learned, iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and honest friend <hi>M. Roger Webb,</hi> some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time student and fellow of <hi>S. Iohns</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxford;</hi> from whose fulnesse I am not asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to confesse I haue receiued that little suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie, whatsoeuer it be, that is in me, and whose learned assistance I haue vsed both in the cull, and altering of such points as were either erroneous, or not otherwise fit to passe the presse. If any man shall thinke, that by this ingenious acknowledgment of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinesse
<pb facs="7"/>
I detract from mine owne sufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, it sufficeth my turne, if I adde vnto mine owne honestie by yeelding this thankfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall of his loue towards me, and his labors bestowed vpon me; which forasmuch as they were not mercenarie, but friendly and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourly, they do binde me the rather with my labours to honour him. Touching the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of this Worke I can say little, because I knew him not, let his worke commend him; and as for the worke, let it commend it selfe: for I had rather with silence passe that ouer which I can not sufficiently commend, than derogate any thing from the worth thereof by speaking too little. Let me only say, That if I haue any way wronged him in these my labors (by turning him out of his holy dayes sute into his worky-dayes apparell) I am so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for it; it was not my purpose so to do, but to honor him. And howsoeuer our English attire may alter him in the outward appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, yet my hope is, that he that pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into him with a single impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall eye, shall finde him no changeling, but one and the same.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>S. L.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>