<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116007_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03082</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13207</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116007</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The gouernement of all estates : wherein is contayned the perfect way to an honest life, gathered out of many learned authors, a boke right profitable for all estates, but especiallie for the trayning [and] bringing vp of the yonger sort: written in Latin by that excellen learned man Andreus Hesse, translated into Englishe</title>
                 <author>Schottennius, Hermannus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Hacket, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>256 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Othing is more profitable in this world (gentle Reader) than ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest precepts, good counsels, worthie and godly perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, how to flée vice, and follow ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, which is the best and chiefest part of all Philosophie, for by this meanes cōmon wealthes are maintained, the true limmit or direction of life frequē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and all good &amp; godly families go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned. This meane the auncient Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natours, or cōscribed fathers of <hi>Rome</hi> with others in tymes past haue fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, yea the Heathē Poets &amp; Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophers, also hauing tasted of the same. The scope of their whole workes doth tende to no other end, but to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of man, howe he should vse him selfe in modestie, counselling him selfe in temperance, by practise, fortitude,
<pb facs="3"/> and imitate iustice. Also y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whiche is the touchstone of all truth, that excellent Iewell of our sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and the bright Lantern of sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie, hath also taught vs the way to all perfection of life, righteousnesse, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse, and sāctification. The principal meane aboue all others, whereby thou mayst learne what mā is at such time as he liueth in the feare of God, &amp; wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vprightly in his calling. So all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruditiō being agréeable vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, may and ought to be enthraced as a guide or Rector of mans life vnto vertue, as this booke which is named the Gouernmēt of all estates, bicause it treateth of the trayning &amp; bringing vppe of man from his childhoode, or as <hi>Terence</hi> wryteth <hi>ex Ephoebis tāquam</hi> till his olde age, wherin ye may learne to attaine to the perfection of a probe or honest life. First written in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine tongue by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> excellent man <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannus Hessus,</hi> wherevnto is added the institution of a Christian man by <hi>Adrianus Barlandus,</hi> and now tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slated
<pb facs="3"/> into English, by those who doe wish thy furtherance. Gentle Reader take this in good part, and in so doing thou shalt cause them to thinke their labours wel bestowed, and encourage them to do greater things to thy god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly furtherance and profite: If that as mindfull of <hi>Demosthenes</hi> thou accept their labour and momentarie practise: Hauing this consideration, that as the Philosopher requesting of an old wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man the steppes of his passage, and she by the assigning of hir finger declared the same, surrendred with a bēded knée thanks for hir demerits, then they (not yet requesting so much curtesie) shal be the willinger, moued by this their industrie, to race or ingresse in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a sequence enterprise. Thus cōmitting thée to the tuitiō of God, I bid thée fare well.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Vale in Christo</salute>.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>