<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER in God, GEORGE, Lord Bi∣shop of London, my singular good Lord.</title>
           <author>Saunderson, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116623_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11454</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21705</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116623</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER in God, GEORGE, Lord Bi∣shop of London, my singular good Lord.</title>
                 <author>Saunderson, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ten sermons : preached I. Ad clerum. 3. II. Ad magistratum. 3. III. Ad populum. 4. By Robert Saunderson Bachellor in Diuinitie, sometimes fellow of Lincolne Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Sanderson, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Young (Junius), Robert</publisher>
                    <distributor>Dawlman (Dolman), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 75, 78-139, 5, 147-470 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER in God, GEORGE, Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of <hi>London,</hi> my singular good Lord.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <hi>My good</hi> LORD:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Had euer thought, the interest of but an ordinary <hi>friend,</hi> might haue <hi>drawne</hi> me to that, whereto the despight of a right bitter <hi>foe</hi> should not haue <hi>driuen</hi> me: till the Fate of these Sermons hath taught me my selfe bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and now giuen me at once a sight both of my <hi>Errour</hi> and <hi>Infirmitie.</hi> The improbitie of some good friends, I had out-stood, who with all their vexation could neuer preuaile vpon me for the publishing of but the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb facs="4"/>
of them: when loe, at length the rest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse importunity of hard censures, hath wrung both it, and the fellow of it out of my hands. So much haue we a stronger sense of our owne <hi>wrongs,</hi> than of our friends <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests</hi>: and so much are we forwarder to <hi>iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifie</hi> our selues, than to <hi>gratifie</hi> them. How euer, if (by Gods good blessing upon them) these slender labours may lend any helpe to aduance the peace &amp; quiet of the Church, in setling the iudgments of such, as are more either <hi>timorous</hi> than they need be, or <hi>contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> than they should be: I shall haue much cause to blesse his gracious prouidence in it, who, with as much ease, as sometimes hee brought light out of darknes, can out of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate wrongs work publike good. In which hope, I am the rather content to send them abroad: though hauing nothing to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them, but <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Plainenesse.</hi> Yet such as they are, I humbly desire they may passe vnder your Lordships protection: whereunto I stand by so many deare <hi>names</hi> engaged. By the name of a <hi>Visitour;</hi> in respect of that <hi>Society,</hi> wherof I was of late a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: when founded by your Lordships
<pb facs="4"/>
godly <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Richard Flemming,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>am,</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops of Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne,</note>
      <hi>Predecessors,</hi> hath had plentifull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of your Lordships singular both <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Iustice</hi> in preseruing their <hi>Statutes,</hi> and maintaining the rights of their founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. By the name of a <hi>Diocesan</hi>; in respect of the <hi>Countrey,</hi> wherein it hath pleased God to seate me: which hath found much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in your Lordships religious and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate gouernment. By the name of a <hi>Master;</hi> in regard of that dependance I haue vpon your Lordship by speciall seruice. Which, as it putteth a <hi>boldnesse</hi> into me, to tender this small pledge of my thankefulnesse to your gracious acceptance: so it layeth a strong <hi>Obligation</hi> vpon me to tender my best pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers vnto <hi>Almightie God</hi> for the continuance and increase of his blessings vpon your Lordship, to the good of his Church vpon earth, and your eternall crowne in heauen.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Booth by Paynell Linc.</hi>
         <date>Nouem. 20. 1621.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Lordships Chapleine in all dutifull obseruance, ROBERT SAVNDERSON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>