<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READERS, CONTEI∣NING THE ANSWERE TO M. NOWELLES PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1565</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116516_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20660</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7061</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116516</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READERS, CONTEI∣NING THE ANSWERE TO M. NOWELLES PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A disproufe of M. Novvelles reproufe : By Thomas Dorman Bachiler of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Dorman, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Laet (Latius), Hans (Jan) de</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1565</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 211 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READERS, CONTEI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NING THE ANSWERE TO M. NOWELLES PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F as in warre where worldly titles vse by dynt of sworde to be determined / so in skirmisshes of learning / where truthe in doubtefull matters / is only attempted to be tryed out: where gods glorye not mannes preferment is chiefelye sought: where the limites and boundes of Christes eternall kingdome the churche / not of worldly do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions which shall perishe and haue their ende / are defended it were laufull (good Readers) to vse false vndermining / and Stratagemes to deceiue / to raise smokes to blinde the eyes of the simple readers / as doth the politike capitaine when to conceale the better▪ the weakenes of his power / which being knowen to the enimie might bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de boldenesse / and encrease courage / he maketh fiers of greene fearne or wette strawe / that vnder the darcke smoke thereof he maye the saufflier lye vnespied) finally if in controuersies about religion / it were lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to saye with Lisander the Lacedemonian / <hi>that where the lions</hi>
      <note place="margin">Plutarch. in Lac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>skyn will not serue, it maie and muste be eached withe the case of the foxe:</hi> then in this respecte / the auctor perhappes of the Reproufe / might for this smoky preface of his haue deserued at youre handes / the name at the least and title of a wary and circumspect capitaine / and be thought herafter worthy / to haue the leading of a greater army then he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto he hathe had. But if on the contrary parte / as the nature of the thinges about the which in these two kinde of warres the strife is / is contrary: so the maner of triall and conquest be also diuerse: if truthe be strong inough of herselfe and nede not the helpe of by practises to be sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by: if her bright beames disdayne to be obscured withe clowdy mystes: then hathe this auctor not furthered but hind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ause / then hathe he discouered his weakenes / not shewed his prowe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se / then maie he be termed a cowardly souldiour / not a valiant capiteine. Nowe here must I desire yow as many as will aduenture to giue iudgement of the euent of this conflicte betwene vs / to open the eyes of youre vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding / and to considre the vaine smokes whereby in this preface of his he laboureth to blinde yow / and to disgrace bothe me and all suche as haue written of late in Englishe. The waye (yow knowe well that be of the learned sorte) to bring this to passe / ought to be by comparing matter with matter / cause with cause / and reason with reason. But the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarye forseing when it shall come to the close / and to the pointe that the matter must so be tried / how weake and feeble he is like to be founde / 
<pb facs="3"/> thought it a pointe of wisdome / first before all thinges to get by stea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>h) / the possession as it were of your mindes / and there leauing <hi>preiudice</hi> his lieuetenaunt / him selfe to be afterwardes occupied about the residue of his affaires. For this cause he raised these foule and thicke smokes / <hi>that suche as haue written of late in englishe, be but seely transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours or borowers of those bokes, whose first authors they would</hi>
      <note place="margin">In the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ste side of his prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</note>
      <hi>seeme to be, that therfore mistrusting that suche kinde of writing or rather translating, should not appeare worthy to be accompted the earnest doing of any learned or wise man, they haue done wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely,</hi>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
      <hi>either to pretend that to be written but lightely for a priuate frende</hi>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
      <hi>or twayne, and not ment to be printed &amp;c. or elles to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point suche to beare the name as authors of their bookes, as maie seme moste meete therefore, being accompted of all that knowe them, for learning and discretiō the simplest men emongest them: that these bookes haue bene elaborated at conuenient oportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
      <hi>by common conference.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Beholde here I praie yow / the fonde coniectures that haue smoked out of M. Nowelles idle braine / wherewith he thinketh so to dymme the eyes of all men / that he maie vnder these clowdes steale when he <note place="margin">
         <hi>To the</hi> 1.</note> will in to their bosoms. If no newe boke maie be made (as here he se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to mainteine) because all that can be spoken is saide allready: if for this cause / who so euer will wright nowe / shall be but a seely transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour <note place="margin">Nihil est dictū quod non est di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum priùs</note> and borower of other: maie we not iustly saie to him and all suche: who be yow that obiecte to vs the translating out of other mennes laty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne worckes in to oure Englishe bokes? Are yowe not of the conspiracy of them / that robbed all the heretikes that euer wrote before yow / to pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che vp youre clouted Apologie? Is there any one sentence there that hathe not bene filched from some one heretike or other? Youre greate <hi>Bassa,</hi> if his doinges be thus examined / is he not like to be nombred emon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest <note place="margin">M. Iuell.</note> the seely translatours? If he shoulde be cruelly called vpon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store to youre Apologie / to <hi>Musculus</hi> his common places / to his maister Peter martir his note bokes / the debte that he hathe borowed of them / might he not think yow become banckerout shortly? Your selfe also / and that other that skirmisheth with the crosse of Christe / shoulde yowe be in any better case / the one of yow borowing from Caluin his in stituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons / Brentius / and suche like / the other takinge out of the historie of Magdeburg / and the Englishe homilie against images / such matter as he founde there ready framed to his handes? But what speake I herof / seing that by this meanes / neither is there any newe booke nowe ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes made / neither of longe time hathe bene / or hereafter can be made. For neither made Cicero the bokes <hi>De Oratore,</hi> neither Plato <hi>De Legibus,</hi> neyther Hipocrates his Aphorismes / neyther Aristotle his <hi>Physica,</hi> because all these learned what so euer they wrote / of other that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. Thus muche maye be saide to M. Nowell susteining thys <hi>paradox</hi> (to deface vs to the worlde) <hi>that we are seely translatours, because nothing can nowe be newely written for the maintena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unce of the popes supremacy, or any other matters whiche we
<pb facs="3"/> nowe treate of, but such as hathe bene allready bothe written and printed many yeares agoe &amp;c.</hi> The which so strange an opinion / as for his small skyll some simple Ideot maye mainteine / so is it for the persone of M. Nowell / one that beareth some countenaunce of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning / and is in deede in the place and roume of a learned man / alltoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnsitting. And this I doubte not but he him selfe / aswell by the experience of his owne writing of late / as of other of his syde that wright daily / knewe well inough. But to muche Rhetorike made him playe the foole / and while he folowed to neare the preceptes of his arte / he straied to far from the rules of all good reason. For allthough it be tricke of Rhetorike / to labour to bring the aduersarie in the verie entry in to the matter / out of credite withe the reader or hearer: yeat is it a pointe of reason to forsee and prouide withall / that the meanes whiche a man vseth / be not suche as maie be returned against him selfe.</p>
   <p>Well this being nowe in the hearing of M. Nowell who peeped by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <note place="margin">
         <hi>To the.</hi> 2.</note> there while in at the key hole) concluded emongest the catholikes in this solemne conference of theirs / that some thing shoulde be set fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the in Englishe / the nexte deuise was of the maner of publishing it. Which was / if the Reporter lye not) <hi>that because they mistrusted dest this kinde of writing or rather translating, should not appeare worthy to be accompted the earnest doinges of anye learned or wise man, they shoulde pretende either their bookes to be written lightely for priuate frindes &amp;c. or appoint suche to beare the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me as authors of such bookes,</hi> as were the simplest men for learning and discretion emongest them.</p>
   <p>If malice had not alltogether blinded him / and as it were bereued him of common sense / neuer woulde he haue abused youre eares (good Readers / with such vaine toyes as these are. For there is none of yow I trust / but that he iudgeth better of the whole nombre o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> catholikes / then that he can be persuaded to thinke / that there shoulde be emongest them anye so wittelesse / (muche lesse that a multitude shoulde agree in conference) to thinke / that to wright of a matter either in the same ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue or anye other / whereof an other hathe written before / were a thing not worthy to be accounted the doing of any learned or wise man. Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che if they shoulde thinke / what were it elles but to condemne all the learned writers of so many hundred yeares / of ignorance and lacke of witte / as either being seely translatours or needy borowers. Beside this / there is none of yow I trust so simple but that he can easely imagine with him selfe / that it is not likely / that anie Catholike shoulde be so far from all reason / as to feare thys that M. Nowelles fantasy surmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth / hauing especially in his eye the example of heretikes them selues / who writing daily in the vulgar tongues / are yeat therefore counted of none but fooles in deede / the lesse learned or wise.</p>
   <p>He noteth in the margent M. Doctour Harding and M. Rastell / for pretending their bookes to be written for priuate frindes. And why ought they not rather (being bothe of them to speake the lest men of no in famouse maners or godlesse consciences) to be beleuid / affirming the same in their seuerall prefaces to the Readers / then M. Nowell withe
<pb facs="4"/> his moste vaine and vnlikely coniectures / being allready infamouse for beelieng that learned man M. Doctour Redman / as to honest / learned / and good men yeat liuing it is notoriously knowen?</p>
   <p>As for vs whome he calleth the simplest emongest the Catholikes for learning and discretion: if that be true / so muche haue we the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cause to rendre thanckes to allmighty God / who hathe preserued free from the infection of their heresies / suche a nombre no worse lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned / nor of lesse discretion then we by goddes grace are. Who maye when it shall please his wisdome to appointe the time / and to moue the harte of oure prince to call vs home / shewe oure selues worckemen in buylding vp that / which heretikes haue destroyed and pulled downe. But I feare me and would it were not so / that euen in this pointe also / M. Nowell hathe made a Rhetoricall lye.</p>
   <p>The nexte thing that he burdeneth vs withall / is common conference. I woulde it were true that he laieth to oure charge. If we were as <note place="margin">
         <hi>To the</hi> 3.</note> wise as we shoulde be / it shoulde be true / and we woulde in this pointe imitate our aduersaries. But our sauiour hath saide (it can not be false) <hi>Filij huius seculi pruden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>iores fili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s lucis in generatione sua sunt.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Lucae.</hi> 16.</note> The children of this worlde be wyser then the children of light / in their generation. And so it happeneth vnto vs. But here I praie yowe good readers / marcke how he doubleth and faltreth in this tale of his / that so yow maye the better vnderstande with whome yow deale in this case. First he saieth that all oure doinges be but seely translations / the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he maketh so easy a matter / <hi>that the meanest</hi> (he saieth) <hi>emon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest vs (haue they onlye a little vnderstanding in the latine ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue) maye after this sorte loade them withe hauocke of bookes.</hi> Here / (forgetting that euer he spake these wordes) he saieth that these bookes <hi>haue bene longe elaborated by common conference.</hi> What shall we saye? If this kinde of writing called by him transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <note place="margin">M. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welles tongue faltreth in his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng tale.</note> be so easy as he maketh it / what nede was there of longe or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conference / whiche thinges be onlye required in matters of greate hardenesse and difficultie? What cause of feare of committing the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dling of matters of suche weight to a fewe / allthough yonge men year vnderstanding the latine tongue as well as him selfe / then which / lesse knowledge by his owne confession woulde serue to loade them withe hauocke of bookes? If this be true / what neded M. D. Harding or M. Rastell either / to vse the aduise of their learned frindes / to haue any suruey made by others of their doinges / seing it is well knowen / that as they are bothe hable to translate out of latine bookes before written in to theirs made in Englishe: so they woulde for their wisdomes tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slate out of suche (beside Pighius / Gropperus / Hosius / whome in this place he nameth) as being neuer yeat by heretike answered / haue by the consent of all learned catholikes / and very silence of heretikes / bene so allready alowed for sounde and good / that to make any doubte therof nowe / might seme a thing alltogether nedelesse and superfluouse? Now here againe I praie yowe considre / how vnlikely it is / that euer anye wise catholikes shoulde be of this minde to publishe their common de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise vnto the worlde / in the name of a fewe of the simplest sorte among them? Their doinges M. Nowell saieth were taken out of the bookes
<pb facs="4"/> of suche catholikes as had written before. This being graunted / that minding to ouerthrowe heresies they woulde choo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e out of the worst / who is so foolishe to beleue? If they chose out of the best whome enuie her selfe can not denie but to haue ben learned / &amp; to haue written lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly / <note place="margin">Roffensis Pighius Gropper{us} Hosius. Alphonsus de Castro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>▪</note> what a high pointe of policy had this bene / to make a fewe of the simplest sorte among vs / to beare the name of suche learned mennes worckes / whereas contrarywise the moste learned (if they would not haue their councell bewrayed) shoulde haue borne the name therof?</p>
   <p>This being good Readers M. Nowelles moste fine discourse tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the late printing of certeine Englishe bookes: yow see I truste / how muche he hathe set forwarde more hastely then wisely. Yeat he v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the same as a truthe moste clearely proued / bringeth in a compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son betwene the chiefe of the catholikes / and the Phariseis sending their disciples to Christe to appose him / when for feare they durst not come in presence them selues. And to giue the more auctoritie herto / he bringeth the exposition of Chrisostome thereupon. A solemne inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation in a matter not necessary / and a sadde bringing in of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to proue that that is not in question. For till this be first proued that the catholikes had suche politike fetches as he imagineth / to resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them to the Phariseis / and to alleage Chrisostomes interpretation vpon the place / it was to giue a sad sentence cleane beside the matter. But suche is the noble courage of M. Nowell: Luther must be Christ and he one of his disciples / yea though he be Iudas that betraied hys maister / who so euer saye naye / as in the processe of this Reprouffe of his / wherein nothing is with him more common / then to call vs Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riseis / and him selfe and his companions Apostles and disciples / moste euidently it dothe appeare. Wherein he semeth to me (I maie saie withe better right then he applieth against vs the exposition of Chrisostome) to resemble very muche madde Hawkins of Bedlem / who persuadeth him selfe and woulde all other to beleue the same / that he is descended of the bloude royall / his father being well knowen to be a meane man / and a bruer of Oxforde.</p>
   <p>Hetherto hathe M. Nowell in generall wordes laboured / to deface <note place="margin">
         <hi>The</hi> 4. <hi>side</hi> §. <hi>and to speake.</hi>
      </note> the doinges of suche as haue written of late in Englishe: nowe step<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth he from thence to me / against whome his speciall grudge is. Of me he saieth: first / <hi>that it was no greate labour to borowe out off</hi>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
      <hi>my maister D. Harding his booke so lately before written, of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorities and reasons ready framed to my handes, so muche as li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked me &amp;c.</hi> secondarily / <hi>that they that doe knowe me better then</hi>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
      <hi>he doth, merueiling of my doings in diuinitie matters, doe thinke that I haue all my learning not of inheritance but by legacie &amp;c.</hi> For the first he might haue beleuid me at my worde if it had pleased <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> him / signifieng in the preface of my boke / aswell to him as to all other / that it was intended to be made / and the greatest parte therof finished / before that euer I Vnderstoode that M. Doctor Harding ment any suche thing▪ And of this coulde I bring right good witnesse / if either I thought my credite not to be as good as M. Nowelles / or the thing it selfe imported so muche / that the triall of the truthe of the contentes of
<pb facs="5"/> my booke dependid therupon. Nowe as for them that knowing m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> better then M. Nowell dothe / merueile at my doinges in diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> surely I can let no man to merueile at his owne shadowe if he list. Of this I am suer / that there is no cause why I shoulde care muche for this their iudgement who so euer they be / if M. Nowell haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported it truly. For he that is so foolishe to make his account / that lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning maie descende by inheritance / or be bequeathed and receauid by le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacie / what were it but to be more foole then he / to care for such a fooles sentence? But I beleue if the matter were well scanned / it woulde fall out to be one of M. Nowelles owne deuises / vttred nowe in the <note place="margin">A shift to conuey a lye.</note> name of some other / because he him selfe had so lately before pronounced / that I had taken my auctorities and reasons ready framed out of M. Doctor Hardinges booke / which if I had met withe suche a legacie / it might haue seemed nedelesse to haue done. But be it his / or be it whose it shall / suer I am that the auctor thereof is none of my acquaintaunce: for neuer was I yeat acquainted I thanke god / with so very a foole. Notwithstanding for the satisfieng of his greate merueiling / maye it please M. Nowell when he meteth him nexte (if it be not him selfe to aske of him by what meanes he that was but Bachilar of arte in the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me colleage that I was of / when I was bachilar of the lawe / start vp so sone a preacher at Powles crosse / and a publike reader of englishe diuinitie in the vniuersitie of Oxford? May it please him furder / for the <note place="margin">Sir Gres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hop.</note> remouing this scruple that so troubleth him / to demaunde of him / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I were not as likely at that tyme in the iudgementes of as many as knewe vs bothe / within three yeares after to wright the booke that I haue written / as he was within lesse then the space of one yeare after / to occupye the place at Powles crosse / or to preach and re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>de publikely di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie in Oxforde? Which sermones and lessons (suche as they were) woulde haue made diuerse bookes (he maye be holde to tell this meruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling man) euery one of them by many partes greater then mine. If these questions be asked / I dare assuer yow / this olde acquaintaunce shal be either thoroughly satisfied / or forced to cōfesse the cause of differēce to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> because as saieth Tertullian: <hi>Nusquâm facilius proficitur</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">He mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the scholes of heretikes rebelling against God and his chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che.</note>
      <hi>quâm</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lib de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>script. hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retic.</note>
      <hi>in castris rebellium, vbi illic esse promereri est:</hi> men come forwarde no where sooner then in the tentes of rebelles / where the very being / is to be aduaunced.</p>
   <p>Where M. Nowell scoffeth at my proceding bachiler of diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie / this I doe him to vnderstande / that I proceded not vpon the bridge / but in the publike schooles / in the face of the whole vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersitie / in the presence of an honorable and a learned audience. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered for my degree in two seuerall questions / the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rst being. <hi>De primatu summi pontificis:</hi> the other / <hi>An liceat homini Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiano diuertore ab vxore propter adulterium, &amp; aliam ducere?</hi> I disputed after the manner of the schooles / a question out of the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences <hi>pro &amp; contra.</hi> I declaimed in the praise of the studie of diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: I reade for my fourme the beginning of the. 6. chap. of the first epistle of S. Paule to the Corinth. And all this vnder a moste Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="5"/> president (as to the worlde his sundry writinges haue made him knowen for no lesse) <hi>Matthaeus Galenus Vestcappellius.</hi> How I behaued my selfe in these exercises / if modestie woulde suffer it / I coulde here by the inserting of the testimonie of the vniuersitie vnd the seale therof / make it appeare to the worlde. This I trust without offence being vrged therto by mine aduersary I maie be bolde to saye / yea in conscience I take my selfe bounde to saye / seing this contemptuouse abasing of me / tendeth to the only discrediting of the catholike faithe (which by goddes grace I maintaine) that my demeanure was suche / as neither my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie susteined dishonour / nor my selfe dishonesty / nor the parte of the questions which I chose to defende (being yeat the first of them / impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with as learned arguments as M. Nowell hath hetherto brought) any preiudice in the iudgement of the learned hearers: as by the degree bestowed vpon me by the colleage of diuines / and the honest commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation giuen to me by <hi>Franciscus Balduinus,</hi> {pre}sent while I answered in the first question two houres together / afterwardes it appeared. Thus mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hathe M. Nowelles slaunderouse reporte / forced me (good readers) to vtter of my selfe / which otherwise it coulde haue becommed me in no wise to haue done. If his good Maister M. Grindall / would trye them as well and sift them as neare / whome he admitteth to prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che at Powles crosse (a place sometimes for bachilers and Doctours in Diuinitie) as I was tryed / suche store of vnlearned but moste railing sermones / shoulde not be made there as daily there are. Nowe I coulde here imitate M. Nowelles Rhetorike / were I disposed to entre in to suche vaine contentions and fruitelesse comparisons / and tell him also / that some one of his acquaintaunce who knoweth him better then I doe / merueileth also at his doinges in diuinitie matters / the knowledge whereof being neither to be founde in Rodolphes logicke (wherein his greatest learning &amp; studye both was in Oxford) neither in westminstre schole where Terence his comoedies will giue no place to Pawles epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles / he thinketh that he met at Geneua or elles where / with some scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred scrappes of Iohn Caluins / old / caste and ouerworne / hereticall diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie / or elles he thinketh he coulde neuer returning home / before he was knowen to be a student in diuinitie / become so soddenly of a meane scholemaister / so valiant a preacher. Vnlesse perhappes / the same spirite that hathe created of late diuines (not on the bridge but in their shop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes / or disputing vpon the alebenche for their degree) so many tinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers / coblers / cowheardes / broome men / fidlers / and suche like / haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so made him a preacher emongest the rest.</p>
   <p>Nowe foloweth a reason of M. Nowelles / <hi>why not prouoked</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>The.</hi> 5. <hi>si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de</hi> § <hi>Now if any doe marueile.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>as maye seme, he answereth my booke written against the B. of Sarisbury.</hi> I thinke no man w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ll merueile of his writing / and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he might haue saued that cost / and rather haue satisfied men in this / why writing only against fiftene leaues of my booke / he is so impudent leauing the substance vntouched / to pretende that he answereth my whole booke.</p>
   <p>After this he addeth certeine other causes / why he answered no soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner / and why he proceded no furder. He staied he saieth in answering / because he vnderstode at the length / that M. Doctour Harding his
<pb facs="6"/> booke and mine were so agreable in substance / that M. Iuell who had then he hearde saye made hys answere to D. Harding readye to printe / shoulde in answering the one / in effecte haue answered both / and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he would in no wife preuent his good Lord. That this is a false for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged cause inuented only to saue the honour of the brotherhode / who lingred so long in answering / he that hathe readen bothe oure bookes will easely perceiue. For of the seconde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> proposition handled in my <note n="*" place="margin">That temporall princes maye not gouerne in religiō.</note> boke / it is cleare / that it hath no maner of affinitie with any article han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled by D. Harding. Excepte M. Nowelles discretion will serue him to saye / that if M. Iuell shoulde be able to disproue the popes suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy / it woulde folowe thereupon that laie princes shoulde gouerne in causes of religion. Whiche if lacke of due consideration shoulde moue him to saye / yeat the wisdome of other woulde not suffer them to beleue. And therfore this being no article of M. Doctour Hardinges / it was neuer likely that M. Iuell woulde euer doe suche a worcke of super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erogation / as to encombre him selfe any furder then occasion was giuen him. Besides / if this were the cause of M. Nowelles staye / why be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan he then to answere me at all: Forsothe he preuenteth this obiection by saing / that he knewe not before he begonne / that oure two bookes were so agreable. Now forsothe a discrete wryter by his owne confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion / that will begynne to answere a boke before he haue readen it ouer. Is this credible good Readers? And yeat thus must it nedes be were it true that he pretendeth. Excepte hauing reade ouer my booke / he had not readen M. Doctours / against which neuerthelesse being longe in England or my booke came / he had vttred before his malice at Powles crosse / and therfore bylike had first readen it / or elles like wrighter like preacher. But well knowe all men / that / that graue and sobre stayed heade of his / coulde not admit any suche rashe and temerariouse facte / and therfore this was but a zelouse lye / wherby to excuse the common lingring of them all / he was content to hazard his owne worship. For whereas nowe he feared lest it woulde be espied / that all this patched tale is but a lewde lye / seing that he neded no more to feare to go before M. Iuell in answering my whole booke / then in answering fiftene lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues thereof / which hauing in his handes he might haue chosen whether he woulde haue deliuered to the printer or no / to helpe that he saieth: <hi>For euen nowe being come thus farre, the Bishoppes answere as</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>The</hi> 7. <hi>si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de § But whē I had passed.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>the reporte went being then not fully finished, and many good men muche desiring some answere, and as many aduersaries as muche bragging that their bookes woulde neuer be answered, the councell of some frindes, and continuall bragge of so many ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries, caused me to suffer this little taste as vntimely fruite, the sooner to come abroade.</hi> Yow must here imagine good Readers / that euen iust at that tyme when the reporte went that M. Iuelles answer was not fully finished / M. Nowell was come to the 15. leafe of my booke. Yow must also thinke that this knowledge was brought to him by common reporte / because yowe maie not suspecte anye conference betwene them. But aboue all thinges as yowe tendrelye regarde M. Nowelles pore honestie / yowe muste vnderstande two repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / and one of them a false reporte / or elles must he be a false reporter.
<pb facs="6"/> And all this dothe M. Nowell / because for his experience he knoweth / that a lye maye better be fathered vpon reporte or common bruite / then vpon one man alone. The first reporte cried as it were to M. Nowell: holde youre handes for goddes sake / the B. of Sarisbury hathe killed them bothe with one blowe. His answere to D. Harding is allrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy made / and ready to printe. Herupon M. Nowell (as he is a verye pitifull harted man) lothe to kill them that were allready deade / by and by staied. But this was false reporte / who was no soner out of sight / but in commeth the other reporte / accompanied with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine of M. Nowelles frindes / and here began a newe crye / that he shoulde giue the onset / the bishoppes bande was not yeat ready. And so he did / so harde a matter it was for him and his companions / to obteine (they had gone so long vpon their credite) any longre time of susteining the expectation of M. Iuelles answere / at the handes of either frindes or aduersaries / that nedes must M. Nowell be thrust furth against his will / to go before M. Iuell. How likely these pretenses are to be true / time will discouer it M. Nowell staye here and goe no furder. In the meane season how likely they are to be true / the wise wil be able to iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge by the circumstances of this his halting and doubtefull tale.</p>
   <p>We are now come to that parte (good Readers) of M. Nowelles <note place="margin">§ <hi>Nowe that I haue</hi>
      </note> preface / wherein he giueth certeine reasons / why <hi>he hathe so diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, largely, and as it maye seme carefully also answered me: whose owne doinges</hi> he affirmeth / <hi>to be more worthy of laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then of anye earnest answere.</hi> I perceiue it troubleth M. Nowell to thinke / that <hi>Demit honoem aemulus Aiaci.</hi> But I pitye him the lesse / because he made the matche him selfe. His reasons are / <hi>that he</hi>
      <note place="margin">The first.</note>
      <hi>answereth not the reasons alleaged by me as mine, but as D. Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges, and not only D. Hardinges, but of Eckius, Pighius, and Hosius, yea &amp; of all those that haue written in latine for the popes vsurped power &amp;c.</hi> Lo the noble corage of M. Nowell / for whome no one man can be founde alone able to matche with him / but they must be all called furthe at once / that euer wrote in latine for the popes supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, Which seing it is so / now be of good comforte M. Calfhill / who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se <note place="margin">Calfhill in epist. ad Martialem.</note> only sorowe yow saie was / that M. Nowell had not a more learned aduersarie. Yow see that there is not only no cause of sorowe / but much occasion to reioise / that with the answering of 15. leaues of my booke / all that euer wrote for the pope shall be answered in me. Where was youre witte when yow feared this? Thought yow that M. Nowell woulde not prouide for suche a fowle blemishe to his honour? But to the matter. I am not ashamed good readers to confesse / that in writing Ipse the learned argumentes of suche as haue handled the like matter before / and that if anie reasons be weaker then other / they be those espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that be of mine owne framing. And is it not so thinke yow withe M. Nowell? Those emongest yow that be of the learneder sorte knowe that it is so / &amp; that in answering him I answer their Apologie / Caluin / Luther / Melancthon / Bucer / Brentius / Peter Martyr / in whose wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges the like reasons are to be founde / and that what so euer he hathe not in them / is foolishe / fonde / &amp; vnworthy to be answered. The seconde <note place="margin">
         <hi>The.</hi> 2.</note>
      <pb facs="7"/> reason why M. Nowell answereth me so diligently and carefully / is he saieth / <hi>because I haue set furthe a booke, sclaunderouse not to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall persones only, but to oure whole countrie, to oure lawes, and to oure gratiouse Soueraigne, whome</hi> (he saieth) <hi>I charge as v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surping vndue auctoritie: sclaunderouse, not at home onlye, but abroade also in foraigne countries. Wherefore whome so euer I shewe my selfe to be, and how sclendre an answere might best be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come me, he thought it shoulde become him not sclendrely to esteme the honour of his prince, his duty to his countrye and to the lawes of the realme, but with earnestnesse to repell suche re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proches, as I haue attempted to blemishe them withall.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>As I haue sclaundred in my boke no priuate persons / nor saide of any one that which is not publikely knowen to be true: so haue I in the whole discourse thereof / had that regarde to my duty towardes my moste redoubted soueraigne / that reuerence to her lawes / that naturall affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to my countrie / that allthough truthe of her selfe be sower and hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full / yeat haue I bene allwaies moste far from these sclaundres where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withe I am burdened. Neither doubte I anie thinge / but if not before / yeat in that greate daye of reuelation her highnes shall moste clearely see / whether oure plaine dealing be sclaunderouse to her persone / or their hypocriticall flattry traiterouse to her soule: whether he be a good bishop or no / <hi>qui laicis</hi> (to vse the wordes of S. Ambrose) <hi>ius sacerdotale subster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ambr. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>epist.</hi> 32.</note> that bringeth the priestely right in subiection to laye men. I char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged neuer her highnesse with the vsurping of vndue auctoritie: I char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged those clawebackes &amp; flattring parasites for forcing vpon her grace a <note place="margin">
         <hi>Fol.</hi> 28. <hi>a. in my first boke.</hi>
      </note> title / which Calain him selfe as I proued) denied to her father. And now I charge them againe for the same / and adde therunto beside / that they are the men them selues that are sclaunderouse to the Quene / to her la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes / to the whole realme. First for bringing in lawes ecclesiasticall the like whereunto in all christendome are not to be founde: then / for forcing vpon her grace a title / which no king or Quene christened will vse be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side: but aboue all thinges for this / that they that call her grace supreme gouernour in all thinges and causes aswell ecclesiasticall as temporall / <note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testantes doinges sclaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouse to the Quene and the realme.</note> are noted / not at home only but abroade also in strange countries / moste lewdely to abuse the same / while euen in a matter of no greater im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance then is the wearing of a square cappe / they refuse the ordre of the supreme gouernour in all thinges and causes &amp; as in wordes they call her) ecclesiasticall and temporall: while for the signe of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>(the crosse)</hi> whiche her maiestie kepeth moste reuetently in her chappell / she is in her owne realme (by a booke printed and set saithe) by a meane and base subiect / inalapertly comptrolled ▪ What maye foraigne princes thinke of suche a cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>mely / if as her graces affection towardes the crosse is vnknowen to none / so the onlye knowledge of the title of suche an infamouse libell rather then a booke / be brought to the eares of anie of them? But what maie they saye / if vnderstanding the tongue / <note place="margin">
         <hi>Calshil. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>pist. ad Martialem. pag.</hi> 7.</note> they shoulde read▪ within foure leaues of the beginning: <hi>As for hir priuate doinges, neither are they to be drawen as a president for all: nor any ought to crepe in to the princes bosome, of euery facte
<pb facs="7"/> to iudge an affection.</hi> What could they gather herof but that the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces honour were vilanously touched / as though in religion which is but one and therfore not subiecte to change / she did vse one religion her sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe / and deliuer an other to her subiectes: as though (which is worse) she kepte for hir owne priuate vse the bad / and gaue to the rest the better: yea (which is yeat worst of all) as though she shoulde pretende one thing outewardly / and be of an other affection inwardly / which coulde not be perceiued but by creeping into hir bosome. But if he that setteth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde so vnhappely) saile the rest of his course withe no better fortune / he shoulde in all wise iudgement haue done more wisely / if he had conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued stil in the quiet hauen at the ancre wherat once he laye / then he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the done by committing him selfe to the mercye of the windes &amp; waues of these troubelouse seas of controuersies / wherein no skilfuller pilote then he sheweth him selfe to be / maye easely make a foolishe shipwreke / and be cast awaye.</p>
   <p>These be the sclaunderouse persons good Readers / whom M. Nowell (if he haue that regarde to the honour of our souereigne ladye the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / his dutie to oure countrye &amp; lawes thereof / that he pretendeth) will shortly haue in the chase / and let me and suche as I am alone / who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test neuer to desire to liue houre longre / then we shall be contented to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue like true subiectes vnder the humble obedience of oure gratiouse so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereigne <note place="margin">The prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce goddes image in earthe.</note> / whome we acknowledge to be the image of God in earthe / in all ciuile and politike gouernement. But nowe here I praie yowe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde / how M. Nowell that maketh these greate bragges / of <hi>repelling withe earnestnesse suche reproches as I haue attempted</hi> (he saieth) <hi>to blemishe my prince, lawes and countrie withall,</hi> quitteth hym selfe of his promise. Doth he not euen then when he commeth to that article where these surmised reproches shoulde be / flee backe and giue ouer in the plaine fielde? Is not this <hi>repelling withe earnestnesse</hi> a plaine mockery to be laughed at / when about the matter that made him (he saieth) to wright so carefully and diligently / of 124. leaues / he bestoweth not fully three: when he endeth there / without entring in to the article / where he shoulde rather haue begonne?</p>
   <p>The thirde reason that hathe moued M. Nowell to wright the more largely against me / he expresseth in these wordes: <hi>because the simple &amp; vnlearned readers haue often best liking in bookes mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re boldely then learnedly written, and are moste in daunger to credite most lewde and sclaunderouse lyes, I therfore, haue in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering more at large, applied my selfe to such as be of meane vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, to whome the guilefull dealinges of the papistes can not with breuitie be made manifest.</hi> These be M. Nowelles causes for his excuse why in so many wordes he hath vttred so little matter. But the truthe is / when after longe streining of curtosy emongest the brethren which of them shoulde answere my booke / they all agreed / first in this / that something muste nedes be saide therto / and finally that M. Nowell of all other shoulde take the matter in hande / as he that for his rare gift of railing were best able to feede the humour of suche simple
<pb facs="8"/> and vnlearned / as here him selfe saieth / <hi>haue often best lyking in bookes more boldly then learnedly written,</hi> then he deepely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering / that the greatest vauntage that he coulde finde against me / mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ste be by making men beleue / that the places of S. Cyprian. S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome and suche like / brought for the confirmation of that first proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of myne / <hi>That there must be one head in earth to gouerne chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stes churche,</hi> were alleaged directly for the B. of Romes supremacy / to the whiche being conteined withein the compasse of 15. leaues of my booke / if he shoulde but answere after like proportion / his answere were <note place="margin">The true cause of M. Nowel les so large writing.</note> like to be counted but a twopeny booke / and he for no better then a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfepeny doctour: his high wisdome in respecte of these considerations founde it best / to dilate so that little stuffe that he had to vtter / that he might seme to haue made a iust volume / and to haue answered therein the whole. For this respecte / because to haue intituled his booke: <hi>A Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proufe written by Alexander Nowell of a piece of a booke &amp;c.</hi>
      <note place="margin">VVhy he termed his boke a Reproufe.</note> had bene to greate a blemishe to his worship / and call it a confutation or an answere to my whole booke by any meanes he coulde not / he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uised to terme it a <hi>Reproufe</hi> of my booke / a worde as he thought suche / as in reprouing only 15. leaues he might seme to be able to iustifie / and which shoulde sounde in the eares of the vnlearned (not accustomed to looke so narowly in to the nature of wordes) asmuche as a confutation of the whole. For this cause / to pacifie the learneder sorte whome he sawe he shoulde not be able by suche a tricke of <hi>ligier de main</hi> so easily to deceiue / and who woulde he knewe well not staye at the title / but take a diligent viewe of the contentes of the whole / he ransacking all the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of his iugglers boxe / brought furthe at the lengthe a tricke of <hi>deceptio visus,</hi> whereby he woulde make them beleue (as you haue heard) that M. Doctour Hardinges booke and mine were so like in substance / that M. Iuell in one shoulde answere bothe / and that therfore his fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der trauell shoulde be nedelesse: whereas yowe knowe / that my seconde proposition &amp; the whole conclusion of my booke / haue no maner of agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with any argument handled in D. Hardinges boke.</p>
   <p>Yow haue heard the effecte of M. Nowelles smoky preface / wherin all his labour taken is bestowed to this end / to excuse the not speedy answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the whole brotherhod / his own parcell answering / his so large &amp; earnest answering to so meane a man as I am / finally to deface me and other that haue written / by moste lewde / foolishe / and vntrue surmises. Which neuerthelesse he aduoucheth so confidently / as though he had bene present at Louaine and priuey to all our doinges / and thoughtes / yea and to more then euer we thought toe. Wherein how vaine he hath shewed him selfe to be / if nothing had bene saide allreadie / euen this that he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the of M. Rastell / whome he affirmeth to haue had his booke lienge by him readye made foure yeares at Louayn (whereas yeat he hathe bene <note place="margin">
         <hi>Nowell in his prae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>face</hi> 3. <hi>side</hi> 35 <hi>Calfhill in his epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle to M. Martiall, and prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the reader.</hi>
      </note> scarse on this side of the seas halfe foure yeare / &amp; at Louain whē he prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his booke not foure full monethes) were alone sufficient to declare. This deceitfull dealing of his / by defacing vs to the world / liked so wel hym that came nexte after him to wrighte / that he thought his parte not to be wel plaied / vnlesse he endeuoured also &amp; inforced him selfe to doe the like. And for this cause forsothe ruffling in the figure of <hi>Ruffinis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>us,</hi> he
<pb facs="8"/> calleth M. Doctor Harding <note n="*" place="margin">How mu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che better woulde this name haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cōmed M. Iuell, that of a catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>like beca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike, of an hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke a catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>like, of a catholike an hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke againe?</note> Apostata: at my name he scoffeth calling me worthy <hi>Man</hi> who gaue but a <hi>Dor.</hi> M. Rastelles because it laye not so open to his scoffing spirite / he depraued vttrely / calling him Rascall. But o I woulde it might please almighty God / who hathe bestowed v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him whome he so calleth / so bountifully so manye excellent giftes of vertue and learning / that they were bothe thoroughly knowen to the worlde for suche as they are. Then shoulde M. Rastell to speake the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ste / be founde to be as farre in all respectes from all base and vile condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion / as this shamelesse man is him selfe from all honesty and Christian-like behauiour in so calling hym. To M. Stapleton this painted poppet threateneth drye blowes / yeat wisely vnder an if / and in the name of an other. The booke of Staphylus he compareth to a Ruffians sworde al to be hacked / calling by the waie a moste learned and graue councelour to the late Emperour <hi>Ferdinandus</hi> / Ruffian. In dede there was a rude blacke <note n="*" place="margin">Iacobus Smidelinus.</note> smythe / that did the best he coulde to breake the edge and to leaue so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e gashes in this sworde / but those litle nickes that he made / the <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Staphyl. In defens. Apol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>g. Calf. fol.</hi> 17. <hi>b.</hi> 33.</note> owner therof grounde out so conningly againe / that the edge of it was after more sharpe then euer it was before. Lest al this should not be inough to discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite vs / last of all he chargeth suche of vs as being in Louain haue ben of newe colleage / withe <hi>the smoky styrres blowen in Scotland, the fyry factions inflamed in Fraunce, the Pholish treason condemned in En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gland, the popishe conspiracy attempted in Ireland.</hi> Commeth not this thinke you of a high wit / and a greate discoursing heade? Thankes be to God it is yeat no horned beaste that assaulteth vs thus cruelly. He chargeth vs with gaping for bishoprikes / but surely if hym selfe laboured not ambitiously to be chiefe councelour to some lorde of misrule at Christ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas / he woulde neuer haue stremed so farre the streightes of his simple brayne / as by this moste singuler discourse vpon these late troubles and treasons (which beside him selfe neuer a man I beleue in England coulde haue dreamed of) to giue a moste vndoubted experiment / what wonders he were able to worcke by his witte / if he listed to bende it. But this is the lewdenesse of oure aduersaries / when to the doctrine that we defende they are able to saye nothing / to deface as muche as in them lieth our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones by vntrue surmises / by false and sclaunderouse reportes / by all mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes directe or indirecte. For this they are once as it should seme by their doinges persuaded (howe trulye God he knoweth) that they shall be able to write nothing so absurde / that shall not with some get credite / and fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de frendely entreteinement. Wherfore this is good Readers the common request of vs all vnto yow / that reiecting vttrely these vaine / vntrue / and impertinenent exceptions of oure aduersaries / whereof youre eares be longe since full / it may please yow to haue a diligent eye to the matter it selfe / and not to suffer youre selues to be thus shamfully abused / and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried from thence to suche sciendre considerations as are these: whether the writers be yong men / or olde: many in conference / or fewe alone: whether they wright in shorte space / or take long leisour: whether they translate or make of their owne. For surelye they that propose these exceptions / as it is an euident argument that they mistrust their cause / so seme they not to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of the spirite of humilitie / which seketh nothing but the honour and glorye
<pb facs="9"/>
      <hi>If S. Cyprian writing this epistle to Cornelius the B. of Rome,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>M. suell in his Replye fo.</hi> 228. <hi>beginneth to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>hrincke from his chalenge.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>name him either the high prieste, or christes vicair generall in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, or vniuersall bishop, or head of the vniuersal church &amp;c. then may M. Harding seme to haue some honest colour for his defence.</hi> For these respectes therfore I saie / and other which here for good causes I conceale / it hathe ben thought good to requier yowe / to signifie to vs / whether yowe will ratifie the doctrine conteined in that boke made against the crosse / lest after yow flee to the <hi>Praetor</hi> his exception: <hi>Quod nomine meo gestum non est raiū nō habebo.</hi> It is reason that we demaunde / and it is lawe. Consulte youre lawier so well knowen in Oxforde for his three giftes of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sye / frenesy and Ialousy / and he will tell yow no lesse. When we vnderstande youre minde here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in / yowe shall knowe more of oures. It woulde doe well that yow declared it at Powles crosse / from whence we are contented to take notice: the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / because we trust yow will saie nothing there / but that whereto yow will stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>