<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE COVR∣TEOVS READER.</title>
           <author>Ford, Emanuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116412_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01066</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11173</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116412</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE COVR∣TEOVS READER.</title>
                 <author>Ford, Emanuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first part of Parismus, the renovvmed Prince of Bohemia : His most famous, delectable, and pleasant historie. Containing his noble battails fought against the Persians. His loue to Laurana, the Kings daughter of Thessalie: and of his strange aduentures in the desolate iland</title>
                 <author>Ford, Emanuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>236, 266 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE COVR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEOVS READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ven as an vnskilfull Pylote lying in safe Harbour, should in time of fowle wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther launch into the deepe, and so bring his Shippe in daunger: So I <hi>(Courteous Reader)</hi> haue aduenturously thrust foorth this <hi>Fancie,</hi> to abide your Censure: which if kinde, care is past: If other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, to abide Shipwrack by your discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. But howsoeuer, I relie vpon your courtesie, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the matter procure you not that delight my trauels did expect, yet you will allow the writers good intent. And although the phrase be not altogether agreeable to your fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, yet you will fauourably iudge thereof, as the first fruites of my labours.</p>
   <p>If my selfe were present to answere all Obiections, those that are discontented should rest better satisfied. But in mine absence, I craue your kinde opinion, wishing no other shel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wherevnder to shrowde the defects, then your Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie.</p>
   <p>This Knight was long since bred in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> but in <hi>Thessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi> hee wanne his <hi>Title of Honour;</hi> where first beganne his Famous deedes, which if they please, my reward is suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, if not, yet pardon: and by your Clemencie, adde life to the second part, whose beeing resteth in your power.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>
Expect not the high stile of a refined wit, but the plaine description of <hi>Ualiant Knights,</hi> and the constant truth of <hi>Loyall Friendes.</hi> Condemne not vnkindely, but Censure fauourably, and impute the defects to my want, not my will, that my desire may take wished ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, which is to please all, and giue offence to none: yet carelesse to satisfie the curious discontented, who contemne all things, but amend nothing.</p>
   <p>And thus for my recompence, let me haue your kinde words, and lawfull fauour, and I aske no more.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Farewell,
E. Forde.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>