<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE: VVhere the Name, Subiect, Purpose, and Method of this VVorke is set downe, with an Aduertisement to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116488_Bo1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18501</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5051</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116488</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE: VVhere the Name, Subiect, Purpose, and Method of this VVorke is set downe, with an Aduertisement to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of wisdome : three bookes written in French by Peter Charro [n] Doctr of Lawe in Paris. Translated by Samson Lennard</title>
                 <author>Charron, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 <distributor>Aspley, William</distributor>
                            <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>38, 550, that is 554, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <head>THE PREFACE: <hi>VVhere the Name, Subiect, Purpose, and Method of this VVorke is set downe, with an Aduertisement to the Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is required at the first entrie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">1 Of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> word Wisdome.</note> this Worke, that wee know what this Wisdome is; and since it beareth that name and title, how we purpose to speake there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. All men in generall at the first view of the simple word it selfe, doe easily conceiue and imagine it to be some qualitie, sufficiencie, or habit, not common or vulgar, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, singular, and eleuated aboue that which is common and ordinarie, be it good or euill: For it is taken and vsed (though perhaps improperly) in both kinds: <hi>Sapientes sunt vt faciant mala:</hi> and signifieth not <note place="margin">
         <hi>Hierem.</hi> 4. <hi>Arist. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Metaphy.</hi>
      </note>
      <pb facs="11"/>
properly a good and laudable qualitie, but exquisite, singular, excellent in whatsoeuer it be. And therefore we doe as well say, A wise Tyrant, Pirat, Theefe; as A wise King, Pilot, Captaine: that is to say, Suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, prudent, aduised; not simply and vulgarly, but excellently: For there is opposite vnto Wisdome not onely follie, which is an irregularitie or loosenesse of life, and Wisdome a regularitie or moderation, well measured and proportioned: but also common base<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and vulgar Simplicitie: For Wisdome is high, strong, and excellent; yea, whether it be in good or euill it conteineth two things: Sufficiencie, that is, Prouision or furnture for whatsoeuer is required and necessarie; and that it be in some high degree of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie. So that you see what the simpler sort imagine Wisdome to be at the first view and the simple sound of the word; whereby they conclude, That there are few wise men, that they are rare as euery excellencie is; and that to them by right it apperteineth to command and gouerne others; that they are as Oracles: from whence is that saying, <hi>Beleeue others, and referre thy selfe to the wise.</hi> But well to define this thing and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to trueth, and to distinguish it into his true parts, all men know not, neither are they of one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, nor is it easie; for otherwise doe the common people, otherwise the Philosophers, otherwise the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines speake thereof. These are the three floores and degrees of the world. The two latter proceed by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and rules, and precepts: the former confusedly and very imperfectly.</p>
   <p>Now then we may say, That there are three sorts <note place="margin">2 The diuisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note> and degrees of wisdome, Diuine, Humane, Mundane, which correspond vnto God; Nature pure and entire;
<pb facs="11"/>
Nature vitiated and corrupted. Of all these sorts and euerie of them doe all these three orders of the world, which before we speake of, write and discourse, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one according to his owne maner and fashion; but properly and formally the common sort, that is to say, the world of worldly wisdome, the Philosopher of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, the Diuine of diuine wisdome.</p>
   <p>Worldly wisdome, and of the three the more base, <note place="margin">3 Worldly wisdome.</note> (which is diuers according to the three great Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and Leaders of this inferiour world, Opulencie, Pleasure, Glorie, or rather Auarice, Luxurie, Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <hi>Quicquid est in mundo est concupiscentia oculo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.</note>
      <hi>concupiscentia carnis, superbia vitae;</hi> for which cause it is called by S. Iames, <hi>Terrena, Animalis, Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolica)</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Iames</hi> 3.</note> is reprooued by Philosophie and Diuinitie, which pronounceth it follie before God: <hi>Stultam fecit</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>Deus sapientiam huius mundi.</hi> Of this wisdome there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we speake not in this Booke, except it be to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praise and condemne it.</p>
   <p>Diuine wisdome, and of the three the highest, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined <note place="margin">4 Diuine wisdome.</note> and handled by Philosophers and Diuines, but somewhat diuersly. As for the common or worldly wisdome I disdaine it, and passe by whatsoeuer may be spoken thereof as prophane and too vnworthy in this Treatise to be read. The Philosophers make it altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Speculatiue, saying, That it is the knowledge of the principles, first causes, and highest power to iudge of all things, euen of the most Souereigne, which is God himselfe: and this wisdome is Metaphysicall, and resideth wholly in the vnderstanding, as being the chiefe good and perfection thereof: it is the first and <note place="margin">
         <hi>Thom.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>quaest.</hi> 57. 2. 2. <hi>q.</hi> 19.</note> highest of the fiue intellectuall vertues, which may be without either honestie, action, or other morall ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.
<pb facs="12"/>
The Diuines make it not altogether so specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, but that it is likewise in some sort Practique, for they say, That it is the knowledge of Diuine things, from which there ariseth a iudgement and rule of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane actions; and they make it two-folde, The one acquired by studie, and comes neere to that of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers; which I am to speake of: The other infused and giuen by God, <hi>De sursum descendens.</hi> This is the first of the seuen gifts of the Holy Ghost, <hi>Spiritus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, spiritus sapientiae,</hi> which is not found but only in those that are iust and free from sinne, <hi>In maleuolam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimam</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Sap.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>non introibit sapientia.</hi> Of this Diuine wisdome likewise our purpose is not heere to speake, it is after some sort and measure handled in my first Veritie, and in my Discourses of Diuinitie.</p>
   <p>It followeth therefore, that it is Humane wisdome <note place="margin">5 Humane.</note> which in this Booke we are to deliuer vnto you, and whereof it takes the name, and of which in this place we must giue some briefe and generall view, which may be as an Argument and Summarie of this whole worke. The common descriptions are diuers and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sufficient; <note place="margin">Wisdome according to the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon sort.</note> Some and the greatest part thinke that it is only a wisdome, discretion, and aduised carriage in a mans affaires and conuersation. This may well be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led common, as respecting nothing but that which is outward and in action, and considereth not at all any other thing than that which outwardly appeareth. It is altogether in the eyes and eares of men, without any respect or very little of the inward motions of the minde: so that according to their opinion wisdome may be without essentiall pietie or probitie, that is, a beautifull cunning, a sweet and modest subtiltie. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers thinke that it is a rude, vnreasonable, rough singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laritie,
<pb facs="12"/>
a kinde of sullen frowning and frampole austeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in opinions, maners, words, actions and fashion of life; and therfore they call them that are wounded and touched with that humor Philosophers, that is to say, in their counterfeit language, fantasticall, diuers, diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and declining from the customes of other men.</p>
   <p>Now this kinde of wisdome according to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of our booke is rather a follie and extrauagancie. You must therefore know, that this wisdome whereof we speake is not that of the common people, but of Philosophers and Diuines, whereof both haue written in their morall learnings. The Philosophers more at <note place="margin">Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines.</note> large, and more professedly as being their true and proper dish they feed on, and formall subiect they write of, because they applie themselues to that which concerneth Nature and Action. Diuinitie mounteth <note place="margin">A compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie &amp; Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie.</note> much higher, and is occupied about vertues infused, Contemplatiue and Diuine, that is to say, about Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine wisdome and Beleefe. So that Philosophers are more stayed, dispersed more certeine, and more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, ruling and instructing not onely the particular knowledge or actions of men, but the common and publike, teaching that which is good and profitable to Families, Corporations, Common-weales, Empires. Diuinitie is more sparing and silent in this point, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king principallie into the eternall good and saluation of euery one. Againe, the Philosopher handleth this subiect more sweetly and pleasingly, the Diuine more austerely and drily. Againe, Philosophie which is the elder (for Nature is more ancient than Grace, and the Naturall than the Supernaturall) seemeth to perswade gratiously, as being willing to please in profiting, as the Poet speaketh:</p>
   <q>
      <l>
         <pb facs="13"/>
Simul &amp; iucunda &amp; idonea dicere vita <note place="margin">Horace.</note>
      </l>
      <l>Lectorem delect ando, pariter{que} monando.</l>
   </q>
   <p>It is enriched with discourses, reasons, inuentions, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, similitudes, decked with speeches, Apoph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thegmes, sententious mots, adorned with Eloquence and Arte. Theologie, which came after, altogether austere, it seemeth to command and imperiously like a Master to enioyne. And to conclude, the vertue and honestie of Diuines is too anxious, scrupulous, deiect, sad, fearefull and vulgar. Philosophie, such as this Booke teacheth, is altogether pleasant, free, bucksom, and if I may so say, wanton too; and yet notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, puissant, noble, generous, and rare. Doubtlesse the Philosophers haue heerin been excellent, not only in writing and teaching, but in the rich and liuely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentation thereof in their honourable and heroicall liues. I vnderstand heere by Philosophers and Wise men, not onely those that haue carried the name of Wise men, such as <hi>Thales, Solon,</hi> and the rest of that ranke, that liued in the time of <hi>Cyrus, Cresus, Pisistra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes;</hi> nor those that came afterwards, and haue publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taught it, as <hi>Pythagoras, Socrates, Plato, Aristotle, Aristippus, Zenon, Antisthenes,</hi> all chiefe Professours apart, and many other their Disciples different and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided in sects; but also all those great men who haue made singular and exemplary profession of vertue and wisdome, as <hi>Phocion, Aristides, Pericles, Alexander,</hi> whom <hi>Plutarch</hi> called as well a Philosopher as a King, <hi>Epaminondas,</hi> and diuers other Greeks: The <hi>Fabricij, Fabij, Camilli, Catoni, Torquati, Reguli, Lelij, Scipio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> Romans, who for the most part haue beene Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals in armies. And these are the reasons why in this my Booke I doe more willingly and ordinarily follow
<pb facs="13"/>
the aduice and sayings of Philosophers, not in the mean time omitting or reiecting those of the Diuines: For both in substance they doe all agree, and are verie sold me different, and Diuinitie doth nothing disdaine to employ, and to make good vse of the wise sayings of Philosophie. If I had vndertaken to instruct the cloister, and the retired life, that is, that profession which attendeth the secrets Euangelicall, I must ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily haue followed <hi>adamussim</hi> the aduice of the Diuines: but our Booke instructeth a ciuill life, form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a man for the world, that is to say, to humane wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, not diuine.</p>
   <p>We say then naturally and generally both with the <note place="margin">6 A generall descripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note> Philosopher and the Diuine, that this humane wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is a kinde of law or reason, a beautifull and noble composition of the entire man, both in his inward part and his outward, his thoughts, his words, his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and all his motions. It is the excellencie and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of man as he is man, that is to say, according to that which the first fundamentall and naturall law doth require; as wee say, That that worke is well wrought and excellent, that is compleat and perfectin all the parts thereof, and wherein all the rules of Arte haue beene obserued; that man is accounted a wise man, that best knoweth after the best and most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent maner to play the man, that is to say, (to giue a more particular picture thereof) that knowing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe and the condition of man, doth keepe and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue himselfe from all vices, errours, passions and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects as well inward and proper to himselfe, as outward and common to other men, mainteining his spirit pure, free, vniuersall, considering and iudging of all things without band or affection, alwayes ruling and
<pb facs="14"/>
directing himself in all things according to nature, that is to say, that first reason and vniuersall law and light inspired by God, and which shineth in vs, vnto which he doth apply and accommodate his owne proper and particular light, liuing in the outward view of the world, and with all men according to their lawes, customes and ceremonies of the countrey where he is, without the offence of any, carrying himselfe wisely and discreetly in all affaires, walking alwaies vprightly, constant, comfortable, and content in himselfe, atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding peaceably whatsoeuer may happen, and at the last death it selfe. All these parts or qualities, which are many, for our better ease and facilitie may be drawen to foure principall heads; Knowledge of our selues, Libertie of spirit pure and generous, Imitation of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, (this hath a very large field, and alone might al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most suffice) True contentment. These can no where be found but in him that is wise: and he that wanteth any of these can not be wise. He that hath an errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous knowledge of himselfe, that subiecteth his minde to any kinde of seruitude, either of passions or popular opinions, makes himselfe partiall; and by enthralling himselfe to some particular opinion is depriued of the libertie and iurisdiction of discerning, iudging and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining all things. Hee that striueth against Nature, vnder what pretence soeuer it be, following rather opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion or passion than reason; he that carrieth himselfe troubledly, disquietly, malcontent, fearing death, is not wise. Beholde heere in a few words the picture of Humane wisdome and folly, and the sum of that which I purpose to handle in this Worke, especially in the Second Booke, which expresly containeth the rules, treatise, and offices of Wisdome, which is more mine
<pb facs="14"/>
than the other two, and which I once thought to haue published by it selfe. This verball description of Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is represented vnto the eye euen at the entrance or threshall of this Booke by a woman all naked, in a place void and empty, resting her selfe vpon nothing, in her pure and simple nature beholding her selfe in a glasse, her countenance cheerefull, merry and manly, vpright, her feet close ioyned, vpon a square pillar, and imbracing herselfe, hauing vnder her feet inchained foure other women as slaues vnto her, that is to say, <hi>Passion</hi> with a changed and hideous countenance; <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> with wandering eyes, inconstant, giddy, borne vpon the heads of the people; <hi>Superstition,</hi> astonished and in a trance, and her hands fastened the one to the other; <hi>Vertue</hi> or Honestie and Pedanticall Science with a sullen visage, her eye-lids eleuated reading in a Booke, where was written, <hi>Yea, No.</hi> All this needs no other explication, than that which heereafter follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, but heereof more at large in the Second Booke.</p>
   <p>To attaine vnto this wisdome there are two meanes, <note place="margin">7 Two ways to attaine this wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note> the first is in the originall forming and first temper, that is to say, in the temperature of the seed of the Parents, the milke of the Nurse, and the first education; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a man is sayd to be either well borne, or ill borne, that is to say, either well or ill formed and disposed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to wisdome. A man would little thinke of what pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and importance this beginning is, for if men did know it, there would be more care taken, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence vsed therein than there is. It is a strange and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable thing, that so reachlesse a carelesnesse should be in vs of the life and good life of those whom we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to make our other selues, when in matters of lesse importance we take more care, vse more diligence,
<pb facs="15"/>
more counsell than we should, neuer thinking of our greatest affaires and most honourable, but by hazzard and peraduenture. Who is he that taketh counsell with himselfe, or endeuoureth to do that which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired for the preseruing and preparing of himselfe as he ought to the generation of male-children, health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of spirit, and apt for wisdome? For that which ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth for the one, serueth for the other, and Nature af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter one maner attendeth them all. This is that which men thinke of least, yea little or not at all (in the act of generation) doth it enter into their thoughts to frame a new creature like themselues, but only like beasts to satisfie their lustfull pleasures. This is one of the most important faults and of greatest note in a Common weale, whereof there is not one that thinketh or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth, neither is there concerning it either law, or rule, or publike aduice. It is most certeine, that if men did heerein carrie themselues as they ought, we should haue other men, of more excellent spirit and condition than we haue amongst vs. What is required heerein, and to the first nourishment and education, is briefly set downe in our Third Booke, <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.</p>
   <p>The second meanes to attaine wisdome is the studie <note place="margin">8 Acquired.</note> of Philosophie, I meane not of all the parts thereof, but Morall (yet not forgetting the Naturall) which is the light, the guide, the rule of our life, which explai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth and representeth vnto vs the law of Nature, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structeth man vniuersally in all things, both publike and priuate, alone and in companie, in all domesticall and ciuill conuersation, taketh away all that sauage na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that is in vs, sweetneth and tameth our naturall rudenesse, crueltie and wildnesse, and worketh and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shioneth it to wisdome. To be briefe, it is the true sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="15"/>
of man; all the rest in respect of it is but vanitie, or at the leastwise not necessarie or little profitable: for it giueth instructions to liue and to die well, which is all in all; it teacheth vs perfect wisdome, an apt iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous well aduised honesty. But this second meane is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most as little practised and as ill employed as the first: for no man careth greatly for this wisdome, so much are all giuen to that which is worldly. Thus you see the two principall meanes to attaine to wisdome, the Naturall and Acquired. He that hath beene fortunate in the first, that is to say, that hath been fauourably for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by Nature, that is, of a good and sweet tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which bringeth forth a great goodnesse in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and sweetnes in maners, hath made a faire march without great paine to the second: But that man with whom it is otherwise, must with great and painfull stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of the second beautifie and supplie that which is wanting, as <hi>Socrates</hi> one of the wisest sayd of himselfe, That by the studie of Philosophie he had corrected and reformed his naturall infirmities.</p>
   <p>There are contrariwise two formall lets or hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances <note place="margin">9 The lets to Wisdome, and means to folly are tvvo.</note> to wisdome, and two counter-meanes or pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull wayes vnto follie, Naturall and Acquired. The first, which is naturall, proceedeth from the originall temper and temperature, which maketh the braine ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too soft, moist, and the parts thereof grosse and <note place="margin">1 Naturall.</note> materiall, whereby the spirits remaine sottish, feeble, lesse capable, plaine diminished, obscure, such as that is, for the most part, of the common sort of people; or too hot, ardent, and drie, which maketh the spirits foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish, audacious, vitious. These are the two extremes, <hi>Sottishnesse</hi> and <hi>Follie,</hi> Water and Fire, Lead and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curie, altogether improper or vnapt to wisdom, which
<pb facs="16"/>
requireth a spirit full of vigor and generous, and yet sweet, pliant, and modest: but the second is more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily amended by discipline than the former.</p>
   <p>The second, which is Acquired, proceedeth either <note place="margin">2 Acquired.</note> from no culture and instruction, or from that which is euill, which amongst other things consisteth in an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinate and sworne preiudicate preuention of opinions, wherewith the minde is made drunken, and taketh so strong a tincture, that it is made vnapt and vncapable to see or to finde better whereby to raise and inrich it selfe. It is sayd of these kinde of men, That they are wounded and stricken, that they haue a hurt or blow in the head: vnto which wound if likewise learning be ioined, because that puffeth vp, it bringeth with it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption and temeritie, and somtimes armes to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and defend those anticipated opinions: it altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perfecteth the forme and frame of follie, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it incurable. So that naturall weaknesse, and acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red preuention are two great hinderances; but science, if it do not wholly cure them, which seldome it doth, strengtheneth them and maketh them inuincible, which turneth not any way to the dishonour of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as a man may well thinke) but to the greater ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thereof.</p>
   <p>Science or Learning is a very good and profitable <note place="margin">10 Of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> staffe or waster, but which will not be handled with all hands; and he that knowes not well how to rule it, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth thereby more hurt than profit. It besotteth and maketh foolish (saith a great learned writer) the weake <note place="margin">See heerof <hi>Li.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 14.</note> and sicke spirit, it polisheth and perfecteth the natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly strong and good. The feeble spirit knowes not how to possesse science, how to handle it, and how to make vse thereof as he should; but contrariwise is possessed
<pb facs="16"/>
and ruled by it, whereby he submits himselfe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines a slaue to it, like a weake stomacke ouerchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with more victuals than it can digest. A weake arme wanting power and skill well to weld a waster or staffe that is somewhat too heauie for it, wearieth it selfe and fainteth. A wise and courageous spirit ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mastereth his wisdome, enioyeth it, vseth it, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployeth it to his best aduantage, enformeth his owne iudgement, rectifieth his will, helpeth and fortifieth his naturall light, and maketh himselfe more quicke and actiue; wheras the other is made thereby more sottish, more vnapt, and therewithall more presumptuous: so that the fault or reproch is not in learning, no more than that wine or other good drugge is faultie which a man knoweth not how to apply and accommodate to his owne needs: <hi>Non est culpa vini, sed culpa bibentis.</hi> Now then against such spirits weake by nature, preoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupated, puffed vp, and hindred by acquired wisdome I make open warre in this Booke, and that often times vnder the word <hi>Pedante,</hi> not finding any other more <note place="margin">Of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vvord <hi>Pedante</hi> or Schoole-master.</note> proper, and which by many good Authours is vsed in this sense. In it owne Greeke Originall it was taken in the better sense, but in other later languages, by reason of the abuse, and bad carriage of such men in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of their learning, it is accounted base, vile, que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stuous, contentious, opinatiue, vain-glorious and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptuous, by too many practised, and vsed but by way of iniurie and derision, and is in the number of those words that by continuance of time haue changed their signification, as <hi>Tyrant, Sophister,</hi> and diuers other. <hi>Le sieur de Bellay,</hi> after the rehearsall of many notorious vices, concludeth as with the greatest, <hi>But of all the rest, Knowledge pedanticall I detest.</hi> And in another place:</p>
   <q>
      <l>
         <pb facs="17"/>
Sayd I thou didst liue but to eat and drinke,</l>
      <l>Then poore were my reuenge, thy faults scantie:</l>
      <l>But that which most doth make thy name to stinke,</l>
      <l>Is, to be short, thou art a Pedantie.</l>
   </q>
   <p>It may be some will take offence at this word, thinking <note place="margin">An aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisement.</note> it likewise toucheth them, and that I thereby haue a will to tax or scoffe the Professors and Teachers of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; but let them be pleased to content themselues with this free and open declaration which I here make, That it is no part of my meaning to note by this word any gown-men or learned profession whatsoeuer: yea I am so farre from it, that Philosophers are in so high esteeme with me, that I should oppose my selfe against my selfe, because I account my selfe one of them, and professe the same learning: only I touch a certaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree and qualitie of spirits, before desciphered, that is, such as haue naturall capacitie and sufficiencie after a common and indifferent maner, but afterwards not well tilled, preoccupated, possessed with certaine opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; and these are men of all fortunes, all conditions, and goe as well in short garments as in long gownes: <hi>Vulgum tam chlamidatos, quàm coronam voco.</hi> If any man can furnish me with any other word as significant as this to expresse these kinde of spirits, I will willingly forgo this. After this my declaration, he that findeth himselfe agrieued, shall but accuse and shew himselfe too scrupulous. It is true that a man may finde other opposites to a wise man besides a <hi>Pedante,</hi> but it is in some particular sense, as the common, prophane, vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar sort of people; and often times I vse these opposits: but this is as the low is opposite to the high, the weake to the strong, the valley to the hill, the common to the rare, the seruant to the master, the prophane to the
<pb facs="17"/>
holy; as also a foole, which indeed according to the true sound of the word, is his truest opposite: but this is a moderate man to an immoderate, a glorious opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiue man to a modest, the part to the whole, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudicate and tainted to the neat and free, the sicke to the sound: but this word <hi>Pedante</hi> in that sense we take it, comprehendeth all these and more too, for it noteth and signifieth him that is not only vnlike &amp; contrary to a wise man, as those before mentioned, but such a one as arrogantly and insolently resisteth it to the face, and as being armed on all sides raiseth himselfe against it, speaking out of resolution and authoritie. And foras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as after a sort he feareth it, by reason that he seeth himselfe discouered euen from the top to the bottome, and his sport troubled by it, he prosecuteth it with a certaine intestine hatred, he taketh vpon him to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure it, to defame it, to condemne it, accounting and carrying himselfe as the truely wise, though he be a foole without peere and an ignorant selfe-conceited Gull.</p>
   <p>After the purpose and argument of this Worke, we <note place="margin">11 The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of this book.</note> come to the order and method thereof. There are three Books: The First is wholly in the knowledge of our selues and humane condition, as a preparatiue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to wisdome, which is handled at large by fiue maine and principall considerations, ech one including in it diuers others. The Second Booke containeth in it the treatises, offices, and generall and principall rules of wisdome. The Third, the particular rules and instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of wisdome, and that by the order and discourse of foure principall and morall vertues, <hi>Prudence, Iustice, Fortitude, Temperance;</hi> vnder which foure is compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the whole instruction of the life of man, and all the
<pb facs="18"/>
parts of dutie and honestie. Finally, I heere handle this matter, not Scholarlike or Pedantically, nor with enlarged discourse, and furniture of Eloquence or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Arte; (For wisdome <hi>(quae si oculis ipsis cerneretur mirabiles excitaret amores sui)</hi> needs no such helps to commend it selfe, being of it selfe so noble and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) but rudely, openly, and ingeniously, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps will not please all. The propositions and verities are compact, but many times drie and sower, like A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorismes, ouertures and seeds of discourse.</p>
   <p>Some thinke this Booke too foole-hardie and free <note place="margin">12 An Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisement &amp; Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie to the Reader.</note> to contradict and wound the common opinions, and are offended therewith, whom in foure or fiue words I thus answer: First, that wisdome which is neither common nor vulgar hath properly this libertie and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, <hi>Iure suo singulari,</hi> to iudge of all, (it is the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> of a wise and spirituall man, <hi>spiritualis omnia dijudicat, &amp; a nemine iudicatur)</hi> and in iudging to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure and condemne (as for the most part erroneous) common and vulgar opinions. What then should she doe? for the case standing thus, it can not be, but she must incurre the disgrace and enuie of the world. In another place I complaine of these kinde of men, and reproue their popular weaknesse and feminine dainti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> as vnworthy, being ouer-tender and delicate, to vnderstand any thing of worth, and altogether vnca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of wisdome. The hardest and hardiest proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are best befitting a hardie and eleuated spirit, and there can nothing seeme strnage vnto him that doth but know what the world is. It is weaknesse to be asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished at any thing, we must rowze vp our hearts, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme and strengthen our mindes, harden and inure our selues to heare, to know, to vnderstand, to iudge
<pb facs="18"/>
of all things seeme they neuer so strange. All things are agreeing and well befitting the palat of the spirit, so a man be not wanting vnto himselfe, and neither do any thing, or yeeld his consent to whatsoeuer is not good and truly faire, no though the whole world per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade him vnto it. A wise man sheweth equally in them both his courage, his delicates are not capable of the one or the other, there being a weaknesse in them both.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, in all that I shall propose, my meaning is <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> not to binde any man vnto it, I only present things, and lay them out as it were vpon a stall; I grow not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to choler with any man that giues me no credit, or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes my ware, that were to play the <hi>Pedante. Passion</hi> witnesseth that it is not reason so to do, and he that out of passion doth any thing out of reason can not doe it. But why are they angrie with me? Is it because I am not altogether of their opinion? Why, I am not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with them because they are not of mine. Is it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I speake something which is not pleasing to their taste, or to the palat of the vulgar sort? Why there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I speake it. I speake nothing without reason, if they knew how to vnderstand it, how to relish it. If they can bring better reason to disproue mine, I will hearken vnto it with delight and thanks to him that shall shew it me. But yet let them not thinke to beat me downe with authorities, multitudes, and allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of other men, for these haue but small credit in my iurisdiction, saue in matter of Religion, where only au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie preuailes without reason. This is authorities true Empire, reason onely bearing sway in all other Arts without it, as <hi>S. Augustine</hi> doth very well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge. For it is an vniust tyranny and an inraged
<pb facs="19"/>
follie to subiect and in thrall our spirits to beleeue and to follow whatsoeuer our Ancestours haue sayd, and what the vulgar sort holde to be true, who know nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what they say, nor what they do. There are none but fooles that suffer themselues to be thus led by the noses: and this Booke is not for such, which if it should popularlie be receiued and accepted of the common sort of people, it should faile much in it first purpose and designment. We must heare, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, make account of our ancient Writers, not cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuate our selues vnto them but with reason. And if a man would follow them, what should he doe? for they agree not among themselues. <hi>Aristotle</hi> who would seeme to be the most sufficient amongst them, and hath aduentured to challenge &amp; to censure all that went before him, hath vttered more grosse absurdities than them all, and is at no agreement with himselfe, neither doth he know many times where he is; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse his Treatises of the Soule of man, of the Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the world, of the Generation of the windes and waters, and so forth. It is no cause of wonder or asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment, that all men are not of one opinion; but it were rather strange and woonderfull, that all men were of one opinion: for there is nothing more befit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Nature and the spirit of man than varietie. That wise Diuine <hi>S. Paul</hi> giueth vs this libertie, in that he <note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.</note> willeth euery man to abound in his owne vnderstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not iudging or condemning that man that doth otherwise, or thinke otherwise. And he speaketh it in a matter of greater moment and more ticklish, not in that which consisteth in outward action and obserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein we say we are to conforme our selues to the common sort, and to that which is prescribed and
<pb facs="19"/>
accustomed to be done, but also in that which concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth Religion, that is, the religious obseruance of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ands and dayes: whereas all that libertie and boldnesse of speech which I challenge vnto my selfe, is but in thoughts, iudgements, opinions, in which no man is quarter-master but he that hath them, euery man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout himselfe.</p>
   <p>Not withstanding all this, many things which may <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> seeme too harsh and briefe, too rude and difficult for the simpler sort (for the stronger and wiser haue sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks warme enough to concoct and digest all) I haue for the loue of them explicated, enlightned and sweetned in this second Edition, reuiewed, and much augmented.</p>
   <p>I would willingly aduertise the Reader that shall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> vndertake to iudge of this Worke, to take heed that he fall not into any of these seuen ouersights, as some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue done; that is: To referre that vnto law and dutie, which is proper vnto action; that vnto action, which is onely to be censured; that to resolution and determination, which is only proposed, consulted of, and problematically and Academically disputed; that to me and mine opinions, which I deliuer from report, and is the opinion of another man; that to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward state, profession, and condition, which is proper to the spirit and inward sufficiencie; that to religion and faith, which is but the opinion of man; that to grace and supernaturall inspiration, which is proper to naturall and morall vertue and action. All passion and preoccupation being taken away, hee shall finde in these seuen points well vnderstood how to resolue himselfe in his doubts, how to answer all obiections, made by himselfe or by others, and informe himselfe
<pb facs="20"/>
touching my intention in this worke. And if neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse after all this, he will neither rest satisfied and contented, nor approue what I haue written, let him boldly and speedily disproue it (for onely to speake ill, to bite, to slander the name of another man, though it be easie enough, yet it is base and pedanticall) and he shall as speedily receiue either a free confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and assent, (for this Booke doth glory and feast it selfe in the truth and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuitie thereof) or an examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the impertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and follies thereof.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>