<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Readers.</title>
           <author>L., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116493_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11408</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21663</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116493</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Readers.</title>
                 <author>L., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Part of Du Bartas : English and French, and in his owne kinde of verse, so neare the French Englished, as may teach an English-man French, or a French-man English. With the commentary of S.G. S. By William L'Isle of Wilburgham, Esquier for the Kings body</title>
                 <author>Du Bartas, Guillaume de Salluste, seigneur</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>17, 4, 4, 5-8, 9-19, 9-19, 20-23, 24-25, 24-25, 26-28, 28-30, 31-36, 31-36, 37-39, 39-43, 44-48, 44-48, 49-51, 51-54, 54-60, 61-63, 61-63, 64-69, 70-77, 70-77, 78-93, 94-100, 94-100, 101-104, 105-109, 105-109, 110-115, 116-118, 116-118, 119-124, 125-133, 125-133, 134-137, 138-142, 138-142, 143-148, 149-151, 149-151, 152-153, 154-158, 154-158, 159-168, 169-171, 169-171, 172-173, 174-176, 174-176, 177-178, 176-181, 181-186, 2 pages, illustrations (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>To the Readers.</head>
   <p>COnyes, whom <hi>Salomon</hi> reckons among the wise Little-ones vpon earth, do make many skraplets and profers on the ground, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they dig earnestly for their neast or litter; and writing-schollers draw first in blotting paper many a dash, roundell, and minime, before they frame the perfect letters that shall stand to their coppie: so entending some worke that may (if I be so happie) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main some while after me, many waies do I essay and try first my stile and pen; that according also to the wise rule of <hi>Horace,</hi> I may thereby iudge my selfe and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne <hi>quid valeant humeri, quid ferre recusent.</hi> Nor do I trust my owne iudgement herein, so likely to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall; but commonly present my worke in writing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it bee printed, vnto some <hi>Quintilius</hi> or other, whose noble disposition will, authoritie may, and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is able to find fault and aduise me. Yet among the sundrie versets or prosets, which besides this, I haue or shall set-out, if you find some that sauour of my younger time; passe by them (I pray you) or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foord them the fauour, that my <hi>Quintilius</hi> doth, to let them passe, because they were the way that led me to a grauer kind: as also the grauest of humain Poetrie,
<pb facs="8"/>brought me at last to the diuine; whereof I haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Essayes, now almost readie for the presse. This translation of <hi>Salust du Bartas</hi> what present occasion draweth from me you may well perceiue: yet thinke me not herein <hi>Acta agere,</hi> to do that which was before done, and very well by <hi>Iosua Siluester;</hi> for it is in a diuers kind, and, many yeares ere he began, this had I lying by me: yea partly published in print (as <hi>Anno 1596,</hi> &amp; <hi>Anno 1598</hi>) and dedicated to the late Noble <hi>Charles</hi> Earle of Nottingham. But now the cause why in this I beginne so abruptly, is for that I was loth to come neere the booke next aforegoing; which our late Soueraigne Lord King <hi>Iames</hi> in his youth so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably made English; yet had I a desire to fall vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that braue commendation of our late Soueraigne La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and her people, in the second booke here, and that of France, in the third; both laid together betokning (as it were) some new bond of Loue shortly to come betwixt that Realme and this; which we all pray the Lord to prosper.</p>
   <p>To make way then yet more for this mutuall acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance by communication of Language, thus much of that Noble Poet I thought meet to counterpage with French and English. Not all, both because the Kings happie match growing on so fast, I had no time to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish and print so great a volume; and for that I may
<pb facs="8"/>say of this Author, as of <hi>Homer,</hi> know foure of his bookes, and know them all: for thus much onely may suffice (I presume) to helpe an Englishman vnderstand the whole French of <hi>Bartas,</hi> or a Frenchman the whole English of <hi>Siluestor.</hi> If you aske me why I keepe this kind of <hi>Hexameter</hi> verse, I need say no more, but that it is the same which the Author kept in the originall: and he doubtlesse, for the more graue, made choice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with great reason, according to the counsell of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race,</hi> who aduiseth all writers, <hi>Descriptas seruare vices, operumque colores:</hi> his reason followes (which with little alteration of the verse I may hereto fitly applie)
<q>
         <l>Indignantur enim communibus &amp; propè socco,</l>
         <l>Dignis carminibus, dici primordia Mundi.</l>
      </q>
And what is our English Pentameter but the same kind of verse which is vsed in our Comedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s? Besides, I had a desire to trie how French and English would go hand in hand; for enter changeable helpe and teaching of the one by the other; now both Nations are so well incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to learne and conferre together. For which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose I found this worke very fit, and readiest on such a sodain to present my Lord the King withall, at the here celebration of his marriage. And herefore onely, if there were none other cause, yet (gentle Readers) my hope is yee will hold me excused. I was about to end; but may not forget to let you vnderstand, that this Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tassian
<pb facs="9"/>verse (not vnlike herein to the Latin Pantame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) hath euer this propertie, to part in the mids betwixt two wordes: so much doe some French prints signifie, with a stroke interposed, as here in the first two pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges you may see, for example. The neglect of this hath caused many a braue Stanza in the F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>irie Queene to end but harshly, which might haue beene preuented at the first, but now the fault may be sooner found then amended. I doe but note it vnto you, that you may the better obserue the true cadence of this our Authors verse: and so craning your fauourable construction of these, and all my like endeauours, I rest willing to doe you what further seruice I am able.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>VV. L.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>