<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS SACRED MAIESTIE.</title>
           <author>Ryves, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116301_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11213</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21478</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116301</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS SACRED MAIESTIE.</title>
                 <author>Ryves, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The poore vicars plea : Declaring, that a competencie of meanes is due to them out of the tithes of their seuerall parishes, notwithstanding the impropriations. Written by Thomas Ryves Dr. of the Ciuile Lawes</title>
                 <author>Ryves, Thomas, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bill, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 152 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO HIS SACRED</hi> MAIESTIE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST Religious and Gracious Souereigne, As it is not vnknowen to the world, in how miserable a plight our poore Church of <hi>IRELAND</hi> standeth at this present; So wee of that Kingdome know right well, and with all thankefulnesse acknowledge, that your Maiestie hath euer made it one of your most Princely and Christian cares, to raise her vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb facs="4"/>
if by any meanes you could, out of the dust, and to set her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Daughters, as sometimes you did her Sister of <hi>SCOTLAND,</hi> which formerly lay buried vnder the like heape of <hi>Impropriations,</hi> as the other doeth at this present time.</p>
   <p>The knowledge whereof, dread Souereigne, hath emboldened mee, the meanest of all the Professours of the Lawes, to present this short Discourse vnto your Highnesse: wherein I haue endeauoured to prooue, that the poore Ministers of that Church, ought to be more competently prouided for, then now they are, and that, out of the Tithes belonging to their seuerall
<pb facs="4"/>
Churches, not by Praerogatiue, whereof your Maiestie is euer sparefull, but by a due course of Law, alreadie there established: Wishing from my heart, that this cause of GOD and of his Church, had found an Aduocate, answera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the dignitie and iustice of it. As it is, I shall humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech your Maiestie, that neither the unworthinesse of my person, neither yet the vnlikelihood of the matter, be any preiudice to the worth and trueth of the cause it selfe; but rather, that your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse will vouchsafe to looke downe upon this poore endeavour of your humble Seruant, with a fauourable eye, and to supply those manifold
<pb facs="5"/>
defects, which may happily bee found in the handling of so great and difficult a cause, out of that abundant and incomparable trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of Learning and Wisedome, which GOD hath so richly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed your Princely minde with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: In hope whereof, with my humble prayers to Almightie GOD, for the preseruation of your Maiesties long and prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Reigne, I rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Highnesse most loyall Subiect and humble seruant, THO. RYVES.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>