<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116697_Bo1_9_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11516</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21762</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116697</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of the Councel of Trent : Conteining eight bookes. In which (besides the ordinarie actes of the Councell) are declared many notable occurrences, which happened in Christendome, during the space of fourtie yeeres and more. And, particularly, the practises of the Court of Rome, to hinder the reformation of their errors, and to maintaine their greatnesse. Written in Italian by Pietro Soaue Polano, and faithfully translated into English by Nathanael Brent</title>
                 <author>Sarpi, Paolo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 <publisher>Bill, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, Bonham</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 881, that is 879, 17 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="423"/>
   <pb n="827" facs="423"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow that thou hast perused this History, I intreat thee to reade ouer these small parcels following. The first is an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle of S. <hi>Gregorie</hi> the great, who was Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> about sixe hundred yeeres after <hi>CHRIST,</hi> and was as lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and as consciencious, as any that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded in that Sea, or that followed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Thou canst not but perceiue, that howsoeuer hee ascribeth to <hi>S Peter</hi> as much preheminence as any other ancient writer hath done, if not more, yet hee doth renounce in most ample tearmes, or rather abominate that swelling Antichristian power which was then chalenged by <hi>Iohn</hi> the Patriarch of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> but long since hath been practised by the Bishops of <hi>Rome,</hi> and neuer more, nor more preiudicially to the Church Catholique, then in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Councell of <hi>Trent.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And that thou mayst not wonder how these Bishops could sore so high as to bee at last aboue Kings and Emperours, to whom S. <hi>Gregorie</hi> and his predecessours professed and performed all dueti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full obedience and seruice, I haue tendred vnto thee in the next place three seuerall passages out of the Historie of <hi>Francis Guic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciardine,</hi> a famous <hi>Florentine,</hi> who knew their practises as well as any, and hath dared to relate them plainly. The Papalins haue been so wise in their wicked generation, as in all late Editions, to cause them to bee left out; thereby the better to conceale their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iust vsurpations, against both Ecclesistiques and Laiques.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="828" facs="424"/>
Now, lest any might vncontrolably say, that howsoeuer they might bee faulty at other times, yet those were worthy who gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> when this Councell was assembled, to cleere the trueth concerning these, looke ouer the passages following, taken out of some Epistles written by men of great esteeme, who resided in the Councell, and gaue account to their Superiours of all that passed, or by their Superiours to them backe againe. By these it will appeare that the spirit of Antichrist, and not the holy Ghost, did gouerne in it. They shew the practises of <hi>Rome</hi> to be so grosse, and so abhominable, that thou mayest easily beleeue, that <note n="*" place="margin">Invita Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li 3.</note>
      <hi>Papirius Massonius,</hi> a Popish writer, had iust cause to say, speaking of the Popes who liued in the time of this Councell; <hi>In pontificibus ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo hodiè sanctitatem requirit; optimi putantur si vel leuitêr mali sint, vel minus boni quam caeteri mortales esse solent.</hi> Englished thus: No man expects any sanctitie in Popes now a dayes; they are thought to be excellent Popes, if they haue neuer so little honestie, or be not so wicked as other men vse to be.</p>
   <p>Last of all, thou mayest reade an Epistle written by that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Prelate, Bishop <hi>Iewell,</hi> as an answere to a friend of his, who liued neere the place, and in the time of this vnlawfull assembly, or conuenticle at <hi>Trent.</hi> In it thou mayest finde reason enough, why the Church of <hi>England</hi> did neither send Prelates to it, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue afterwards the Decrees and Constitutions of it. As like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise the Church of <hi>France</hi> refused to doe, though their Bishops were present in it. When thou hast read these things, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der well of them, and the Lord giue thee a true vnderstanding in all things.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>GREGORIE</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>