<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Preface]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116309_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11229</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21492</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116309</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Preface]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sacræ heptades, or Seaven problems concerning Antichrist : 1. of his place. 2. Of his state. 3. Of his names. 4. Of his rising. 5. Of his raigne. 6. Of his words and actions. 7. Of his times. Necessarie to be read and knowne of all men, who professe Christ Iesus, and hope t be saved by no other name. By G.S</title>
                 <author>Salteren, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles, Successors of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 215, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <opener>To all Kings, Princes, and Potentates, especially to King <hi>Charles</hi> Defendor of the Fayth, and to the King and Queene of Bohemia professing the Fayth, and therefore per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted. Also to all other Christians, whether Reformed, or Romish.</opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongst all those controversies, which like cloudes overcast the Church of Christ at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, so that many stumble at noone day as at night, and but a few are truely resolved of their owne aright walking with God, according to knowledge, there is none more necessarie to be generally understood, then that of <hi>Antichrist</hi>: both because this <hi>Egiptian darknesse,</hi> which is in the land <hi>of Goshen,</hi> proceeds from his inchantments, to hold <hi>Pharoh</hi> still in the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of heart: and also because the externall splendor and glorie of his seate, supported with the countenance of <hi>Magicall science, bellish unitie, carnall succession, corrupt custome, ragged antiquitie, Idolatrous universalitie. Counterfeit miracles, hypocriticall sanctitie, stupenduous amplitude, blinde devotion, formidable tyrannie, Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique power,</hi> and <hi>worldly felicitie</hi> (as Salomons throne was with ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons cunningly carved) doe much dazle vulgar judgments,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 10, 19, 20.</note> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maze the sillie Lambes of Christ. But if this Magitian were fully discovered to be but an Impostor, and onely to bumbast his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation with lyes, forgeries and usurpations (like a spirituall Quack-salver) then the more that Princes and people had doted upon him, and deified him, the more they would hate him,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rev.</hi> 17, 16, 17.</note> as those Kings shall, who out of godly indignation, <hi>hate, strip, eate the flesh of the whore, and burne her with fire.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>This the learned Limbs of <hi>Antichrist</hi> understand verie well, and therefore eyther terrifie all men from looking into the <hi>booke of God,</hi> where Antichrist is described (at least from looking into the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> where he is set out to the life) or else, as the Scribes and Pharises did with their corrupt glosses and Comments made upon the Prophets, <hi>darken</hi> the comming of Christ, and <hi>denye</hi> him being come, <hi>putting off</hi> the time of their Messias hitherto, <hi>deferring,</hi> and <hi>dallying,</hi> as the Turkes doe with their Mahomet, yea <hi>fayning</hi> his person to be <hi>humaine onely,</hi> and his <hi>Office temporall,</hi> thereby to hold the Iewes still in spirituall Captivitie, by causing them to deny the Sonne of God their Saviour: so doe these waue the comming of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and with their corrupt glosses, and misapplications turne the truth of God into a lye, causing the world to embrace the <hi>Sonne of perdition</hi>; by telling them of an Antichrist, that must be <hi>a singular person,</hi> and not a succession (as if we designed such a succession,<note place="margin">
         <p>This they would proue, by the names giuen him in the singular number, <hi>2</hi> Thes. <hi>2, 3.</hi> As also by the article <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>, or <hi>ille,</hi> being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstratiue particles. But Gramarians say that not onely proper names, and words that signifie indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduall things, but names that signifie a multitude or succession, nownes appellatiue, collectiue, and successiue, are both in Greeke and Latin expressed in the singular number, and joyned with that demonstratiue particle. <hi>As hic populus, ille rex,</hi> in aggregation, succession, or collection. <hi>1</hi> Pet. <hi>2, 17.</hi>
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>.</p>
         <p>Philosopher; say that <hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>num</hi> one, may be taken not onely singulatim, but congregatim, and summa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim. And that a thing may be idem numero, not onely as the sunne, but as a heape of corne, a flock of sheepe, a river, whose parts it may be may increase or diminish, and be in continuall motion and altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, some going away, and others comming in place, and yet continue one and the same singular, heape, flock, river, to which both the singular number, and demonstratiue particle are joyned.</p>
         <p>Divinitie sayth, that Antichrist is not onely opposed to Christ the Head, who is one, but to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, the bodie, the members, who are a succession of kings &amp; priests annointed, or a royall priesthood. <hi>1</hi> Pet.<hi>2, 9.</hi> And for the use of a demonstratiue particle, or the singular number or name they referr us to <hi>1</hi> Pet. <hi>2, 17.</hi> Dan. <hi>2, 38.</hi> Thou, O King, art this head of gould. Thou &amp; thy predecessors, thou and thy successors; though per excellentiam, thou aboue all before or after. So <hi>1</hi> Pet. <hi>5, 8. ho Antidicos,</hi> not one adversarie or one divell onely, but all. Rev. <hi>13, 2.</hi> and <hi>2</hi> Thes. <hi>2, 7.</hi> with divers other places.</p>
         <p>Thus neither Grammer, Philosophie, nor Divinitie will teach me, what these new Roman Pithagorians wou'd force me to beleeue. But ipse dixit is sufficient in the schole of Antichrist, to silence not onely his schollers, but Grammer rules, &amp; the Logicall rules of reason, &amp; the Scripture, yea Christ himself. But he that will not heare Christ, Christ will not heare him, though he crie Lord, Lord never so loud.</p>
      </note> as did not admitte and containe singulars) <hi>a Iewe,</hi> and perhaps, of the <hi>Tribe of Dan,</hi> the sonne of a <hi>Divell,</hi> or of <hi>an Incubus,</hi> of <hi>a virgin</hi> or of <hi>a Whore,</hi> or of some bodie: that he shall raigne <hi>three yeares and an halfe,</hi> sitte in the <hi>Temple of God in Ierusalem,</hi> kill <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> with much other strange legiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie stuffe, concerning Antichrist, his <hi>person, office, Raigne, warre,</hi> and <hi>overthrow.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>And least men should examine, and so finde their falsehood, they obtrude these opinions aforehand upon the Church, to be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as Articles of Fayth, by all their members, viz. <hi>That the Church is for the Head, or principall part, Romish, and so particular: for the bodie, Catholique.</hi> That <hi>the Pope is the Head of the Church, and so as Head of the Church, Judge of the Scripture: and the onely true expounder of it: having that infallible and universall spirit, which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects the whole in all truth. That his seate is the Rock immoueable, to which in all stormes the shipwrackt soule should resort for safeguard. That Salvation is no where else to be found. And that his Decrees are to be believed, and obeyed, not to be questioned, or examined in the least.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Loe, thus he hath made sure not to be <hi>discovered,</hi> except, out of good nature, he will <hi>confesse himselfe to be the thiefe,</hi> and restore the stollen goods to the right owner. But as the <hi>acknowledgement</hi> of error, and of injurie, is not to be expected from him or his, who loue the world, the pompe, glorie, and power thereof, a little too well, to resigne their <hi>Soveraigntie:</hi> So in all these cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, whilst he thinkes cunningly to <hi>hide himselfe,</hi> he <hi>bewrayes</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe the more to be ANTICHRIST unto such as haue spirituall eyes, illuminated by grace from aboue, to discerne trueth from falsehood.</p>
   <p>Thus you see their <hi>Egiptian wisedome,</hi> and what paines they take with those Magicall Iuglers, <hi>Iannes</hi> and <hi>Iambres,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3, 8.</note> to conceale them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, and how much it concerns them so to doe.</p>
   <p>On the other side, it concernes us, with <hi>Moses</hi> to relye upon the Hebrew simplicitie and sinceritie for our salvation, <hi>but withall to be learned in all the Egiptian wisedome,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 7, 22.</note> the better to discover An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist his clowdie walking, that so diverse Controversies may be at an end. For were he fully discovered, then all that belieue in Christ, and loue him, and desire his glorious comming, would hate this Monster, who is like <hi>Iudas</hi> amongst the twelue a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit Apostle, <hi>carrying the bagge, an Hypocrite,</hi> playing the parte of a <hi>Vicar,</hi> a <hi>Deputie,</hi> a <hi>Substitute</hi>; but from the <hi>stage</hi> appearing a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, ragged, beggerly vacabond. And doubtlesse, his <hi>person</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus discovered, his <hi>lawes</hi> and <hi>decrees</hi> would be rejected, and Kings, Princes and people, would cast the <hi>Egiptian yoake</hi> from
<pb facs="4"/>
their overgalled neckes: Yea such as thinke, they doe now <hi>God good service,</hi> in murthering the poore Lambs of Christ in all places for him, would leaue him, <hi>come out of his Babylonish profession,</hi> and not so much as trade or trucke with him in the least exchange of those <hi>doubtfull commodities,</hi> or touch <hi>any of those garments spotted with the flesh.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>It cannot be denyed, but <hi>Iesabell</hi> was once <hi>young,</hi> and <hi>Chast</hi> and <hi>faire:</hi> But this proues not, that she is so now. It cannot now be denyed, but that she is <hi>full of wrinckles,</hi> and a <hi>royall whore</hi>; the <hi>Mother of fornication</hi>;<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rev.</hi> 2, 20.</note> fitte for all commers; and withall <hi>painted,</hi> to uphold her rotten reputation. And we doubt not, but God will stirre up some <hi>Iehu</hi> (zealous perhaps for his owne interest, if not for Gods) to cause her owne <hi>Eunuchs,</hi> those Fryars, Monks, and other Votaries,<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 9, 30</note> to throw her out of the windowe, that he may treade her under his horses feete. And doubtlesse, as this shall in time come to passe by the <hi>powerfull preaching of the word,</hi> which shall <hi>wast him by degrees</hi>;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 2.</note> so, as an effect of the word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, first, <hi>the usurped authoritie of the Papacie, and Roman Cleargie over Kings and Princes,</hi> shall be broken, and <hi>reformation</hi> shall begin, where <hi>deformation</hi> came first into the Church. So that Antichrist shall say, as Hanniball once did: <hi>Eadem arte qua prius cepimus, Tarentum amisimus.</hi> And this is with Iehu to treade Iesabel under foote.</p>
   <p>Bellarmine confesseth, that Constantine the Greate gaue the Pallace of Laterane,<note place="margin">Bellarm. li. <hi>2,</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi> de Rom. Pontif.</note>
      <hi>&amp; multa alia temporalia,</hi> to the Pope, <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem tamen spiritualem neque dedit ullam, neque dare potuit.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>So the spirituall dition, made way for the temporall donation, and then was <hi>poyson powred into the Church,</hi> when the <hi>bountie</hi> of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces sought to satisfie the <hi>ambition</hi> of Priests. The Priests then grew <hi>downwards</hi> towards the earth, and Princes then began to climbe <hi>upwards,</hi> towards heauen: And the coveteous Clergie finding the <hi>fayth of fewe</hi> (for the faythfull are but fewe, a verie little flock, and oftentimes not very rich in wooll) <hi>not to be so fruitfull as the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition of many,</hi> they nourished that profitable and liberall hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour by their uttermost arte, and from hence got S. Peter a rich <hi>patrimonie</hi> being dead, who when he lived, had scarse a house, wherein to hide his head. This temporall <hi>patrimonie</hi> graced with
<pb facs="4"/>
so holy a patronage, as the reverenced name of S. Peter, did spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily and mightily increase in all places, especially where <hi>superstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> was interteyned in the name and stead of <hi>true Religion,</hi> and where Clergie men knew how cunningly to raise questions and quarrels under hand, and then to intrude themselues as equall arbitrators, and impartiall umpires; but ever to manage and determine all for the advantage of the <hi>Catholike cause,</hi> as they called it, and for the ruine of particulars: as it is reported of that Lawyer, who decided the difference betwixte the lame man and the blinde, concerning their oyster, that each of them should haue a shell, and he the meat. Thus dealing for the Church by <hi>pretence</hi> (themselues being mostly single and unmarried, and so unsuspected to trade for the world, and posteritie) they had oportunitie to inrich themselues, and their <hi>particular fraternities,</hi> and to performe such actes with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, because they pretended <hi>S. Peter,</hi> and the <hi>Church,</hi> not themselues, as would haue been counted cousenage, treacherie, exaction, oppression, injustice, and perhaps forgerie and Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berie, if perpetrated by any other persons, or to any other ends. But the generall opinion of their <hi>Cause</hi> and <hi>Persons</hi> (supposed and stiled <hi>sacred</hi>) made all passe currant without question or controule. Thus in a short time, where they were lately glad to be <hi>graced by Kings</hi>; Kings were now glad to be <hi>graced by them:</hi> And where Kings had <hi>persecuted</hi> their predecessors for <hi>the trueth,</hi> they now <hi>persecuted</hi> Kings for <hi>falsehood</hi>; and chalenged the <hi>investiture</hi> of such Princes by right, upon whom their predecessors, out of the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of their pietie, and the superstitious desire to be inaugurated by so blessed an omen, had been sometimes formerly invited or admitted, to lay their holy hands. Now therefore they began to cutte out large cantles of the earth for their owne share, and made so manie <hi>sanctuaries,</hi> and <hi>Citties of refuge,</hi> that they incouraged ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors, who ought to haue represt them, and gotte well by the bargaine too. For they so mightily grew by this meanes, that <hi>the world,</hi> and the <hi>wealth of it</hi> was found with <hi>Priests</hi>; and <hi>pietie</hi> was onely found with the <hi>poore:</hi> the <hi>secular</hi> was onely <hi>regular</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Christ, and the <hi>Regular</hi> was master of misrule in all <hi>secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar affaires: Marchandize, forraigne negotiations,</hi> and the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment civill and ecclesiasticall,</hi> first, by the civill and imperiall lawes,
<pb facs="5"/>
after by the Cannon Law, a Law of their owne) was wholly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derated, and managed by them: Kings were made their wardes, and deposed for Hereticks, as soone as they once thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues of age to rule themselues and their people aright, without their helpe: Yea Mars himselfe was interteyned into their service, and the <hi>Crosse of tribulation, fayth</hi> and <hi>patience,</hi> which was at first but a staffe in the hand of the Cleargie, to support them in their constant sufferings, was now <hi>perverted</hi> in the use, and <hi>turned up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,</hi> in prosperitie and spirituall pride, and so became <hi>a sword</hi> in everie Cleargie mans hand, to invade and disturbe the peace of Christendome: and <hi>Confession</hi> served, as a secret racke or torture of Conscience, a kinde of holy inquisition, to finde out that <hi>sweete sinne,</hi> and to <hi>pardon it,</hi> which might be most <hi>profitable</hi> to the Church, as having command over the purse of the partie peccant. Thus it grew in time to be rightly called the <hi>Sacrament of pennance</hi> indeede: for if it had not <hi>contrition</hi> at the first, yet it ever ended in <hi>repentance,</hi> though ever a little too late, and therefore to small purpose for the <hi>pennilesse penitent.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The Cleargie having by these artes and infinite others (as Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie is full of invention, for he that can once make his Creator can make all other things) ingrost almost all into their owne hands, they made divisions of <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> and cutte them out into <hi>Bishop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks,</hi> as all Countries, especially Germanie can well witnesse. Where the Emperor was shackled with <hi>Ecclesiasticall Officers</hi> of the Sea of Rome, as with <hi>fetters of gold</hi>; till the necessitie of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie, about the rising up of Luther, forced the Pope, to permit the house of Austria to grow a little too great, to the lessening of Antichrists <hi>immediate authoritie.</hi> In so much, as now the Papacie is made a servant to the House of Austria, under a <hi>Catholike title:</hi> as the Papacie before made both that <hi>House,</hi> and <hi>all others</hi> servants, to increase and support the excessiue greatnesse of that Sea, under the like <hi>Catholike title and pretence.</hi> But this was then, and is now a violent motion, and therefore not perpetuall: then permitted and practised, to prevent the losse of all, which was justly feared upon probable grounds; and now to hold what that Sea still pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sesseth, but feareth to loose: and to regaine (if it be possible) what she hath lost alreadie. Which if ever she could regaine by
<pb facs="5"/>
this meanes, she could then be content to burne the <hi>rodde of her wrath,</hi> or to <hi>weare it out</hi> in her worke, with whipping others. In the meane time she is content to make the <hi>Spanish kingdome the Catholique sword:</hi> so that the <hi>Roman Church</hi> may still be the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique scabberd</hi> to that sword, and <hi>draw</hi> it, or <hi>sheath</hi> it at the Popes pleasure. But I beleeue, that as by <hi>these arts</hi> that Antichristian Sea hath ascended up to that superlatiue height, wherein it now sitts; so it shall loose all, by the <hi>same</hi> or <hi>the like meanes.</hi> For whensoever the world shall be so happie, as to haue an <hi>understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Emperour,</hi> who <hi>knowes</hi> his owne, and is <hi>able</hi> to discover, and recover <hi>Antichristian</hi> usurpations, that such a man, taking Henry the VIII. of England for a patterne, shall and may easily doe that in Germanie, and so consequently in other places, which that <hi>Resolute King,</hi> by the <hi>advice</hi> of the Lord Cromwell, and the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample</hi> of Cardinall Wolsey, did in his owne dominions. viz.</p>
   <p>That King intending to <hi>dissolue all Monasteries,</hi> made a division of part to the Nobles and Commons, from whence it first came, and so mette no opposition; The <hi>patterne</hi> was the Popes owne, who made Church-men Princes, and changed the title and name of those Lands, which were often by them acquired, and posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by ill arts, as if he could haue changed the nature thereof, and made them, what he called them <hi>spirituall.</hi> The King therefore did but <hi>reduce</hi> things backe to their right and former order. Here onely was the error of that worke; that the King did not restore the <hi>Tenths</hi> to the constant maintenance of the ministerie; which portion, whether it now belong to the Church or no, <hi>jure divino,</hi> I intend not to dispute <hi>pro</hi> or <hi>con:</hi> But I dare say, <hi>Gods owne order</hi> hath manifested it to be both <hi>competent</hi> and <hi>convenient</hi> for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, beyond all old exceptions or new inventions, and so proues it to agree with the law of nature, if not to flow immediately from thence, deserving therefore to liue after the honourable buriall of the <hi>ceremoniall Law,</hi> as it breathed long before it.</p>
   <p>Had these things been better ordered, and some Bishopricks <hi>broken into lesser pieces,</hi> so that they might haue been sitte for <hi>honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble burthens,</hi> but not too greate for the <hi>portage of one person,</hi> who laden with too much temporall honour and revenue, as men o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vergrowne with flesh and fatte, become unwealdie and dishonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb facs="6"/>
burthens themselues to the Church; then the undertaking had been absolute. For whether it be fitt, that <hi>one who will not preach the Gospell,</hi> should haue power to silence such <hi>as would</hi>; that <hi>one</hi> should haue power to silence a <hi>whole Diocesse</hi> of learned mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, and <hi>a whole Diocesse</hi> of these, should not haue power to open the mouth of <hi>one</hi>? That <hi>one</hi> should haue double honour for the <hi>single worke</hi>; Nay for his <hi>wilfull idlenes,</hi> and <hi>obstinate</hi> hindering the conscionable worke of others: and <hi>others</hi> no honour, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zumelie, and scorne for doing the double worke diligently? That <hi>one</hi> should haue the provender belonging to manie labouring oxen for lying in the manger, and hindering the poore asses from meate: whilest <hi>divers</hi> oxen that <hi>would tread out the corne,</hi> want come to eate, or corne to treade out, or are muzzeled whilest they treade? That <hi>one</hi> should rule a place manie miles from his person, as if he had both an <hi>infallible,</hi> and <hi>infinite</hi> spirit: and <hi>manie</hi> should not be able to rule a pettie parish, or to catechise a household without helpe? whether this thing be according to the patterne of the Apostolicall Hierarchie, are problemes, which some thinke fitt to be published amongst those of <hi>Antichrist.</hi> because it may be doubted, that he who would doe <hi>thus,</hi> would not perhaps startle at a <hi>Cardinals cappe,</hi> or the <hi>triple Crowne,</hi> it they were profered, or could be compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed easily: and therefore such a man is no fitte instrument to be used against Antichrist, in the pulling downe of Babylon, or to sit for Christ and rule,<note place="margin">Obiect.</note> upon the top of Sion. <hi>Object.</hi> But kinges and Princes governe by substitutes farre off. <hi>Answ.</hi> True: <hi>But it shall not be so amongst you.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ans. Mat, <hi>20, 26.</hi>
      </note> Matth. 20, 25, 26. Take these words of Christ as a <hi>Precept</hi> to shewe Bishops what they should doe; or as a <hi>prophesie,</hi> to shew all men the estate of the true Church what it shall be, it is all one. And doubtlesse such <hi>Princes</hi> as shall hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>reforme,</hi> will learne to mend what is amisse, by the sight of other mens errors: and so whensoever God shall blesse Germanie with an able and religious Emperour, and shall put it in his heart to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the Church, it is but changing those greate <hi>Bishopricks</hi> of <hi>Mentz, Tryers, Collen, Munster,</hi> and the rest into <hi>absolute Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipallities,</hi> and making them <hi>Hereditarie,</hi> where now they are <hi>Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue,</hi> and the worke is at an end; they will joyne to uphold their <hi>owne interestes,</hi> and soone exclude the Papacie, and mince the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacie
<pb facs="6"/>
somewhat finer.</p>
   <p>A speedie and certaine preparation for this, is the <hi>discoverie of Antichrist</hi>: and it is the duetie of all men therefore that <hi>can,</hi> to doe their best, according to their talents, in this subject; and amongst others, this <hi>learned Author</hi> hath done much, and deserues much in this respect of the Church. The Course he takes by Problemes to handle this controversie, is not as if he doubted, or any other man neede to doubt of the trueth; but as it should seeme, being <hi>no profest Churchman,</hi> he modestly disputes the point, as a man that would learne himselfe and others, by asking questions wisely; and withall inquiring, whether it can be imagined, that any man can be more like Antichrist then the Pope is; he concludes <hi>nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely,</hi> that <hi>none can</hi>; and plainely layes downe in everie Probleme the obstinate absurdities of such, as looke for Antichrist, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue he <hi>shall come,</hi> yet cannot now see him to <hi>be come</hi>; because either he stands too neare them, as a beame in their eyes, and they are <hi>parte of him; bone of his bone, and flesh of his flesh</hi>; or, they expect him, when he comes, to be so qualified for publique observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the Church of Rome hath cunningly, and poetically de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed him: <hi>But such an Antichrist they shall never see</hi>; for the church of Rome did so paint him in policie; not for the disclosing, but for the concealing, and clowding of his proper and personall appearance, and diverting the eyes of all men from beholding the right object. For my parte, meeting with this Booke in a manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>script, and seeing the profit it may bring to all, I could doe no lesse, then be <hi>a midwife</hi> for the <hi>edition</hi> of this, since I am not able to be <hi>parent,</hi> for <hi>procreation of the like.</hi> And I haue taken the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes upon me, to dedicate it to no lesse persons, then to the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Potentates</hi> of the Earth, for it concernes them all especially, aboue and more then others, to reade, and to understand this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversie, least they should be made drunke, or kept drunke; with the dregges of that <hi>abhominable cuppe of Inchantments,</hi> wherewith diverse of their forefathers haue been <hi>intoxicated,</hi> and <hi>slept to death</hi>; and least they should under the <hi>appearance of Christianitse,</hi> counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and support Antichristianisme, and so thinking to doe Christ good service, <hi>persecute his poore members ignorantly.</hi> Besides many of them haue suffred much from the hand of Antichrist, and
<pb facs="7"/>
his members. The <hi>Kings of France</hi> haue beene butchered by their instruments, and the kingdome put in Combustion, by their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiaries of the Roman Catholique league or partie. Our <hi>Queenes Father Henrie IIII. of renowmed memorie,</hi> must not be forgotten: his blood is yet too fresh upon their fingers, to be hidden from her Majesties eyes; except they force her weake sexe (as they haue done manie of the masculine gender) to winke; by threatning to dippe their fingers, as deepe in her bloud, (which the Lord forefend) if she cast an eye towards her Fathers Funerall, or so much as inquire whether or no, <hi>he dyed by age,</hi> or by some injurious and <hi>traiterous hand. Our Kings</hi> haue beene, and are still, <hi>excommunicated, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, exposed to slaughter,</hi> and <hi>deposition</hi> by them. The <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queene of Bohemia,</hi> haue beene pursued from place to place; and <hi>all Christendome</hi> imbroyled with bloodie warres for the upholding of Papall usurpation, against <hi>regall Iurisdiction. Other Princes</hi> haue formerly felt, and may <hi>hereafter</hi> feele the strength of his <hi>Imperiall</hi> and <hi>Catholique Armes</hi>; and therefore it concernes these also, to knowe the <hi>man of sinne,</hi> for their owne <hi>comfort,</hi> that they may the better beare their Crosses, considering from <hi>what head,</hi> and <hi>hand</hi> they come; and that they may with more courage and assurance, <hi>looke up towards deliverance,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Luke</hi> 21, 28.</note> as Christ hath willed them, who at the length will be too hard for Antichrist, and giue a happie yssue to all their afflictions.</p>
   <p>And as it concerns Princes especially, so it concerns others also, as much as their salvation may concerne them, to know <hi>Christ</hi> their Saviour, and Antichrist the chiefe enimie of their Saviour, and of their Salvation, from each other; and therefore I haue dedicated it to all Christians. But if any wonder, why in the Title of the Dedication, I use these words: <hi>To all Christians Reformed and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish,</hi> as if I contradicted my selfe, in calling the <hi>Romish professors Christians,</hi> which in other places I terme <hi>Antichristians</hi>: I answer that the <hi>Pope</hi> himselfe could not be <hi>the Antichrist,</hi> except he were a <hi>Christian,</hi> and tooke upon him also to be the <hi>chiefe Christian,</hi> in externall profession. A man may in diverse respects be a <hi>Christian,</hi> and an <hi>Antichristian</hi> at once. The Pope is baptized, professeth the fayth in generall termes, as Peter did; and thus he is <hi>a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> and one of <hi>S. Peters successors,</hi> as all other Bishops are; but
<pb facs="7"/>
as he chalengeth to be <hi>head of the Church, universall Bishop,</hi> of an <hi>infallible spirit, Iudge of the Scripture,</hi> &amp;c, he is <hi>Antichrist,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Rev. <hi>18.</hi> Rome, as head of the church is Babylon, &amp; such as so dwell in it, mystically by adhering to it, are in Babylō whether they be in Rome or no, &amp; such as renounce this Babylonish do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie &amp; suprela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, holding the true head, which is Christ Iesus alone, those are with out Babylon, though they dwel in Rome▪</note>
      <hi>for Christ▪ in shew,</hi> but <hi>against him in trueth.</hi> So those of the church of Rome, are Christians in outward profession, but as they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to the Pope, as to <hi>the Ʋicar of Christ,</hi> and <hi>head of the Church,</hi> they are <hi>Antichristians:</hi> and such of them as belong to Gods electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are called out of Babylon by the holy spirit, and may <hi>come out</hi> from thence, by renouncing the Babylonish doctrine of the Church of Rome, though for their <hi>persons and dwellings</hi> they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the same place and cittie still. And that these Romish Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians may be <hi>informed,</hi> and all other <hi>Reformed</hi> Christians <hi>established in the trueth,</hi> is the end which the Author proposed to himselfe in the collection and composition, and I in the publication of this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise.</p>
   <p>All that I feare is, that both this worke, and my owne indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour shall meete the greatest discouragements from some of those, that should protect and countenance us: who eyther from <hi>error of judgment,</hi> deny the Pope to be Antichrist, and yet <hi>separate from him</hi> (at which I wonder) or else out of <hi>humane wisedome and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi> seeme still to be in doubt, and will not be resolved, as fearing a diminution of their worldly greatnesse and glorie, if this truth should be generally acknowledged. Because they suppose <hi>much</hi> of their <hi>authoritie</hi> would be found to be built upon the <hi>sandie foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Antichristian usurpations.</hi> But shall we loose heauen for earth? or looke so low, as to bring <hi>temporall</hi> respects into the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance with <hi>eternall?</hi> Can there be no provision for upholding the <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>countenance</hi> of the Clergie, from <hi>common contempt,</hi> and for the <hi>incouraging</hi> and <hi>rewarding</hi> of learning, but what Antichrist invents to uphold himselfe withall? Then let me rather be still <hi>poore</hi> and <hi>despised</hi> with Christ, and accounted <hi>ignorant</hi> with his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, then <hi>rich</hi> and <hi>respected</hi> &amp; <hi>learned</hi> with those of Rome: <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>simplicitie</hi> are the chiefe ornaments of Church-men, and should be inseparable. Their <hi>serpentine wisedome</hi> should not be used for this world: for that naturall subtiltie, which hath no mixture of doue-like simplicitie infused by grace, Christ did not teach to his Apostles: but Adam and Evah learned it of the <hi>old serpent,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving therewith lost Paradise, left it then, with the wide world to
<pb facs="8"/>
boote, as a Legacie for all their posteritie. I would faine therefore finde that <hi>simple Christian Policie,</hi> which lookes <hi>directly forward, to the price of the high calling,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Phi.</hi> 3, 13, 14</note> and contents it selfe with that respect, which <hi>followes the worke,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 2, 29.</note>
      <hi>whose praise is of God and not of men.</hi> If the worldes wages comes with it, I shall take it as the faithfull performance of his gracious promise, who hath wild us, <hi>first to seeke the kingdome of God;</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.32.</note>
      <hi>and his righteousnes, and all needfull things for this life, shall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded unto us.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This is my resolution, and I am resolved besides, that he, who upon those earthly respects, before mentioned, or any the like humane grounds, and motiues, opposeth this booke, or the like, doeth therein sufficiently declare himselfe to be <hi>Antichristian,</hi> and shall neede no further eviction or confutation, then the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of his owne actions. <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> therefore must cast an eye upon such, and they shall soone see all their Councell is to uphold their owne <hi>earthly commaunds,</hi> for personall respects: <hi>a watchword sufficient for him that is wise, to beware of such, for they are wolues in sheeps cloathing.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And now to conclude, how much are we to magnifie the Lord for our <hi>King, Nobles, Cleargie,</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> mette together lately in the high Court of Parliament, and there so well according, for matter of Religion, that the <hi>Subiect</hi> no sooner shewed his grievance with complaint, but the <hi>Soveraigne</hi> applied the remedie with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion. Such a <hi>Head</hi> shewes it selfe sensible of the suffering of the <hi>feete:</hi> and such <hi>members</hi> will never forget (as they haue protested) thankfulnesse to <hi>such a Head.</hi> Thus they are happie <hi>in knowing each other</hi>; So that the king having any attempt against Antichrist, neede not doubt the bodie: And the people fearing the incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Antichrist, neede not doubt to acquaint the Head with their feares. How happie a thing is it to heare that ecclesiasticall corruptions had no backs in eyther house, nor no sonne of Belial there to pleade for Baal. It is the <hi>bellie,</hi> and not the <hi>conscience,</hi> that speakes in such cases;<note place="margin">Whether they be greater friēds to schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for a few covetous and ambitious persons; or they that provide for the generall number of carefull and con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>cionable persons, blinde men may see and judge: what portion had Fulke, Fox, Whitaker, Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds, Perkins, with many others in the Church. Or were not these men learned? Or who was more learned, painfull, and profitable to the Church of Christ, then these? He that thinkes me an enimie to the Bishops for this, is deceived. Nay rather I wish, that where there is but one Bishop now, there were twentie, so farre am I from schisme, or from being Antiepiscopall.</note> and howsoever of old, such <hi>penny-wise Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> haue been applauded, as the onely pillars of the Church, and friends (forsooth) to schollers: yet now the world knowes better,
<pb facs="8"/>
that, as a man cannot fill his mouth, and speake, both at one time; so they who are most greedie and unsatiable in seeking after <hi>offices,</hi> haue least leasure and desire to performe the <hi>Dueties</hi> of them. And that both the Parliament that <hi>desired,</hi> and his Majestie who <hi>graunted,</hi> and the Cleargie who never <hi>opposed</hi> the reimployment of silenced Ministers, (who were not turbulent) did well understand. For these men will be <hi>contented</hi> with litle, and yet withall will labour to giue much <hi>contentment</hi> in the workes of their vocation: so that if they may haue free and peaceable passage, we shall see <hi>Superstition</hi> and <hi>Idolatrie</hi> haue a greater blowe in a few yeares by their labours, then in manie yeares before by the unfruitfull &amp; unprofitable warre stird up against them, as betwixt Fathers and their children, which gaue way to the contrarie humour to increase. And were some of these men well <hi>provided for,</hi> and <hi>protected in Ireland,</hi> I doubt not to say, we should soone see the happie effect thereof, and that an <hi>Armie of Priests</hi> would do more perhaps, then an armie of secular souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; and so settle that kingdome in obedience to <hi>Christ,</hi> that we should not fear any invasion or inward motion by <hi>Antichrist,</hi> or his instruments in those parts. He that doubts this may looke into <hi>Scotland,</hi> a place sixt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e yeares since, as obstinately averse from the fayth, as Ireland is now; where in a few yeares Poperie was wholly rooted up, and scarce a man to be found, that would professe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to be a Papist; till these late dayes, when the <hi>unhappie division betwixt the Cleargie</hi> gaue them oportunitie and incouragement to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease and multiplie. It is our charge to conquer the Irish <hi>soules</hi> to Christ, as well as the <hi>Irish lands</hi> and <hi>bodies</hi> to our selues; and I am perswaded, God hath not prospered our worke for <hi>our parte,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we haue had no greater care to compasse <hi>his parte:</hi> If they were <hi>Christs,</hi> they would be <hi>ours</hi> too, in spite of Rome and Spaine: but being <hi>Antichrists</hi> in affection, their able bodies are imployed as instruments against us in all places, and <hi>their Countrie</hi> used now by <hi>Spaine,</hi> as <hi>Scotland</hi> of old by <hi>France,</hi> to <hi>divert</hi> and <hi>distract</hi> our warlike attempts, and to hold us busied at home. Their <hi>conversion</hi> would haue beene the <hi>glorie</hi> of our church government, shewing
<pb facs="9"/>
that our Cleargie did not seeke themselues, but Christ; as now it is our <hi>shame,</hi> that whilest the Romish Cleargie haue conquered ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Countries for Antichrist, in the East and West Indies, we should neglect a <hi>neighbour countrie, long in our possession,</hi> suffering them still to liue in spirituall captivitie, under the hands of <hi>ignorance, Idolatrie, darknesse,</hi> and <hi>death.</hi> But now we haue better hope, seeing the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilement of the Fathers to their brethren, and doubt not, but that will be effected there, which hath been performed in England and Scotland heretofore, by the <hi>conscionable, plaine, painfull,</hi> and <hi>powerfull</hi> preaching of the Gospell; whilest men are not distracted, nor their hearts alienated from each other, by domestick contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versies. For these Church quarrels about Ceremonies, besides the <hi>distraction,</hi> do by the <hi>scandall</hi> hinder the progresse of Religion, causing the enemie to insult in their <hi>unitie,</hi> against our <hi>truth,</hi> because they see us divided, and in our divisions pursuing each other more bitterly, for those things, which we professe to be <hi>circumstanciall and indifferent</hi>; then we doe them in <hi>fundamentall</hi> controversies: And so they say truely, we shew little charitie, and therefore can haue no true fayth.</p>
   <p>The Lord therefore joyne the hearts of our King, Peeres, Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, and Commons <hi>in one,</hi> to finish this good worke which they haue begun, to the overthrow of Antichrist: and blesse this worke to his full discoverie; that Kings, Princes, Priests and People, may learne to leaue him. And so craving pardon for that <hi>capitall crime</hi> of <hi>plaine-speaking,</hi> which I haue herein used, I ende with the Authors owne Epistle, or Preface to the Reader.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Quod à suis olim Lectoribus, petiit, pater doctissimus, id te oratum volo (pie Lector) ut sicubi me errasse animadvertes, me corrigas: siteipsum, mecum redeas; ubi pariter cerius es, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gas mecum; ubi pariter haesitas, ores mecum; ut sic Christianae unitatis &amp; pietatis leges inviolatas teneamus.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>