<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the
Reader.</title>
           <author>Hutchins, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1587</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116114_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20591</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6992</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116114</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the
Reader.</title>
                 <author>Hutchins, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Straunge newes out of Calabria : prognosticated in the yere 1586, vpon the yere 87. and what shall happen in the said yere: Praying the Lord to be merciful vnto vs</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Robinson, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Perrin (Perin), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1587</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface to the
Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE READER, WE
may see with deepe considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
the mercifull woorke of the
Lorde from tyme to tyme, shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
vnto vs many strange Signes
and tokens, forewarning vs vnto
repētāce: But such is the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō
and hardnes of this our age,
that we cōtemne and neclect all
tokens in the Heauens, by respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting
our owne securitie for the tyme present, and yet if
any man would recken the course of this life past, hee
shoulde see in himselfe greate cause to tremble at these
things: And also if wee doe consider what great route of
euils doth beset vs, and how many hath bene destroyed,
or what hurtes hath bene by Lightnings, Earthquakes,
Ground-openings, Fluddes, Tempestes of the Sea, great
Windes, Infections, Ayre, Warres, Mortalities, Plagues,
straunge disseases and such like, which things, Commets
doth commonly Prognosticate to ensue. I suppose that
the remembraunce of such daungers, should make vs not
to be altogether careles of these tokens, threatning vnto
vs calamities for our vnthankefulnes, and therfore who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer
doth make light accoumpt of Earthquakes and
gleaming Starres: and is not moued with the sight there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
with the feare of Gods heauy displeasure: the same
people doe also as lightly and as little regard their owne
consciences and amendment of life. And now let vs beare
in mynde the fourth Starre, that was seene in <hi>Calabria,</hi>
which signifieth great alteration this yeere. 1587. and
<pb facs="2"/>
that the world will not long indure, God make vs all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
against the day of the Lorde. This Starre Maister Iohn
Doleta, a learned Astronomer doth write, and with hym
also doe agree, in wryting all the learned men in <hi>Grecia,
Alexandria, Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> That is to say, in the yere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresayd,
the Sunne shalbe couered with a <hi>Dragon,</hi> in the
Morning from fiue a Clocke vntill nine, and will shewe
forth as fire, and in this yere is thought to be great Fluds,
Windes; Tempestes and Earthquakes. I pray God defend
and keepe vs from the same, and giue vs grace to repent,
and beare in mynde the fearfull signes and tokens. For as
before the destruction of the first World, like signes and
tokens appeared, &amp; yet they would not turne from their
wickednesse, and so were drowned in the Flood. And as
before the destructions of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorra,</hi> appeared
like wonders, but they would not call to God for mercy,
and so were cōsumed with Fire and Brimstone. And that
goodly Citie <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> for their abhomination was made
desolate, and not one stone left vppon an other. Yet
now let all these signes and tokens cause speedie repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce,
and amendment of life, and then no doubt the
wrath of God, which is now kindled against thee, will be
turned to his wonted mercie: and thē possesse that place
of felicitie, which is prepared for all those that feare and
tremble at the threatning of our GOD: to which
place of perfect rest, I beseech God to graunt
his Spirit of liuely repentaunce, in the
harts of all true beleeuers. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>