<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Worship∣ful Sir Nathanael Brent Knight, Doctor of the Civill Law, Vicar ge∣nerall in causes spirituall for the Pro∣vince of Canterbury, Commissary for the Diocesse of the same, and Warden of Merton Colledge in Oxford: And to the Right vertuous and honoured Lady, the Lady Martha Brent his wife:</title>
           <author>Cobbes, Edmund</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116664_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19037</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5454</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116664</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Worship∣ful Sir Nathanael Brent Knight, Doctor of the Civill Law, Vicar ge∣nerall in causes spirituall for the Pro∣vince of Canterbury, Commissary for the Diocesse of the same, and Warden of Merton Colledge in Oxford: And to the Right vertuous and honoured Lady, the Lady Martha Brent his wife:</title>
                 <author>Cobbes, Edmund</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The parable of the vncleane spirit : pithily opened, and plainly applied; wherein is shewed Sathans possession, his dispossession, and repossession. A worke needfull for these secure times, in which the most neglect the meanes oftheir salvation. Preached, and now published, by Edmund Cobbes minister of the Word of God</title>
                 <author>Cobbes, Edmund</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cotes, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bellamy, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>38, 175, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sir <hi>Nathanael Brent</hi> Knight, Doctor of the Civill Law, Vicar ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall in causes spirituall for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Commissary for the Diocesse of the same, and Warden of <hi>Merton</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxford:</hi> And to the Right vertuous and honoured Lady, the Lady <hi>Martha Brent</hi> his wife:</head>
   <head type="sub">The best blessings of this life, and eternall blessednesse in the world to come.</head>
   <p>RIght Worshipfull, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Gods word can countenance it selfe, and needes no shelter from the arme of flesh: yet experience shewes, that not
<pb facs="3"/> onely the writings of the most, but even some of those sacred bookes which were breathed from heaven, have beene dedicated to renowned Saints on earth. If that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Evangelist, dedicated his<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uke 1: 3:</note> Gospell, and Treatise of the holy Acts of the Apostles un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<note place="margin">Acts 1: 1:</note> that most excellent <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus:</hi> And that eminent pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of the Church, directed<note place="margin">2 Iohn 1: 1:</note> that heavenly Epistle to that elect Lady whom he loved in the truth: In imitation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I have made bold to devote this poore mite (in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of that rich treasure) unto
<pb facs="3"/> your Worships, whose ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and pieties have also dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified you for the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and respect which you beare to religion and learning. The subject of my discourse is divine, answerable to your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections; not unbefitting your place, and most necessary, and so not unworthy your studies. Here I have discovered Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans inveterate malice against the godly, and for their sakes have prescribed such spirituall Antidots as Christ the Saints comforter hath confected. In which if I have passed the bounds of modestie, I humbly
<pb facs="4"/> crave pardon for the same, relying upon the innate goodnesse that rests in your nature, I have presumed to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer unto your acceptations a taste of such fruits as my bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren orchard could afford; my meaning hereby is not to crave any thankes or praise where none is deserved, but (that so farre as I may) I might make evident to others for imitation, those excellent ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues which God hath made so eminent in you. And also ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my poore abilitie, leave to the world a testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall of that duty and respect
<pb facs="4"/> which I beare unto either of your Worships, for those ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny favours you have extended towards me, which I have no other way to requite, saving my prayers; which shall be, that you may goe forward in your pious courses to serve God, your King, and Country; that you may stand couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously for religion before men, and then it will stand for you before God. Thus shall you gaine glory from your God, favour from your King, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase peace to your consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and shame them that say Law and piety cannot stand
<pb facs="5"/> together, or that greatnesse is any hinderance to goodnes; then shall you cause all them that feare God to love and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence you; and mee among the rest to be your servant in Christ, and remaine</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships humbly devoted and ready to be commanded, Edmund Cobbes.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>