<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116327_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16604</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3511</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116327</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A preparation to the receiving of the Sacrament, of Christs Body and Bloud : Directing weake Christians how they may worthily receiue the same. By W. Bradshavv. With a profitable treatise of the same argument, written by another</title>
                 <author>Bradshaw, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Macham, Joyce</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 108, 5 leaves, 146 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>LEt it not offend thee (good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) that in this Edition I haue varied somewhat from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. When J first published this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, I little thought it should haue beene thus often called to the Presse, which (as I suppose) is not so much for any speciall worth in it, as for the worthinesse of the other Treatise of the same Argument, vnto which it is adioyned; and which, this was a meanes to bring into the light. How-euer, seeing by this meanes it comes to passe that this of mine falleth into the hands of many, that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise (I assure my selfe) would neuer haue looked after it, and those such, as (if it had the Authors sense) it would blush to looke in the face, being so meanly set out and furnished as it is: I haue deemed it fitting this once to review the same, &amp; to send it forth in this forme thou seest; wherein some
<pb facs="5"/> defects in the former are (as I thinke) supplied, though not so many as either thou or I could wish. The old plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse thereof doth still continue, which I esteeme as no disgrace therevnto, it being by that meanes fitter for the vse of plaine and simple hearted Christians, for whose helpe and direction I first published it.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>