<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right honorable Earle, and vertuous Lord, the Lord GILBERT TAVLBVT, Earle of Shrews∣burie, and Knight of the noble order of the gartar, Grace, mercie, and peace through Christ Iesus, with increase of honor, health, and all happinesse, &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116009_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00945</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11053</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116009</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right honorable Earle, and vertuous Lord, the Lord GILBERT TAVLBVT, Earle of Shrews∣burie, and Knight of the noble order of the gartar, Grace, mercie, and peace through Christ Iesus, with increase of honor, health, and all happinesse, &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine very proper, and most profitable similies : wherein sundrie, and very many, most foule vices, and dangerous sinnes, of all sorts, are so plainly laid open, and displaied in their kindes, and so pointed at with the finger of God, in his sacred and holy scriptures, t signifie his wrath and indignation belonging vnto them, that the Christian reader, being seasoned by the spirit of grace, and hauing God before his eies, will by very fearfull, euen in loue that he beareth to God, to pollute and to defile, his hart, his mind, his mouth or hands, with any such forbidden things. And also manie very notable vertues, with their due commendations, so liuely and truely expressed, according to the holy word, that the godly reader, being of a Christian inclination, will be mightily inflamed with a loue vnto them. Collected by Anthonie Fletcher, minister of the word of God, in vnfained loue in the Lord Iesu, to do the best, and all that he can, to pleasure, and to profite all those that desire to know the Lords waies, ... This present yeere of our happines 1595</title>
                 <author>Fletcher, Anthonie</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jackson, John 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bing, Isaac</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 160, 16 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Right honorable Earle, and vertuous Lord, the Lord GILBERT TAVLBVT, Earle of Shrews<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie, and Knight of the noble order of the gartar, <hi>Grace, mercie, and peace through Christ Iesus, with increase of honor, health, and all happinesse, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing very desirous (Right honorable) in the feare of God, to do good, and to profit (among all) at the least some, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the weakest sort, whose neede of helpe in heauenly things, that they may see both vertue and vice, and learne to imbrace the one, and to auoide the other, is exceeding great, I haue ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to take a little paine to collect, and to bestowe some labour to gather togither, a little booke of Similies, to testifie my loue in Christ Iesu, to all the seruants of God: and haue presumed to dedicate the same vnto your Honor: not doubting, but that, as it may do good, and profit very manie, concerning the knowledge of God, and of his iudgements due to sinne, so your Honor will accordingly, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the same in good part, and be as glad to be a patrone, to any true seruice to God, as any man in the world, is or can be able to offer, and to performe it. Your Honors continuall and faithfull care, to do good to your natiue countrie: your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained and most hartie zeale, in fauouring true religion: your very good liking and loue, towards all that feare the Lorde: your misliking of vice, and loue to vertue: your readinesse to do good to all, both for their bodies and soules, and to hurt none: These things (I say) haue giuen me this boldnes, vnder your Honors protection, to publish and to send abroad, this my little labour, as a poore token of my good will, and loue in Christ, towards all the seruants and children of God, nothing doubting, but that for your Honors sake, it will be the better welcome, to all that feare God, and with the greater diligence read, imbraced, and imitated of all: And I my selfe the more incouraged to labour heerafter, and to thinke no pains great, whatsoeuer I am able to vndergoe and to indure, to profite
<pb facs="4"/>
others, to increase knowledge in the ignorant, and to further the saluation of all men. Againe, the remembrance of that most vertuous and godlie Ladie, Ladie <hi>Marie</hi> your Honors good and gracious sister, wife to the very worshipful and good Knight, sir <hi>George Sauill,</hi> when I was preacher in Wakefield, to me and to all that feare God, a most Christian friende, did euen seeme to warrant me (though I am vnknowen to your Honour) that you are readier to further, than I am to perform any good worke. Lastly, the readinesse to knowe God, and their obedience vnto the highest and almightie, that I found in those gracious branches, sweete virgins, and most towarde Ladies, your Honors owne daughters, when I being preacher at Clerkenwell, they were with that vertuous, gracious, and very religious gentlewoman, somtimes mother to hir Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Maides of honor, and my very worshipful friend mistresse <hi>Winfield,</hi> hath giuen me great comfort, to thrust out this little booke of mine, vnder your Honors protection, to do good to them, that you and I both do loue (as I assure my selfe) in Christ Iesu. Thus without troubling your Honor any longer, I beseech the Almightie to blesse your Honors selfe, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and godlie Ladie your wife, your Ladie daughters, and all that appertaine to your Honor, if they appertain to God. This 22. of May, 1595.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors most humble to command in<lb/>
Christ Iesu, during this temporall life,
<hi>Anthonie Fletcher preacher<lb/>
of the word of God.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>