<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL Sr NATHANIEL BRENT Knight, Vicar Generall, and the most vigilant Warden of Merton College in OXFORD, Health, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Rous, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116252_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11082</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21350</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116252</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL Sr NATHANIEL BRENT Knight, Vicar Generall, and the most vigilant Warden of Merton College in OXFORD, Health, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Rous, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Archæologiæ Atticæ libri tres. = Three bookes of the Attick antiquities : Containing the description of the citties glory, government, division of the people, and townes within the Athenian territories, their religion, superstition, sacrifices, account of their yeare, as also a full relation of their iudicatories. By Francis Rous scholler of Merton Colledge in Oxon</title>
                 <author>Rous, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lichfield, Leonard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Forrest, Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 149, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE <hi>RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL S<seg rend="sup">r</seg> NATHANIEL BRENT Knight,</hi> Vicar Generall, and the most vigilant <hi>Warden</hi> of <hi>Merton College in OXFORD,</hi> Health, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the custome of most, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose a patronage of their errours upon some eminent person. But it shall bee my ambition in this my Dedication to manifest my observancie. Others make their choice of potent men, thereby to shun the darts of envy. It shall bee my glory to be thought worthy of invidency; whose ignorance is not so great but well
<pb facs="3"/>
knowes that ever some will bite in secret; &amp; scourge these errours of my youth with pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate reproaches. But such malignant tongues I will counterpoise with the winde; and set as lightly by as they are vaine. And although I am confidently perswaded that the covert of your wings bee sufficiently able to shelter my faults; yet had I rather to expresse my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie towards you in these naked infirmities, whose goodnesse truely knowes how <note n="*" place="margin">Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ignoscere Vegetius in Prolog.</note> to pardon the bold adventures of learning. I present you therefore with ATHENS, whose deplorable raggednesse my papers well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble▪ which may challenge this excuse, that they assimulate themselues to the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise in them contained. Which of all men, I my selfe am conscious most unfitly to haue handled. That Citie once the <note n="*" place="margin">Cic. Epist▪</note> nurse of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son; <note n="*" place="margin">Patercul. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> which flourisht in eloquence, &amp; braue atchieuements more then all <hi>Greece,</hi> could not, unlesse in her miserable ruines, haue without her disgrace beene spoken of by me. That ATHENS whence the learned Fathers of the Church suckt rare literature, <hi>Basil</hi> his
<pb facs="3"/>
eloquence, <hi>Nazianzen</hi> his strength, &amp; others their flowing Oratory. That ATHENS which who had not seene is by <note n="*" place="margin">Apud D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caearchum <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>Lysippus</hi> accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a block. Accept, <hi>Honoured Sir,</hi> these Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of that famous Vniversitie, though by me offered, as Devotion paid to Antiquitie, by you well esteemed of, though among most of these our daies accounted durt; whose labour it is to seek new fashions, and like nought but what may be accounted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty. Resembling the brute, of which <hi>Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro. Ad id solum quod adest, quod{que} praesens est se accommodat, paulum admodum sentiens praeteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp;c.</hi> never caring for what is past. But you weigh well the excellency of talking with those Champians of Learning, hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of yeares since gathered to their former dust. By whose pensils wee see drawne the liuely images of deceased Monarchs, the formes of goverment, and very liues of states. Out of which patternes, if you please to deeme the least part of this to haue beene ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, it shall heap to my ioy that the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tract will not seeme a spurious and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate▪
<pb facs="4"/>
ofspring. Vpon presumption of which I feare not, as the Eagles doe their young, to expose my brood to the rayes of the open Sunne. Thus with continuall wishes for addition to your happinesse, I take leaue, From my Study in <hi>Merton College</hi> Iun. 9. 1637.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your VVorships in all humility to be commanded F. ROVS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>