<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE TRANSLA∣TOVR TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1567</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116558_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03769</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13889</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116558</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE TRANSLA∣TOVR TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of the expresse vvorde of God : A shorte, but a most excellent treatyse and very necessary for this tyme. Written in Latin, by the right reuerend, lerned, and vertuous father Stanislaus Hosius, Bishop of VVarmia, Cardinal of the Holy Apostolyke See of Rome, and one of the presidents in the late general councel holden at Trent. Newly translated in to English</title>
                 <author>Hozjusz, Stanisław</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bogard (Bogardus), Jean</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Louvain</pubPlace>
                    <date>1567</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 113, 3 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE TRANSLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TOVR <hi>TO THE</hi> READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eing the Iniquyte of the present tyme to be suche, that the mouthes of al Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyks being stopped, the aduersaryes only of Christ and his Crosse are suffred to crie and crowe with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen mouthe against our common mother the Catholyke Churche, seing the faithe of our Fathers assalted with heresy, Truthe ouercra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with falshood, Religion turned in to opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, Vnite in to sectes, I coulde not but thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke it high tyme for euery honest and faythful Chrystian, in suche sorte as he were able, to steppe to the susteining, and repayring the Rā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pars of the Churche, being daily bothe by se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret vndermyninges and suche open shott, so fiercely assaulted and shaken by Sathā and his Ministres.</p>
   <p>And being vpon these and other iuste res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectes entred in to that mynde and determy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion, fynding yet my selfe (in myne owne conceyte) vnable to yelde of myne owne, any thinge worthe the reading, I thought not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse (for a beginning) to Imparte by the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modyte of our vulgar toūge to my vnlerned
<pb facs="3"/>
countremē (in which sorte I thinke the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test number of the deceyued to consiste) some worthy worke of some other mannes.</p>
   <p>Amonge the whiche, fynding (in myne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion) none more leekly to induce reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, to see their owne faulte, and by what meanes they haue bene, and daily be decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, I haue selected out of the notable workes of the light of this our age, that most vertuous and lerned Father, <hi>Hosius,</hi> nowe Cardinall, and one of the Presidētes in the late general Coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell holden at Trident, that discourse and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyse, which he made and intytuled, <hi>Of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse worde of God,</hi> a worke allready translated in to diuerse vulgar tounges, sette forthe in sondry editions, distracted and solde by greate numbers, for the singular and euident cōmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyte thereof. And this pece the rather amōge the rest I haue selected, for that I haue by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peryence noted, that there is no one deceyte vsed by Sathan, that dothe so muche enlarge his kingedome, or so muche withdrawe the membres of Christ from his Mysticall body, the Churche, as dothe that glorious shewe, which by his Ministres he maketh of his ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne worde, vnder the plausible name of the VVorde of God.</p>
   <p>For well ye wote, nothinge is in the mow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes of these newe and sedytious Ministers, and promoters of the v. Ghospel, more ryse
<pb facs="3"/>
and cōmon then the scripture, the Gospel, and the worde of the Lorde.</p>
   <p>The worde of the Lorde, the worde of the Lord, is euer in their mouthe. Of this they iā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle. This they ringe allwaies in our eares. But the Catholike church, of whō we shoulde ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne what in dede the word of God is, of whose mouthe only we must harken for this worde, and by whom only we knowe, which is the true written worde of God, and what the true sence of that worde is, this Catholyke Churche they speake not of. VVe professe in our Crede, that we beleue in the Catholy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke Churche. If we did in the Crede, so expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sely professe, we beleue in the worde of God, howe vehemently should that Article haue bene beaten into our heades? VVhat vauntes, what exclamations, what repetityōs woulde here haue suffised? Nowe the Church, not the worde being expressed, the Master and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, not the lesson it selfe beīg professed, they crake of the lessō, and forget their teacher: they bable, the word. And no word of the Church.</p>
   <p>The parte of lerned and playne dealing mē, had bene first to define, and make playne vnto the worlde, what that is which they call the clere and expresse worde of God, and which they make as it were, their shooteanker, their touchestone and their cōmō refuge, whēsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they be by the Catholiks pressed with soū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de
<pb facs="4"/>
and vnuincible Authorite of the Churches doctrine. In dede Epicure (out of whose scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<note place="margin">Lib. 2. de sinibus bo norum &amp; malorum</note> this voluptuous ghospell may seeme to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue issued) did not leeke to haue thinges plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defined. But Cicero sayeth, that without definition it can not be that they which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend aboute any thinge, can agree what is the thinge in question. These men therefore see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to kepe in store blinde and vnknowen Angles to flee vnto, when they be chased, wil not orderly define what is that their Gods worde, of which they triumphe so much, nor allowe any expositiō thereof, but their owne: or any iudge but the vnlerned multytude.</p>
   <p>Sins therefore that is the swete bayte, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewith the mortal hooke is coouered, and the softe flese wherin the wolfe is wrapped (who gladly will not discouer him selfe) this graue, vertuous and lerned Father, <hi>Hosius</hi> the Auctor of this treatyse, moued with Christian pietye will herein manifestly open and displaye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, what is hiddē vnder the glorious she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we of Gods worde: howe farre the bare and darke letter of the scriptures, where in they only comprehend their Gods worde (at the lest yf they lymit it within any compasse) is from being so clere and playne as they suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se it. And farther that the same being by them peruerted and deliuered to thee, with a wrōge sence and a wrye hereticall expositiō, differing
<pb facs="4"/>
from the Churche (which is the sure groūde and piller of al truthe, the faitheful interpreter<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.</note> of Gods worde, aud the storehowse of al right knowkeadge) is in dede so farre frō being the expresse worde of God, as that thou shallt plainely perceyue it to be the expresse worde of the diuell.</p>
   <p>Finally thou shalt (besides many other no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table things by the waye, whereof in the Tab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le to this Booke annexed thou shalt see grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Copie) lerne also herein the true definition of Gods worde, and which is the very true, expresse, and (as they call it) the liuely worde of the Lorde, that is, the quickening and life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing worde of God. VVhich in dede is open and clere: Yea so clere, shorte and easy, as it maye of all persons, of all sortes, ages and capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cytees be lerned, euen without euer reading the Scriptures. And that is this worde. <hi>Loue or</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1. Rom. 13. Galat. 5. Leuit. 19. Matth. 22.</note>
      <hi>Charyte:</hi> The only scope of al scriptures. The ende of all the Cōmaundemētes: The cōsum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiō and accōplishemēt of the whole lawe. Frō the knowleadge and sight of which true, clere, and expresse worde of God, conteyning in it the somme and effect of all the wordes that euer God vttered in the lawe, and the prophetes, thou shalt perceyue in the discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se hereof, howe farre these men be, that yett thinke thē selues of suche sharpe wytte, and quicke sight, that they see beyond all the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue
<pb facs="5"/>
and lerned Fathers that haue bene, or be at this daye. And doo with their forged Gods worde (which is in very dede but their owne worde) labour and tēde to none other ende, but to the dissoluing of vnite, and māgling the misticall body of Christ, the Churche.</p>
   <p>This true worde of God therefore, this Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, I saye and Charyte which on the other si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de dothe not dissolue, but vnyte, not mangle, but amende: not rente and wounde, but ioyne and heale, and is euer occupied, in doīg good, hath nowe moued me to bestowe this trauayl in imparting to thee (my dere Countrey mā) this godly and lerned Treatyse most necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for thy health and sauegarde in this peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous tyme.</p>
   <p>Reade therefore with humilyte, and suspēd, I praye thee, thy partial foreiudgemēt, (if thou be of the nūber of the seduced) vntill thou ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue read it to the ende. And then if thou fynde thy selfe to haue receyued good thereby (as I beseche God thou mayest, and nedes thou must, if thou haue any sparke of grace left, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenched in thee:) then geue the honour and glory thereof to almighty God: And for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence bothe to the Auctor, and Transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, afford them in thy deuoute prayers a place amonge thy frendes. Fare well. From Louayne: The 3. of Ianuary.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>