<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, MY SINGV∣LAR GOOD LORD, THE LORD Archbishop of Canterburie his GRACE, Primate of all ENGLAND, and Metropolitane, and one of His MAIESTIES most Honourable Priuie Councell.</title>
           <author>Brent, Nathanael</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116697_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11516</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21762</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116697</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, MY SINGV∣LAR GOOD LORD, THE LORD Archbishop of Canterburie his GRACE, Primate of all ENGLAND, and Metropolitane, and one of His MAIESTIES most Honourable Priuie Councell.</title>
                 <author>Brent, Nathanael</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of the Councel of Trent : Conteining eight bookes. In which (besides the ordinarie actes of the Councell) are declared many notable occurrences, which happened in Christendome, during the space of fourtie yeeres and more. And, particularly, the practises of the Court of Rome, to hinder the reformation of their errors, and to maintaine their greatnesse. Written in Italian by Pietro Soaue Polano, and faithfully translated into English by Nathanael Brent</title>
                 <author>Sarpi, Paolo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 <publisher>Bill, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, Bonham</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 881, that is 879, 17 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, MY SINGV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAR GOOD LORD, THE LORD Archbishop of <hi>Canterburie</hi> his GRACE, Primate of all ENGLAND, and Metropolitane, and one of His MAIESTIES most Honourable Priuie Councell.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost Reuerend in Christ, It may seeme strange (and I am sure it is without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample) that of one Councell onely so large an Historie should be written, and so full of all varietie of matter. For in those of former ages, in which the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> did really and effectually assist the Fathers, howsoeuer more Prelates and Diuines were assembled from pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces more remote, and the actions guided by the greatest Princes of all those times, yet nothing was attempted to encrease or maintaine the Heresies and abuses that raigned then, nor was any thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable, but the very Doctrines and Decrees themselues. But after that the <hi>Bishops</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> scorning to be Ministers and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, made themselues Masters and Monarkes of the Church of God, the practises and inuentions of worldly men chased away the heauenly inspirations of the blessed Spirit, and greater confusions and troubles did arise in handling Diuine Mysteries, then did happen at any other time in negotiating the affaires of Kingdomes and of Common-wealths. This hath ministred a whole Ocean of occurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and affoorded a most copious Subiect to this present Treatise.</p>
   <p>And so irresistable is the force of Truth, and the Diuine Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence so great, that howsoeuer the Romanists haue vsed all possible diligence to hinder the finding out of their vnlawfull proceedings in
<pb facs="6"/>
this Councell, by suppressing all publique writings and monuments, by which their treacheries and abuses might bee discouered more plainely to the eyes of the world, the writer of this Historie (a man of admirable learning, exquisite iudgement, indefatigable industrie, and integritie scarcely to be matched) hath been raised vp by God, who, out of the <hi>Diaries, Memorials, Registers,</hi> and other wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, made and preserued by the Prelates and Diuines themselues, and by the Ambassadours of Princes and Republiques, who were assistants herein (which are the most infallible grounds that any writer can haue) hath reuealed an infinite of intolerable abuses, and (as the prouerbe saith) <hi>Cornicum oculos confixit.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This Booke I haue translated out of Italian into our vulgar lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, presuming to commend it to the royall protection of his sacred Maiestie, for whose sake (as some reasons induce me to beleeue) it was principally composed. And because I vndertooke this worke at your <hi>Graces</hi> command, who haue beene the chiefest cause why the originall crossed the Seas before the iust natiuitie of it, and saw the first light within his Maiesties dominions, as also in regard of the high place you most deseruedly beare in the Church of God, I thought it my dutie to craue your fauour likewise; that as the birth of it hath beene happie by your <hi>Graces</hi> meanes, so the growth may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly proceed, and the fruit of both (which is to remooue an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious opinion of the infallibilitie of this pretended Councell) may constantly endure vntill the worlds end.</p>
   <p>In publishing heereof, if my Pen hath not merited such praise as others might, yet my desire to benefit Gods Church hath not beene wanting, and my zeale to serue your <hi>Grace,</hi> in whatsoeuer I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, shall neuer yeeld to any. Vnto whom I wish (for the publike benefit of Church and Common-wealth, and for your owne particular contentment) a perfect accomplishment of all your pious and honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble designes.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Grace's most obliged to doe you seruice,
NATHANAEL BRENT.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>