<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116713_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68060</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11109</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116713</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An apolagy of the Holy Sea apostolicks proceeding for the gouernment of the Catholics of England during the tyme of persecution : VVith a defense of a religious state, vvritten by Daniel of Iesus reader of Diuinity</title>
                 <author>Floyd, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Courant, Nicolas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 13, 243, 243-263, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="1" facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HRISTIAN history recordes memorable exampl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> of famous men▪ who hauing written victoriously <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst heresy, towar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s the end of their dayes by a certaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cclipse darkened the glory of their former re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne, the causes of their declining hauing been their immoderat desire of Episcopall dignity from which they were held backe, or emulation against some persons singularly honoured by the soueraigne Pastour, or ouerbould censuring of the sea Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolique for some proceeding by them disliked. As I may ranke M. Doctour amongst those worthies in regard of his morning euer honoured writings, so I will not goe to compare this his later labour with their euening workes, further then with a wish they were more vnlike, and that there were lesse of that smoake which doth not vse to fume frō heauēly fier.</p>
   <p n="2">2. In the drift of his writing he may seem to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble the Sea-Crabb, which looketh on way and goeth another, or a riuer which seeming calme &amp; stil aboue, inwardly runnes with mayne force. His tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atise titularly pretendes to be written against the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy of <hi>Caluine,</hi> and a Chapter or two be inserted in which that cōtrouersy is superficially hādled: that
<pb n="2" facs="3"/> which his whole discourse would really performe is to condemne that forme of gouerment for the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes of Englād, which the holy sea thought most fit for vs during persecution, to wit, by doing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the honour to make England the speciall charg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f their Episcopal care without any other part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cular B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>shop, wherein those holy Princes &amp; Pastour, haue shewed towards vs such fatherly prouidence by founding themselues, and inducing Catholike Princes to found Seminaries of clergy abroad, that in greatest straights a competent number of vertuous Priests was neuer heer wanting, &amp; now, (as M. Doctour doth glory) we enioy a flourishing Cleargy, which we could neuer haue expected had the principall care of vs been leaft vnto a Domesticall Bishops</p>
   <p n="3">3. Notwithstanding in this treatise this course of gouerment is impugned as Anarchicall, as taking away the uery essence of a particular Church; as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuing vs of that Sacrament without which Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans cannot be perfect in that very time when perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is specially necessary; as being a continual vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the deuine Law; as a going against the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall practise of the ancient Church, which in the greater fury of persecution neuer omitted to giue their Bishops to euery particular Church. Heerwith he mingleth mighty cōmendaciōs of Episcopal digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye &amp; state to make the vulgar sort to be enāoured of a Bishop, and to be the readier to yeeld to his sugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to admit of my Lord of Chalcedon as their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, their spirituall King and <hi>Prince of Pastours;</hi> wheras his Hollines will haue him receaued but as a delegate at the most, In the ordering likewise of the Ecclesiasticall Hierarchy though he pretend therin to proceed with great contradiction of <hi>Caluine;</hi> yet
<pb facs="3"/> would he faine displace those sacred Rankes, which <hi>Caluin</hi> did more feare and hate then some of those M. Doctours affection would prefere.</p>
   <p n="4">4. His treatise in the inward disposition thereof &amp; very bowels tending to reprehēd the constant practi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>se of the <hi>piller of truth,</hi> hardly may we expect his doctrine should be euery way sound; yet the censure thereof I leaue to others, the <hi>iudiciall</hi> to the chaire of Peeter, the <hi>iudicious</hi> to the learned reader to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vpon exact discussion, which I haue endeauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to make in this my Answere. Onely this I dare affirme, that strong affectio to the reuerend Order of Secular English Priests, ioyned with ardent desire to see Bishops amongst them, hath caused his pen to runne towards that side, (I will not say from Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like like truth) but from Catholike current opinion, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than otherwise his learning deuoyd of partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity would haue gonne. The same zeale is the cause that euery where about these matters he vseth darke and ambiguous sentences, which the vulgar reader can hardly cōceiue, but in an erroneous sense, fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his cause, though perchance by some subtill distinction he may contend that was not his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
   <p n="5">5. This also I may say (and learned men that haue perused the treatise will concurre in opinion with) me that this treatise is not to compare with his former writings for exactnes; yea he giueth his here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall aduersary (against whom he would seem to write) many aduantages to insult ouer, him, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks for his sakes. Such be some m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sprisiōs in scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as where he saith. c. 1. n. 13. Iob in his fourth chapter, <hi>speaketh of Behemoth the great fish,</hi> wheras Iob there describeth Behemoth as a great beast feeding
<pb n="4" facs="4"/> vpon the grasse of mountaines. And againe, in the same nūber the <hi>scripture compareth Lucifer to Behemoth adorned with mine preatious stones;</hi> where is Behemoth adorned with preatious stones found in scripture? He saith c. 9. n. 14. that at the first Bishops &amp; Priests only preached the Ghospell, and conuerted coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys; is not this great forgetfulnes? Who doth not know that <hi>S. Stephen,</hi> neither Bishop nor Priest, but only Deacon preached the Ghospell, as also did <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Deacon,</hi> who by preaching conuerted Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria? To preferre Bishops before Angels for office, he saith c. 7. n. 2. <hi>cut Angelorum dictum est paescite qui in vobis est gregem Dei?</hi> to which of the Angels was it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer said, feed the flocke of God that is amongst you <hi>as to Bishops it was sayed.</hi> To which questiō one might readily answeare out of the Woord of God, to those Angels of whom the Psalmist saith Psalm. 90. v. 12. <hi>Angelis suis manda <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>it de te in omnibus vijs tuis. He hath giuen chardge to his Angels ouer thee to keepe thee in all thy wayes.</hi> For Angels to haue charge to keep the sheep &amp; flocke of God, what is it but to be their Pastour?</p>
   <p n="6">6. The like mistaking he hath about Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal history, as c. 13 n. 11. where discribing the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty of the Arian Tyrant Trasimūdus, he citeth for authour Orosius l. 1. c. 10. where no such thing is found, and Orosius was dead many a faire yeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that time. In the number of Popes that suffered from Nero to Constantine, he placeth <hi>Ioannes. Silue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> and <hi>Martinus</hi> who suffered more then two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares after; c. 13. n. 6 amongst the persecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church he putteth the persecutiō of <hi>Vespa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianus</hi> a thing neuer before named, or hardof. In the same place he commendeth the Roman Bishops namly <hi>Corn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>llus</hi> that then in persecution they neuer
<pb n="5" facs="4"/> intermitted the Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cession by long Sea-uacancy, where as before the election of Cornelius there was a Sea-u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ancy of sixteen monthes, longer then any euer happened before, or after either within a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand yeares.</p>
   <p n="7">7: He hath discourses that do rather eneruate then giue force vnto the Catholike arguments he bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roweth of others As c. 3. n 14, hauing that proued S. Peter was made Pastour of the church of Christ by the words <hi>Pasce oues meas,</hi> he makes S. Peter speake to extoll his owne dignity ouer his fellow Apostles in this manner. <hi>If</hi> saith he) <hi>S. Peter after that he had recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued this charge ouer Christs sheep should haue demaunded of the rest of the Apostles are you the sheep of Christ they could not haue denied it▪ and then Peter m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ght haue subsinned; If you be the sheep of Christ you are m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> sheep, because Christ without d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>stinction c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mitted al his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>heep to me. And if you be my sheep, I am your Pastour &amp; Superiour, because <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Sheep is a name of subiection; so Pastour is a name of superioritye. And if I be your Pastour, who are all soe Pastoures, I am</hi> Pastor Pastorum, <hi>the Pastour of Pastours, and for the Pastour of you and your shepe, and consequently of all the Church.</hi> Seing M. Doctour was pleased to play the Rhetorician in this place and vse a <hi>pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>opopea,</hi> he might more discretely haue giuē the speech in prayse of S. Peter and his dignity to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>me other person than S. Peter himselfe, and haue followed that aduise of wisedome <hi>laudet te os aliruum &amp; non os cuum</hi> be thou praysed by anothers mans mouth, and not by thine owne Yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the making of S. Peter to dispute with his fellow Apostles about his primacy was more thē needlesse; us who should say they were doubtful the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof. And M. Doctours vrging the commō argumen would haue been mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, had it been further
<pb n="6" facs="5"/> from the least insinuatiō of Apostolical backeward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in this poynt to be disputed agaynst, as indeed there was none, they being after our sauiours Ordin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance euer more ready to acknowledge thā S. Peter to exercise his supreme iurisdiction ouer them.</p>
   <p n="8">8. He maketh Doctrines to be of faith vpon groundes uery weake, as c. 8. n. 8. hee saith, it is certaine that Deacōs &amp; Subdeacōs are of the deuine institution because the Councell of Trent doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce <hi>Anathema</hi> to any that shall say that the Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy instituted by Diuine Ordinance doth not <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stare ex Episcopis et Presbiteris &amp; Ministris, confest of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, Priests and Ministers, by Ministers</hi> (saith he) <hi>in the plurall we must needs vnderstād at least Deacons &amp; Subde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acons;</hi> who wil not presētly perceaue the weaknesse of this arguing? For the Councell also saith in the plurall <hi>Priests</hi> are of the Hierarchy, and yet this doth not import different kinds of <hi>Priests</hi> but only many Priests of the same kind. In like manner the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels might say <hi>Ministers</hi> in the plural to signifye many Ministers of the same kind, to wit many of the order of deacons. How poore a proofe then is this that M. Doctour should hereō conclude, that it is certaiē that there be Ministers of different kindes; at the least Deacons &amp; Subdeacons. These and the like exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of some ouersight and weakenes that may be brought, shew that M. Doctour in writing this treatise was not moued with so light some zeale and so deuoyd of smoake, as he did his former workes, that with much honour both to himselfe, &amp; the Church this might haue been suppressed.</p>
   <p n="9">9. Howsoeuer; veneration due to his person will make me firmely perswaded, that whatsoeuer defect may be found in this writing; yet it is not
<pb n="7" facs="5"/> such, but we may compare him with one frō whom a temporall slipp <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nto e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>or tooke not away the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall stile of Saint, I mean <hi>S. Cyprian.</hi> I will presume that conceiued necessity of a Bishop without any ambition of that honour, sincere loue of presumed truth in the behalf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of the Secular Cleargy, no se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret instinct of enuy against Regulars, moued his hād and hart in this writing, that wherin he may seem to mistake, is but a token of humane frailty, &amp; no such fayling in Charity, but <hi>S. Augustines</hi> excuse for <hi>S, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> may agree vnto him, <hi>naeuum in candidissimo pectore sanctae illius animae charitatis vbera contegebant (l.</hi> 1 <hi>de Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tismo cap.</hi> 19.) the mole that did somwhat blemish, the candide breast of that holy soule with the breasts of his charity was hidden.</p>
   <p n="10">10. Which charity (I confide) will moue him not to be offended at this <hi>Apology</hi> for the proceeding <hi>of the sea Apostolike,</hi> &amp; for the perfection of Religious state, it being for the good of human kind, and for the salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of soules most important, that these two pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, the one of Truth, the other of Sanctity be not in the least manner violated, especiall by any of our English nation, we being behoulding aboue all to the one, and the other for our conuersion from Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganisme, yea to the first also at this present for our subsisting in persecution (for of the second how they concurre both at home and abroad to the furtherāce of this worke and aduancing of the Cleargy in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp; holy education I wil say nothing). If in this treatise I discouer his mistaking in citing au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours to his purpose against their meaning, &amp; some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times not so fully and faythfully, he will not be soe much greeued at our laying open that defect, as at his owne ouerferuent vndertaking a cause that could
<pb n="8" facs="6"/> not be without such helpe (which truth neuer nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth) defended, and what Bellarmine said of <hi>S. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian (l.</hi> 4. <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> verb. Dei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. c.</hi> 11.) may without much dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit of his learning be true in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>m <hi>nurum non est <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m errantem errantum more rati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>art:</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> what himselfe saith p. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>3. of the worthy Cardinal Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recremata. <hi>He was a most learned man, though learned men be men &amp; so may be ouer seen.</hi>
   </p>
   <list>
      <head>The points that be handled.</head>
      <item>1. <hi>That a particular Church may subsi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap> wi hout a Bishop.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>2. <hi>That Confirmatiō is not so necessary in time of persecutiō.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>3 <hi>That the Diuine law doth not so inuiollably require a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop in euery Church.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>4. <hi>That the Primitiue Church in such circumstances we are in would neuer haue placed Bishops in En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>land.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>5. <hi>Whether Regulars haue an eminēt place in the Hierarchy?</hi>
      </item>
      <item>6. <hi>That the state of Bishops is not so absolutely &amp; in all res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects more perfect than the state of Religion.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>VVhether the Apostles were Regulars?</hi>
      </item>
      <item>8. <hi>Whether s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>culars haue by diuine ordinance right and authority to preach to Gentils &amp;c. Regulars only by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall authority?</hi>
      </item>
      <item>9. <hi>How M. Doctours vrging Catholikes to entertaine my Lord of Chalcedon as their Bishop and spirituall Prince is not reasonable.</hi>
      </item>
   </list>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>