<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CATHOLIKES of Irland.</title>
           <author>P., S.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116152_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11947</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4551</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116152</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CATHOLIKES of Irland.</title>
                 <author>P., S.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discours hapned. Betwene an hermite called Nicephorus &amp; a yong louer called Tristan, who for that his Mistresse Petronilla entred into religion would faine become an hermite. All faithfullie dravven out of the historie of Petronilla, composed in French by the Right Reuerend Father in God Iohn Peter Camus Bishop of Belley. And translated into English by P.S.P</title>
                 <author>Camus, Jean-Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Blageart, Jerome</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Paris</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 171, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE CATHOLIKES of Irland.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>ENOWNED Catholikes the Histoire of Petro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nilla Coming to my hands, composed by the Right Reuerend Father in God Iohn Peter Camus Bishop of Belley a man of Knovvne learning, emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <note place="margin">He vvra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te many bookes.</note> pietie &amp; of an Apostolicall life, the fancie tooke me to imploy some time in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of it, not doubting but coming from so famous an Authour, I should find some thing in it worth my labour. Going then forward in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="3"/> therof, amongst many other good things, I lighted vpon this Treatise, which when I considered, I said thus to my self: it might be thought, that this man had reuelation, or some notice giuen him of the emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; variāce which is betweene the Hierarchicall Clergie and the Regulars in Irland, &amp; that in consequens therof he framed this Discours. For it is said, that the Regulars there, thinking therby to magnifie and extoll themselues (for I know no other reason they can haue for it) make no conscience nor scrupule both in their publike sermons, and in their priuat cōuersations amōgst you, to say and affirme, that Priests are but meere Seculars,
<pb facs="3"/> that thēselues are true Pastours, that it belongs to them only to be called Fathers, that they are the choice and best part of the Ecclesiasticall Hierarchie, &amp; which is more absurd, that their Regular Superiours are more worthy then Bishops. All which assertions manifestly false, and ill becoming men whose institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is chiefely grounded in humilitie and contempt of worldly honour and respects, being touched and discussed in this Treatise, I thought in my loue and naturall affection towards you, my deere Country men, that I was in a manner bound, fearing these things should giue you some erronious impressions, to impart it vnto
<pb facs="4"/> you. Wherupon I tooke the paines to translate it out of French into English &amp; to haue it printed. And if I shall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand that it takes effect, &amp; cause the Delinquēts reflect vpon their errour, herin &amp; vpon that saying of S. Iames the Apostle: <hi>If any man think himself to be Religious</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Iac.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 26</note>
      <hi>not bridling his tongue, but seducing his hart, this mans Religion is vaine,</hi> then will I think my labour well imployed. And that which is most to be desired of them is, that they doe consider first, that such assertions and comparisons doe more hurt then good, do rather destroy then edifie, rather peruert then conuert the people from their euill courses, &amp; rather breede hate &amp; enuie, then loue
<pb facs="4"/> or charitie: and secondly that they consider, that Priesthood, which is the fontaine and fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all Ecclesiasticàll fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, is the same in Secular Priests (as they terme them) and in Regulars, whence Priests may iustlie say to the Regulars with saint Paul, that if they be He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes so are they, if they be <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 22.</note> Israëlites soe are they, if they be the seede of Abraham so are they, if they be Ministers of CHRIST so are they; yea more, that they are their elders and haue higher offices and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the Church then they haue. And for you worthy cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions I shall desire you not to be scandalized to see one Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike write against an other,
<pb facs="5"/> beleeuing that Catholikes as Catholikes doe agree in matters of Faith, but as men that they may varie in other opinions. S. Peter and S. Paul, S. Austin <note place="margin">
         <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 15. <hi>Hieron. ep.</hi> 86. <hi>Aug. ep.</hi> 8 <hi>&amp; sequ. Eus. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 25 <hi>Bedal.</hi> 3. <hi>Histor. Angl. cap.</hi> 24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 25. <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 16. <hi>Dan.</hi> 20.</note> and S. Hierome disagreed in some opinions without breach of fayth or charitie. About the obseruation of Easter there was great debate betwixt Saincts &amp; Saincts till the Church decided the controuersie; yea Angels haue dissented in opinions. But this you may note in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie, that learned Doctours in these Countries, and some of them Religious men, with whom I did cōfer of the same, do much admeere that the Regulars in Irland do cōtest with the Clergie for the said points, wheras in no
<pb facs="5"/> Catholike Countries do the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulars speake of the like, but cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine themselues within the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinct of their Monasteries, and the obseruance of their Rules, which teach the quit contrarie of all that they doe in this kind And if they will alleage that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no Monasteries in Irlād they must goe vp &amp; downe amongst you, like other Priests, me thinks they should the lesse claime any perfection or respect ouer other Priests, and my warrant for this is S. Hierome, who speaking of such Monks and Religious men saith: <hi>Sicut piscis extra aquam ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret vita sic Monachus extra Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasterium.</hi> As fish being out of the water doth want life, so doth a Monke or Religious man
<pb facs="6"/> being out of his Monasterie. For the life of a Religious man, as such, is to obserue his Rules, and keepe his vowes, which he cannot doe so well, if he do it at all, being cóuersant in the world, &amp; not doing it, what prerogatiue can he claime ouer others? To conclude if the Regulars be true Pastours as is aboue said, how can they excuse themselues that they take no more care of their flock then some odd times like passingers to preach vnto them, God knowes with litle fruict? Who will not say but the good Priest is more like to be the true Pastour: <hi>Who giueth his life for his sheepe,</hi> seruing them, not by starts but all the yeere long, by day and by night, in heate and in
<pb facs="6"/> cold, in raine and in tempest, with much miserie &amp; litle profit? Lastly who can beleeue that the Regulars are true or proper Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stours whenas they cannot take any such chardge vpon them if first they be not dispensed with all in their vovves. Add that in Catholike Countries, where all Clergie men get their due, they cannot preach nor Minister any Sacrament out of their owne Conuents without the expresse leaue of the Bishop of the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cese, and of the Pastour of the place, conformable to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell <note place="margin">
         <hi>Sess.</hi> 24.</note> of Trent? Howsoeuer they will answere to all these things, I make no doubt but after their accustomed manner, some of them vvill say (for I Knovv that
<pb facs="7"/> many good men amongst them doe not approue such things) that he is no frend of Religious men that doth propound them. But God is my vvitnesse, I do honour &amp; respect all Religious men, and vvish all others to do the same, as long as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine themselues vvithin the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of their Rules, &amp; that they do not prefer the honour of their order, as many seeme to doe, to the honour and seruice of God, to vvhose diuine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection I commit you, and pray him, to giue vs all the Spirit of vnion and charitie, &amp; so rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your deuoted seruant in CHRIST IESVS P. S. P.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>