<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Right excel∣lent and Honourable Lord, Hen∣ry Earle of Darby, Lord Stanley, and Strange: Lord of Man, and Th'Isles, one of hir Maiesties most honorable priuie Counsell, Lord Lieutenant of the Coun∣ties of Lancaster, and Chester, and of the Citie of Chester, and knight of the noble order of the Garter. I. F. wisheth all happinesse.</title>
           <author>Florio, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116232_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11025</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21292a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116232</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Right excel∣lent and Honourable Lord, Hen∣ry Earle of Darby, Lord Stanley, and Strange: Lord of Man, and Th'Isles, one of hir Maiesties most honorable priuie Counsell, Lord Lieutenant of the Coun∣ties of Lancaster, and Chester, and of the Citie of Chester, and knight of the noble order of the Garter. I. F. wisheth all happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Florio, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A letter lately written from Rome, by an Italian gentleman, to a freende of his in Lyons in Fraunce : Wherein is declared, the state of Rome: the suddaine death &amp; sollemne buriall of Pope Gregory the thirteenth. The election of the newe Pope, and the race of life this new Pope ranne before hee was aduanced. Thereto are adioyned the accidentes that haue fallen out, not onely in Rome, but in Naples &amp; other parts of the worlde also. Newely translated out of Italian into English by I.F</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>80 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the Right excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and Honourable Lord, Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Earle of Darby, Lord Stanley, and Strange: Lord of Man, and Th'Isles, one of hir Maiesties most honorable priuie Counsell, Lord Lieutenant of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Lancaster, and Chester, and of the Citie of Chester, and knight of the noble order of the Garter. I. F. wisheth all happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the testimonie of a duetiful mind, might prooue a sufficient counterpeise to a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite, I might now (right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) discharge the bande, where with I am so deepelie indebted to your honor: But because I am not able with wordes, to match so high and honorable deedes, I am contēted to remaine a debter still. For as the magnificence of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
was so great, that such as haue gone about to lift it vp with commendation, were suddainly stopt and enforst to confesse, they had rather say nothing, then say too little. So when I consider the excellencie of your calling, the nobility of your bloode, and the vertues wherin you shine, though I be desirous to giue a tast of your prayses vnto the world, yet find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my sight too weake to stare vpon such a sun, I am cōpelde to turne away my face and giue it ouer. Neuerthelesse, knowing it to be the parte of a Princely coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellour, to haue an eye in the head of euery common weale, I haue presumed to publish these newes of forraine partes in your honors name, and so much the rather, because I finde in your honor the
<pb facs="3"/>
disposition of <hi>Panthoidas,</hi> who being sent Ambassadour into <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sia,</hi> regarded not their goodly and sumptuous buildings, the rich or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naments of their houses, &amp; such other pleasaunt showes, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther endeuoured himself to learn their policies, their gouernment, their customes, their Lawes and proceedings, the manner of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of theyr battayle, the order of theyr fight, with such like en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries woorthy a Noble man, whose notable steps your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship in your honourable last Am<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bassage did honourably followe: to the perpetuall eternising of your honours auncient and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble name, and the perfect conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of both their Maiesties.</p>
   <p>Thus being lothe to be too te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, I leaue these nouels to
<pb facs="4"/>
your honours consideration, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till time shall yeelde better, and better woorthy your honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble viewe. Till when and euer wholy dedicating my selfe to your honour, I wyshe your honour all felicity, and grace. The 29. of Iune 1585.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors most humble &amp; duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to commande. <hi>Iohn Florio.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>