<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, AND truly worthy of all honour, WILLIAM Earle of Pembroke, Lo. Chamberlaine to his Majestie, Knight of the thrice Noble Order of the Garter, and one of the Lords of his most Honorable Privie Councell.</title>
           <author>Reynolds, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116165_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10668</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20944</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116165</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, AND truly worthy of all honour, WILLIAM Earle of Pembroke, Lo. Chamberlaine to his Majestie, Knight of the thrice Noble Order of the Garter, and one of the Lords of his most Honorable Privie Councell.</title>
                 <author>Reynolds, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The triumphs of Gods revenge against the crying and execrable sinne of (willfull and premeditated) murther : VVith his miraculous discoveries, and severe punishments thereof. In thirtie severall tragicall histories (digested into sixe bookes) committed in divers countries beyond the seas, never published, or imprinted in any other language. Histories which containe great varietie of mournfull and memorable accidents ... With a table of all the severall letters and challenges, contained in the whole sixe bookes. Written by Iohn Reynolds</title>
                 <author>Reynolds, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lee, William 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lee, William 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 75, 3, 81-181, 7, 187-260, 259-294, that is 293, 7, 303-414, 10, 425-527, 9, 337-404, 409-464 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="109"/>
   <pb facs="109"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, AND truly worthy of all honour, <hi>WILLIAM</hi> Earle of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> Lo. Chamberlaine to his Majestie, Knight of the thrice Noble Order of the Garter, and one of the Lords of his most Honorable Privie Councell.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT HONOURABLE,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not your <hi>Dignities,</hi> but your <hi>Vertues;</hi> not your <hi>Greatnesse,</hi> but your <hi>Goodnesse</hi> which first conjured my affection, then comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded my resolution to direct these (forraigne) <hi>Tragicall Histories</hi> to your <hi>Honours</hi> prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and patronage; For whiles others (sai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with the corrupt Tyde and Current of the times) not only admire, but adore the exteriour parts of men, their <hi>Fortunes,</hi> I, for my part, both honour and reverence their interiour qualities and ornaments, <hi>Pietie, Fidelitie, Generositie,</hi> (three Daughters of <hi>Heaven,</hi> embleming and personating the three Heavenly Graces on Earth, <hi>Faith, Hope, Charitie)</hi> who transport and convey our <hi>Memories</hi> as farre as the limits of <hi>Time,</hi> and a degree beyond it, and (on the wings of <hi>Truth)</hi> mount our <hi>Fames</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rom <hi>Earth</hi> to <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> from <hi>Envy</hi> to <hi>Glory,</hi> and from <hi>Mortalitie</hi> to <hi>Eternitie.</hi> Not but that
<pb facs="110"/>
I every way respect and honour that blood which is <hi>Noble,</hi> but that I yet more dearly honour and deeply affect those <hi>Vertues</hi> which have a secret, and (as I may justly say) a sacred power in them to ennoble <hi>Nobilitie,</hi> both which transcendent <hi>Privileges,</hi> finding hand in hand cheerefully to march, and really to sympathize in your <hi>Ho.</hi> (sith upon the resplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent lustre of your actions, <hi>Envie</hi> is not capable to insinuate a blemish, nor <hi>Detraction</hi> of power to introduce or inforce a disparagement) was the sole prevailing motive of this my <hi>Zeale</hi> and <hi>Ambition.</hi> And when I consider that the Moralitie, Ends and Punishments of these foule and crying sinnes of Murther, which my two former Bookes (of this <hi>Nature)</hi> have already related and divulged to the world, have not only been ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, but applauded of our most <hi>Excellent</hi> and <hi>Sacred King,</hi> (as only aiming at Gods glory, and our owne reformation and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ervation) I rather hope than despaire, that this <hi>Third</hi> (wherein the just revenge of <hi>God,</hi> the Great and Supreme <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> is no lesse apparent and conspicuous) will be accepted and received of your <hi>Ho.</hi> Againe, it fights against Murther, which not only seekes to slay <hi>Humanitie,</hi> but therein to murther <hi>Religion,</hi> which is the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Soule</hi> thereof. It denounceth war against <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> against the Divine Ordinances of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and the Coactive and penall Lawes of <hi>Earth,</hi> whereby they are esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished and maintained, as being the <hi>Cymment</hi> and <hi>Sinewes,</hi> the <hi>Veines</hi> and <hi>Arteries</hi> of <hi>Monarchies</hi> and <hi>Common weales;</hi> as also against the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie of <hi>God,</hi> and the Crownes and Dignities of <hi>Soueraigne Kings</hi> and Princes, his Royall <hi>Deputies</hi> and <hi>Vice-gerents</hi> here on earth, sith thereby he loseth soules, and these subjects; yea, so generall and so prodigious a progression doth this scarlet sin of premeditated and wilfull murther make in the universall World, and with so bloodie a deluge and inunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it not only washes, but (as it were) drownes the face of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian,</hi> that wee have now far truer cause to cry out, and juster reason to exclaime, than did <hi>Quintus Catulus</hi> (so many centuries of yeeres since) <hi>O with whom, or where shall wee liue in safetie, sith in wars wee kill those who are armed, and in Peace, who are unarmed?</hi> Yea, your <hi>Ho.</hi> who (with a happy constancie, and constant happinesse) is still a professed Champion for <hi>Charitie</hi> against <hi>Enuie,</hi> and a <hi>Tutelarie</hi> Protector for <hi>Vertue</hi> against <hi>Vice,</hi> (whiles divers great ones of the World make it not only their practice, but their glory to performe the contrary) will, I hope, run over these mournfull <hi>Histories,</hi> (and the severall accidents they relate) with your eye of pittie, and spirit of compassion; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in with a religious joy, and pious insultation, not only admire the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence,</hi> but applaud and magnifie the <hi>Iustice</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> in so timely cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="110"/>
off these Monsters of <hi>Nature,</hi> and bloudy Butchers of Mankinde, with these their condigne punishments and deserved deaths: In which Hope and Confidence, this Booke is no more mine, but your <hi>Honours,</hi> and no lesse is he who collected and penned it; and that my Name may futurely oblige mee to make this present promise of my pen reall; Whiles many others (in a vertuous emulation) contend to deserve the <hi>Honour</hi> of your <hi>Fauour,</hi> and strive to purchase the felicitie of your <hi>Commands,</hi> none shall doe it with more Integritie and lesse Vanitie, than</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours truly deuoted
IOHN REYNOLDS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>