<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116610_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18939</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5357</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116610</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Holy incense for the censers of the saints. Or, A method of prayer : with matter, and formes in selected sentences of sacred scripture. Also A praxis upon the holy oyle shewing the vse of scripture-phrases. And choyse places taken out of the singing Psalmes, digested into a method of prayer and praises</title>
                 <author>Clarke, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 283, 1, 6, 40, 12 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O gratifie the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of friends, and to satisfie some to whom I have long beene much obliged, rather than for any conceited worth of any thing that is <hi>mine,</hi> in these formes and method of Prayer, are they thus now presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to thy view (<hi>Christian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi>) There be many (blessed be God) in manifold respects, farre beyond <hi>these</hi> of mine. Excellent moulds and formes of <hi>prayer.</hi> That which I here undertake, is but to gather into heapes, and heads some <hi>graines</hi> of sweet gummes, <hi>myrrh,</hi> aloes, cassia, and <hi>frankincense</hi> (more precious than all the perfumes, and pouders of the Merchant) out of the Spouses
<pb facs="11"/>
garden of spices, which <hi>thou</hi> maist scatter on the burning coals of thy z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>alous Devotions. If any, even the meanest that calleth God <hi>Father,</hi> can make use <hi>hereof</hi> in framing his <hi>petitions,</hi> to bee put up, and presented to the high Court of Heaven, I have my ends and desires, how ever they shall be <hi>taken,</hi> or take <hi>others.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I prescribe no man a way, the spirit of God is not limited by me. Private prayers may bee framed, as the holy spirit gives us utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; and it is a vaine thing when the heart is full, and boyles upward, to quench and restraine its free operations. No, poure out thy heart in prayer as thou feelest enlargement.</p>
   <p>Publike prayers would bee more composed, and set to that exact and heavenly platforme, and prayer of our Saviour, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who pray with us, may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the orderly passing from one part to another, and so bee helped,
<pb facs="11"/>
edified, and affected thereby.</p>
   <p>For the <hi>Common-prayers</hi> in our Church Liturgie, it were to be wished, that in great and noble families, which are more than a modell of a little Church, they would use the Common-prayer-booke, there they may have most excellent prayers, for almost-any occasion incident and imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: <hi>such</hi> as both Martyrs <note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour</hi> taking his leave of his vvife, vvith vvee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and teares, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, gave her for his <hi>Fare well</hi> and last to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, a book of the <hi>Church-ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> set out by K. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> which in the time of his impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonment he daily used. Mr. <hi>Fox.</hi> Acts and <hi>Mon</hi> vol. 3. pag. 175 col 1. lin 10. (a) <hi>Pet. Martyr,</hi> and the Arch-Bishop of Canterbury offered to defend the Protestants Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer Booke against Queene <hi>Maries</hi> Religion. <hi>Acts</hi> &amp; <hi>Mon.</hi> vol. 3. pag. 18 col. 2. lin. 50. The Prelates in King <hi>Edwards</hi> time, after long, learned, wise, and deliberate advise, did finally conclude and agree upon one Vniform order of Common-Prayer, Sacraments, &amp;c.—<hi>vol.</hi> 2 <hi>pag.</hi> 659. lin. 47. And Doctor <hi>Taylour</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of <hi>Hadley,</hi> saith therof, that the book of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>service, vvas so fully perfected according to the rules of our Christian religion in every behalfe, that no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian conscience could bee offended with any thing therein contained. <hi>vol.</hi> 3 <hi>pag.</hi> 171. lin. 20.</note> and all other, peaceable and sober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded Christians have ever ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, extolled, vindicated, and practised. Pitie it is to see some, out of I know not what humour, to cavill, carpe at, and cry downe (not onely formes of <hi>private</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, such as these, but) that which all antiquitie hath so much magnified, and hath under so gracious and pious <hi>Princes, a</hi> by
<pb facs="12"/>
publike authority, so long beene established in the Church. Certes <hi>Publike</hi> Prayers of the people of God, in Churches throughly set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, did never use to be voluntary Dictates▪ <note n="b" place="margin">M. <hi>Hooker.</hi> lib. 5. Sect. 26. Eccles. policie.</note> proceeding from any mans private spirit, gift, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporall wit. <note n="*" place="margin">Pause be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou speak, <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> caveat <hi>Be not rash▪</hi> an <hi>Extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore</hi> orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before a <hi>Prince,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes not, much lesse to open our mouthes rashly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ker. Mr <hi>Harr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> Ha▪ in <hi>Epist.</hi> to <hi>Peters</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement.</note>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note n="c" place="margin">Nu 6. 23.</note>
      <hi>God</hi> himselfe framed to his <hi>Priests,</hi> the very speech where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they were charged to blesse the people. And our Lord even of purpose to prevent this fancie of extemporall and voluntary Prayers, hath left us of his owne framing, <hi>one,</hi> which might both remaine as a part of the Church-Liturgie, and serve as a paterne whereby to frame all other Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, with efficacie, yet without su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluitie
<pb facs="12"/>
of words.</p>
   <p>Prayers, doubtlesse, are accepted of God otherwise than being cōcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved alwayes anew according to the exigent of present occasions: being not actions which ought to waste a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way themselves in the making; they may bee resumed, and used a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine as Prayers, and yet no instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of superstition. <note n="d" place="margin">From the tyrannie of the Bishop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and all his detestable errours, idolatries, and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, good Lord deliver us. <hi>Acts</hi> &amp; <hi>Mon.</hi> vol. 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 170. lin. 19. <hi>Hooker ibid.</hi>
      </note> Moses hath left a prayer, (for that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable victorie given them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Pharaoh</hi>) cast into a Poeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call mould which grew afterward to be a part of the ordinary Iewish Liturgie—&amp;c.</p>
   <p>The <hi>Lord</hi> grant unitie, and concord to all that call upon his name, that they may agree in the truth of his holy Word, and live in Godly love one with another: that all unhappy differences in opinion may bee composed, and those swellings and great thoughts of heart layed downe. That wee may all mind one thing, to serve our God out of a pure heart,
<pb facs="13"/>
without evill surmisings, or making things worse by jealous, and suspicious censurings, which exasperate rather than heale our breach. Let us pray and labour hereunto. The prayers of the <hi>Christian</hi> Souldiers brought raine to the fainting armies of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Emperours. <hi>Elias</hi> a man sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to passions, as others bee, by <hi>Prayer</hi> shut &amp; opened heaven. <hi>Est quaedam precum omnipotentia,</hi> one calls it, <note n="e" place="margin">Preces hirudo curarum, <hi>Luth Ep. ad Melan Swanus</hi> King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> to all his ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges done in <hi>Eng.</hi> and his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap>ing exces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive impositions upon the people, having entred the territory of St. <hi>Edmund,</hi> spoyling the countrey, and despising the holy Martyr, menacing also the place of his S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>pulture, the men of that countrey fell to prayer, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting; so that <hi>Swanus</hi> shortly after died suddenly, crying and yelling among his <hi>Knights,</hi> See the vertue of Christian mens prayer. <hi>Acts &amp; Mon. vol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> pag 208 col. 2 lin. 20.</hi> K. <hi>Ethelred,</hi> then at service, and meditations when his bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>er <hi>Alured</hi> was in fight with the <hi>Danes,</hi> being required to make ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e, (such was his devotion) hee would not starre out one foote, before their <hi>service</hi> was fully complet, his brother being in great danger then: neverthelesse the King through the gracious assistance of that <hi>God,</hi> whom hee invoked, wan the field, and the <hi>Danes</hi> lost both the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and their lives Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> Acts. &amp; <hi>Mon. vol. 1. pag. 182. li 58.</hi> Pious <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ld</hi> also, K. of Northumberland, boat <hi>Penda &amp; Ced<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall,</hi> by the power, not so much of his <hi>sword,</hi> as <hi>prayer.</hi> Strength of prayer overcōmeth armies <hi>Act. &amp; Mon. vol. 1. pa. 157 col. 1. lin 71.</hi> What should I speak of his <hi>Praiers,</hi> which were soardent unto Christ that they which stood under his win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, as hee was praying, might see his teares falling &amp; arop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping downe. <hi>Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>cth. de Luthero</hi> Againe with such power hee prayed, that <hi>he</hi> (as himselfe confesseth) had obtained of the <hi>Lord,</hi> that so long as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ed the Pope should not prevaile in his country, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>my</hi> death (said hee) let them pray who can <hi>M. Fox Act &amp; Monn. vol. 2 pag 88.</hi>
      </note> the wonder-working power of <hi>Prayer,</hi> able to beate backe the very <hi>Ord'nance</hi> of Hell, a spirituall Engine, able to batter downe all the Bull warks of the
<pb facs="13"/>
      <hi>Devill,</hi> the most precious, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most (if not altogether) omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Grace, and great Master of miracles wrought both in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth. Beleeve it, if then wert in a state more dangerous than Death, in a place worse than Hell, yet if <hi>thou</hi> couldst but thence pray truly, thou shouldst find com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. Out of the belly of hell cried I, <hi>Iona. 2.</hi> Hereby thou mayst have accesse to <hi>God</hi> on all occasions; for <hi>Prayer</hi> beares about the privie <hi>Keyes</hi> of heaven, yea forceth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, when all is <hi>locked.</hi> Be in love with this so heavenly a grace, f and that time, &amp; breath, and spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits which others spend in prating<note place="margin">f. An exercise (I can assure thee) of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable strength and comfort, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which thou canst not live, and by which thou maist live in the mouth of death▪ &amp;c. <hi>Mr.</hi> Harris <hi>of</hi> Han. <hi>in Epist. before</hi> Peters <hi>enlargement.</hi>
      </note> of, and censuring the actions of su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours, doe <hi>thou</hi> in praying to <hi>God,</hi> for thy selfe, for the Church, for our gracious <hi>King,</hi> and all in authority under <hi>him,</hi> that <hi>wee</hi> may still lead a quiet and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able life in all godlinesse and hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, which is the <hi>Prayer</hi> of thy fellow servant in Christ Iesus,</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>