<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCES, FREDERICK and ELIZABETH, by the Grace of God, King and Queene of Bohemia, Princes Pa∣latines of the Rhine, &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116994_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11808</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22104</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116994</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCES, FREDERICK and ELIZABETH, by the Grace of God, King and Queene of Bohemia, Princes Pa∣latines of the Rhine, &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second part of Vox populi, or Gondomar appearing in the likenes of Matchiauell in a Spanish parliament : wherein are discouered his treacherous &amp; subtile practises to the ruine as well of England, as the Netherlandes faithfully transtated [sic] out of the Spanish coppie by a well-willer to England and Holland</title>
                 <author>Scott, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Janss, Ashuerus, pseud.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 60 pages, illustrations (engravings), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCES, FREDERICK and ELIZABETH, by the Grace of God, <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queene</hi> of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> Princes <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latines</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
   <head type="sub">AS ALSO To the most Illustrious and victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, <hi>Maurice,</hi> Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> Count of <hi>Nassau,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most High Most Illustrious Princes,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT I haue adventured in these vnfaithfull times, so full of suspition and danger, to passe (without leaue) your guardes, and to presse into your Presence, I most humbly craue pardon, having I confesse no other excuse
<pb facs="3"/>
then that common one of the Countrie, it was out of my loue, out of my loyalty, for such (most gracious Q: <hi>Elizabeth</hi>) hath heeretofore your respect beene towards mee (farre vnworthy God knowes of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the least favours from so Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent a Princesse) that ever since, I haue contended with my selfe, to adventure and Act something, that might haue pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er still to preserue me in your Royall Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, but albeit I had the will, I find my selfe wanting in my Abilitie. And most Illustrious, Prince <hi>Maurice,</hi> since I haue had sometime dependance on your Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, I hold it my Dutie gratefully to repay, some part of what (I cannot say iniustly) I haue gained vnder you that is <hi>Observation,</hi> especially of the double dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and cunning Iuggling of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> with all Nations. And since a little <hi>Treatise</hi> of a <hi>Spanish</hi> Consultation (whether really acted, or poetically faigned I know not) came to my hands, first written in <hi>Spanish,</hi> now by my selfe translated into <hi>English,</hi> onely for the behoofe and loue I beare as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well to <hi>England</hi> my natiue Countrie, as
<pb facs="3"/>
to the <hi>Netherlands.</hi> I haue sent it abroad, good it may doe, hurt it cannot. <hi>Abundans. cautela non nocet</hi>: heerein you shall perceiue the Curtaine (though not fully) drawne, from before the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> that the world may for certaine see, that hee is not so beautifull, as many of our <hi>English</hi> (who so long haue doated on him) would make him to be, nor on the other side so terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that your <hi>Dutch</hi> neede to feare him, how grimme &amp; terrible soeuer he lookes vpō them. But your Excellence knoweth him (as we say) <hi>Intus &amp; in cute</hi>; &amp; can limne to the life better, then any penne in the world can decipher him, wherefore I vrge him no farther. I onely leaue it to the world to thinke of (since hee aymeth at the Monarchy of the <hi>West,</hi> euery thing els being to little for his Ambitiō (whose great Grand-sire the Earle of <hi>Halspurge</hi> was within these ninescore yeares, of as mean estate and revenue, as an ordinary knight of <hi>England,</hi>) how much I say, concernes it <hi>England,</hi> and your vnited <hi>Provinces,</hi> to hold fast each by either, which now by all meanes he laboureth to part and divide,
<pb facs="4"/>
not vnmindfull of a Matchivillian and old Maxime;<note place="margin">
         <hi>Divide, et Impera.</hi>
      </note> But I trust Almighty God (as hee hath already begun) will open the eyes of all Christian Kinges and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in time not onely to prie into, but ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually to oppose, these his immense and ambitious designes, which else in time may fall heauie vpon our children and posteritie, I end; humbly beseeching the King of Kings and Kingdomes, the Almighty Lord of Hoastes: Most High, Most Illustrious Princes, to protect the persons of your selues and children, with his grace to multiplie your Honors and Dignities, foure-fold to restore your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states, and after many yeares to crowne you in Heaven, with the Diademes of Glorie and endles happines.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Who is most devoted vnto your <hi>Highnesses,</hi> in all Loyall affection <hi>T. S.</hi> of <hi>Ʋ.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>