<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Honourable and Chi∣ualrous Knight, Sir Charles Blunt, Lord Mountioy, Knight of the most honourable or∣der of the Garter, and Captain of her Maiesties Sea∣fortresse, and towne of Portsmouth, I. K. wi∣sheth the accomplishment of all perfect ho∣nour and felicitie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116155_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11048</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21311</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116155</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Honourable and Chi∣ualrous Knight, Sir Charles Blunt, Lord Mountioy, Knight of the most honourable or∣der of the Garter, and Captain of her Maiesties Sea∣fortresse, and towne of Portsmouth, I. K. wi∣sheth the accomplishment of all perfect ho∣nour and felicitie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The courtiers academie : comprehending seuen seuerall dayes discourses: wherein be discussed, seuen noble and important arguments, worthy by all gentlemen to be perused. 1 Of beautie. 2 Of humane loue. 3 Of honour. 4 Of combate and single fight. 5 Of nobilitie. 6 Of riches. 7 Of precedence of letters or armes originally written in Italian by Count Haniball Romei, a gentleman of Ferrara, and translated into English by I.K</title>
                 <author>Romei, Annibale, conte</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 295, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Honourable and <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualrous Knight, Sir Charles Blunt, Lord</hi> Mountioy, Knight of the most honourable or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Garter, and Captain of her Maiesties Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortresse, and towne of Portsmouth, I. K. <hi>wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth the accomplishment of all perfect ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and felicitie.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Thinke it no waies requisite (right Honorable) to prosecute that ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worn methode of exaltation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting in an vnsauorie inculcation of their honour and praise, whose glorie by the shrill Trumpet of Fame, in euerie corner resounded by a blubbering and vnpolished penne, is both extenuated, it offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring further no small offence, to the modestie of that Noble eare or eye which vouchsafeth either the hearing or peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of the same. These worthie discourses written by no vnwoorthie Gentleman in Italian, grounded on the firme foundations of <hi>Aristotelian,</hi> and Platonical discipline, and yet accompanied with a liuely touch and feeling of these times, I thought no lesse woorthie to be offered to the view and censure, of noble and courteous constructions. Seeing some vnderstand not Italian at all, others pretend, beyond their knowledge, and those exquisite therein, do yet manie times meete with such ambiguities, as not willing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende too laboriously in that, which they onely retaine for
<pb facs="3"/>an ornament, giue no smal impediment to the beneficial im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression, of the subiect they reade and meditate vpon. And in that the first Author supposeth these discussions to haue fallen out in the Court of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> and in the noble assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of diuers Ladies &amp; knights, couertly herein expressing an excellent forme of Court-like exercise: I haue presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to intitle it, The Courtiers Academie. The onely interpretation of them, may in a man of my obscure humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie be deemed a singular presumptiō, except your honorable and gracious patronage both protect them, as also me theyr vnperfect translator. What defects soeuer in the same ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, proceeding either from my selfe or others, may gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciously bee sheltred vnder the noble wings of your woonted clemencie, to whose Lo. of my first labours, I haue ouer-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptuously offered dedication, no lesse vowing vnto the same, the propagation of all my future and faithfull en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships humble and thrise duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full poore affectionate,</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>