<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Hester, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116126_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20902</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7277</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116126</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Hester, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Sclopotarie of Iosephus Quercetanus, phisition. Or His booke containing the cure of wounds receiued by shot of gunne or such like engines of warre. Whereunto is added his spagericke antidotary of medicines against the aforesayd woundes. Published into English by Iohn Hester, practitioner in the said spagiricall arte</title>
                 <author>Du Chesne, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Ward, Roger</publisher>
                    <distributor>Sheldrake, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 95, 9 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is credibly recorded that one and the selfe same Citie of <hi>Ments</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> about one and the selfe same time found out and deliuered to posteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie two inuentions of rare and woonderfull impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, the Print and the Gunne: the former not so gratefull for the exceeding good, which thereby to euery man doth or may ensue: as the latter, for the excessiue hurt threatned to all men is vngratious, and yet both at this day in such request, as it were hard to say whether <hi>Mars</hi> his knights more va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue the one, then <hi>Mineruas</hi> schollers account of the other, so that as both haue for beginning their authors and founders, so for continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance they both want not their fautors and maintainers: neither is or can the priuiledge of the one be any way preiudice to the other, but either stands or falles in estimation, as sundrie men to either are seuerally conceited. Leauing therefore the print to the learned, who when and where they list, can deliuer you in good and sweete termes the vse, necessitie, and commendation thereof: I haue cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen with mine Author to speake a little of the other, or rather of the cure of such deadly wounds, as by the furious breath of so dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a deuise are procured to vs, and that not in smooth and curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous phrase, or picked eloquence, the roughnesse of the matter vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reiecting, any such soft handling, but in blunt and rude wordes, such as best sute and sort with the subiect it selfe. And here it is no part of my meaning with any curiositie to enquire whether the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie inuention of this churlish engine be fetcht from the Fryar, or from the diuell, or from a ioynt councell of them both, helde by consent in Vulcans fyery shoppe, I leaue that charge and the search thereof to my masters the Germaines, or to any man else, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> seekes out of so boisterous an inuention. To challenge any ciuil commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, it shall suffise me, in an English toonge to tel you a French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans tale, a tale, or rather a discourse as auailable to redresse the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries inferd by shot (where the stripe is not mortall) as the gun al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most was to inforce the harmes: wherein although diuers authors haue diuersly written, euery one according to the model of his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and experience, as of the french <hi>Laurentius Iubertus</hi> and <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellus:</hi> of the Italians <hi>Alfonsus Ferrius</hi> and <hi>Iohannes Vigo,</hi> of the English <hi>Thomas Gale</hi> and <hi>William Clovves,</hi> and sundry of
<pb facs="4"/>
other countries, as euery man hath founde leisure and aff<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>ion to trauell in a matter so needfull: some laying open the nature of the wounds, as well in concusion as dilaceration, some deliuering the malignant and venomous qualitie, proceeding from the mixture of the powder: others leauing both these, bestow their whole ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour in the discouery of such medicines, as to themselues or to such of whom they borowed their light, might any way seeme fittest. Among all which our <hi>Quercetanus,</hi> as it werem a middle course betweene both lightly goeth ouer the causes, and settles himselfe wholly vpon the cure: in which as his method is exquisite, so are his medicines singular: the same for the most part agreeing in sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance with those of Antiquitie, but differing much in preparation, for the which many condemne him, as straying from the old bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and knowne way, but these men forget that artes which whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lome were in their nonage, haue grown in processe to a more ripe and perfite middle age, and if they be not in time prouided for, may easily decline (as most things els do) and fall into a dotage, of such force and waight is and euer yet hath bene the due considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of time and circumstance, let vs shew our selues thankfull to such, as pittying the imperfections of others, seekes to furnish vs with better supplies. And as <hi>Quercetanus</hi> with his owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimen, and all that vnderstand the Latine tongue, hath herein de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued wonderfull commendation: so let me (gentle reader) that haue laid him as open to thee, as he is to any other, find thy friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acceptacion, and so much the rather because whatsoeuer I haue offended in the rudenesse of my translation, in the diligent prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the medicines, I heere promise to amende. Many things not without great charge and painefull labour, I haue already per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, to these and diuers other hard cures not impertinent, and if there be any thing else to make, that to this <hi>Spagiricall</hi> art doth any way belong, the learned, or practitioned shall finde me ready vpon reasonable consideration to performe all, and whatsoeuer my poore tallent can afford.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Iohn Hester.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>