<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable and Vertuous Lady, the Lady LVCY, Countesse of Bedford, and one of the Ladyes of her Maie∣sties Priuie-Chamber, A. S. wish∣eth all gifts of Honour, with eternall happinesse.</title>
           <author>Saul, Arthur</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116800_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11524</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21772</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116800</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable and Vertuous Lady, the Lady LVCY, Countesse of Bedford, and one of the Ladyes of her Maie∣sties Priuie-Chamber, A. S. wish∣eth all gifts of Honour, with eternall happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Saul, Arthur</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The famous game of chesse-play : truely discouered, and all doubts resolued; so that by reading this small booke thou shalt profit more then by the playing a thousand mates. An exercise full of delight; fit for princes, or any person of what qualitie soeuer. Newly published by A.S. Gent</title>
                 <author>Saul, Arthur</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 <publisher>Jackson, Roger.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Games and recreations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable and Vertuous Lady, the Lady LVCY, Countesse of <hi>Bedford,</hi> and one of the Ladyes of her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Priuie-Chamber, <hi>A. S.</hi> wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all gifts of Honour, with <hi>eternall happinesse.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT Honourable and vertuous Lady, hauing receiued many courtesies from your Honourable Father, late deceased; whose misse hath caused many to mourne for the losse of so Honourable and worthy a friend, and from your Honourable and worthy selfe, who in duty I doe euer reuerence, I haue in desire of shewing thankfulnes made bould to present to your Honour this small Booke, hauing no other gift to tender you; and knowing you euer to
<pb facs="4"/>
be a fauourer of all Vertue: Therefore may it please you to accept this Worke, being a Princely exercise, whose grace will be a chiefe ornament to the subiect I treat of: It is the discouery of all the secrets of <hi>Chesse-play,</hi> which of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther games is the worthiest that euer was deuised, and hath beene practised now <hi>2227.</hi> yeers. This therefore being so excellent a game, and so much estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of by the Nobility and Gentry of this our Kingdome, as also in all other Countryes in Christendome. This consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, J haue therefore imbouldned my selfe to referre the perusing hereof to your Honour, and my selfe to your good opinion, which I tender as that I esteeme most deere: euer remayning in all duety at</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours commaund Arthur Saul.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>