<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RJGHT Honorable, Sir Thomas Bennet Knight, Lord Maior of the Honorable Citie of London: a prosperous and peaceable Maioralty, with a plentifull encrease of all God his blessings and gra∣ces, for the effecting thereof, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Hooke, Christopher</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116953_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03582</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13703</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116953</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RJGHT Honorable, Sir Thomas Bennet Knight, Lord Maior of the Honorable Citie of London: a prosperous and peaceable Maioralty, with a plentifull encrease of all God his blessings and gra∣ces, for the effecting thereof, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Hooke, Christopher</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon preached in Paules Church in London : and pvblished for the instruction and consolation of all that are heauie harted, for the wofull time of God his generall visitation, both in the citie and in the countrie: and fit for the comfort of Gods children at all times</title>
                 <author>Hooke, Christopher</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>68 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RJGHT</hi> Honorable, Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> Bennet <hi>Knight, Lord Maior of</hi> the Honorable Citie of London: <hi>a prosperous and peaceable Maioralty,</hi> with a plentifull encrease of all <hi>God his blessings and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> for the effecting thereof, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He hope fayling mee of your honorable presence at the Crosse (for I vnderstand since it is not the custome for the Lord elect to come thither) I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ost humblie heere offer to your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ading (at your good leasure) that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> then you should haue heard:
<pb facs="3"/> which, if it answere not vnto your expectation, impute (I pray) the defect, partly to the want of the effect of the liuely voyce, which being great in other things, as appeareth by the speeche of <hi>Ctesiphon</hi> to the <hi>Rhodians,</hi> wondring at the Oration of <hi>Demosthenes,</hi> which he read vnto thē: <hi>Quanto magis admiraremini si audissetis ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum:</hi> By how much more would yee haue marueiled if you had heard himselfe, is in this of most impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, by the ordinance and blessing of God, who hath in his wisdome appoynted faith to bee of hearing. And fauorable pardon I beseech you all other the imperfections; I inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the vtmost of my power, to minister a word as of instruction, so especially of consolatiō, necessary for this woful time; &amp; it was accepted of by your honorable Predecessor: And as I haue bene enformed by the rest
<pb facs="3"/> of the audience then assembled, that which the weakenesse of my voice could not then performe to all, if by your Honorable acceptance, by this meanes it may be made the more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and so the more acceptable: I shall be much bounden to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, as a chiefe furtherer of my good meaning; If I haue not entred deepe into particulars, and searched sores so far as they needed, let it be excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of mine ignorance, vnacquainted with publicke affaires, as hauing alwaies liued a priuate life: and the absence of them to whome such a search especially belonged, whom bebinde the backe I thought it no part of discretion, to speake that which by a second report might be made more offensiue. For conclusiō, let mee beseech you, as I besought (in this sermon) your Predecessor, to double the care, to double the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage,
<pb facs="4"/> to double the zeale and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of all your Predecessors, and that not for the first quarter, or for a while, as it were, <hi>quinquennium Neronis,</hi> the first fiue yeeres of Nero, but during the time of your whole Maioraltie, euen to the last houre thereof: yea, during the whole time of your naturall life, which long may it be, wherein you are to liue by this most honorable entrance, in a perpetuall magistracie: and hee that is God among Gods, shall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance you from this temporall Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to an euerlasting Crowne of glorie, Amen. From my house in Deptford this xxxi. of October.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honorable Lordships in Christ Christopher Hooke</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>