<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the true-hearted British Readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116957_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11774</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22069</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116957</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the true-hearted British Readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Belgicke pismire : stinging the slothfull sleeper, and avvaking the diligent to fast, watch, pray; and worke out their owne temporall and eternall salvation with feare and trembling</title>
                 <author>Scott, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 100 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the true-hearted <hi>British</hi> Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>DEare Christian Country-men</hi>; I send out this <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise,</hi> in this doubtfull and dangerous time, not only to shew you the necessarie dependancie betwixt our Kingdome of <hi>Great Brittaine</hi> and the <hi>vnited Provinces,</hi> but also to comfort &amp; strengthen you against all feares, that are or may be interjected, by the subtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and malice of our Adversaries, or our owne mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceite or diffidence. For I do not finde the Enemie more busily practising to discourage vs, and to raise false fires to affright vs, then vvee our selues (as Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy persons vse) apt to misconster all things, and to imagine the worst, vpon the sight of euery shadow.</p>
   <p>And yet I must confesse, that, as there are many of those who labour to effect a division betwixt vs, and to this end, reviue old grudges, and provoke new quarrels; so the common current seemes to runne a contrarie course to that vvhich it had wont, (as tides have their ebbes) and the generall disposition of most men is wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering, as persons light of loue, who desire to shift their old approued friends for fresh Suiters, and prefer the change of an adulterous bed before the married. But I take this to be but a fit or throw of passion, which vvilbe easily cast off, vvith more hate and loathing, then it is now hotly pursued vvith longing, when some discontents are setled, and men on both sides are come to themselues againe. And for the State it selfe (I meane that maine Axeltree vvhereon our Kingdome
<pb facs="3"/>
turnes) I do assure my selfe, it is the same it was, firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grounded on former principles extracted from expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience on both sides; and that wee only move, vvhilst it remaines constant, though wee imagine otherwise; as simple passengers sayling swiftly by the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, suppose the trees, steeples, towers, and rockes to goe backward.</p>
   <p>Thus wee are distracted &amp; affrighted with our owne shadowes; ignorance makes vs Infidels: and vvhilst vvee see the face, but vnderstand not the intention and scope of some passages of State, vve and our friends waxe suspicious of each other; and that suspicion raiseth many rumors; and those rumors, though false, may beget and nourish a true and dangerous hate betwixt vs. My owne Countri-men haue tongues laxatiue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and Strangers are in their vvordes, as in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse other things, libertines. That vvhich I write may helpe to make both sides more confident of each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers loue, more retentiue and sparing of their cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures; at least it shall haue that effect in me, till I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the yssue, vvhich I hope vvill be happie.</p>
   <p>The bell is rung out, and I heare the sound and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it gives on both sides. Vpon the <hi>States</hi> side, men feare the passages and cariages of all things in <hi>England</hi>; and for this, are liberall and free in their discourses, making the feare greater then the cause requires. On the <hi>contrarie side,</hi> they are doubtfull or rather desperate, and therefore prosecute his Majestie with all kind of calumny. <hi>Pictures</hi> and <hi>Pasquills</hi> are day by day there vented thicke and threefold one vpon the necke of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, vvherein not only the <hi>King of Bohemia</hi> and the <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi> but our <hi>King</hi> also is basely traduced and abused. This comforts me, and assures me they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute
<pb facs="3"/>
none of their owne, and therefore hold his Majestie to be an enemie. Let this assure vs, that he is the same vve vvould haue him, howsoever for some respects of State, he seemes, (to weake eyes who behold things aloofe off) to be otherwise inclined. But, for my owne part, I comfort my selfe especially, and desire you would be comforted against all these suspicions, feares, and jealousies, out of two considerations; the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and mercie of our <hi>God,</hi> and the vvisedome and policie of our <hi>King.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>First, let vs consider wee haue a good and gracious God watching over vs, who vvill not suffer his Truth to be extinguished, but as he hath hitherto miraculous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preserved it, so still he will continue to do the same.</p>
   <p>And though, for our abuse and contempt of the <hi>Gospel</hi> (together vvith our barrennesse in good,<note place="margin">Psal. 89.32.33.</note> our fruitfulnesse in euill) <hi>he visite our transgressions with the rod, yet will he not vtterly take his mercie from vs, nor suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer his truth to faile.</hi> Let vs then rest in peace;<note place="margin">Psal. 121.4.</note>
      <hi>for hee that keepeth vs doth neither slumber nor sleepe.</hi> And let the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of those many former deliverances, which he hath wrought for vs, after an extraordinary and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous manner, assure vs of the like fatherly care and protection still, if wee faint not,<note place="margin">1. Sa. 17.34 35, 36, 37.</note> but faithfully and constantly depend vpon his mercifull promise.</p>
   <p>Secondly, consider the vvisedome of our <hi>Prince,</hi> which is so renowned, as for it he is gladly admitted a generall Arbitrator in forraine parts to determine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversies of State. Let this comfort vs, and assure vs, that God hath not given Him so much light for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, much lesse for evill. Let vs thinke, that since He was intertained with so much love, and so great signes of joy into this Kingdome, and hath beene served since
<pb facs="4"/>
with so much obedience, (farre more then a father could expect from his children) that Hee will so much seeme to neglect his owne honour and safety, or our lives and liberties, as to leave vs in the hands of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, or abase vs in the eyes of other Nations, to leade vs, or suffer vs to bee led into temporall or spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall captivity. Let vs thinke also he cannot forget ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 88. or the <hi>Powder-plot,</hi> (though now perhaps, it be vnseasonable to remember them) nor yet the many at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts and practises against His person, Crowne, Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and the Truth he professeth: nor that God will suffer him to sleepe securely in the armes of such, as He knowes watch onely for oportunity to destroy Him and His. Thinke also, that Nature will reviue and worke in Him, though it seemes to lye in a trance for the present time: and that He cannot but see, that it is impossible to love the Root, and hate the Branches; or to love the Fruit and Branches, and hate the Roote. Our love to his Royall Progenie must needes assure our love to Him; and the hate of others to Them, assure their inward hate against Him. And for such as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade otherwise, that our love to the Kings Children, and hate to the adverse party, proceedes either out of discontent, or a Puritanicall humour in vs leading to disloyalty,<note place="margin">Psal. 7.16.</note>
      <hi>Let their lyes turne vpon their owne pates</hi>; and let <hi>evill happen to them that thinke evill,</hi> and that would poyson and pervert all good purposes with practise.</p>
   <p>And though the subtill Enemies labour to breed je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousies betwixt Him and His, knowing it to be for their advantage, and the onely way to blemish the Gospel, and discredit good men, by breeding this suspicion, which may estrange and alienate the heart of the Prince from his people, and friends from each other; yet
<pb facs="4"/>
thinke it cannot sinke into his Majesties brest, that such <hi>servants,</hi> such <hi>subjects; Professors of the Gospel,</hi> should intend the least hurt to him, who is the <hi>Defender of their Faith.</hi> It is for <hi>Heathens, Turkes, Papists,</hi> to become Assassinates, Parricides, and bloody Traitors; and it is for Tyrants a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst these, to suspect their friends, brethren, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and therefore to cut them off at the motion of their Flatterers, <hi>Bashawes, Iesuites,</hi> and other tame tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher-Traytors. Good Princes, who are fathers of the Common-wealth, cannot do thus, will not doe thus; whilst in themselves they see no cause of their subjects hate; or if they see any, can finde a readier way by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, to remove the cause, and prevent the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, then by seconding one evill with another, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the overthrow of all, and to make the disease desperate, by endevouring a contrarie cure; or the flame rise higher, by casting in fresh fuell, or quenching it with oyle.</p>
   <p>Thinke also it is our Enemies plot, to stirre vp our heady and hastie humors, and to cause the Prince to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content his best and truest subjects; and, if it were possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by all meanes to provoke them to impatience and resistance, that so themselves might be armed in His co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourable defence, and have occasion also to bring in other borrowed Ayde vnder the same pretence, but with assurance of His and all our ruines in the yssue; as hath ever happened to that vnfortunate State where they haue become <hi>Sticklers.</hi> But thinke his Majestie cannot but see this aswell as vvee and much better; and therefore be you quiet, that their intents and projects may be frustrate.</p>
   <p>Finally, thinke now your <hi>King</hi> is making of his owne <hi>Monument,</hi> vvriting his owne <hi>Chronicle</hi>; both
<pb facs="5"/>
which are raised and composed by deedes, and not wordes: and assure your selves, <hi>Hee</hi> that can speake and write so wel, will never so farre contradict his owne vvordes with repugnant actions, as thereby to race his Armes, to staine the honour he was borne vnto, and vvhich hee hath made good and bettered hitherto, by high and holy enterprizes of act and <hi>admonition</hi> against <hi>Rome</hi>: but thinke therefore, that all this time, Hee is acting his part in the eye of the whole vvorld; that he is working his Master-piece in the publique market, and trying his exact skill in <hi>King-craft</hi> vvith the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Statists</hi> in Christendome; that is, vvith <hi>Rome, Spaine, Austria, Italy, Machiauel,</hi> and the extracted strength and quintessence of all these, the <hi>Iesuites.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And therefore thinke, howsoever for the present he carries himselfe, and seemes to be led by some of that side, yet in the end, the Lyon may awake, breake loose and teare his keeper; or else leade, vvhilst he seemes to be led; and then the vvorld shall see, that neither the opinion of his sinceritie in the <hi>Truth,</hi> nor of his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matchable wisedome and policie, were vaine mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, but that our harmelesse <hi>David</hi> can vse honest <hi>Hushai</hi> to ouerthrow their craftie <hi>Achitophel.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Then the <hi>Church</hi> shall triumph and be comforted, the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> flourish, His <hi>honor</hi> shal be eternized; neither shall you repent of your patience, nor I of my perswasion to this end; vvherein I rest, vvith an assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Gods mercy herein, and that wee shall see our desire vpon our Enemies.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>To the half-hearted <hi>English-Spanish</hi> Reader:</head>
      <p>DEsiring him, if he finds me too tart in his taste a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst that Nation, and (as he thinks) too much to
<pb facs="5"/>
neglect their honors in some passages, that he would consider there are three things mouing me to this; any of which when they come in my vvay; may force me to strike them vvith my tongue, since I cannot reach them vvith my hand.</p>
      <p n="2">2. The first is the <hi>Libertie of the Gospel,</hi> to vvhose free passage they are open and profest enemies, altering Religion for the worst where they conquer, taking part vvith the Serpent against the Seed of the woman, and desiring to bee knowne Catholique persecutors of all true <hi>Christians.</hi>
      </p>
      <p n="2">2. The second is the <hi>Libertie of life,</hi> that by the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of nature each Nation hath and seekes to preserue vnder their owne rules; vvhich likewise the <hi>Spaniard</hi> labors to take from humane societie, and to prescribe Lawes to all Christendome. Which ambitious mood hath possest them euer since that Catholique title was confer'd vpon them by that Sea,<note place="margin">Luke. 4.6.</note> vvho next and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly vnder Satan, hath the disposition of all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the Earth at his pleasure.</p>
      <p n="3">3. The third is the bloody, inhumane, and vnchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian dealing vvith the Kings Children, even when they pretend to desire affinitie vvith that House, and that dallying about restitution of wrongs, tossing the ball from one to another; and laughing in their sleeues, that their dissimulation hath deluded our plaine mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and possest them of so rich a Country, vvhich is a fit roade to invade all Christendome. For now they haue a high vvay, or thorow-fare to convey their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies commodiously from <hi>Flanders</hi> to <hi>Austria</hi> all the way in their owne Command. But vvhome have they not thus delt vvithall for their owne advantages, if former presidents could make men beware of their courses?</p>
      <p>
         <pb facs="6"/>I do protest, sauing these quarrels, I beare nor spleene nor malice to any <hi>Spaniard</hi> living, much lesse to the Nation, whome (these things excepted) I honor as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits me: but when any of these considerations come crosse my thoughts, they stir vp a salt humor, vvhich fals from my eyes into my inke, and turnes it more blacke and bitter, and more sharpe vvithall then the Gall and Coperas vvhich gaue it the first tincture; and this makes my stile harsh, when I touch vpō that string. No other good can cause me to forget these euils, or perswade me to take those for my friends who are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to these, or affoord them good words, who loade these vvith opprobrious scoffes and open injuries. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice in them begets indignation in others, and no man that doth euill, can euer hope to heare well from any but Cowards, or flatrerers.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>To the indifferent Dutch Readers.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>I</hi> Assure them and all the world, these three considerations aforementioned, worke contrarie effects in me towards them. I loue them first for Religions sake, they being a hiding place for the pore persecuted members of Christ hunted out of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and other distressed Countries. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, being become a Bulwarke for the libertie of all Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome at this present. Thirdly, being a happie Sanctuarie for the Kings Children, when very few <hi>Christian Princes</hi> durst professe themselues their friends.</p>
      <p>Men may say, their owne respects worke these effects, and I willingly grant, that perhaps, they are involved together. And what Nation is there, or what State; nay, what man, that in all friendship lookes not inward and homeward with one eye? when I thinke vpon these things, I cannot but loue them, and speake well of them; nor can particular injuries (which
<pb facs="6"/>
may be raised from their and our enemies, intermixt with them,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Ios. 23.13.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>as pricks in their sides and thornes in their eyes</hi>) nor generall wrongs in any other kinde though profest and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified, worke me so much to hate and diuision, (though they may tempt me shrewdly) as these to loue and vnion.</p>
      <p>Yet because I praise this <hi>Belgicke</hi> friend, as I thinke, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily in the body of the booke, I must in the Preface admonish him of such faults as I heare or see, that he may mend them (if there be cause) in the beginning, and so be truly worthy of those praises I giue him, and thinke he deserues in the course of this Treatise. He is a foole that cannot see his friends faults as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as his perfections; and he is a flatterer that (if he sees them) will not be his friends glasse for amendement to dresse him to Glorie and perfection. Let him neuer take me for a friend, that loves not this plainenesse: if for this he proues my foe, I haue lost nothing, but saued much I might haue lost, had I ventured any thing in so light, weake, and vnbalast a bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome.</p>
      <p n="1">1. First therefore they say, <hi>Children</hi> are not generally there well educated, hauing too much libertie allowed them, so that they soone learne to forget that duty to their <hi>Parents,</hi> which they were neuer taught to remember.</p>
      <p n="2">2. Secondly, they say, <hi>frugality</hi> makes men neglect <hi>pietie,</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>1. Tim. 6.5.6. Mar. 11.15</hi>
         </note> and the <hi>gaine of vngodlinesse</hi> makes marchandize of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; so that <hi>buyers and sellers, and spirituall theeues possesse the temple;</hi> I meane the labor proper to sixe dayes, makes a sacrilegious vsurpation and horrible profanation of that <hi>Rest</hi> proper to the <hi>Seuenth;</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>Exod. 20.9.10.</hi>
         </note> and many for feare of see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Iewes, become Gentiles.</p>
      <p n="3">3. Thirdly, they say, the reuerend Ministers are respected but not rewarded according to their labors and merits. The <hi>oxe is muzled,</hi> &amp; in the meane time the <hi>Asse</hi> and <hi>Mule</hi> eate vp his provender in prodigality, ryot, and euery excesse.<note place="margin">
            <hi>1. Cor. 9.9.10.</hi>
         </note>
      </p>
      <p n="4">
         <pb facs="7"/>4. Fourthly, your profest Enemies taxe you with vnthanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, and make this a just motiue to prouoke his Majestie to leaue you.</p>
      <p>They chalenge you of ingratitude to his <hi>Majesty,</hi> to the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish Nation,</hi> to the <hi>Souldier.</hi> I know not whether these be truthes or slaunders, I tell you what I heare and reade in their writings. If they say true, amend it, if they come neere the truth,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Ingratum dixetis, &amp; omnia dixeris. Senec.</hi>
         </note> avoyd so monstrous a shadow as ingratitude: remember how much <hi>English</hi> blood hath beene spilt to saue yours; this cannot be recompenced without extraordinarie respects; for <hi>Mony</hi> payes some, <hi>Honor</hi> others, <hi>Love</hi> all. Nor is there a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whose loue hath beene, or is more vsefull to your State, nor that is more worthie of it then the <hi>British.</hi> You neither disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, disprofit or weaken your selues by this admittance and conjunction, but should euery way reape advantage by it. Now thus you haue heard what others thinke and say, for my owne opinion, if you thinke it woorth any thing, you may reade it in that which followeth.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>