<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116286_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11187</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21454</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116286</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The dialogues of William Richworth or The iudgmend [sic] of common sense in the choise of religion</title>
                 <author>Rushworth, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mestais, Jean</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Paris</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 133, 136-582 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>M.r <hi>William Richworth</hi> borne in <hi>Lincolneshire</hi> studied in the English College at <hi>Doway,</hi> there was made Priest, and afterwards discharged the place and office of <hi>Prefect</hi> with much commendation, all which time he was knowne by the name of Charles Rosse. Comming into England he liued in diuers places with good esteeme vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the yeare <hi>1637</hi> in which he dyed. He was a man curious in <hi>Diuinitie, Controuersies, Mathematikes,</hi> and <hi>Physicke,</hi> but cheefely delighted in <hi>Mathematickes,</hi> and by the name of Robinson entertained correspondence with the learned <hi>Oughtred.</hi> He affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the rigor of mathematicall discourse euen in his controuersies, as you may
<pb facs="3"/>
perceiue by this worke, and thought no man truly learned but who aymed to doe the like. These Dialogues he framed so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me yeares agone, and shewed them to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall friends of his, which finding they gaue content to diuers iudicious persons, he intended to enlarge and publish thē, but hindered by some occasions so that he could not finish and perfect them before his death, he bequeathed his papers and this charge to a friend, to whom he had often communicated his designe. Here now you haue them deuided into three parts, The first containing and declaring how, and what points of controuersies are of necessitie, The second shewing that scripture alone is not a fitt iudge nor able of it self to decide controuersies in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, The third and last demonstrate's an euident and infalible meanes of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining and deciding all questiōs and disputs of faith and Religion, which God grant may be to your profit.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>