<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Mas∣culine Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116956_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20499</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6908</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116956</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Mas∣culine Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discourse of the married and single life : Wherein, by discovering the misery of the one, is plainely declared the felicity of the other</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Jonas (Jonah)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 115, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culine Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Euer was there any thing so perfectly good, that by traducing tongues hath not been made to seeme euill, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath there any thing been so absolutely euill, that either by co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourable speeches, or faire pretences may not be made to seeme good.</p>
   <p>Some men apply themselues to reading onely, to procure matter of contradiction, that what others de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, they would disproue, and what by others is disallowed, shall by them be highly commended. But such as are wise, haue learned to su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spend their iudgements in, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that which either pleaseth or displeaseth them, vntill they haue laid such infallible grounds, as may
<pb facs="3"/>iustly cleere them from al suspition, either of folly for approuing that which in it selfe is knowne to be ill, or of maliciousnesse, for disprouing that, the goodnesse whereof. (it is likely) they neuer vnderstood. The Authors intent in this ensuing dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, is not to breede in mens minds a dislike of that which in it selfe is good, both in respect of him that ordained it, as also the ends wherefore it was ordained, which are most good. But since his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course is of Marriage, he is to be conceiued either as a detector of the miseries thereof, proceeding rather from the persons, then the thing it selfe, or as a director to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts thereof; which chiefly consist in such qualities and dispositions, as are directly contrary to such as here be mentioned. As therefore we haue iust occasion to loue them that shew vs a good way, and direct
<pb facs="3"/>vs in it: so are we not to despise them that by detecting vnto vs the euill way, teach vs to auoide it.</p>
   <p>The differences that are betwixt the married and the single life, as there was neuer any man so wise as to know them all, so neuer as yet hath any man discouered them all, which makes it a poynt of great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty for a man to know which is the better, vntill hee haue tasted both; and then shall he only learne, that the inferiors of the one doe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exceede the inconueniences of the other.</p>
   <p>If we should take this Authors o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, who will perhaps be iudged partiall, hauing neuer tried both, he doth certainly prefer the single before the double, and in so doing, will also giue vs some reason why he may be beleeued, because the actions of many of the best men haue wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nessed the truth of that which he
<pb facs="4"/>maintaineth; and so much the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther also, because there are many reasons why that should be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before this, &amp; but one only, why this should be preferred before that.</p>
   <p>The temptations of the single life, are subiect to perswade a man to marry; the incumbrances of the married life, to disswade a man therefrom. Let vs consider of that happinesse wherein man liued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be inioyed the company of a woman, and so behold that miserie wherein he is inwrapped since the time he partaked therein; and it will be an argument sufficient to induce a man to approoue that, which in it selfe was good, rather than of that which in it selfe was the onely cause of the deprauation of that onely good. Let but a man consider the many qualities, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he that will be married must bee burthened, and those few
<pb facs="4"/>that will serue for the single life, and he shall be rather induced to chuse that whereunto nature of her selfe hath fitted him, one only being wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, than desire that whereunto there is so much requisite, as it is not almost possible for a man to attaine in the whole course of his life. He that would liue without a wife, needs striue for no other qualitie, but Chastitie, all other will offer themselues; he need only entertaine her. But he that will be married, must measure both his words and his actions according to the disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his wife; he must both be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in looking to her, that her steps goe not awry, and he must be also carefull to looke to himselfe, lest he incurre the suspition of Ielousie.</p>
   <p>The subiections, that hee must yeeld both to her and her kindred, if he be any thing imperious (and so he will if he be not a naturall) are most
<pb facs="5"/>intolerable: the censures that hee must vndergoe, and the hard taxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that will be imposed vpon him, euen for his priuatest speeches, will, if he come to know them, make him wish he had neuer felt them.</p>
   <p>Let a man also consider the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, wherewith women are indued, which for the most part are opposite to those of men: as, her wantonnesse, to his sobrietie; her frowardnesse, to his meekenesse; her stubbornnesse, to his patience; her pride, to his humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie; her lightnesse, to his grauitie; her disliking, to that which he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth; her coueting of which he denieth: wherein they iustly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble the shadow of a mans body, which if a man pursue, it will runne from him; if he goe away, it will follow him: this is all the comfort that a man in his choyce can haue, that perhaps it may be his fortune, <hi>inter malos, non habere pessima:</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>amongst many that are euill, not to light of that which is worst of all: but as this Prouerbe is, that amongst blinde men, hee is counted happie that hath but one eye; so in a world of miseries and inconueniences, he is not the worst, whose fortune it is, either to light of the fairest, or to beare the easiest. Many haue thought it impossible to know which is the worst qualitie of a woman; some haue made it a great question, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were better for a man to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie a shrew, or a sheepe, but hardly can it be resolued. If the former, then is shee Tyrannicall; and the greatest cruelty, is the crueltie of a woman; if the latter, then can she not be endured: for there is no bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then more grieuous than the folly of a woman. Let a man but weight the infidelity of women, and that in matters of greatest importance, and then let him iudge what secure trust
<pb facs="6"/>can be reposed in them, by whom he shall vnder stand, not onely Townes and Citties, but also Kingdomes and Dominions haue been vtterly rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, either by their treacherous practices, or for the satisfying of their ambitious humours; so that when there shall be nothing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straine them, but the feare of the Husbands displeasure, which, when occasion is offered, is as likely to change the mischiefes of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, as the breath of a man to refell the fury of the winde; or the sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of a straw to daunt the heart of a Lyon; I cannot see by what means he can auoide or escape destruction, that violently casteth himselfe vpon the edge of her ouer-sharpe patience.</p>
   <p>Let a man but further consider the great dissiculty that consisteth in the bringing vp of Children, if he haue them; the infinite discomfort, if he haue them not. For their bringing
<pb facs="6"/>vp, we see by daily experience, that in their tender yeeres, they are either by too much lenity made to become dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute, and effeminately prone to all manner of vice, seeing that indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence is the onely bellowes to Kindle the sparke of a corrupt nature; or else by ouer-much seuerity they are made vnapt and vncapeable of any thing that is good; and so the expectation of the chiefest happinesse, is turned into the fruition of the greatest euill: and he that will diligently obserue, shall finde, that children haue by the bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of their mothers disposition, bin made the only instrument of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers discontentment: yea, and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time the author of their destruction.</p>
   <p>The husband is, by the very insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of marridge, ordained to be the head; and the head was made to rule and gouerne the body. Now, the difficulty that is incident to this regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is such, and so great, that few
<pb facs="7"/>men take pleasure in possessing it, none at all performe it in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner they should; the greatest wisdome that herein is required, consisteth in the counselling and discouery, as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion serueth, of his passions, and in the right applying of his affections, according to the condition of his wiues humor. If he loue her too much, then will she condemne him: for plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty alwaies breeds lothsomnes. If he do not manifest his loue in that sort that she desireth or expecteth, then she pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently imagineth, that he bestoweth it some-where else; and so being pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest of that Ielousie, there is no misery that will not follow of it. If he let her haue her will, souerainety is straight turned into Tyranny: If he abridge her, she then falls into a thousand in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences. If he be ready to obey her commandements, then will she be most importunate. If he deny her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest, though it be neuer so vnreaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable,
<pb facs="7"/>then is he presently iudged vnkinde and hard-hearted.</p>
   <p>Many men ouer-venturous, will put their hands into the Hiues for hony; but at the last they are stung with Waspes; and no maruaile is it, where there are more Wasps thā Bees. Yet the stings of a thousand Waspes do not so wound, as the tongue of one woman: for of the one there be many remedies; the other remaineth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies incurable: for diseases that be mortall, men should be carefull to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, because there remaineth no hope to cure them: and such are they that are herein mentioned, namely, the diseases of marriage, the which when men study to cure, the remedy doth oft-times proue worse, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them more danger, then the euil it selfe was likely to haue done; which as it is not vnknown to any that haue obserued the vsuall proceedings of the world, so haue they felt the smart
<pb facs="8"/>thereof, whose fortune it hath been to partake therein. He therefore that would know the difference betwixt the married, and the single life, shall neither finde the one to be absolute good, nor the other to be altogether euill: but herein he shall see the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence chiefely to consist, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences of the one may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medied when a man wil, the miseries of the other remaine vncurable; which as they are many, so it is not possible to recken them vp: some of them in this discourse are touched, the most remaine discouered, he that plungeth not into all, shall be sure to leape into some; the benefit he shall get by reading of this, is, that though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps hee cannot bee forewarned by wisdome to preuent them, yet he may be forewarned with patience to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure them; which is the onely drift which herein is aymed at.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>