<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Gentlemen Readers.</title>
           <author>Chettle, Henrie</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116845_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18595</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5123</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116845</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Gentlemen Readers.</title>
                 <author>Chettle, Henrie</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Kind-harts dreame : Conteining fiue apparitions, vvith their inuectiues against abuses raigning. Deliuered by seuerall ghosts vnto him to be publisht, after Piers Penilesse post had refused the carriage. Inuita inuidiæ. by H.C</title>
                 <author>Chettle, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Wright, William 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 <publisher>Danter, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Gentlemen Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath beene a custome Gentle men (in my mind commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able) among former Authors (whose workes are no lesse beautified with eloquente phrase, than garnished with excellent example) to begin an exordium to the Readers of their time, much more conuenient I take it, should the writers in these da<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es (wherein that grauitie of enditing by the elder excercised, is not obseru'd, nor that modest decorum kept, which they continued) submit their labours to the fauourable censures of their learned ouerseers. For seeing nothing can be said, that hath not been before said, the singularitie of some mens conceits, (otherwayes exellent well deseruing) are no more to be soothed, than the peremptorie posies of two very sufficient Translators commended. To come in print is not to seeke praise, but to craue pardon: I am vrgd to the one; and bold to begge
<pb facs="3"/>
the other, he that offende<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> being forst, is more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusable than the wilfull faultie, though both be guilty, there is difference in the guilt. To ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue custome, and auoid as I may cauill, oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing your fauors against my feare, Ile shew reason for my present writing, and after proceed to sue for pardon. About three moneths since died M. <hi>Robert Greene,</hi> leauing many papers in sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Booke sellers hands, among other his Groats<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth of wit, in which a letter written to diuers play-makers, is offensiuely by one or two of them taken, and because on the dead they cannot be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenged, they wilfully forge in their conceites a liuing Author: and after tossing it two and fro, no remedy, but it must light on me. How I haue all the time of my conuersing in printing hindred the bitter inueying against schollers, it hath been very well knowne, and how in that I dealt I can sufficiently prooue. With neither of them that take offence was I acquainted, and with one of them I care not if I neuer be: The other, whome at that time I did not so much spare, as since I wish I had, for that as I haue moderated the heate of liuing writers, and might haue vsde my owne discretion (especially in such a case) the Author beeing dead, that I did not, I am as
<pb facs="3"/>
sory, as if the originall fault had beene my fault, because my selfe haue seene his demeanor no lesse ciuill than he exelent in the qualitie he professes: Besides, diuers of worship haue reported, his vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightnes of dealing, which argues his honesty, and his facetious grace in writting, that aprooues his Art. For the first, whose learning I reuerenee, and at the perusing of <hi>Greenes</hi> Booke, stroke out what then in conscience I thought he in some dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure writ: or had it beene true, yet to publish it, was intollerable: him I would wish to vse me no worse than I deserue. I had onely in the copy this share, it was il written, as sometime <hi>Greenes</hi> hand was none of the best, licensd it must be, ere it could bee printed which could neuer be if it might not be read. To be breife I writ it ouer, and as neare as I could, followed the copy, onely in that letter I put something out, but in the whole booke not a worde in, for I protest it was all <hi>Greenes,</hi> not mine nor Maister <hi>Nashes,</hi> as some vniustly haue affirmed. Neither was he the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an Epistle to the second part of Gerileon, though by the workemans error T. N. were set to the end: that I confesse to be mine, and repent it not.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>Thus Gentlemen, hauing noted the priuate cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, that made me nominate my selfe in print; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aswell to purge Master <hi>Nashe</hi> of that he did not, as to iustifie what I did, and withall to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme what <hi>M. Greene</hi> did: I beseech yee accept the publike cause, which is both the desire of your delight, and common benefite: for though the toye bee shadowed vnder the Title of <hi>Kind-hearts Dreame,</hi> it discouers the false hearts of diuers that wake to commit mischiefe. Had not the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer reasons been, it had come forth without a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and then shuld I haue had no cause to feare offending, or reason to sue for fauour. Now am I in doubt of the one, though I hope of the other; which if I obtaine, you shall-bind me hereafter to bee silent, till I can present yee <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> some thing more acceptable.</p>
   <signed>Henrie Chettle.</signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>