<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE GENTLE
and discreet Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116574_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17081</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3958</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116574</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE GENTLE
and discreet Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discourse of ciuill life : containing the ethike part of morall philosophie. Fit for the instructing of a gentleman in the course of a vertuous life. By Lod: Br</title>
                 <author>Bryskett, Lodowick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 103, 106-279, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE GENTLE
and discreet Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight well saith the Wise man, that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
new vnder the Sunne; and further, that
there is no end of writing books. For howsoeuer
in a generalitie the subiect of any knowledge be
declared; yet the particulars that may be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
out of the same, be so many, as new matter may be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
out of the same to write thereof againe: so great is the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie
of mans vnderstanding able to attaine further know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
then any reading can affoord him. And therefore <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race</hi>
also affirmeth, that it is hard to treate of any subiect that
hath not bene formerly handled by some other. Yet do we see
dayly men seeke, partly by new additions, and partly with or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments
of stile, to out-go those that haue gone before them:
which haply some atchieue, but many moe rest farre behind.
This hath bred the infinitenesse of bookes, which hath intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced
the distinction of good from bad, vsed in best Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weales,
to prohibite such as corrupt manners, and to giue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation
to the good. For that the simpler sort by the former
drinke their bane in steed of medicine, and in lieu of truth
(the proper obiect of mans vnderstanding) they introduce
falshood decked in truths ornaments, to delude the vnheedful
Reader. Whereas on the other side, the benefite which we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
by the reading of good books being exceeding great, they
deserue commendation that offer their endeuours to the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiting
of others with books of better matter. Which hath made
me resolue to present vnto thy view this discourse of Morall
Philosophie, tending to the wel ordering and composing of thy
<pb facs="4"/>
mind, that through the knowledge and exercise of the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues
therein expressed, thou mayst frame thy selfe the better to
attaine to that further perfection which the profession of a
Christian requireth; and that euerlasting felicitie, which, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted
with Gods grace (neuer refused to them that humbly
and sincerely call for the same) thou mayst assuredly purchase.
As my meaning herein is thy good chiefly: so let thy fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
censure thankfully acknowledge my labor and goodwil,
which may moue me to impart after vnto thee another trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
of the Politike part of Morall Philosophie, which I haue
likewise prepared to follow this, if I shall find the fauourable
acceptation hereof such as may encourage me thereunto. The
booke written first for my priuate exercise, and meant to be
imparted to that honorable personage, <hi>qui nobis haec otia
fecit,</hi> hath long layne by me, as not meaning (he being gone)
to communicate the same to others. But partly through the
perswasion of friends, and partly by a regard not to burie that
which might profit many, I haue bin drawne to consent to the
publishing thereof. Gather out of it what good thou canst: and
whatsoeuer thou mayst find therein vnperfect or defectiue,
impute charitably to my insufficiencie and weaknesse; and let
not small faults blemish my trauell and desire to benefite thee.</p>
   <p>But say to thy selfe with that worthy bright light
of our age <hi>Sir Philip Sidney, Let vs loue men
for the good is in them, and not
hate them for their euill.</hi>
Farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>