<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Diuine Poem.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116485_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16740</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3647</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116485</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Diuine Poem.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Divine considerations of the soule : concerning the excellencie of God, and the vilenesse of man. Verie necessarie and profitable for euerie true Christian seriously looke into. By N.B. G</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Tapp (Tap), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 9, 154, 5, 6 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>A Diuine Poem.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>O Lord that knewst me ere that I was knowne,</l>
      <l>And sawst the cloath before the thred was spunne</l>
      <l>And framd'st the substance, ere the thought was growne</l>
      <l>From which my being in this world begunne:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Oh glorious God, that onely of thy grace:</l>
      <l>Didst all and onely to thy seruice make me:</l>
      <l>and hauing giuen me heere an earthly place:</l>
      <l>Vnto the Guard of thy faire grace dist take me.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb n="2" facs="8"/>
      <l>Of all pure bright, and euer-seeing eye:</l>
      <l>That seest the secret thoughts of euerie heart,</l>
      <l>Before whose presence doth apparantlie,</l>
      <l>Heauen, earth, Sea, Hell, in all and euerie part.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>In wisdome more O then wit can comprehend!</l>
      <l>That mak'st and iudgest, gouern'st euerie thing▪</l>
      <l>power of all powers, on whome all powers attend,</l>
      <l>Spring of all grace from whence all glories spring</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb n="3" facs="8"/>
      <l>From that high, holy, heauenly throane of thine:</l>
      <l>Where mercy liues to giue thy glorie grace.</l>
      <l>Looke downe a little on this soule of mine,</l>
      <l>That vnto thee complaines her heauie cace.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Oh sweetest sweete of my soules purest sence,</l>
      <l>That in thy mercie, madst me first a creature!</l>
      <l>And in the truth of loues intelligence,</l>
      <l>The neerest image to thy heauenly Nature.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb n="4" facs="9"/>
      <l>And hauing framde me to thy fauours eye,</l>
      <l>Didst with thy finger fairely write me out,</l>
      <l>In holy writ of heauenly Misterie,</l>
      <l>How I should bring a blessed life about.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Forbidding onely what might be my harme,</l>
      <l>Commaunding onely what might doe me good:</l>
      <l>preseruing me by thy Almigtie arme</l>
      <l>and feeding me with a celestiall foode.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb n="5" facs="9"/>
      <l>Thou madst the ayre to feede the life of nature,</l>
      <l>That I might see how weake a thing it is▪</l>
      <l>The earth, the labour of the sinfull creature,</l>
      <l>Which beares no fruite but onely by thy blisse.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Thou madst the water but to clense or coole,</l>
      <l>Or serue thy creatures in their sundrie vse:</l>
      <l>That carefull wit, might reason not befoole</l>
      <l>In vsing nature to the soules abuse.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb n="6" facs="10"/>
      <l>The fire thou madst to c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eere the chilling colde,</l>
      <l>With a reuiuing heate of natures ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>de;</l>
      <l>That reason might in natures ruine holde</l>
      <l>How farre that Force might stand the life instead.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Thus vnder heauen, thou madst these Elements</l>
      <l>To maintaine all those creatures thou hast made,</l>
      <l>But so, that nature with her ornaments</l>
      <l>shall haue a time to flourish, or to fade</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb n="7" facs="10"/>
      <l>But that same heauenly fire that doth enflame</l>
      <l>The heart and soule with a continuall heate:</l>
      <l>Whose loue doth liue but in thy holy name,</l>
      <l>Where faith doth mercy but for grace intreate.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Where that did kindle, or that Cole to finde,</l>
      <l>Or smallest peice or sparckle of the same:</l>
      <l>I found the eye of nature was too blinde,</l>
      <l>To finde the sence, or whence thee secret came.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb n="8" facs="11"/>
      <l>Till by the inspiration of that grace,</l>
      <l>That to thy seruants doth thy goodnesse showe:</l>
      <l>I found thy loue the euer liuing place,</l>
      <l>From whence the substance of this sweete doth flowe</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And when I saw within this soule of mine,</l>
      <l>How farre thy loue exceedes the life of nature,</l>
      <l>and natures life, but in that loue of thine,</l>
      <l>Which is the being of each blessed creature:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb n="9" facs="11"/>
      <l>Then I beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n to finde the foile of sinne,</l>
      <l>And onely long'd to liue in mercies grace,</l>
      <l>and hate the world, that doth their hel begin,</l>
      <l>That doe not long to see thy heauenly face.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And thus perplexed in that passions griefe:</l>
      <l>That hath no ease but in thy mercies eye</l>
      <l>To thee that art the faithfull soules releife</l>
      <l>haue I laide open all my misery:</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>