<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣norable Sir Christopher Hatton, Knight of the most noble Order, and Lord Chancellor of England: Richard Ihones Printer, wisheth long life, with encrease of happinesse.</title>
           <author>Jones, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116992_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11862</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22163</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116992</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣norable Sir Christopher Hatton, Knight of the most noble Order, and Lord Chancellor of England: Richard Ihones Printer, wisheth long life, with encrease of happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Jones, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The booke of honor and armes</title>
                 <author>Jones, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 104, 75, 1 page, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Games and recreations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Sir Christopher Hatton, Knight of the most noble Order, and Lord Chancellor of England: <hi>Richard Ihones</hi> Printer, wisheth long life, with encrease of happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold testimonies of your loue both vnto Honor and Armes, haue induced me to think the first sight of this small booke doth of right belong vnto your Lordship, being by the due degrees of vertue as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended to that place, which among others in this Realme, is (and long hath been) reputed most honorable. To your L. therefore I humblie dedicate the same, as vnto him, that by censure of our Soueraigne, with the applause of people, hath in hand the consideration of actions ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteining to equitie, Honor and Iustice. The
<pb facs="4"/>
propertie of which vertue (as <hi>Cicero</hi> saith) is to foresee that no violence be offered, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie by him that with iniurie is thereunto prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: and that things common should bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlie vsed, and priuate things priuatlie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed. By which rule appeareth, that vertue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth iust reuenge, and admitteth the defence of propertie and right. But for that your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship hath been as well an actor in Armes, as a knower of what is due to Honor, I omit to say more, either of the one or the other: beseeching your good Lordship to pardon my boldnesse, and take in acceptable wise the entent of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, who both by election and obligation ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth himself yours.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships euer to commaund: <hi>Richard Ihones.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>