<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE CHARLES, the hopefull Prince of Great Brittaine, France and Ireland, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Scot, Patrick</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116871_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11619</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21860</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116871</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE CHARLES, the hopefull Prince of Great Brittaine, France and Ireland, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Scot, Patrick</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A table-booke for princes : Containing short remembrances for the gouernment of themselues and their empire. Wherein also respectiuely the seuerall members of state, and all sorts of subiects, may finde matter worthy their obseruation. By Patricke Scot, Esquire</title>
                 <author>Scot, Patrick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Bernard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 113, 110-215, 5 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE CHARLES, the hopefull Prince <hi>of Great Brittaine, France and Ireland, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F PHILLIP of <hi>Macedon</hi> did yeelde no lesse thankes to his false gods, that his Sonne <hi>Alexander</hi> was borne in the time of <hi>Aristotle,</hi> then in blessing him with so hopefull a child: your Highnesse hath iust cause to ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate the Name of the true God, that you are the Sonne and Heire of a Mightie King, and of a Religious, Wise, and Learned Father, who (besides the appointing of godly and learned Tutors) in his owne
<pb facs="3"/> person, (exceeding <hi>Aristotle</hi> both in the Theoricke and Practicke of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment) hath so seasoned your Highnesse tender yeares, with the (Giliadlike) odoriferous Balme of Diuine and Morall instructions, as the sweete perfume thereof hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready rauished the hearts of all loyall Subiects, with the extreamitie of ioy; and one day (by Gods Grace) will make knowne to the World, the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse you haue in your birth-right, but the perfection of happinesse in such a Father, who hath so emptyed the profound Ocean of Diuine and Humane learning, that (except bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from the rich Treasure of his store, nothing that belongs to the true institution of young <hi>Alexander,</hi> can either be found or added.</p>
   <p>Wherefore SIR, I humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech your Highnesse to censure these lame Essaies of my barren braine (or rather crums falne from the Princely Table of your more then Salomon-like Father) as the Widowlike Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boll
<pb facs="3"/> of my deuotion; pleadge of my Faith, or Subiect to try your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, clemencie in pardoning, or Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice in condemning of me, who haue rashly persumed to prefer my <hi>home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spun labours</hi> to so powerfull a <hi>Mece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> whose approbation or dislike may enrich me with the fulnesse of content, or expose me vpon the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Rockes of vntimely sorrow. But SIR, either in life or death I shall be</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Highnesse humble and true Seruant, <hi>PATRICK SCOT.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>