<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my honoured Kinsman Mr. George Sandys,
on his admirable Paraphrases.</title>
           <author>Wiatt, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116693_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11474</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21725</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116693</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my honoured Kinsman Mr. George Sandys,
on his admirable Paraphrases.</title>
                 <author>Wiatt, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A paraphrase upon the divine poems. By George Sandys</title>
                 <author>Sandys, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Hebb, Andrew</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Hebb, Andrew.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 55, 13, 171, 1, 15, 3, 33, 1 page, music, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>To my honoured Kinsman M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. George Sandys,
on his admirable Paraphrases.</head>
   <l>VVHy com'st thou thus attended to the Presse?</l>
   <l>Thou wants no Suffrages, the Subject, lesse:</l>
   <l>At first, in confidence of thy full Worth,</l>
   <l>Single, unknowne, Thou didst adventure forth:</l>
   <l>Thy living Works since oft have past the Test,</l>
   <l>And every last (to wonder) prov'd the best.</l>
   <l>Thy Prose and Verse each other Aemulate,</l>
   <l>From Rivals free, at home their Right debate:</l>
   <l>Divide the Iudgement, whether most t'admire</l>
   <l>Roabes loosely flowing, or fine shap't Attire.</l>
   <l>Nor art thou to be blam'd, for having past</l>
   <l>Pernassus hill, and come to Sion last.</l>
   <l>The Schooles from Comments on the Stagyrite,</l>
   <l>To heavenly Speculations rais'd their Flight:</l>
   <l>The Progresse fit, though of Philosophy,</l>
   <l>'Tis justly fear'd, they tooke too deepe a Dye.</l>
   <l>God chiefely warm'd their Breasts with sacred Heat,</l>
   <l>Who were in other Knowledges compleat:</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="6"/>
Though all alike to him, but that he meant</l>
   <l>To give some honour to the Instrument.</l>
   <l>He who in other Structures merits praise,</l>
   <l>May without diffidence a Temple raise.</l>
   <l>And sure, Bezaleel-like, Heav'n did instill,</l>
   <l>For this intended Frame, that Matchlesse Skill:</l>
   <l>Till then thy restlesse Mind mov'd Circular,</l>
   <l>Like the touch't Needle, till it find the Starre.</l>
   <l>Well did'st thou from the East thy entrance make,</l>
   <l>From whence the light of Poetry first brake.</l>
   <l>The Hand unknowne, that God this Piece might own,</l>
   <l>(Like the two Tables) for his Worke alone.</l>
   <l>The Marke of his immediate Worke it beares,</l>
   <l>Even at the Spring a boundlesse Sea appeares.</l>
   <l>For what his Hands, without a Second, make,</l>
   <l>At once their Being and Perfection take.</l>
   <l>His first Day Adam a full Man beheld;</l>
   <l>And Cana's Water choicest Wine exceld.</l>
   <l>This first of Authors, first of Poets, flew</l>
   <l>So high a Pitch, as almost out of View.</l>
   <l>And this was not of Iobs rewards the lest,</l>
   <l>That his rare Story such a Pen exprest.</l>
   <l>What high expressions in such depth of Woe!</l>
   <l>How sweet his sighes and grones in Numbers flow!</l>
   <l>When God himselfe was pleased Iob to cite,</l>
   <l>Who could such Language worthy Him endite!</l>
   <l>His just Reproofes so great a Terrour beare,</l>
   <l>As if each Word a clap of Thunder were.</l>
   <l>From hence in smaller Drilles her course she keeps;</l>
   <l>And scarce discern'd, along the Vallies creeps</l>
   <l>Through Moses and the Iudges; yet we may</l>
   <l>In these discover her continued Way.</l>
   <l>But when the State into a Kingdome grew,</l>
   <l>When all did with their blessed King renew;</l>
   <l>In the sweet Singer then againe it flowes,</l>
   <l>Her bounds extends, and to a River growes.</l>
   <l>His large soul'd Son from Heaven full Light receives,</l>
   <l>For every Path and Step direction gives.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="7"/>
Discovers to our long-seduced Eyes,</l>
   <l>Her Fucus off, the Worlds deformities.</l>
   <l>And by a Purer quenches sensuall Fire,</l>
   <l>The Object chang'd, preserves the Heat entire.</l>
   <l>These two, who might with Iob dispute their Right,</l>
   <l>Rais'd Numbers to their Apogaeon height.</l>
   <l>Thence through the Prophets We her Current trace,</l>
   <l>Whose graver Works Poeticke Iems enchace:</l>
   <l>To shew how aptly both assume one Name,</l>
   <l>Both Heaven-inspir'd, compos'd of Zeale and Flame:</l>
   <l>Above the Rest, that funerall Elegy,</l>
   <l>Presents sad Iuda, to th'admiring Eye</l>
   <l>So lovely in her Sable Vaile and Teares;</l>
   <l>Scarce any Bride in all her Trim appeares:</l>
   <l>Of such a winning sweetnesse: O what Heart</l>
   <l>But must due Pitty to her Woes impart!</l>
   <l>All these, for Prose had still mistaken beene,</l>
   <l>Their Native grace our Language never seene:</l>
   <l>Had not thy speaking Picture shew'd to All</l>
   <l>The wondrous beauty of th'Originall;</l>
   <l>Had lien like Stones uncut, and Oare untri'd,</l>
   <l>Their Reall Worth the same, though scarce espi'd,</l>
   <l>But by the skilfull Linguist; To the Most</l>
   <l>In the darke Sense, and hard Expressions lost.</l>
   <l>Thy Art hath Polish't them to what they were,</l>
   <l>Vnvalued Iewels for the Breast, and Eare.</l>
   <l>Here fixe thy Pillars, what remaines there high'r,</l>
   <l>But th'unknowne Ditties of the heavenly Quire.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Francis Wiatt.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>