<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my worthy Kinsman Mr. George Sandys,
on his excellent Paraphrase upon Iob.</title>
           <author>Digges, Dudley</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116693_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11474</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21725</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116693</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my worthy Kinsman Mr. George Sandys,
on his excellent Paraphrase upon Iob.</title>
                 <author>Digges, Dudley</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A paraphrase upon the divine poems. By George Sandys</title>
                 <author>Sandys, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Hebb, Andrew</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Hebb, Andrew.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 55, 13, 171, 1, 15, 3, 33, 1 page, music, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>To my worthy Kinsman M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. George Sandys,
on his excellent Paraphrase upon Iob.</head>
   <l>YOu teach us a new Pleasure, and have so</l>
   <l>Penn'd the sad Story, we delight in Woe.</l>
   <l>Teares have their Musicke too; this mournfull Dresse</l>
   <l>Doth so become Iob's sorrows, and expresse</l>
   <l>Affliction in so sweet a grace, that we</l>
   <l>Find something to be lov'd in Misery.</l>
   <l>Here Griefe is witty, that the Reader might</l>
   <l>Not suffer, in the patience you write.</l>
   <l>Let others wanton it, while I admire</l>
   <l>Thy warmth, which doth proceed from holy Fire.</l>
   <l>'Tis Guilt, not Poetry, to be like those</l>
   <l>Whose wit in Verse, is downe-right Sin in Prose:</l>
   <l>Whose Studies are Prophannesse, as if then</l>
   <l>They were good Poets only, when bad Men.</l>
   <l>But these are purer Flames, nor shall thy Heat</l>
   <l>Because 'tis good, be therefore thought not Great.</l>
   <l>How vainly doe they erre, who thinke it fit</l>
   <l>A sacred Subject should be void of Wit?</l>
   <l>I boldly dare affirme, He never meant</l>
   <l>We should be Dull, who bids, be Innocent.</l>
   <l>'Tis no excuse, when you your charme reherse</l>
   <l>So sweetly, not to heare, because 'tis Verse.</l>
   <l>Religion is a Matron, whose grave Face</l>
   <l>From Decent Vestures doth receive more Grace.</l>
   <l>In holy duties fondly we affect</l>
   <l>A mis-becomming Rudenesse, and suspect</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="6"/>
Cleane Offerings; wee thinke God likes the Heart</l>
   <l>Where least appeares of th'Vnderstanding part.</l>
   <l>As if Gods Messengers did but delude,</l>
   <l>Vnlesse what they deliver us, be rude.</l>
   <l>Choice Language is the clothing of your Mind;</l>
   <l>Your matter (like those Saints which are inshrin'd</l>
   <l>In Gold, or like to Beauty, when the Lawne</l>
   <l>With rosie cheeks bepurpled ore, is drawne</l>
   <l>To boast the lovelinesse, it seemes to hide,</l>
   <l>And shew more cunningly the blushing Bride.)</l>
   <l>Hath hence a greater lustre; they not love</l>
   <l>The Body lesse, who doe the Clothes approve.</l>
   <l>So we upon this Iewell doe not set</l>
   <l>Lesse price, because we praise the Cabinet.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Dudley Digges.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>