<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PRFEACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116796_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11585</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21828</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116796</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PRFEACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The relation of a wonderfull voiage made by VVilliam Cornelison Schouten of Horne : Shewing how south from the Straights of Magelan, in Terra Del-fuogo: he found and discouered a newe passage through the great South Sea, and that way sayled round about the world. Describing what islands, countries, people, and strange aduentures he found in his saide passage</title>
                 <author>Schouten, Willem Corneliszoon</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newbery, Nathaniel</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 36, 36-82, 1 page, map (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE PRFEACE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE generall <hi>States</hi> of the vnited <hi>Netherland Prouinces,</hi> hauing granted their Letters Pattens to the <hi>East India Company</hi> resident in the sayd <hi>Prouinces,</hi> to trafficke into the <hi>Indies,</hi> and none others but they onely, with a stricke prohibition vnto all other Marchants, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the sayd Countries, not to sayle or trafficke Eastward beyond the Cape <hi>de bona espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> nor through the Sraights of <hi>Magelan</hi> Westward, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into <hi>India,</hi> or any other vnknowne or not discouered coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. <hi>Isaack le Maire</hi> a rich Marchant of <hi>Amsterdam,</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Egmont,</hi> hauing a great desire to trafficke into strange and farre Countries, and <hi>William Cornelison Schouten</hi> of <hi>Horne,</hi> (a man well experienced in Seafaring, who before that time had sayled thrice into most partes of the <hi>East Indies,</hi> for Maister, Pilot, and Marchant) and yet verie desirous to sayle into and to discouer new and vnknowne Countries, oftentimes speaking and conferring together, reasoned among themselues, whether they might not enter into the great South sea, by an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, (then through the same wayes which in the <hi>East In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian Companies</hi> Letters Pattents are formerly forbidden &amp; prohibited.) There to discouer great and rich Countries, where they might lade their ships with rich wares and marchandises,
<pb facs="4"/>whereof the sayd <hi>le Maire,</hi> affirmed he had some knowledge, and that if it did not fal out as they desired, yet that they might passe through the afore said great South seas, into the <hi>East Indies,</hi> and there trafficke freely with great profite: vpon which conference at the last they agreed together, to make a discouery through the South vndiscouered and vnknowne part of the World, South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward from the Straights of <hi>Magelan,</hi> to seeke out a passage in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the sayd South Sea, which they thought very likely to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed: for diuers circumstances and reasons to them knowne and by others at sundry times found about the sayd Straights of <hi>Magelan.</hi> And to that end agreed, betweene them to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise such a Voiage, taking order that <hi>Isaac le Maire</hi> should prouide the one halfe of the money, and <hi>William Cornelison Schouten</hi> the other halfe, to furnish the said Voiage, by the help and furtherance of their friendes, the care whereof, and to make prouision for the sayd voyage being referred to <hi>William Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelison Schouten,</hi> who to effect the same, procured <hi>Peter Clementson</hi> a Brewer, an ancient Burger Maister of <hi>Horne, Iohn Ianson Molenwerf</hi> one of the Schepen, <hi>Iohn Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentson Keis</hi> Senatour of the sayd Towne, and <hi>Cornelius Segetson</hi> a Marchant of <hi>Horne,</hi> to contribute in the same with them, and they together with the aforesayd <hi>William Schouten, Isaac le Maire</hi> and <hi>Iacob le Maire</hi> his Sonne, in short time prepared so much money, as they thought conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and sufficient for the sayd voyage, not once making knowne to the owners of the ships, what their pretence was touching the sayd voyage, but kept that secret to themselues that disbursed the money for the same.</p>
   <p>And to finish the sayd voyage, the Marchants aforesayd pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared and rigged a great and a small ship of <hi>Horne,</hi> The great ship called the <hi>Vnitie,</hi> of <hi>360.</hi> tuns whereof <hi>William Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lison Schouten</hi> was Maister and cheife Pilot, and <hi>Iacob le
<pb facs="4"/>Maire</hi> Marchant and principall Factor, in it hauing <hi>65.</hi> men, and <hi>19.</hi> great peices, and <hi>12.</hi> slings, with muskets and other munition for warre proportionably, with a Pinnace to sayle, an other to row, a boate, and a Scute, anekors, cabells, ropes, sayles, and all other necessaries belonging thereunto. The lesser shipp called the <hi>Horne,</hi> of <hi>110.</hi> tuns, whereof <hi>Iohn Cornelison Schouten</hi> was Maister, and <hi>Aris Clawson</hi> Marchant, in it <hi>22.</hi> men, <hi>8.</hi> great peices, <hi>4.</hi> slings, and other furniture as neede required, and was necessary for such a voyage. And for that they would not make knowne to any man as I sayd before whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they meant to goe, they hyred all their men, both common Saylers and Officers to sayle vnto euery place whether the Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters and the Marchants would goe, which made the common saylers and people to speake and gesse of that voyage diuersly, and at the last gaue them the name of the gold finders, but the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants named them the South Company. The ships being rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, vpon the <hi>16</hi> of May <hi>1615.</hi> the men were mustred by the Scout and Schepen of <hi>Horne,</hi> and the <hi>25.</hi> of the same moneth the <hi>Vnitie</hi> set sayle, and arriued at the <hi>Tessell</hi> vpon the <hi>27.</hi> The <hi>3.</hi> of Iune, the lesser departed from <hi>Horne,</hi> and the next day came to the <hi>Tessell:</hi> What further happened and fell out vnto them during the sayd voyage, is in this Booke at large set downe, and declared from the reportes and writings of those that saw and tryed the same, and which in the same voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age were the cheife and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall persons.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>