<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The order of this view.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116040_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B15559</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21166</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116040</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The order of this view.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A practicall catechisme: or, A view of those principall truths according to godlinesse, which are contayned in the catechisme : diuided into three parts: and seruing for the vse, (as of all, so) especially of those that first heard them. By D.R. B. of Divin, minister of the Gospell</title>
                 <author>D. R. (Daniel Rogers)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 <publisher>Man, Samuel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 136, 139-162, 171-268, 2, 135, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>The order of this view.</head>
   <p>FIrst, I will chuse such Scriptures as doe natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and in briefe containe the summe of each of the three parts; premising a text to each part, that we may heare God, and not man to speake. Then in the second place I will more fully subioyne the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Articles of each part, which belong thereto, with the proofes, openings and vse thereof. And both these in forme of Catechizing.</p>
   <p>The text for the first part.</p>
   <q>
      <bibl>
         <hi>TITVS 3.3:</hi>
      </bibl>
      <p>For we also were in times past, vnwise, disobedient, deceaued, seruing the lusts and diuers pleasures, liuing in malicious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and enuy, hatefull, and hating one another.</p>
   </q>
   <p>Question. <hi>WHat is the connexion of this text?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> The Cretians, to whom <hi>Paul</hi> writes, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing receiued the profession of the Gospell vpon them, teaching them to beleeue in Christ the Lord of all, and to stand fast in the liberty by him purchased to the conscience; began to thinke themselues too good to serue their Superiours, Princes, Magistrates, or Masters. But
<pb facs="8"/> the Apostle presseth them to a close obedience and walking with God; both in this and all other commandements. And hee vrgeth this point of obedience to GOD and man (which is the summe of the third part of the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chisme) by a comparison of the first and second parts of the Catechisme▪ <hi>viz.</hi> Sinne and grace; thus, It were a shame for Christians to walke vnder grace, as they did before, during the tyme of sinne and ignorance. But of this latter sort were ye <hi>Cretians,</hi> sometimes, <hi>viz.</hi> foolish, diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient, deceaued, &amp;c. Now, since the Grace of God appeared, ye are saued and vnder grace. Bee ashamed therefore to liue now as then, and become obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</p>
   <p>Thus we see by this Argument the three parts of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techisme are couched together.</p>
   <p>Q. <hi>What is the meaning of the third verse, in which the Doctrine of the first part is conteined?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> He describes the misery vnder which these <hi>Cretians</hi> lay in their vnregeneracy. In which although all be not sayd which other Scriptures conteine; yet so much is sayd, as may be a ground-worke to the rest. The order is this. First hee layes downe the misery of their mindes: they were <hi>Foolish,</hi> that is, void of all sound knowledge in Gods mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or their owne good, meere spirituall fooles in the midst of their carnall wisdome. This foolishnes, is partly Originall, partly actuall. Originall is the deprauednes of the vnderstanding, and the guilt thereof. As in fooles there is a naturall disability of the powers and Organs of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and so an vtter impotency to reach the truth of things▪ euen so in all naturall men, whether vnder me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ues or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them they are fooles in respect of wisdome to saluation. And, as Law strips fooles of all right to an estate, making them obnoxious to a kind of misery: so doth spirituall igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance robbe the soule of Heauen. Secondly, this foolishnes is actuall, standing in the natural defilement of the mind, with all idle and erroneous thoughts of God &amp; themselues, with pollution of iudgement and vnderstanding issuing thence.</p>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <p>Q. <hi>What else doth the Apostle adde?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> The next is, Corruptednes of the heart or will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed in the terme of <hi>Disobedience,</hi> which is also Originall or Actuall. Originall is the vtter losse of true freedome of the will, in point of Subiection to the mind. So that, as the mind is wholy blynd, so is the will wholy rebellious and vnsubiect, voide of all submission to any Commands of God, quite auerse from any thing which hee doth or can impoze: And the guilt heerof is lyablenes to wrath or Iustice. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, hence issue all Actuall habits of Rebellion, as Impious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, vnrighteousnes, intemperancy and the like.</p>
   <p>Q. <hi>Is this all which Paul describes sinne by?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> No: hee vseth three other descriptions: first he sayth <hi>they were deceaued,</hi> that is, As a foole is cheated easily by euery one: so is a spirituall foole: this toucheth the Actuall Sinnes of the mind. The second is <hi>Seruing lusts:</hi> which implyes a Slauery to the Deuill, world and lusts, lusts of the heart, lusts of the eye, and pride of life: as a beast led to the Shambles. The third is, Trading and Conuersing in actuall sinnes, such as accord with the particular nature of each sinner: some of which distempers are noted, a few of the cōmonest for all the rest, <hi>Pleasures &amp; riot, enuy, hating, &amp; being hated, &amp;c.</hi> all which are added to giue a bitter rellish to this misery.</p>
   <p>Q <hi>Why sayth he nothing of the other part of misery, standing in the curse?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> Not because he excludes any essentiall part of it, but because one text will not conteine all, but that which the drift of it lyes vnto. Some texts include all three parts in one Verse, as <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.8. Some expresse one generall part, some another, and in that part, some one Branch, some another. Therefore what is heere lacking, must bee sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed by some other. This for a ground of Scripture may same, and its good that such draughts of Scriptures bee before our eyes, when we handle these grounds, that as corner stones, they may hold in the building. The which, God willing, shalbe framed more distinctly in the Article follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
   <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
      <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
   </gap>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>