<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the judicious Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116899_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02679</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12810</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116899</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the judicious Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The excommunication published by the L. archbishop of Dublin Thomas Flemming aliàs Barnwell : friar of the Order of S. Francis, against the inhabitants of the diocesse of Dublin, for hearing the masses of Peter Caddell D. of Divinity, and Paul Harris priests, is proved no onely injust, but of no validity, and consequently binding to no obedience. In which treatise is also discovered that impious plot and policy of the aforesaid archbishop and his friars in supplanting the pastors and priests of the clergy, thereby to bring all into the hands of the friars, of whose disorders and foule abuses (especially in this kingdome) something is noted. The second edition, enlarged. By me Paul Harris priest</title>
                 <author>Harris, Paul</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stationers’ Society, Dublin</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Ireland--Dublin</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 98 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the judicious Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>ST tempus cacendi, &amp; tempus lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendi,
Eccles.</hi> 3. There is a time of
silence, and a time of speaking. Eight
moneths of silence have now passed
since the following Censure was publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed,
in which space as well Priests, as
people have expected a redresse of so
great wrongs. But since so long a time hath not wrought
that effect which was dayly looked for, we thought it full
time to expect no further time, but rather to breake off
so prejudiciall a silence, and better late, then never, to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest
unto the world, as well the insufficiency of that
sentence, as the innocency of the censured, and if it bee
possible to undeceive such as are possessed of the contrary.
Our delay in this affaire (I confesse) hath bred us this
Inconvenience. That the contrary opinion being so long
sucked in, hath so seasoned the Potts, as hardly now will
they smell of any other liquor. Three sorts of Readers (and
so the most) I doe exclude from this discourse.</p>
   <list>
      <item>1. First, such as are carelesse how the matter passeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
us.</item>
      <item>2. Secondly, such as are obstinate in the contrary opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</item>
      <item>3. Thirdly, such as are not capable of reason when they
see it layde downe.</item>
   </list>
   <p>
      <pb facs="5"/>
Onely to the fourth, anll the fewest sort of Readers is
this Apology addressed. (I say) for their onely sakes,
who are willing to have satisfaction, and are capable
thereof.</p>
   <p>If any bee offended, That this our Apology or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
of our Innocency is published, and made common
to many. Let them consider, that so was the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishops
Censure: And that to many moe, then into
whose hands these writings can come. For wee are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded,
none will take the like paines to publish them
unto hundreds, and thousands!, as the Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication
was thorough all the Oratoryes of Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blin,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> well by the Parish Priests, as so many Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
of F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iars, yea republished againe, and againe, from
time to time, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t happily it might grow out of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
with the people.</p>
   <p>If any doe except, That this our Answer is in the
English tongue, Let them consider, that so was the
Censure: They both speake one language. But you
will say, That this is made common both to Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes,
and Protestants, whereas the Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
was onely communicated unto Catholickes. I say,
in this also they are alike. For as a matter made
publicke among the Protestants, can not be concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
from the Catholickes; no more can any thing publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed
among the Catholickes be kept from the Protestants.
Neither can any man of understanding conceive how it
can f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ll out otherwise.</p>
   <p>If matters heerein layde downe be very fowle and odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>us
against the Archbishop, and his Friars, and sound ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
harsh in mens eares; Oh then thinke how farre worse it
<pb facs="5"/>
was for them to be the Authors thereof: vnlesse we bee
arrived at those times of which <hi>Cassidorus</hi> speaketh, or
rather prophesieth: That the dayes shall be, and such times
come, as it shallbe a farre more odious and dangerous
matter to reprove injustice, and to reprehend vice, then to
commit the same. Experience whereof we have had in
our late Appeale. Wee the Appellants having received
of the injudicious and partiall multitude, more rebuke
then they who were the Authors of all those injuries, &amp;
greivances, of which, and of whom, we made complaint
unto lawfull Superiours. But as the world commends ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
whom God condemnes, and of the contrary: So I doubt
not but many who are justified upon the benches of the
multitude, shall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> be found in the Magistrates la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
Tribunalls.</p>
   <p>The thing that we demaund is justice, we call for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice,
we cry for Iustice, and with our clamours will we fill
both the Heavens, and the eares of all lawfull Superiours
on earth; Thoughts have voyces sufficient for the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,
words and writings are necessary for the earth; by
which if we doe not prevaile in our principall intent of
attaining Iustice, yet at least in opening our innocency, &amp;
venting of our greifes, wee shall give s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e ease unto our
minds. For so saith S. <hi>Gregory, Si illatas molestias
lingua dicat, à conscientia dolor emanat, vulnera e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim
clausa plus cruciant. Hom.</hi> 6. If the tongue doe
utter sustained wrongs, greife passeth from the mind. For
wounds shut up doe more torment. Let then that text of
the Prophet be verified of us. <hi>In omnem terram exivit
sonus eorum. &amp;c. Psal.</hi> 18. Their sound is gone forth
thorough all the earth, and their words to the utter most
<pb facs="6"/>
bounds thereof, yea in the name of God say I
<q>
         <l>Audiat has nostras, cleri, populique querelas,</l>
         <l>Et Tagus &amp; Ganges, gens etiam Antipodum.</l>
      </q>
      <q>
         <l>Let the world witnesse our complaints, above, and under,</l>
         <l>As far as Tagus sandes, and Ganges lye asunder.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>