<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE BODY AND BLOOD OF ou Sauiour Iesus Christ vnder the foormes of bread and wyne all honour praisc and thanks be geuen for uer.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116428_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11445</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21695</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116428</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE BODY AND BLOOD OF ou Sauiour Iesus Christ vnder the foormes of bread and wyne all honour praisc and thanks be geuen for uer.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The supper of our Lord set foorth according to the truth of the Gospell and Catholike faith. By Nicolas Saunder, Doctor of Diuinitie. With a confutation of such false doctrine as the Apologie of the Churche of England, M. Nowels chalenge, or M. Iuels Replie haue vttered, touching the reall presence of Christe in the Sacrament</title>
                 <author>Sander, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Fowler (Fouler), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Louvain</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>3, 25, 22-425, 2 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE BODY AND BLOOD OF</hi> ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> Sauiour Iesus Christ vnder the foormes of bread and wyne all honour praisc and thanks be geuen for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>uer.</head>
   <p>IF he that mainteneth a right good cause, yet partly for feare of the deceits and suttiltie of his aduersaries, partly for mistrust of his own knowledge and memoric, dare not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere in iudgement without his aduocate or pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>tour with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>: seing y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> sending foorth of a booke into y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> light of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> world is y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering to haue it sūmoned to so manie courts, as it shalbe brought into howses, &amp; y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> appering before so manie iudges, as be readers thereof: what aduocat and proctour, yea rather what Doctor and Patrone am I constrayned to seek, who do not only set foorth mie book to be readen of whatsoeuer English man, but also write of suche a matter, as being of most weight, is most diligently examined in these our dayes? and wherein I am sure to find as wel the Lutherans as the Zuinglians, (though vtterly dissa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greing betwene themselues) yet against me not only agreing to be seuere iudges in the reading, but also to be cruel aduersaries in their iudgement. Which seing it is so, let noman wonder, that I, not mistrusting anie whit the vniuersal cause of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks, but misdoubting mine own wit, and the shamelesse shifts of our aduersaries, haue chosen to dedicate this work to y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> mysteri of thy glorious body and blood (Lord Iesu Christ,) to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, those that now take vpon them to misiudge y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> manifest &amp; effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all words of thy blessing and thanksgeuing, pronounced by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>o in thy last supper, making a figuratiue speache of a proper: and, whereas thy true body and blood itself worthie of all honour, is
<pb facs="3"/>
through thy godhead made really present, teaching not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing for their parte, the substance of bread and wine still to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, and therefore an idol to be falsely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>et vp and worshipped by the Catholiks: to th'inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>t, I saie, those false teachers maie either through thy grace be conuerted from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>r misbelefe, (whereof I most humbly beseche the) or els if they wil stubb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>nly persist in their detestable opinion, maie euen presently be confounded with the maiestie of thy name whose glorie they opp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>gne.</p>
   <p>For what can be more dishonorable to thy goodnes, then if it maie be truly reported, that the wisedome of god did institute his chief Sacrament in such words, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which either being true and not beleued, should b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rden our consciences with infidelitie, or being earnestly beleued, and yet not concea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ed in proper speache, should bring vs into manifest da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>nger of idolatrie? sith no faithfull man beleuing this to be thy body (as thou hast said it is) can ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>teine<note place="margin">Mat. 26. Psal. 98.</note> from the singular worshipping of that singular fotestole of God. Now soeuer it be with other men, I adore thee my God and lord really present vnder the formes of bread and wine after couse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration dewly made. Beseeching thee of pardō for my synnes by the same propitiatorie sacrifice of thy body and blood, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made once with bloodsheding vpon the crosse, causeth the<note place="margin">Heb. 10. Malac. 1.</note> fruits therof to be daily applied in that cleane and vnbloody sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the masse. To this great mysterie of thy real presence I dedicate these my paines, as to the most vndoubted fountain, cause, and supporter of them. In this faith I was baptized and made a member of thy mystical body, in the hope to mainteine this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> parents and frinds did set me to schole, in the vehement loue and affection thereof I haue written this rude and simple work. And to whom should I refer the praise and thanks for it, but vnto the alone? Or of whom shuld I craue the
<pb facs="3"/>
protection thereof, but of thee? seing thou only art a meet patrone for the defence of any booke, which only art alwaies present, wheresoeuer and whensoeuer it shalbe examined. To the honour therefore of thy body and blood I offer this poore mite of my sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vnderstanding (thy mercifull gift, whatsoeuer it be) trusting thou wilt not suffer, neither the truthe of thy gospel to be long vnrestored in the desolate Ile of pitifull England, nor me thy poore seruant through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> or naughty liuing to perish euerlastinglie.</p>
   <closer>AMEN.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>