<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>OT THE GENE∣ROVS READER.</title>
           <author>S., P.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116886_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11621</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21863</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116886</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>OT THE GENE∣ROVS READER.</title>
                 <author>S., P.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Vox vera: or, Obseruations from Amsterdam : Examining the late insolencies of some pseudo-puritans, separatists from the Church of Great Brittaine. And closed vp with a serious three-fold aduertisement for the generall vse of euery good subiect within his Maiesties dominions, but more especially of those in the kingdome of Scotland. By Patricke Scot, North-Brittaine</title>
                 <author>Scot, Patrick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Bernard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 62 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>OT THE GENE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ROVS READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F (as is wittily mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized) infants at their first entry into the world, bewaile the fall of our first <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents;</hi> I finde no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son why those that are of full age may not <hi>vera voce, condole</hi> either priuate <hi>distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers</hi> or <hi>publike calamities;</hi> or that I should not publish this <hi>abortiue birth,</hi> expostulating a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst those <hi>Empiricks</hi> and <hi>firebrands,</hi> that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to enflame the <hi>Church,</hi> and incense the <hi>state,</hi> that thereby a <hi>plurisie</hi> of <hi>troubles</hi> and generall <hi>combustion</hi> might ensue indange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the peace of the one, or troubling the calme of other.</p>
   <p>As my <hi>stile</hi> is <hi>dull,</hi> plaine without <hi>affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> rather to deliuer <hi>trueth</hi> then shew <hi>art:</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/> so are my <hi>aimes sincere</hi> and <hi>free</hi> of all <hi>squint-eyed</hi> inducements.</p>
   <p>My dutie to the <hi>Church, allegeance</hi> to my <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> and danger of <hi>schismaticall praesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents</hi> are the <hi>fires</hi> that haue tempered this <hi>Telamonian shield,</hi> vnder whose shelter this <hi>Shepheard-like subiect</hi> opposeth the naked simplicitie of <hi>trueth</hi> against the enraged <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liahs</hi> of this <hi>age,</hi> armed with glistring shows of finest <hi>forgery.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>One fauour I craue, that thy <hi>misprision</hi> wrong me not, as if I did not distinguish such <hi>graue, sober,</hi> and peaceable <hi>spirits</hi> in the <hi>Clergie</hi> or <hi>Laitie,</hi> at home or abroad, that (though different in opiniō in some points of externall discipline and <hi>policie</hi>) containe themselues within the <hi>precinct</hi> of that vnity and modesty prescribed by the <hi>Apostles</hi> in like cases.</p>
   <p>As I esteeme it <hi>sacriledge</hi> to detract from the least desert of any sober <hi>Christian:</hi> so hold I it <hi>Religion</hi> to vnmaske the <hi>viperous brood</hi> of <hi>Parricidos,</hi> whose inuenomed <hi>shafts</hi> I passe by with contempt, neglecting whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther such <hi>dogs barke, snarle</hi> or <hi>fawne. Dum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scientiae satisfacio nihil in famam laboro sequatur
<pb facs="3"/> vel mala dum bene mereor;</hi> darke <hi>shadowes</hi> doe no lesse attend beautifull then deformed <hi>bodies,</hi> in brightest <hi>Sunshine.</hi> If I should labor other satisfaction, it were an effect of <hi>frenzy</hi> not of <hi>hope,</hi> since it is no <hi>trueth</hi> but <hi>opinion</hi> which trauelleth the <hi>Coasts</hi> without <hi>pasport,</hi> that I am to suruey.</p>
   <p>If thou read iudiciously without partiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty I expect thy fauorable <hi>censure</hi> of this <hi>task,</hi> meditated whē the raging <hi>waues</hi> of stormy <hi>Seas</hi> incensed with <hi>thundring winds,</hi> aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>deaths pale colours</hi> to the terrour as well of <hi>Mariners</hi> as <hi>Passengers;</hi> penned after my safe exposall vpon a forraigne <hi>shore,</hi> when the sad remēbrance of some of my friends &amp; familiars lately sunke into the <hi>vnsatiable belly</hi> of the vast <hi>Ocean,</hi> much distempered my <hi>braine,</hi> and confused my <hi>memory;</hi> now published to the praise of that <hi>supreame Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie,</hi> by whose grace I hope hereafter, in a more calme aire, to erect a thankfull <hi>memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall</hi> of so great a deliuery. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>P. S.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>