<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most Learned and Celebrious ACADEMIANS of Oxford and Cambridge EDMVND CAMPIAN wisheth Health.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116202_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17867</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4535</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116202</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most Learned and Celebrious ACADEMIANS of Oxford and Cambridge EDMVND CAMPIAN wisheth Health.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Campian Englished. Or A translation of the Ten reasons : in which Edmund Campian (of the Societie of Iesus) priest, insisted in his challenge, to the Vniuersities of Oxford and Cambridge Made by a priest of the Catholike and Roman Church</title>
                 <author>Campion, Edmund, saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>192, 2 pages, 16°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb n="31" facs="16"/>
   <head>To the most Learned and Celebrious ACADEMIANS of Oxford and Cambridge EDMVND CAMPIAN wisheth Health.</head>
   <p>WHEN this yeare past, by my chosen institution of life, and commaund of my Superiours (<hi>Most excellent Men)</hi> I returned into this Iland, I did finde stormes much more boysterous and rugged vpon the coasts of England, then those, which I had lately escaped in the Brittan Ocean. After <hi>I</hi> had entered into the hart of the Realme, I saw no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more vsuall then vnusuall punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;
<pb n="32" facs="17"/>
nothing more certaine, then vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaintie of danger. I closed myself to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather, as well as the present state of things would permit, being mindefull of the Cause, mindefull of the Times. And for feare, that perhaps I should be appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, before my entrance-in was ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moured, I presently did set downe in wryting, Who I was, that was come; What I sought after; What manner of warre, and against whome, I did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime. The first draught of it, I eue<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> kept about me, that, if so I were taken, it also with me might be taken: A Copie thereof I deliuered to a friend, the which (truly without my intention and priuitie) was made knowne to manie. The Aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes doe with great indignitie and atroci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie entertayne this Wryting being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulged; And among other things, they most maliciously insist vpon, that I being but <hi>One,</hi> dare in matter of Religion send
<pb n="33" facs="17"/>
this Challenge to them <hi>All;</hi> Although it is certaine, that I should not be alone in this Combat, if the disputation might procede by publike Warrant. <hi>Hanmer</hi> and <hi>Chark</hi> haue shaped an Answer to my Demaunds. What was it at the length? Most idle and friuolous. For not anie answer sorting with their honours, but <hi>one</hi> they giue, which <hi>one</hi> they shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer giue: <hi>We embrace your challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, the Queene promiseth open se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie, make haste, and fly ouer to vs.</hi> In lieu hereof, these two blotters of paper crye out, with a multitude of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>streperous words: <hi>Fye of thy Sodalitie, thy seditious molitions, thy arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie, thou art a Traytour, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesly a Traytour.</hi> Ridiculously! Why do Men, as if scarse they enioyed but their fiue senses, make such profusion and waste of labour, charges, and their owne repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation? But as concerning these two (of
<pb n="34" facs="18"/>
which the fi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st out of Religion vastly runneth vpon my said Wryting; the other euen brea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hing malice, rudely tumbles &amp; tosses it vp and downe) there is late<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished a small Treatise for them to pe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vse, which discourseth (so farr forth, as is th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ught conuenient) of our Societie, of the iniuryes offe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed vs by these kinde of men, and of the function, which we vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe. Now to me it remayned; (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I see, the chiefe Protestant Doctours prepare for me the rack and gallowes, not the Schooles) to war<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ant with you the cause of this my proceeding; and to poynt out those branches and heads of Matter (harbingers of my desired future D<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>spu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation) which haue distilled into me so great confidence and securitie: And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I would hereby wish you, who are more peculiarly <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>bliged thereto then others to espouse you<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> seruiceable dayes chiefly to t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>is incumbencie and lab<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ur; since
<pb n="35" facs="18"/>
CHRIST, the Church, the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and your owne Sou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e's wellfare exact thus much from you. If I, as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying pregnancie, learning, art, reading, memorie, should prouoke anie one skilfull and experienced Aduersarie, I might iustly haue thereby bewrayed in me a swelling vent<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sitie and pride, as neither rightly balancing myself, nor them: But if I looking vpon the Cause of Religion with a dispassionate, vnpreiudging, and single eye haue thought myself able enough, to demonstrate this <hi>Sunne</hi> to shine in its <hi>Meridian,</hi> your <hi>Ingenuities</hi> ought not to rest disedifyed thereby; but freely to grant to me (being imbarked in so great an Action) this seruour, which the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of IESVS CHRIST my King, and the impugnable Truth haue produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. You well know, that <hi>Marcus Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> in his Oration for <hi>Quintius,</hi> when <hi>Roscius</hi> did <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> to obta<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne the
<pb n="36" facs="19"/>
Cause then controuersed, if he could but euict, that seauen hundred miles could not be runne in the space of two dayes, did not only litle rega<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>de the elocution of <hi>Hortensius,</hi> but neither of those, whe excelled <hi>Hortensius</hi> in his Art, as the <hi>Philippies,</hi> the <hi>Cottae,</hi> the <hi>Antonies,</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e <hi>Crassi,</hi> who<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e re<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e countenāces were full of R<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>etorike, &amp; to wh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ch men himself ascribed all perfection in Oratorie, and stoare of fyled w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rds; For there is as c<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Truth of that radiancie and splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, that no impostures either in gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of speach, or in the matter itself can ouerclowde it. Now this, which we here vnde<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>take, is more cleare and illustrious, then was the <hi>Thesis</hi> or Subiect of <hi>Roscius.</hi> For if I can but make good, that there is a Heauen, that there is a God, that there is a Fayth, that there is a CHRIST, I do come of victorius. May I not then be he<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e courageous? may
<pb n="37" facs="19"/>
I not here shew an inexpugnable confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Certainly, hangd, drawne, &amp; quartered I well may be, ouercome I cannot be;</hi> Since I ancker myself on those Doctours, whome that Spirit did i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>struct, which is neither vanquished, nor deceaued; How then can I here loose the honour of the day? I humbly beseech you, that you would be but content to be saued; this is the <hi>Butt</hi> ob my desires; which one request if I may obtayne, <hi>I</hi> shall be farre more hopefull in all the rest In the meane-time render yourselues wholy vp to this solicitude and Warrfare, batter at the eares of CHRIST with your incessant payers, become breathlesse in your diligence and labour herein; And then doubtlesly you shall finde the matter to stand, as (abstracting from all Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances) it is in itself; that is you shall finde our Aduersari<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o vse strange tergi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sations of distrust and despayre; and
<pb n="38" facs="20"/>
vs (as being securely grounded) readie to expect and wayte for this field of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, with all composed se<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>enitie of minde, and spirituall resolution. I here forbeare to spreade myself in more words, since in the rest following I direct further speaches to you.</p>
   <closer>Fare you well.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>