<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An Advertisement to the Reader concer∣ning Polanus his Symphonia Catholica, and Mr. Robert Cooke his booke concerning counterfet Fathers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116093_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10907</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21177</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116093</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An Advertisement to the Reader concer∣ning Polanus his Symphonia Catholica, and Mr. Robert Cooke his booke concerning counterfet Fathers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An answer to Mr. Fisher the Iesuite, his fiue propositions concerning Luther. By Mr. Rogers, that worthy Oxford diuine. VVith some passages also of the said Mr. Rogers with the said Mr. Fisher. Hereunto is annexed Mr. VV.C. his dialogue of the said argument, wherein is discouered Fishers folly</title>
                 <author>Rogers, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 28 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="publishers_advertisement">
   <pb n="28" facs="17"/>
   <head>An Advertisement to the Reader concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Polanus</hi> his <hi>Symphonia Catholica,</hi> and M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Robert Cooke</hi> his booke concerning <hi>counterfet Fathers.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>Polanus</hi> his <hi>Symphonia Catholica</hi> is written in common-place manner, out of the ancient Fathers and other good Authors, from the dayes of Christ and his Apostles to the times of <hi>Luther,</hi> handling the principall controuerted points methodically betwixt the Protestants and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists, written purposely to satisfie that demand of Papists, <hi>Where was the Protestants religion before the times of</hi> Luther? Oh that some good religious Scholler or other would translate it into English, for the common profite of the Church of England, against the insulting brags of <hi>Fisher</hi> and other Papists, who say, we had no religion before <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> times, that hee hatched it, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>I wish likewise that M. <hi>Robert Cooke</hi> his Latin Treatise concerning <hi>counterfet Fathers</hi> was translated into English, for the good of those who vnderstand not Latin; Papists alledging counterfet Fathers so often.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   <pb facs="17"/>
   <pb facs="18"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>