<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE ENTRANCE INTO THE BOOKE, OR PREFACE TO THE READER, which containes these foure things: First, the generall summe of the whole. Secondly, the reasons why it was set foorth. Third∣ly, the matter and argument of euery particular treatise. Fourthly, a directing of the Christian reader, how to reade it with most profit.</title>
           <author>Rogers, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116354_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10945</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21215</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116354</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE ENTRANCE INTO THE BOOKE, OR PREFACE TO THE READER, which containes these foure things: First, the generall summe of the whole. Secondly, the reasons why it was set foorth. Third∣ly, the matter and argument of euery particular treatise. Fourthly, a directing of the Christian reader, how to reade it with most profit.</title>
                 <author>Rogers, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Seuen treatises : containing such direction as is gathered out of the Holie Scriptures, leading and guiding to true happines, both in this life, and in the life to come: and may be called the practise of Christianitie. Profitable for all such as heartily desire the same: in the which, more particularly true Christians may learne how to leade a godly and comfortable life euery day. Penned by Richard Rogers, preacher of the word of God at Wethersfield in Essex</title>
                 <author>Rogers, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 <publisher>Dexter, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>—English Stock</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 18 pages, 19-20 leaves, 21-480 pages, 484-490 leaves, 489, that is 491-599, 33 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE ENTRANCE INTO THE BOOKE, OR PREFACE TO THE READER, which containes these foure things: First, the generall summe of the whole. Secondly, the reasons why it was set foorth. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the matter and argument of euery particular treatise. Fourthly, a directing of the Christian reader, how to reade it with most profit.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N so great varietie of all learning, as God hath fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished this age withall, it were not onely needlesse, but arrogancie and follie, for me to put any in hope, that I goe about to teach that, which hath not been taught, and set foorth alreadie by godly and learned brethren. But yet, least any should thinke my labour vaine, in that which I enterprise, I would all such might vnderstand, that howsoeuer I shall bring no other thing, then some haue, in generall, or in some part heretofore pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished; yet they shall not be glutted with the same thing in particular, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they respect the treatise and argument it selfe, or the manner of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing and prosecuting the same. At leastwise, I may say, that there hath not come to my hand any booke directly tending to this end, which I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound here in the seauen Treatises following, to helpe the frailtie of Gods children, and namely, by setting before their eies as in a glasse, the infinite, secret, and deceitfull corruptions of the heart: from whence (without a gracious regarding of the same) sore and dangerous euils doe arise and breake out in their life. Neither haue I seene any treatise, and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction particularly drawne and gathered for mens liues to gouerne and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, which tieth them to daily vse of the same throughout their whole course: of both which my purpose is most chiefly,<note place="margin">The intent of the author, and generall summe of the whole booke.</note> as well faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as louingly, to intreate, and to aide my poore neighbours and brethren, with that which I haue gathered by reading, and noted by experience, if by any meanes I may be able hereby, to make the Christian way any thing more easie and pleasant vnto them, then many finde it: and to bring it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to more price, then the most doe value it at.</p>
   <p>In few words, this is that which I aime at, that such as <hi>haue tasted how good the Lord is, and haue felt the power of the life to come,</hi> by any worke of faith and Christian life, which they haue obtained by the preaching of the Gospell, may after that, see their wants, their infirmities, their corruptions, rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, hindrances, &amp; other discouragements, from that blessed estate wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into
<pb facs="6"/>
they are entred: and how they may euery day in the best manner, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie, or at least wise weaken and diminish them, and that they may also behold their liberties and prerogatiues, which they haue by Christ: as the certaintie of Gods loue, deliuerance from the feare of the great and euill day, peace and comfort through faith, and the blessednes of such an estate, and daily inioy the same. And therefore, not to be as men that haue no such priuiledges, either cast downe with needeles feare, or possessed with an earthly or vaine reioycing, or destitute of incouragement to walke forward in an heauenly course:<note place="margin">The fruite and benefit of it to the true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian.</note> But that they may be mery in the Lord, and yet without lightnes; sad and heauie in heart for their owne sins, and the abominations of the land, and yet without discouragment, or dumpishnes: resting and beleeuing in God, without bold presumption, and fearing their owne weaknes, but yet without dreadfull and deadly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spayring. And that thus the Christian man, and he who is faithful indeede, may so carrie himselfe in his course, as he may haue no thought or purpose to reuolt and turne from this hope which is set before him, but be perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that he is infinitly incouraged, to hold out constantly therein, against all that might come in his way to the contrarie. And that the vngodly may see how such are blessed in comparison of other, and what they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues goe voyde of which they might inioy,<note place="margin">What the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly may learne by it.</note> and therefore may seeke how to become not almost, but altogether Christians with them.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <p>The second point.</p>
         <p>The reasons of setting out this.</p>
      </note>To these (I say) who haue set themselues in a full, and resolute purpose to passe their daies godly in the midst of many encombrances, and <hi>to walke with the Lord,</hi> so far as of fraile flesh may be obtained (how weake so euer in their owne perswasions) to these (I say) I desire in this treatise of mine to be some helpe and assistance, and to speake plainely, that such as would faine doe well,<note place="margin">The first.</note> and yet cannot tell how, may hereby be eased and relieued. And if any (who yet are in superstition,<note place="margin">The authors desire that they might profit by it.</note> hypocrisie, prophanenes, or as yet in darknes) desire to be partakers thereof also, and so to like of that aduice and instruction, which is written for the beleeuers, that they be willing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the wicked, crooked, and cursed way, which they haue walked in: I should be so farre from enuying them this blessing, that (although this was not set out directly for them) yet they may vnderstand, that with such a willing mind, as I haue vndertaken this worke for their good who <hi>are in Christ</hi> alreadie; with the like, I am readie to further and helpe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them, who thinke and know themselues as yet to be <hi>strangers from Christ</hi> altogether; and to reioyce, if I might vnderstand, that they haue been moued hereby with their brethren, to become the true disciples of Christ.<note place="margin">This worke e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to better the good.</note> Indeede I haue not laboured so much, to perswade these to returne from their miserie, and to become penitent, because many both examples of the like, and reasons to moue them, are plentifully, plainely, and in good order, extant among them alreadie; and for that I know, that for the most part, they profit not by our writing, who doe not before regarde and take good by our preaching: and yet they shall haue my best aduice in the end.</p>
   <p>But as for such as haue alreadie been in the truth of their hearts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted vnto the Lord, and vnfainedly been called backe <hi>from the former lusts of their ignorance,</hi> and the fashion of the world, after the which some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time
<pb facs="6"/>
they framed themselues: for such (I say) I know it is the earnest de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of their hearts, that they may as well haue a path-way to godlines, and a direction to the same lie by them, to the which they may alwayes at neede resorte, when publike helpes by sermons cannot euermore be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed: as also to be made more fit thereby, to profit by them, when they doe repaire vnto the same. And although I looke not for it, that such ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count should be made of this booke among the greatest number, who haue resolued with themselues either not to learne or imbrace any thing more, thē alreadie they haue, especially proceeding from a meaner person then themselues: or to scorne whatsoeuer agreeth not with their humor, and to cauill and quarrell with that, which naturall reason doth not allow; yet (wishing better things vnto such) I am not discouraged, but for their sake who would desire the same in practise which here they shall finde by reading, I will goe forward in this enterprise.</p>
   <p>I know it can doe the best no harme.<note place="margin">It is of vse to all sorts of good christians, and that was one reason of set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it out.</note> I am sure (trusting and looking for the blessing of God) that it shall do many good, such I meane as would doe well, if they knew how; and would grow wiser, sounder and more constant in faith and a godly life, if they had helpe and direction thereto plainely set before them. And I am not ashamed to say,<note place="margin">The second reason of set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it forth.</note> that for mine owne furtherance as well as other mens, and the better carriage of my selfe through this my pilgrimage; I haue been willing to gather some such things together, as in this small volume I haue contriued.<note place="margin">The third.</note> Neither had it come into the hands of others, vnlesse such as are of account aboue my selfe for their gifts, as well as my neighbours,<note place="margin">The fourth.</note> among whom I haue preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the doctrine, had perswaded me to set it forth. Besides all that hath been said, I haue chiefly in this enterprise (as God doth know) sought this, that this vnperfect &amp; weake labour of mine may stir vp and moue some of my godly brethren (who for the habilitie and grace which God hath giuen them, if their leasure had been as much as mine, might tenne-fold more profitably and substantially haue vndertaken it) to enlarge and perfect the same, the argument being so needfull and profitable, to the further be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of Gods Church and people.<note place="margin">The fift.</note> Another reason of setting out this treatise was this, that they who desire it, may see, by the diligent marking of the same, the beauties of the Christian life more clearely, then by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Christians liues it can bee seene, and that it may bee brought into greater account with many, who thinke it (through errour) ouerbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>densome.</p>
   <p>And partly also I was moued hereunto by this reason,<note place="margin">The sixt.</note> that the Papists cast in our teeth, that we haue nothing set out for the certaine and daily direction of a Christian, when yet they haue published (they say) many treatises of that argument. For answere to the first poynt of this obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they cannot deny (but that they care not what they say, to bring the people out of loue with our religion) they cannot (I say) deny, that both in catechismes, sermons, and other treatises, there is set forth by vs that which may cleerely direct Christians, and stir vp godly deuotion in them, though all be not gathered together into one volume: for the second part concerning their treatises, I graunt there are two which I haue seene,
<pb facs="7"/>
set forth by them in our English tongue, the one called a Christian Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectorie, the other the Exercise of a Christian life, wherein the author doth, though both superstitiously and nothing properly, goe about to teach and giue direction for euery day in the weeke; (the one bearing the name of <hi>Robert Parsons</hi> the King of Spaines confessor: the other by an <hi>Italian a Iesuite Doctor in Diuinitie,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iasper Loarte.</note> and translated into English by some fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourite of Poperie) the first is nothing lesse then a direction for a Christian though it be called a Directorie, tending rather to perswade men to resolue with themselues to leaue some grosse euils, then to shew them soundly how to attaine pardon, or teaching how to liue christianly: the other is a ridiculous tying men to a daily taske of reading some part of the storie of Christs passion, and saying certaine prayers throughout the weeke euery day a taske; but indeede nothing lesse then directing, after the will of God, him who desires to leade a Christian life. Both of them I dare boldly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, being deceiued themselues, doe deceiue others, especially the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who is not able to discerne and trie the lying spirit in them. The one, that is to say, <hi>Parsons,</hi> hath vnder a pretence of a holines and deuotion, set downe sundrie impediments to resolution: But yet they are put in among other things to take away the harshnes and tartnes of manifold errours of merit, and other superstition mixed with them and vpholden in that religion, and as it were, with sugar to season them, which else no taste could abide, and in the depth of a subtill heart, put in, to make the world beleeue, that the <hi>Popish religion</hi> is the onely holy religion, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors thereof the godliest liuers; when yet Antichrist is their captaine, and head, or (as they will not deny) the Pope of Rome, who yet doth, and for these many yeares hath vpholden and maintained open, and almost infinit heresies and abominations.</p>
   <p>And as their religion and worship is composed and framed of heresies and lies, and a confused heape of superstitions, and outward dead workes, euen Iewish and Heathenish ceremonies; so the persons themselues who professe they know most, and that they are able to giue rules vnto others, vpholding and building vpon so rotten foundations, are furthest off from well guiding others, so that no man may euer looke by any Popish direction to liue christianly. Although I will not dissemble what I thinke, namely, that some doe meane more simply and truely then the rest, and thinke that they serue God aright hauing deuout minds, but being igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the truth, must needes be deceiued.</p>
   <p>But of Maister <hi>Parsons</hi> booke of Resolution, seeing he and some other haue set it out in a glosing stile to insinuate with the ignorant and vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned reader, that he seekes no other thing but to draw him to pietie and godlines, I cannot forbeare, but I must say a little, which otherwise I would not haue done. And the rather, for that I know, he hath snared many sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple peoples consciences thereby, who being themselues willing to be led in a right way, beleeue that he meanes as he speaketh; and therefore are left, I say, deceiued, and in a bottomles gulfe; out of the which, if God helpe them not some other way, it is not possible for them to get. And this I say first, for the deliuering of such out of the snare and maze in which
<pb facs="7"/>
they haue lost themselues by reading of that booke, that although there be a pretended shew of godlines in it, and much superstition; yet the best of it is farre from true pietie and godlines, seeing that, and euery part of it proceedeth from faith ioyned with assurance of Gods fauour,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.22. Act. 15.9.</note> which is that alone that purifieth the heart, and maketh it able to bring fourth fruits of amendment of life; without which, mens best actions are wrought by the strength of corrupt nature, and are fruites of the flesh, and workes of darkenes, and so abominable. And yet this faith doe Papists make no rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning of, neither therefore can the booke of Resolution teach or hold it.</p>
   <p>Further, I say that the law onely is vrged in that booke, without teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the poore soule that may be terrified thereby, how to lay hold on the promise of eternall life, and without the Gospell:<note place="margin">Esay. 61.1. Ezech. 34.4. Ioh. 8 32.</note> the truth and glad ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings whereof, is onely able to set at libertie the consciences of such as are strangled by the threats and terrible curse of the law: for if that truth make free (as our Sauiour saith) then are men free in deede. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it may be obiected to me, that I doe the author of the booke open wrong in saying, that he ioyneth not the Gospell with the law; for he that readeth it, may finde, that he speaketh of Iesus Christ, that he was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by his father to the world, that many might be saued; and of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise: and how say I then that he teacheth the law without the Gospell? I answere, that he doth indeede mention both the promises of the Gospel, and also Christ; and this he doth in that chapter which is intituled [diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in Gods mercie] but yet is that true that I say:<note place="margin">Rom. 1.16.</note> For the Gospell is the power of saluation to him that beleeueth: and it is not the Gospell if it be not beleeued: for that is a part of the description of it: Now belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing or faith hath assurance going with it, as I shewed out of the epistle to the Hebrues: Which the author of that booke with the rest of his religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, doth flatly deny; and therefore it is cleere, that he doth not teach the Gospell, neither in that booke doth plainely and soundly guide the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring soule which seeth it selfe lost, to finde remission of his sinne, and euerlasting life; and consequently, that he doth not direct his reader to liue godly, as I said, but holdeth him in darknes and in the state of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and deceiueth him.</p>
   <p>And what reckoning he maketh of faith (which the word of God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth before all other things, and saith,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.4.</note> that it ouercommeth all difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the world) we may see by his owne words, in his preface fol. 6. I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort the discreet reader (saith he) of whatsoeuer religion and faith he be, to enter into the carefull studie and exercise of good deedes, assuring him, that this is the right way, to obtaine at Gods hands the light of true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe. And a little after he saith, It is more easie to beleeue as we ought, then to liue, as we should. Here we see, he preferres good deedes before faith: as if the fruite should be said to be more precious, then the tree that beares it. And yet as not marking what he said, he vttereth these words a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, which cannot stand with the other: Our fathers receiued one vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme faith from their mother the holy Catholike Church, and did at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend only to builde vpon that foundation good workes and vertuous life, as holy Scripture commaundeth vs to doe. Here he affirmeth, that good
<pb facs="8"/>
life commeth from faith. Thus while he speaketh such contraries, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, that good workes must be built on the foundation of faith; and with an other breath, that good life is the right way to bring faith, (and yet all may see he speaketh of one and the selfe same faith in both places) must he not needes by so teaching, deceiue the simple reader while he not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to vnderstand what is taught, cannot possibly practise that which he ought?</p>
   <p>And it was not to be doubted (to speake euen in charitie as in conscience we ought) that the said author promising in that his booke of Resolution, that he would adde two other parts to it, (as thereby confessing, that it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone was an insufficient worke of it selfe, to be set forth; and therefore dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to intangle and snare the ignorant) and yet cannot in eighteene yeares finde a time to fulfill his promise; it was not to be doubted (I say) but that he was well content to deceiue and trouble many that should reade it: As if one should but preach the wrath of God for sinne to a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth persons, (whereas his booke hath been in the hands of thousands) and should come no more in eighteene yeares, to helpe them out of feare and doubt, and how to liue afterwards, it would be condemned and that iustly, and cryed out of by all aduised people. And yet we may conclude, without any doubt, knowing his religion what it is (if euer he had any such meaning, to set out two other parts) that they should haue been as sound as this one is, that is to say, vnwholesome, full of damnable errors, and vncomfortable: For can men gather grapes of thornes, or figges of thistles? No more can any sound fruite be reaped or comfort gotten by false and vnsauorie doctrine. But for <hi>Parsons</hi> deuotion (whereof his booke beares so great a shew) or how little of the labour was his, or how little honestie is in the man, yea rather how great iniquitie: let them of his owne religion testifie, I meane the secular priests in their bookes against the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suites.</p>
   <p>But to say no more of <hi>Parsons:</hi> The other hath little in him worthie any account or reckoning, and to this purpose very nothing. To goe forward therefore, seeing this was one cause why I tooke this worke in hand, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Iesuites cast in our teeth the want of such bookes, as may direct a Christian aright through his whole course towards the kingdome of heauen, and yet that which they teach tending thereto, is but as poyson in a golden cuppe; although, as I haue said, there are many of my brethren, who had been fitter for this seruice then my selfe, if they had not been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed some other way: yet I nothing doubt by the helpe of God, to frame out of the word of God by that little helpe of my knowledge and experience, such a direction for Christians (all ostentation, and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison of learning set aside) as shall giue them small aduantage of boasting, and shall be both more pleasing to God, and more for the comforting the heart of him, who listeth to be directed by it, then poperie can affoord: and withall, a direction, that hath not only been shaped out after the rules of the Scripture, but also such as hath been and is practized and followed so farre forth, as of sinfull flesh may be looked for, both of minister and people, and approoued of those who haue excelled, &amp; gone before many, in both.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="8"/>And although I denie not, but that many things might haue been farre better set downe, and expressed, then I am able to doe; yet that none thinke me to haue taken in hand a matter aboue my reach, and wherein I haue no skill, thus much I say, that for these twentie yeares and more I haue ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at this, in my reading, preaching, and liuing, and in the obseruing of my selfe, and the example of others, what communion and neere ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance there may be betwixt God and a Christian, what hold may be laid on the promises of God, what strength may be gotten against sinne, what freedome and libertie we may haue by faith, what setlednes and constancie in a godlie life, what comfort, and reioycing the children of God by his free graunt, may haue, euen in this life, and that both sound and constant, which shall not be taken from them: also how farre the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit may ouercome the flesh, and how the diuell may be resisted. And more especially for these seauen yeares and more, I haue more particularly set my selfe about the matter, which in this booke is contained (which how weakely soeuer it be performed, I haue therein a good conscience:) First, to shew, both how a man may become a true beleeuer, be brought into the fauour of God, and afterwards how he may be directed to leade his life daily: And therefore I haue not suddenly nor vnaduisedly set vpō this. And what helpe I haue been able to get from others, as my conuenient opportunitie hath giuen leaue, I haue not neglected. The which I set downe (as I said) that none may thinke me fantastically to haue gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to broch some noueltie, but rather to offer that to the people of God, which hath with good aduise been gathered for their edifying.<note place="margin">The seuenth reason.</note> But now to returne, the last reason mouing me to take this worke in hand, is, that they who haue inioyed my ministerie aboue these twentie yeares, might haue me (as many of them haue oft desired) after a sort putting them in remembrance of that which I haue taught them in my life time, many yeares after I shall be taken from among them. This shall suffice to be spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of my intent and purpose in this treatise, with the reasons thereof.</p>
   <p>Now it remaineth further to acquaint the reader with the order,<note place="margin">The third point in the preface.</note> which I vse in the same, and to giue some instructions, that hee may reade it with the more profit; and that it may be more plaine and easie to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand (which I doe especially intend) then otherwise it should be. First, therefore, because I haue written it for their sakes chiefly, which are truely called to be Gods Children, and haue an interest in his promises, as being conuerted to him from the subiection of the diuell: first I say,<note place="margin">The contents and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the whole booke, in seuen seuerall trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises.</note> my purpose is in the formost treatise to shew, who are his, and who they are which in an holy, and humble manner may rest satisfied in his promises, against all dreadfull feare and doubt which might disquiet them: that so neither the loose liuers may deceiue themselues with an opinion of that, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth not to them: nor Gods children be depriued of that,<note place="margin">The first trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise.</note> which is their owne, and the ignorant of both sorts that list, may learne to know better and amend their estate. In the second, I meane to shew,<note place="margin">The second treatise.</note> what course of life such persons must walke in, throughout their dayes, and how they are to carie themselues both towards God and men, which I thinke ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to lay forth as cleerely as I can, and in some ample manner for
<pb facs="9"/>
the more full satisfying of the ignorant sort. From these two, all the other points handled in this booke doe arise.<note place="margin">The third trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise.</note> Therefore in the third, I will shew what are the meanes whereby this life may be maintained, and how the beleeuer shall vse the same, to the end that this whole and great worke of worshipping &amp; seruing God, may not be taken for a bare matter of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as the most doe make it: or (which is little better) for a seruing of God by halues, as too many professors of the Gospell doe vse it: but for a faithfull regarding of our wayes, that they may be shaped out after Gods will.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The fourth treatise.</note>Now this practising of the godly life is performed by following a daily direction to guide vs, and whiles we doe euery day with conscience set our selues to honour and obey God, as in our callings, and by other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions offered, we shall be able, and not wanderingly and vncertainly, as we haue been wont to doe. And so this shall bee set downe in the fourth treatise. And this is one of the points in this booke which requireth to be read againe and againe, as being neither commonly intreated of, and of singular vse to such as desire to take good by it, especially not being able otherwise to guide themselues.<note place="margin">The fift trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise.</note> In the fift, I make the reader acquainted with the lets, which will hinder him (though he be willing to be directed daily) from this course, except he will be perswaded to arme himselfe with such helps, as wherby he may withstand them: and remedies against these lets shall in this fift treatise be set downe, as farre as shall be thought expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient.<note place="margin">The sixt trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise.</note> The sixt shall set before thee sundrie priuiledges and blessings, which God doth peculiarly bequeath vnto, and bestow vpon his beloued ones, besides such benefits as they haue in common with the men of the world. By the which, as by other reasons, the faithfull may see themselues perswaded,<note place="margin">The seuenth treatise.</note> with much more chearefulnes, and greater willingnes to leade a christian life daily, and to shine as lights in example to others. In the seuenth and last, such obiections as may be brought and alledged by any, either weake christians, or carnall cauillers, against the practising of the daily direction, shall be sufficiently answered; that thereby the truth appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring more clearely, many such as desire vnfainedly to doe well, and yet haue not learned to guide themselues by any plaine direction, out of the Scriptures, may haue this as an helpe vnto them to see that which the Scripture hath reuealed hereof. All which, though I direct not this worke to the vnreformed, may be in stead of an exhortation vnto all loose and careles persons, (though more briefly, seeing there is enough written of that argument) to moue them to rouse vp themselues, and to awake out of their deadly sleepe, and not to cast away their soules for the loue of their sinnes, (which they may be sure that God will finde out howsoeuer they hide them) but to seeke betimes, that they be vnburthened of them, cast them vp as a most filthie gorge, and auoide the vengeance of Gods wrath which wil otherwise most surely come vpon them for it: For though sinne be sweete in the committing of it, yet it will be bitter, when it comes to be repented of: and most bitter, when without repentance, it must be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted for.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The fourth point of the preface, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting the reader, how to reade this booke with most profit.</note>Now it remaineth to direct the reader how to bestow his time profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb facs="9"/>
herein, and how he may reade it to his benefit. For I doubt nothing, but he that shall be conuersant in it, desiring to be directed in his course, shall thinke his time well spent, so as he be helped to vnderstand the same. First therfore let him reade the contents of it briefly set downe in the table before the booke, to helpe his memorie; then the marginall notes of the chapters. And if he conceiue and vnderstand the short summe of it so set downe; then let him reade the booke it selfe, till he be acquainted with and vnderstand it: wherein if his capacitie be the weaker and shallower, he must desire the helpe of some which are more skilfull (and better able to see the drift, scope and meaning of it) then himselfe, especially in such points of it, as are more hard and difficult, either to vnderstand, or to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise. For although many shall haue no neede of this directing of them to reade it with profit, because they can easily direct themselues when they once know the generall parts, and argument of it, as before is mentioned: yet because my desire herein is as well to helpe and benefit the plaine, and simple, (such as many of them are, amongst whom I haue preached the same) as well as to bring the wiser and more learned sort acquainted with the practise of it, therefore I know they shall haue neede thereof.</p>
   <p>Now when they shall vnderstand it in some good sort, let them weigh and consider, how far forth they haue had vse of it heretofore, as whether they haue according to the first part of this booke, by the ministerie of any sound preacher of the Gospell, attained to the assurance of their saluation, and of the forgiuenes of their sinnes, wherein if any will take it as granted, though falsely, (as they are most readie to doe so, who haue least felt the burthen of their sinnes, and therefore are indeed furthest off from it) here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I say, if any will needs deceiue themselues, I cannot helpe it, but they are like to reade the rest with lesse fruit and comfort, and to goe without the vse of it in their liues, whatsoeuer they hope for. And therefore such I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise to take most paine in the first part: I meane in the doctrine of it, and reading other treatises concerning the matter, as Master <hi>Mores</hi> and other catechismes; and Maister <hi>Perkins</hi> workes, namely, his booke intituled the graine of mustard seede: And to raise all the doubts they can to any expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced teacher or brother, and to looke for, and see those things worke vpon them which are taught there, both the doctrine of humiliation, and also of iustification and deliuerance.</p>
   <p>If this be attained, let them consider for the better assuring themselues hereof, that they cannot but affect, loue, imbrace, and delight in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of sanctification, and <hi>repentance from dead workes,</hi> I meane they shall desire to practise the godly and christian life when they see that it is the commaundement of him who loueth them most dearely, and what it is, and wherein it consisteth, which is the summe of the second treatise of this booke. And to this end, let them reade, and by marking seeke, (as such who would finde) that they may see what sinne there is in them which they are not willing nor desirous to forsake (if there be any) or among duties ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally appertaining to all, or particularly touching themselues, which they cannot submit themselues vnto. If there be either of these found in them, as that they cannot leaue nor be brought to renounce some parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb facs="10"/>
sins, nor obtaine of themselues to be subiect to some speciall duties, as thinking it too strict (as thus it may be with many, and no doubt is) such must know, that it is the doctrine of the Scripture, that all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of God be had in account of vs,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.10. Heb. 13.18. Matth. 5.18.</note> and conscience made of one as well as of another: which if they see and acknowledge according to the word of God, they cannot but submit themselues thereunto, if they haue rightly imbraced the doctrine of the former treatise, that as in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and knowledg they yeeld; so their heart and affections may goe with the same. And so doing, God will worke in them by little and little (seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it by prayer of faith) euen as he wrought the like in them before, and weakned such rebelliousnes in their hearts alreadie.</p>
   <p>If therefore the teachable and christian reader be thus farre wrought vpon by the spirit of God, that he thus fauour, approoue, and giue ouer himselfe to be made truely repentant, which is that that is required in the second treatise of this booke; then is he fit to occupie himselfe about, and to be conuersant in the third and fourth part of it, that is to say, in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which requireth a daily walking in a Christian course, by the vse of such helps as are appointed of God for that purpose; and some of them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so daily, as in the proper place shall appeare. For euery true Christian is to know, that the religion and worship of God must be in vse and practise among the imbracers of it, as well one day as another. But how shall any be able to keepe his heart in frame, and reforme his life daily by the meanes which God hath appointed, as in the third and fourth part of this booke is required: except he be first a liker, and an allower of all knowne points of dutie, and doe hartily renounce all euill, as is required in the second part? Which being done, let him looke to grow daily more strong in faith, whereby he may hold, and keepe fast the certaintie of Gods fauour daily, and constantly. And not as too many (and yet the people of God) doe, who are not acquainted with this: that their confidence should be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained daily, or a good conscience in their particular actions regarded, and that on one day as another, but thinke it enough at sometimes to haue this care. Neither let any looke to repell this as too strict, vnder pretence of weightie affaires, and their owne infirmitie. For this is but the delusion of the diuell, as shall be shewed, who will easily perswade it to be more then needeth. This is that which must be learned out of the third and fourth part.</p>
   <p>And when this is vnderstood, approued, consented vnto, and aymed at, the fift part of the booke shall be cleare and easie to vnderstand, and what vse he should make of it, namely, of the lets and hinderances which the diuell raiseth vp to hold him backe from this course of life, and the practise of the same: of the which some I will set downe, and helpe him the better to know many others thereby. And he that shall indeuour to direct his life, and take heede to his wayes, as he shall by Gods word be taught, shall breake through many of the lettes, which yet shall strongly hold backe and hinder other men, as the fift part will shew: and if he be for a season withdrawne from a godly course, yet he shall there finde helpes and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies to recouer againe; and little ease, otherwise.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="10"/>And if there be any difficultie in conforming a mans selfe after this forementioned doctrine (as I deny not but the flesh will finde many) yet against them all, let him proceede and reade with good regard the sixt Treatise, wherein are set downe the manifold and goodly prerogatiues and priuiledges, which God hath bequeathed to his people to hearten them on, and incourage them to godlines, and to make the christian life easie; and he shall see great light, and finde exceeding force therein, to stirre him vp to goe forward mightily against all fainting. And then he shall not be moued for all the obiections, cauils and fleshly reasons which he shall reade in the seuenth part. For the comfort and experience, which he shall partly enioy alreadie, and partly hope for and expect afterwards, shall make thē vanish away as smoke, although otherwise they are able to hurt and sting, as fier. And then when in the due consideration of the whole, he shall see what the blessednes and manifold good things are, which he in part hath alreadie, and shall afterwards inioy both here and in the life to come, he shall see what infinit cause he hath to praise God for his portion, that he hath rather beautified and blessed him with his fauour and graces then many other, whereby he may walke so comfortably, and that in this vale of miseries, to Gods kingdome.</p>
   <p>And thus I aduise thee (good reader, as I know it shall be best for thee) to bestow thy trauel about this booke: wherein I appoint thee no certaine time, nor houres, seeing all which would profit by it, cannot spend their time alike about this, or any other such exercise. But this know, that this booke tendeth to teach thee the practise of thy knowledge, and not to know onely: and that I haue gathered together into this one, the things which are dispersedly contained in many other. And therefore in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, ouer and besides the ordinarie reading of the holy Scriptures, thou maiest bestow the more time about it, as thy leasure will permit, conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that once or twice reading a booke for practise, is not enough.</p>
   <p>Lastly, seeing the whole matter herein contained, is to serue thee and stand thee in steed, as setting before thee a direction to gouerne thy whole life, thou must not thinke thy labour and time much, though thou beest occupied in it for many yeares together: for as much as the fruite shall be greater, the longer that thou hast been exercised in it: and yet thy labour lesse, yea easie and pleasant: for so shalt thou grow better acquainted with the vse of it, which in one word is to make thy life more sweet and sauorie, then thou couldest looke for, that is, happie here, and hereafter, for euer. Reade therefore not onely to be able to report what thou hast found here, but especially to finde it thine owne which I doe teach: and to be setled daily in the gouernment which this doctrine drawne out of his word offereth thee, so as thou maiest see that God, in the setting forth of it, hath directed me.</p>
   <p>Reade with a quiet, teachable and a meeke spirit, desirous of that which I labour to bring thee to, rather then with a curious head to carpe and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill; or censure that which thou dost not practise nor follow. A dramme of grace is better then a pound of censorious wittines: remember that all our naturall gifts, and faculties of our soules should be sanctified: I goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb facs="11"/>
to make thee see thy selfe inwardly and outwardly to be trained vp in Gods family: where the heart must be well seasoned, as well as thy whole life well ordered, till thou findest that which many a thriftie person doth in his outward estate; namely, that diet to be ordinarie with him, which sometime had been feasting cheere: for, when a poore man by his trauell and paine hath brought this to passe, hee thinkes his estate good, and that which pleaseth him exceedingly well: So, labour thou in thy spirituall worke and seruing of God, to finde that gaine, and thriuing therein, that thou maiest make thy soule as ioyfull euery day, and at as great peace with God, as sometime thou scarcely haddest obtained once in the weeke or month. Which grace and prerogatiue that thou mayest make much of, when thou hast it, looke backe and remember with thankes vnfained how farre thou hast been off from it, and how little hope thou once haddest of obtaining it, when thou wert easily mastered of thy sinnes and passions, and know that it must cost him many a prayer, and grone for it, who is yet without it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he shall be partaker of it.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>RICHARD ROGERS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>