<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS MVCH HO∣NORED FATHER, Sr. ANTHONY ROVS of Halton in Corn∣wall, Knight.</title>
           <author>Rous, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116243_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11067</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21338</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116243</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS MVCH HO∣NORED FATHER, Sr. ANTHONY ROVS of Halton in Corn∣wall, Knight.</title>
                 <author>Rous, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The arte of happines : Consisting of three parts, whereof the first searcheth out the happinesse of man. The second, particularly discouers and approues it- The third, sheweth the meanes to attayne and increase it. By Francis Rous</title>
                 <author>Rous, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Parker, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 <publisher>Fetherstone (Featherstone), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Parker, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 438, 441-506 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HIS MVCH HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORED FATHER, S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. ANTHONY ROVS <hi>of Halton in Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall, Knight.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the Author and the work bee conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, it is no hard matter to finde, to whom the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor should first of all offer his worke. A sonne cannot
<pb facs="3"/>
present his labours more fitly then to a Father, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially when they bring with them so excellent a thing as Blessednesse. And although I know you haue beene an ancient Trauailer in the path of Felicitie, so that the commendation of your posteritie shall bee to follow your steps, yet I am assured, it cannot but bee a comfort to you, to see some increase from aboue, where your careful education hath planted &amp; watered below; in which you haue farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the vsuall prouidēce of Fathers, that ordinarily lookes no farther then the bodie, pride, and earth. I cōfesse, the outward shewes
<pb facs="3"/>
of this world had so farre transported me, that I was very vnlikely to haue made this kinde of Matter the maine busines of my Time, but I tooke ship to goe to <hi>Tarsus,</hi> euen to forraine Countries, and in mine owne beganne the studie of the Law, vntill a storme from heauen chased mee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to the studie of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, wherein I haue found so much comfort and assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance from aboue, that the incouragement thereof is to mee in stead of a voice speaking in mine eare; This is the way, walke in it: And in this way I desire to walke as stedfastly, as bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly infirmitie, and the neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie
<pb facs="4"/>
distractions of this life will permit, vntill my Time shall bee no more, that so I may passe immediately from the contemplation of Felicitie, vnto the fruition. This felicitie I likewise wish vnto you with most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and heartie prayer, and that this worke following may giue some (though small) aduancement to it, that so you may reape a little, where you haue sown much.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From my house in Laurake, <date>Aprill 29.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your sonne in all du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and obseruance.
FRANCIS ROVS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>