<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his singuler goode frendt and bro∣ther in Christ Master. D. G. N O. desyreth grace and pea∣ce from God the fat∣her / thorowe the∣lorde Iesus Christ.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1528</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116283_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04489</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1462.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116283</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his singuler goode frendt and bro∣ther in Christ Master. D. G. N O. desyreth grace and pea∣ce from God the fat∣her / thorowe the∣lorde Iesus Christ.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Rede me and be nott wrothe for I saye no thynge but trothe : I will ascende makynge my state so hye, that my pompous honoure shall never dye. O caytyfe when thou thynkest least of all, with confusion thou shalt have a fall</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schott, Johann</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Strasbourg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1528</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To his singuler goode frendt and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Christ Master. D. G. N O. desyreth grace and pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce from God the fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her / thorowe the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorde Iesus Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y youre last letter / dere brother in Christ / I perceved / that youre desyre was / to have the lytle worke which ye sent / wele examened / and diligently put into prynt. Which thynge (the bōde of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite / <note place="margin">Ioh. xv</note> where with not alonly you ād I / but we with the whole nombre of Christis cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen flocke / remaynge amonge oure nacion of englisshe mē / are knet together / purly for the truthes sake pondered) I coulde do no lesse but fulfill and accōplysshe. For as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as it is a thynge so necessary. Where of no doute / shall sprynge grett frute vnto the fāmisshed / and lyght vnto theym which of lōge seasō have bene sore blyndfolded.<note place="margin">Ma. xxv</note> Th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough the rāmysshe resydue of gotes / so far re envred with man̄is blynde reason (wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ich repute grett felicite to make men beleve / goode to be the naturall cause of evill / dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to procede oute of light / and lyinge to
<pb facs="3"/>
be grownded in trouth / <note place="margin">Mat. xxiiij.</note> and to make of the worde of lyfe the glave of death / contrary to all trueth) that scripture calleth theym faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce teachers / and bryngers in prevely of da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mpnable sectes / <note place="margin">ij. pe. j.ij</note> evē denyinge the lorde that bought theym / and brynge on their owne heddes swyfte dampnacion / for their lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge of many into their dampnable waies.<note place="margin">ap. xviij Ma. vij</note> Of whose boddies annd soules thus once blynded and ledde out of the narowe waye of lyfe / into the broade waye of perdicion / thorowe covetousnes they make their mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandyse.<note place="margin">ij. Pet. ij</note> Wherby the waye of trueth (that is to saye the glorious gospell of Christ) is evill spocken of. In so moche that they after this man̄er sealed with the marke of the gr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ett beast of the erth / whose consciences.<note place="margin">apo xvj j.<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>i.iiij</note> S. paul descrybeth to be singed with the hott ye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rō of blasphemy / only geve hede to the spr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etes of erroure / and dyvelysshe doctryne of theym which speake faulce through hrpocri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sy / <note place="margin">iiij.</note> forbyddynge to mary / and cōmaundyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge to abstayne from meates and soche wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) cannot but barke there art / forbid it / ād with all violence persecute the reders there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of. Yet.<note place="margin">ij. Pet. j</note> I neverthelesse with you / doinge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fter the apostles erudicion / as longe as I folowe no decevable fables / <note place="margin">ij. Pe. jij</note> will not be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligēt
<pb facs="3"/>
to put my brethren in remembraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce (thogh they partly knowe them their sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves / and are stablysshed in the present tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) of those thynges wherby they maye the more evidētly note the disceatfulnes of mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tall man / and the better come vnto the kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wledge of the im̄ortall god. Seynge the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me at hōde wherin god of his infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy / <note place="margin">Luc. j Rom. j Ac. xiij Ebre. iij mar. iij xvj lu. iiij.ix j. Io. v Lu. viij. Ma. vij</note> hath ordened before to make theym tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe Christ oure lorde parte takers also of his glorious will and porpos. evē as in the gospell oure saveoure before to all his hadd promesed. I therfore cōsyderynge the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lde thus to be wrapped in mysery and blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dnes (ād now ī these latter dayes becom an hole or denne of falce foxy hipocrites / and a manciō for all ravenynge wolves disgysed in lambes skynnes / which hate all love / and with oute drede of god wander but for thei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re praye) have iudged it a thynge moste con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>veniēt / to sett this smale treatous as a glas or myroure most cleare before all mens ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. In the preface where of manyfestly they shall perceave / howe gretr daunger nowe a dayes it is / the trueth other to describe with penne / or with tonge to declare.<note place="margin">Luc. vj</note> In the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaciō folowynge / made by a bely beast / engendred amonge the gresy / <note place="margin">Ro. xvj</note> or anoynted
<pb facs="4"/>
heap / wother wyse called the papysticall se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cte (whom Christ calleth a croked / <note place="margin">Ma. xvj xvij Luce. ix</note> vntaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arde / and cruell generatiō of venemous vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers) they may surly groape and fele / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of oure spretuall lordes / masters / ād ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lars (falcely so named) have proceded / and are come. with what presomcion they disd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ayne the auncient and true noble bloud. ād what preeminēce and dignite they have ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayned through their faulce ād crafti bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge vppe of the blasphemous masse / <note place="margin">ma. xxiij</note> wh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ich principlally is their holde / stede / and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Forthermore in the dialoge ensuynge or brefe interlude / is mas descrybed with his abhominable ministers. as Popes / Car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinalls / bisshops / abbotes / montes / fryres / and lyke wother. wherin also is declared whatt trees they are with their frute.<note place="margin">ma. vij. epis. Iu.</note> annd what they shall remayne their masse once disanulled / ād putt downe. Which all well consydered / I hoape that the reder what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he be / will nott take this worke as a thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nge convicious / or a principle of hatred ād debate.<note place="margin">Rom. ij</note> nor yett despyse the ryches of the go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dnes / and of the pacience / of the longe so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance of god. but will remember that his kyndnes only leadeth hym to repentaunce.<note place="margin">1. Cor. ij</note> and mekely with the sprete of quyetnes / fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
<pb facs="4"/>
iudge it / and then cōsydre hym silfe. and fautlesse he shall fynde it a grett occasion / to love / and also to thācke god his father most mercifull / which of his tender mercy hath nott delyvered hym vppe vnto a leawd my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nde / <note place="margin">Rom. j. Ioa. viij Rom. ij</note> with these vessels of wrathe / ād child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren of the devill / to do those thynges which are nott comly / ful of all vnrightousnes / for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nication / wickednes / covetousnes / malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnes .<abbr>c</abbr>. and sofered hym nott to become lyke vnto theym / a hater of god / and of his godly worde. agaynst whose vngodlines / and vnrightousnes / the wrath of the heven<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly god apereth. because they with holde the true rightōsnes of god / <note place="margin">Rom. j</note> whiche cōmeth th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the lyght of the gospell of Christ / in the vnrightousnes of mans lawes and tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions. Ye / ād as sayth. S. paul / though th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey knowe the rightousnes of god / howe th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey which soche thynges cōmitt are worthey of death / yett not only do the same / but also have pleasure in the doars of them. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are before god with oute excuse. seinge that knowinge god / they glorify hym nott as god. nor yett are thanckfull. but we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re full of vanities in their ymaginacions. countynge theym selves wyse where as in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dede they are foles. For with their folysshe
<pb facs="5"/>
and blynde hert / they tourne the glory of the immortall god / vnto the similitude of the y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of mortall man. He shall lykwyse cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly perceve / that we of duty colde do no le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sse / but for the preservaciō and tutell of the innocent and simple / to declare the pestilent doblenes / and decevable seducciō of the w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icked. acordīge to the doctryne shewed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs every where by Christ oure master.<note place="margin">Ioan. vj.x.</note> wh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ich cam co save / annd not to destroye. For one rottē apple / lytell and lytell putrifieth an whole heape.<note place="margin">mat. xiij Luc. xij j. Cor. v</note> a lytell sower leven the whole lompe of dowe. one rancklynge member / the whole boddy. Shortly to cōclude. Here in I am well persuaded / lett the vngodly ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>are and barcke never so lowde / that the fyre which Christ cam to kyndle on erth / cannott butt burne.<note place="margin">Luc. xij</note> that is to saye / his godly worde forevermore encreace and cōtinue.<note place="margin">ij. re. xxij Psa. xvij ciiij cxviij</note> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dere brother / yf eny mo soche smale stic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes come vnto youre hondes / which ye shall iudge apte vnto the augmētaciō of this fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / sende them vnto me (yf in englonde they maye not be publisshed) and by godd is gr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ace with all my power ād possibilite / I sh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all so endever my sylfe to kyndle theym / that as many as are of the sede of abrahā shall se their light / <note place="margin">Ioa. viij Mat. v</note> and therby gloryfy their father
<pb facs="5"/>
celestiall / which kepe you and youres conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nully strengthynge you with his spre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of comforte to his glory for ever Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>