<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116656_Bo2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03006</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13147</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116656</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true relation of the French kinge his good successe, in winning from the Duke of Parma, his fortes and trenches, and slaieng 500. of his men, with the great famine that is now in the sayd dukes campe : With other intelligences giuen by other letters since the second of May. 1592. A most wonderfull and rare example, the like wherof, neuer happended since the beginning of the world, of a certaine mountaine in the Ile of Palme, which burned continually, for fiue or six weeks together, with other both fearful &amp; stra [n] ge sightes, seene in the ayre, ouer the same place</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 20 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="19" facs="11"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, this note comming to my hands before the impres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion hereof vvas ended, <hi>I</hi> thought it good to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part it vnto thee, rather out of place, then not at all, as a thing vvhich vvill giue thee great light to the great vnderstanding of the vvhole book.</p>
   <p>This Ile of <hi>Palme</hi> spoken of before, is one of the seuen Ilandes of the <hi>Canaris,</hi> vvell knovvne to diuerse merchantes here in London. <hi>Ingenio</hi> is scituate vvithin the same Iland.</p>
   <p>Manie of the inhabitantes vvhereof <hi>I</hi> meane of the <hi>Ile</hi> of <hi>Palme,</hi> vvere forced to go out, and to depart from thence, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saking their landes, goodes and all, and to dvvell some of them at Gomorra, some
<pb n="20" facs="12"/> of them in the <hi>Ile</hi> of Tenerife, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some to the graund <hi>Canaris,</hi> supposing verily that the same Iland vvoulde haue sunke. And for the great aboundance of ashes, vvhich rained dovvne, they coulde not sovv their corne in October follovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
   <p>The lieuetenant of the Iland, sent the narration heereof to the court of Spaine being at <hi>Madrill,</hi> penned by a notarie publick, vvith three other notaries hands to it, desiring certaine Lordes of the same Court, to send their opinion, vvhat these fearefull tokens might prognosticate.</p>
   <pb facs="12"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>