<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader, IOHN BRADFORD wisheth the true knowledge and peace of Iesus Christ, our alone and sufficient Sauiour.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116484_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16596</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3503</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116484</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader, IOHN BRADFORD wisheth the true knowledge and peace of Iesus Christ, our alone and sufficient Sauiour.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A double summons : the one, to vnfained repentance. The other, to the worthie receiuing of the Lords Supper. Deliuered in two notable sermons: made, by that worthy martyr of Christ, Iohn Bradford: who suffered in Smith-field An [n] o. Domini. 1555</title>
                 <author>Bradford, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 140, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the Christian Reader,</hi> IOHN BRADFORD wisheth the true knowledge and peace of Iesus Christ, our alone and <hi>sufficient Sauiour.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>REAT and heauy is Gods anger against vs, as the most grieuous plague of the death of our late King (a Prince of all that euer was since Christs ascension into Heauen, in any Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, peerlesse) doth Prognosticate. For when Gods iudgement hath begun with his Childe, let other men thinke as they can, I surely can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be perswaded otherwise, but that a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and bitter cuppe of Gods vengeance, is ready to be poured out for vs English-men to drinke. The whelpe God hath beaten to fray the bandogge: Iudgement is begun at Gods house: In Gods mercie to him-wards, hee is taken away, that his eyes should not see the miseries which we shall feele.</p>
   <p>He was too good to tarry with vs, so wicked,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.</note> so froward, so peruerse, so obstinate, so malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<pb facs="3"/>so hypocriticall, so couetous, vncleane, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true, proud, and carnall a generation. I wil not goe about to paint vs out in our colours: God by his plagues and vengeance, I feare me, will paint and point vs out: Wee haue so mocked with him and his Gospell, that we shall feele it is no bourding with him.</p>
   <p>Of long time we haue couered our couetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and carnality, vnder the cloake of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell; so that all men shall see vs to our shame, when he shall take his Gospell away, and giue it to a people that will bring forth the fruits of it: To let his Gospell tarry with vs, he cannot; for we despise it, contemne it, are glutted with it. Since his Gospell came amongst vs, we say now, we had neuer plenty; therefore, againe, let vs goe and worship the Queene of heauen, and to prouoke the Lord to anger. The earth cannot abide now the words and Sermons of <hi>Amos.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Amos</hi> 7. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.</note> The cause of all rebellion, is <hi>Amos</hi> and his preaching. It is <hi>Paul</hi> and his fellowes, that make all out of order. <hi>Summa,</hi> the Gospell is now, <hi>Panto on peripsema,</hi> &amp; <hi>catharma tou cosmou,</hi> The our-east and curse of the Realme, and so are the Preachers: therefore, out of the dores with them. So that, I say, God cannot let his Gospell tarry with vs, but must needes take it away, to doe vs some pleasure therein: for so shall we thinke for a time; as the Sodomitanes thought, when <hi>Lot</hi> departed from them: as the old world thought,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. <hi>Gen.</hi> 7</note> when <hi>Noe</hi> crept into his Arke: as the Ieru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>olomitanes thought, when the Apostles went thence to Peltis. Then
<pb facs="3"/>were they merry, then was all pastime. When <hi>Moses</hi> was absent, then went they to eating and drinking, and rose againe to play: But alas,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Exod.</hi> 32</note> sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly came the floud, and drowned them: Gods wrath waxed hot against them. Then was lamentation, mourning and woe: then was crying out, wringing of hands, renting of clothes, sobbing and sighing for the miseries fallen; out of the which they could not scape. Well, if hee take that away, for a time, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance, we shall be quiet, but at length we shall feele the want to our woe, at length hee will haue at vs, as at them.</p>
   <p>O bee thou mercifull vnto vs, and in thine anger remember thy mercy: We haue sinned, we haue sinned, and therefore art thou angrie; ô be not angry for euer. Giue vs peace, peace, peace in the Lord: set vs to worke against sin, against Sathan, against our carnall desires, and giue vs the victory this way. This victory we obtaine by faith. This faith is not without Repentance, as her Gentleman-Vsher before her.</p>
   <p>This Vsher then, Repentance, if wee truely possessed, wee should be certaine of true faith, and so assured of the victory ouer death, hell, and Sathan. His workes then which hee hath stirred vp, would quaile, God would restore vs politique peace, right should be right, and haue right: Gods Gospell should tarrie with vs, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion should bee cherished, Superstition sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed: and so we yet something happy, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the great losse of our most graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="4"/>Liege, souereigne Lord. All these would come to passe you see, if the Gentleman-Vsher I speake of, I meane, Repentance, were at Inne with vs. As if he be absent, we may be certaine, that Lady Faith is absent. Wherefore, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be vanquished of the world, the flesh, and the diuell, and so wil Sathans workes pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, though not in all things to bleare our eyes, yet in that thing which he most of all desireth. Therefore, to Repentance, for our selues pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately, and for the Realme and Church pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly, euery one shall labour to stirre vp both our selues and others. This, to the end, that for my part I might helpe, I haue presently put forth a Sermon of Repentance, which had lyen by me halfe a yeere at the least, for the most part of it. For, the last Summer, as I was abroad preaching in the Countrey, my chance was to make a sermon of Repentance, the which was earnestly of diuers desired of me, that I should giue it them written, or else put it forth in print, which I could not doe, for I had not written it, and so I told them.</p>
   <p>But when no nay would serue, I promised to write it as I could, at my leisure; this leisure I prolonged so long, that (as I think) I offended them: so did I please my selfe, as one more glad to reade other mens writings, then in such sort to publish mine owne, for other men to reade: not that I would others not to profit by mee, but that I, knowing how slender my store is, would be loth, the enemies should therby take occasion of speaking.</p>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <p>But when I considered this present time, to occasion men now to look vpon all things, in such sort as might mooue them to godlinesse, rather then to any curious questioning: I, for the satisfying of my promise, and profiting of the simple, ignorant, and rude, haue now cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed this Sermon to be printed: the which, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech God for his Christs sake, to vse as a mean, whereby of his mercie, it may please him to worke in me, and many others, true hearty repentance for our sinnes, to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his name.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Thus fare thou well in the Lord,</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>The xij. of Iuly.</hi> 1553.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>