<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the curteous and beneuolent Reader.</title>
           <author>K., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116155_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11048</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21311</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116155</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the curteous and beneuolent Reader.</title>
                 <author>K., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The courtiers academie : comprehending seuen seuerall dayes discourses: wherein be discussed, seuen noble and important arguments, worthy by all gentlemen to be perused. 1 Of beautie. 2 Of humane loue. 3 Of honour. 4 Of combate and single fight. 5 Of nobilitie. 6 Of riches. 7 Of precedence of letters or armes originally written in Italian by Count Haniball Romei, a gentleman of Ferrara, and translated into English by I.K</title>
                 <author>Romei, Annibale, conte</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 295, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the curteous and beneuolent Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Esides many defects, the which acknowledging in my selfe (curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reader) craue thy benigne and fauorable construction, there may bee also some imperfections, which either comming shorte, of the singularity of these times, or lightning on the view of malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant eies, may, besides a generall deprauation for the most part in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to al mens labours, turne me further to some bitter, and particular reprehension. Translation therfore in generall by some vaine pretendants, in tongues, and languages, hath bin thought alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether a thing, not only vnnecessary, but further preiudicial, the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest reason leading them thereunto, being this, as I suppose, that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge being an ornament, most befitting those noble or honorable, who command ignorance agreeing best with the vulgar sort, who be sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect and obey: it is therfore requisit (say they) that high wisedome, and excellent workes, should be concealed from common sight, lest they through equall experience, and knowledge in things (according to the ordinary condition therof) puffed vp, shake off likewise that humility of spirit, which shuld comprehend them vnder the obedience of laws and magistrates. Neither in my opinion, for some arguments in bookes discussed of, doe they greatly mistake, when this their opinion shal be grounded vpon so sound a consideration, rather then on a vaine osten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in, themselues wherby they would willingly retaine, some co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of excellencie, by reseruing vnto themselues in a restrained tongue, that which peraduenture therin they do not absolutely vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, or which howsoeuer by publication, may be an occasion of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall document, and instruction to al men: To leaue comparison of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and whether straungers or our selues haue therein attained to
<pb facs="4"/>greatest excellencie and iudgement: obserue the ciuilest amongst christen nations who perceiuing (no doubt) the instability of men in al arts and professions, proceeding from the Chaos of opinions, grounded on the conceits of particular men, thoght good by this mean to reduce them to some reuiew of foundations and therfore we seethem to haue infinitely trauelled in the translation of Plato Aristotle Plutarch, and diuers other ancient writers into their vulgar tongues: as they themselues when they writ, made choise of their owne mother lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages: and we see daily that managed horses yeeld sooner to the bit of a disereet rider, then rough, and vnsadled coltes: and people well instructed, know best howsweet a thing it is to liue vnder gouernment.</p>
   <p>In a growne storme of heauy misfortune, it was my hap, to put in with the harbour of a worthy gentlemans house, where amongst sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie other relaxations for a distressed mind, a multitude of good, and commendable writers in the best languages was not the least, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to peruse these discourses, (although of too high a tenor for my hūble fortune) partly by perswasion, as likewise, in that I could not call to mind any so important booke, touching these subiects in the English tongue, I attempted this homely, &amp; vnworthy interpretation of them, wherin if I haue presumed any thing, either aboue my own conceit, or the good opinion of others, impute it to the special desire I had, that al mē honorable, either by birth, or instructiō, might be partakers of so necessary &amp; excellent discussions, alwaies crauing pardon, of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer defacement they endure, by my vnperfect and mother expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: whatsoeuer Poesie you herein meet withal (as with some you shal) it being rather accidental, then any waies by the noble author at the first intended, you may the more gratiously winke at my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects therein, as one, whom the oppression of fortune hath denied that serenity of mind, from whence (for the most part) that pleasant fury hath his deriuation, I haue therefore contended, only with bare rithming desinence voyd of all ornament, to expresse the meaning of such poetical citations as the author vseth, they being ordinarily alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged out of Petrarch whose verse in my opinion, euen in Italian, is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther weighty or sententious than heroical. And therfore I remēber I haue seen some of the same verses in this booke cited, by a good appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Laureate translated into English, the which, though they retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="4"/>the pith and substance, of the first author, yet (excepting alwaies better iudgements then my owne) they came very short of that lofty and aboundant profluence, with which many of our moderne Poemes are accompanied: considering withal, how too labored a transforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of words and sence, might haue offered my first author capital iniury, seeing he setteth them downe but as authorities wherein mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, more then wordes is to bee required: No lesse doubte I also of reprehension, for some words I haue vsed beyond common vse, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety leading me therto, rather then any affectation which consisteth not in so tollerable and commendable liberty, but rather in a friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous accumulation of words vnnecessarily produced in dilating of any argument: yet if any may lay vp in this our common treasury of lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, any choise ornaments, for the decorum &amp; coppy of our tongue. I know not who may better then they, conuersant in forraine writers, seeing besides a laudable emulation of others aboundance, euen very necessity in explication, inuiteth them thereunto: and therefore for want of better tearmes I haue bin driuen to vse some forged words, as spiritally, vertually, armiger, and other, which otherwise I could not wel tel how to haue expressed. Another thing there is, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation wherof maketh my eares to glow, with an imaginatiue ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearing of some bitter taxation: especially it consisting in that dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, whereof the least expectation wil not be had: for in the meane this author setteth downe for reducement of quarrels to peace, he hath prescribed a certaine forme of words, which no doubt to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny will seeme ridiculous, as, sauouring too much of feare, and pusillani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, which seuere censure notwithstanding in my iudgement, may deserue mittigation, if not in respect of the daungerous abuse of armes in these times: at least yet in calling to minde, what in the former discourses hath bin enioyned euery honorable man, vpon the instant of receiuing an iniury, to performe: the which once past, this voluntary, and kind accord, is not to spring from themselues, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from some other, who shall offer themselues to such vertuous solicitations, when it wilbe requisite (as he himselfe saith) to so good an end, to vse al commendable fallation, and by words of equiualent, and plausible signification to couer offences, preuenting by this meanes so many lamentable effects, as too ordinarily ensue, vpon inueterate,
<pb facs="5"/>and prosecuted quarrells: These be not al, but the principallest occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions (as I sùppose) which detraction in this my labor wil take hold of: the which notwithstanding curteous, and iudicial vnderstanders will so gratiously passe ouer, as that ther is no doubt but for al this, they wil find themselues wel satisfied by <hi>Patritio,</hi> in the explanation of true, essentiall, and sensible Beautie in Humane Loue by <hi>Guirino,</hi> in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Combate, and fighting for reputation by <hi>Gualinguo:</hi> in Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity by <hi>Varano:</hi> in riches by <hi>Taslone,</hi> and last of al, in that high and worthy controuersie touching precedence of Letters or Armes, after resolute conflict, beeween <hi>Patritio,</hi> and <hi>Brancaccio</hi> noble champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for each partie, the deepe, and iudicial doome of gratious Madam de <hi>Sala,</hi> will determine herein al scruple, and attribute due right, and desert: And therefore as this worthie circumstance of Iustice, shineth like a bright beame in euery noble, or liberall minde, so doe I hope also for my labour, to reape curteous and fauourable constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not onely of my own imperfections, but euen of those also that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily depend on the error of impression, &amp; if my poore battered name light into the fatal hands of malicious Impostors or odious scof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers: <hi>di buffoni mi beffo:</hi> and as it was said of that miserable Iaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine: <hi>C'est l'enfer, que les á crées.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>To be commaunded. I. K.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>