<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116748_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20853</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7232</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116748</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The tragicall legend of Robert, Duke of Normandy, surnamed Short-thigh, eldest sonne to William Conqueror. VVith the legend of Matilda the chast, daughter to the Lord Robert Fitzwater, poysoned by King Iohn. And the legend of Piers Gaueston, the great Earle of Cornwall: and mighty fauorite of king Edward the second. By Michaell Drayton. The latter two, by him newly corrected and augmented</title>
                 <author>Drayton, Michael</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                    <distributor>Ling (Lyng), Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>224 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>GEntlemen, since my first publishing of these tragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call cōplaints of <hi>Piers Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swton</hi> and <hi>Matilda</hi> it is not vnknowne to any which traffique with Poetry, how by the sinister dealing of some vnskilfull Printer, <hi>Prers Gawston</hi> hath been lately put sorth contrary to my will, with as manie faults as there be lynes in the same, beeing in deede at the suit no perfect Coppy, but left vnformed and vndigested, like a Beare vvhelpe before it is licke by the Dam. But now of late vnderstanding by the Statio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that they meant the thyrd time to bring it to the Presse, for which purpose as it seemed, they kept <hi>Matilda</hi> from prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, onely because they meant to ioyne thē
<pb facs="4"/>
together in one little volume, I haue taken some paine in them both to augment and polish them, sith I see they must goe to the publique view of the world: and with the old conceite of <hi>Apelles,</hi> (hearing the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of all that passed by) amended so much as the latchet. To these complaints written by mee two yeeres since, I haue added this third, of <hi>Robert</hi> Duke of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandie: A subiect in my poore opinion, as worthy as any, how soeuer I haue hanled it in the writing. Thus submitting my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to your discreet censure, I end.</p>
   <byline>M. D.</byline>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>