<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>B., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116327_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16604</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3511</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116327</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>B., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A preparation to the receiving of the Sacrament, of Christs Body and Bloud : Directing weake Christians how they may worthily receiue the same. By W. Bradshavv. With a profitable treatise of the same argument, written by another</title>
                 <author>Bradshaw, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Macham, Joyce</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 108, 5 leaves, 146 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="115"/>
   <pb facs="115"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>GOod Reader, after I had yeelded to the publishing of mine owne poore me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations vpon 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23. there came to my hands in writing, this ensuing Treatise, written some yeeres since by a godly and faithfull Pastor, for the direction of his owne people, in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy receiuing of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, at what time hee was first called vnto them.</p>
   <p>In the perusall whereof, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in my selfe well perswaded of the fulnesse and perspicuity of that doctrine of preparation, which it propoundeth to intreat of, the orderly method of euery part thereof, the plaine and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar
<pb facs="116"/> handling of the matter, &amp; that it did supply many need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full points of instruction that are wanting in mine owne Treatise; I was earnest with the Author to giue me leaue to publish the same, and to adioyne it as an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament and helpe vnto mine: which with much impportunitie at length I haue obtained.</p>
   <p>For the spirituall good that thou shalt receiue thereby, blesse the Lord; and pray for the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, that God would restore him again, to that former liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in his Church, which heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore to the glory of God, and the comfort of many a Christian soule, he hath enioyed.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in the Lord,</hi> W. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>