<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ADVERTISEMENT to the READER, prefixed before the FRENCH Copie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116164_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10389</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20667</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116164</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ADVERTISEMENT to the READER, prefixed before the FRENCH Copie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A revievv of the Councell of Trent : VVherein are contained the severall nullities of it: with the many grievances and prejudices done by it to Christian kings and princes: as also to all Catholique churches in the world; and more particularly to the Gallicane Church. First writ in French by a learned Roman-Catholique. Now translated into English by G.L</title>
                 <author>Ranchin, Guillaume</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Forrest, Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Turner, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Webb, William 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 388 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT to the READER, prefixed before the FRENCH Copie.</head>
   <p>THis Booke is not for those that have made separation in point of Religion; but for such good Catholiques as desire to see an holy reformation of it. Here you shall finde the demands that were put up to that end at the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, the King of <hi>France,</hi> and other Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Princes, not Protestants, and the small regard that was had of satisfying them. Here you shall read the tricks that were used both in this and some precedent Councels, to wave that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation which was so earnestly sought after: and withall you shall understand a good many of the points wherein it consisteth. The method which the Authour hath used, may bee set downe in few words. Hee makes two kinds of nullities; one in the forme and manner of proceeding, [which he delivers in the first Book]: the other in the matter. And these later consist either in denyal of justice [which is handled in the second Book;] Or in the injustice of the Decrees themselves: concerning which he sets downe two maxims. The first, that they advance the Pope to an unlawfull power, stripping Councels, Clergy, yea Kings and Princes of that authoritie which belongs unto them, to transferre it upon the Pope; [and this is proved in the third, fourth, fifth and sixt Books]: The second, that they pull downe the honour and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Christian Princes, and Secular powers: [which is treated
<pb facs="7"/>
of in the last Book]. See here the subject wherein many learned men, both Devines and Lawyers have travailed long agoe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the names of <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> and such as embrace their doctrine, were ever heard of: which doctrine is not here defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, nor shall you find any thing that concernes them in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. The ancient liberties of the Church are represented here in divers passages, the very same with those that carry now the name of the <hi>Gallicane</hi> Church; whither they made their retreat when they were chased out every where else: yet not without danger of being lost, and that not in part but in whole, by a blow from <hi>Trent.</hi> VVhich would plunge us again into those miseries, wherof our Ancestors begun to bee sensible long agoe: which they have left unto us by tale upon record, in the ancient Histories and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts of our Kings, the Rolles of the States General, the Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strances of the Courts of Parliament, and many other ancient Monuments. Nor doth it lesse concerne the interest of our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord the King; whose honour and dignitie are shamefully disgraced, his authoritie vilified, his power rebated; with a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall prejudice to all the <hi>French,</hi> who in particular are egregi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously wronged in divers things, as may be fully knowne from this discourse. You must further observe that the Authour was not willing to meddle with what properly concernes divinitie, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to transgresse the bounds of his profession, or speake any thing upon this occasion of those demands which were made, by Catholique Princes in this Councell, touching the reformation of abuses about Images, Pilgrimages, Reliques of Saints, keeping of Holy dayes, convenience of the marriage of Priests, Communion in both kinds, celebration of divine service in a vulgar tongue, and such like; contenting himselfe with a bare mention of those demands, and no more.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>