<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY PROFESSED FRIEND, MVLD SACKE, None of the least of the ancient Societie of Chimney-Sweepers.</title>
           <author>Mvlier, Hic</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116332_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11273</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21538</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116332</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY PROFESSED FRIEND, MVLD SACKE, None of the least of the ancient Societie of Chimney-Sweepers.</title>
                 <author>Mvlier, Hic</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Muld sacke: or The apologie of Hic Mulier: to the late declamation against her : Exprest in a short exclamation. Non est mollis è terris ad astra via. Muld sacke, muld sacke</title>
                 <author>Hic Mulier</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Meighen, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO MY PROFESSED FRIEND, MVLD SACKE, None of the least of the ancient Societie of Chimney-Sweepers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter I had wearied my vnsetled brayne, with the finding out of a fit Patron, or indifferent Iudge, for the defence or equall censure of my Apologeticall answer, to a bitter Declamation, lately come abroad against me, I could hit of none more fit then your <hi>Gaffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,</hi> whose equall carriage, both to mee, and <hi>Haec Vir</hi> (since I did first know you) hath beene such, that it can be hardly iudged, to whom you are most inclined. One day you weare yellow Bands, Feathers, Scarffes; cuts your haire and powders it, paints your face so all the weeke, that vpon Sunday, a pound of sope will not reduce it
<pb facs="3"/> to the right colour; you dance, sing, and vse o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther jouiall conceits, wherein I (poore Wench) much delight; but when I looke vpon your Hornes, your Garters, Roses, and other your Feminine masculine fashions, then J perceiue you participate also with <hi>Haec Vir,</hi> and are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently affected to vs both. Wherefore (good <hi>Gaffer</hi>) seeing Truth hath yeelded it selfe to be the Clyent of my answer, let this poore Apologie find such rich fauour with you, that you will become Patron thereof, censuring this Exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mine, rather by my passions and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stractions, at the writing thereof, then by the iudicious or formall dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting of it,</p>
   <p>In the doing whereof, you shall oblige me to continue</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours, so long as you correspond HIC MVLIER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>