<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ An admonicion to the reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1540</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116014_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10887</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21153</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116014</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ An admonicion to the reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The byrth of mankynde, newly translated out of Laten into Englysshe : In the which is entreated of all suche thynges the which chaunce to women in theyr labor, and all suche infyrmitees whiche happen vnto the infantes after they be delyuered. And also at the latter ende o in the thyrde or last boke is entreated of the conception of mankynde, and howe manye wayes it may be letted or furtheryd, with diuers other fruytefull thynges, as doth appere in the table before the booke</title>
                 <author>Roeslin, Eucharius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Raynald, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1540</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>1, vi-lxxxviii leaves, 2 leaves of plates, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ An admonicion to the reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or so muche as we haue enterprysed the interpretation of this present boke, offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge and dedicatyng it vnto our moste gracyous and vertuous Quene Kate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryn onely, by it myndyng and tenderyng the vtilite and wealthe of all women, as touchynge the greate parell &amp; dangeours, which moste commenly oppresseth them in theyr paynefull labours. I requyre all suche men in the name of God, whiche at any tyme shall chaunse to haue this boke, that they vse it godlye, and onely to the profet of theyr neyghbours, vtterly eschuynge all rebawde and vnsemely communi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cacion of any thynges contayned in the same, as they wyll answere before God, whiche as wytnesseth Christ, wyll requyre a counte of all ydell wordes, and muche more then of all rebawde and vncharitable wordes. Euery thynge, as sayth Salomon, hath his tyme, and truely that is farre oute of tyme, yea and farre from all good honestie, that some vse at the commune tables and without any difference before all companyes rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and leudelye to talke of suche thynges, in the which they ought rather to knowe muche, and to saye lyttell, but only where it maye do good, magnifyeng the mygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye God of nature in all his workes, compassionatynge and pytyenge oure euen Christians, the women whiche sustayne and endure for the tyme so greate dolor and payne for the byrth of mankynde and delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of the same in to the worlde.</p>
   <closer>Prayse God in all his workes.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>