<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Harris, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116602_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02698</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12831</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116602</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Harris, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Gods goodnes and mercy : Layd open in a sermon, preached at Pavls-Crosse on the last of Iune. 1622. By Mr Robert Harris, pastour of the church of God in Hanvvell in Oxfordshire</title>
                 <author>Harris, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, John 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bartlet, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 29, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>❧ To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE READER;</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>Vnderstand, that I was then Summoned to the Crosse, when I was not in case, either to Studie or to speake; the former straight, (when I could not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused) forced me to a familiar and easie Text, the later to a briefe and short kind of speech, which car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with it an appearance of that, which I ever shund, <hi>Affectation</hi> and <hi>Obscuritie.</hi> It may bee, thine Eye will conceiue mee better then thine Eare, and therefore I yeelde to importunity, and present my selfe to thy view, entreating <hi>2.</hi> things of thee, <hi>1. Charity, 2. Conscience,</hi> Charity towards the Printer, in case some faults (in my absence) escape him: towards me, in case so frequent quotations offend thee: my now pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise agrees with my ancient Iudgement; at home, my people neither vnderstand nor desire tongues, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Authorities, and therefore I am sparing, on the other side, when I fall vpon an Auditorie that conceiues and receiues both, I vse both, as I see my advantage. All is thine if thou canst be content, and wilt add <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>(the second thing) to <hi>charity.</hi> It grieues my soule to see the guise of many hearers; they desire novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: when they haue heard, théy iudge the man and his method▪ and then sit downe, seldome practising what is preached. Reader be not such an hearer, lest thou cosen thy selfe <hi>Iames 1.22.</hi> thou here seest, that if thou be of God, and Gods goodnesse, and special mercy shall be thine, thou must be good, and do good, be mercifull and shew mercie, the times require this, the Lord expects this, our vnthankfulnes and vnfruitfulnes hath welmost vndone vs, if wee, who haue more peace in the State, more preaching in the Church, then any other knowne Nation vnder Heauen, be not more fruitful and aboun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dant in goodnes, then other people, our light wilbe turnd into darknes, our Sunne into blood: what shall I say? or to whom shall I turne my selfe? we cal til we are hoarse, we speake till we spit forth our lungs, yet will not the Sonnes of Men heare vs, they wil not heare, I say (with teares) they will not heare, we can doe no good: O Lord perswade <hi>Iaphet</hi> for we can not, and be mercifull to this barren Countrey: Reader I leaue thee, adding to the <hi>Martyrs,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Fox <hi>his</hi> Martyrol. &amp;c.</note> pray, pray, pray, worke, worke, worke.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord, RO. HARRIS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>