<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A GENERALL PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116528_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21279</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7628</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116528</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A GENERALL PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine briefe notes vpon a briefe apologie set out vnder the name of the priestes vnited to the archpriest. Dravvne by an vnpassionate secular prieste friend to both partyes, but more frend to the truth. VVhereunto is added à seuerall ansvveare vnto the particularites obiected against certaine persons</title>
                 <author>Ely, Humphrey</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Sevestre, Pierre 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Paris</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 2, 19, 1 leave, 23, 9, 312, 43, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="2" facs="3"/>
   <head>A GENERALL PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>VERE it not à principle vvell knovven to all men by the very instinct of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that euery one hath greater reason to defend his good name, then any other parte off his riches: and that they principally, vvhose credites are necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye for the behoofe of others, are by the lavve of God bound therevnto: I should besorie (I assure thee good Christian rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) to heare of any more vvritinge of this lamentable subiect, of our ciuill dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vvho ought (like bretherne) to lyue together in perfit peace and vnity. But hauinge read a most indiscrete and odious Apologye [published vnder the name of vnited Priestes in the maintenance of a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vve founded Hierarchie,] vvhich VVan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
<pb facs="4"/>far and vvide from the Question in controuersie, see<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eth occasion to sturre in the vnsauorye puddle of humaine frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, such as he deemeth to haue hapned amonge our poore exiled countrimen, for aboue this tvventy yeares: I could not (I say hauinge seen such à pitifull peece of vvoorke) but esteeme him to haue no feelinge of à true English nature in him, that vvould not be much moued at that not Onely Vnchristianlyke, but vnciuill and Barbarous behauiour: and should not also thinke it very requisyte and neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarye, that à reasonable ansvveare vvere retourned, to preserue and defend our deare countryes, and country mens repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
   <p>VVhich hath been the cause that M. Doctor Ely [à very auncient, vvise &amp; led<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Prieste, lyuinge in honour and at his ease, far from his natiue soile, and farther from all such debate and contention] ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peninge to read that venemous Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye, could not hold his hande any longer, but quittinge his ovvne repose, hastened to come to succour them, vvhom he (to his great griefe) perceiued, to be verye iniuriously set vpon and assailed. Not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the good bloud in a mans body, vv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hich feelinge the harte assaulted, flieth frō euery part, to assist aid and confort it.</p>
   <pb n="3" facs="4"/>
   <p> And truly vvhosoeuer knovveth this right vvourshipfull Doctor (as his auncient stā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge in the seminarie, euen from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginninge, and his kind hospitality sithen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to all cōmers, hath made him vvel kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vven to many:) cannot thinke it strange, that his feruent affection vnto our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon father, CARD: ALLEN off godly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morye (vvith vvhom he vvas very intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secall) and his tender loue tvvardes vs all, hath pushed him on, to sett penne to Paper and to imploy some parte of his goodly talent, about the decision of this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersy, and appeasinge of our troubles.</p>
   <p>And to speake in differently, vvho is there of our nation that should be sooner hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened vnto, or better beleeued in this cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se, then M. D. Ely? For first he not beinge partiall, but alike affected vnto both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, (as in his Epistle folovvinge he she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vveth at large) hath vvith all indifferency heard, read, and diligently perused, vvhat eyther side hath to say for them selues.</p>
   <p>Then his sound naturall iudgment, refined and accomplished vvith a profound kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vveledg of both ciuill and canon lavve, (vvhereof he hath been publike professor in à famous vniuersity for many yeares:) inableth him, to discerne &amp; see on vvho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se side the right is. Finally his sincere hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty, voide off dissimulation, full of Zeale to
<pb facs="5"/>truth and equity, maketh him bold to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuet in plaine tearmes that vvhich in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science he knovveth to be the verity.</p>
   <p>VVherefore enery considerate an aduised reader, must needs giue singular regard to his opinion, and may vvithout any doubt safely relie vpon him, as vpon à most pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable Authour.</p>
   <p>Notvvithstandinge it is to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eared lest some [ouer vvillfully bent to dvvell in their ovvne errours, and vvho cannot in any sorte endure to be controled] not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge any exception against the vvork<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, vvill coyne some cauill against the vvorke, that so plainly discouereth their deceites: and not findinge any other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, may peraduenture say, that his holines Brene of the 17. of August 1601. Doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barr them from readinge all such bookes as this is. VVhich scruple I thought expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to remooue in this Preface. Because those good felovves that thrust into their blind folovvers handes, bookes flatly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited by that Breue, vvith vvarrantise: are as earnest on the other side to dissunde them from touchinge others: lest readinge them they should espie their errours, and so for sake them. First then it is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered that these learned notes of M. D. Ely come not vvithin the compas of the bookes forbidden by the Breue. Bicause
<pb n="4" facs="5"/>they be not vvritten by any of either par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to kindle more coales and to increase discord and debate: but by à charitable, discrete and indifferent person, to quench the flames of strife &amp; to induceboth sides to atonement. Againe yf ther vvere such à prohibited booke, yet may they novve be read securely, vvithout incurringe the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill of that Breue. For the sayd Breue vvas not at the first receiued and admitted.</p>
   <p>The one part seeinge hovve it vvas abused appealinge from it. And the other, to vvitt M. Archpriest, deludinge and defeatinge of it. For it beinge sent to vvardes him frō Rome shortly after the 17. of August, and comning to his hande about Michaelmas, he kept it close and suppressed it vntill tovvardes the end of Ianuarye folovvin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge; that in the meane season, the goodly peece of vvorke of their Apologie might be hatched: and then it peepinge out vvith an antidate, might seeme to the simple, to haue been made before the Breue.</p>
   <p>VVhat boldnes and presumption vvas this? Vievvinge his hol. vvill and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, vnder so seuere a penalty as the greater excommunication, euen hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge his breue in his hande to be so auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious as at the very nose of it, to thrust out bookes so oposite to it, as darkenes is to light, vvas certainly to contemne it in the
<pb facs="6"/>highest degree, &amp; to the greater scorne off it, they gaue out, that the breue did onely forbid bookes of our side, but admitted all of theirs. It beinge made vvithout partialitye as vvell against the one as the other. This vvas the first pageāt they plaid against it, but vvas this all? Noe. For some monethes after both the publishinge off the Breue, and their Apologyes, one in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, and another in English: To the infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye and exasperation of diuerse sortes off persons both Ecclesiasticall and temporall, there creepeth forth an Appendix to them of the same railinge qualitye: vvhich very peartly playeth at bo-peepe vvith his holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Breue. The Author confesseth ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iously, that he had in deed heard of such a breue, but had not seē it: orels he vvould not for all the good in the vvorld, haue so violated it, for vvhat vvilfull contempt should that haue been? and yet the seely man vvas so ouerseen, as to relate in the same place the somme of it, and runninge ouer it orderly as it lieth, to cite certayne sentences of it AD VERBVM, vvord by vvord. vvhich plainely bevvrayeth his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>simulation, and declareth sufflciently, that he had both seen and perused the Sayd Breue, but meant to jest vvith it. So obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient be they to the see Apostolike.</p>
   <p>But I vvould faine knovve vvhat shift
<pb n="5" facs="6"/>they haue yet in store for their larger A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie vvhich is reported to be already published. Shall that also beare date befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the breue? Or shall it be fathered vpon some one that lyeth in an vnknovven cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner? vvho vvill say in like manner, that he had not seen the said Breue: or vvhat other ioly deuise shall vve see next? be not these to vvardly and dutifull Children, vvho vnder the pretext of such triflinge excuses dare so delude and resist our holie fathers authority? vve vvere by them stiled, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normous disobedient, rebels, vvorse thē Magitians and Idolaters, for that vve de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laid to subscribe to a lately deuised subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, erected by a Cardinall his letter: vvhat doe they then deserue to be called, vvho so vvilfully trangressed our supreme Pastours Autentike vvritts? for euen as there is incomparable difference betvve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the Popes Parson and a Cardinalls, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvveen his Breue and this man bare letter: so vvas there in that vvhich vvas commā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. For the Card: imposed an intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble burden vpon vs of that lavveles subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination: VVheras his holines charged vs onely to refraine from offendinge one an other by inuectiues and bitter vvritinge. Euerie one therfore that is not blinded by affection, May easly see vvhat Difference there vvas in the breach of those tvvo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandementes.
<pb facs="7"/>I vvill here passe ouer a fift pamphlet. VVhich they haue also put to light since the Breue. Because the subiect of it is so absurd in it self, and so vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto all our Catholikes that be in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution, that it cannot be vvelcome into England. It is [if it please you] that vve notvvithstandinge our longe indurance of manifold afflictions, should not accept of a tolleration in matters of religion, noe not yf her maiestie of her singular clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, vvould offre it vnto vs. Need you hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re any more? do you not thinke these men to haue lost four of their fiue sences? or els that lyuinge to lōge out of guneshott at their ease, haue cast of all humaine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion of their Bretherne? and shall vve be so assotted on them still that vve vvill vphold all they Say? And tather indure any hardnes then once mislike their folish o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions? But to returne to our purpose, seinge they haue four or fiue tymes by ouuert act gone against that his Hol. Breue, they haue made it frustrat &amp; of noe force For (as the learned Casuistes hold) after à Superiours lavve or precept publis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed, is by tvvo or three open actes contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried and resisted: it doth not bind any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, vvhen the Superiour vnderstandinge off it, doth not rebuxe or punnish such transgressors and renevve his former de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree.
<pb n="6" facs="7"/>Novve vve haue longe since giuen his hol: to vnderstand, by his Nuncios in France and Flanders, and by our Brether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne at Rome, of their often violatinge off the sayd Breue; and yet he stirreth not in it vvhich signifieth that he is content that Breue exspire, and bind no longer. But as I aforesayd, if the Breue did stand in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer force and vertue, yet it comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not these notes, vvritten so modestly, by such à Venerable Person, vvho in the spirite of mildnes charitably commendeth or reprehendeth both parties, as he taketh eyther of them to haue deserued. And he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re I vvould end this preface, vvere it not that I thought it expedient in this place to examine brieflie, that vvhich is cited in the Apologye out of Card:
<note place="margin">
         <hi>Cap:</hi> 2. <hi>f:</hi> 11.</note> Allens letter vnto M. Mush. For that he novve folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvinge our common cause at Rome, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not as yet ansvveare for him self. After the good Card. had exhorted vs secular Prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes to loue, honour, and respect one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, accordinge vnto euerye ones age, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and profession, he hath these vvordes: <hi>And those of the secular order, specially those that haue been brought vp by the fathers, and haue found so greate loue, charity and helpe at their handes (as verye fevve of late haue done) to be correspondent in all gratitude and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, reuerencinge them in vvorde and deed, as
<pb facs="8"/>is requisite to their merites and callinge, &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Out of vvhich vvordes the Iesuites and their adherentes dravve, the Card: to haue been of opinion, that the secular Priestes should take them for their Superiours, or at lest, should giue them the preeminence in all places. All vvhich is far vvide both from his vvordes and meaninge. For as I vvill not say but that they, VVho haue found Courtesie at their handes, are tied to acknovvledge and requite it: see doe I affirme, that to fish out of his vvordes any kind of superiority or equality either vv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ith secular Priestes, sauoreth of Ambition: the Card; I graunte aduiseth and chargeth vs to reuerence them, according to their callinge: but their callinge and profession requireth not, that they be preferred befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re vs, as out of the Auncient Fathers, and holy canous may be proued at large: but this place doth not permit it: take for a tast the decree of a councell holdē at Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me abovve 1300. past, vnde pope Silue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, vvhere (charge beinge giuen that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours giue reuerence to their Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours) it is declared vvho be those Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours and inferiours, in these vvordes as it is related in the decrees. PORRO PON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIFICI PRESBITER,
<note place="margin">
         <hi>dist</hi> 93. <hi>li: a Subdia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>no.</hi>
      </note> ET CET. <hi>Let the Priest do rerence to the Bishope. The deacon to the Priest. The Subdeacon to the Deacon. Tha Aco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite
<pb n="7" facs="8"/>to the Subdeacon, the exorciste to the Acoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite, the lector to the exorciste, the portor to the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor;</hi> OSTIARIO ABBAS, ABBATI MO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NACHVS IN OMNI LOCO REPRESEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TENT OBSEQVIVM: let the Abbote giue obeisance vnto the keper of the church dooer in all places asvvell in publike as vvith in the church; as the monke Doth to the Abbote. behold the iudgment of the primitiue church concerninge secular Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>estes and religious, in their opinion (vv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hich vvas most pure and sound) a secular Priest so far excelleth a religious man: that the Abbote vvho is Chiefe amonge them, is to exibite and to doe reuerence, vnto a dore keper the meanest minister aut atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant vpon a secular Priest. VVhich is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by another Canon taken out off that true religious, and most learned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of the Church S. Hierome. <hi>VVho beinge demaunded by Heliodorus a Bishope, vv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hether the order of secular Clerkes,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Cap.</hi> 16. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>alia causa.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>or of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligeous vvere more vvorthy, gaue ansvvere that the order of Clerkes vvas far vvorthier,</hi> And proueth it by four seueral reasōs as is to be seen in that place. One of the principall is, that they are of the ecclesiastical hierarchy theyr callinge beinge to take charge of soules, to teach others the vvorde of God, and to administers the holy sacramentes, vvhich are the diuinest offices, that the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
<pb facs="9"/>hath communicated vnto men. And therefore sayd this great holy father. MIHI ANTE PRESBITERVM SEDERE NON LICET. It is not lavvefull for me to fit abovve a Priest. True it is (as the glos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se vpon the former place signifieth) that since the religious tooke holy orders, an Abbote is to take place afore a secular Clearke; but noe other monke or religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. As the ordinary practise of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian vvorld in publike processions and all other solemne assemblies Doth make most manifest. VVhere the precedence is alvvayes giuen vnto the secular. And that these sharpe censurers take no exception of the vvord MONACHVS, vsed in the former places. and say that secular Priestes be there onely put before monkes, but not before such religious as they are: it is to bee vnderstood, that in those Authors, MONACHVS, is taken for all sortes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, for that in those dayes there vvere noe other maner of religious: or yf they vvill needes haue a distinction betvven them: then monkes vvilbe the vvorthier, and must march before other poore friers, as the ordinary course of the vvorld allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vveth. And amonge all mendiants, or begginge friers (in vvhich order the Iesui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes recken them selues) they are to march in one of the lovvest ranckes not onely
<pb n="8" facs="9"/>because, their societi is one of the last foū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but also for that they haue fevvest religious obseruances; they not beinge bound to rough and rude apparell, osten and longe fastes, or continuall risinge at midnight to Canonicall houres, as other ligious mē are the, kepinge onely the essē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall vovves of religiō: of vvhich also some tearme all those that haue not made their last profession but tenantes at vvill, and noe freeholders. For vvhen it shall please their generall to dimitt them, they incōti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nētly become secular &amp; be no lōger Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious. All vvhich I say, (God is my vvitnis) not to disgrace any order of the religious, for albeit in the rāckes of the vvorld they be the lovvest: Yet in the sight of God for vvhose sake the leaue all, they may be of the hiest, yf they excell in vertue: as many good deuoute poore vvoman, shall in the kingedome of heauen, be placed far abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vve many ladies not so vertuous as they. Yet as vve giuinge the place to a lady be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a poore vvoman here, do not offend God or man: so vvhosoeuer preferreth a secular Priest afore a religious man, doth not offend against Card. Allens graue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise, of giuinge them such reuerence as is requisite to their callinge. Their vocation beinge inferiour to the other, as hath been prooued. Neither can the addition of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious
<pb facs="10"/>ioyned vnto their Priesthood gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly aduāce thē (of vvhich yet I haue heard some to bragg) vvhen as the hiest dignity of religion, is not equall vnto a poore por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tershipp in the church of God, as is by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of antiquity abovve declared.</p>
   <p>And because I am a litle entred into this matter,
<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ca.</hi> 16. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>Eccles.</hi>
      </note> I vvill to this purpose add one sentence more, out of the next Canon of the same question. The summe and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance vvhereof is, that it is not lavvefull for monkes and religious to do any thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge (specially belonging vnto the ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall hierarchie), vvithout the counsaile of Priestes. Thus taught blessed S. Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome 1200. agoe: and this holy charch e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steemed conuenient to be rāged amonge her sacred decrees. VVhat shall vve then say to those vvisemen, vvo leppinge out of the limittes of their ovvne profession, durst avovve, that Priestes vvere out to be trusted vvith the guidinge of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences of layfolkes, vnlesse they depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on some religious man. The discipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of holy church sendeth religious for direction and Counsail, vnto secular Prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes: this vnaduised vvriter cleane cōtrary, vvould not haue secular priestes credited vvith the charge of soules, yf they be not ruled by some religious: vvhich is also so much the more absurd for that the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naginge
<pb n="9" facs="10"/>of lay persons spirituall saluation apparteyneth most properly vnto secular Priestes, that beinge their peculiar voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and profession. And (as all men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse,) God most assuredly assisteth and concurreth, vvith those instrumentes, of vvhich he maketh choise him self for any purpose: novve the very institution of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Priestes by our blessed Sauiour, vvas to giue them the charge of both conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, instructinge, and guidinge mens sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les into the knigedome of heauen: vv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herfore by the diuine lavve of his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie prouidence, he doth more specially perfitt this his holy vvorke by the seruice of secular Priestes, then by any other vv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hat soeuer. He then that leaueth them, and seeketh after others for the directinge of his conscience, may be resembled to him that forsaketh the hight vvay, and folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vveth bypathes, of vvhich be cannot bee so vvell assured.</p>
   <p>For as I take religious men to be the fittest to handle religious affaires so it cānot vvith any colour of reason be denied but that se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Priestes are the most proper for the conductinge of secular mens consciences. And therfore I chiefly take them to be <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secular,</hi> for that they liue in the vvorld to be lanternes and guides vnto vvorldly men. VVich should be a singular motiue
<pb facs="11"/>vnto all lay men, to cast their eyes princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally vpon them and to loue honour, and respect them abovve the rest, as their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie Pastours, vvho haue quitt their ovvne friends and all other thinges to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne and dye amonge them, and to assist them vvhih the vvord of life, and the holy sacramentes liuinge and dieinge: VVheras the religious (loue they them neuer so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvell) must needes forsake them on the sudden at the commaundement of their Superiours.</p>
   <p>VVhich I do not relate to Diminish in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny sorte the orderly affection, that any man or vvoman carieth tovvardes them: but to correct the fond opinion of them, that thinke nothing cā be vvell done vvith out them. And to complaine a litle of the incongruity of such religious, vvho con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to their rule and profession, plunge them selues ouer head and heares into ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical affaires, vvith such audacity and obstinacy, as they haue tourned all topsie turnie. And hovve can it almost be other vvise so longe as they meddle so peremtorily in matters, vvherin they haue verie smale skill: hauinge neither stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died much in the holy canons, by vvhich principally the discipline and regiment of the church is directed: nor had any greate practise in ecclesiasticall affaires; they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge
<pb n="10" facs="11"/>as it vvere out of the vvorld, in a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stincte and far different gouernmente. And finally God doth seldome blesse the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ir enterprises vvith good successe, vvho runne before he send them, and intet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meddle farther then they haue comission from him or his vicar and vicegerent in earth. VVhefore (to conclude) I most hartely request them, to retire them selues vvith in their ovvne boundes, and to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue that golden rule, REGVLARIA RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GVLARIBVS, lett religious men deale in matter appertayninge to religion and the cloister: and leaue SECVLARIA SECV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LARIBVS. The orderinge of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon affaires of the church, to secular Prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes, and so vve shall come to line quietly togither. VVhich Almighly God; of his infinite mercy and goodnes grannt vs spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely, throught the merites of our blessed Sauiour, Christ Iesus.</p>
   <p>Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>