<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRI¦STIAN
READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116171_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11010</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21281</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116171</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRI¦STIAN
READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lectures vpon the first and second Epistles of Paul to the Thessalonians: preached by that faithfull seruant of God M. Robert Rollock, some-tyme minister of the Euangell of Iesus Christ, and rector of the Colledge in Edinburgh</title>
                 <author>Rollock, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charteris, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 246, that is 346, 4, 173, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRI<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>STIAN
READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>WE</hi> offer vnto thee, Christian Reader, these Lectures of that
most reuerent and faithfull seruant of Iesus Christ M. <hi>RO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BERT
ROLLOCK,</hi> vpon the tvvo Epistles of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle
<hi>Paul</hi> to the Thessalonians. We haue taine painos and traueile
that thou mightest finde profite and edification. For not onely haue
vve conferred sundry coppies gotten from the hands of them vvho
vvrote them from his mouth, but also vve haue conferred them vvith
the Latine Commentarie vvritten by the Author himselfe, that
thou mightest haue fullie, so farre as vvas possible, both his ovvne
phrase and matter. In conferring of the Copies vve omitted repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
cleered thinges obscure, and filled out imperfite sentences, that in
nothing thou mightest finde inlack. If thou doubt, either of the style
or matter, or if any vvould moue thee to conceiue any eye-list or mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liking
of this vvorke (as vve are not ignorant hovv readie many are
oft-tymes, vpon small or rather no ground, before they haue either
seene or read, in such cases to giue out sentence) vve pray thee shovve
vs this fauour to superceede thy iudgement vntill thou hast red and
considered, then mayest thou pronounce vvith the better vvarrand.
If thou read vvith an hart indifferent and desirous to be edified, vve
trust thou shalt finde thou hast not lost thy labours. And if thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne
glorie to God, and get grace to thy ovvne soule, vvhich vvere
the cheefe ends of our traueiles, vve vvill thinke vve haue gotten a suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
recompence and obtained our desires.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>