<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHORS EPISTLE TO HIS FRIEND.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116935_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03452</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13576</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116935</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHORS EPISTLE TO HIS FRIEND.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Obseruations concerning the present affaires of Holland and the Vnited Prouinces, made by an English gentleman there lately resident, &amp; since written by himselfe from Paris, to his friend in England</title>
                 <author>Verstegan, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>131, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prefatory_letter">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>THE AVTHORS EPISTLE TO HIS FRIEND.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>ORTHY, &amp; wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued Friend, you shal please to vnderstand, that at my late being at the <hi>Hage</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> I receaued your leter, wherin you desire me
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>
to describe vnto you the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; &amp; condition of the people, as also to know my opinion of their cause and quarrell against the King of <hi>Spayne,</hi> about which they haue so long troubled the world: Moreouer how I find thē in their thankefulnes vnto our State, for so longe sticking vnto them, and ayding them: And what those differences are which are lately risen vp among them about matters of Religion.</p>
   <p>This letter of yours I had no tyme to answere frō thence, neither would the answering it there haue beene conuenient; I therefore deserred the answere, vntill my comming into <hi>France,</hi>
      <pb n="5" facs="3"/>
to which iourney I was resolued before the receit of your letter; because (to deale truely with you) I could not any longer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to heare the lauish and vile speaches, which a sort of base vnbridled people dayly disgor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged against the Maiesty of our King, whereof in the ensuing discourse somwhat more shalbe spoken. And indeed this intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable demeanour of theirs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Maiesty of so great and so bountifull a Prince, and to whome they are so much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding, hath giuen me good cause aswell to looke into the iustnesse of their wars against the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> as into their
<pb n="6" facs="4"/>
in gratitude vnto the King and State of <hi>England,</hi> and therby to become the more able to giue you satisfaction to the demands in your letter.</p>
   <p>I must notwithstāding con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, that since my aryuall heer in <hi>Paris,</hi> I haue for some whyle deferred it: for as on the one side I had a great desyre thereunto, so on the other syde, I found in my selfe a kind of vnwillingnes to begin it; which vnwillingnes I protest vnto you, proceeded of a conceaued feare to offend you, when in deliuering you the very true and playne truthe of thinges as they are, you might fynd me altered in mynd and
<pb n="7" facs="4"/>
iudgment from what I was when I was cōuersant with you in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</hi> But considering that the true duety of a friend is, with his friend to deale vnfaignedly, I haue now at last vndertaken the taske so to do. And in such re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard must intreate you, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse me, and not to let my igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the time when I cōuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with you be put in oppositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on against the better knowledge which experience of ryper years hath yielded me; for you must think that by trauailing abroad in other Countryes, &amp; conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing with men of vnderstanding of diuers nations, who in these parts are accustomed to frenesse
<pb n="8" facs="5"/>
of speach; by reading the iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious writings of such credible Authors, as haue noted downe the actions of State of this time; as also by the obseruatiōs which myselfe haue made, I haue seen as it were a mist wip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d away frō before myne eyes, and thereby am come to discerne that, which truth &amp; reason hath made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest vnto me, as I make no doubt you also will become to do, when with vnpartial patiēce you will haue pleased to read, what heere for your satisfaction I haue written; that thereby we may agre aswel in mind &amp; iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as we do in ancient ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And thus leauing you to
<pb n="9" facs="5"/>
God, in all kind affection I take of you my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>You know the hand.</signed>
      <dateline>From Paris <date>the 20. of March, after this stile &amp; computation.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>