<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CVRTEOVS GENTLEMEN REA∣DERS, HEALTH.</title>
           <author>B., G.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116564_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00209</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1026</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116564</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CVRTEOVS GENTLEMEN REA∣DERS, HEALTH.</title>
                 <author>B., G.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A fig for the Spaniard, or Spanish spirits : VVherein are liuelie portraihed the damnable deeds, miserable murders, and monstrous massacres of the cursed Spaniard. With a true rehearsal of the late trobles, and troblesome estate of Aragon, Catalonia, Valencia, and Portingall: Wherevnto are annexed matters of much marueile, and causes of nolesse consequence. Magna est veritas, &amp; preualet</title>
                 <author>G. B.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wright, William 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE CVRTEOVS GENTLEMEN REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DERS, HEALTH.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entlemen, though</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip <hi>of Spaine be olde and bed-redde yet hee is not quite dead, and though his forces for the present be somewhat weakned, yet is hee not vtterly conquered: in good time hee may be by diuine assistance, and your worthy valors, shew your selues ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the right inheritours of the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of your auncestours: that is, in peace to be mindful of warre, and in war most studious of peace, bearing</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>alwaies vpright minds, and forward heartes, to helpe your friendly neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. For if our friendly neighbors farewell, then like all friends we shal fare the better, but if they faile of peaceable successe, wee can looke for nothing but warlike vproares: your wisedomes know what I meane, let it be then brieflie, pro lege, pro rege, pro grege: Macte virtute sitis.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours at commandement, G. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>