<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Postscript]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116531_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02681</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12812</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116531</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Postscript]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Fratres sobrii estote. I. Pet. 5. 8. Or, An admonition to the fryars of this kingdome of Ireland : to abandon such hereticall doctrines as they daylie publish to the corruption of our holy faith, the ruine of soules, and their owne damnation which sleepeth not. By Paul Harris priest</title>
                 <author>Harris, Paul</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stationers’ Society, Dublin</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Ireland--Dublin</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 30, 35-92, that is 82 84-99 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="postscript">
   <pb n="99" facs="49"/>
   <p>I Heare, that some of our divines (if worthy that name) take great exceptions unto me, for calling the Catholicke Bishops of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Titulary Bishops, by which tearme they understand no true Bishops at all. But sure if I had beene able to have put wit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their heads as well as a booke into their hands, they had beene freed from that error. Let them then consult with the <hi>Canon,</hi> or if they have it not, let them look into <hi>Bellar. de Clericis lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. And they will finde this to be a good argument, <hi>teneus tam de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> de materia. Hic est episcopus titularis. Ergo verus:</hi> even as that. <hi>Hic est parochus. Ergo presbiter.</hi> But I am no better then my predecessours, as many as have exposed themselves to publicke consures by their writings. For all of us may say with <hi>Terentianus Manrus.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Pro captu lectoris habene sua fata libelli.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>