<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE GENEROVS READER.</title>
           <author>S., P.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116871_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11619</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21860</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116871</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE GENEROVS READER.</title>
                 <author>S., P.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A table-booke for princes : Containing short remembrances for the gouernment of themselues and their empire. Wherein also respectiuely the seuerall members of state, and all sorts of subiects, may finde matter worthy their obseruation. By Patricke Scot, Esquire</title>
                 <author>Scot, Patrick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Bernard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 113, 110-215, 5 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE GENEROVS READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Nowing (Generous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) that these ill dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted labours of mine, shal be as well exposed to the byting censure of base and enuious Criticks, (whose peruerse and obstinate disposition hath taught them to detract from others, and forget their owne obliquities) as to the view of High borne, true, Noble, and generous Spirits, (whose birth and education in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites them to looke with a more fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aspect vpon the weake endeuours of good meaning.) For thy better satisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I am to aduertise thee; that at my first seizing vpon this Subiect, (a task I grant farre aboue my reach) I did not
<pb facs="5"/> iealously suspect, but altogether distrust my owne insufficiencie; and therefore did make choyce rather to loose my thus spent time, and commit my confused Papers to a fiery tryall, then to be the Herald of my owne ignorance: hut when I had better aduised, I did finde that the Supreame King is well pleased with the least dram of true deuotion: that his Vicegerents ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great Monarches, and braue Princes haue taken in good part, the smalest oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their meanest Seruants: that euery good subiect (amongst whom in loyaltie I am inferior to none) are by the most strict bonds of allegiance tyed, to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate their talent to the seruice of their Prince and Countrey: then (I say) I did recall my fire-threatning sentence, and was content that this obortiue birth should come vnto the world; But vpon assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance (least thou should expect more then I promise) that the Tytle of a <hi>Table-Booke</hi> might be Charactered vpon the front is piece thereof: which very name, enforceth rather a necessitous vse for memory, then an elaborat intire deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
<pb facs="5"/> or methodicall disposition of the matter.</p>
   <p>Sith then I hold vp my hand at the bar of thy iudgement, I intreate that this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing Treatise (blemished with the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollished ornaments of Art) may be shel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered vnder the wings of thy fauorable censure, and the rather because this sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect is more neerely aliyed to truth and sinceritie, then to art and affectation. So shall I remaine</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy constant welwiller, <hi>P. S.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>