<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO ALL TRVE FAITHFVLL CHRISTIANS, Beleeuing and beloued Seruants of our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ.</title>
           <author>Rowlands, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116249_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11137</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21405</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116249</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO ALL TRVE FAITHFVLL CHRISTIANS, Beleeuing and beloued Seruants of our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ.</title>
                 <author>Rowlands, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sacred memorie of the miracles wrought by our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ : Written by Samuel Rowlands</title>
                 <author>Rowlands, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Bernard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 50 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem" subtype="to_the__reader">
   <pb n="2" facs="4"/>
   <head>TO ALL TRVE FAITHFVLL CHRISTIANS, Beleeuing and beloued Seruants of our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ.</head>
   <l>DEere Christian soule, with humble mind and thought,</l>
   <l>Admire the wonders that thy Sauiour wrought,</l>
   <l>The most true miracles that haue beene done,</l>
   <l>By Gods beloued de<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re and onely Sonne,</l>
   <l>When he for sinnefull man (without intreat)</l>
   <l>Descended from Gods owne right hand and seate;</l>
   <l>The mansion of the blessed Cherubins:</l>
   <l>To dye on earth for our accursed sins,</l>
   <l>When no inducing merite, thine or mine,</l>
   <l>Could thus procure his mercy to incline:</l>
   <l>But when free loue, his lifes free ransome cost,</l>
   <l>To saue the sinners that themselues had lost:</l>
   <l>Then liuing lowly in contempt and scorne,</l>
   <l>Despised of the world, most poorely borne,</l>
   <l>With painefull trauell, preaching vp and downe.</l>
   <l>On shore, in ship, in mountaine, field and towne;</l>
   <l>Confirming, that he taught to be diuine,</l>
   <l>By many a wonderfull admired signe,</l>
   <l>
      <pb n="5" facs="4"/>Euen such as the beholders did confesse,</l>
   <l>The very hand of God, and no power lesse</l>
   <l>Effected, for so wonderfull they were,</l>
   <l>That all spectators stood amaz'd with feare,</l>
   <l>They saw his works to be so strangely rare,</l>
   <l>So Admirable, and so past compare;</l>
   <l>Those (that borne blind) did neuer see worlds light,</l>
   <l>To haue perfection giuen them of sight,</l>
   <l>Dead <hi>Lazarus</hi> that lay foure dayes in graue,</l>
   <l>Calde forth from thence, his life againe to haue,</l>
   <l>The dumbe to speake, the cripples sound to goe,</l>
   <l>The figge-tree cursde, to dye and neuer grow,</l>
   <l>The winds and seas when they outragious swell.</l>
   <l>At his rebuke turne calme as any well:</l>
   <l>The diuels driuen out of men to Swine,</l>
   <l>The water turned into purest wine,</l>
   <l>The Souldiers (in the false betraying howre)</l>
   <l>All strucken to the ground by <hi>Iesus</hi> power;</l>
   <l>The dropsie healed, and the Leapers cured,</l>
   <l>His presence by the Diuells not endured,</l>
   <l>His walking on vnfirme and liquid water,</l>
   <l>His giuing life vnto the Rulers daughter,</l>
   <l>His healing <hi>Malcus</hi> eare most perfect sound,</l>
   <l>When <hi>Peters</hi> sword had lopt off to the ground:</l>
   <l>And many more (as those fowre holy men,</l>
   <l>Which did the life of our Redeemer pen)</l>
   <l>Haue registred, of wonders <hi>Iewes</hi> did see,</l>
   <l>Which <hi>Iesus</hi> onely wrought, that we might bee</l>
   <l>Faithfull, and true beleeuers in his name;</l>
   <l>And in our liues expresse and show the same.</l>
   <l>These Myracles for Christians may suffice,</l>
   <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
      <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <l>
      <pb n="8" facs="5"/>Not any thing of truth in actuall deed▪</l>
   <l>And therefore as the Scripture warnings giue,</l>
   <l>Those men that will not in obedience liue</l>
   <l>Vnto the truth, but doe the same despise,</l>
   <l>They shall by strong deceyuings, follow lyes,</l>
   <l>False Christs shall come, and shall such wonders show,</l>
   <l>That many will beleeue them to be so,</l>
   <l>Not hauing knowledge to discerne aright</l>
   <l>Gods power, true working from the wicked sprite.</l>
   <l>But Christian soule, most constantly abide,</l>
   <l>Let not the Deuill draw thy heart aside,</l>
   <l>For that which Christ and his Apostles taught,</l>
   <l>And all the miracles which they haue wrought,</l>
   <l>For to confirme what they had preach'd before,</l>
   <l>Is all sufficient, and we need no more:</l>
   <l>And he thou mindfull what S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth say,</l>
   <l>Within thy soules best treasurie it lay,</l>
   <l>If I, saith he, strange doctrine should defend,</l>
   <l>Nay should an angell from the heau'n descend,</l>
   <l>And preach another Gospell then the first,</l>
   <l>Receyue it not, but hold him for accurst▪</l>
   <l>Remember God of his free loues intent,</l>
   <l>Hath left an euerlasting testament</l>
   <l>Vnto vs all, in Christ our Sauiours bloud:</l>
   <l>In this alone consisteth all our good;</l>
   <l>All Prophesies had hereunto relation,</l>
   <l>All miracles to this gaue confirmation,</l>
   <l>Therefore if any take in hand to frame</l>
   <l>A miracle in Saint or angels name,</l>
   <l>If any mortall creature vndertake</l>
   <l>His power that makes the earth and heauens quake,</l>
   <l>
      <pb n="9" facs="5"/>If Sathan and his Ministers endeauour</l>
   <l>To worke strange wonders, this beleeue, that neuer,</l>
   <l>Can any miracles bee truely done,</l>
   <l>But by the power of God, and Christ his Sonne:</l>
   <l>To which eternall maiesty and power,</l>
   <l>Ascribe we, till the worlds last ending howre,</l>
   <l>Till Sunne and Moone decay, past date of dayes,</l>
   <l>All honour, glory, Worship, endlesse prayse.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Sa: Rowlands▪</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>