<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHOR to the Reader: AND IN SPECIALL to the Parishioners of St MARY ABCHVRCH London, sometime his Christian Auditors, Grace and Peace from the Prince of Peace.</title>
           <author>Rogers, Nehemiah</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116104_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10929</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21201</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116104</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHOR to the Reader: AND IN SPECIALL to the Parishioners of St MARY ABCHVRCH London, sometime his Christian Auditors, Grace and Peace from the Prince of Peace.</title>
                 <author>Rogers, Nehemiah</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The true conuert. Or An exposition vpon the vvhole parable of the prodigall. Luke. 15. 11.12. &amp;c : Wherein is manifestly shewed; 1. Mans miserable estate by forsaking of God. 2. Mans happie estate by returning to God. Deliuered in sundry sermons, by Nehemiah Rogers, preacher of Gods Word, at St Margarets Fish-street. And now by him published, intending the farther benefit of so many as then heard it; and the profit of so many as shall please to read it</title>
                 <author>Rogers, Nehemiah</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Brewster (Bruster), Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 343, 9 pages, folded table, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE AVTHOR to the Reader: AND IN SPECIALL to the Parishioners of S<seg rend="sup">t</seg> MARY ABCHVRCH London, sometime his Christian Auditors, <hi>Grace and Peace from the Prince of Peace.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow vnwilling I was to bring these vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollished Collections to light, there are many that can witnesse with my consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. For first I knew the great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence that is betwixt preaching, and reading, of one and the same matter: Liuely voice hauing a kinde of secret force,<note place="margin">Habet nescio quid latentis <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> viua vox. Hier.</note> and more liuely energie in it, then writing or reading hath. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, I well remembred, how censorious the world is growne; so that no mans workes, how godly soeuer, lacketh some enuious calumniator and reproacher: and can I look to speed better, then my betters haue sped be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me? Thirdly, I considered how many aged Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, haue refrained, and do yet refraine, from labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in this kinde: Now for me to speake, when they are silent, doth argue intolerable boldnes and presum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption.
<pb facs="5"/>
Fourthly,<note place="margin">Quam sit mihi curta supellex.</note> I know my owne insufficiencie, and am priuie to my owne weaknes, ingeniously confessing, I haue more neede to sit at home, mending my nets, then thus to launch forth into the Ocean. These many and weighty discouragements, did cause me for a time to with-hold the publishing of these Notes, and reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely to withstand the earnest requests of some of my louing freinds for the printing of them. But at length (what through importunacie of some (the common excuse for the Presse in this p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>inting age) and my owne weaknesse yeelding thereunto) I came to some second thoughts, and began to consider; First, what good might redound hereby to the Church of God: for albeit Preaching be the cheife; yet writing is not without it vse and profit. Some are lame, and sicke, and weake, and cannot come to the hearing of the word preached: now for such to haue some plaine Exposition or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vpon some part of Scripture, must needs be very comfortable and vsefull Yea, and in some respect, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting may seeme to claime the priuiledge;<note place="margin">Quo liceat libris, non licet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>re mihi.</note> for this reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth far and neere. My bookes may be admitted where I cannot come. And further, this tendeth for the good, not onely of the liuing, as Preaching doth, but also for the good of such as are yet vnborne: In which respect, saith one, <hi>He that speaketh profiteth for an houre, but he that writeth profiteth for euer.</hi> Secondly, I considered, what an excellent helpe it was, both for the <hi>Ʋnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> as also for the <hi>Memorie.</hi> Alas I how dull are we of conceiuing, in the things of God? so that a thing once spoken, is as good as neuer spoken, such is our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. But this giueth a man leaue to pawse vpon, and ponder on the things we haue heard deliuered: So that, though Preaching, moueth the Affections, and worketh more vpon them: yet Printing may be said to teach more, and better to informe the iudgment. And so for our <hi>Memories;</hi> who findes not how leaking &amp; siue-like they are in reteyning of diuine truth? strawes &amp; haires
<pb facs="5"/>
indeed will these sieues hold; some odd conceit or bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken phrase shall be remembred, when the pure water shall runne out: Sound solid matter shall be quite for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten. But now by our often reading, things are brought againe into our mindes, and a long time retey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in our memories; and what formerly wee haue heard deliuered, is as it were still sounding in our eares. Thirdly, I remembred, (what neuer can sufficiently be bewailed) my time mis-spent and lost; which caused me to redeeme some time with the losse of my owne case and pleasure, that I might doe good this way to Gods Church and people. And lastly, the euill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports that some malignant spirits made of me, when I preached them, (<hi>viz.</hi> that I taught noueltie, and false Doctrine; and what I did, proceeded from a spirit of gall and bitternes, and the like,) hath much moued me to this worke. All these things being well weighed, did darken my former thoughts, and caused me to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vse my Notes, and as I had time, to fit them for the Presse; which now I send into the world, desiring the blessing of heauen to accompanie them, that they may be profitable.</p>
   <p>As for the <hi>Matter,</hi> I doubt not, but it is sound and good, and how euer,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Eccles.</hi> 1.9.</note>
      <hi>There is no new thing vnder the Sunne;</hi> And that there can be nothing sayd, but what hath beene said before, as the <hi>Heathen</hi> man could say;<note place="margin">Nihil est iam di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum, quod non sit dictum prius.</note> yet there may be a more full opening, and a more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spicuous deliuering of poynts: yea, and daily is, to the great benefit of the Church of God, though happily in regard of the summe and substance of matters; the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer saying may be true. I cannot then here promise thee (Christian Reader) any new thing, which thou hast not before heard of; but this I can promise thee, though nothing els; Thou hast here this <hi>Parable</hi> handled more amply and fully, then (to my knowledge) thou euer hast had it heretofore, for I know not any that haue trauailed throughout in the opening of it. I doe confesse, I (with
<pb facs="6"/>
the little Bee) haue flowne ouer many a Garden, and suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked many a flower for this little, and haue beene behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to many an Author, both old and new, for some matter and stuffe, towards the erecting of this building. But blame me not for this, seeing I haue done no other then all other <hi>Expositors</hi> haue done before me; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all haue laboured by enlargement to make those things as vsefull to thee, as I could.</p>
   <p>As for the <hi>style,</hi> it is plaine and homely (though I trust not ouerhomely) I haue euer desired, (and I hope for euer shall) so to speake, as that the simplest might vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, ayming in all my teaching, at that to which the whole Scripture driues, viz <hi>Humilitie, Comfort,</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science of obedience.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.27.</note> First, at the humbling of the obstinate and impenitent, and abasing of their pride. Secondly, at the comforting of the distressed soule,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1.</note> and setling of his conscience in true solid peace, through the assurance of Gods loue. Thirdly, at the framing of mens hearts to a constant desire, and care of pleasing God, and to the prouoking and stirring vp of the penitent to more obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.1.4.</note>Now this I know cannot be performed <hi>with excellencie of speech, nor with the enticing words of mans wisedome.</hi> If then the <hi>style</hi> dislike thee, as too homely, harsh, or rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, being neither round, nor fluent; know, that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was more regarded, then Rhetoricall termes: And the Author desires rather to work vpon the conscience, then to tickle the eare with affected eloquence. And to be plaine, he hath no skill in crooked conceits; which if he had, yet he would be loath to spend his time so idly, as to feed that itching humour of many, which hath more need to be purged then to be nourished. But to be briefe, seeing that this booke is come into thy hands, let me desire thee, first, to read it through; begin not onely but make an end: thou knowest not, the best wine may be reserued vntill the last.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.10.</note> To read by snatches, and by peece-meales, here a little and there a little, or els by fits,
<pb facs="6"/>
as it were, vpon rainie dayes, seldome proueth profitable: read constantly, and read it ouer; and when thou hast so done, ouer with it againe; vpon thy second reading, what formerly seemed difficult, will appeare more plaine.</p>
   <p>Secondly, I desire thee before thou readest to amend those faults which are escaped in the Printing, and where so euer thou findest words falsyfied; sentences dismem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, or confounded by false poynting, or the like, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them with thy loue. Besides literall and punctuall faults, which are too too many, there are many materiall faults, which doe much peruert, and obscure the sence, especially in the former part of this booke (for a more heedfull regard was had for the remainder, after it was perceiuied) as page 1.1. line 23. it is thus sayd, <hi>It speakes against the Deuils Diana, this Idoll of vice with so many wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippers,</hi> when it should haue beene thus printed, <hi>That speakes against the Diuels Diana, this Idoll vice which so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worship.</hi> And so againe, page 29. line 16. you shall finde it thus printed, <hi>I confesse this affection in worldly mens iudgements is a strange Paradoxe,</hi> when it should haue bin thus, <hi>I confesse this assertion, &amp;c.</hi> And in the 45. page, and the last line, you haue it thus, <hi>God is immediately the first cause of all things, produced by the two causes,</hi> when it should haue beene, <hi>produced by the second causes.</hi> And in the next page to that, line 3. it is thus, <hi>the same writer also doth confirme the third,</hi> when it should haue beene, <hi>doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the second.</hi> And in the 47. page, and 23. line, it is thus, <hi>For put case many so be,</hi> when it should haue beene, <hi>for in such a case they may be.</hi> And page 225. line. 11. there is <hi>far more,</hi> for, <hi>for in one:</hi> though this fault in most cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies is amended. I will not trouble thee with any more errors here, thou shalt find them set downe at the end of the Booke, onely these I doe in speciall manner menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, because they are so grosse, and desire thee in speciall manner to correct, how euer thou dealest with the rest. I must needs say, the coppie was very close, and much of
<pb facs="7"/>
it not re-written, but deliuered to the Printer, as it was set downe at the first draught; for my employments would not afford me so much time, as indeed it was fit I should haue had. It is needlesse to say more, for what <hi>Apelles</hi> sometimes said to a foolish painter, thou mayst say to me; <hi>I should haue iudged thy worke to haue bin done in hast, though thou hadst said nothing.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">In omnibus meis scriptis non modò pium lectorem, sed liberum cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectorem deside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro. Aug. in Proam. lib. <hi>3.</hi> de Trin.</note>I submit my weaknesse to thy censure, smite me friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, such balme shall not breake my head. Remember, I am a man, and it is not incident to humane frailtie to be without faults. What faults I find, or heare off, shall be amended, if I liue to see it come againe vnto the Presse. In the <hi>interim,</hi> accept of this, as it is meant vnto thee. I meane thee no hurt, if thou meanest me any, the Lord forgiue thee. And amōgst others, I especially intreat you that were my Auditors, to take my meaning in good part; it is your good I especially intend and ayme at. If any of you receiued comfort when these points were preached, or shall get any good by them now that they are Printed, giue God the praise, and mee thy prayers, that true grace may be more and more increased in mee, and so Gods people haue more and more profit by mee. If thou doest thus, I shall be sufficiently recompenced, and euer rest;</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From my Studie in S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
         <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garets,</hi> Fish-street, <hi>London</hi>
         <date>this 7. of <hi>Ianuary.</hi> 1619.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Thy true friend, in the Lord to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; <hi>NEHEMIAH ROGERS.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>