<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Iohn Casimire by the grace of God Count Palatine by the Rhein, Duke in Bauire &amp;c. and appointed Lieutenant Generall of the said Palatinate be∣sides the Rhein, sendeth greeting.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116026_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01236</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11348</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116026</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Iohn Casimire by the grace of God Count Palatine by the Rhein, Duke in Bauire &amp;c. and appointed Lieutenant Generall of the said Palatinate be∣sides the Rhein, sendeth greeting.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A Christian confession of the late moste noble and mightie prince, Friderich of that name the third, Count Palatine by [the] Rhein, one of the electours of the holy Empire, and Duke in Bauire: wherein constantlie and meekelie he departed out of this world the 26. of October in the yere of our Lord God 1576. Taken word for word out of his last will and testament. Whereunto is added the Lantgraue his answere to the French King</title>
                 <author>Friedrich, III, Elector Palatine</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barker, Christopher</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Iohn Casimire by the grace of God Count Palatine by the Rhein, Duke in Bauire &amp;c. and appointed Lieutenant Generall of the said Palatinate <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the Rhein, sendeth greeting.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the highe and mightie prince, &amp; our entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie beloued Lorde and father, Friderich late Paltzgraue by the Rhein, and Elector of the holie empire, of worthie memorie, in the whole time of his gouernement, and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the yere of our lord god 1566 at the time of the diet holden at Augusta, where he was present about the confession of his christian faith: and also in the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chisme and booke of the reformation and orders of the churches in his dominions heretofore published, hath sufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared &amp; witnessed to the whole world, that neither he him selfe held or mainteined, nor in his landes and dominions had suffered to be set forth and published, anie other kinde of religion then that which was in all partes agreeable vnto the doctrine of the holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical and apostolical scriptures, &amp; besides
<pb facs="3"/>
conformable with the confession of Augusta and apologie thereof, as the same was allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed of by the Princes &amp; Estates assembled at Nawmburg: yet sithe the time of the departure of our said lord and father out of this vale of miserie, we haue partly our selues with our own eares heard, and partly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoode from other places to our great grief, that it hath bene giuen out by some (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though vntruelie) that our said father before his death should haue bene remoued from his former confession, as though aforetimes he had proceeded to farre in such matters. And albeit wee for our owne part, sith the time that by the grace of God we were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out of Poperie, haue alwayes taken and founde his said Confession to be no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, then Christian, &amp; groūded in the infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible word of God, and especially at the time of the said dyet of Augusta, where we atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon our said father, and by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandemēt exhibited the bookes of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Bible and Confession of Augusta before the Electours and other Princes of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire then present, and the Commissioners &amp; Ambassadours of those which were absent. Out of which in our said fathers behalf we desired, that an other and better confession
<pb facs="3"/>
might bee shewed and taught vnto him: where seeing none of them brought any thing at al against our said fathers confessiō, wee were at that time the more confirmed therein: And since according to the same haue not onely with heart and mouth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed, but also being accompanied with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers noble men, &amp; other vertuous &amp; honest persones fearing God, haue at two seueral times sufficiently in the face of the whole worlde witnessed our zeale therein. And yet in like sort (as we haue bene enformed) it hath bene imputed vnto vs, that if we were not wholy departed &amp; remoued from our fathers said Cōfession yet at the lest we were become somewhat lesse earnest then before.</p>
   <p>For which cause seeing our said Lord and father in the absence of the noble &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Prince, Ludouick Palzgraue by the Rhein, now Electour of the holie Empire, our wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued Lord and brother, about the space of one moneth before his departure called and sent for vs in this place vnto him, where we remained with him still vntill his ende, in which time we vnderstoode from himselfe that not onely the aboue mentioned Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession heretofore published was with his owne hands made, but also that he had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb facs="4"/>
the same to be written and inserted in his last will and testament. And further are witnesses that we haue both heard &amp; seene, that vntil his last breath he with good remē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance and great constancie cōtinued in the profession of the same, and so blessedly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted in our Lord Christ Iesus. And where as afterwards our said welbeloued brother comming hither, and with common cōsent opening the said will and testament, which in the meane time remained not onely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touched by anie person, but also kept vnder the handes and seales of good and sufficient witnesses, and further was in euerie leafe sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed with our said fathers owne hande: we not onely founde therein contained his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue mentioned Confession, but also that we his children appointed executours of his said last will, vpon paine of the auoiding of Gods displeasure, anger and curse, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and worldly punishment, by vertue and power of Gods immutable precept of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience due vnto him, were commanded and enioyned both to mainteine our said fathers confession, and also to do our endeuours for the planting and spreading of it further. For which cause with a good conscience (as we trust) and also without any discredit or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice
<pb facs="4"/>
to our fathers said will, and for diuers other weightie and necessarie causes, wee could not any lōger forbeare for knowledge of the truth, &amp; answering of such reportes as haue bene vntruely bruted and spred abroad to the contrarie, openly to giue herewith a true testimonie of the saide matter, causing the said Confession as it was word for word written and inserted in our fathers said te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament, to be published and printed: To the intent that the duetiful accomplishment and fulfilling of his said last and deare will, which is not onely committed to the charge of the Electour our said lord &amp; brother (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though to him chiefly) but also to his sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, Counsellours, officers, and especially to the vniuersitie here, the Schole, and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, &amp; also to the whole posteritie, &amp; euery man in particular (as is expressely conteined in the said testament) might be knowen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them and they thereby vnderstande their duetie what they haue to do: and further e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie person whatsoeuer, be thereby assured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie perswaded in his conscience, that our sayd lord and father, in no other confession nor in any erronious condemned opinion, but in a most Christian confession and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging of the infallible and inuincible truth
<pb facs="5"/>
of our common true and auncient Christian faith, departed most godlie out of this vale of miserie into euerlasting ioye and quietnes. By which confession as grounded vpon the right rocke Christ Iesus our Lord and Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and his most godlie worde, the right touchestone, we also through the helpe and assistance of almightie God, minde to perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere and continue vnto our last ende: and beseche the almightie that he will not onely gratiously preserue vs and all our fellowe members in Christ Iesus, from all contrarie errours and deprauations, which by vnquiet and contentious persons and members are moued in matters of religion and brought into the Church, but also mainteine &amp; keepe in vs his knowen veritie, cōfort &amp; strengthen vs in all troubles and tentations, and of his goodnes once in these latter daies open the eyes and hearts of all Christian people, that we may haue a regarde not vnto traditions of men or priuate affections, but only to his most godly worde as the truest and infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blest line &amp; direction of our consciences and faithes, and graunt vnto vs all grace, that brotherlie, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian and due charitie may take place and dwell among vs.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>