<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Readers, grace and
peace through Iesu Christ our Lord.</title>
           <author>Harvey, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116708_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11462</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21713</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116708</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Readers, grace and
peace through Iesu Christ our Lord.</title>
                 <author>Harvey, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sermons made by the most reuerende Father in God, Edwin, Archbishop of Yorke, primate of England and metropolitane</title>
                 <author>Sandys, Edwin</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Middleton, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Chard (Chare, Chayre), Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 384 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Readers, grace and
peace through Iesu Christ our Lord.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F other thinges besides these,<note place="margin">Eccl. 12, 12. 13</note>
my sonne, take thou heede: for
there is none end of making ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
bookes, and much reading is
a wearinesse of the flesh. Let vs
heare the ende of all, feare God,
and keepe his commandements,
for this is the whole dutie of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
man. By which wordes of weight, proceeding from
the Oracle, not of Apollo, but of God himselfe, what
effect hath beene wrought, both in the heartes, and in
the handes of many great learned Clerkes, both heere
and elsewhere; both heeretofore, and at this day, to
make them withdraw their mindes from writing, and to
withholde their pens from paper: some witnesses wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie
credite could testifie, but that dayly experience
needeth no farther proofe. Howbeit, when it is well
knowen, and ought accordingly to be considered, that
the place alledged shold rather correct the bookish hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor
of cōmon writers, &amp; idle discoursers, then control
the writing of necessarie and needefull workes, which
to the singular aduancement of kingdomes &amp; cōmon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weales,
to the most excellent seruice of almighty God,
to the inestimable benefit and blessing of his Church,
many hundred yeeres, sithens that saying of Salomon,
haue beene printed and published notwithstanding:
(as by large volumes innumerable, of Scriptures and
fathers, of histories and artes in all kinds of knowledge
<pb facs="3"/>
may euidently appeare): Euery man of abilitie, should
rather by those examples encourage himself, the suffer
himselfe by these wordes to be disswaded, to imploye
the talent, as wel of his hand, as of his tongue, to meete
with, and ouertake all practises, &amp; inconueniences, and
as it were, to applie a salue to euerie sore; to minister a
medicine to euerie maladie, that may occurre. Againe
when we perceiue Sanballat, Tobiah, Geshem, Noadi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah
the Prophetesse, and their accomplices, continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to hinder and impeach, as much as in them lyeth, the
worke of Gods Temple; that is Papistes, Iesuites, and
Malecontentes, with their adherents, all aduersaries
&amp; enimies to the euerlasting truth of the Gospell, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
intermission to abuse their great leasure, and small
learning, to plant error and heresie in the heartes of
our brethren, thereby to supplant all religious woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe
of almightie God, all audience of his woorde
and reuerence to his Sacramentes, all humble obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
to lawefull Magistrates, all dutifull regarde of
wholesome lawes, all carefull obseruation of aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
discipline, all sincere and seemely conuersati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of Christian life and honest manners: howe can
the holie Ghost (who reprooueth the woorlde of
sinne) but require vs to bestowe all the forces and
habilimentes wee haue, not onely as good Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rias
and Aggeus to prophecie, but as godly Zoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babell
and Salathiell, to reedifie, that is, aswell by
writing, as by preaching; aswell by our bookes, as
by our sermons, and as it were with a trowell in the
one hande, and a sworde in the other, to rayse and
erect the newe Ierusalem, supplying the decayes,
<pb facs="3"/>
repairing the ruines, filling vp the breaches, building
vp the wals and towers of Sion in perfect beauty? The
consideratiō wherof together with some other earnest
and vehement perswasions to the like effect vsed: did at
the last though long first, induce the most reuerend au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour
of this booke, euē another Esdras or Nehemias
to suffer these his labours to come to light: aswell for
that he mought leaue behinde him a witnesse and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
of his godly &amp; zealous affection, that the professiō
of his faith mought become the sweete sauour of life to
life in all rather thē the sauour of death, to death in any:
as also for that words spokē are soone come soone gon
but written withall, may make a deeper impression,
&amp; so by striking aswell the eye of the reader, as the eare
of the hearer, may perse his heart the better: &amp; saue his
soule the sooner. Of the booke it selfe I will saie but
this: that for myne owne parte, I am verilie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded,
there is no worke, written in this kinde, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
men of principall estate, or particular callings, may
be either more sufficiently enformed to know, or more
plainely directed to performe their seueral duties: The
superiour how to gouerne, the inferiour how to obey:
the Minister what to teach, the people what to learne:
the Parliament what to establish, the Realme what to
embrace: her Maiestie and counsaill what to heare,
Courte, Citie, and Countrie what to amend: why Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trones
especially professing godlines should be vncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt:
why Pastours vndergoing such a charge shoulde
keepe the flocke from the foxe and wolfe; why Bishops
should be more vigilant &amp; precise not to admit Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters
hand ouer head: why the rich should be open han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="4"/>
and poore Christ in his needie members compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenlie
relieued: how the Church to be disciphered by
hir proper marks of the word to be heard with diligēce,
and the sacramentes with reuerence to be frequented:
how the Temple to be purged of idolatrie, superstition
and superfluitie, the Church men of ignoraunce, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence
and simonie, the commonweale of vnmerciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
couetousnesse, and vsurie, the iudgement seates
both ciuill and Ecclesiasticall of briberie, extortion &amp;
partiality: why the Gospell to be preached with fauour,
the Law with terrour, yet both with a caueat: how God
to be worshipped, our neighbours intreated, our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
&amp; families catechised, our selues conformed to
Christ his image, the simple aduised, the subtill preuē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
the weake supported, the obstinate corrected, what
patience to be vsed vnder the crosse, what thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
to be shewed for Gods great mercies, what pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
in our extremest necessities to be powred out: what
sorrow must throw downe the sinfull man, what faith
raise him vp, what hope sustaine him, what charitie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame
him, what worthy fruites commend him to the
world: finally, how the truth may be cōfirmed, falshood
refelled, vice reproued, vertue aduaunced, and so the
child of God made a man wise vnto saluation, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly
enabled vnto euery good worke: Besides many
other most profitable obseruations, sooner taught
then learned, yet sooner learned then followed, such &amp;
so many, as in so few sermons you shal hardly finde
I beleeue, but in the same. Nor is this my single opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
only, but many mens censure of greater learning
&amp; better iudgment: who know what belonges to mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="4"/>
and method, to times and persons, to place and
occasions, with other due circumstances of well and
wise meaning, speaking and writing. But as those ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
be best praysed euer, that be euer best practised:
so if these shall be receiued into the good grounde of
your heartes, with the same affection and spirite they
were preached first, and nowe be published, no doubt
but the sower, the seede, the soile, the increase and all,
will be founde to the glorie of his grace, that worketh
all in all. Wherfore as not onely Paul, Apollos, &amp; Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas,
but all are ours, and we are Christs, and Christ is
Gods: so let vs comfort and strengthen one another,
in our holy faith, holding nothing more deere vnto vs,
then the saluatiō ech of others: and in Gods holy feare
commend we one another to that faithful creator, who
is father of all, aboue vs all, and through vs all,
and in vs all. To him be rendred all thanks,
and all honour geuen for euer
and for euer.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>