<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY MVCH HO∣noured Lady, the Ladie MAR∣GARET HELE of Weu∣burie in Deuon.</title>
           <author>Hieron, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116028_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03302</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13417</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116028</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY MVCH HO∣noured Lady, the Ladie MAR∣GARET HELE of Weu∣burie in Deuon.</title>
                 <author>Hieron, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The life and death of Dorcas : VVherein, hee that pleaseth to reade, may finde both good direction for the ordering of his course: and a necessary warning to be prepared for his end. By Samuel Hieron</title>
                 <author>Hieron, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bradwood, Melchisidec</publisher>
                    <distributor>Macham, Samuel 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 21, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO MY MVCH HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Lady, the Ladie MAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GARET HELE of Weu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie in Deuon.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adame, many things, which I haue obserued in you, do euen assure me, that this small present shall finde some fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour with you: these two especially; your reuerent estimation of the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God (the word preached) and your more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular respect vnto my ministrie: Other things I could name, but that I do abhorre the very smell and shadow of flatterie. It hath pleased you some time, to craue of me the notes of some things which I haue (in your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring) taught in publique: Being much desired by many to commit to printing, that which God enabled mee very lately to deliuer, at the funerals of a worthy gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle-woman of these parts, I thought to inscribe it vnto your Ladie-ships name, as a pledge of my true desire to further you (all I may) in your iourney towards Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. The matter is, of a woman, in the Scripture well reported of, both for her holy profession, and for her
<pb facs="3"/>
gracious fruit, to whom the more like your Ladie-ship shall become, the better shall your assurance be of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into rest: I commend the Sermon to your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, the person treated of to your Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and your bodie and soule to the protection of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, my selfe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Ladie-ships ready seruitor in any Christian office SAM. HIERON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>