<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116967_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20684</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7083</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116967</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of diuorcement : A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the 10. of May. 1601. By Iohn Doue, Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Dove, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dexter, Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 62, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Had not published my
late Sermon, the world
beeing alreadie so full of
bookes, had I not bene
mistaken by some which
vnderstood it not, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iustly
traduced by others
which heard it not, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting
of it, as they would haue it, and not as
I deliuered it, not so much offended with the
Sermon, as with the Preacher. They take ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions:
Against the matter, as if the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine
were not sound. Against my words, and
maner of deliuering it, as irreuerend, because
I presumed not onely to speake against <hi>Beza</hi>
without crauing pardon, without ascribing
praise and commendation otherwise due to his
great deseruings, but also to passe him ouer
slightly, calling him by his bare name, without
addition; as if so doing, I did <hi>Peccare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trà formam
sanorum verborum,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1. 13.</note> not keepe


<pb facs="3"/>
the patterne of wholsome words. Against the
text it selfe, as vnseasonable for the time, and
vnpleasing to the auditory. Against my diuision
and reading of the text, as straunge and inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,
the like neuer heard of before: as if I had
offered violence to the holy scriptures.</p>
   <p>I answere with the Apostle: I passe litle
to be iudged by you,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.</note> or of mans iudgement. I
haue builded vpon no other foundation then
that which is already laid,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.</note> that is, Iesus Christ:
whether I haue builded gold, siluer, pearles, or
timber, haye stubble, whether my worke will
abide, and proue such for the which I shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
wages, or not: let it bee made <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>est,
I feare not that day, I refuse not the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,
which is the onely true iudge of all mens
workes. The holy Ghost hath taught me in the
meane while that the Ministers of Christ must
passe through many things,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Cor. 6.</note> honour and disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
good report and bad report, as deceiuers,
and yet true.</p>
   <p>M. <hi>Beza</hi> cannot blame me for dissenting
from him, because he hath done so by S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi>
and all the Fathers: nor for vsing his
name without addition, because hee hath done
the like by S. <hi>Paul</hi> and all the Apostles. I dare
not follow S. <hi>Paul</hi> farther then hee is a fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower
of Christ,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> and therefore must dissent frō


<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Beza</hi> when he dissenteth from Christ. I was
not then ignorant how thanklesse an office it
was to speake of him, whose authoritie is with
some, more canonicall then the canonicall
scriptures, to name <hi>Beza</hi> before them which
haue onely heard of his name, but knowe not
how to spell it, (for they call him <hi>Bezer,</hi> as
also <hi>Bellarmine</hi> they call <hi>Bellamye,</hi>) they
would bee Doctors of the Lawe,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 17.</note> but knowe
not what they speake, or whereof they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme,)
it is very likely they haue read his
workes, and are able to iudge of his doctrine.
But I came thither to preach Christ, not
to commend any man, for so had I not beene
the seruant of Christe. And this I may
speake without offence: M. <hi>Beza</hi> hath
not deliuered all truth, but left some to others
to bee deliuered. And therefore I exhort
them that they would not condemne this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine
because hee holdeth the contrarye,<note place="margin">Epist. Iudae v. 10. &amp; 16.</note> least
they immitate the false Prophets which
speake euill of the thinges which they knowe
not, and haue mens persons in admiration,
whom also they knowe not, and so commit
grosser Idolatrie by worshipping a man, then
Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> did by worshipping an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell.</p>
   <p>If an Angell from heauen preach new doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine,<note place="margin">Apoc. 19.</note>
      <pb facs="4"/>
he is accursed,<note place="margin">Gal. 1. 8.</note> much lesse may the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine
which any man publisheth, be presently
receiued without further triall, <hi>Eô nomine,</hi>
because hee taught it:<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 4.</note> but the spirit must be
tried, the doctrine must be examined, be the
credit of the Doctor neuer so great.</p>
   <p>I haue alwaies opposed my selfe against
popularitie, as an enemie to true godlinesse,
supposing that they which preach mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
ought their selues to bee mortified from
vaine ostentation of great auditories, ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
desire of many followers, and glorying in
multitudes of Disciples,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6. 15.</note> by the example of
our Sauiour, which withdrew himselfe from
the multitude, when he sawe they would take
him vp and make him a King. And therefore
haue I refrained to intrude my selfe into such
great assemblies; as also that I might not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud
mine owne congregation, but contented
my selfe to keepe my station in mine owne
watch-tower, ouer that flocke onely, ouer
which God hath made me an ouerseer. I desire
his glory and not mine owne: I say with <hi>Iohn</hi>
the Baptist,<note place="margin">Ioh. 3. 30.</note> he must increase, and I must de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease.
But beeing called to that place of so
great expectation, I thought it fit to choose
mine owne text; in which choise, if the wiser
sort of men will say I haue erred, I will craue


<pb facs="4"/>
pardon for mine error.</p>
   <p>I was required by the Magistrate, vpon
shorter warning then ordinary, to supply a
course, which else had stood voyd; so that my
tongue was become the pen of a swift writer:
yet haue I not by reason of haste,<note place="margin">Ier. 48.</note> done the
worke of the Lord altogether negligently, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
was I with the Disciples carelesse what
I should speake,<note place="margin">Math. 10▪</note> looking that it should be giuen
me in that houre; but my heart did with the
Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 45.</note> first indite the matter before
I spake it. In expounding this text, I did as
<hi>Daniel</hi> expounding a dreame,<note place="margin">Dan. 2.</note> vse both pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
and meditation: and I assure my selfe, I
haue according to the Apostles rule,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.</note> shewed my
selfe approued vnto God, a workeman which
needeth not to be ashamed diuiding the word
aright. And whosoeuer will stand to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thechisme
and rudiments of Christian religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and submit himself to the rules of Logicke,
will he, nill he, he must confesse, that my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
and diuiding the text is very naturall,
and no way forced. Concerning this point, I
am to satisfie a kinde of men differing from the
other of which I spake before, which will haue
marriage after diuorcement, as well of the
partie innocent as of the nocent, to be adultery;
and yet the diuorcement it selfe, which they


<pb facs="5"/>
graunt to be a dissolution of marriage, to be
lawfull, so that they will build without a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,
and make a consequent without an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent.
For how can marriage after diuorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
be vnlawfull, if the diuorcement it selfe
stand good? How is it possible to graunt a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorce,
but with full power to marry againe?
when the first mariage is lawfully dissolued,
what can hinder a second marriage? But to
strengthen their error▪ they except against the
diuision of my text: they will haue it to be but
categoricall, which I haue said to be hypotheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,
they alleadge that no proposition can be hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheticall
vnlesse it be conditionall. To oppose
themselues against me, they except against the
Cathechisme it self, against the grounds of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke,
by which they lay themselues open to no
small reproach. Euerie young scholler which
hath learned <hi>Seron</hi> can tell thē that all hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theticall
propositions are not conditionall, but
some copulatiue, some disiunctiue, and that all
propositions are hypotheticall, which may bee
resolued into two categoricalls, and that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
these words as they are set downe in Saint
<hi>Matthew,</hi> and more plaine in S. <hi>Marke,</hi> and
most plaine in S. <hi>Luke,</hi> the commas and points
being in all three alike obserued: to wit, <hi>Vxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m
dimittens, &amp; aliam ducens, maechatur,</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
That is, both he which diuorceth his wife, and
he which marrieth an other, committeth adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
are an hypotheticall copulatiue proposition,
and containe in them two categoricalls: <hi>Vxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem
dimittens maechatur, &amp; vxorem aliam
ducens maechatur,</hi> Both of them being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
exception perfectly true propositions in
Logicke, according to the definition and forme
of a proposition. But for as much as <hi>I</hi> haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided
my text according to forme, which is the
very life of all diuisions, my diuisions is iustified
who haue diuided the whole text into three
propositions. The case being cleare concerning
the forme, that this text conteineth three
true propositions, they can contend with mee
onely about the matter of the first proposition,
whether it bee <hi>Secundum qualitatem in <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e,
vera or falsa.</hi> They aske how it can be adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie
for a man to put away his wife, when hee
dooth not onely abstaine from the second
marriage, from all carnall knowledge, but
also from coueting of any other? Adulterie
say they, consisteth onely in carnall knowledge,
and in coueting, and no writer of credit will
say that there can bee any other adulterie.
By which wordes they make Saint <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sostome</hi>
to bee a Writer of no credite,<note place="margin">Dè inuent. sanctae crucis. Hom 20.</note>
which saieth: <hi>Viro casto qualiscun{que} vxor


<pb facs="6"/>
bona videtur, quia perfecta charitas vitia
non sentit. Qui diligit vxorem, de soluen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do
matrimonio legis praecepta necessaria,
non habet, vbi autèm de soluendo matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monio
lex requiritur, illic iam odium de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstratur,
vbi odium inuenitur, illìc iam
fornicatio esse cognoscitur.</hi> A chaste man
will thinke well of his wife though faultie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
perfect charitie will not espie offences.
He which loueth his wife, thinketh the lawe of
diuorcement superfluous and very needlesse:
but where aduantage of lawe is required for
the vndoing of marriage, there hatred appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth;
but where there is hatred of a mans wife,
there is also fornication. Againe, <hi>Quemad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modùm,
si videas hominem assiduè amici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias
medicorum colentem, exipsâre sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim
intelligis quià infirmus est: sic &amp; cùm
videris siuè virum siuè mulierem dè dimit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tēdis
vxoribus aut viris legē interrogantes,
cognosce quia vit iste lasciuus est, &amp; muli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
illa meretrix est.</hi> Euen as that man which
continually resorteth to the Phisitian to aske
aduise, sheweth that his body is not sound: so
when man or wife asketh counsell of the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer
how they may be diuorced, the man so do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
is vnhonest; the woman so doing, is adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous.
Likewise, they make <hi>Vrsinus</hi> to be a


<pb facs="6"/>
writer of no credit, which interpreteth this
commaundement, <hi>Thou shalt not commit
adulterie,</hi> in this maner. The scope and drif<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
of this commaundement (saith hee) is the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation
of chastitie, and the vpholding of
marriage, and all things are by it forbidden,
which any waies are causes, or effects, antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,
or consequents, contrary to chastitie, or
contrary to marriage. But say I, by diuorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
marriage is dissolued, and therefore not
vpheld or maintained by such a diuorcemēt as
is allowed to be good; and yet with a restraint
from a second marriage, men and women are
caused to burne in lust, and defrauded of that
benefit which God hath appointed to be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie
against fornication: and therefore by it,
chastitie is not preserued, and by a consequent
adultery is committed. But to answere them
in a word, how hee which diuorceth his wife
committeth adultery, he committeth adultry
two maner of wayes: first as a principall offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
because he breaketh wedlocke; for so di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorcement
is defined the dissolution of marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,
or vntying of the knot of sacred wedlocke:
and the briefest sort of the English and Duch
Cathechismes, haue in stead of thou shalt not
commit adultry, in more generall termes, thou
shalt not breake wedlocke: whereby it is the


<pb facs="7"/>
iudgement of the Churches of <hi>England</hi> and
<hi>Germanie,</hi> that all breach of the law of wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke
is adultery: and wedlocke is in no degree
so highly broken as by diuorcement▪ by which it
is dissolued. Secondly he committeth adulterie
as a partie accessary, for he giueth his wife al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance
to marry againe, which my aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
do confesse to be adultery. That the intent
and meaning of diuorcement is to vndoo the
first marriage, and giue license to the second
marriage, who can speake better thē the Iewes
themselues, of whom the Christians did learne
it, and the Christian Churches which doo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
it and put it in practise? That the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorcement
which was permitted by <hi>Moyses,</hi>
was with permission also to marry again, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth
by <hi>Moses</hi> himself. <hi>Deut. 24.</hi> That it is
so among the Iewes, in these dayes it appeareth
by the very forme of their Schodule or Bill of
diuorcement, which hath these words, <hi>do vx<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ori
meae potesttatem eundi quò velit, nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendi
cui velit.</hi> I giue my wife libertie to goe
whither she will, and to marry whom she will.
That it is so vnderstood among the Christian
Churches where diuorcement is practised, it is
plaine by the confession of M. <hi>Beza</hi> in his
booke <hi>De diuortio,</hi> as in my Sermon I haue
declared. As for my maner of reading, let them


<pb facs="7"/>
readie as I haue read it, or as it is in the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall,
all is one in substance, (I did it but for
explication sake, as an Interpretor, not as a
bare reader) they cannot vnderstand it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
then I did read it: let them diuide it as I
did, or otherwise, it will make a difference in
outward forme, the doctrine will be the same.
Onely this aduertisement I will be bold to giue
to some kind of Preachers in our Church: that
true preaching doth not consist in heaping vp of
common places, in prolixitie and length of
speech, in multitudes of quotatiōs of Authors,
chapters and verses, nor in rash deliuering of
doctrine taken by tradition, vpon the bare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
&amp; credit of others, without further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination.
But he which will expound such a
text as this is, must suppose it to be like the
Hebrew Bible, which needed the Chalde pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphrase
that the Iewes might vnderstand it:
the rocke in the wildernesse which was to bee
cleft by <hi>Moses</hi> his rodde before water would
issue out of it:<note place="margin">Ex. 17.</note> the Land of promise,<note place="margin">Psal. 59.</note> which was
not presently discouered:<note place="margin">1. Reg. 18.</note> the heauē which was
shut vp, and opened but by <hi>Elias</hi> his prayers,
before it rayned:<note place="margin">Deut. 25.</note> the corne which was troden
with the oxes foote, and rubbed by the hands
of the Disciples before it was eaten:<note place="margin">Math. 12.</note> the booke
to be vnsealed by the Lambe, before the myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
in it could be reuealed:<note place="margin">Apoc. 5.</note> the face of <hi>Moses,</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
which had a vaile or couering before it,<note place="margin">Ex. 34.</note> to bee
remooued before his beautie could appeare:<note place="margin">Iud. 14. &amp; 15</note>
the tooth in the Asses iaw-bone, and the Lyons
carkasse which required <hi>Sampsons</hi> strength,
before his thirst could bee quenched, before
sweetnesse could be drawne out of the strong,
or meate out of the eater: the handling of it
may not be triuiall or vulgar.</p>
   <p>Hauing thus according to my poore talent,
deliuered that which I hope will not be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siue
to the godly, because it is cōsonant to Gods
word, nor scandalous to the state, as tending to
schisme, or maintenance of strife, because it is
according to the Decree established the last
Parliament, by the generall consent of the
Cleargie; my humble desire is, that the world
would so thinke of vs, as of the Ministers of
Christ, and disposers of the secrets of God, of
whom it is required that euery one should bee
found faithfull, and to thinke of mee concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
M. <hi>Beza,</hi> that I do blesse and magnifie
God mightily for all the good parts which are
in him, that I am <hi>Famulus seruorum Dei,</hi>
touching all the true seruants of God, I liue to
do God and them seruice. And so I commend
them to the gracious protection of him whom
they serue.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>