<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Honourable Syr Henry Compton Knight, Lorde Compton of Compton.</title>
           <author>D., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116352_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21163</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7518</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116352</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Honourable Syr Henry Compton Knight, Lorde Compton of Compton.</title>
                 <author>D., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The paradyse of daintie deuises : Contayning sundrie pithie preceptes, learned counsels, and excellent inuentions: right pleasaunt and profitable for all estates. Deuised and written for the most part, by M. Edwards, sometimes of her Maiesties Chappell: the rest by sundry learned gentlemen, both of honour, and worship, whose names hereafter followe</title>
                 <author>Edwards, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Disle (Disley, Dizle), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>3, 51, that is 45 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Right Honourable Syr Henry Compton Knight, Lorde Compton of Compton.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT HONORABLE, AND MY</hi> very good Lord, (presuming vpon your courtesy) I am bolde to present vnto your Honour, this small volume, Entituled, <hi>The Paradice of daintie Deuises,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing penned by diuers learned Gentlemen, and col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected togither through the trauaile of one, both of worship and credite, for his priuate vse: who not long since de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted this life, which when I had perused ouer, not without the aduise of sundry my friendes, I determined by their good motion to set them in print, who therevnto greatly perswaded mee, with these and like wordes. The writers of them, were both of honour and worship, besydes that, our owne countreymen, and such as for their learning and grauitie, might be accounted of, among the wisest. Furthermore, the ditties both pithie and pleasaunt, as well for the inuention as meeter, and will yeelde a farre greater delight, being as they are, so aptly made to be sette to any song in 5. partes, or song to instrument. Which well considering, I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed not to forsake so good an occasion, beseching your honor to accept in good part, cheefelye for the Authours sake: who though some of them are departed this life, yet their worthy do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings shall continue for euer, for like as the shadow followeth the body, so praise followeth vertue, and as the shadowe goeth sometimes before, and sometimes behinde, so doeth praise also to vertue: but the later it cōmeth, the greater it is, and to be the better esteemed. Thus fearing to offend your Honor with these my rude speeches, I end, wishing your L. many yeres of ioy.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your good Lordships wholy to commaund. H. D.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>