<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST EXCELLENT, HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE CHARLES KING OF GREAT BRITAINE France, &amp; Ireland &amp;c. Health and eternall felicitie.</title>
           <author>Eremita, Anonymvs</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116351_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20672</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7072.4</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116351</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST EXCELLENT, HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE CHARLES KING OF GREAT BRITAINE France, &amp; Ireland &amp;c. Health and eternall felicitie.</title>
                 <author>Eremita, Anonymvs</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of the visible sacrifice of the Church of God· The first part. VVritten by Anonymus Eremita</title>
                 <author>Doughty, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Antoine—Velpius, Hubert 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Brussels</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>99, 200-246, 235-248, that is 238, 2, 40, 43-154, that is 155, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST EXCELLENT, HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE CHARLES KING OF GREAT BRITAINE France, &amp; Ireland &amp;c. Health and eternall felicitie.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost dread Soueraigne;</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>So many are the temporall bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings, which All<seg rend="sup">tie.</seg> God hath bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon your Royall Maiestie, that scarcely can they be paralelled in any other: A <hi>Monarke</hi> of three Kingdomes, all fortefied with the Ocean sea; a <hi>Queene</hi> wyse, vertuous, beutifull, and fruitefull; subiects without number, all in peace, and plentie, stry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing how to expresse their loues and obedience to so worthie a soueraigne; health of Body, and dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition of mynd fitt for any heroicall action: so that not knowing what to wish, or how to adde any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
<pb n="4" facs="3"/> vnto your present temporall estate, and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, as much as in me lyeth I desyre with all my heart, that these your temporall blessings, may also be seconded with spirituall, &amp; eternall. And for this cause, and to this end hauing occasion to wryte of a <hi>Medecine against mortalitie, of a Receipt against all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seases, corruption and death; of a Soueraigne Balme,</hi> which whosoeuer will vse worthely, shall liue eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally: I could not but dedicate, these my labours vnto your Maiestie vnto whom aboue all men liuing I wish compleat felicitie; that protected by your royall fauour, this <hi>Cordiall</hi> may worke the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect I desire, which is euerlasting happines to your selfe, &amp; subiects. And so imploring your royall cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie with most humble respects, and profound submission I cast my selfe and labours vnder the shadow of your <hi>gratious protection,</hi> euer to remaine,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Of your Sacred Maiestie A most humble, and most faithfull subject,</hi> ANONYMVS EREMITA.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>