<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Dr. AMES HIS PREFACE to Mr. Bs. Answere.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116130_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11736</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3533</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116130</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Dr. AMES HIS PREFACE to Mr. Bs. Answere.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The unreasonablnes of the separation : made apparent, in an examination of, and answere to, certaine reasons of Maister Francis Johnson: whereby he laboureth to justifie his schisme from the church assemblies of England; By Maister VVilliam Bradshaw deceased. Together wit a rejoinder, in defence of the said answere against the late reply of Maister Iohn Canne (a leader to a company of Brownists in Amsterdam) thereunto, by a freind [sic] of the deceased</title>
                 <author>Bradshaw, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 149, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="1" facs="5"/>
   <head>D<seg rend="sup">r.</seg> AMES HIS PREFACE to M<seg rend="sup">r.</seg> B<seg rend="sup">s.</seg> Answere.</head>
   <head>To the well-meaning Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hinke not evill, if thou meanest well. wee intend not to insult over him that is down, or to pursue a man that is flying of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe; but to lend him a hand, that knoweth not well which way to take. M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Iohnson indeed is rather to be pittyed, then much opposed. wee need but stand stil as lookers on, he falleth willingly on his owne sword. But that his fall may be a rising againe, not onely to himselfe, but to others also, both armour-bearers &amp; fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of his; it was judged necessary to guide them a little while their heads are dizzy, &amp; bring them fairely from of the bog they have stood on.</p>
   <p>It is not M. Iohnson that is dealt withall alone. For change the name onely &amp; put in Mr. Ainsworth, or any such: themselves wil not say, but the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons are theirs, and the Answere to them as well as to him. It may be, that they having lesse acquaintāce with Logical formes of dispute, wil looke for large discourse, or heaped quotations out of Scripture. But reason wil tell them, that many words do rather hide, then untie the knot of a Syllogisme: and much quoting may prove something; but answereth not directly to any thing. Now the writers meaning was, not to gather proofes; but to point at the weaknesse of such as these men have gathered. Reade therefore with under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, &amp; learn a mean betwixt <hi>all</hi> &amp; <hi>Nothing.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>