<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Christian READER.</title>
           <author>Rogers, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116092_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10908</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21178</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116092</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Christian READER.</title>
                 <author>Rogers, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Protestant Church existent, and their faith professed in all ages, and by whom : with a catalogue of councels in all ages, who professed the same. Written, by Henry Rogers D.D. prebendary of Hereford</title>
                 <author>Rogers, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Badger, Richard 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Parsons, Marmaduke</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 176 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Christian <hi>READER.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome passages betweene Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>Fisher</hi> and my selfe, about twelve yeares past were published and Printed without my knowledge. Master <hi>Fisher</hi> delivered to divers Parsonages of good qualitie, certaine propositions concerning the Protestant Faith, Church, and Succession; to which (though then farre from home, and from my Bookes) I gave a short Answer, with a Catalogue of Orthodox Writers, who professed our Faith in the first 700 yeares. To this Answer of mine, some yeares after, a reply was published (whether by Master <hi>Fisher</hi> himselfe, or some
<pb facs="6"/>
other in his behalfe, I know not) a sight whereof I could not get in a yeare or two af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. To that reply of his, I answer in this ensu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Discourse, with a Catalogue from the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Centurie to the fifteenth, of such as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed our faith; which Catalogue of perticular men being finished, I have added a Catalogue of Councels in all Ages, who professed our faith. This booke of mine was finished seven or eight yeares past, as a noble personage now imployed by our Soveraigne King in forraign parts can testifie; who bestowed some books upon me, which were very usefull unto mee in this Worke, which he did read; as did also many learned Doctors of our Church of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reford.</hi>
      <note place="margin">D. Kernit. D. Best. D. Hoskin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed.</note> I was slow in publishing it, having no desire to be in Print: but the perswasions of some of our Church, and the brags of some of our Adversaries, saying that I neither had, nor could answer Master <hi>Fisher,</hi> caused me to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent it to the licencer. And so to send it into the view of the world, requesting the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Reader, first to peruse the former booke printed without my knowledge. Secondly, to observe how my Adversarie doth passe by many principall things, in my first answer,
<pb facs="6"/>
without any mention at all of the same. Thirdly, that of what he hath written against me, I passe not by any one sentence un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>answered.</p>
   <p>My Booke hath two generall heads.</p>
   <p>First, what our Faith and Church is, and how proved; primarily, and properly by Scriptures; secondarily, and improperly by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons and humane testimony.</p>
   <p>Secondly, that by this way of a Catalogue of those who taught their faith, or <hi>Trent</hi> Creed, as distinct from ours, they cannot prove their succession, for many reasons alleadged by me in the thirteenth Chapter of this booke, as first the uncertainty of humane testimony. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, their purging out of Authors, that which makes against them. Thirdly, their forging of Authors, and Councels; fourthly, their slighting and abasing of the Ecclesiasticall Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storians of the Primitive Church, example whereof shall be shewed as occasion shall be offered.</p>
   <p>I will conclude this my Preface with those words of Saint <hi>Augustine,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ep.</hi> 48.</note>
      <hi>Necesse est incerti sint qui pro societate sua testimonio utuntur, non divino
<pb facs="7"/>
sed suo.</hi> But let us with S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Augustine</hi> cleave to the Scriptures, and say with him, <hi>Ecce ubi didi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimus Christum,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ep.</hi> 166.</note>
      <hi>ecce ubi didicimus Ecclesiam,</hi> Loe where we have learned Christ, loe where we have learned <hi>to find</hi> his Church. Give the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to God for what is well, and impute the imperfections and defects to my weaknesse, who will to my poore ability be</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in the Lord.</hi> H. R,</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>