<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Breuiat of the Historie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116620_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11366</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21625</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116620</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Breuiat of the Historie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The tvvo most vvorthy and notable histories which remaine vnmained to posterity (viz:) the conspiracie of Cateline, vndertaken against the gouernment of the Senate of Rome, and the vvarre which Iugurth for many yeares maintained against the same state. Both written by C.C. Salustius</title>
                 <author>Sallust</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Jaggard (Jagger), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Jaggard (Jagger), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jaggard, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 60, 6, 8, 7-110, 2 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb facs="45"/>
   <pb facs="45"/>
   <head>A Breuiat of the Historie.</head>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Now the Realm of</hi> Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>is <hi>in</hi> Barbary.</note>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>VMIDIA,</hi> contayneth that part of <hi>Affrick,</hi> wherein <hi>Massinissa</hi> the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full friend and confederate of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> people, sometime raigned. This <hi>Massinissa</hi> had three Sonnes; <hi>Micip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sa, Manastaball</hi> and <hi>Gulussa. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nastaball</hi> and <hi>Gulussa</hi> died; by whose death the Kingdome entirely descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to <hi>Micipsa. Micipsa</hi> had issue, <hi>Adherbal</hi> and <hi>Hiempsal; Iugurth,</hi> he fostered as the Sonne of his Brother <hi>Manastabal,</hi> for that his Grand-father <hi>Massinissa</hi> had left him vnaduanced, as his base Grand-Childe begotten on the body of a Concubine. The man was ambitious, well qualified, of a ready wit, and great spirit, elder then <hi>Adherbal</hi> or <hi>Hiempsal.</hi> In iealousie whereof, <hi>Micipsa,</hi> fearing that if he should die during the mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his children, that their Cousin <hi>Iugurth</hi> might happen am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biciously to vsurpe the Kingdome, resolued to oppose him to daungerous aduentures, in hope by these meanes to see him miscarry.</p>
   <p>About the same time it happened, that the <hi>Romans,</hi> vnder the conduct of <hi>Scipio,</hi> besieged <hi>Numantia</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto <hi>Micipsa</hi> sent certaine Regiments of Horse and foote, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the commaund of his Kinsman <hi>Iugurth,</hi> their Generall; making full accoūt in this iourney, to heare newes answerable to his plotted desseignements, but Fortune had otherwise decreed: for in this war, the reputation of <hi>Iugurth</hi> more and more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased; yea, he made so many faire proofes of his valour in this Action, that <hi>Scipio</hi> not only commended him in a publicke Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but (the warre ended, and <hi>Numantia</hi> razed) he inuested him with many military honors; by his Letters commending his seruice to <hi>Micipsa,</hi> in very worthy and honourable tearmes,
<pb facs="46"/>
which bred so sodaine an alteration in the King, that whereas before, he fully minded his destruction, hee now wisheth and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth nothing so much as his welfare and aduancement; adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him his Sonne, and shortly after dying, left him Co-heire with his Children, throughout his whole estates and dominions. After whose disease, the three Roytelets, <hi>Adherbal, Hiemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal</hi> and <hi>Iugurth,</hi> deuising with themselues about the portion of the Kingdome, <hi>Iugurth</hi> trayterously slayeth <hi>Hiempsal,</hi> the younger of the twaine, and casting in his haughty mind, how by the death of the other, he might become sole Lord of the whole, firmely resolueth to leuy an Army, wherwith he giueth the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw to the elder Brother <hi>Adherbal.</hi> Who after this defeature, flyeth to <hi>Rome,</hi> and there aggrauating his Brothers death, his owne banishment, and <hi>Iugurths</hi> treasons, beseecheth aid of the Lordes of the Senate. The Lords accord, and send tenne Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners into <hi>Affricke,</hi> to make diuision of the Kingdome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them: who had no sooner ended the businesse, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their backes, but <hi>Iugurth</hi> entertayned his former practises, and a new inuadeth his Brothers portion with warre and slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. To represse this his insolency, <hi>Adherbal</hi> of meere necessitie is driuen to leuy an Army, and to march against <hi>Iugurth,</hi> but is againe ouerthrowne, and with a few Horsemen in his company forced to fly vnto <hi>Cirtha,</hi> whether <hi>Iugurth</hi> aduaunceth his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and besiegeth the Citty. Hereof <hi>Adherbal</hi> by Letters cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifieth the Lordes of the Senate, giuing them to vnderstand, vppon what desperate tearmes his estate depended, how hee was depriued of his kingdome by <hi>Iugurth,</hi> and forced by warre and famine to vndergoe such vtmost extremities, that long time he was not able to make good the place of his refuge, euen the sanctuary of his life: That his aduersary little regarded the censures of the Senat: finally, that they would vouchsafe to send him potent and speedy succours. Vpon the opening of these Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters many gaue their opinions, in fauour of the distressed estate of <hi>Adherbal,</hi> but others corrupted by the <hi>Numidian,</hi> aduised rather to send Commissioners vnto <hi>Iugurth,</hi> with authority to commaund him in the name of the Lordes and people of <hi>Rome,</hi> to abstaine from farther violence. <hi>Iugurth</hi> gaue these Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners during their imployment in <hi>Affricke,</hi> faire language and faithfull protestations, but after their departure fell a
<pb facs="46"/>
fresh to his former proiects. Wherupon, the besieged, desire <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herbal</hi> to pitty the estates of so many innocent people in the Towne, that seeing he could not otherwise prouide for his safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that he would yeelde the place vpon assurance of his life one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Which being granted, and the towne surrendred, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of Oth or kindred, <hi>Iugurth</hi> falsifieth his Faith, and cruelly murdereth his innocent Brother. The newes whereof much dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted the Lordes of the Senate, and therefore they posted away <hi>Lucius Calphurnius Bestia</hi> (the Consull) with an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my into <hi>Affricke,</hi> to giue stop to his further proceedinges: but he being corrupted by <hi>Iugurth,</hi> in stead of punishing the Traitor, concluded a most dishonorable peace. Wherewith the Lordes of the Senat being much more moued then before, dispatched away <hi>Albinius</hi> the Consull, with order and authority to represse the Traytors insolencies: but him <hi>Iugurth</hi> so long deluded with promises and counterfeit demonstrations of submission and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, that the yeare beeing spent, without doing any thing, he was inforced to leaue all as he found it, and to hasten to Rome against the day of election, nominating his brother <hi>Aulus</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant of the Army &amp; <hi>Prouince.</hi> This man, either on a foolish opinion to reap the glory of finishing this warre, or vppon aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice to fill his priuate Coffers, in <hi>Ianuary,</hi> in the depth of Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, leadeth the Army into the open field. <hi>Iugurth</hi> quickly fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the insufficiency of this new <hi>Generall,</hi> pretending feare and cowardize, trayneth his enemy into woody and mountanous Countries; yea, and to colour his subtilty, sendeth his humble pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition to the <hi>Roman</hi> Generall, with offers of submission and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction. The faster he fled, the more eager was <hi>Aulus</hi> in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suit, vntill <hi>Iugurth</hi> taking the benefit of time, and the aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the place, found easie meanes to rout the whole <hi>Romain</hi> Army. The day following, they fell to composition: First, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Prisoners should be dismissed <hi>Sub iugum</hi>: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the whole army within ten daies cleerly to depart the bounds of <hi>Numidia.</hi> This daunted the people, for the present, but ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering againe their spirits (notwithstanding the composition of <hi>Aulus,</hi> and his peoples ouerthrow) they dimitted <hi>Numidia</hi> to <hi>Metellus</hi> (the Consull) for his Prouince. This excellent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunder finding the Army corrupted by the remisse carriage of
<pb facs="47"/>
his Predecessors, first restored the Ancient discipline, &amp; then by hazarding a set-battell with <hi>Iugurth,</hi> put him to the worse. After him, <hi>Marius</hi> (Consull elect) succeeded in this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince of <hi>Numidia,</hi> who persecuting the war with courage and good Fortune, vtterly vndid the <hi>Numidian,</hi> and getting him into his possession by policy, led him through <hi>Rome</hi> as a Captiue, before his Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphall Chariot.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>