<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116933_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03420</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13544</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116933</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Hocus Pocus Junior : The anatomy of legerdemain. Or, The art of iugling set forth in his proper colours, fully, plainly, and exactly; so that an ignorant person may thereby learn the full perfection of the same, after a little practise. Unto each trick is added the figure, where it is needfull for instruction</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Grove, Francis</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Games and recreations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, do you not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? if you doe not, well you may, to see so sleight a Pamphlet so quickly spent; but lightly come, and lightly go; it is a Juglers term and it well befits the subject. Would you know whence it first came? why, from <hi>Bartholomew</hi> Faire: would you know whither it's bent? for the Faire againe; its a straggler, a wanderer, &amp; as <hi>I</hi> said, as it lightly comes, so it light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goes; for it means to see not only <hi>Bartholomew</hi> Faire, but all the Fairs in the Kingdom also, and therfore in the front, <hi>Hiccius Doccius</hi> is the Post<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>master, and what he wants there, ile give him here, a word or two of command, a term of art, not so much substantial, as circumstantial, <hi>Celeriter, vade,</hi> over hedges and ditches, thorow thick and thin, to come to your Fairs. Room for a Jugler: al in post, yet with a desire to give you ful satisfaction. If you like it, then buy it &amp; read it, if otherwise, leave it for them that list.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>