<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Grounds and Contents of these Histories.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116165_Fr6_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10668</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20944</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116165</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Grounds and Contents of these Histories.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The triumphs of Gods revenge against the crying and execrable sinne of (willfull and premeditated) murther : VVith his miraculous discoveries, and severe punishments thereof. In thirtie severall tragicall histories (digested into sixe bookes) committed in divers countries beyond the seas, never published, or imprinted in any other language. Histories which containe great varietie of mournfull and memorable accidents ... With a table of all the severall letters and challenges, contained in the whole sixe bookes. Written by Iohn Reynolds</title>
                 <author>Reynolds, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lee, William 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lee, William 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 75, 3, 81-181, 7, 187-260, 259-294, that is 293, 7, 303-414, 10, 425-527, 9, 337-404, 409-464 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summaries">
   <pb facs="294"/>
   <head>The Grounds and Contents of these Histories.</head>
   <list>
      <item>
         <hi>History XXVI. Imperia</hi> for the love she beares to young <hi>Morosini,</hi> seduceth and causeth him (with his two Consorts, <hi>Astonicus</hi> and <hi>Donato)</hi> to stifle to death her old Husband <hi>Palme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> in his bed; <hi>Morosini</hi> misfortunately letting fall his gloves in <hi>Palmerius</hi> his chamber that night which he did it; They are found by <hi>Richardo</hi> the Nephew of <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merius,</hi> who knowes them to be <hi>Morosinies,</hi> and doth thereupon accuse him and his Aunt <hi>Imperia,</hi> for the Murther of his Vnkle; So they together with their accessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries <hi>Astonicus</hi> and <hi>Donato,</hi> are all foure of them apprehended and hanged for the same.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>History</hi> XXVII. Father <hi>Iustinian</hi> a Priest, and <hi>Adrian</hi> an Inne-keeper, poyson <hi>De Laurier,</hi> who was lodged in his house, and then bury him in his Orchard; where a moneth after a Wolse digges him up, and devoures a great part of his body; which father <hi>Iustinian</hi> and <hi>Adrian</hi> understanding, they flie upon the same, but are afterwards both of them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and hanged for it.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>History XXVIII. Hippolito</hi> murthereth <hi>Garcia</hi> in the street by night, for the which he is hanged. <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minica</hi> and her Chamber-maid <hi>Denisa,</hi> poysoneth her husband <hi>Roderigo; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisa</hi> afterwards strangleth her owne new borne Babe, and throwes it into a Pond, for the which she is hanged; On the ladder she confessed that she was accessary, with her Lady <hi>Dominica</hi> in the poysoning of her Husband <hi>Roderigo;</hi> for the which <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minica</hi> is apprehended, and likewise hanged.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>History XXIX. Sanctifiore</hi> (upon promise of mariage) gets <hi>Ursina</hi> with childe, and then afterwards very ingratefully and treacherously rejecteth her, and marries <hi>Bertranna: Ursina</hi> being sensible of this her disgrace, disguiseth herselfe in a Friers habit and with a case of Pistols kils <hi>Sanctifiore</hi> as he is walking in the fields, for the which shee is hanged.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>History XXX. De Mora</hi> treacherously kils <hi>Palura</hi> in a Duell with two Pistols: His Lady <hi>Bellinda</hi> with the aid of her Gentlman Vsher <hi>Ferallo,</hi> poysoneth her Husband <hi>De Mora,</hi> and afterwards she marieth and murthereth her said Husband <hi>Ferallo</hi> in his bed; so shee is burnt alive for this her last murther, and her ashes throwne into the aire for the first.</item>
   </list>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>