<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Poste of Pernassus to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116983_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11791</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22080</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116983</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Poste of Pernassus to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Nevves from Pernassus : The politicall touchstone, taken from Mount Pernassus: whereon the governments of the greatest monarchies of the world are touched</title>
                 <author>Scott, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>92, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="47"/>
   <head>The Poste of Pernassus <hi>to the Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>THese Papers comming by chance into my hands, I perceived there was something in them that I could not perceive; wherefore I thought best to communicate them with better vnderstandings: for my part I could see no hurt in them, but did imagine by that little good vvhich I saw, there was much more that I could not see, and therefore judged them fit for all mens eyes. Yet finding the names of <hi>Spayne</hi> and <hi>Austria,</hi> or <hi>Austria</hi> and <hi>Spayne,</hi> (pardon me, politicke Reader, for I am not certaine vvhich should have priority; and I know in such Catholike points, a little error is deadly) so often inserted, I durst not be too bold with sacred things. For I well saw those two names joyntly considered, are now growne of such estimation, as all Nations and Kings bend their knees, and doffe their Bonnets at the naming of them; more superstitiously for destroying, then reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently at the Name of Iesus for saving. Therefore I could not resolve, vvhether it were treason or sacriledge, or I wot not what greater sinne, to touch sacred things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanely with common and vnwasht hands; especially when I saw all such as had done the like, or lesse then thus, made miserable examples of disobedience, as if they had offended <hi>Adam</hi> himselfe, or a house miraculously raysed vp by God, or rather originally created in nature, to rule over all the vvorld in <hi>Adams</hi> stead; and that to be
<pb facs="48"/>
the sonne of a King, could not protect an offendor in this kind from punishment, yea, from being cast out of his Paradise. O (thought I) vvhen I saw this, how wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy is he, that doth thus to be counted onely the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique King: for he is a King of kings indeed, fit to be the executioner of his Holinesse divine Decrees, and to consume all vvith Lightning, vvhere the sacred fulmina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vvent before. Tremble all Princes, and looke to your Crownes; especially you perty ones in <hi>Germany,</hi> that are but fatted to be swallowed one after another, as his stomacke can digest, or your turne comes to bee served vp. You see it is safer beeing his servant, then the sonne of any Potentate besides. Therefore strive for place and preferment there, and helpe vvith all the speed yee may, to betray one another to ruine. You that are Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants or <hi>Lutherans,</hi> it is no matter for Religion; hold some the stirrop, and let others lift <hi>Spayne</hi> into the sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, to ride one another like Poste-horses by turnes. You see how honourably hee deales with that Prince, whose peaceable patents made him easie entrance; and how fauourably vvith the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> vvhom hee rides in bloud, and spur-galls on both sides, vvhilst you stand laughing on, and see not that your day is comming.</p>
   <p>Thus I thought, and thought withall to be silent, and to keepe these Papers from flying abroad, for feare of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving my owne vvings clipt. But vvhen I saw in defect of greater, God had raysed vp petty Princes to defend the Faith, and put that spirit into the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> the Count <hi>Man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>felt,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Brunswicke,</hi> vvhich hee had taken from <hi>Saxony</hi> and <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and others, it made me resume courage, beholding the immediate hand of God in this vvorke, and to thinke, surely God vvill have
<pb facs="48"/>
all the glory to himselfe, that hee employes such instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, vvhose estates, in comparison, are but drops to the <hi>Spanish</hi> Ocean: I vvill not therefore be guilty of so much cowardize, as to reserve my selfe, vvhere these men fight, and seeme prodigall of their owne lives; or at least, not of so much dishonesty, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale what God hath sent into my hands, perhaps to publish for the generall information and benefit of all Christendome. Goe out therefore, and pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in Gods Name.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>