<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL Mr IOHN HORNER ESQVIRE, and to the devout ANNA his wife, at MELLES in Somerset, mercy and peace be multiplied.</title>
           <author>Sclater, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116861_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11604</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21845</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116861</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL Mr IOHN HORNER ESQVIRE, and to the devout ANNA his wife, at MELLES in Somerset, mercy and peace be multiplied.</title>
                 <author>Sclater, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The sick sovls salve. By William Sclater. Batchelar of Diuinity and minister of the word of God at Pitmister in Somerset</title>
                 <author>Sclater, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Barnes, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Barnes, Joseph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Parker, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 36 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>IOHN HORNER</hi> ESQVIRE, and to the devout ANNA his wife, at MELLES in <hi>Somerset,</hi> mercy <hi>and peace be multiplied.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orshipfull, If to any thing<note n="a" place="margin">Isa. 50.4.</note>
      <hi>the tongue of the Learned</hi> be necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in a minister, it is to the <hi>mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>string of comfort to the weary soule.</hi> To most other parts of our fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, knowledge speculatiue in a sort sufficeth. To this and the appertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, only sensible experience. And he shall in vaine temper with a wounded spirit, that cannot subscribe himselfe <hi>a</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Apoc. 1.9.</note>
      <hi>Brother and copartner in the same tribulation.</hi> The wiles of <hi>Satan</hi> in this kind, none knowes, but by experience; nor prevents or defeats, except by<note n="c" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.4.</note>
      <hi>the same comforts, wherewith himselfe hath beene comforted of God.</hi> If I said also, experience only makes fit h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>arers, I should not erre. How God hath dealt with my poore soule, either in the wound, or cure, I had rather thankfully acknowledge to my gratious God, then foolishly publish to inexpert men. This on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I say: God is wroth, when he hardens; iust, when he breakes; gracious and rich in mercy when he binds vp the sinners
<pb facs="3"/> heart. The<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 8.15.</note>
      <hi>spirit of adoption,</hi> is ioyfull: the spirit of feare, dreadfull: but the<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 10.8.</note> spirit of slumber, most wofull. They are dead that feele nothing; in the way to life, that feele wrath; they liue indeed, that feele Gods loue in their hearts, infused, or instilled by the holy Ghost. I had rather feele wrath, then feele nothing. But Lord how should they loue thee: whom thou hast brought from securitie, to feare; from feare, to feeling &amp; experience of thy favour? But I forget the measure of an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle. You haue here what you haue felt; the intolerable mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of a wounded spirit. Balme also from Gilead, if not to cure, yet to asswage the griefe. I pray God the Father of mercies, and God of all consolation, make it soveraigne to your souls: that as you haue felt the wound, which who can beare? so you may tast<note n="f" place="margin">Phil. 4.7.</note> the peace, that passeth all vnderstanding. Lord Iesus say Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours Worships in the neerest bond. VVILLIAM SCLATER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>