<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY PRINCE CHARLES, PRINCE OF GREAT BRITAIN.</title>
           <author>Saltmarsh, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116513_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11378</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21637</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116513</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY PRINCE CHARLES, PRINCE OF GREAT BRITAIN.</title>
                 <author>Saltmarsh, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Holy discoveries and flames. By John Saltmarshe, Mr. of Arts of Magdalen Colledge in Cambridge, and rector of West-Ileslerton in York-shire</title>
                 <author>Saltmarsh, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Young (Junius), Robert</publisher>
                    <distributor>Nevill, Philip</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 225, 1 page, illustrations (metal cuts), 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY PRINCE CHARLES, PRINCE OF GREAT BRITAIN.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most excellent Sir,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Rawing my breath every day more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily by the favour I received from Your Royall Father, if my Pen should forget You, it had more Inke then either allegiance, or loyalty, or duty: The <hi>Eyes</hi> that I here present
<pb facs="3"/>
Your. Highnesse, I confesse durst not looke his Majestie in the Face; He hath so much of <hi>Caesar</hi> about Him as strikes me into a <hi>non pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum ferre fulmen:</hi> but Your Selfe, being yet a divine spark and ray from Him, and not ascended Your Meridian of Soveraigntie, is not become so awfull, nor so inaccessible. We may see that Sun in his Rising, whose Beames may at his Noone chide our weake eyes for the attempt: This Sir I speake of You, who is but now in Your East, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Your Noone-point be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore You, and may You drive
<pb facs="3"/>
on happily to Your glory both in Your Heaven and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome below, and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven above.</p>
   <p>And be pleased, Gratious Sir, to let these <hi>Eyes</hi> here light but a beame of Yours to the holy Scripture, and to ayre but Your Bosome at these <hi>Flames,</hi> and to suffer these Leafes, thus seeded with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine thoughts, to be a robe of holy Ermins to Your Soule: I lay my selfe and papers at Your Royall feet, and am</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>A Beadesman for Your Highnesse
J. Saltmarshe.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>