<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL THE Maister, Wardens, and the Assistants of the worthy and fa∣mous Company of Gouldsmithes, of this Honourable Ci∣tie of London.</title>
           <author>Carter, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116227_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18056</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4698</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116227</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL THE Maister, Wardens, and the Assistants of the worthy and fa∣mous Company of Gouldsmithes, of this Honourable Ci∣tie of London.</title>
                 <author>Carter, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Carters Christian common vvealth; or, Domesticall dutyes deciphered</title>
                 <author>Carter, Thomas, of London</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 275, 11 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL THE Maister, Wardens, and the Assistants of the worthy and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Company of <hi>Gouldsmithes,</hi> of this Honourable Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>London.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Worshipfull Sirs,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ngratitude, was a sin even vnto the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens so odious, that <hi>Periander</hi> among the <hi>Corinthians</hi> made this law, that if any in a Common weale prove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> vnthankefull hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued a benefit, he was to bee put to death, and as the reliques of
<pb facs="3"/> Gods Image in them: soe nature in the sensible creatures hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted thankefulnesse, to passe by those presidents produced by Historians, which may seeme in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible; the Naturalists obserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Merlyon not to prey on the Larke which hath giuen warmth to her cold feet, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable: And the spirit of God in Scripture hath plentifully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned it. That I may proue my selfe therefore instructed in this duty, not by nature onely, but by grace, in this glorious light of the Gospell; I present vnto your view and patronage, these poore indeavours, the fruit of a thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heart, expect you cannot a
<pb facs="3"/> loftie stile or curious phrase, for I take not vppon mee to instruct, but onely to remember: your curteous acceptation I doubt not of, from the former experience of your worthinesse. Surely if the poore <hi>Persians</hi> water in a potsheard was exceptable to the Emperour; and an Apple from a poore Pessant was received by <hi>Artaxerzes</hi> a great Prince; if <hi>Alexander</hi> tooke curteously wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from a common Souldiers hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met; and our Sauiour crowned the poore widdow with everlasting prayse for two Mites to the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sury: your generous dispositions will sparingly censure and curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously accept these my poore la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours;
<pb facs="4"/> which howsoeuer, they bee your worships, and so is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in all humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to continue, THOMAS CARTER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>