<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER in God, and my very good Lord, THOMAS Lord Bishop of LON∣DON, I. H. wisheth all grace and happinesse.</title>
           <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116595_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02571</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12699</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116595</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER in God, and my very good Lord, THOMAS Lord Bishop of LON∣DON, I. H. wisheth all grace and happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Pharisaisme and Christianity : compared and set forth in a sermon at Pauls Crosse, May 1. 1608. By I.H. Vpon Matth. 5.20</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bradwood, Melchisidec</publisher>
                    <distributor>Macham, Samuel 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 87, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER in God, and my very good Lord, THOMAS Lord Bishop of LON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DON, <hi>I. H.</hi> wisheth all grace and happinesse.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <hi>RIGHT REVEREND</hi> and <hi>HONORABLE,</hi>
      </salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know there is store of Sermons extant; The pulpit scarce affordeth more than the Presse. I adde
<pb facs="3"/>
to the number, and complaine not: In all good things abundance is an easie burden. If the soule may feed it selfe with varietie, both by the eare, and by the eie, it hath no reason to finde fault with choice. But if any weaker stomack (as in our bodily Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles) shall feare to surfet at the sight of too much, it is easie for that man to looke off, and to confine his eies to some few: who cannot much sooner abate to himselfe, than multiplie to another? Let not his nice sullennesse preiudice that delight and profit which may arise to others from this number. For mee, I dare not bee so enuious, as not to blesse God for this plentie, and seriously to reioice that Gods people may thus liberally feast
<pb facs="3"/>
themselues by both their senses: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther know I for whether more; The sound of the word spoken pierceth more, the letter written endureth longer; the eare is taught more sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, more stirringly: the eie with leasure and continuance. According to my poore ability I haue desired to doe good both waies, not so much fearing censures, as caring to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difie. This little labour submisse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie offers it selfe to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, as iustlie yours: being both Preached at your call, and (as it were) in your charge, and by one vnder the charge of your fatherly iurisdiction, who vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedlie desires by all meanes to shew his true heart to Gods Church,
<pb facs="4"/>
together with his humble thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse to your Lordship; and professeth still to continue</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships in all humble duty and obseruance <hi>IOS. HALL.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>