<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The preface or the proheme.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1547</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116196_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16471</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3380</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116196</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The preface or the proheme.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A compendyous regyment or a dyetary of healthe : made in Mountpyllyer, by Andrewe Boorde of physycke doctour, newly corrected and imprynted with dyuers addycyons dedycated to the armypotent Prynce and valyent Lorde Thomas Duke of Northfolke</title>
                 <author>Boorde, Andrew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1547</date>
                 <publisher>Powell, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Powell, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>84 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ The preface or the proheme.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>☞ To the armypotent Prynce and valyent lorde Thomas Duke of Northfolke Andrewe Boorde of physycke doctor r dothe surrender humyle commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon with immortall thankes.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the tyme that I had tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelled for to haue the notycyon &amp; practes of Physycke in diuers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyons and countres &amp; returned in to Englande and requyred to sary and to remayne and to cōtynue with syr Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Drewry knyght, for many vrgēt causes. Your grace heryng of me dyd sende syr John̄ Baruyngham nowe beynge knyght to me to come to youre grace to haue my counsell in physycke for your infyrmytes. The mesage done, I with festynacyon &amp; dylygēce dyd nat prolonge the tyme but dyd come to your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te accordynge to my deuts. The whiche was in the tyme, whan lorde Thomas Cardynall Archebysshop of Yorke was cōmaūded to go to his see of Yorke. And after my cōmynge to you and felynge the pulses of your herte: the pulses of your brayne, and the pulses of your lyuer, and that I had lene your vryne &amp; your egestyon I durste nat to enterpryse or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyll with out the counsell of Mayster doctor
<pb facs="2"/>
Buttes, the which dyd know nat onely your cōplexcion &amp; infyrmite but also he dyd know the vsage of your dyete. And the imbe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yllyte and strength of your body, with other qualy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes exuedyent &amp; necessary to be knowen, but brefely to conclude your recuperatyng or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couering your health. And for synguler trust and hygh fauour the which the kyng had to you was compocated to be in the presence of his magesty, I than dyd passe ouer the sees agayne and dyd go to all the vnyuersytes and great Scloles the whiche be approbated with in the precynet of Thrystendome for to haue the practes of physycke, I seynge many expedyent thynges in dyuers regyons at the last I dyd staye my selfe at Mountpllyoure which is the hed vniuersite in al Europe for the practes of physycke &amp; surgery or thyrmig I beinge there. And hauyng a cotydyal remē<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brance vpon youre bountyfull goodnes, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d consulte with many egregyous Doctours of physycke what maner that I m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ghte wryte the whiche myght be acceptable for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruacyon of the health of youre body. The sayde doctors knowynge my zele and true in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tencyon had to you, dyd aduertyse me to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke a boke of dyete nat only for your grace but also for your noble posteryte and for all men lyuynge wherfore I do nomyaate thys boke The Dyetary of health, the which doth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract howe a man shuld order him selfe in all
<pb facs="3"/>
maner of causes partenynge to the health of his body, yf your grace or any man wyl haue forther knowledge for dyuers infyrmites let him loke in a boke of my makynge named y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Breuyary of health. And where I haue dedy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cated this boke to your grace. And haue nat ornated hit with cloquence &amp; retorycke ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, the whiche in all maner of bokes and wryttynges is vsed these modernall dayes. I do submytte me to your bountefull goodnes. And also dyuers tymes in my wrytynges I do wryte wordes of myrth, truely it is for no other intēcion, but to make your grace mery for myrth is one of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> chefest thynges of phy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sycke the which doth aduertise euery man to be mery, and to bewere of pentyfulnes, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stynge to youre affluent goodnes to take no displeasure with any of the cōtentes of this boke, but to accept my good wyll &amp; dylygent labour. And forthermore I do truste to your super abundaunt gracyousnes, that you wyll consyder the loue and zele, the which I haue to your prosperyte, and that I do it for a com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon weale, the which I beseche Jesu chryst longe to continue to his wyll and pleasure in this lyfe. And after this transytory lyfe to remunerate you with celestyall ioye and eter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nal glorye</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From Mountpyller. <date>The fyft daye of Maye. The yere of our Lorde Jesu Chryste. <hi>M. CCCCC. XLVII.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>