<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>L. D. vnto the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1562</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116098_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20450</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6850</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116098</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>L. D. vnto the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A boke named Tectonicon : briefely shewynge the exacte measurynge, and speady reckenynge all maner lande, squared tymber, stone, steaples, pyllers, globes [et] c. Further, declaringe the perfecte makinge and large vse of the carpenters ruler, conteyninge a quadrant geometricall: comprehendinge also the rare vse of the squire. And in thende a lyttle treatise adioyned, openinge the composicion and appliancie of an instrument called the profitable staffe. With other thinges pleasaunt and necessary, most conducible for surueyers, landemeaters, ioyners, carpenters, and masons. Published by Leonarde Digges gentleman, in the yere of our Lorde. 1556</title>
                 <author>Digges, Leonard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1562</date>
                 <publisher>Geminus (Gemini), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harrison, Luke (Lucas)</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>44 pages, 2 folded tables, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>L. D. vnto the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthoughe (gentle Reader) many excellente in
Geometry, vppon infallible groundes haue put
forth diuerse most certayne and sufficient rules,
touchyng the measuring of al maner Superfici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecis:
yet in that the arte of numbring hath ben required (yea,
chiefely those rules hyd, and as it were locked vp in straunge
toungues) they do profite, or haue furdered verye lyttle the
moste parte: certes nothing at al, the Landemeater, Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
or Mason, wantyng the aforesayde: for theyr sakes I am
here prouoked not to hide, but to open, and so encrease the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
which I haue receyued: yea, to publishe in this our tongue
very shortly (if God geue life) a volume conteynynge the flow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers
of the Sciences Mathematical, largely applyed to our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde
practise, most profitably pleasaunte to all maner men
of this realme. In the meane time I shall desire the Artificers
aboue named to be contented with this lyttle booke (a taste of
my good wyll towardes them) which I wyshe euen so to farder
the readers, as I knowe it suffycient for the true measurynge
and readye accompte of all maner Lande, Timber, Stoone,
Borde, Glasse, Pauemeut. &amp;c.</p>
   <p>Here mine aduise shall be to those Artificers that will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite
in this, or any of my bokes, nowe publyshed, or that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after
shall be, first confusely to reade them thorow, then with
more iudgement, and at the third reading wittely to practise.
So fewe thinges shalbe vnknowen. Note, oft diligent reding,
ioyned with ingenious practise, causeth profitable laboure.</p>
   <q>Thus most hartely farewell (louinge Reader) to whom I wishe my
selfe present to further thy desire and practise in these.</q>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>