<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The Authour to the Pretended Catho∣liques.</title>
           <author>Pestell, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116034_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03333</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13453</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116034</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The Authour to the Pretended Catho∣liques.</title>
                 <author>Pestell, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe consideration of mans iniquitie, and Gods iustice : wherein the distinction of 1. sinnes into veniall, mortall, 2. sinnes and punishments into æquall, vnæquall is scholastically examined</title>
                 <author>Higgons, Theophilus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bradock, Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 32, 6 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ The Authour to the <hi>Pretended Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>CHVRCH</hi> (in the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall significati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the word) is a Body vnited togither, in all the partes ioyned with the Head by a mysticall vnion. And the <hi>Old Enemie</hi> hath diuerslie assaulted both Head and Bodie, with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable malice, but limited po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer.</p>
   <p>Yet still hee attempteth some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and as he is a spirituall E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, so are his weapons spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall.</p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>Sometimes he prouoketh vs to sinne in <hi>Morall</hi> things, as in sins of <hi>action, Contra bonum.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Sometimes in things <hi>Intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,</hi> as in sins of <hi>Opinion Contra ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The latter is of two sorts: either <hi>haereticall</hi> against the Head: Or <hi>schismaticall</hi> against the Body.</p>
   <p>The Heresies against the Head, are eyther against his Natures or Persons, or Offices.</p>
   <p>The two former were olde he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resies, and long since condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
   <p>The latter, are diuers heresies sprung vp as tares amongst good wheat in succeding ages.</p>
   <p>Such are diuers of your opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; namely against the Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of Christ consisting in <hi>Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> and <hi>Intercession.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The former you haue sundry waies violated, and not a little by
<pb facs="3"/> your misapplyed distinction of <hi>Veniall</hi> and <hi>Mortall</hi> sinnes: which I haue a little rectified in this briefe Declaration, and also re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued that imputation of the <hi>Aequality</hi> of sinne and punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which you say, must necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily ensue, if your conceipt should vanish.</p>
   <p>If you make no answere hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, you either want Charitie to free me from errour, or ability to discharge your selues from suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof. And if you make any aunswer, let your lynes be more full of substance to satisfie the point, then of malice to disgrace the Author: who entirely wishing your saluation in Christs Iustice, commendeth you to Gods mercy in him.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Fare ye well,</salute>
      <dateline>
         <date>14. Octo. 1607.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>