<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVOR∣SHIPFVLL Sir THOMAS SMITH Knight, Gouernour of the East Indian Companie. &amp;c.</title>
           <author>P., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116796_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11585</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21828</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116796</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVOR∣SHIPFVLL Sir THOMAS SMITH Knight, Gouernour of the East Indian Companie. &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>P., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The relation of a wonderfull voiage made by VVilliam Cornelison Schouten of Horne : Shewing how south from the Straights of Magelan, in Terra Del-fuogo: he found and discouered a newe passage through the great South Sea, and that way sayled round about the world. Describing what islands, countries, people, and strange aduentures he found in his saide passage</title>
                 <author>Schouten, Willem Corneliszoon</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newbery, Nathaniel</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 36, 36-82, 1 page, map (woodcut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL Sir <hi>THOMAS SMITH</hi> Knight, Gouernour of the <hi>East Indian Companie. &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Treatise of the Description of a Voyage, made by <hi>VVilliam Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelison Schouten</hi> of <hi>Horne,</hi> by a newe vnexpected and neuer heretofore discouered Passage, by him found out in <hi>Terra del-Fuogo</hi> Southward, from the Straights of <hi>Magelan,</hi> into the great South sea, and that way into the <hi>East Indies,</hi> and so round about the World: comming to my hands I iudged no man more fitte (for the protection there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) then your Worship, not onely because of the great desire you haue, and paines you dayly take to aduance such trauels: but also in regard of your place of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of the <hi>East Indian Company,</hi> whom this Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age specially concerneth. If it please you to accept it, I shall thinke my paines well bestow'd in the translati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof out of the Dutch, wherein it was written: wishing it a meanes to further and aduance your trade in <hi>India:</hi> and to your Worship health in this worlde, and eternall felicitie in the world to come.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships to command, <hi>W. P.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>