<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ Vnto the most gracious / and in all good∣nesse most excellent vertuous Lady Quene Katheryne / wyfe and most derely belo∣uyd spouse vnto the moste myghty sapient Christen prynce / Kynge Henry the .viii. Richard Io∣nas wyssheth perpetuall ioye and felicyte.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1540</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116014_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10887</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21153</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116014</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ Vnto the most gracious / and in all good∣nesse most excellent vertuous Lady Quene Katheryne / wyfe and most derely belo∣uyd spouse vnto the moste myghty sapient Christen prynce / Kynge Henry the .viii. Richard Io∣nas wyssheth perpetuall ioye and felicyte.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The byrth of mankynde, newly translated out of Laten into Englysshe : In the which is entreated of all suche thynges the which chaunce to women in theyr labor, and all suche infyrmitees whiche happen vnto the infantes after they be delyuered. And also at the latter ende o in the thyrde or last boke is entreated of the conception of mankynde, and howe manye wayes it may be letted or furtheryd, with diuers other fruytefull thynges, as doth appere in the table before the booke</title>
                 <author>Roeslin, Eucharius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Raynald, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1540</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>1, vi-lxxxviii leaves, 2 leaves of plates, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb n="vi" facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ Vnto the most gracious / and in all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse most excellent vertuous Lady Quene Katheryne / wyfe and most derely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd spouse vnto the moste myghty sapient Christen prynce / Kynge Henry the .viii. Richard Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas wyssheth perpetuall ioye and felicyte.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here as of late (moste excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vertuous Quene) many goodly and proper treatyse / as well concernynge holye scripture / wherein is contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the onely comforte and consolaciō of all godlye people: as other prophane artes and sciences ryght necessary to be knowen &amp; had in vse / haue ben by the paynefull dyligence of suche clarkes which haue embusyed them in the same very earnestlye and circumspect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye set forth in this oure wulgare Englysshe tunge / to the greate enrytchynge of our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther langage / and also the greate vtilite and profet of all people vsynge the same / and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge all other thynges / oute of the noble scyence of Phisyke haue ben dyuers / proper / 
<pb facs="3"/>and profitable matters compyled and trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated from the Laten tunge in to Englyshe / by the readynge of the whiche ryght manye haue confessed them selfes to haue receaued greate lyght and knowlege of such thynges in the which they haue founde no smal com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forte and profet. And in this behalfe there is in the Laten speche a boke entytled / depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu hominis: that is to saye / of the byrthe of mankynde / compyled by a famous doctor in Physycke / called Eucharius / the whiche he wrote in his owne mother tunge / that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge a Germayn / in the Germayne speche / afterwarde by an other honest clarke / at the requeste and desyre of his frende transposed in to Laten: the whiche boke for the syngu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar vtilite and profete that ensueth vnto all such as rede it / and moste spetiallye vnto all women (for whose onely cause it was wryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) hathe bene sythe in the Doutche and Frenche speche set forthe and emprynted in greate nomber / so that there be fewe matro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and women in that partes / but (yf they can rede) wyll haue this booke alwayes in readynesse: consyderynge then that the same commodite and profet whiche they in theyr
<pb n="vii" facs="3"/>regyons do obtayne by enioyng of this lytle boke in theyr maternall langage / myght al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so ensue vnto all womē in this noble realme of England / if it be set forth in the Englyshe speche / as concernynge this / I haue done my symple endeuoure for the loue of all wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manhode / and chieflye for the moste bounde seruyce / the whiche I owe vnto youre moste gracyous hyghnes to translate the same in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to oure tunge. Moste humbly desyryng fyrst your graces hyghnes / and then consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye all noble ladyes and gentylwomen with other honeste matrones to accepte my pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and good wyll employd in the same: the whiche thynge as I doo not doubte for the woonte and incomperable benignite / good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / and gentylnes inset &amp; planted in youre graces nature / so shall it be no lyttell encour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ragynge vnto me hereafter with farther de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation and paynes to reuyse and ouerse the same agayne / and with much more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence / to set it forthe. For consyderynge the manyfolde / daylye / and imminente daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>georus and parelles / the which all maner of women of what estate or degre so euer they be in theyr labor do sustayne and abyde: yea
<pb facs="4"/>many tymes with parell of theyr lyfe / of the whiche there be to many examples nedelesse here to be rehersed. I thought it shulde be a very charytable and laudable dede: yea and thankefullye to be accepted of all honorable &amp; other honest matrons / yf this lyttell trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyse so frutefull and profytable for the same purpose were made Englysh / so that by that meanes it myght be redde and vnderstande of them all / for as touchynge mydwyfes / as there be many of them ryght expert / diligēt / wyse / circumspecte / and tender aboute suche busynesse: so be there agayne manye mo full vndyscreate / vnreasonable / chorleshe / &amp; farre to seke in suche thynges / the whiche sholde chieflye helpe and socoure the good women in theyr most paynefull labor and thronges. Throughe whose rudenesse and rasshenesse onely I doubte not / but that a greate nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber are caste awaye and destroyed (the more petye.) For this cause and for the honor of almyghty god / and for the moste bounde ser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyce / the which I owe vnto your grace / most gracyous and vertuous Quene / I haue iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged my labor &amp; paynes in this behalfe ryght well bestowed / requyrynge all other women
<pb n="viii" facs="4"/>of what estate so euer they be / whiche shall by readynge of the same fynde lyght and cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte to yelde and render thankes vnto your moste gracyous hyghnes / wysshyng greate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that it myght please all honeste &amp; mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye mydwyfes dylygently to reade and ouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>se the same / of the which althoughe there be many / which do knowe muche more perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture / then is here expressed / yet am I sure in the readynge of it / theyr vnderstandynge shall be muche cleared and haue some what farther perceueraunce in the same. It is no small charge the which they take vpō them / for yf when anye straunge or peryllous case doth chanse / the mydwyfe be ignorant / or to seke in suche thynges which are to be had in remembraunce in that case / then is the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie loste and vtterlye doth perysshe / for lacke of due knowledge requysite to be had in the mydwyfe. Wherfore I beseche almyghtye God / that this my symple industrye and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor maye be throughe youre grace vnto the vtilite / wealth / and profet / of all Englysshe women / accordynge to my vtter and hartye desyre and entente / to whome also I daylye praye longe to preserue and prospere youre
<pb facs="5"/>moste gracyous hyghnes bothe to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynuall comforte &amp; consolacion of our moste redoubted &amp; withoute cōparyson moste excellent Christen Prynce / and also the ioye and gladnesse of all his louynge subiectes.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>