<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           <author>S., A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116919_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21185</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7538</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116919</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 <author>S., A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ordinary lecture. Preached at the Blacke-Friers, by M. Egerton. And taken as it was vttered by characterie. Macte: officium, officii, fructus</title>
                 <author>Egerton, Stephen</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Dalderne, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath bin (chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader) till of late, much wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, that there were an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie way of swift writing, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, Sermons and Lectures of godly Preachers might bee preserued for the vse of the absent and posteritie hereafter. That whereas no more remaineth after the hower passed, then so much as the frailtie of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie carieth away. By the benefit of speedie writing the whole bodie of the Lecture and Sermon might be regestred. This desire of manie, hath lately bene satisfied, by an Art called Characterie, which I hauing
<pb facs="3"/>learned, haue put in practise, in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting sermons therby to preserue (as it were) the life of much memorable doctrine, that would otherwise bee buried in forgetfulnes: whereof I here giue thee a fruit, (christian rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) in publishing this godly sermō so takē. I haue not missed one word; wherby, either the truth of doctrine might be peruerted, or the meaning of the Preacher altered. Such is the vse of the art, which I haue learned. And as at this day God is plentifull in varietie of gifts, so if some occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had not hindred, I would haue made thee partaker, (and may here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after) of other godly mens labours in this kind, that, although one can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not heare al: yet by Charactery and my indeuour, the diuers giftes of God may by this meanes bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to many. Farewell in the Lord.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy well willer A. S.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>