<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right worshypfull Sir Francis Drake Knight: Roger Cotton, wisheth con∣tinuance of health, with prosperous estate and felicitie.</title>
           <author>C., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116424_Bo1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19443</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5869</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116424</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right worshypfull Sir Francis Drake Knight: Roger Cotton, wisheth con∣tinuance of health, with prosperous estate and felicitie.</title>
                 <author>C., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A spirituall song : conteining an historicall discourse from the infancie of the world, vntill this present time: setting downe the treacherous practises of the wicked, against the children of God: describing also the markes and ouerthrow of antichrist, with a thankesgiuing to God for the preseruation of her Maiestie, and of his Church. Drawen out of the holy Scriptures, by Roger Cotton</title>
                 <author>Cotton, Roger</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 <publisher>Simson, Gabriel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 18 pages, plates, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right worshypfull Sir Francis Drake Knight: <hi>Roger Cotton,</hi> wisheth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of health, with prosperous estate and felicitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He happie estate of the present, with the constant hope of fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prosperitie (Right worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) by the glorious conquest of the heauenly armie of holy ones, and the vertuous zeale that you haue, alwayes had to defende Gods trueth, her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties right, and Countries tranquilitie, hath imbolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned mee (being a poore brother of the Worshypfull societie of Drapers, whereinto you were lately incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated) to present vnto you an Historicall discourse and short thankes giuing, which I haue rudely, but truly, and according to the storie, collected out of the holy Scriptures, declaring therein the extreame ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kour of the wicked agaynst the godly, throughout all ages, with the iust iudgementes of God, duely rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their impieties; and also a description of the marks of that Tirannicall Sea of Antichrist, the sworne ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to the gracious Gospell of eternall saluation, heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hoping to encourage all such as would auoyde the heauie burthē of that Egyptiecal yoke, the captiuitie of
<pb facs="3"/>
that misticall Babell, and the persecution of Gog and Magog, to study the holy worde of God, which is the sworde of the spirite; and to take vnto them the whole armor thereof, whereby they may be able to resist all the assaultes of the euyll one, with all his souldiers, and may also haue a full hope in the Lord, that in the ende they shall haue a victorious conquest, as now we haue, and so learne with Martyrs, Apostles, and holy Prophets, to reioyce and sing <hi>Hosanna</hi> and <hi>Haleluiah</hi> for the wound of that seauen headed Oragon, and dyly to pray for the ouerthrow of his whole rage: so shall their naked sores be couered &amp; healed with the leaues of that florishyng Tree of euerlasting lyfe, which gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth by the Christall streames of that pure Riuer, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning through the Citie of God, the celestial Ierusalem. This if your Worshyp shal accept, being the first frutes of my small paynes, not regarding the barbarousnes of my phrase &amp; verse, being no Scholler, but the zealous affection of my hart, to the loue of your godly care, for the vpholding of Gods Religion. I shall (hauing so skilfull a Pilote to stirre my sterne, and so worthy a Captaine to encounter the enimie) be imbouldned hereafter to wade into deeper discourses (as God shall blesse, and time permit) to gratifie your worthinesse withall: Vntill which time, I humbly commende your selfe, and your most vertuous proceedinges, to the gracious gouernment of the puissant Iehouah, the victorious King of eternall glorie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your worships to command, <hi>R. C.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>