<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Printer to the Reader. Gentle Reader many faults escaped the Author being ab∣sent, and the coppie somewhat darke, which if it please thee to correct take this direction. The former number sheweth the page: the latter the line. m. the margen. d. dele. certaine figures are twice printed and so both in the table and here twice quoted.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116041_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10958</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21228</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116041</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Printer to the Reader. Gentle Reader many faults escaped the Author being ab∣sent, and the coppie somewhat darke, which if it please thee to correct take this direction. The former number sheweth the page: the latter the line. m. the margen. d. dele. certaine figures are twice printed and so both in the table and here twice quoted.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The faith, doctrine, and religion, professed, &amp; protected in the realme of England, and dominions of the same : expressed in 39 articles, concordablie agreed vpon by the reuerend bishops, and clergie of this kingdome, at two seuerall meetings, or conuocations of theirs, i the yeares of our Lord, 1562, and 1604: the said articles analised into propositions, and the propositions prooued to be agreeable both to the written word of God, and to the extant confessions of all the neighbour churches, Christianlie reformed: the aduersaries also of note, and name, which from the apostles daies, and primitiue Church hetherto, haue crossed, or contradicted the said articles in generall, or any particle, or proposition arising from anie of them in particular, heereby are discouered, laid open, and so confuted. Perused, and by the lawfull authoritie of the Church of England, allowed to be publique</title>
                 <author>Rogers, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>36, 56, 53-196, 187-122, that is 222, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="141"/>
   <head>The Printer to the Reader. Gentle Reader many faults escaped the Author being ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, and the coppie somewhat darke, which if it please thee to correct take this direction. The former number sheweth the page: the latter the line. m. the margen. d. dele. certaine figures are twice printed and so both in the table and here twice quoted.</head>
   <p>Pag. 2. lin. 30. who flatly. 3.5. the inhabitants. 8. liniaments. 23. horae b. 4.36. Saturninus, Menander, Cerin. 6.28. Eunome us 29. Tretheites. 7.2. These did. 6. Seruetus. 19. Priscilianists. 9.4. d. the. 10.32. Harmon. 11.20. Valētiniās <seg rend="sup">p</seg>, 16.11, As man; and. 20.4. d were. 13. Him God. 22.8. tures teach. 23.9. assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. 29.14. precepts, offendeth no lesse then if he contemned Gods ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse commandements <seg rend="sup">k</seg>. And. 22. adversaries. 30.24. Castellio. 31.6. Barco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas &amp; Barcolf. 24. all the. 34.16. Bethlehem 35.16. the redde sea. 37.12. sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices. 39.10. Antinomies. 6. d. 0.40.11. d. in. 17. for his. 46.1. m. Carranza 47.15. may doe. 48.22. naturall. 49.22. d and the mind. 23. the body. 29. reveale. 52.10. or Loues. 53.1. m. Horae. 8. scandere. 9. for thee. 54.17. the profit. 55.3. as the. 8. Villauincentio. 22. destitute. 53.33. &amp; violating. 35. them, by the papists. 58.19 they doe. 61.7. as not. 65.10. and fall. 66.20. Hieracites 67.15. d. by. 68.25. yee. 33. vp. 35. Onesimus. 69.5. d. as. 14. d. most. 71.12. d. his. 72.24. Hieracites. 73.24. whom hee. 74.24. Catabaptists. 25. misery. 32. Bolseck. 77.36. Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. m. execut. of iust. 79.7. Hieracites. 80 5. can away. 81.12. or which are. 84.3. be held. 4. The obs. 85.5. they revolted. 19. Desider. Burdegal. 9217. Vigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erius. m. Theol. 95.18. because 96.21. d. a 97.30. Pius 5.100.31. they. 103.11. embrace. 104.6 interpretation. 14. Villauincence. 21 examinent, vt. 27. fetcht. m. Hervaeus. 106 m. next. im. 13. Festivalls 16. in the 107.29. the odde. 108.3. Cusan. 16. Heare. 18 d. the 22. d. the. 110.34. disciplin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> 111.5. Iobelaea of the Sci. 35. Cyrillus. 112.8. to summon. 23. Turon. 114.24 Selneccerus. 115.17. Paphnutius. 27. d. <seg rend="sup">h</seg>. 31. erre. <seg rend="sup">a</seg> m. <seg rend="sup">•</seg> Test. 117.19. Epicurus 126. m. 35. vix. 130.17. we may 131.25.<seg rend="sup">3</seg> or 26.<seg rend="sup">•</seg> before. ibid. be <seg rend="sup">6</seg> chosen. 27. work.<seg rend="sup">5</seg> 132.21. d. the. 136.26. but that. 41. m. Towres. 141.30. But there. 144.12. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians from the. 31. in any. 145.9. Saravia. 11. appertaine. 147.12. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment); 149.8. Eutychites. 14. Sacraments. 30. d. of. 154.10. d. be. 12. Exorcists 29. the Cardinall. 155.19. Acolyte. 20. not alwaies in his Church. 30. as a. 158.31. great. 159.4. Alva. 8. abused by. 15. guise is. 162.7. are but 20. Hēriciās 166.13. Not Manicheans. 167.8. d. they. 26. Iouinians. 169.21. a sect a. 29. d. the 34. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> se sub ii.38. nowe. 172.8. the Lords supper is a sacrament. 173. m. 5. communion 19. sacrilegious. 21. Antwerp. an. 17428. whole christ is. 176. m. 14. vt substan. 23. nil est. 177.3. &amp; therefore. 17. at. Masse. or borne about to the sicke, he shall kneele downe deuoutly &amp; say his pater noster or 178.3. in the. 12. signe 179.14. doctrine. 180.6. hath so 20. the Artotarites 23. Eucratites. 183.8. d. and no woman 9. and came 185.4. religion 187.9. vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continent
<pb facs="142"/>
life 188.30. alliteration 189.3. which error. 4. Ochinites 191.21. ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mine when they haue annoyed. 195. m. 23. Sab. do. 196.9. d. by. 197.17. Rhene, Frankeland, and S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uland▪ 36. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>▪ doest it. 191.24. the well. 192.3. d. both. 194.24. vt plurimis. 25. Smeton. 199.22. consecration. 26. d. l. 202.16. of the. 204.15. d. there. 208.16. Monet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rius. 211.13. Hugh. Capet. 215.4. &amp; goods.</p>
   <pb facs="142"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>