<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>CHristian Reader, the many literall and punctuall faults, toge∣ther with those that violate Rules of Orthographie, impute ra∣ther to others hast or ill speed, then to my ignorance or incircumspe∣ction. Mistakes peruerting sense, or making the Author absurd, bee pleased to correct with thy pen, before thou reade.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116803_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11588</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21830</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116803</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>CHristian Reader, the many literall and punctuall faults, toge∣ther with those that violate Rules of Orthographie, impute ra∣ther to others hast or ill speed, then to my ignorance or incircumspe∣ction. Mistakes peruerting sense, or making the Author absurd, bee pleased to correct with thy pen, before thou reade.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe exposition vvith notes, vpon the second epistle to the Thessalonians. By VVilliam Sclater Doctor of Diuinitie, and minister of Pitmister in Summerset</title>
                 <author>Sclater, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Vincent, George 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 307, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="158"/>
   <head>CHristian Reader, the many literall and punctuall faults, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with those that violate Rules of Orthographie, impute ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to others hast or ill speed, then to my ignorance or incircumspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Mistakes peruerting sense, or making the Author absurd, bee pleased to correct with thy pen, before thou reade.</head>
   <p>PAge 2. l 32. for ought, aught, <hi>&amp; sic deincept,</hi> p. 5 l. 31. perfits. p. 8. l. 6. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> p. 11. l. 2. styles, <hi>&amp; sic deinceps.</hi> l. 15. for be, is. l. 20. is. p. 13. louely. p. 16. l. 32. worke it. p. 22. l. 17. merum. p 29. l. 17 inflicted l. 29. Hellish p. 39. l. 6. for hotnesse, what<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es. <hi>Item.</hi> 45.8.50.21. preterition of. 63.13.15. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> 68.1. for relation, resolution. 72.33. simpliciter. 75.25. elicit. 81.7. by our gathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing. 82.37. <hi>dele</hi> l. 84.27. for indeed, iudged. 86.5. for greater, generall. 19. they were. <hi>Ibidem</hi> for losse loose. 88.22. restlesnes. 27. seene rising. 89.22. for imitate, intimate. 91.4. certertie. 90.26. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> 93.16. apparitions. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>5.6. for comming, cunning. 9. for in, is. 11. for yet, yee. 97.7. swelling words then follow of vniuersality. 12. for act, art. 98.33. for aptly, apertly, <hi>&amp; sic sape deincept.</hi> 102.26. to denote. 104.29. full keeping. 38. decretally. 105.10. know how. 26. for passage, presage. 109.16. contiguous. 17 homonumie. 110.27. denoting. 34. <hi>quot verba.</hi> 111.32. Baalisme. 112.3. some few daies. 113.25. for handship, headship. 114<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Ile confesse. 6. for Asher, Anshe. 115.8. <hi>dele</hi> is. 26. <hi>portenta.</hi> 116.25. but passiuely. 31. <hi>dele,</hi> proper element. 117.16. despousata. 119.1. for expect, expiate. 17. ascending. 18. <hi>dele,</hi> and. 121.35 for fame, iure. 36. for aduice, aduance. 37. <hi>si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> ergo.</hi> 123.12. second. 124.24. for all. ad. 28. for oh, vah. 125.25. venditabit. 127.1. for need, read. 129.9. wordy. 131.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> 133.9 for aptly, apertly. 23. for best, left. for cauell, nouell. 134.32. for new, now Antiquity. 135 19. <hi>homo</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> 137.38. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> 139.27. Epither. 142.8. for bid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, bindes. 146.28. Lutheran. 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>.36. for as, is. 149 38. in genere. 151.3. differred. 37. for qualitas, genetiuus. 152.6. for vsing, poysoning. 14. obeliske. 153.12. for. doctrine, decree. 156.3. for as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, assert. 159.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>imous. <hi>&amp; sic deinceps.</hi> 160.28. for instructions, iniunctions. 161.31. for is, as. 166.8. for of, and lies. 167.8. for hope, ope. 171.8. papisme. 27. <hi>dele,</hi> he. 173.38. for pats. thats. 178.4. for Apostles, Apostates. 36. for new, wearie. 180.14. In the choice. 183.11. dispose. 30. hath secreted. 186.11. eramus. 190.7. for confuting, comforting. 192.21. velleitas. 195.26. infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diat. 201.30. deliuered. 206.6. more, none. 209.2. befall. 4. for securely, securitie. 210.19. di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiuely, 211.20. for adoration, obduration. 214.5. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> 13. of these. 214.27. for saith, such. 28. for this, thus. 215.8. <hi>dele,</hi> to. 32. for bee, and bene. 36. crownes. or. 222.28. nice. 32. for rent, rout. 223.29. vaguing. 224.4. if it. 226.10. legales. 13. dispeream. 228.13. faithlesse. 15. for bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sednes, blindenes. 230.5. Argument. 231.31. Gods called. 233.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>4. eminenter. 37. for whence, where. 235.16. for if, that. 236.3. dolosus 21. by God. 237.1. intuit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>cepti. 21. for To, Lo 238.20. nemore. 239.7. quaecunque. 13. for must, most. 14. for crost, most. 21. fatting from. 17. iustum. 34. for rectum, reatum. 240.24. for moder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ely, mediatly. 241.14, &amp; 25. Magistrate. <hi>&amp; sic dein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps.</hi> 30. for oratur, order. 36. for both, loth. 242.9. dissolutas scopas, <hi>vlt.</hi> hath the name. 244.13. for dilation, dilectation. 245.8. for profit, perfect. 11. for affections, affectuous. 19 for fame, some. 246.11. legatur. 247.7. the Auayle. 248.5. for peruerting, preuenting. 249.1. Rough and vrgid. 20. manuall. 250.11. Iudex feriat. 33. <hi>Quid in?</hi> 251.3 those. for was, now. 27. <hi>dele</hi> ergo. 33. separation 252.3 &amp; 19 donatians. 4 for samis, sacris 20. for aptly, apertly. 253.1. sacris. 255.24 for open, opine 263.38. lineing. 264.12. Ast. 23. Idiot <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> 267.1. for followes, falles. 5 wicked 16. for haec, heu 268.3. for out, eat. 10. for bee. see <hi>Moses</hi> 33. for the, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>riacle. 269.10 for exception, execution 25 for strength, straites 32. of preceyt. 276.35. for meum, nostrum. 277 15 if by no. 20. prolepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal 284.25 for aptly, apertly 288.1. strengthener 291.4. for and, not without. 293.38. constat. 295.17. for as, an 296.2. for secretly, securely. 22. for stayne, slaine. 37. is a vertuous. 298 37. Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans. 299.4. prosecuting 300.2 yet is it <hi>Pauls.</hi> 9. to vnderualye. 301.14. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> 104.24. wee nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. 30. should we be. 301.34. for proued, prouoked. 269.21. for most li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, mostly 38. for respect, rescue. 271.32. for heresie, hearesay. 272.25. for nourisheth, monisheth. 275.21. for his, this.</p>
   <pb facs="158"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>