<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my Mayden Muse.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116940_Fr1_12</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03470</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13592</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116940</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my Mayden Muse.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Pancharis : the first booke. Containing the preparation of the loue betweene Ovven Tudyr, and the Queene, long since intended to her maiden Maiestie: and now dedicated to the inuincible Iames, second and greater Monarch of great Britaine, King of England, Scotland, France, and Ireland, with the islands adiacent</title>
                 <author>Holland, Hugh</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Knight, Clement</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>86 pages, illustrations, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_his_muse">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>To my Mayden Muse.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>GOe Virgin Muse to her Diuinity,</l>
      <l>That is the Vesta of Virginity:</l>
      <l>For vnto whom shouldst thou goe rather</l>
      <l>So bound to her, and to her father?</l>
      <l>Be gonne, and when thou com'st before her,</l>
      <l>Vpon thy knee, see thou adore her.</l>
      <l>For thou mayst gather by her feature,</l>
      <l>She is more then an earthly creature.</l>
      <l>In whom no Elements are combined,</l>
      <l>But a fift Essence well refined</l>
      <l>Aboue the vulgar grosse confections</l>
      <l>Of any of the fower complexions,</l>
      <l>Flegme, Sanguine, Melancholy, Coler.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Tell her that once I was her Scholer,</l>
      <l>And how in Grammer I was grounded</l>
      <l>In the best schoole she euer founded,</l>
      <l>By two great Clerkes (two greater wasters</l>
      <l>Of oyle then houres) that were my Masters:</l>
      <l>Where I liu'd partly of her larges,</l>
      <l>And partly of my parents charges.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <l>Thence was I had to learne more knolledge</l>
      <l>To <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and her fathers Colledge,</l>
      <l>Of him whose fame is flowne ALL-OVER</l>
      <l>As well beyond as this side <hi>Douer.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>On <hi>Aristotle</hi> oft I pored,</l>
      <l>And here and there him ouer-skored.</l>
      <l>Where Poetrie too I found defined,</l>
      <l>To which by birth I was enclined.</l>
      <l>Yet heard I worthy DOVVNES in <hi>Homer,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>And euery day I glean'd my gomer.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Thus hauing there for <hi>Lea</hi> serued</l>
      <l>Though some saide <hi>Rachel</hi> I deserued)</l>
      <l>Some thought the house could stand without me.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>I then began to looke about me:</l>
      <l>And forthwith desperately did ventre</l>
      <l>The wide world, in whose little Centre</l>
      <l>My friends (of whom death hath bereft me)</l>
      <l>My louing friends some liuing left me,</l>
      <l>Enough (if God the grace but lend me)</l>
      <l>From Cold and Hunger to defend me:</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="11"/>
That I may study still by leasure,</l>
      <l>Without all paine, and at my pleasure.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Now the blacke Doune began to couer</l>
      <l>My pale Cheekes (for I was a Louer)</l>
      <l>And sung Acrosticke Sonets sweetely;</l>
      <l>For (if that some can iudge discreetely)</l>
      <l>I neede not feare that daintie DAVIES,</l>
      <l>Though he sing sweeter then the Mauis.</l>
      <l>And of my Loue they were. But stay thee,</l>
      <l>No more of that my Muse I pray thee.</l>
      <l>For either it must show my folly,</l>
      <l>Or else renew my Melancholly:</l>
      <l>Yet was she faire, and Honourable,</l>
      <l>And Vertuous (had she beene more stable.)</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Though she perhaps did but forget her,</l>
      <l>And now likes May denhead the better:</l>
      <l>Whereof she is the richest border</l>
      <l>Next CYNTHIA Soueraigne of that Order.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>When <hi>Loue</hi> my bosome thus had fired,</l>
      <l>Me for his Prophet he inspired:</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="11"/>
That euery line, and euery letter</l>
      <l>Of my deuise might passe the better.</l>
      <l>Yet of this Legend but the writer</l>
      <l>Was I, and he the sole inditer.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For how alas can it be other?</l>
      <l>I am not I the Muses brother.</l>
      <l>My lips I neuer yet haue sowsed</l>
      <l>In Hippocrene, nor carowsed</l>
      <l>The lusty Liquor thence distilling</l>
      <l>The braine with holly fury filling.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The Climat where I was begotten</l>
      <l>Of father <hi>Phoebus</hi> is forgotten,</l>
      <l>No Parnasse there (though Mountaines many)</l>
      <l>Nor Muse (though Nymphs as faire as any)</l>
      <l>God wote it is too farre remoued</l>
      <l>From her, to be of them beloued.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Apollo,</hi> they and all the <hi>Graces,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Attend her onely in all places.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>This in effect when thou hast told her,</l>
      <l>Thou must be yet a little bolder:</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="12"/>
And beg that thou mayst waite vpon her,</l>
      <l>Among her many May des of Honor;</l>
      <l>A modest Maide with chaste variety,</l>
      <l>To lull asleepe that sweete Society.</l>
      <l>Who may as well as any other,</l>
      <l>Reade euery line before the Mother.</l>
      <l>So shamefa'cd are they, and so holly,</l>
      <l>Voide of all loosenesse, and light folly:</l>
      <l>Else had it beene too much impiety,</l>
      <l>To vow them to so great a Deity.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>This done, againe on knee lowe bended,</l>
      <l>And hands as high to heauen extended,</l>
      <l>Ascribe me of this golden story</l>
      <l>Onely the paine, and her the glory:</l>
      <l>Praying she would but reade the proem,</l>
      <l>And so breath life into my Poëm</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>