<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣SHIPFVLL GENTLEMEN, LO∣uers of learning, Piety and Charity, the Gouernours of Christs Hospitall in London, foster fathers of the poore Orphans, and helplesse Children there releeued; Grace &amp; Peace be multiplied.</title>
           <author>B., G.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116231_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17031</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3908.2</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116231</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣SHIPFVLL GENTLEMEN, LO∣uers of learning, Piety and Charity, the Gouernours of Christs Hospitall in London, foster fathers of the poore Orphans, and helplesse Children there releeued; Grace &amp; Peace be multiplied.</title>
                 <author>B., G.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An introduction to pietie and humanitie : containing, first, a short catechisme for vnderstanding the grounds of religion: secondly, certaine briefe and effectuall rules for life and conuersation. Penned specially for the vse of the poore children of Christ's Hospitall in London: but generallie may serue for any other that would be instructed therein. By Gregorie Brovvne</title>
                 <author>Browne, Gregory</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Weaver (Wever), Edmund</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 50+ pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL GENTLEMEN, LO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of learning, Piety and Charity, the Gouernours of Christs Hospitall in London, foster fathers of the poore Orphans, and helplesse Children there releeued; Grace &amp; Peace be multiplied.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He giuer of all goodnesse, Right worshipfull, hauing, promised that the best good things, being first sought and preferred, the second <note place="margin">
         <hi>Luke</hi> 12.</note> necessary for life shall neuer faile; I haue accordingly endeuored to my poore talent, and leasure, together with others, to wish the speciall good of these poore Children, which by God his prouidence are cast vpon your louing care and fatherly protection: desiring that in priuate euen from their infancy, they might be seasoned with some taste of piety and humanity, which might make for their better good when they are
<pb facs="3"/> in publike to be further trained vp in the practise of Religion and Arts: for man new born is like a wild Asses coult; &amp; folly is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally in the heart of a child, vntil by edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation &amp; discipline it be made fit to beare &amp; bring forth better fruit. If any good shal come hereof to that end; I haue my desire, as the chiefest good which I know is here intended in their fostering and educating in this Christian gouernment; which hath and shall cause many prayers and praises to God for your worships, that you may be had in an euerlasting remembrance, and the whole benefit in the end to redound vnto you and others, who haue ruled with faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, &amp; distributed with cheerefulnes; when God shall haue the glory, Religion the credit, our King the honor, the Citie and whole State the profit, and your selues comfort of conscience, &amp; blessing of peace and plentie, which the God of peace and loue graunt vnto you all, <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships in all Christian duty, <hi>G. B.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>