<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116093_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10907</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21177</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116093</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An answer to Mr. Fisher the Iesuite, his fiue propositions concerning Luther. By Mr. Rogers, that worthy Oxford diuine. VVith some passages also of the said Mr. Rogers with the said Mr. Fisher. Hereunto is annexed Mr. VV.C. his dialogue of the said argument, wherein is discouered Fishers folly</title>
                 <author>Rogers, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 28 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>CHristian Reader,</hi> There came to my hands by the good prouidence of God this small Treatise, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a conference betwixt one <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>.</hi> Rogers an Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford Diuine, and one <hi>Mr. Fisher</hi> a Iesuite: as it should seeme it was sent inclosed to a Gentleman of good worth and worship one this side the Seas, hauing read it ouer, and perceiuing it to be of very necessary vse for my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men of England, (whose good I desire from my heart) I haue aduentured to publish it to the view of the world: the rather, because therein is notably laid open and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced, the weake grounds of the fiue propositions of <hi>Mr. Fisher</hi> the Iesuite, who is as I heare, so much admired of English papists; the which <hi>Fisher, Sweet, Brierly, Clerk,</hi> with others of that company, doe studie and striue with all might and maine by divulging their written papers, as also their Printed Bookes full of lyes and vntruths: nay I say, Bookes full of blasphemie against the grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> God of heauen, as namely that Booke Intituled. <hi>The vncasing of Heresie,</hi> written by <hi>O. A:</hi> and all to make proselites of their owne faction, to ruine that flourishing Church and Common-wealth. I beseech the great God of heauen, to raise vp dayly worthy Diuines more and more to defend his owne cause, against the Kingdome of Antichrist, and wicked instruments, being very dangerous persons both against Church and Common wealth. Read it with the
<pb facs="4"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> ioyned, &amp; so by Gods blessing thou shalt reape <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> fit by it, and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ue all glory to God aboue, who in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>esse things that are amisse.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>