<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116197_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16980</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3864</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116197</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Master Broughtons letters, especially his last pamphlet to and against the Lord Archbishop of Canterbury, about Sheol and Hades, for the descent into Hell, answered in their kind</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Xpect not (gentle Reader) any matter of great weight and substance in this answer, the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellers</hi> defence (as he cals it) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nought else in ballance of sound iudgement, but the fume of enuie, and the fome of vanitie: only accept it as <hi>a rod for a fooles backe,</hi> I feare <hi>incorrigible, nam senex Psittacus non capit ferulam:</hi> who though he be brayed in a morter, will still continue to bray like himselfe. If thou thinkest it too bitter, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare his <hi>Libell</hi> and this answere; the reuerend <hi>Archbishop,</hi> whom with his foule mouthed slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders he defileth, and himself a vainglorious <hi>Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so,</hi> a fugitiue abroad, a schismatike at home, a tormentor of soules with mysticall riddles, a cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous trumpetor of his owne praises, and so iudge of both. Some, I know, haue said, he is
<pb facs="3"/> halfe mad that should answere him; <hi>a smooth co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour for idlenes,</hi> and a goodly couer to shadow <hi>their ingratitude,</hi> who serue a master for fee, not loue, and care not how he is abused, so they be exalted. I say with <hi>Dauid, Adhuc vilior fiam plusquam factus sum,</hi> and, as it is, haue done it: if thou approue it, I glorie not: if other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, I care not. <hi>Ʋale.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>