<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A farewell to his booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116380_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02935</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13076</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116380</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A farewell to his booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first booke of the preseruation of King Henry the vij. when he was but Earle of Richmond, grandfather to the Queenes maiesty : compiled in English rythmicall hexameters</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 <publisher>Bradock, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Broome (Brome), Joan.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Potter, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>104 pages, oblong 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>X to the Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_book">
   <head>A farewell to his booke.</head>
   <l>MY prety book farewell: God send thee prosperus accesse</l>
   <l>Vnto the Court: to the Queene vouchsafe my name to be namelesse.</l>
   <l>Thy soueraigne Patronesse (if please her grace to defend thee)</l>
   <l>Can patronize thy defectes. Whom God preserue, as a bay tree,</l>
   <l>Long to be predominant, with Lords of her priuie Counsail:</l>
   <l>Namely the Lord Keeper, with learned lawes who doth excell:</l>
   <l>That Metropolitan eake, whom I think my selfe to be bound to;</l>
   <l>Th'Archbishop, at <hi>Lambeth:</hi> that wise Lord Treasurer also:</l>
   <l>And Senator <hi>Cecill;</hi> that apeares to the Realme a defender:</l>
   <pb facs="13"/>
   <l>Sonne to the Lord <hi>Burleigh</hi> late deade, his wise witie father,</l>
   <l>That sapient <hi>Nestor:</hi> which did by pollicy compasse</l>
   <l>Much quiet vnto the Realme. For like as <hi>Caelifer Atlas,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>On large broad shoulders sore pressed, propped vp heauen:</l>
   <l>So with his experience, this noble Realme was vpholden.</l>
   <l>For why? The state of a Prince consisteth chiefly by counsel</l>
   <l>Of witie graue Senators, whose witte with vertue doth excel.</l>
   <l>And I beseech God blesse that noble pillar of highnesse,</l>
   <l>Glorius Earle, <hi>Talbot,</hi> stout Earle of <hi>Shrewsbury;</hi> doubtlesse</l>
   <l>Vertues trew president: of al humane curtesy mirror:</l>
   <l>Mirror of armipotence. Whose nobel name was a terror</l>
   <l>Vnto the Frenche Regiment: to the Crowne still knowne to be constant:</l>
   <l>Worthy to be credited with a Prince, as a faithfull atendant:</l>
   <l>And to be chiefly preferd; that he may with bounty the better</l>
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <l>Stand a defense to the Prince, to the Publick weale as a pillar.</l>
   <l>And God graunt to that Earle of Oxford, mirror of highnes,</l>
   <l>Happines in this world: God blesse his Ladie the Countesse,</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Elizabeth Trentam,</hi> that right trew Maiden of honnor,</l>
   <l>Immaculat Virgin: whose house and name I doe fauor,</l>
   <l>With reuerence as I should. For I came my selfe of a <hi>Trentam,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Aunt to thee, Lady renoun'd: yet I am not knowne to thee Madame.</l>
   <l>Loth I am yet to be knowne. For I should be knowne to the best sort:</l>
   <l>Knowne to that Earle <hi>Deuereux:</hi> whom I pray God daily to comfort.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Vere, Deuereux, Talbot,</hi> three nobel principal howses,</l>
   <l>Ar to be greatly renoun'd, for their nobilitie peerelesse.</l>
   <l>
      <note place="margin">Quae supra nos nihil ad nos.</note>And I do charge thee my book, with things not rashly to meddel,</l>
   <l>Which ar aboue our reach, that concerne vs but a littel:</l>
   <l>Nor to detract any fame, from Peeres or States that are highest.</l>
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <l>For littel meddling, of most is thought to be wisest.<note place="margin">Ouid. Viue ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi, &amp; longèno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina magna fuge.</note>
   </l>
   <l>As the Poet poetiz'd, that <hi>Naso</hi> Poetical Author;</l>
   <l>Frugaly liue to thy selfe: flee far from great men of honnor.</l>
   <l>For many men that atend some Lords, or daily do follow,</l>
   <l>Do but as <hi>Aesops</hi> dogge, that a substance lost for a shaddow.</l>
   <l>Yet many men be preferd, by the meanes of great men of honnor;</l>
   <l>Such speciall persons which they most dearely do fauor.</l>
   <l>Farewel againe prety book: be dutiful vnto thy betters:</l>
   <l>Humbly with al reuerence, submit thy selfe to thy Rulers.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>