<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE COVRTEOVS READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116788_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11580</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21825</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116788</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE COVRTEOVS READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>De numeris geometricis. = Of the nature and proprieties of geometricall numbers. First written by Lazarus Schonerus, and now Englished, enlarged and illustrated with diuers and sundry tables and obseruations concerning the measuring of plaines and solids: all teaching the fabricke, demonstration and vse of a singular instrument, or rular, long since inuented and perfitted by Thomas Bedwell Esquire</title>
                 <author>Bedwell, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 82, 2 pages, folded table, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE COVRTEOVS READER.</head>
   <p>IT is now, as farre as I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, well neare fortie yeares since a Rular, for the measuring of Plaines and Solids, was first de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uised by mine vnkle M. Thomas Bedwell. The vse of this, himselfe hath taught in a litle Treatise, which I haue seene long ago in his studie amongst other his writings of like nature and argumēt. The fabrick or maner of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it, he did not, to my knowledge, impart to any. That I suppose be reserued for a larger volume of diuerse o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther such inuentions of his, which he bad purposed to haue published, if God had spared him longer life. But these all being suppressed by some, who haue, as it see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, more respected their owne priuate gaine, then either his honour or the common good; I did, about a dozen yeares ago, as some learned louers of these stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies can testifie, labour to shadow out that worke of his. And at last hauing finished a Treatise, both of the construction and vse of the same, I offered it vnto some to haue it imprinted: But they seeing in the copie
<pb facs="4"/>
diuers figures and diagrammes, refused to meddle with it, except my selfe would beare a great part of the charge of that first impression. That I being vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to do, I was forced to deferre the publishing of it vntill I might meete with some one that would of himselfe vndertake the businesse. In this <hi>interim,</hi> I found yet another scruple, which I thought necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie first to be remoued. For as the construction of the first Author was meerely Geometricall, so that of ours was wholly Arithmeticall, and could not be done without the helpe of numbers: and therefore was such as might not easily be taught or conceiued, except first the nature and proprieties of such like numbers were well vnderstood. Whereupon, before that Treatise of the Rular, this of <hi>GEOMETRICALL NVM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BERS</hi> was first to be published. Geometricall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers I call them; not Figurate or Cossicke numbers, as commonly they are called: For of those infinite sorts of this kinde of numbers, we haue to do with none but such as do represent and expresse some true Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricall figure, such as the Quadrate, Parallelogram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oblong, Prisma, and the Cubicke are. Now whereas haply some man may obiect and say, that these things haue bene often handled and sufficiently taught by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; let him know, that although in generall we do confesse it to be true, yet no man, to our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb facs="4"/>
hath applied those rules to that vse that we haue done: And therefore those Treatises of theirs, do in no waies fit our purpose. For first out of these rules, as afterward shall appeare, we haue framed certaine Tables for sundrie vses in measuring of Plaines and Solids. One of these, called <hi>TRIGONVM ARCHI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TECTONICVM, The Carpenters Squire,</hi> we cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed for the publicke good, more then a twelue-moneth since, to be imprinted at our owne cost and charges. Moreouer, sundrie practises and workes of these rules more plaine and easie then commonly are vsed, are here shewed and discouered. Lastly, we haue here gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thee a taste or sample of a forme and maner of resoluing any intricate demonstration mathematical, whereby it shall be made so plaine and easie, that it may be conceiued of the simplest. This we haue vsed these seuen or eight and twentie yeares; and because we see it to be approued of the most learned Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticians of this kingdom, we shall ere long, God willing, more fully manifest it by many examples.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>