<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, Their most louing Friende in the Lord, SYR WILLIAM SCOT OF ELIE, KNIGHT, &amp;c. Grace in this life, and euerlasting Glo∣rie in the Life to come.</title>
           <author>A., H. C. W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116143_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11006</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21277</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116143</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, Their most louing Friende in the Lord, SYR WILLIAM SCOT OF ELIE, KNIGHT, &amp;c. Grace in this life, and euerlasting Glo∣rie in the Life to come.</title>
                 <author>A., H. C. W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Fiue and twentie lectures, vpon the last sermon and conference of our Lord Iesus Christ, with his disciples immediately before his Passion : contained in the fourteenth, fifteenth, and sixteenth chapters of the Gospel of Sainct Iohn. As also vpon that most excellent prayer, contained in the seuenteenth chap. of the same Gospel. Preached by that reuerend and faythfull seruant of God, M. Robert Rollok, minister of the Kirke (and rector of the Colledge) of Edinburgh</title>
                 <author>Rollock, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hart, Andro</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 270, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, Their most louing Friende in the Lord, SYR WILLIAM SCOT OF ELIE, KNIGHT, &amp;c. Grace in this life, and euerlasting Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in the Life to come.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LBEIT, RIGHT HONOVRABLE,</hi> the whole Scripture, and euerie parte thereof, bee of Diuine inspiration, and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to teach, to conuince, to correct, and to instruct in Righteousnesse; Yet it is no absur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie to affi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>me, that some partes thereof, for some respectes and causes, are to bee preferred, and more accounted of than others. The Apostle giueth vs a sufficient proofe of this▪ while he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth the Gospel to the Law, <hi>2. Cor vers. 3.</hi> And the Euangelistes, in setting downe in w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t sundrie thinges, <hi>(Iohn 20. vers. 30.)</hi> declare the same to be true in the Gospel, and consequentlie amongst those thinges which are written, the Spirite of God would haue vs to esteeme
<pb facs="3"/>
most of those thinges which hee hath more particularlie, painfullie, carefullie, and at greatest length put in Register. Amongst the which, there are none to bee preferred vnto his last <hi>Sermone,</hi> which hee made to his Apostles and his <hi>Prayer</hi> vnto his Father immediatlie before his departure. The excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie whereof, and howe highlie the LORD would haue vs to regarde and account of them, (to speake nothing of the Author, I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>S CHRIST, because, by his holie Spirit, not onelie this, but also the whole Scripture, is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,) shall more euidentlie appeare, if we consider a little, first the time of the vttering of them: next, the manner: and thirdlie, the matter therein contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. The time was immediatelie before his <hi>Passion</hi>: for after that by his owne example, in washing his Disciples feete, he had recommended vnto them Humilitie, as a vertue most singular and beseeming a Christian; hee vttereth these wordes, partlie in the time of the Supper, and partlie after the Supper. And wee knowe, that the speaches of men, which immediatelie preceede death, as they proceede of a moste holie and Heauenlie disposition, (for then all affections are layde aside, nature reuiueth, and reason getteth place, then moste wiselie the soule resolueth concerning its owne estate and condition, then hee testifieth most plainlie his will towardes his Children, his Seruantes, his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and other Friendes whatsoeuer,) so are they thought worthie to bee moste attentiuelie heard, most carefullie receiued, and most deeplie kept in memorie. If wee consider the manner, seeing the holie Spirit taketh more paines, and is more plentifull and copious in penning heereof, than of anie other <hi>Sermone</hi> whatsoeuer, hee would haue vs to knowe howe precious a Iewell they are, and howe highlie wee ought to account of them: For if wee search all the Records of the LORDES <hi>Sermons</hi> in the New Testament, wee shall finde none so particularlie and fullie set downe in register, as this is. Lastlie, if wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider the matter, it is full of manifolde Heauenlie consolations. It is true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, sundrie times before, the LORD in his <hi>Sermons</hi> hath comforted his Apostles, and all penitent sinners: but in no place at so great length, and with such varietie of Heauenlie consolations: For heere at length hee meeteth and re-encountereth almost with euerie griefe, scandale, and particular temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation that exercised and assailed their soules. They were sadde and sorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, when they heard that hee was to leaue the worlde, and to ascende vnto the Father. Hee meeteth this, by bidding them belieue in him, and fayth in him should supplie his bodilie absence: and hee telleth, that the ende wherefore hee ascended, was to prepare a place for them, that where he was, there they might bee also. It was a griefe to them, that they should want such a comfortable Guide, who alwayes directed and conducted them. This hee meeteth, by telling them, that hee would not leaue them comfortlesse, but hee would giue them his Holie Spirit. They feared, that they should bee depriued of manifolde conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,
<pb facs="3"/>
which they found in his presence. This hee meeteth, by assuring them that howbeit in the worlde they should finde trouble, yet in the middest of trouble hee should giue and leaue them that peace that the worlde should not take from them: and if they belieue in him, as the Vine-tree furnisheth the Branches, so hee should furnishe vnto them solide and manifolde consolations, and make them to bring foorth fruite aboundantlie. And to the intent that they might haue the better warrand to looke and exspect for those graces in him, as hee chargeth them by fayth to haue vnion with him, so hee chargeth them by loue to haue communion amongst themselues. The troubles and crosses that were to befall them in the worlde for CHRISTES sake, after his departure, might haue wonderfullie discouraged them, and brangled their fayth. This hee meeteth, partlie by fore-warning them before they came to passe, and partlie by exhorting them to patience, and partlie by setting downe manie argumentes to establish them, Hee telleth them, that the worlde should hate them, persecute them, excommunicate them, and put them to death. Hee comforteth them, partlie because hee hath fore-warned them, and partlie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they had done so to him who was their Lord and Master, and partlie for the goodnesse of the cause, because it was for his Names sake. Againe, hee knew it would bee no small temptation vnto them, to see his shamefull and ignominious handling, to see him, who was their Lord, to bee so wonderfullie humbled, to see him taken, and bound by wicked and profane men, to see him made a spectacle of derision, first in the Hall of <hi>Annas,</hi> and thereafter of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>japhas,</hi> to see all sortes and rankes of people crie out against him, to see him at last to bee condemned and ignominiouslie crucified: hee knewe that this temptation would bee so strong, and so vehement to brangle their fayth, that at the last all should bee offended in him, and should flee away from him, and leaue him. Of this hee fore-warneth them, and furnisheth consolation vnto them, notwithstanding of their foule fall.</p>
   <p>Now againe, if yee looke to the <hi>Prayer,</hi> it is wonderous Heauenlie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable: For after that as a Prophet hee hath instructed the people, and the Apostles, nowe before (as an high Priest) hee offer vp his owne bodie vpon the Crosse, for the sinnes of the worlde, hee prayeth most earnestlie for himselfe, for his Apostles, and for them who should belieue through their Ministerie. For himselfe, That the Father would nowe glorifie the Sonne, when hee is going out of the worlde. For his Apostles, That the Father would alwayes haue a car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of them whome hee left in the worlde behinde him. And thirdlie, for all them that through the Ministerie of the Apostles should bee liuing to the ende of the worlde, That the Lord would blesse them, and by his prouidence guarde them. And so both the matter of the <hi>Sermone</hi> and <hi>Prayer</hi> is wonderous excellent, and in them both wee may see, not onelie Diuine knowledge, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeing
<pb facs="4"/>
and fore-telling those thinges that were to come to passe, which, if hee had beene onelie man, hee could neuer haue done; but also a loue vnspeakable, and more than wonderfull, in that when the wrath of God was persuing him for the sinnes of the Elect, when the bitter Cuppe of the Passion was to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pined vnto him, when the terroures of Death were nowe before his eyes, when Sathan, and all the power of darknesse, was nowe to assaile him, when all rankes of men were to raile vpon him, and all his owne were to bee offended at him, when <hi>Peter</hi> should denie him, <hi>Herode</hi> should mocke him, <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> should condemne him, in a manner, hee was forgetfull of all those thinges that should come to himselfe, and mindfull alwayes to offer joye and consolation vnto his owne.</p>
   <p>Nowe this matter so excellent, haue manie learned and godlie men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortablie and fruitfullie handeled, and amongst the rest, that famous and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Minister of Iesus Christ, in the Kirke of <hi>EDINBVRGH,</hi> M. <hi>ROBERT ROLLOK,</hi> of happie memorie, for his painfull and comfortable trauels therein, and for his manifolde other graces, deserueth to bee praysed with the first: For hee was a man whom God beautified with manie rare gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and whome the Lord made manie wayes to bee steadable to his Kirke: his vntimelie death, when the Lord first called him, did manie lament, and when their teares were spent, they entertained dolour and griefe in their heartes: Yea, euen nowe the faythfull, seriouslie considering these dayes of decaye, (wherein that <hi>Antichristian</hi> rabble set themselues to smoare the Trueth, and to bring in darknesse againe: and wherein by some, Religion is mocked, and disdained, and some are content with a bare showe and outward profession, without power and vigour thereof, and a life answering therevnto) are compelled to sigh for the great wound and losse that the Kirke suffered, as in the death of manie others, so namelie in the death of that most faythfull man of GOD. Through his death this <hi>Citie</hi> lost a good Citizen, the Flocke a good Pastor, the Colledge a good Rector, his Brethren a faythfull Fellow-labourer, wandering sinners a wise guide, and in a worde, what sorte of people found not some losse, and had not their interesse in his death? Who was more carefull than hee to haue GOD glorified? Who walked more carefullie with GOD? Who was more crucified to the worlde? Who was more seuered from all entangling worldlie pleasures, and commodities? Who more had their conuersation in Heauen? Who more carefull to gaine soules to the Kingdome of GOD, publicklie and priuatelie, by voyce and by penne, by worde and by writ, at home and abroade, aliue and dead? And his conuersation was so answ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rable to his profession and calling, that the verie malicious Aduersaries, and enemies themselues, could not, nor durst not, charge him with anie imputation. But wee neede not, Syr, to prayse him vnto you, who
<pb facs="4"/>
knew him so well, and who was so familiarlie conuersant with him; and his wordes doe speake sufficientlie to others who knew him not.</p>
   <p>Nowe, Syr, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se his <hi>LECTVRES</hi> wee graunt are not so absolute as manie would require, and wee our selues would wish: for neither deliuered hee them of purpose that they should see the light, neither sawe hee them euer after hee had deliuered them▪ neither did his Schollers receiue them from his mouth on the purpose, but onelie for the helping of their owne memories: And yet wee trust, that such as regarde more matter in edification, than delicate language, and plau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ible wordes, shall finde no small comfort in perusing of them: For, not onelie for the duetie wee ought to the Author, our louing Master, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so for your cause and earnest request, to whome wee are so much obliged, haue wee taken some, yea, no small paines, heerein, (as they who are accustomed with such cases, may easilie consider,) that his owne matter might bee sette downe in his owne phrase and stile so neare as possiblie wee could, that with the greater liking and approbation they might bee perused by such as seeke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o bee edified.</p>
   <p>And so much the more carefull were wee heerein, because wee found that his other <hi>LECTVRES,</hi> published by vs before, as on the <hi>COLOSSIANS, THESSELONIANS,</hi> and other seuerall Textes of Scripture, and nar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lie the <hi>Lectures</hi> last published, vpon the <hi>Passion</hi> and <hi>Resurrection,</hi> euer recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with great liking and contentment of manie, who acknowledge themeselues to bee greatlie edified thereby.</p>
   <p>Nowe, Syr, these last <hi>LECTVRES,</hi> and our laboures therein, wee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent vnto you, to bee published abroade vnder your protection, because moste justlie in all respectes they belong vnto you: For first, fewe are ignorant howe louing and alwayes beneficiall you were to the Author himselfe, from the first time yee knewe him, euen to the houre of his death, and thereafter to his Wife, and nowe you continue the same kindnesse to his posthume Daughter. Next, as while hee liued hee acknowledged and professed himselfe to bee m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re oblieged to you than to anie, so at the houre of his death, in his latter Will, hee ordained, that whatsouer of his workes thereafter should see the light, should come out in your Name, that where his workes were read, your deseruinges might bee knowne, and that they who gotte fruite of them, might also esteeme of you, and giue you thankes therefore. Thirdlie, for the great Paines, Exspences, and Trauelles that yee haue bestowed in making them to come to the light. For by you they were gathered in from the handes of <hi>SCHOL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LERS,</hi> that wrote them: and by your exspenses they were written ouer and ouer againe: without you they had neuer beene reuised and corrected: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out you they had not beene made meet for the <hi>PRESSE.</hi> Fourthly, because as the Lord hath blessed you with many worldly comforts, with an honorable esta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, &amp;
<pb facs="5"/>
good account in the worlde, so hath hee indued you with graces of his Spirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlie, with true Pietie and Religion in the soule, and outwardlie with an answerable profession and practise thereof vttered in the true loue which yee carrie to all Gods Children, and namelie to those who carrie the Message of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, in helping and furthering them both priuatelie and publikelie, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your power. And finallie, wee dedicate our laboures heerein to you, as a testimonie, that wee acknowledge our selues to bee manie wayes debt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound to you, for your vndeserued kindnesse vttered so manie wayes towardes vs, and continuing so long without alteration.</p>
   <p>Nowe, the Lord, who is infinite in mercie, whose loue is constant, without alteration, and endlesse, who hath hitherto giuen you plentifullie and aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantlie manifolde tokens of his loue, both for the vse of the bodie and this tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitorie life, and also for the weale and comfort of your soule in this your pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and who hath honoured you with manie good turnes, and namelie, with loue and kindnesse towardes Gods Children for his cause, make you more and more finde the loue of God shed abroad in your soule, so that you neuer wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in well-doing, but that yee may daylie goe on forward in the course of sanctification: that yee seeking, fearing, louing, and alwayes ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him, and being comfortable to his Sainctes on Earth, yee may bee assured, when this short life is ended, the Lord shall crowne you with, eternall Glorie in Heauen, with all his Saincts in JESƲS.</p>
   <closer>AMEN.</closer>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the Lord, <hi>H. C. W. A.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>