<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT
HONOVRABLE, GRAVE, VER∣tuous,
and Religious Lady, the Lady Kathe∣rine
Hastings, Countesse of Huntington,
T. C. wisheth health, and happines,
in this life, and in the life to come,
Eternall felicitie.</title>
           <author>Collins, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116067_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19155</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5566</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116067</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT
HONOVRABLE, GRAVE, VER∣tuous,
and Religious Lady, the Lady Kathe∣rine
Hastings, Countesse of Huntington,
T. C. wisheth health, and happines,
in this life, and in the life to come,
Eternall felicitie.</title>
                 <author>Collins, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The penitent publican : his confession of mouth. Contrition of heart. Vnfained repentance. And feruent prayer vnto God, for mercie and forgiuenesse</title>
                 <author>Collins, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Johnson (Jonson), Arthur</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT
HONOVRABLE, GRAVE, VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous,
and Religious Lady, the Lady Kathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine
Hastings, Countesse of Huntington,
T. C. wisheth health, and happines,
in this life, and in the life to come,
Eternall felicitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may seeme somewhat strange
vnto your Ladiship, that I should
thus presume to publish this my
poore &amp; <hi>Penitent Publican,</hi> vnder
your Honorable protection: yet
in regard of your Ladiships Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie
of heart vnto God, manifes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
by your most vertuous life, and zealous loue
vnto true Religion. I am animated to aduenture
him in the worlds view, being shadowed vnder the
shield of your sacred vertues, which (like the bright
beames of <hi>Phoebus)</hi> may Illustrate, and giue a long
life, to this my illiterate, &amp; litle-worth labour, which
(wanting your fauorable reflection) might with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
regard. For (Madame) I am not ignorant,
that Enuie attends vpon all good attempts: <hi>Ismael</hi>
will scoffe, and mocke at <hi>Isaack,</hi> euen in <hi>Abrahams</hi>
house, and <hi>Shemy</hi> will reuile <hi>Dauid</hi> to his teeth, and
<pb facs="5"/>
therefore the godlie in these dayes, may well say
with holy <hi>Iob,</hi> my soule is cut off, though I liue. <hi>Iob</hi>
the 10. and 1. verse. The righteous as the prophet
speaketh, are most despised: for let <hi>Elisha,</hi> goe vp to
<hi>Bethel,</hi> and euen the little children will call him
Bald-pate: and so he that labours to liue vprightly,
and to keepe the true path, he is accounted precise,
and called a Puritan: the consideration whereof,
makes manie men that would be feruent, to be
fearefull; and like <hi>Peter,</hi> to follow a far off, and rather
to denie him, that died for vs; then to the face of his
enemies, affirme that we knowe him: such is the
times impietie, and our infirmitie, that we are easily
intreated to retire from any godly action, or good
intention. And with <hi>Demas,</hi> quickly drawne to
abandon God, and imbrace the world: yea euen
this vild &amp; vaine world, which many excellent wise
and worthy men, haue most fitly compared vnto a
sea of glasse, of the which S. <hi>Iohn</hi> speakes, <hi>Reuelat.</hi>
the 4. and the 6. verse, for it is both so slipperie and so
vncertaine; so full of troubles &amp; tempestious waues,
one wallowing vpon the necke of another, that it is
high time for vs to say with the Disciples: <hi>Maister
saue vs, or else we perish: Mathew.</hi> 8. and, the 25. verse,
for so small is our faith, that we soone faint: especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
in Gods affaires.</p>
   <p>Yet wee seeme vnto men, as though wee were
both so constant and so confident in God, that we
might say with <hi>Iob, Though he kill mee, yet will I trust
in him. Iob.</hi> the 13. and the 14. verse. But (alas) if
we do behold but a litle persecution, lay hand vpon
<pb facs="5"/>
our profession, for feare of the one, wee are readie
to flie from the other. Forgetting the charge that
Saint <hi>Paul</hi> giues vnto <hi>Timothie, Fight the good fight
of Faith, and lay holde of Eternall life. Timot.</hi> the 6.
and the 12. verse: Wee are not onely cold in loue,
but also carelesse in Religion. For like the readie,
(yet recanting) sonne, some say, they wil come into
Christs congregation, but come not: &amp; others say,
they wil not come, yet they do: but it is at the end of
the day, before they will drawe neere; And long
doth <hi>Wisedome crie in the streetes,</hi> before she can call
them together, to <hi>goe to the Tabernacle, and returne
to the Lord,</hi> who by his Prophet <hi>Ezekiell,</hi> makes this
proclamation: <hi>Ezek.</hi> the 18. and the 23. verse. <hi>Haue
I any desire</hi> (saith hee) <hi>that the wicked should die? or
shall hee not liue, if hee returne from his owne wayes?</hi>
And againe, in the 31. verse of the same chapter, he
saith, <hi>Cast away your trangressions, wherewith you haue
transgressed, and make you a new heart, and anew spirit,
for why will yee die, oh yee house of Israel?</hi> Nay more,
hee promiseth by the same Prophet, in the 34. and
the 16. verse, <hi>I will seeke that which was lost, and bring
againe, that which was driuen away, and builde vp that
which was broken, and will strengthen the weake;</hi>
wherby we may see, that the Lord would haue none
to be lost, but with the penitent Publican, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse
our sinnes, and to reforme our selues, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the counsell of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> in his 2. chap.
and 1. verse, laying aside all maliciousnes, all guile,
and dissimulation, all Enuie, and euill speaking, as
new borne babes, let vs desire the sincere milke of
<pb facs="6"/>
the word: that wee may growe thereby, from ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
to vertue, and from grace to grace, vntill we be
come perfit men in <hi>CHRIST IESVS;</hi> which wee
can neuer be, vnlesse with the <hi>Penitent Publican,</hi> we
doe truely humble our selues before the Almighty,
and vnfainedly craue mercie and remission.</p>
   <p>The which, that we may the more be animated
vnto, I haue here (though but in a homely habit) set
him, to be a patterne of true penitence, to all such
persons, as haue any desire to imitate him, in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
and repentance: by whose example, if any be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited
(as I hope there shall) to confesse their sinnes,
and craue pardon for the same; let them first giue
glorie vnto God, by whose holy aide I did indite it,
and then thankes vnto your <hi>Honour,</hi> vnder whose
protection I haue presumed to publish it, that it may
thereby (as with a buckler) be defended from the
venemous tongues of the Enuious.</p>
   <p>And thus with my most humble and hartie prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
vnto the Almightie, for your Ladiships
long life, and prosperitie, I ende,
this 6. of <hi>Iulie.</hi> 1610.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors, most
humblie deuoted,
<hi>Thomas Collins.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>