<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Worshipfull Ed∣ward Cooke Esquier, Atturney Generall to the Queens most excellent Maiestie, grace, mercie, and peace from God the Father, and from our Lord Iesus Christ.</title>
           <author>Bradley, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116905_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16598</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3505</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116905</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Worshipfull Ed∣ward Cooke Esquier, Atturney Generall to the Queens most excellent Maiestie, grace, mercie, and peace from God the Father, and from our Lord Iesus Christ.</title>
                 <author>Bradley, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A godly sermon preached before the right worshipfull Edvvard Cooke Esquier : Atturney Generall vnto the Queens most excellent Maiestie, and others of worship, in Tittleshall in Norfolke: by F.B</title>
                 <author>Bradley, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>47 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Worshipfull <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Cooke</hi> Esquier, Atturney Generall <hi>to the Queens most excellent Maiestie,</hi> grace, mercie, and peace from God the Father, and from our Lord Iesus Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong the sinnes in generall (Right Worshipfull) posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing our peruersenature, ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude chalengeth to hir selfe a speciall propertie in vs, a thing repugnant to reason, disagreeing to humanitie, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the expectation of man: that it dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeth with humanitie, Nature her selfe may best be Iudge, who hath not dealt so spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in bestowing of her gifts, but she will censure him as most vnkind whom shee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth tardie in this sin of ingratitude. Which sinne (as it is common) so it is contagious, and hath infected many, and yet for my own part I desire to be asmuch as may be free frō it; which I should hardly be, if I should bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie so many fauours receiued from your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship
<pb facs="3"/>in the graue of forgetfulnesse: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (in token of my dutie) I haue presumed to publish this my poore talent vnder your good acceptance, desiring your fauourable pardon for the same. I must confesse I stoode long in suspence with my selfe vnto whom I should commit this small trauell; but your wonted affection, and zeale towards the word soone stirred me vp to present it vnto you, not being much dismaied hauing so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reasons to induce me thereunto: among the rest, this being one of the chiefest, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, your patient and godly attention when it was preached; of whom I may say as Paul saith to the Thessalonians, you receiued it not as it was the word of man, but as it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede the word of God.
<note place="margin">1. Thess. chap. 2. vers. 13.</note> Thus with my hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie prayer vnto Almightie God, that it will please his Maiestie to blesse you with many prosperous yeares and daies in this life, and in the end eternall life with eternall ioyes, I humbly take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your worships most bounden to commaund</hi> Francis Bradley.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>