<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right VVorshipfull my much honoured Patron, Sir NICHOLAS SAVNDERSON of Filingham, Linc. Knight and Baronet.</title>
           <author>Saunderson, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116623_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11454</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21705</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116623</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right VVorshipfull my much honoured Patron, Sir NICHOLAS SAVNDERSON of Filingham, Linc. Knight and Baronet.</title>
                 <author>Saunderson, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ten sermons : preached I. Ad clerum. 3. II. Ad magistratum. 3. III. Ad populum. 4. By Robert Saunderson Bachellor in Diuinitie, sometimes fellow of Lincolne Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Sanderson, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Young (Junius), Robert</publisher>
                    <distributor>Dawlman (Dolman), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 75, 78-139, 5, 147-470 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="78"/>
   <pb facs="78"/>
   <head>To the Right VVorshipfull my much honoured Patron, Sir NICHOLAS SAVNDERSON of <hi>Filingham, Linc.</hi> Knight and Baronet.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing first, vpon <hi>slow</hi> deliberation, resolued to <hi>publish</hi> these three Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons: my next resolution came on more <hi>readily,</hi> to <hi>present</hi> them to you. For which there was no need I should deliberate long: the consideration both of the <hi>Author</hi> and <hi>Argument</hi> prompting mee thereunto. For <hi>my selfe</hi> first; As you haue abundantly witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed vnto the world your <hi>good affection</hi> to mee, both by sundry other <hi>courtesies,</hi> and especially in being the chiefest meanes, (vnder the good Prouidence of God) by your free collation of a <hi>Benefice</hi> vpon me, of draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me from the Vniuersitie into these parts, where I am now settled: so I haue beene euer couetous of some faire opportunity, to witnesse vnto the world my <hi>thankfull acknowledgement</hi> of your kinde fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours;
<pb facs="79"/>
whereof▪ for want of better meanes I desire this <hi>Dedication</hi> maybe some expression. And then for the <hi>Argument;</hi> I knew none more fit to Patronage a Theame of <hi>Iustice,</hi> than your selfe: whom God hath endowed with strong abilities▪ many wayes, of <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, Affections, Courage, Elocution, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>trie</hi> together with outward <hi>Meanes</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> in a gracious measure, and aboue many of your fellowes in the same office; to doe <hi>Him,</hi> and his <hi>Annointed,</hi> and their <hi>People,</hi> good seruice, in aduancing the course of <hi>publike Iustice,</hi> in the Countrie where you liue. In both which regards, as I presume these <hi>my</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations concerning <hi>Iustice</hi> will not come altogether vnwelcome: so I am confident, that the <hi>manner</hi> of handling vsed therein, in taxing the <hi>Abuses</hi> with such <hi>Freedome,</hi> as (it may be) some will not rellish, will yet be by so much more acceptable to you, by how much more <hi>freely</hi> your owne <hi>heart,</hi> when you reade of them, shall witnesse your owne <hi>freedome</hi> from them. In which confidence, with all due respect. I commend these <hi>Sermons</hi> into your hands; and with my faithfullest deuotions, your <hi>selfe,</hi> and your <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Lady,</hi> and whole <hi>family</hi> into the hands of <hi>God:</hi> who alone is able hath to <hi>continue</hi> and <hi>multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply</hi> his <hi>blessings</hi> vpon you in the meane time, and in the end to <hi>crowne</hi> his owne <hi>graces</hi> in you with <hi>glory.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the Lord, ROB. SAVNDERSON.</signed>
      <dateline>Booth by Paynell Line, <date>1. <hi>Mar.</hi> 1626.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>