<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIP∣FVLL SIR EDVVARD Winckfield Knight.</title>
           <author>C., A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116495_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18771</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5262</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116495</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIP∣FVLL SIR EDVVARD Winckfield Knight.</title>
                 <author>C., A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Beawtie dishonoured vvritten vnder the title of Shores wife : Chascun se plaist ou il se trouue mieux</title>
                 <author>Chute, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 <publisher>Windet, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>54 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FVLL SIR EDVVARD Winckfield Knight.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>YR since such is the industrious nature of our owne Poetes, as though Italie sleepes in the charme of a sweet Hierusaleme, and France waxes proud in the weeke labours of her toyling-mused <hi>Bartas</hi> (the first as conceiptiuely Allegoricall, as the other is labour some significant) yet our owne clyme, challendging vnto her selfe hardly a second esteeme, to the first: and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing produced such witty, &amp; so happy conceiptes, as wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering in the secresie of some passionate Elegies, blush at their owne apparance: How might I be esteemed guiltie of myne owne disgrace, that daring to make myselfe priuie to the knowledge thereof, should not sticke, to argue my selfe improuidēt, in not bequeathing to silence the first in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention of my beginning Muse? not first to the last, nor better to the worst, of many, that conceiuyng lower opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of their owne merite, then the merite might thincke worthely due vnto herselfe, remaine content with that prayse, which in her guist inuieth the pure excellencie of the deseruer: But young conceiptes, as they are young: are withall seeking increase of them selues, and therefore choose what they hold most aunswerable to such desires: And will lesse stand on desiring pardon after offence, then
<pb facs="3"/>
be carefull at all not to haue offended: Wherein if I note myne owne fault, I craue that pardon, which those will not denie, that respect the nature of confession. And therefore humbly desiring your selfe would be pleased, to hold excuse, to be as great an Argumēt of your own hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable disposition as it might be esteemed a passing stayne to myne infant labours: I wish as many worthy applauses may attend your owne sweet inuentions, as the worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of them selues deserue, and I haue euer desired.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your worships most bounden. A. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>