<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS MOST SACRED MAIESTIE.</title>
           <author>Brent, Nathanael</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116697_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11516</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21762</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116697</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS MOST SACRED MAIESTIE.</title>
                 <author>Brent, Nathanael</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of the Councel of Trent : Conteining eight bookes. In which (besides the ordinarie actes of the Councell) are declared many notable occurrences, which happened in Christendome, during the space of fourtie yeeres and more. And, particularly, the practises of the Court of Rome, to hinder the reformation of their errors, and to maintaine their greatnesse. Written in Italian by Pietro Soaue Polano, and faithfully translated into English by Nathanael Brent</title>
                 <author>Sarpi, Paolo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 <publisher>Bill, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, Bonham</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 881, that is 879, 17 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HIS MOST SACRED MAIESTIE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Offer to your MAIESTIES view the truest and most iudicious Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall Historie, that either mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne times, or any antiquitie hath afforded to the world; impaired (I confesse) in beautie, as being trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported out of the naturall lustre both of stile and phrase, by a rude and vnskilfull Translator, but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing altered in the trueth and sincerity of the matter, which it handleth.</p>
   <p>The Author, a stranger to these parts, conuersant onely where the Gospell cannot be truely preached, was moued to write it, as for the common good of all Christendome, so par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in contemplation of your Maiesties seruice. For as you hold the highest place amongst all Kings and Princes, and are Gods greatest Lieutenant vnder the whole cope of heauen, so your admirable perfections, of Wisdome, Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Iustice, and Religion (with which your royall breast is inriched beyond all comparison to bee made with any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) cast foorth their bright shining rayes into all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treis and quarters of the world, and rouse vp the endeauors of the worthiest, euen in places the farthest remote, to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the building vp, or repairing of Gods Church, so
<pb facs="3"/>
farre as the tyranny of Antichrist, vnder which they liue, and the safetie of their liues, which nature bindes them to preserue, doth giue them leaue. In which number, is the Author of this present Treatise. The end and scope whereof being the glory of <hi>God,</hi> by discouery of those practises, which, for many yeeres, haue beene concealed by the enemies of CHRIST, the aduancement of true pietie and Religion, I know not to whom it may be addressed more iustly, then to the greatest Maiesty vpon the whole surface of the earth, and the chiefest <hi>Defender</hi> of the true faith amongst vs.</p>
   <p>And surely if euer any booke (except onely the Booke of God) did deserue the protection of so excellent a Patron, it is this Historie of the Councell of <hi>Trent.</hi> For, of all the things in the world, Religion is of the greatest consequence, and, in Religion, Ecumenicall Councels (next after the holy Writ) haue euer caried the greatest sway; which being true, and guided by the <hi>holy Ghost,</hi> haue beene causes of infinite blessings, but being pretended onely, and gouerned by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane policies and Arte, haue brought foorth as many mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes and afflictions to the Church of God.</p>
   <p>Now in this of <hi>Trent</hi> it is plainely discouered, that the <hi>Bishops</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> (of whom eight liued and died, during the time of the Synode and treatie thereof) in stead of being CHRISTS holy <hi>Ʋicars,</hi> as they pretend, haue beene the greatest, and most pernicious <hi>quackesaluing iuglers</hi> that euer the earth did beare.</p>
   <p>It would be infinite to relate the Stratagems they vsed to diuert it, before it began; their postings to and fro, to hinder the proposing of those things which they thought would di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minish their profit, or pull downe their pride; their policies, to enthrall the Prelates and Diuines, by hopes and feares; their diligence in sending their adherents to <hi>Trent,</hi> and so, by procuring a <hi>maior</hi> part of voices, to make themselues the absolute Lords of all the determinations that passed. By which deuices that which was desired by godly men, as the onely remedy against all the errors in manners and doctrine, both in Church and Common-wealth, and especially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the greatest enormities of the Popes themselues, hath
<pb facs="3"/>
beene wrested to a quite contrary vse, to weaken the lawfull rights of Kings and Princes, to peruert the doctrine and Hierarchie of the Church of GOD, and to lift vp the Papacy to an vnsufferable height of pride. This is that holy and great Synod, of which the Romanists doe boast themselues so much.</p>
   <p>And indeed euery one of any meane capacitie may easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know, that many controuerted points betweene them and the true Professors, necessary (as they maintaine) for the sauing of mens soules, had neuer any colourable establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but this; which insensibly creeping in by the superstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the vulgar, or secretly set on foote by those that were ambitious and couetous, or (at the best) blindly zealous, haue alwaies beene opposed by the Orthodox, euen pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely, vntill the malitious industry of the greater part, put to silence (though neuer quite ouercame) the paucitie of the better. So that their vanting of the Antiquitie of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and of the infancie of ours, is vaine and idle.</p>
   <p>And if they will glory (as vsually they doe) of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersalitie of their doctrine, because it was established (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sooth) by <hi>the holy Ecumenicall Councell of Trent,</hi> as they terme it, none can better iudge then your MAIESTY how factious and how vnlawfull that assembly was, and, by this Historie, the whole world may vnderstand the weaknesse of that foundation.</p>
   <p>The Almightie blesse your MAIESTIE with length of daies, strength of bodie, loyaltie of your people, and with all imaginable happinesse in your most Royall Progenie, and in swaying the Scepter of your Dominions.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Sacred Maiesties most humble, and most faithfully deuoted Subiect,
NATHANAEL BRENT.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>