<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY SACRED SOVERAIGNE, CHARLES, KING OF GREAT BRITAINE, FRANCE, and IRELAND, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Reynolds, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116165_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10668</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20944</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116165</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY SACRED SOVERAIGNE, CHARLES, KING OF GREAT BRITAINE, FRANCE, and IRELAND, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Reynolds, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The triumphs of Gods revenge against the crying and execrable sinne of (willfull and premeditated) murther : VVith his miraculous discoveries, and severe punishments thereof. In thirtie severall tragicall histories (digested into sixe bookes) committed in divers countries beyond the seas, never published, or imprinted in any other language. Histories which containe great varietie of mournfull and memorable accidents ... With a table of all the severall letters and challenges, contained in the whole sixe bookes. Written by Iohn Reynolds</title>
                 <author>Reynolds, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lee, William 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lee, William 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 75, 3, 81-181, 7, 187-260, 259-294, that is 293, 7, 303-414, 10, 425-527, 9, 337-404, 409-464 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO MY SACRED SOVERAIGNE, CHARLES, KING OF GREAT BRITAINE, FRANCE, and IRELAND, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S Rivers, though in their passing they fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to many neighbour Currents yet finally emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty themselves into the Sea, so let these my poore Labours (though formerly Dedicated to divers Illustrious Peeres of this your Realme) bee suffered at last to terminate in the <hi>Ocean</hi> of your Princely <hi>Greatnesse</hi> and <hi>Goodnesse,</hi> whereinto all vertuous endeavours (as so many lines in their Centre) desire to be united.</p>
   <p>What private respests might challenge of me towards their Honors, the same towards your <hi>Majesty</hi> will claime the publicke Bond of Common Allegiance, whereby I am more eminently, and more universally obliged. I am not so over<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> weening of my weake Endeavours, as to thinke them wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb facs="4"/>
of your <hi>Majesties</hi> view, much lesse able to adde any thing to your Royall Uertues; Rivers adde nothing to the Maine, yet thither they naturally send the Tribute of their Streames; and if my Loyaltie reach me to doe the like, it will not (I hope) be conceived as done out of an opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Merit, but onely out of a desire to discharge the Duty of a Subject to your <hi>Majestie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And I am the rather imboldned to this Confidence, because I have formerly adventured the like, when to your Princely View, being then the Second Hope of this Kingdome, I (about eleven yeares since) presented a Translation of a Worke of <hi>Monsieur de Refuges,</hi> intituled <hi>A Treatise of the Court;</hi> the Gratious and Undeserved Acceptance whereof, if it hath inspired me with farther Courage, to present You (now advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to a greater State) with a greater Increase of mine owne Labour, your <hi>Majestie</hi> will not (I hope) condemne me of groundlesse Presumption.</p>
   <p>The former three Bookes had the Honour and Happinesse to bee perused by the Iudicious Eye of <hi>King IAMES,</hi> your Renowned Father, (of happy Memory) In whose incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Iudgement they failed not of Approbation, though De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to Inferiour Names; the more am I now incouraged to Inscribe and Intitle the whole Sixe to your Sacred <hi>Majesty,</hi> as being no lesse Heire of <hi>His</hi> Uertues, then of <hi>His</hi> Crowne and Dignitie.</p>
   <p>And one thing more (arising from the Consideration of the Subject it selfe) made me thinke it a Present not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unworthy of your Regall Estate; for the Contents of it being the Execution of <hi>Iustice,</hi> upon the unnaturall Sinne of <hi>Murther,</hi> where can it bee more fitly addressed, then to the Great Patron of <hi>Iustice</hi> among us (God's immediate Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent) by whose Sword (as the Minister of Heaven) such
<pb facs="4"/>
odious Crimes are to bee chastised, and Innocent Bloud justly expiated with Guilty.</p>
   <p>And it may more fitly sute with your <hi>Majesty,</hi> who as you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell in the carefull Administration of <hi>Iustice</hi> upon all Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, so especially upon those (most hainous of all others) the Violaters of Gods sacred Image, in the perpetration of wilfull <hi>Murther,</hi> towards whom <hi>Clemencie</hi> even changeth her na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and becomes <hi>Cruelty</hi> to the <hi>Weal-publicke.</hi> Never had any Land lesse cause to complaine of too much Indulgencie this way, then ours, as may well appeare, both by the rarenesse of such Occurrences in your Kingdome, and the severe vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of them, whensoever they happen, or by whom, or how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever performed.</p>
   <p>These <hi>Histories</hi> therefore, which may serve as a Looking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glasse to all Nations, shall to these of Yours be a speciall Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament and Mirrour of their felicity, and set forth and publish Your Praise, in the peaceable and quiet Government of your People, whose Climate (seldome or never) affords such <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedies;</hi> nor will doe, whiles Your Christian resolution shall continue to prevent them in the Spring, and to punish the ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter degrees of Bloudinesse with due retaliation. The great <hi>Author</hi> of <hi>Iustice</hi> (who is <hi>Goodnesse</hi> and <hi>Iustice</hi> it selfe) long preserve your <hi>Majesty</hi> to Vs, and the Happinesse Wee enjoy in your Sacred Person, so neere resembling Him whose Authority and Image You beare. So prayeth</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your <hi>Majesties</hi> most humbly devoted in all Dutifull Allegiance,
IOHN REYNOLDS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>