<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The preface to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1560</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116544_Bo1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01297</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11420</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116544</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The preface to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Antiprognosticon that is to saye, an inuectiue agaynst the vayne and vnprofitable predictions of the astrologians as Nostrodame, [et] c. Translated out of Latine into Englishe. Whervnto is added by the author a shorte treatise in Englyshe, as well for the vtter subuersion of that fained arte, as also for the better vnderstandynge of the common people, vnto whom the fyrst labour seemeth not sufficient</title>
                 <author>Fulke, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Sutton, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1560</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="27"/>
   <head>The preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsyderyng with my selfe, (gentyl reader) that so manyno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table workmen at thys tyme, hathe by theyr cunning, &amp; also by their diligēt laboure, haue layde the foundation of a moste woorthy buildynge: &amp; also brought the same a good waye aboue the grounde, intendynge by gods helpe not onely to finishe the playne worke thereof, but also to garnishe it with suche ornamentes as myghte beseeme so princely a palayce: I thoughte it not my parte for the good affection that I heart to the woorke, to stande altogyther ydell, yf by any meanes I myghte be profytable in the same. And walkynge about to see the compasse and fasshion of it, I perceyued that the great stones whiche pertayned to the structure were suche as neither by my strengthe I was able to lyste theym, nor
<pb facs="28"/>
yet by my cunnyng in that kynd of mas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> ry to place and ioyne theim: but as for he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng or fashionyng them, I sawe it was so farre aboue my knowledge and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standyng, that I dyd not ones applye my selfe to haue any medlynge with them. At the last when I had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ewed all other thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges sufficiently, I espied a lyttle heape of rubbyshe whyche not only hyndered them that wente to and fro o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>er it, in specdynge their worke, but also semed to be no small deformitie to the leuelled playnesse of the statte forme, whereon the buyldyng should stande, I myghte see also that some of the master masons them selues had taken pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in remouynge the same vnprofytable Chaos: which caused me to thynke, that I coulde not be better occupied then to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney the same quight out of the way, that it shoulde neyther be a lette nor an yll sight, in the procedyng of so necessary busynes. Wherefore I prepared and made for my selfe as it were a lyttell wicker baskette, whiche I myght easily beare, so cary away this hyndryng heape, where it shalbe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused and utterly dispersed abroade. And although the substance of my bas kette be symple and weake, yet it is good enoughe to cary tubb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>he and suche lyght stuffe as
<pb facs="28"/>
I put therin. But as soone as I beganne to tourne vp the vpper parte therof, I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstode, that because it had lyenge longe compacte togyther, thers was bredde in it a great numbre of toades and snakes that beganne to hysse and spewe out theyr poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son agaynst me, bycause I diseased theim of their nesle and barrborowe. But God be thanked I come not naked among them, I haue an armoure called <hi>Veritas,</hi> that is able to withstande the malice euen of dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons, and crocodiles. Som men perchāce wolde meruayle why I woulde not strike <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>eim, that so furiousely haue gone about to stynge me. In deede I haue prepared al redy moderate defence, but I staye vppon certayne dóubtes that are these:</p>
   <p>Fyrst, whether it be the poynte of al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned manne to rayle or no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
   </p>
   <p>Secondely, whether the conclusion in <hi>Syllogismo litigiolo</hi> bee good or no?</p>
   <p>And thirdly whether there be a kynde of argument called <hi>Syllogismus conuciato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> or no? these doubtes resolued I wold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> procede. As for Uaughan I haue nothing to dooe with hym, but to wysshe hym his tyghte wyttes and a good tongue.</p>
   <p>I haue taken vpō me to dissolue this masse at astrologie, and that by goddes helpe I
<pb facs="29"/>
wyll doo to the vttermoste of my power, so that my contention is agaynst no mā. But my labour is to remoue this obstacle out of good menues waies, and if any yll men hereafter exercise their malyce vpon me, I must nedes say as Socrates sayde: Though an asse spurne agaynst me, I wil not go to lawe with hym. Therefore they that haue delyte in railyng, let them rayle and spare not: They that haue pleasure in scoffyng, lette theim scoffe and flowte tyll they haue proued theym selues cōmen pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rasites and sycophantes in so dooynge, I wyll not ones be moued with suche vnho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neste meanes. But yf any man shall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde any probable argument to mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne this cause, I wyll doo the best I can to answer it, and if I be not able (as I haue always offered) I wyll yelde vnto hym. Wherefore gentyll reader, if thou cansts fynde thy selfe eased with any of these two small trauayles, I haue my request.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>