<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST RE∣VEREND FATHER IN GOD, WILLIAM L. ARCHBISHOP OF CANTERBVRY, Primate of all England and Me∣tropolitane, Chauncellor of the Vni∣versitie of Oxford, and one of his Majesties most Hon: Privy Counsell.</title>
           <author>Saunderson, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116631_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11460</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21710</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116631</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST RE∣VEREND FATHER IN GOD, WILLIAM L. ARCHBISHOP OF CANTERBVRY, Primate of all England and Me∣tropolitane, Chauncellor of the Vni∣versitie of Oxford, and one of his Majesties most Hon: Privy Counsell.</title>
                 <author>Saunderson, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tvvo sermons : the former, concerning the right use of Christian liberty, preached at S. Pauls Crosse London. May 6. The later, concerning the perswasion of conscience, preached at a metropoliticall visitation at Grantham Lincoln: Aug. 22. 1634. By Robert Saunderson chaplaine to his Maiestie</title>
                 <author>Sanderson, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <distributor>Dawlman (Dolman), Robert</distributor>
                            <distributor>Fawne, Luke</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 98, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE MOST RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEREND FATHER IN GOD, WILLIAM L. ARCHBISHOP OF CANTERBVRY, Primate of</hi> all England <hi>and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitane, Chauncellor of the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versitie of</hi> Oxford, <hi>and one of his Majesties most Hon:</hi> Privy Counsell.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have been ever wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, (most Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in God) as at all other times upon just occasion▪ so especially when cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to preach at any publique meeting of the Clergy, to vindicate the <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Rites</hi> established in <hi>the Church of England,</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
from the unjust aspersions, which in this last age have beene, and still are, cast thereon by ill affected spirits, with a great deals more noyse then there is cause. Not any way to <hi>comply</hi> (farther then duty and reason require) with the <hi>times;</hi> (which is the ready objection a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this course in every mouth: God pardon their <hi>uncharitablenesse</hi> and <hi>unrighteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi> who so mis-judge!) but out of an earnest, and as I hope sinc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re, <hi>desire</hi> of advancing the peace of this flourishing <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State:</hi> wishing unfainedly, that all wee who live in the visible communion of the same body as <hi>bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> might also as <hi>brethren</hi> (so far as were possible) <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 15. 6.</note>
      <hi>With one mind and one mouth glorify God even the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ.</hi> It was no other then this very <hi>desire,</hi> that gave these two Seri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s their first <hi>life;</hi> nor is it any other thing now that bringeth them into farther <hi>light,</hi> then the <hi>possibility,</hi> if not rather <hi>hope,</hi> of prod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cing some good effect that way: For as it is at all times in the <hi>hand</hi> of God, so is it many times his good <hi>pleasure</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, to blesse well-meant (though weake) endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, far beyond the proportion of their wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th.
<pb facs="3"/>
I know there are some <note n="b" place="margin">1 Thes. 5. 14.</note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> and <note n="c" place="margin">Tit. 1. 10.</note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, men that will not be brought into <hi>order</hi> by any meanes, nor satisfied with any <hi>reason,</hi> so per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versely minded are they, and so stiffened in their resolutiōs: who albeit they deserve very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle regard other wise, yet euen in respect of them also it is requisite the truth in these points should be sometimes opened; either to <note n="d" place="margin">Tit. 1. 11.</note>
      <hi>stoppe their mouthes</hi> from clamouring, if it may be, or at leastwise (if they will needs be doing) to render their obstinacy the more <hi>inexcusable.</hi> But it is principally requisite for those mens sakes, and in compassion to their soules, whose honest <hi>sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity</hi> hath been abused, and their weake <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences</hi> mis-guided, by such <hi>Incendiaties,</hi> that they may be better <hi>informed:</hi> and partly also for the confirmation of those that are <hi>regular,</hi> that they may continue in their right minds, and not suffer themselves to be wrested out of their good beleef by the cunning engines of those that are chiefe <hi>factours</hi> for the <hi>faction.</hi> To any of which ends, if (by Gods good blessing) these my slender labours shall lend the least furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, it shall nothing repent mee to have pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished them. But this is all I am able to say for
<pb facs="4"/>
them onwards: first, for the <hi>arguments,</hi> that I made choice to entreat of such as to mee seemed very <hi>usefull</hi> for these licencious times, wherein too too many plead <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Conscience,</hi> in barre to <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Obedience:</hi> and then for <hi>the manner of handling</hi> the same, that I gave all diligence to deliver my selfe in the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>truth</hi> and of <hi>meeknesse;</hi> that is to say, with all cleare <hi>evidence</hi> of reason, but without all either <hi>gall</hi> of bitternesse, or <hi>leaven</hi> of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality. However such as they are, I hubly present them to the service of <hi>God</hi> &amp; his <hi>Church,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Graces protection: as unto whom, by a double title they most properly belong. First, for that they were both preached by <hi>appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> from your Grace: the former, in <hi>the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> when you were <hi>L: Bishop of London;</hi> the other, in <hi>the Country,</hi> at your late <hi>Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticall Visitation:</hi> and to what hand should they rather returne, then to that that first occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioned their being? As also, for that they tend to the suppressing of <hi>Novelties,</hi> and to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> (of both which you are most zealous) in that Church, wherein (under <hi>God</hi> and <hi>the King)</hi> you worthily sit at
<pb facs="4"/>
the sterne. The God of heaven <hi>multiply</hi> his blessings upon you; <hi>prosper</hi> the affaires of his Church in your hands, that <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> may flourish therein more and more; and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member</hi> you according to all the good deeds you either have already done, or entend farther to doe for his house, and for the prosperity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. So prayeth</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces in all humble service, ROBERT SAUNDERSON.</signed>
      <dateline>Boothby Paynell <hi>Linc.</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>4. Febr. 1634.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>