<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116329_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11253</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21514</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116329</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Iesuites play at Lyons in France : as it was there presented. Both to the amazement of the beholders, and the destruction of the actors, in August last past. Credibly informed by a factors letter (who was an eye witnesse) to his right worshipful maister in London</title>
                 <author>R. S.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Butter, Nathaniel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 25, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E who euer hath seene rebellions discouered, he that hath knowne that Traitors liue like Moles, who worke vnseene till they be thrown vp to their deaths▪ and liue abroad like Flyes who sucke the sweete of others, yet infect them, shall find by this discourse that Religion is made the Target to defend Treason: Ambition, the Originall, and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion the end. Yet for thy further satisfaction (Reader) that this discourse &amp; euery particuler relation therein, may haue credit in thy iudgement, know, that there is nothing therein mentioned, but is to be approued by diuers Merchants and men of credite, now resident in this Citty, and that in reading thereof, thou maist wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to thy selfe, that this wonder and stroke of hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen vpon them, is reuealed and sent vnto thee as a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning peece shot off, to admonish thee that thou fall not into the presumption into which these Iesuits and their Desciples run headlong. I haue as in a map or Dutth Lanskip, shewed thee a Module in half an howers rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, of what held them two dayes in action: as the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the place where they played, the forme of their representing heauen and hell, the dignitie wherein the Actors sat, the causes wherevpon they prepared this iudgement: namely, Ambition (whose end is alwaies as theirs was, destruction) In any part of which, if thou beest eyther satisfied or admonished, my paines were a pleasure vnto mee.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewel</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>