<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Iohn̄ More to the crysten sten reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1533</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116675_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01828</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11966</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116675</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Iohn̄ More to the crysten sten reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The legacye or embassate of the great emperour of Inde prester Ioh⁻n, vnto Emanuell kynge of Portyngale, in the yere of our lorde M. v.C.xiii. Of the fayth of the Indyans, ceremonyes, relygyons [&amp;] c. Of the patryarche [and] his offyce. Of the realme, state, power, maiesty, and order of the courte of prester Ioh⁻n</title>
                 <author>Góis, Damião de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Rastell, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1533</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>26, that is 30 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="2" facs="2"/>
   <head>Iohn̄ More to the crysten sten reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as myche as euery mā natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is desyrous to here new thinges and straunge (as both authours te<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>styfye, and expery<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence proueth) all though there were none other com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>modyte therof then the neweltye: I thought yt a thynge worthe the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, to translate this lyttell worke, late happed in my hande through the helpe of a specyall familyar frende of myne / syns surely I thought it shuld be a worke not onely new, trew, and plesaunt to the reader, but also for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> knowlege of sundrye thynges therin conteyned very profytable and neces<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sary. For in this lytle treatyce be con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyned, the state, the fayth, the rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyon, the ceremonyes, the Patry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arche wyth his offyce, the powre, the lawes of the lande and empyre of pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stre Iohn̄, besydes his royall maiestie
<pb facs="3"/>
and order of his courte. All whyche thynges were rehersed vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and pusaunt prynce Emanuell kynge of Portyngale, by the mouth of one Mathew, sent frō themperour of Inde prester Iohn̄, vnto the forna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med Emanuel, in the yere of our lord M.v. hundred .xiii. And all though of this prester Iohn̄ syr Iohn̄ Maū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defeld knyght, in a worke y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he made of the dyscrypcyon of coūtrees, som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what hath made mencyon: yet this embassatour that came from thens to the kynge of Portyngale, as he to whome euery thynge perteynyng ey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther to the religyon and fayth of that people, or to the polytyque order of that lande, was myche more perfyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowen, yt is no meruayle though he myche more perfytely descrybe theym, namely to that prynce, whych from poynte to poynte was curyouse to enquyre. This empyre of prester Iohn̄ ys reputed as great a maygne countre in a maner (yf yt be not gret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter) as all the remanaunt that nowe remayneth christened, except the new founden landes, that haue ben byco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="3" facs="3"/>
chrystened wythin few yeres of late. And therfore yt greatly may, &amp; of reason greatly ought to reioyce all good chrystē people, to perceyue that though there are dyuerse thynges wherein they and we dyffere in rytes lawes, customes, and ceremonyes: yet in all other thynges necessary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perteynynge as well to the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of fayth and relygyon, as all other vertues morall, they so farre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth accorde and agre wyth these cri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sten nacyons of ours, and wyth the catholyque doctryne of the chyrche, that yt may well appere euen by that thynge alone, that the spyryte of god hath wrought and worketh this full agrement &amp; consent, in so many thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges necessary to saluacyon, thorowe so many great countreys and regyōs as ours are and theyres both, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> tone by so longe space hauynge so lytle ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cesse vnto the tother, that of many ye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res tyl nowe very late, we coulde not wel tell whyther they were well criste<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned or not. Howe be yt yet appereth well nowe by many thynges, not in this boke onely, but in those letters
<pb facs="4"/>
also, whyche now very late the empe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rour of that lande that nowe is, &amp; son vnto him that sent thembassatour vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the kynge Emanuell, dyd send not onely to the noble kynge of Portyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gale that now is, sonne vnto the said noble kynge Emanuell, but also to the popes holynesse that now is Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that name the .vii. by his em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bassatour, wyth his obedyence after the maner of other chrysten prynces: by this treatyce and those letters yt doth I saye well appere, that the said emperour and all the chyrche, that ys to wytte all the chrysten people of that empyre, be of the same fayth that we be. And in this treatyse ye also se, that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> great thynges whych haue ben byfore this tymes establyshed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynst heretyques by generall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayles of olde, agaynst whych old de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>termynacyons these new heretyques make newe besynesse nowe, the selfe same thynges haue the chrysten peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of that great chrysten empyre frō the tyme of theyre fyrste cōuersyon, whych was forthwyth vpon the deth of Chryste, cōtynually byleued and
<pb n="4" facs="4"/>
euer obserued styll. So y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> this poynt is able alone yf yt be pondered as yt is worthy, eyther to tourne and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert or putte to sylence for shame, all the besye bretherne that wolde make men so madde, as to wene that those thynges were new deuysed and late brought vppe here by prestes / whych thynges theym selfe se well ynough (though they dyssymyle and say nay) in the bokes of old holy sayntes, and whych thynges are now well knowē to haue ben this .xv. hundred yere by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leued and vsed thorough that great empyre as great a people as oures, into whyche our prestes as farre as men can tell of, neuer came hense to teache them. But syth that we begyn nowe eache to heare more of other, I pray god as there is in bothe many thynges very good, and some thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that myght be better: eche peple may lerne &amp; take of other those thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that be good, and lette the badde go by. And that we may make bothe so but one chyrche mylytant here in erth, that we may both be partes of one gloryouse chyrche, that euer shall be tryumphaunt in heuen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>