<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right honorabel, worshipfull, gentel, and learned Readers, whosoeuer; that are bothe trew fauorits of poetry, and of right ancient Heroicke Hexameters.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116380_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02935</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13076</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116380</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right honorabel, worshipfull, gentel, and learned Readers, whosoeuer; that are bothe trew fauorits of poetry, and of right ancient Heroicke Hexameters.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first booke of the preseruation of King Henry the vij. when he was but Earle of Richmond, grandfather to the Queenes maiesty : compiled in English rythmicall hexameters</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 <publisher>Bradock, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Broome (Brome), Joan.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Potter, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>104 pages, oblong 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right honorabel, worshipfull, gentel, <hi>and learned Readers, whosoeuer; that are</hi> bothe trew fauorits of poetry, and of <hi>right ancient Heroicke Hexameters.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight honored, worshipfull, and gentell Reader, these Hexame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Pentameters in Englishe, are misliked of many, because they are not yet come to their full perfection: and specially of some, that are accounted and knowne to be Doctors and singular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly well learned and great Linguistes: but especially of the plaine Rythmer, that scarce knowes the footed quantitie or metricall scanning thereof; much lesse to reade them with a grace according to the same. But for him, I say thus; <hi>Scientia nullum habet inimicum, praeter ignorantem.</hi> Whose bookes are stuft with lines of prose, with a rythme in the end; which euery
<pb facs="3"/> fidler, or piper, can make vpon a theame giuen. Neuerthelesse, I confesse and acknowledge that we haue many excellent and singular good Poets in this our age, as Maister <hi>Spencer,</hi> that was, Maister <hi>Gowlding,</hi> Doctor <hi>Phayer,</hi> Maister <hi>Harrington, Daniell,</hi> and diuers others whom I reuerence in that kinde of prose-rythme: wherein <hi>Spencer</hi> (without offence spoken) hath surpassed them all. I would to God they had done so well in trew Hexameters: for they had then beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified our language. For the <hi>Greekes</hi> and <hi>Latines</hi> did in a manner abolish quite that kinde of rythme-prose: And why should not we doe the like in Englishe? But the ignorant and aduerse part will say, our speach is not copious enough: But I say that it is: and besides it would be the more inriched, adorned, and more eloquent, if they would make triall thereof, or could compose them artificially and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to delight the Readers, to resound with a grace in their eares. <hi>Nam ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil difficile volenti.</hi> But this is the trew cause why they doe not so; <hi>Hoc opus, hic labor est:</hi> which the chiefe Doctors and best learned of them all, cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny;
<pb facs="3"/> And perhappes some of the best of them, that are curious carpers and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenders of this trew metrified verse, though skilfull in other arts, cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally compose the like as <hi>Fraunce</hi> did; who obserued a better Prosodia then <hi>Stani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurst.</hi> For <hi>Tully</hi> was not so good a Poetician as he was an Orator. God bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his gifts seuerally, and more bountifully on some then on others. For <hi>Homer</hi> in Greeke, and <hi>Virgill</hi> in Latine, surpassed all that euer were before or since, in trew footed Hexameters; but not in prose. Neither were <hi>Homer</hi> and <hi>Virgill</hi> the first that versifyed in their naturall language: But others did attempt to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etize afore them, in the like verse; or else in truth I suppose they could not haue done so well. Euery thing hath a beginning, which at first cannot be made so per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. Those verses which <hi>Ennius</hi> made, before <hi>Virgill</hi> made any, were not so well liked: as for example; <hi>Vnus homo nobis cunctando restituit rem:</hi> Yet <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gill</hi> most commonly had his booke about him. Therefore I reuerence <hi>Stanihurst;</hi> who being but an Irish man, did first attempt to translate those foure bookes of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neados,</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/> which (if he be liuing) I desire him to refile them ouer againe; and thus haue written in verse:
<q>
         <l>If the Poet <hi>Stanihurst</hi> yet liue and feedeth on ay-er,</l>
         <l>I do request him (as one that wisheth a grace to the meter)</l>
         <l>With wordes significant to refile and finely to polishe</l>
         <l>Those fower <hi>Aenëis,</hi> that he late translated in English.</l>
         <l>I doe the man reuerence, as a fine, as an exquisit Author:</l>
         <l>For that he first did atempt, to translate verse as a Doctor.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>For at the first, Maister <hi>Askam</hi> had much ado to make two or three verses in English: but now euery scholler can make some. What language so hard, harsh, or barbarous, that time and art will not amend? As I haue written in an other place, thus;
<q>
         <pb facs="4"/>
         <l>Naught can at once be begonne, or present made, to be perfect.</l>
         <l>By trauel, all hard thinges are brought to singular effect.</l>
         <l>Yet that <hi>Apelles</hi> could <hi>Cytheraeas</hi> beawty depolish;</l>
         <l>Had not he time to delyne, hir picture finely to finnysh?</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>This trew kinde of Hexametred and Pentametred verse, well bring vnto vs foure commodities. First it will enrich our speach with good and significant wordes: Secondly it will bring a delight and pleasure to the skilfull Reader, when he seeth them formally compyled: And thirdly it will incourage and learne the good &amp; godly Students, that affect Poetry, and are naturally enclyned therunto, to make the like: Fourthly it will direct a trew Idioma, and will teach trew Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thography. For as gould surpasseth leade: so the Hexameters surpasse rythme prose. And as concerning the same, this haue I written:
<q>
         <pb facs="5"/>
         <l>As yelo gould purified doth surmount euery mettell:</l>
         <l>So fine verse metrifyed, this rythme-prose greatly doth excell.</l>
         <l>With wordes significant, such rurall rythmery confound,</l>
         <l>And metricall verses with a new rythme lawraly compound.</l>
         <l>For sily <hi>Muse</hi> feare not: since euery paltery Rythmor</l>
         <l>With wordes vnmetrifyed would seeme to be counted a Doctor:</l>
         <l>Whose workes seeme to be good, representing <hi>Tantalus</hi> appels,</l>
         <l>Which did apeare to be gold; but toucht were, turned in ashes.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>And in another place.</p>
   <q>
      <l>Clowde not your Orient fyne skyll, with dregges of a drowzy</l>
      <l>Conterfaited prose: This Romane verse hath a glory.</l>
      <l>As redolent Gilyflowers perfumes a delight to the senses;</l>
      <l>Mens memories to refresh: So scanning Rythmery verses</l>
      <l>Bringes a delight to the mindes, &amp;c.</l>
   </q>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <p>For these rybaud and baudy Poets be but the diuels agents, and are to be detes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; but the vertuous and godly Poets are to be both reuerenced and regarded: as I haue here written;
<q>
         <l>As <hi>domiport</hi> slug-y snayle, his passage plainly to disclose,</l>
         <l>Leaueth a print as he goes, but a shining slyme to no purpose:</l>
         <l>So doth a bawdy Poet (his brainesicke folly to publish)</l>
         <l>Write amorous madrigals; some lewd loue-toy to recognise.</l>
         <l>Aime at a trew Period, Christ Iesus: flee from al euil:</l>
         <l>Roaue not aside to detract his praise: learne rightly to leauell.</l>
         <l>VVits misabus'd will apeare as a goulden ring in a swines snowte.</l>
         <l>Gods worde such reprobate lewde wits doth worthily confute.</l>
         <l>Shew me the tree by the fruite: so saith Saint <hi>Luke</hi> that Euangel,</l>
         <l>Do men gather grapes of thornes, or fygges of a thystel?<note place="margin">Saint Luke, ca. 6. verse. 45.</note>
         </l>
         <pb facs="6"/>
         <l>
            <note place="margin">Saint Mathew ca. 13. verse. 30.37.38.</note>Christ shewes by parables, who be tares and who be the good seede:</l>
         <l>Th'one by the diuell sowen, and th'other sowne by the goddhead:</l>
         <l>Bothe to be reapt at a time, and both to be parted asonder:</l>
         <l>Bothe to be bound in sheaues, and bothe to be laid from another:</l>
         <l>Th'one to be laid in a barne, th'other to be throwne by <hi>Iehoua,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Into that burning lake, that burning fyry <hi>Gehenna.</hi>
         </l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>And wee, that professe Christianity, should not vse any paganisme, to detract gods glorie, as the paganis'd Poets did, in the time of ignorance. For this I haue written of them: I meane, of <hi>Homer, Virgill,</hi> and others;
<q>
         <l>Only the fault was this; they liu'd in a time then of error,</l>
         <l>And to the Pagan goddes most of them yeelded an honnor.</l>
         <l>Those secular sages, which gods trew worde did abandon,</l>
         <pb facs="6"/>
         <l>Wilfully lost them selues, and others left at a randon.</l>
         <l>But should we Christians (confessing one God Imortall,</l>
         <l>Trinity, Vnity, one, deifyed with glory coequall)</l>
         <l>Call to the Pagan gods; to detract praise from the Redeemer,</l>
         <l>Our soules sole-sauiour? Should we such blasphemy suffer?</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>In truthe, all they that professe trew Poetry should seeke to further the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of gods glory what they may (which I pray God they may doe, to ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish all these fond fantasticall and Veneriall Poets) and also to doe their best en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour in trew Hexameters, to abolish this plaine rythme-prose; that wee may imitate and follow the best learned, and auncient Poets: as <hi>Homer, Virgill,</hi> and <hi>Lucan</hi> in Chronicles. For that an heroicall verse composed in Hexameters, is most correspondent to a right honorable nature: as appeared by <hi>Alexander</hi> the great: as I haue composed in Hexameters following.</p>
   <q>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <l>When that <hi>Alexander</hi> did come to the Tombe of <hi>Acbilles,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>That monument to behold; he pronounced these very speaches,</l>
      <l>And with a sigh thus said: Thrice <hi>Larissaeus</hi> is happy,</l>
      <l>For that he greek <hi>Homer</hi> had, to record his glory so worthy.</l>
      <l>* And when he had conquerd great spoyles from king <hi>Darius,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>There was a chest of gould, that, he said, was fit for <hi>Homerus</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Bookes, to be safely repos'd. For he kept them safe, as a Iewell,</l>
      <l>Vnder his owne beads-head: whose worke diuinely doth excell.</l>
      <l>And <hi>Maro</hi> laurigerent, in verse most glorious enrold</l>
      <l>Venturous <hi>Aeneas</hi> exployts, and worthines extold.</l>
      <l>Which brought <hi>Rome</hi> in a muse, with a grace so loftily slowing.</l>
      <l>Whose praise still wil abide, while seas or earthe ar abiding.</l>
   </q>
   <p>And that we may imitate them as neere as we may, in poetizing of verified Chronicles, I haue elsewhere written thus;
<q>
         <pb facs="7"/>
         <l>Learne of <hi>Maeonides;</hi> who writeth of <hi>Hector, Achilles,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Of <hi>Troilus, Diomede,</hi> of craft-contriuer <hi>Vlisses.</hi>
         </l>
         <l>If so be that Chronicles had not bin skilfuly written,</l>
         <l>Kinges valiant exployts, lordes fame, and knightes valor had bin</l>
         <l>Drowned in obliuion. For time (fames greedy deuowrer)</l>
         <l>Leaues fame vnmemoriz'd; as a tree consum'd with a canker.</l>
         <l>You fine metricians, that verses skilfully compile</l>
         <l>(As fine artificers hard Iron do refile on an Anuile)</l>
         <l>This verse irregular, this rustick rythmery bannish:</l>
         <l>Which doth abase Poetry: such verse such meter abolish.</l>
         <l>For lily milke-white swannes flote on streames cleare as a crystall.</l>
         <l>And in a fowle mud-y lake, donguehill duckes striue for an offall.</l>
         <l>Both Greekes and Latinists such verselesse verse did abandon:</l>
         <l>Whose verse is purifi'd, as gould is try'd by the touchstone.</l>
         <pb facs="8"/>
         <l>As vineger doth aford, no pleasant taste to the palate:</l>
         <l>So wordes vnmetrifi'd, which rythmers rudely promulgate,</l>
         <l>Bringe no delight to the wits, nor sound with a grace in a mans eare.</l>
         <l>Euery worthie Poet will such rude rythmery forbeare.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Surely this kinde of scanning verse is not to be discommended: and who so doth, hath no warrant so to doe. And who so doth discommend <hi>Stanihurst,</hi> or <hi>Fraunce,</hi> let them make so many verses. For many will dispraise their bookes, that cannot whiles they liue make the like. For it is more easie for euery man to finde a fault, then to make so many: as I haue written, thus;
<q>
         <l>For curious cauilist but a small mote easily will see,</l>
         <l>Sooner in each strangers eysight, then a beame in his owne eye.</l>
         <l>Hardly he will such bookes in a trew verse notably perfect.</l>
         <pb facs="8"/>
         <l>For many men ready be to finde faults, hasty to correct.</l>
         <l>Such Sycophant humorists, like quayles feede chiefly by poyson:</l>
         <l>Whose Stoicall censures and selfe-mindes stand for a reason.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>And whosoeuer shall discommend mine, I would request him to make so many as I meane to make in fiue bookes, in rythming Hexameters. For, as I thinke, the rythme doth giue thē a grace in our english tongue especially, aboue other tongues; so it be good rythme, though they be the harder to make. The best verse that <hi>Fraunce</hi> made, was in rythming Hexameters, of the natiuitie of Christ. And if he make so many better, I will reuerence him: If so many, &amp; not better (so that he raile not) I will commend him. I discommend no mans workes; for that I know none haue more defects then myne owne. For it is the enriching &amp; beautifying of our language, and the credit and glory of the verse, that I regarde. For I am no mercinary man, nor write with an hyred penne, nor expect vaine glorie.
<pb facs="9"/> But who so doth slander these verses, and cannot amend them, nor make so many, let him keepe his winde to coole his potage. For my answere shall be silence. As <hi>Diogenes</hi> answered one that asked him a foolish question; saying that silence was an answere fit for such a fond demaund. And in respect of them I will say, as the bird said to <hi>Caesar: Operam &amp; laborem perdidi.</hi> But as for you, that are trew fauorits both of Poetry, and of this trew metricall and scanning verse; I wholly submit and referre my selfe to your fauorable censures and assistance: to see if we can yet once againe, set on foote this footed verse; that it may runne smoothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with a grace and credit. I would I were but as <hi>Ennius</hi> to a fine <hi>Maronist,</hi> or to a skilfull <hi>Maeonides.</hi> And also I request you to take in good part these simpel ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of mine: wherin, at idel times, I haue both taken pleasure &amp; paines. For al those that professe learning (and especially such as are descended of honor or of trew gentilitie) should chiefely like of this kinde of heroicke Hexameters: as <hi>Alexander</hi> did, of <hi>Homers;</hi> or <hi>Augustus,</hi> of <hi>Virgils.</hi> And if these shall like you, I shall be
<pb facs="9"/> glad: and do purpose (God willing) yer that a yeare come about, to set forth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther booke.</p>
   <p>I doe not vtterly discommend or condemne this prose-rythme; but do only prefer this Romane verse farre aboue it. And I know, most of them that be learned wil so thinke; and especially when it is brought to perfection: vnlesse they be some carping Cauilists paradoxically captius, or preiudicius. For I know, plaine song is good; but pricke song is knowne to be better: and there is great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt an Orient pearle, and a blacke simpel bugel. If you finde any faults in my booke, I would request you to amend them, and to send them in a priuie note to the Stationer. But now least I should be too tedious, wishing to you all as to my selfe, in our Lord and Sauiour Christ Iesus; I most humbly take my leaue: resting yours, in all loue and duetie to commmand.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>