<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE LORD Robert Deuorax, Earle of Essex and Ewe, Vicount of Hereford and Bowrchier, Lord Ferrers of Chartley, Burchaier and Louaine, maister of the Queenes Maiesties horse, and knight of the most honourable order of the Garter I H. wi∣sheth all heauenly happinesse, and increase of honourable vertue.</title>
           <author>Hester, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116126_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20902</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7277</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116126</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE LORD Robert Deuorax, Earle of Essex and Ewe, Vicount of Hereford and Bowrchier, Lord Ferrers of Chartley, Burchaier and Louaine, maister of the Queenes Maiesties horse, and knight of the most honourable order of the Garter I H. wi∣sheth all heauenly happinesse, and increase of honourable vertue.</title>
                 <author>Hester, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Sclopotarie of Iosephus Quercetanus, phisition. Or His booke containing the cure of wounds receiued by shot of gunne or such like engines of warre. Whereunto is added his spagericke antidotary of medicines against the aforesayd woundes. Published into English by Iohn Hester, practitioner in the said spagiricall arte</title>
                 <author>Du Chesne, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Ward, Roger</publisher>
                    <distributor>Sheldrake, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 95, 9 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE LORD <hi>Robert Deuorax,</hi> Earle of Essex and Ewe, Vicount of Hereford and Bowrchier, Lord Ferrers of Chartley, Burchaier and Louaine, maister of the Queenes Maiesties horse, and knight of the most honourable order of the Garter I H. wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth all heauenly happinesse, and increase of honourable vertue.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He state and condition of true nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie, subiect still to fatall destinies, or rather to the deuine direction of the most highest is such (right honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) that whether you regard the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, from which it originallie sprong: or respect the honour by which it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually holdeth, you shall neuer find it vnfauoured of the better, nor vnspighted of the baser sorte: By which two spurres of praise, and dispraise, as it were pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked foreward, it runneth in a speedie and voluntarie course, the right, and perfect race to earthly felicitie, the rich, and present possession, whereof is a plaine, and easie passage, to that heauenly paradise, to which your father to the great griefe of all good men, though to his great, and vnspeakeable ioy, is lately gone: who leauing behind him, the same steps for you to tread in, that he traced, the same pathes for you to wander in that he walked in before you, least at his death, so liuely a pattern for you to imitate, as neither our present age can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foord you any more vertues, nor any age past: many more va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant? Sith then of these two points, the very sound and solide substance of true nobilitie) you haue in your own house, so rare a president of fresh memorie, proceed right honorable (as you haue well begun) so by this line to leuell all your actions, as in becomming such a sonne, of such a father, you may proue more wise, then by inioying his lands, &amp; possessions seem fortunate. The way that he walkt in, lay as far wide of vice, as vertue her selfe, in flesh and bloud cold pace it out, by which he grewe so deare to her sacred Maiestie, so acceptable to his peeres, &amp; so regarded of the multitude, that it were hard to gesse whether he were more fauoured, more beloued, or more honored. This vvay though in some apparance it lie opē to the vvide vvorld, and so by that meanes, common to you vvith many, yet by a
<pb facs="3"/>
special prerogatiue, it is peculier but to a fevv, among whom, your honour so hold it by inheritance, that not to challenge your right therein, vvere but to disclaime your dissent, and to assume the possession, is but to accept of your ovvne title: vvhich in the opinion of such as knovve you vvell, you may lavvfully auerre: vvhereunto I vvill forbeare longer to exhort you, as vvell for that your forvvardnesse already, stirred vp by a naturall inclination, preuentes all forraine perswasions: as for that I knovv you to be furnished vvith men ofsuch vvorth, vvhom in all honorable affabilitie it pleaseth you to conuerse vvith, as that herein, an abler mans councell then mine ovvne, may seeme either superfluous, or friuolous. Your late expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into <hi>Portingall</hi> (hovvsoeuer the euent sorted out) yeelded to the indifferent censure of euerie man, a moste pregnant proofe of a martiall mind: at vvhat time the skilful and expert captain, took as good occasion to wonder at your singuler val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor: as the sick, maymed, and poore simple souldier to cōmend your liberal boūty: both which are so deeply impressed in their harts that saw, &amp; felt them, as nothing but death shall enforce a forgetfulnesse. And now right honorable acknowledging my slender report herein, to be too base, &amp; beare a record, for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of so great consequence, and carrying no minde (for sundry dutifull respects) to register anie part of the voiage: I leaue to speake more thereof: In all lowly humilitie, moste humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeching you, to auouch the patrionage of this my simple, and plaine translation, wherein I haue endeuoured to deliuer into Englishe, that vvhich sometime <hi>Iosephus Quercetanus</hi> the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, left both in lattin, and in fresh, to the great benefite of his countrey men: and all other that take notice thereof, the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect being a most learned, &amp; profitable discourse, of the cure of vvoundes, gotten by gunshot, a matter in this tumultious and troublesome time in knovvledge acceptable: and for necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie commendable, in vvhich patronage, you shall not onely ioyne partner vvith a mightie Prince, Frances late brother to the french king, but also, by countenancing the booke, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue the good opinion, that soldiers generally haue conceiued of you, vvhereof I presume you make no small accompt. And so vvishing to your honor, all maner of happinesse, euen to the fulnesse of your ovvne content, I humbly take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your honours most duetifull, Iohn Hester.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>