<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, NOBLE, PRV∣denc, and vertuous Ladie, the Countesse of Essex, the Almightie graunt euerlasting Honour and Happinesse.</title>
           <author>Ford, Emanuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116412_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01066</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11173</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116412</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, NOBLE, PRV∣denc, and vertuous Ladie, the Countesse of Essex, the Almightie graunt euerlasting Honour and Happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Ford, Emanuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first part of Parismus, the renovvmed Prince of Bohemia : His most famous, delectable, and pleasant historie. Containing his noble battails fought against the Persians. His loue to Laurana, the Kings daughter of Thessalie: and of his strange aduentures in the desolate iland</title>
                 <author>Ford, Emanuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>236, 266 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="120"/>
   <pb facs="120"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, NOBLE, PRV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denc, and vertuous Ladie, the Countesse <hi>of</hi> Essex, <hi>the Almightie graunt</hi> euerlasting Honour and Happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nimated by the view of your manifolde vertues, <hi>(Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Ladie,)</hi> I haue presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to shrowde this simple worke, vnder the Harbour of your protection, resting in confidence, your <hi>Honour</hi> will vouchsafe to accept the same, although not for the worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, yet for the well mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning intent of the Writer; who in all dutie Dedicateth his endeuors, to deserue your Honourable fauour. Trusting your fauourable and prudent Censure, will extinguish the blemish of my ouer boldnesse: and your wisedome receiue with fauour, what is offered with affection</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pythias Apollo,</hi> re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>used not to drinke in woodden dishes: <hi>Alexander</hi> the great and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ghtie Monarke disdained not to Trauell to visite simple <hi>Diogenes,</hi> in his Cell. Not the giftes value but the giuers good will, hath bene alwaies esteemed. Euen so I rest in hopefull assurance, that (of your owne <hi>Most Honourable and vertuous inclination to fauour Learning)</hi> you will
<pb facs="121"/>
daine to take this small gyfte, proceeding from my heartie good will. Which I am bolde to present to your protection, thereby in some sort to expresse my humble dutie, which bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth me to giue your worthinesse a farre better present then this, if my abilitie were correspondent.</p>
   <p>The dutyfull regard I beare to your laudable gyfts, being such, that I am vnable (hauing no other meane) to expresse the same: Humbly beseeching your Honour to accept this gyft in place of a better; and my humble and dutifull mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, in steede of a better performance: And (according to your vertuous Bountie) vouchsafe to protect this Talent of my poore Labours, vnder the title of your Honourable Patronage. Which shall binde me to inuocate the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to indue your Noble minde with innumerable vertues, increase your Honours, inrich you with all blessings, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward you with eternall happinesse.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours in all dutie.
Emmanuell Forde.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>