<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ Annotations in ye .xiij. Chapiter to y• Romaines. ¶ The Prologe.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1551</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116553_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03631</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13756</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116553</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ Annotations in ye .xiij. Chapiter to y• Romaines. ¶ The Prologe.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Godly and most necessary annotations in ye .xiij. chapyter too the Romaynes</title>
                 <author>Hooper, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Oswen, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Worcester</pubPlace>
                    <date>1551</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64+ pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>¶ Annotations in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> .xiij. Chapiter to y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Romaines. ¶ The Prologe.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE office and duetye of a christian man, is conteined in twoo partes. The firste, that he use himselfe aryght and reuerently with God. The second, that he vse hym comely and honestly w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> man. In the Epistle to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maines from y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> beginning Sainct Paul hath fullye and sufficyently declared the vnty and offyce of man, towards god: to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wards the end, he declareth how we may honestly do our duetyes towardes men. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>othe these offices must dilygentlye be knowen and exercised. And because a Ci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyle and outwarde lyfe, seme it neuer so honest, is mere and verye hipocrisie, and can not please god, except the mynd and soule inwardly be well affected towards hym, I thinke it conuenyent brieuely to declare wherin Sainct Paule in this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pystle doth put the religyon of the heart of man, towardes GOD: and then we hall the better descend vnto suche duty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s and offices, as appertaineth to al ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of persons as well publyque as pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="8"/>Fyrste, Sainte Paule perceyueth that in grace and promises of God can no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> be knowen of man vntyll suche tyme a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> he be brought to acknowledge and dys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure of his sinnes. The phisition an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> phisicke be vnprofytable vntoo suche a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> knowe not that they be sicke, as Christ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> sayd, I came not to call the iust, but syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>s<note place="margin">Mathe. 9.</note> to repentaunce. Therfore we must know the wounde of our soules, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> syckenes of synne, before we can get any profyt by the grace of God. We must confesse that all men and women, except Christ, are borne the chylderne of ire an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of goddes dyspleasure, and that we bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> aboute in vs synne, that alwayes repu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the spiryt, whereby we are acertay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned that we be alwayes subiect vnto sy as Sainte Paule sayth, he concluded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <note place="margin">Roma. 11.</note> men vndersinne, because he might ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> mercy vpon al. Seing we be al sinners<note place="margin">Roma. 6.</note> the reward of sinne, is death, Saint Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les conclusyon where he saythe, we ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <note place="margin">Ephesian. 2</note> borne al the chylderne of Gods dysple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sure, is true. Nowe then may we be de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from thys great Ire and dysple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sure?<note place="margin">1, Ioan. 4, Roma, 5.</note> By the mercy of god the father re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardes vs, that fyrste loued vs, we lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="8"/>
hym, whiles we were yet his enemy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es. But what is that, where with all we may be annexed and reconciled vnto god by hys mercye, when there is noo good thyng in vs, but all fylthy and sinnefull? It is Iesus Christ, y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> sonne of god, moste <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>erebeloued, in whome the father is con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ented, and by whom he is reconciled vn to all synners that repent and beleue his<note place="margin">Math. 3. 17. Ephe. 1. 2. Col. 1. 2. Roma. 8. Philip, 2.</note>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>romyses, for the merites and shedynge of Christes blud, his derebeloued sonne. After that, we se and perceyue so great a mercy and pitie of our heauenly father. y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> would not fanoure nor spare hys onelye sonne, to die for our redemptiō, but gaue hym to the most cruell and vyle death of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e crosse for vs, how shuld not we trust <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> so mercyfull a father in all oure trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and aduersityes, whether they be of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>die or soule? Whye should we not call<note place="margin">Math. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> onely vpon so mercifull a god? If we do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>us amend our liues, beleue his promy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>, &amp; study a better life, we shal not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <note place="margin">Luce▪ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> ve saued by his mercy, but also glad to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>ue hym, and walke before him in inno <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>cie and purenes of life: and also obedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>tly and quyetly in the world, yeue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>rence &amp; loue to all persons accordingly
<pb facs="9"/>
to whom honoure, honoure: to whome loue, loue: to whō iustyce, iustice: to whō mercy, mercy. Vntoo this christian quy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnes, reuerence, loue and feare, doth all the scripture exhorte vs, and chiefly thys presente xiii. chapiter to the Romaynes. For the vnderstanding wherof the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I note at the beginning a certain dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersitie and difference of persons. There be, and euer hath bene some publike per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sons, &amp; some pryuate persons. Publyke persons, be those that beare ony offyce, rule, regiment or Dominion, in a cōmon wealth, as a kyng with all his iustyces, Maires, Sheriffes, Baylynes, Consta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and other, Priuate persons, be such as be subiectes, and vnder these officers. These two persons must be diuersely v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and the duety that is due vnto y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> one is not due vnto the other in ciuell respec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. And seing we must lyue with bothe these persons and states appointed to be in the world by almighty God, Saincte Paul in this chapiter is very diligent to teache and instructe vs howe we shoulde lyue accordingly in trueth and honestye towardes them bothe.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>