<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my much honoured Friend
Mr. George Sandys.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116693_Bo1_2_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11474</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21725</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116693</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my much honoured Friend
Mr. George Sandys.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A paraphrase upon the divine poems. By George Sandys</title>
                 <author>Sandys, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Hebb, Andrew</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Hebb, Andrew.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 55, 13, 171, 1, 15, 3, 33, 1 page, music, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>To my much honoured Friend
Mr. George Sandys.</head>
   <l>IT is, Sir, a Confest Intrusion here,</l>
   <l>That I before your Labours doe appeare:</l>
   <l>VVhich no loud Herald need, that may proclaime,</l>
   <l>Or seeke acceptance, but the Authors fame.</l>
   <l>Much lesse that should This Happy Worke commend,</l>
   <l>VVhose Subject is its Licence, and doth send</l>
   <l>It to the World to be Receiv'd and Read,</l>
   <l>Farre as the glorious Beames of Truth are spread.</l>
   <l>Nor let it be imagin'd, that I looke</l>
   <l>Only with Customes Eye upon your Booke;</l>
   <l>Or in this service that 'twas my intent</l>
   <l>T'exclude your Person from your Argument.</l>
   <l>I shall professe, much of the Love Iowe</l>
   <l>Doth from the Root of our Extraction grow.</l>
   <l>To which though I can little contribute;</l>
   <l>Yet with a Naturall joy, I must impute</l>
   <l>To our Tribes honour, what by You is done,</l>
   <l>VVorthy the Title of a Prelates Sonne.</l>
   <l>And scarcely have Two Brothers farther borne</l>
   <l>A Fathers Name, or with more Value worne</l>
   <l>Their Owne, then Two of you: whose Pens, and Feet</l>
   <l>Have made the distant Points of Heav'n to meet:</l>
   <l>Hee by exact discoveries of the West,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Sr. Edwin Sandys</hi> view of Religion in the Westerne parts.</note>
   </l>
   <l>Your Selfe by painfull Travels in the East.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="41"/>
Some more like you would powerfully Confute</l>
   <l>Th'Opposers of Priests Mariage by the Fruit.</l>
   <l>And (since 'tis knowne, for all their Strait-vow'd life,</l>
   <l>They Like the Sexe in any stile but Wife)</l>
   <l>Cause them to change their Cloister for that State,</l>
   <l>Which Keeps men Chast by Vowes legitimate.</l>
   <l>Nor shame to Father their Relations,</l>
   <l>Or under Nephewes Names disguise their Sons.</l>
   <l>This Child of yours, borne without spurious blot,</l>
   <l>And Fairely Midwivd as it was begot,</l>
   <l>Doth so much of the Parents goodnesse Weare,</l>
   <l>You may be prou'd to owne it for your Heire.</l>
   <l>Whose Choice acquires you from the Common Sin</l>
   <l>Of such, who finish worse, then they Begin.</l>
   <l>You mend upon your selfe, and your Last Straine</l>
   <l>Does of your First the start in judgement gaine.</l>
   <l>Since, what in Curious Travell was begun,</l>
   <l>You here conclude in a Devotion.</l>
   <l>Where in delightfull Raptures we descry;</l>
   <l>As in a Map, Sions Chorography:</l>
   <l>Lay'd out in so direct, and Smooth a Line,</l>
   <l>Men need not goe about through Palaestine.</l>
   <l>Who seeke Christ here, will the Streight Rode preferre,</l>
   <l>As neerer much then by the Sepulchre.</l>
   <l>For not a Limbe growes here, but is a Path</l>
   <l>Which in Gods City the blest Centre hath,</l>
   <l>And doth so sweetly on each Passion strike,</l>
   <l>The most phantastick taste will somewhat Like.</l>
   <l>To the Vnquiet Soule Iob still from hence</l>
   <l>Speaks in th'Example of his Patience.</l>
   <l>The Mortifi'd may heare the Wise King Preach,</l>
   <l>When his Repentance made Him fit to Teach:</l>
   <l>Here are choice Hymnes and Carolls for the Glad;</l>
   <l>And melancholy Dirges for the sad.</l>
   <l>Last, David (as he could his Art transferre)</l>
   <l>Speaks like Himselfe by an Interpreter.</l>
   <l>Your Muse, rekindled hath the Prophets Fire,</l>
   <l>And Tun'd the Strings of his neglected Lyre;</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="42"/>
Making the Note and Ditty so agree,</l>
   <l>They now become a perfect Harmony.</l>
   <l>I must confesse, I have long wisht to see</l>
   <l>The Psalmes reduc'd to this Conformitie:</l>
   <l>Grieving the Songs of Sion should be sung</l>
   <l>In Phrase not diff'ring from a Barbarous Tongue.</l>
   <l>As if, by Custome warranted, we may</l>
   <l>Sing that to God, we would be loth to Say.</l>
   <l>Farre be it from my purpose to upbraid</l>
   <l>Their honest meaning, who first offer made</l>
   <l>That Booke in Meter to compile, which you</l>
   <l>Have mended in the Forme, and Built anew.</l>
   <l>And It was well, considering the Time</l>
   <l>Which scarcely could distinguish Verse and Rhime.</l>
   <l>But now the Language, like the Church, hath won</l>
   <l>More Luster since the Reformation;</l>
   <l>None can condemne the Wish, or Labour spent</l>
   <l>Good Matter in Good Words to represent.</l>
   <l>Yet in this jealous Age some such there be</l>
   <l>So (without cause) afraid of Noveltie;</l>
   <l>They would by no meanes (had they power to chose)</l>
   <l>An Old Ill Custome, for a Better loose.</l>
   <l>Men who a Rustick Plainesse so affect,</l>
   <l>They thinke God served best by their neglect.</l>
   <l>Holding the Cause would be Prophan'd by it,</l>
   <l>VVere they at Charge of Learning or of Wit.</l>
   <l>And therefore bluntly, what comes next, they bring</l>
   <l>Course and ill study'd Stuffe for Offering;</l>
   <l>Which, like th' Old Tabernacles Covering, are</l>
   <l>Made up of Badgers skins and of Goats haire.</l>
   <l>But These are Paradoxes they must use</l>
   <l>Their Sloth and bolder Ignorance to excuse.</l>
   <l>Who would not laugh at one will Naked goe,</l>
   <l>'Cause in Old hangings Truth is pictur'd so?</l>
   <l>Though Plainnesse be reputed Honours note,</l>
   <l>They Mantles adde to beautifie the Coat.</l>
   <l>So that a Curious (unaffected) dresse</l>
   <l>Addes much unto the Bodies comelinesse:</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="42"/>
In Vice and Barbarisme supinely rowles;</l>
   <l>Their Fortunes not more slavish then their Souls.</l>
   <l>Those Churches,<note place="margin">Easterne Churches.</note> which from the first Hereticks wan</l>
   <l>All the first Fields, or led (at least) the Van;</l>
   <l>In whom those Notes, so much required, be;</l>
   <l>Agreement,<note place="margin">Of Doctrine. Of Persons. As Antioch.</note> Miracles, Antiquity:</l>
   <l>Which can a Never-broke Succession show</l>
   <l>From the Apostles down; (Here bragg'd of so:)</l>
   <l>So best confute Her most immodest claime,</l>
   <l>Who scarce a Part, yet to be All doth aime;</l>
   <l>Lie now distrest, betweene two Enemy-Powers,</l>
   <l>Whom the West damnes, &amp; whom the East devoures.</l>
   <l>What State then Theirs can more Vnhappy be,</l>
   <l>Threatned with Hell, and sure of Poverty.</l>
   <l>The small Beginning of the Turkish Kings,</l>
   <l>And their large Growth, shew us that different Things</l>
   <l>May meet in One Third; what most Disagree,</l>
   <l>May have some Likenesse: For in this we see,</l>
   <l>A Mustard-seed may be resembled well</l>
   <l>To the Two Kingdomes, both of Heaven and Hell.</l>
   <l>Their Strength, &amp; wants this work hath both unwound;</l>
   <l>To teach how these t'increase,<note place="margin">Turks.</note> and that confound:</l>
   <l>Relates their Tenets; scorning to dispute</l>
   <l>With Errors, which to tell, is to confute:</l>
   <l>Shews how even there, where Christ vouchsaft to Teach,</l>
   <l>Their Dervices dare an Impostor Preach.<note place="margin">Priests.</note>
   </l>
   <l>For whilst vvith private Quarrels vve Decaid,</l>
   <l>We vvay for them, and Their Religion made:</l>
   <l>And can but Wishes novv to Heaven preferre,<note place="margin">Ovids Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphosis.</note>
   </l>
   <l>May They gaine Christ, or We his Sepulchre.</l>
   <l>Next Ovid cals me; vvhich though I admire,</l>
   <l>For Equalling the Authors quickning Fire,</l>
   <l>And his pure Phrase: yet More; remembring It</l>
   <l>Was by a Mind so much distracted Writ:</l>
   <l>Bus 'nesse and Warre, Ill Midvvives to produce</l>
   <l>The Happy Off-spring of so sweet a Muse:</l>
   <l>Whilst every unknowne Face did Danger Threat;</l>
   <l>For every Native there was twice a Gete.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="43"/>
More;<note place="margin">om mentar.</note> when (return'd) thy Work review'd, expos'd</l>
   <l>What Pith before the hiding Bark inclos'd:</l>
   <l>And with it that Essay,<note place="margin">Virg. Aen. lib. 1.</note> which lets us see</l>
   <l>Well by the Foot, what Hercules would be.</l>
   <l>All fitly offer'd to his Princely Hands;</l>
   <l>By whose Protectiō Learning chiefly stands:</l>
   <l>Whose Vertue moves more Pens, then his Power Swords;</l>
   <l>And Theme to those, and Edge to these affords.</l>
   <l>Who could not be displeas'd,<note place="margin">Panegyrick.</note> that his great Fame,</l>
   <l>So Pure a Muse, so loudly should proclaime:</l>
   <l>With his Queenes praise in the same Model cast;</l>
   <l>Which shall not lesse, then all their Annalls, last.</l>
   <l>Yet, though we wonder at thy Charming Voice;</l>
   <l>Perfection still was wanting in thy Choice:</l>
   <l>And of a Soule, vvhich so much Povver possest,</l>
   <l>That Choice is hardly Good, vvhich is not Best.</l>
   <l>But though Thy Muse vvere Ethnically Chast,</l>
   <l>When most Fault could be found; yet novv Thou hast</l>
   <l>Diverted to a Purer Path thy Quill;</l>
   <l>And chang'd Parnassus Mount to Sions Hill:</l>
   <l>So that blest David might almost Desire</l>
   <l>To heare his Harp thus Echo'd by thy Lyre.</l>
   <l>Such Eloquence, that though it were abus'd,</l>
   <l>Could not but be (though not Allow'd) excus'd.</l>
   <l>Ioin'd to a Work so choice, that though Ill-done,</l>
   <l>So Pious an Attempt Praise could not shun.</l>
   <l>How strangely doth it darkest Texts disclose,</l>
   <l>In Verses of such sweetnesse; that even Those,</l>
   <l>From whō the unknown Tongue conceales the Sense,</l>
   <l>Even in the Sound, must finde an Eloquence.</l>
   <l>For though the most bewitching Musick could</l>
   <l>Move men, no more than Rocks; thy Language would.</l>
   <l>Those who make wit their Curse, who spend their Brain</l>
   <l>Their Time, and Art, in looser Verse, to gain</l>
   <l>Damnation, and a Mistres; till they see</l>
   <l>How Constant that is, how Inconstant she;</l>
   <l>May from this great Example learne, to sway</l>
   <l>The Parts th'are Blest-with, some more Blessed way.</l>
   <l>Fate can against Thee but two Foes advance;</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="43"/>
Sharpe-sighted Envy, and Blind Ignorance:</l>
   <l>The first (by Nature like a shadow, neare</l>
   <l>To all great Acts) I rather Hate then Feare:</l>
   <l>For them, (since whatsoever most they Raise</l>
   <l>In Private, That they most in Throngs Dispraise;</l>
   <l>And know the Ill they Act Condemn'd within)<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
   </l>
   <l>Who envies Thee, may no man envy Him.</l>
   <l>The last I Feare not much, but Pity more</l>
   <l>For though they cannot the least Fault explore;</l>
   <l>Yet, if they might the high Tribunall Clime,</l>
   <l>To Them thy Excellence would be thy Crime:</l>
   <l>For Eloquence with things Prophane they joine;</l>
   <l>Nor count it fit to Mixe with what's Divine;</l>
   <l>Like Art and Paintings laid upon a Face,</l>
   <l>Of it selfe sweet; which more Deforme then Grace.</l>
   <l>Yet, as the Church with Ornaments is Fraught,</l>
   <l>Why may not That be too, which There is Taught?</l>
   <l>And sure that Vessell of Election, Paul,</l>
   <l>Who Iudais'd with Iewes, was All to All:</l>
   <l>So, to Gaine some, would be (at least) Content,</l>
   <l>Some for the Curious should be Eloquent:</l>
   <l>For since the Way to Heaven is Rugged, who</l>
   <l>Would have the Way to that Way be so too?</l>
   <l>Or thinks it fit, we should not leave obtaine,</l>
   <l>To learne with Pleasure, what we Act with Paine?</l>
   <l>Since then Some stop, unlesse their Path be Even,</l>
   <l>Nor will be led by Soloecismes to Heaven;</l>
   <l>And (through a Habit scarce to be control'd)</l>
   <l>Refuse a Cordial, when not brought in Gold;</l>
   <l>Much like to them to that Disease Inur'd,<note place="margin">Tarantula▪</note>
   </l>
   <l>Which can be no way, but by Musick cur'd:</l>
   <l>I Ioy in Hope, that no small Piety</l>
   <l>Will in their Colder Hearts be Warm'd by Thee.</l>
   <l>For as none could more Harmony dispense;</l>
   <l>So neither could thy flowing Eloquence</l>
   <l>So well in any Task be us'd, as this:</l>
   <l>To Sound His Praises forth, whose Gift it is.</l>
   <q>
      <note place="margin">Virg. Georg. 2.</note>
      <l>—Cui non certaverit ullae</l>
      <l>Aut tantum fluere, aut totidem dur are per annos.</l>
   </q>
   <closer>
      <signed>FALKLAND.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>