<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116960_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11800</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22089</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116960</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Symmachia: or, A true-loues knot : Tyed, betvvixt Great Britaine and the Vnited Prouinces, by the wisedome of King Iames, and the States Generall; the kings of France, Denmarke, and Sweden, the Duke of Sauoy, with the states of Venice being witnesses and assistants. For the weale and peace of Christendome</title>
                 <author>Scott, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 34, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am to let all men know, that besides those grieuances which I haue fauourably and sparingly mentioned &amp; minced in these fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Papers, I heare of another one ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing which is of greatest moment and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liest to produce most alteration, if it be not preuented. And that is the hard and extreme measure which the Merchant Aduenturers here setled, meet with in their Staple commodity. Concerning which if there be not order presently taken, to giue them contentment, in some good and indifferent manner, but that they be forced to seeke courses for reliefe of themselues by their Petitions and Complaints to his Maiestie (whereabout I heare they are meditating) a worse businesse then that of East <hi>Indya</hi> will breake forth to trouble both States, and alien hearts from each other. For it concernes the King: Peeres, and Commons when the Wooll is puld from their backes by any abuse; since euerie condition of men in the Land, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most euerie person, haue interest in that Commoditie. This breach therefore, I wish with all my heart were stopt by timely prouision, and the rude, boorish and proud dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition of such, in these parts, restrained, as by their too strickt, surly, and imperious courses, for their priuate pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit prouoke the complaint of our people, and driue them to seeke ease and remedie by the shift of place and trade where they may hope to be better vsed, and to finde loue, respect, and iustice, with indifferencie.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>