<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE VVELL-MEANING PVBLISHER HEREOF TO THE VNDERSTANDING READER, of what ranke or degree soeuer.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116680_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11467</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21718</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116680</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE VVELL-MEANING PVBLISHER HEREOF TO THE VNDERSTANDING READER, of what ranke or degree soeuer.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Europæ speculum. Or, A vievv or suruey of the state of religion in the vvesterne parts of the world : VVherein the Romane religion, and the pregnant policies of the Church of Rome to support the same, are notably displayed: with some other memorable discoueries and memorations, never before till now published according to the authours originall copie</title>
                 <author>Sandys, Edwin, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Sparke (Sparkes, Wreichionen), Michael 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--The Hague</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 248 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>THE VVELL-MEANING PVBLISHER HEREOF TO THE VNDERSTANDING READER,</hi> of what ranke or degree soeuer.</head>
   <p>WHereas not many yeares past, there was published in print, a Treatise entituled, <hi>A Relation of Religion of the Westerne parts of the World,</hi> printed for one <hi>Simon Waterson, 1605.</hi> without name of Authour, yet generally and currantly passing vnder the name of the learned and worthy Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman <hi>S<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Edwin Sandys Knight;</hi> Know all men by these presents that <hi>the same Booke</hi> was but a spurious stolne Copie; in part epitomized, in part amplified, and throughout most shamefully falsified &amp; false printed, frō the Authors Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall: In so much, that the asme <hi>Knight</hi> was infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely wronged thereby: and as soone as it came to his knowledge, that such a thing was printed,
<pb facs="3"/>
and passed <hi>vnder his name, he</hi> caused it (though somewhat late, when, it seemes, two Impressions were for the most part vented) to be prohibited by Authoritie; and as I haue heard, as many as could be recouered, to be deseruedly burnt, with power also to punish the Printers: And yet, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthelesse, since that time, there hath beene ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Impression of the same stolne into the world. Now, those so adulterate Copies being scattered abroad, &amp; in the hands of some men, I (whoeuer I am) though liuing here in these Transmarine Batavian Belgique parts, yet studious of the truth, and a louer of my Countrey; and having obtayned by a direct meanes, of a deere friend, a perfect Copie, <hi>verbatim</hi> trans<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ribed from the Authours Originall, and legitimate one, of his own hand-writing, haue thought good to publish it vnto the world; first, for the good of the Church; secondly, the glory of our English Nation; third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for the fame of the <hi>ingenuous &amp; ingenious and Acute Author,</hi> a Gentle-man, who (as I haue beene most credibly informed) hath (here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore) deserued right well of his Countrey, in seruice of the <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi> &amp; <hi>the Lords
<pb facs="3"/>
the States generall,</hi> his Maiestie of Englands <hi>fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t friends and Allies,</hi> yet &amp;c. And lastly, that the world may be no longer depriued of so rare a Iewell, in its owne lustre, nor abused by the other counterfeit-one, before named.</p>
   <p>It may bee, I hereby shall incurre some dislike from the <hi>learned Author,</hi> (if He be yet liuing,) who haply in <hi>his</hi> modestie, and for some other causes best knowne vnto <hi>him selfe,</hi> (for some writers loue not to haue their labours published in their life time) hath so long obscured and sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed his <hi>pregnan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> view, from the worlds pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique view, farther then now and than by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating it vnto <hi>his</hi> friends, such as impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuned <hi>him</hi> to haue it copied out: And <hi>certes;</hi> though I professe to honour <hi>him</hi> with all my heart, yet I thinke it better, <hi>he</hi> be herein displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, than the world longer wronged, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all hoping howeuer, that hee will candidly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strue it to be but <hi>amoris error.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>I</hi> cannot see how any else should be offended hereat, but such as are sworne slaues to their Lord God the Pope; whose Roman kingdome, and Babylonian tottering tower, hath such a
<pb facs="4"/>
blow giuen it hereby, as I know but few of such force; and not many such blowes more, will make the same Kingdome and Tower fall downe to the ground, with vtter desolation. As for the <hi>Arminians,</hi> when this Treatise was written, that sect, was either in the shell, or the cradle, and their mungrell and squint-eyed Diuinitie s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>arce knowne, or v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nted to the world: yet they haply will be offended hereat, because savouring of the Orthodox trueth, and let that sect so bee: But if there chance to bee any other moderate Christian offended hereat, of such I humbly▪ craue pardon.</p>
   <p>Reade it therefore, beloued Reader, for thine owne solace, and much good maist thou learne &amp; reape thereby; giuing God the glory, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour his deserued due praise, and mee thankes (if thou canst afford me any) for my honest endeavour here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, for thy benefit.</p>
   <closer>From the HAGH in HOLLAND.
Vale in Christo, &amp; fruere.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>