<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The first wordes of the translators preface are these.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S116732_Bo1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11509</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21757</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S116732</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The first wordes of the translators preface are these.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An apology, or, apologiticall answere, made by Father Paule a Venetian, of the order of Serui, vnto the exceptions and obiections of Cardinall Bellarmine, against certaine treatises and resolutions of Iohn Gerson, concerning the force and validitie of excommunication. First published in Italian, and now translated into English. Seene and allowed by publicke authoritie</title>
                 <author>Sarpi, Paolo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Welby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 68, 65-72 pages, 73-103, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <head>The first wordes of the translators preface are these.</head>
   <p>A common report being spread throughout this Citie, that vpon Christmas day last there were censures and excommunications pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely denounced, against the most glorious renowned and religious common wealth of <hi>Venice,</hi> because they refused to submit vnto the will &amp; discretion of an other, that liberty which God had giuen them.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>If we shall carefully examine all the kindes of liberty, which a priuate person or a common wealth is capable of, we shall finde no more but these six following: Liberty, or fredome of wil, opposit to naturall necessitie: Christian Liberty, oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site to the bondage of sinne: Ciuil liberty, opposite to slauish bondage, liberty of a common wealth or free state, opposite to the subiection of a King or Monarch: Liberty of an absolute Prince, which acknowledgeth no superior in temporall matters, opposite to the rightfull subiection of an inferiour Prince, to a greater
<pb n="5" facs="4"/>
or superior: And lastly, Libertie to doe euill, opposite to the seruice or subiection of righteousnesse, which liberty to doe euill, Saint Paule affirmes to bee all one with the bondage of sinne.</hi> Cum cerui essetis peccati, liberi fuistes iustitiae. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>I do not thinke that the Author of this preface meant to speake of the freedome of will, which is naturall, and cannot be lost by any meanes, but in the erronious conceipt and fancy of</hi> Lutherans, <hi>and other such heritickes: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can hee with any reason meane Christian liberty, which is opposite to the bondage of sinne: for that is not lost by obeying Christs vicar, but rather by not obeying him: Nor can we thinke that he intends to speake of ciuill liberty, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of all slaues are depriued; nor of the liberty of an Aristocracie, or Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy, (that is where some few of the better sort or the generality of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple beare the rule) which kinde of liberty those people doe lacke, that are subiect to a kingely power, or as wee may call it a monarchy: for neither the present Pope, nor yet any of his predecessors, hath euer attempted to change the forme of gouernement of the Cittie of Ʋenice, as knowing very well, that there is noe forme of regiment, bee it of a Monarch, or of some few principall personss, or of the whole people, but may well stand with Christiā religion, whereof the Pope hath the principall care and charge. Nay rather this varietie, doth not a little adorne and beautifie the Cittye of god, which is the vniuersall Church.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>