<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117234_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04542</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14663.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117234</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of the ministery of the Church of England : Wherein is handled this question, whether it be to be separated from, or joyned vnto. Which is discussed in two letters, the one written for it, the other against it. Whervnto is annexed, after the preface, a brief declaration of the ordinary officers of the Church of Christ. And, a few positions. Also in the end of the treatise, some notes touching the Lordes prayer. Seuen questions. A table of some principal thinges conteyned in this treatise</title>
                 <author>Johnson, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Low Countries</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 141, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <head type="sub">To the Christian reader, grace and peace from Iesus
Christ our Lord.</head>
   <p>GReat strife there is at this day, about the ministery of the Church of England, vvhether
it be the same that Christ hath ordeyned in his Testament, or an other. And many by
conference, some also by vvriting, have controverted this question. There coming to
my hands, these tvvo Letters follovving, the one vvritten in defence of the said ministerie,
the other as aunsvver therto, and disproving the same: I have thought them meet and needfull
to be published for thy good (gentle reader) that the truth in this point may appeare. Neyther
will they that vvrote these thinges, blame me for thus doing (I trust), seing the matter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
off it ovvne nature publik, and concerneth al men: 2. besides both of them doubtlesse have set
dovvne that vvhich they are persvvaded is the truth, and vvhich they vvould vvish others vvith
them to receyve and follovv: 3. and sundry copies [especially of the first letter] are already
spred abroad in vvriting vnto the handes of many.</p>
   <p>The ground and occasion of these letters (as I vnderstand and as may be perceived also
by the vvritinges themselves) vvas this. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e vvas a gentlevvoman imprisoned, because she
vvould not ioyne vvith the publick ministerie of England in the vvorship of God. She being
much sollicited to the contrarie, gave in vvriting, a reason of that her faith and practise, to
one Mr A: H. a minister, and a man very learned. The reason vvas this (as may also be seen
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the letters follovving).</p>
   <p>Whosoever he be that dealeth with the holy thinges of God and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
vpon the consciences of men, by vertue of an Antichristian po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
office and calling, him the people of God ought not to receyue
and joyne themselves vnto.</p>
   <p>But al the ministers that stand ouer the Church-assemblyes in
England, deale with the holy thinges of God and worke vpon mens
consciences, by vertue of an Antichristian power office and calling:</p>
   <p>Therefore the people of God ought not to receive them, or ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
themselves vnto them.</p>
   <p>VNto this argument Mr H. made aunsvver by a letter vnto her vvhich follovveth. The let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
she communicated vvith some of her friendes: they together advised to get it auns<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ered:
vvhich vvas obteyned of one Mr. F: Io. prisoner for the same cause: vvho also directed
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> aunsvver to the foresayd gentlevvoman. Both of these (vvith some fevv other things) are
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> set forth for thy benefit (good reader) that comparing one vvith an other, and vveyghing
thinges by the vvord of truth, thovv maist discerne the right, through the helpe of God and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of his grace, vvhich it shalbe thy dutie instantly to crave, that so knovving his heaven▪
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>vvil in these things, thovv maist also be blessed, doing the same. Iohn. 13. 17.</p>
   <closer>Farevvell.</closer>
   <epigraph>
      <q>
         <l>Desier the peace of Ierusalem: let them be prospered
that love thee.</l>
         <l>Let peace be in thy fort, tranquillitie in thy pallaces.</l>
         <l>Because of my brethren and my fellow-friendes,</l>
         <l>I will speak now, peace in thee.</l>
         <l>Because of the howse of the Lord owr God,</l>
         <l>I will seek-out good for thee.</l>
      </q>
      <bibl>Psal. 122. 6. 7. 8. 9.</bibl>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>