<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117620_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00948</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11058</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117620</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Christs victorie, and triumph in Heauen, and earth, ouer, and after death</title>
                 <author>Fletcher, Giles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legge (Legg), Cantrell</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 45, 3, 47-78, 81-83, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hear are but fewe of many that can rightly iudge of Poetry, and yet thear at many of those few, that carry so left<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handed an opinion of it, as some of them thinke it halfe sacrilege for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Poetrie to deale with divine and heauenly matters, as though <hi>David</hi> wear to be sentenced by them, for vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ng his graue matter vpon the harpe: others something more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>olent in their censure, but sure lesse reasonable (as though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>oetrie corrupted all good witts, when, indeed, bad witts cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>pt Poetrie) banish it with <hi>Plato</hi> out of all well-ordered Commonwealths. Both theas I will strive rather to satisfie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>en refute.</p>
   <p>And of the first I would gladlie knowe, whither they sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ose it fitter, that the sacred songs in the Scripture of those he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oicall Saincts, <hi>Moses, Deborah, Ieremie, Mary, Simeon, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>id, Salomon,</hi> (the wisest Scholeman, and wittiest Poet) should <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ee eiected from the canon, for wante of grauitie, or rather this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rroure eraced out of their mindes, for wante of truth. But, it maye bee, they will giue the Spirit of God leaue to breath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hrough what pipe it please, &amp; will confesse, because they must <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eeds, that all the songs dittied by him, must needs bee, as their Fountaine is, most holy: but their common clamour is, who may compare with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, &amp; yet as none may compare without presum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> all may imitat, and not without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation:
<pb facs="3"/>
which made <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> on of the Starrs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Greeke Church, that nowe shines as bright in heauen, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> did then on earth, write so manie diuine Poems of the Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> alogie, Miracles, Parables, Passion of Christ, called by him h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, which when <hi>Basil,</hi> the Prince of the Fathen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> and his Chamberfellowe, had seene, his opinion of them was, that he could haue deuised nothing either more fruitfull to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: because it kindely woed them to Religion, or more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable to himselfe, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, because by imitating the singing Angels in heau'n, himselfe became, though before his time, an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angel. What should I speake of <hi>Iuvencus, Prosper,</hi> &amp; the wise <hi>Prudentius?</hi> the last of which liuing in <hi>Hieroms</hi> time twelue hundred yeares agoe, brought foorth in his declining age, so many, &amp; so religious poems, straitly charging his soule, not to let passe so much as one either night or daye with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out some diuine song, <hi>Hymnis continuet dies, Nec nox vlla va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cet, quin Dominum canat.</hi> And as sedulous <hi>Prudentius,</hi> so pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Sedulius</hi> was famous in this poeticall diuinity, the coetan of <hi>Bernard,</hi> who sung the historie of <hi>Christ</hi> with as much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion in himself, as admitation to others; all which wear followed by the choicest witts of <hi>Christendome: Nonnius</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slating all Sainct <hi>Iohns</hi> Ghosipel into Greek verse, <hi>Sanazar,</hi> the late-liuing Image, and happy imitator of <hi>Uirgil,</hi> bestowing ten-yeares vpon a song, onely to celebrat that one day when Christ was borne vnto vs on earth, &amp; we (a happie change) vnto God in heau'n: thrice-honour'd <hi>Bartas,</hi> &amp; our (I know no other name more glorious then his own) M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Edmund Spen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi> (two blessed Soules) not thinking ten years inough, layeing out their whole liues vpon this one studie: Nay I may iustly say, that the Princely Father of our Countrey (though in my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, God hath made him of all the learned Princes that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wear the most religious, and of all the religious Princes, the most learned, that so, by the one, hee might oppose him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<pb facs="3"/>
the Pope, the peste of all Religion, and by the other, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Bellarmine</hi> the abuser of all good Learning) is yet so far enamour'd with this celestiall Muse, that it shall neuer repent mee—<hi>calamo triuisse labellum,</hi> whensoeuer I shall remember <hi>Hac eadem vt sciret quid non faciebat Amyntas?</hi> To name no more in such plenty, whear I may finde how to beginne, sooner then to end, Saincte Paule, by the Exāple of Christ, that wente singing to mounte Oliuet, with his Disciples, after his last supper, exciteth the Christians to solace themselues with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ymnes, and Psalmes, and spirituall songs; and thearefore, by their leav's, be it an error for <hi>Poets</hi> to be Divines, I had rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rr with the Scripture, then be rectifi'd by them: I had rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dore the stepps of <hi>Nazianzen, Prudentius, Sedulius,</hi> then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>owe their steps, to bee misguided: I had rather be the deuoute Admirer of <hi>Nonnius, Bartas,</hi> my sacred Soueraign, and others, the miracles of our latter age, then the false sectatie of these, that haue nothing at all to follow, but their own naked opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: To conclude, I had rather with my Lord, and his most di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Apostle sing (though I sing sorilie) the loue of heauen and earthe, then praise God (as they doe) with the woorthie guift of silence, and sitting still, or think I dispraisd him with this poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical discourse. It seems they haue either not read, or clean <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>orgot, that it is the dutie of the Muses (if wee maye beeleeue <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>indare,</hi> and <hi>Hesiod)</hi> to set allwaies vnder the throne of <hi>Iupiter, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ius &amp; laudes, &amp; beneficia</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, which made a very worthy German writer conclude it <hi>Certò statuimus, proprium at{que} pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uliare poetarum munus esse, Christi gloriam illustrare,</hi> beeing good reason that the heavenly infusion of such Poetry, should <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nde in his glorie, that had beginning from his goodnes, <hi>fit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ator, nascitur Poeta.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For the secound sorte thearfore, that eliminat Poets out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>heir citie gates; as though they wear nowe grown so bad, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hey could neither growe woorse, nor better, though it be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>omewhat hard for those to bee the onely men should want ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb facs="4"/>
that wear the onely causers of the building of them, and somewhat inhumane to thrust them into the woods, to liue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the beasts, who wear the first that call'd men out of the woods, from their beastly, and wilde life, yet since they will needes shoulder them out for the onely firebrands to inflame lust (the fault of earthly men, not heauenly Poetrie) I would gladly learne, what kind of professions theas men would bee intreated to entertaine, that so deride and disaffect Poesie: would they admit of Philosophers, that after they haue burnt out the whole candle of their life in the circular studie of Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, crie out at length, <hi>Se nihil prorsus seire?</hi> or should Musi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians be welcome to them, that <hi>Dant sine mente sonum</hi>—bring delight with them indeede, could they aswell expresse with their instruments a voice, as they can a sound? or would they most approve of Soldiers that defend the life of their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen either by the death of themselues, or their enemies? If Philosophers please them, who is it, that knowes not, that all the lights of Example, to cleare their precepts, are borowed by Philosophers from Poets; that without <hi>Homers</hi> examples, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ristotle</hi> would be as blind as <hi>Homer:</hi> If they retaine Musitians, who euer doubted, but that Poets infused the verie soule into the inarticulate sounds of musique; that without <hi>Pindar,</hi> &amp; <hi>Horace</hi> the Lyriques had beene silenced for euer: If they must needes entertaine Soldiers, who can but confesse, that Poets restore againe that life to soldiers, which they before lost for the safetie of their country; that without <hi>Uirgil, Aeneas</hi> had neuer beene so much as heard of. How then can they for shame deny commonwealths to them, who wear the first Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of them; how can they denie the blinde Philosopher, that teaches them, his light; the emptie Musitian that delights them, his soule; the dying Soldier, that defends their life, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie, after his owne death; let Philosophie, let <hi>Ethiques▪</hi> let all the Arts bestowe vpon vs this guift, that we be no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> thought deadmen, whilest we remaine among the liuing: it is
<pb facs="4"/>
onely Poetrie that can make vs be thought liuing men, when we lie among the dead, and therefore I thinke it vnequall to thrust them out of our cities, that call vs out of our graues, to thinke so hardly of them, that make vs to be so well thought of, to deny them to liue a while among vs, that make vs liue for euer among our Posteritie.</p>
   <p>So beeing nowe weary in perswading those that hate, I commend my selfe to those that love such Poets, as <hi>Plato</hi> speakes of, that sing divine and heroical matters. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding theas my idle howers, not idly spent, to good schollers, and good Christians, that haue ouercome their ignorance with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eason, and their reason, with religion.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>