<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An aduertisment to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117977_Bo1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13169</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23464</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117977</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An aduertisment to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The examination and confutation of a certaine scurrilous treatise entituled, The suruey of the newe religion, published by Matthew Kellison, in disgrace of true religion professed in the Church of England</title>
                 <author>Sutcliffe, Matthew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Weaver (Wever), Edmund</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sergier, Richard 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 113, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="71"/>
   <head>An aduertisment to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IDICVLOVS it is, gentle Reader, for him, that entreth into the Battle, to complaine of blowes. He that cōmeth to strike others must not thinke strāge, if he be striken himselfe. And yet I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue my aduersaryes blush not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, that heerein they haue receiued wrong. They, I say, that come like wolues with open mouth to deuoure vs, &amp; raile at M. LVTHER, Maister CALVIN, &amp; al the church of <hi>England,</hi> as if it consisted of <hi>Heretikes, Schismatikes, loose liuers,</hi> &amp; <hi>Atheistes,</hi> nay of a sort of men worse then <hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Pagans,</hi> finde fault with me, if I tell them of their heresies, Treasons, Gun-powder practises, Idolatryes, infidelitie, perjuries, and other vilanies.</p>
   <p>Whether they, or we haue reason, I referre my selfe to indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent judges, that shal read the Treatises of both the partyes. HILARY in his Book against CONSTANTIVS thought it no fault to speake sharply, if truely. <hi>Si falsa dicimus,</hi> saith he, <hi>infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis sit sermo malidicus.</hi> That is, <hi>if we speake vntruth, let our tarte speache seeme infamous.</hi> Otherwise he challengeth <hi>the liberty of Apostles in censuring manifest faults. Si vniuersa haec manifesta esse ostendimus</hi> saith he, <hi>non sumus extra apostolicam libertatem, &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destiam.</hi> Saint HIEROME <hi>apolog.</hi> 2. <hi>in Ruffin.</hi> thinketh it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>to barke for Christ, because Dogges barke for their Maisters. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes latrant pro dominis suis, tu non me vis latrare pro Christo?</hi> Beside that, when a man is accused of Heresie, hee <hi>would not haue him patient.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If then we neither shew impatiency, nor speake doggedlie, but only report those crimes truely, of which our aduersaryes are most guilty; it is then our aduersaries euill conscience that pincheth, rather then our tart stile that byteth. To let Dogges
<pb facs="71"/> baule without correcting were nothing else, but to encourage them in their dogged snarling and barking: and <hi>Bishop Iewell</hi> of reuerend memory and others, that haue vsed this mildenesse haue greatly confirmed our aduersaryes malice.</p>
   <p>This therfore vnderstand, that it is not out of stomacke, but out of iudgment, that wee take this course of plaine dealing. <hi>Phryx plagis emendatur.</hi> The PHRYGIAN, and such as are of his base humor, <hi>are bettred with stripes,</hi> rather then with gentle wordes. There distemper is <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, as THEOPHRASTVS saith <hi>in sympos. apud Plutarchum,</hi> That is, <hi>a drunkennesse without wine.</hi> But it may be corrected with a sad and tart answere. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, necessity forced vs, for the repelling of their malicious slaunders, to shewe, that they are to bee charged with those crimes justly, which they impute to innocēt men most falsely. And it may bee, if truth make them not cease their barking, yet shame will make them barke more softly.</p>
   <p>This is the reason of our doing: which if thou be indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, I hope thou wilt allow. If enimie, I hope thou canst not justly condemne. And if thou beest experimented in these courses, thou canst not chuse but acknowledge the same to bee both profitable, honest, and necessary. Profitable to represse the malice of such Curres, as continually barke against truth: honest for the defence of the pious memorie of the innocent: and necessary for the ending of these brablements. If the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries giue vs no occation to lay open theit faultes, we shall be content to burye them in silence. If they persist in rayling and reuiling at honest men, they must haue patience to heare our free answer. Against Popes, Cardinals, Monkes, Fryers, Masse-priestes and their seditious Salt-peter followers, wee cannot want either wordes, or matter. This is that which I thought good to aduertise thee, and which I hope will satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie all, if they bee indifferent. If not indifferent, they haue no reason to take vppon them, to bee our judges, nor we to vnder-goe their cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, nor you to mislike our stile, as too sharp and vnfitting.</p>
   <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>