<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>IOHN DE SERRES, TOVCHING THE VSE of this his Inuentorie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117097_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11931</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22244</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117097</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>IOHN DE SERRES, TOVCHING THE VSE of this his Inuentorie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A general inuentorie of the history of France : from the beginning of that monarchie, vnto the treatie of Veruins, in the year 1598. Written by Ihon de Serres. And continued vnto these times, out off the best authors which haue written of that subiect. Translated out of French into English, by Edward Grimeston Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Serres, Jean de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ponsonby, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ponsonby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 209, 5, 1052, 26 pages, portraits (woodcuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>IOHN DE SERRES, TOVCHING THE VSE of this his Inuentorie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S an Historie is the Theater of mans life, whereby all may learne one common lesson,<note place="margin">The general<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> vse of Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</note> by the goodly examples she repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents vnto their eyes, eares, and vnde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>standings. Euen so she inuites all men to view, heare, and to conceiue them well, what language soeuer she speakes, what subiect she <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of, what time shee notes, and what person soeuer shee represents. Thus offring her selfe to all with this excellent vse, she de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>erues rustly to bee imbraced, Experience verifying the testimonie which Antiquitie doth giue her. <hi>That shee is the Mis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>resse of Mans Life, the Testimonie of Trueth, the Recorder of Iustic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, the resplend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>t Beames of Vertue, the Register of Honour, the Trumpet of Fame, the Examiner of Actions, the Comptrouler of all Times, the</hi> Rendez-vous <hi>of diuerse Euents, the Schoole of Good and Euill, and the Soueraigne Iudge of all Men, and all Actions.</hi> This praise is common to all Histories▪ But as in a generall action euery one ought to haue a more speciall care of that which concernes his dutie: So in the generall Historie of all Nations, euery man is bound to be more perticularly informed of that which toucheth himselfe, and instructed in the mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the State, vnder which he is borne: By reason whereof I haue alwaies held the complaint of <hi>Thucidides</hi> (one of the chiefe Architects of a History) very considerable, <hi>That it was a great shame for</hi> Grecians <hi>to be Strangers in</hi> Greece; when as (busying themselues in forreine Histories) they were ignorant of their owne. May we not in like sort say, <hi>That it was a great shame that</hi> French-men <hi>should be strangers in</hi> France: for why should the ignorance of our Historie bee more excusable in vs, then of theirs in them. Doubtlesse we often seeke for that a farre off, which is neere vnto vs at home:<note place="margin">The partie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> vse of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>storie of <hi>France.</hi>
      </note> I commend the diligence of our men in searching out of forr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ine Histories. But if it may be lawfull to speake of this Subiect (as one of the common sort) I dare say there is no Nation vnder the cope of Heauen (without flattering my selfe with the loue of my Countrie) since Man was borne, that hath more admirable matters, or more worthy euents in euery kinde, and by consequence a History more memorable, then ours of <hi>France.</hi> Bee it <hi>for the forme of Gouernment</hi>: there was neuer Kingdome nor Common-weale established with goodlier lawes then our Monarchie. It is the true patterne of a perfect estate, such as the wise Politicians in former times vsed to discourse off in their <hi>Academie.</hi> A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oueraigne Commander, with Authoritie absolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oueraigne, but fortified with a power so well qualified with the Counterpoise of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour offices, that we may rightly call the <hi>French</hi> Monarchie, a mixture of all the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full gouernments of a Common-weale, by a well gouerned proportion, if the lawes prescribed be well obserued, the which I haue (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> that end) planted in the front of this building. Bee it <hi>for the greatnesse and st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ength of the State,</hi> although I know well that the foure Monarchies which comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nded ouer Nations, had larger dominions then the <hi>French</hi> yet was there neuer any Empire better vnited, better grounded, nor of longer continuance, more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> for the beautie and bountie of the Land, scituation
<pb facs="5"/>
of the Country, Riches of the people, and excellencie of wittes, eyther in Peace or Warre. As for the greatnesse of her Prouinces, what is the <hi>French</hi> Monarchie? but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse kingdomes vnited in one, and sundry Crownes annexed to one. But herein it excels the rest, that although they all in generall hold as it were of the Church, yet ours hath herein a speciall priuiledge, hauing diuerted from <hi>Europe</hi> that great deluge of Infidels, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> all Christendome with Shipwracke. To conclude, it yeelds to no Monarchie whatsoeuer, neither needs it any thing but good husbandrie. As <hi>for worthy men,</hi> which be a liuing law, and as it were the soule of an Estate, is there any nation whatsoeuer that can shew so many excellent personages, yea and Kings, as <hi>France</hi> may? There is no Vanitie more vaine, nor more vnworthy of a free minde, making profession of an Historie, wholy vowed to truth, then flatterie. But the most strictest <hi>Areopagite</hi> that euer was, cannot deny, but ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Monarchie may produce as many excellent Kings and Princes, as any other whatsoeuer. The three Races haue made shew in diuerse times: But the third had the continuance of a more temperate season, for the estab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>shing of an Estate. Let iudgement bee made by an vnpassionate tryall of their Reignes and Actions: to set downe Kings beautified with sundry gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as necessitie required, Valiant in Warre, Wise for Counsell, Resolute in Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie, Milde to pardon faults, when as Forgetfulnesse was necessary for the good of the State, and the quiet of the Realme.</p>
   <p>What shall wee say <hi>of great and worthy Euents,</hi> such as may chance to Man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good or euill? Hath any Historie more rare Examples then ours? eyther ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in the common sufferance of Prosperitie or Aduersitie, or extraordinarie in the greatest, and most <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ragicall rare accidents that may bee noted in any other Nation. there was neuer State reduced into greater difficulties, both within and without the Realme, and not subuerted: And in these extreame dangers, what valiant Resolutions. Truly our History sets downe in diuerse Reignes, the Courage and Constancie of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse Kings and People, in shew conquered, in effect Conquerors, in that they neuer dispaired of the Common-weale, in the middest of their dispaire: what loue of Kings to their Subiects, and of Subiects to their Kings, in common calamitie? Our Historie is full of these Examples, and of all things else considerable in the societie of Man, eyther in Warre or Peace, and which depends vpon their vertues, which held the Helme of this great Barke.<note place="margin">Excellencies remarkable in the miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous cons<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> State.</note> But as wee cannot hide, nor depriue of their due praise, (those goodly lights which shine in diuers parts of our History) by the many examples of Valour, Equity, Wisdome, Magnanimity, Modesty, Dexterity, and other Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> Vertues of our Kings, so to iudge thereof soundly, wee must flye to the Father of lights, who vsing these great and worthy personages for the building, preseruation or increase of this Monarchie, hath inriched them with great and pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ious graces, that acknowledging him the Author aswell of all these Vertues, as of the happy suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>e of things managed by them, we may learne to yeeld him Homage, for the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation, Continuance, and Increase of this great Estate.</p>
   <p>The negligence of our Kings hath too often brought our Royall Diadem into danger, whereof they made themselues vnworthy, making it weake and contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in their persons, who (by their basenesse and chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sh gouernment) suffered their Seruants to command absolutely. The Kingdome hath beene as it were dismembred by the diuision of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oyall commands. And by this meanes Brothers deuided by strange and selfe-wild discentions, haue abandoned all to spoyle: and from these domesticall diuisitions, haue sprung ciuill Warres, am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ddest the which, the Inferiours (fishing in a troubled Water) freed themselues, and opposing against their Soueraigne, became petty Kings. Wee haue seene their rage extend fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ther, attempting against the Kings person, imprisoning him, forcing him to quit his Crowne, and in the end reducing him to that extremity, as to dye despera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ely seeing himselfe so outragiously dealt withall. Wee haue seene Kings p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iso<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ers in their enemies hands, and abandoned by their Subiects, Kings besieged in their houses. We haue seene a poore young man ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb facs="5"/>
to guide a Ship (during the fury of a storme) without Helme, without Maste, without Sayles, and without Oares: beaten without by the Tempests, and within by the Saylers: Seized on in his Cabin by madde men, imbrued with the bloud of his most trusty Seruants, murthered before his eyes, yea euen in his bosome. Wee haue seene the Crowne of Kings in their minorities, set to sale by their Tutors, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came murtherers, and of Regents, Theeues, making themselues Kings: We haue seene a King in his non-age become madde, gouerned by the passions of Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, holding the chiefe degrees in state, which did striue to ruine it with in-b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Rages, and populer Tumults, by tragicall Massacres, and furious Hostilitie. Wee haue seene amidst these Combustions, the Stranger not onely awaked at this brute, but also Armed; entred within the Realme, and lodged within the bowels of the goodlyest Prouinces. And (which is more) installed in the Kings Authoritie by the Edict of a lawfull King, seated in the royall throne, hauing the Crowne on his head, with the Scepter and Purse in his hand, and a Daughter of <hi>France</hi> in his bedde, for a gage of this vniust pretension, a Sonne to warrant his possession, with the force and obedience of the Capitall Citty, and the first Princes of the bloud, armed with Power and Counsell to countenance these horrible confusions. Amiddest these ruinous disorders of our Countrie, who hath preserued the Realme of <hi>France,</hi> but hee that with one and the same hand, hath made both the lawe and the King of <hi>France</hi>?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>O my Countrymen,</hi> it is to you to whome your History is directed, hauing the chiefe interest in the estate of our Mother, although Strangers are forced to admire it. But what? Our Ancestors haue seene all these things specified here, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented in particuler in the discourse I now offer vnto you. But I beseech you what haue wee seene with our owne eyes, within these thirtye and fiue yeares? haue wee felt lesse miserie, or tryed weaker Remedies? What were our troubles, and to what extremitie were wee brought vnto of late yeares? By the conference of our Historie, with our Ancestors, ours serues as a Comentarie for the well vnderstanding thereof, yet can wee not denie but our age hath seene things farre more extraordinary and miraculous: So as wee may say <hi>That wee haue liued in a time of myracles</hi>; Without doubt our posterity will admire in particuler the Historie of our time, as the rarest part of the whole body, wee that haue seene it, should often belye our Eares and Eyes in reading or hearing it, when shee shall appeare in publ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ck to put vs in minde of that whereof wee were Eye witnesses, and therefore witnesses aboue all exception: But euery thing must bee done in order and time. Behold the first part of my enterprise, which it behooues you to looke vnto: SHALL IT then bee in vaine,<note place="margin">The speciall vse of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> Historie.</note> and without any fruite? it is not my intention, if the end of euery commendable enterprise be the VSE: Shall wee thinke that the knowledge of our Ancient Estate is vnprofitable, and in a time when as wee haue so great need of consolation? Truly in the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of our long calamitie, wee must needs bee oppressed with a troublesome care. But in feeling the paine, why seeke wee not the remedie? If wee often apply the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to things wee do eyther without lawe or against the lawe, how much more should it auaile vs being ioyned with reason? An Example rightly represented in the Historie of our Ancestors, serues vs now as a good guide to comfort vs, when as the like misery is common to vs and them. And if it please God to make vs like in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tion, what reason haue wee to complaine? At the least wee may therein obserue, that not at this time alone <hi>France</hi> is afflicted, and hath shewed her indisc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>etion. So likewise by the same reason, it is not now alone that shee hath felt the succours of her Protector, who preserues her, amends her follyes, and repaires her defects: without this p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>otecting hand, shee had long since perished. What shall wee then say? truely wee were much too blame to accuse our Fathers, and seeke to excuse our selues, of the like or greater errors: our waywardnesse were not pardonable, if our hearts should faint in these difficulties, seeing that wee learne in the same Historie, that our
<pb facs="6"/>
Fathers haue deliuered from the li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e afflictions. It is therefore a speciall vse of this History, to cast our eyes vpon the condition of our Predecessors, to mollifie our lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishings, as a necessary symptome of our inciuill warres, which like a continuall fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hath suckt (euen to the marrowe) all the vigour of this Estate, and hath not yet left it.</p>
   <p>We must accuse our impatience and nicenesse, if we shall complaine to haue been worse intreated then our fore-fathers, seeing wee obserue in them the like afflictions. Experience layes goodly grounds to reason, this certaine experience ingenders in our hearts hope of future things, without confusion or deceit. Do wee not then reape ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent fruites of this Historie? if by the deliuerance of our Fathers wee conclude and hope for ours, but in such sort and at such times, as the wise prouidence of God hath appointed, which ordinance neither Enemies can hinder, not Friends adu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nce: and theref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re the direction of this truth doth teach vs to saile in this Sea, euery one as hee ought according to his degree, expecting a happy harbor by the bountie and wisdome of him that rules the waues of humane confusions, as the soueraigne Iudge, holding in his hands both the hearts of Men &amp; the euents of Things▪ Do we greeue at our long troubles: let vs read the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eignes of <hi>Iohn, Charles</hi> the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t, <hi>Charles</hi> the sixt, and <hi>Charles</hi> the seuenth of our late los<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es? Let vs read the reigne of <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Val<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>is,</hi> and wee shall see that the losse of the same Cittie was deerer to him then to vs. As wee may neuer dissemble our losses, so i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> there a time to loose, and a time to gaine, if in our houses in the Countrie or Citty, all things succeed not as wee desire, who can with reason re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire alwaies the like successe in a State. To conclude, it to flatter the disease be no meanes to cure it, or to compaire without remedie, (seeing that choller and despaire brings no helpe to the diseased) let vs rather seeke for remedy then increase the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease, by a bootlesse complaint. If we wish for peace abroad, let vs lodge it first in our hearts at home. This inward peace shall be a good warrant for the generall, but wee are very sick, if we thinke by waywardnesse and furie to cure the disease. If then wee seeke any sound cure for our griefes, the Apothecaries shop is open, behold some pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiues. But what is that in regard of the serious reading of the Historie it selfe, as necessary at this day for <hi>French-men,</hi> as necessity doth force vs to seeke for consolation?</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">My end and purpose in this labour.</note>I haue endeuored therefore (<hi>my Countrymen</hi>) to trace out some slender obseruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for you in this little worke such as I could, I see it is not according to the dignitie and greatnesse of the subiect, worthy in truth of a good writer, rather fit for that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure age, when the most ancient <hi>Druides</hi> had a maxime, <hi>not to write at all,</hi> or of those which haue left vs these small Abridgements, the which we now vse for <hi>want of better.</hi> and without doubt if our History had incountred such spirits as the <hi>Greeke</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> did▪ it had been nothing i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>feriour to any of them, in Beauty and Profit. This is the onely cause why our Countrimen haue not read our History, hauing not enioyed the light of Excellent Writers▪ to represent her in her liuely colours, according to her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serts. And although ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>France</hi> hath heretofore had cause to complaine in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, yet now that fault is partly repaired, by the industrie of some that striue to plant and beautifie it. Amongst all that haue laboured in this subiect, <hi>Du Haillan</hi> in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion exceeds all others with immortall commendations, hauing so happily clensed these ouer-growne busnes and made so plaine a pathe in this thick and obscure forrest: if zeale to doe my Countrie seruice, and hop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> by my example to awake the learned to doe better, we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e not my iust excuse, where should I hide me from the blotte of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>considerate rashnesse? especially being in this Citty of <hi>Paris,</hi> nor onely the capitall Citty of <hi>France,</hi> the fertile Mother of goods wittes, but also the <hi>Rendez-vous</hi> of the greatest miracles in the world. I will therefore speake freely, that in presuming to beautifie this History, I haue taken for the onely obiect of my aime, <hi>To seeke the truth with the vse thereof,</hi> and to giue you some cause of content. Regard not my tongue, I offer you the simple truth without painting, the which I haue curiously searched for in many good Bookes, which my necessary aboade here hath giuen me meanes to
<pb facs="6"/>
obtaine, and the desire I haue to serue you, occasion to imploy them, for as I am who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vowed to the publike, so will I yeeld an accompt not onely of my idlenesse, but also of my imployments, I haue therefore resolued to vndertake a labour that should not bee vnprofitable, in preparing you a way to learne your Historie in the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls, with lesse paine and more profit. I do therefore call this my endeuour an IN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VENTORIE, by the direction whereof, you may see the body and euery part at your pleasure. If I may perswade the Reader to conferre this my labour with the writings of others vpon this subiect (both old and new) I shall not then need to put in caution, but be of an assured hope to obtaine a testimonie of my fidelitie, And it may be in time, of some diligence, at the least I bring nothing, that hath not beene well purified and applyed to the vse. The fruite depends on the blessing of God, by the iudgement of such as shall read mee, I will protect onely for that which doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne my selfe: I haue vsed the Rule, Square, Lead and Compasse, to obserue propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion both in s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>le and subiect, that in my course I might direct you to the firme truth; if it bee with that light and breuitie I pretended, I shall haue cause to thanke God, and to labour in some subiect of greater moment, yet I haue done my best indeauour that the learned may supply my defect, in doing better. The course is open, euery one may runne it. I leaue the prize to them that shall doe best, my intent was onely to profit the publique: and therefore I bring not an Abridgement, but an INVEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TORY. I haue searched the very Springs of such as went before me. The first haue not hindred the second: and why should the second take it ill to be followed by others? one kinde of meate may be diuersly seasoned to good purpose. A small Dyall markes the houres in like proportion to a great Clock: It is one of my wishes, that this good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie subiect may be set to open view, that the learned may stri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e to exceed one another, and leaue no excuse for our <hi>French-men</hi> to be any more strangers in <hi>France,</hi> making the way easie and profitable: If in this resp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ct my zeale and integritie may bee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued of my Countrie, why should I repent the imployment of some houres in so goodly and worthy a worke, as a testimonie (at the least) that I desire to discharge my dutie.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>To conclude, my Countrymen,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The occasion of this Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</note> I must not conceale from you the chiefe cause that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced mee to compile this worke. About sixe and twenty yeares since, I was thrust forth vpon the Theater, (being very young) to represent the Historie of our mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: the desire of forraine Nations begat this desseigne, being curious to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand a particuler relation of our Tragedies. By reason whereof I presented this my first worke in Latin, that Strangers might vnderstand it. I held it for an Abortiue, and esteemed the losse but lightly, yet was the successe greater then my proiect, for being imbraced by the publique beyond desert, it hath so increased, that of one Booke there is made fifteene, and corrected with diuerse impressions. And as the Child increased, so the Father had meanes to do him good. GOD suffering me to liue to be a witnesse of great accidents, not onely as many of my Country-men, that sees the danger from a safe Porte, but imbarked in full Seas amidst these common tempests: for being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in some and no small affayres (both within and without the Realme) I had the Honor to be admitted into Kings and Princes Cabinets, to manage publique causes of Prouinces, and to conferre with the heads of Parties, to learne from their owne mouthes, and from others that had authoritie and imployment vnder them, the Truth of all that passed: so as being able to giue a reason for many things which I had seene, I may likewise giue an account of most that hath passed, by the proceedings and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions of both parties. I will adde to this opportunitie the priuate deuotion which hath alwayes held my minde inclined to this care, to gather together whatsoeuer was done, when as necessity of affaires thrust mee into imployments: and this my desire succeeded so happily, that both great and small haue fauourablie imparted vnto mee whatsoeuer might benefit concerning this subiect. So as I haue made a iust collection of all the substance, that may serue for the building of a perfect Historie, from the
<pb facs="7"/>
beginning of the troubles to this day. The end of this painfull labour depends of him from whom proceeds the euents of all our prayers. To him therefore I referre my selfe, protesting onely of that which is in mee. As therefore I aduow my selfe both Debtor of this worke, and Author of these Bookes, which wander among men: so I protest the fault shall not be mine, if all turne not to the publique good, wherevnto it is appointed, as by the order shall be found most expedient. And expecting an end of this great masse, my intent was onely (as may easily appeare by the Table of the third Race) to set before your eyes (as in one Mappe) a Summarie of the ancient History, very necessary for the vniting and resemblance of that which hath happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in our time. But the iudgement of my learned friends, hath made mee to take a new course, that the length of so tedious a paiment might not bee troublesome vnto you, in giuing you the whole Historie vnto this day, fashioned of this meane and base stature, whereof I now offer you this first part, as a Patterne of the whole peece, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barking my selfe from the maine land in this tempestuous Sea, which must needs bee fearfull vnto mee, both by the feeling of mine owne weaknesse, and the apprehensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of diuerse iudgements, as the Ebbing and Flowing of the Ocean. I durst not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard all this small modell at one voyage. Goe forth my first parcell, and seeke thy fortune, learne by the Chapmen, how the market goes, that by thy successe I may resolue with lesse danger to Ship the rest, the which in the meane time shall attend (in a safe Harbor) the winde of your fauourable contents.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>