<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Here followeth the Letter of an vn∣knowne Priest, remaining in London, sent to the Authour, excepting against fiue points in this booke.</title>
           <author>Bl., Th.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117166_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19252</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5665</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117166</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Here followeth the Letter of an vn∣knowne Priest, remaining in London, sent to the Authour, excepting against fiue points in this booke.</title>
                 <author>Bl., Th.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Worke, more vvorke, and a little more work for a masse-priest : Reviewed and augmented by the authour. VVith an epistle of an vnknowne priest remaining in London, sent to the authour, excepting against fiue points therein. With the authours answere thereunto: returned vnto the priest within twelue dayes after the receipt of the priests exceptions</title>
                 <author>Cooke, Alexander</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 153, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="correspondence">
   <pb n="136" facs="74"/>
   <div type="letter">
      <head>Here followeth the Letter of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne Priest, remaining in London, sent to the Authour, excepting against fiue points in this booke.</head>
      <head type="sub">To Mr. Alexander Cooke at Leeds in York-shire.</head>
      <p>MAster <hi>COOKE,</hi> with the like desire of your spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall good, as of mine owne, I addresse this briefe letter vnto you, in stead of larger an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere to your booke now twice augmented: which in the first Impression you call: <hi>Worke for a Masse-priest:</hi> in the second, <hi>More Worke for a Masse-priest:</hi> and in the third, <hi>Yet more Worke for a Masse-priest.</hi> All which sheweth your zeale against the Romane Church, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Sacrifice of Masse, and all the Romane Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke religion: but neither disproueth the same which you so hate, nor proveth your contrary opinions to bee groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in truth. Neither doe you herein obserue any forme or good method of doctrine, whereby to discusse which is the true Church of Christ, what assurance of truth it hath, nor how necessarie it is, that every one, which desireth to bee saved, must bee a living member thereof: and therefore no marvell that no Catholike hath hitherto bestowed labour and cost to answere in print your confused triviall obiections. Which of how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle importance they are, and vpon how silly surmises, you impute errours to the Catholike Religion, may sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="137" facs="74"/> be conceived by examination of a few of them: For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, all proceeding from one spirit. See then, deare Sir, your faults committed in your first obiections; and so I shall suppose you will be as loath to haue the rest discussed, as I hold it superfluous to proceede further in confuting them.</p>
      <p>First, our noble King reporteth (say you) that his mother sent word to the Archbishop who did baptize him, to forbeare to vse spittle in his baptisme; for she would not haue a pockie Priest to spit in her childes mouth. Marke, I pray you, foure manifest vntruths in these words. For His Maiestie could not, at the time of his baptisme, know what message his mother sent to any man, but onely hath heard since what some other hath reported: therefore it is a manifest vntruth to say, His Maiestie reporteth that, which he cannot, and therefore doth not report.</p>
      <p>Secondly, it is incredible that the Catholicke Queene would forbid the ceremonie of spittle, which holy Church vseth.</p>
      <p>Thirdly, it is doubtlesse a wicked lie, to say, that she cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Archbishop a pockie Priest.</p>
      <p>Fourthly, she could not say, and consequently would not say, that the Priest spitteth into the childes mouth. For the spittle is not spit into the childs mouth, but is gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put to his mouth with the Priests finger; which cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie holy Church vseth, amongst others, by imitation of Christs example, putting spittle and dust vpon a blind mans eyes, and putting his finger into the eares, and touching the tongue of a deafe and dumbe man whom hee cured.</p>
      <p>To these foure, you adde three more vntruths in your first obiection, against the worthy Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine:</hi>
         <pb n="138" facs="75"/> first, you vntruly translate his wordes, where hee saith: <hi>Non est verum, eâ ceremoniâ salivam Presbyteri in os infantuli inspui:</hi> which words in true English are these: It is not true, that by that ceremonie the Priests spittle is spit into the childes mouth: for which you would make him to say thus: It is not true, that the Priests spit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle vsed in Baptisme is put into the childes mouth.</p>
      <p>Secondly, you vntruly charge him to denie that spittle is put into a childes mouth, for he denieth it not to be <hi>put,</hi> but to be <hi>spit</hi> into the mouth of the baptized.</p>
      <p>Thirdly, you vntruly conclude that the Cardinall calleth his Maiesties report into question, which he doth not, but their report that told his Maiestie so incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a thing.</p>
      <p>In your next obiection you vntruly charge the same renowned Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> to contradict both our noble King, and Pope <hi>Pius Quintus.</hi> For neither doth hee name our King in those words which<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>your selfe here cite, saying onely in generall: <hi>Non est verum, nomen Cardinalis ademptum alijs, &amp; solis Romanis reserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum:</hi> It is not true that the name of Cardinall is taken from others, and reserved onely to Romanes. Neither doth he contradict the Popes decree, the tenure whereof decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, that the eminent and proper title of Cardinall belongeth to the onely Cardinalls Colledge of Rome, and not to any other Church. Neverthelesse, the name Cardinall in a lesse dignitie, and lesse autoritie, is given to other Ecclesiasticall persons in the Church of Toledo: whose Archbishop, &amp; also the Archbishop of Compostella, are ordinarily Cardinalls of Rome.</p>
      <p>In your third obiection you charge the same gracious Cardinall with a lie, for saying: <hi>Nefas est apud Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantes
<pb n="139" facs="75"/> quenquam creari Episcopum, nisi vnius sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem vxoris virum:</hi> which hee reporteth as their generall practise according to their common doctrine, not allowing the vow and obligation of single life. And albeit some of your Bishops doe not marrie, yet they doe not binde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues from marrying. And the farre greater part haue taken wiues, the rest hold it vnlawfull to vow perpetuall chastitie.</p>
      <p>In your fourth, you charge all Catholickes with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth, for saying, that all the Apostles were continent from their wiues, after they followed Christ; which is clearely gathered by our Saviours wordes, naming wiues amongst other things, which his Apostles had left for his sake. Against which cleare testimonie you oppose improbabilitie, as you imagine, that Saint <hi>Peters</hi> daughter could not bee beautifull at the age of sixty eight yeares, to wit, in the ninety eight yeare of Christ. But perhaps there is an errour in the number, and for ninety eight should haue beene written the sixty eighth yeare of our Lord: and then shee was but thirie eight yeares of age. Also she might be faire and beautifull at sixty eight yeares of age, which is more reasonable to be supposed then to denie the plaine assertion of the Gospell,<note place="margin">Mat. 19. 27▪</note> that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles left all things for Christs service, and namely their wiues. By the way also obserue, that Saint <hi>Peters</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dwelt &amp; died in <hi>Rome,</hi> where Count <hi>Flaccus</hi> a <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> desired to marry her; which is a signe of <hi>Saint Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> residing there sometimes, besides many more euident proofes and monuments testifying the same.</p>
      <p>In your fifth obiection you would proue that all nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Bishops did not liue continent from their wiues whom they had married before Priesthood, by the words of Saint
<pb n="140" facs="76"/>
         <hi>Gregorie Nazianzen,</hi> bringing in his father in a verse, saying thus vnto him: <hi>Nondum tot anni sunt tui, quotiam in sacris mihi peracti sunt victimis;</hi> Thou hast not yet so many yeares as are passed with me in holy sacrifices. Which must either bee vnderstood in some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sense, then of the yeares of Saint <hi>Gregories</hi> age, or else it should be contrary to his cleare affirmation, saying in his funerall oration, that himselfe was borne before his father was either Priest or baptized. And so being rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable to interprete his verse by his proofe, this instance will not serue your turne. But it sheweth evidently, that his father was a sacrificing Priest. And such are Masse-priests whom you so contemne, because we offer the holie sacrifice of Masse.</p>
      <p>And this may suffice to shew by example of your fiue first obiections how feeble and frivolous the rest also are. And therefore Masse priests are imployed in better workes then to lose good time in answering your idle questions: And your selfe may be better occupied in seeking the true Church, and the infallible authoritie thereof, and so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning into the same, may saue your soule, which I wish you to doe with all my hears. From London this Feast of <hi>Corpus Christi.</hi> 1623.</p>
      <closer>
         <signed>Yours to serue you in Iesus Christ, <hi>Th. Bl.</hi> a Masse-priest.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="response">
      <pb n="141" facs="76"/>
      <head>Now come wee to the answere of the said letter, returned vnto the Priest within twelue dayes after the receipt thereof.</head>
      <p>SIR Masse-priest, I received the letter which you (as you phrase it) addressed vnto mee, in stead o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> larger answere vnto a booke of mine, intitled: <hi>Yet more Worke for a Masse-priest.</hi> In which letter you taxe me in generall, with confusion of matter, with want of forme and good Method; with proposing feeble, and frivolous, and triviall obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and idle questions; with imputing errours to your Catholike Religion vpon silly surmises; with failing in proofe of my owne opinions, and disproo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving yours: All which I passe over as words of Course, holding opinion; That generall and naked accusations of adversaries, deserue not so much as generall and naked denialls: the rather, for that you show a great deale of simplicitie, and ignorance, in the particulars, wherein you vndertake to let me see my faults committed: for I take it no breach of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, to thinke, that he hath nothing to say for proofe of his generall assertions, who saith nothing to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose for proofe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> his speciall.</p>
      <p>Now that you haue nothing to say to purpose for proofe of your speciall accusations against mee, I doubt not to make it plaine to your owne selfe,
<pb n="142" facs="77"/> though forestalled with preiudice. For thus at the first rush you bring me in saying: <hi>Our Noble King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, that his mother sent word to the Archbishop who did baptize him, to forbeare to vse spittle in his Baptisme, for she would not haue a pockie Priest to spit in her childes mouth.</hi> And presently you crie: <hi>Marke, I pray you, foure mainfest vntruthes in these wordes:</hi> yet the proofes you make thereof are ridiculous: for in way of proving the first, thus you argue; <hi>His Maiestie could not at the time of his Baptisme know what Message his Mother sent to any man, but onely hath heard since what some other hath reported. Therefore it is a manifest vntruth to say, His Maiestie reporteth, His mother sent word to the Archbishop, &amp;c.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Which Argument of yours is brainelesse; for it presupposeth, that no man can report any thing from the report of another. No man can report a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing which was done about the time of his Birth, and Baptisme; much lesse before he was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and borne. If this Argument of yours bee good, I cannot report what lascivious talke passed betweene an English woman, and <hi>Aeneas Sylvius</hi>
(who not long after was poped, and called by the name of <hi>Pius</hi> 2.) in an Inne at <hi>Strawsburgh,</hi> where they casually met: I cannot report, how he wished her, when shee went to bed, to leaue her chamber doore vnbolted, promising hee would come and lie with her, as indeede he did: she proving with childe vpon that nights meeting: I cannot report, that this <hi>Aeneas Sylvius</hi> committed the bringing vp of that child thus begotten, to his father, wondring that his father was not glad, that by it (though got
<pb n="143" facs="77"/> in whoring) he was made a grandfather: for at the time of my Baptisme, I knew no more of this, then his Maiestie at the time of his Baptisme knew what Message his Mother sent to any man. Only I haue heard since, what some other, or rather, what <hi>Aene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Sylvius</hi> himselfe hath<note n="a" place="margin">Epist. 15 Genito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri de suo filio, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter opera Sylvij, impress. Basil. pag. 510, 511.</note> written hereof.</p>
      <p>At the time of my Baptisme, I knew not that any man had written,<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. Raulins ser. 31. de poeni. tentia, impress. Paris. 1514.</note>
         <hi>Qui sunt Romae, et prope loca in quibus habentur magnae Indulgentiae, &amp; vbi sunt mag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>a peregrinagia, quia prope remedia habent, communiter sunt pessimi:</hi> That they who dwell at Rome, and neere vnto such places where large Indulgences are granted, &amp; whereunto there is greatest resort of Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims, are commonly the worst people, because they haue so present remedies. I knew not at the time of my Baptisme, that any man had written,<note n="c" place="margin">Molinaeus teste Gregorio Capuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cino in Enchirid. Eccles. impress. Venetij▪ 1588.</note>
         <hi>Quàm peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culosum Principi habere Consiliarios Papisticos:</hi> It is very dangerous for Princes, to haue popish Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellours. I knew not then that any was so evill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited of the Romanes, that they should write,<note n="d" place="margin">Salvianus Massil. Episcopus de gubernat. Dei lib. 6.</note>
         <hi>Vbi Romani, ibi vitia:</hi> where Romanes come, there is ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guerie enough. Onely since I haue heard, or rather read so much in others. And therefore if your Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke be good, I cannot report these things: hee, who (though I told them) should say, I did report them, should say a manifest vntruth. But if this be a grosse conceit (as doubtlesse it is) you must acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge you did me wrong, yea your selfe wrong, in charging me with vntruth: for saying, <hi>Our Noble King reporteth, &amp;c.</hi> though he knew not at the time of his Baptisme what Message she sent to any man, &amp;c. for therin you belied me, and bewrayed much weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in arguing.</p>
      <p>
         <pb n="144" facs="78"/> But perhaps you haue quit your selfe better in proving the second vntruth wherwithall you charge me.</p>
      <p>Truly never a whit: for you gather the vntruth wherewith you charge me, from those words, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I report from our Noble King, <hi>That his Mother forbad the vse of spittle in Baptisme:</hi> and your onely reason to convince me of vntruth therein is, for that
(as you say) <hi>it is incredible the Catholicke Queen would forbid the Ceremonie of spittle which holy Church vseth.</hi> Which answer first presupposeth, that he is chargeable with vntruth, who reports any vntruth from another: else how can I bee charged with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth, who am the reporter onely from another man what was said? Secondly, this presupposeth, that holy Church vseth to put spittle into their mouthes who are baptized: else, why should the practise of holy Church bee mentioned to proue that a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Queene would not forbid such a Ceremonie? But these are false suppositions; for which concerns the first: That every man is not chargeable with vntruth who reports an vntruth, it is plaine by Scripture, wherein many vntruths are truly report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. As for example, Gen. 37. 33, <hi>Moses</hi> truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports that <hi>Iacob</hi> said, A wicked beast had devoured his sonne <hi>Ioseph:</hi> though indeed it was vntrue that a wicked beast had devoured <hi>Ioseph.</hi> Secondly, that holy Church, your holy Church, vseth not to put spittle into their mouthes who are to bee baptized, all your bookes, which speake of the Ceremonies v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in Baptisme at this day, generally doe witnesse: but especially your Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine;</hi> for he saith
<pb n="145" facs="78"/> expressely,<note place="margin">Apolog. pro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> sua ad magnae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> Brit. Regē, cap. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>▪</note> that <hi>solùm aures &amp; nares salivâ tanguntur:</hi> the eares and nostrills onely are touched with spittle in Baptisme. Neither hee, nor any other writer in this age, knew of any spittle, which was put into the mouthes of such as were to be baptized. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the second vntruth, which you would fasten on me, returnes vpon your selfe, accompanied with Arguments proceeding from a little head.</p>
      <p>And so will the third vntruth wherewithall you charge me, returne likewise: for it consists in this, that I say, <hi>Our noble King reports, his Mother said shee would not haue a pockie Priest to spit in her childes mouth.</hi> Which, as you say, (but proue not) <hi>is doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse a wicked lie.</hi> For to suppose it were a wicked lie (which I beleeue not) what is that to me? It is true I say, <hi>Our noble King reports it.</hi> If there were an vntruth in it, yet I should be innocent of it. But why Sir Masse-priest, are you so confident, that <hi>it is doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse a wicked lie, she called him a pockie Priest?</hi> I hope you doubt not, but that your Church, notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her holinesse, hath had many pockie Priests: and perhaps she knew more by him then either you or I: Sure I am, that his Maiesties grandfather
(who as some of you say was a Catholike) hanged him within a few yeares after for an arrant Traytor: And if an arrant Traytor, why not a pockie Priest? And if hee being a Catholike hanged him; why might not she (though a Catholike) call him pockie Priest?</p>
      <p>The fourth vntruth wherewithall you charge me is, That I say our noble King reports, his Mother said, <hi>the Priest spitteth in the childes mouth;</hi> for shee
<pb n="146" facs="79"/> could not say so, and con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>equently would not say so, say you: whereof you giue this reason, <hi>viz. That the spittle is not spit into the childes mouth, but is gently put into the childes mouth with the Priests finger.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>In this, Sir Priest, you shew your selfe a young Priest, and one of little skill in your Pontificalls, and of small practise in your profession: for at this day, and in those Countreys, there is no spittle put into any childs mouth by any manner of way, as before I noted: though if it vvere as you say, my credit is no vvay tainted by this, for I onely relate it as from our King, in vvhose booke you may finde it.</p>
      <p>Here by the way you take occasion to tell, how your holie Church vseth this Ceremonie by Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Christs example, putting spittle and dust vpon a blind mans eyes, and putting his finger into the eares, and touching the tongue of a deafe and dumbe man whom he cured.</p>
      <p>Which note you might more honestly haue pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by, then made, considering it bewrayeth a great deale of foolerie in your holy Church. For is it not foolerie to vse <hi>your spittle</hi> in baptizing, because our Saviour Christ with <hi>his spittle</hi> made a kind of clay, by which hee miraculously cured a man that was blind? Is it not foolerie, to touch with your spittle the eares and nostrills of such as are to bee baptized; because our Saviour Christ touched the eares and the tongue of one whom he cured of deafnesse and dumbnesse with his spittle? Is your spittle answera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his spittle? Is there any wisdome, in apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that to spirituall vses, which he applyed onely to
<pb n="147" facs="79"/> corporall? to doe that ordinarily, which he did one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly once extraordinarily? to doe that to every one, which he did to one onelie? To omit, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing your shew of imitating him, you neither vse Clay in Baptisme, nor touch the tongue of the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, as he touched the tongue of the dumbe. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinkes this your imitation is Apish: certainlie you haue no warrant for it from antiquitie: the holie primitiue Church knew no such Ceremonie in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme. Wherefore I subscribe to him who said, <hi>Your spittle</hi> is fitter for the <hi>Spittle,</hi> then for the <hi>Church.</hi> And let this serue for answere vnto the first fower vntruthes which you thought you did see, but did not see, in the first words of my first obiection as you call it.</p>
      <p>To the foure former vntruthes, you say, I haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded three more against <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> The first whereof is, that I vntrulie translate his wordes, making him say thus: <hi>It is not true, that the Priests spittle vsed in Baptisme is put into the childes mouth: Whereas he saith no more in true English then: It is not true, the Priests spittle is spit into the Childes mouth.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>But this is one of your fooleries, and no vntruth of mine: My translation of his wordes is answera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his meaning; for he fansied no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene spitting in, and putting in of spittle: Hee knew no vse of spittle for any part, but for eares and Nostrills. <hi>Solùm aures &amp; nares salivâ tanguntur,</hi> saith your Cardinall.</p>
      <p>And the answere which I make to this supposed vntruth, may seeme to cleere me from the next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth,
<pb n="148" facs="80"/> wherewithall you charge me: If so be there be any difference betweene the one, and the other, which my wit serues me not to see. For, secondly you say, <hi>you vntruely charge him to deny, that the spittle is put into a childs mouth, for he denyeth it not to be put▪ but to be spit into the mouth of the baptized.</hi> For, if <hi>so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lùm aures et nares tanguntur salivâ,</hi> then spittle is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>spit in,</hi> or <hi>put in.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>
         <hi>The third vntruth against</hi> Bellarmine <hi>wherewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all you charge me is,</hi> I vntruely conclude, the Cardinal calleth his Maiesties report into question, which he doth not, but their report who told his Maiestie so incredible a thing.</p>
      <p>To which I answere, That his Maiestie reporting all that I report from him, without any intimation, that he had it by information of others, (though no doubt hee had it from others) your Cardinall answering thereto saith, <hi>Non est verum &amp;c.</hi> Its not true &amp;c. Which argueth your Cardinall calleth his Maiesties report into question, and no other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons: for there is no mention in your Cardinals words of any third person. And so of the seven vntruthes wherewithall you charge me, you haue not proved one.</p>
      <p>In my second obiection, as you call it, you say: I <hi>vntruely charge your Cardinal with contradicting both our Noble King &amp; Pope Pius Quintus.</hi> And first in way of proving, that your Cardinall did not contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict our Noble King, you tell me: that he names not our King in the words I cite, saying only in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall: <hi>Non est verum, nomen Cardinalis alijs ademp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ac solis Romanis reseruatum.</hi> It is not true that
<pb n="149" facs="80"/> the name of Cardinal is taken from others, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued only to Romaines.</p>
      <p>In rendring which reason you shew your selfe a strange man, in that you require to the contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of one another a particular naming of the person contradicted. You affirme I made seven vntruthes in my first instance; I say, not naming you, but speaking in generall, yet answering you: <hi>Non est verū, &amp;c.</hi> It is not true, that I made seven vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths. Do not I▪ for all the generality of my speech, contradict you? Now such is the case of our King, and your Cardinall; our King saith, that the title of Cardinall, Priests and Deacons, is restrained one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Parish Priests and Deacons of Rome: your Cardinall answering thereto saith, <hi>Non est verum, &amp;c.</hi> Doth not your Cardinall contradict his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty, though he name him not? I am sure hee denies that to bee true, which his Maiestie affirmes to bee true, and is not that to contradict him?</p>
      <p>
         <hi>In way of proving that I vntruly charge your Cardinall with contradicting the Popes decree, you tell me:</hi> That the tenure of your Popes decree declareth that the eminent and proper title of Cardinall belongeth to the onely Cardinalls Colledge of Rome, and not to any other Church: Neuerthelesse the name Cardinall in a lesse dignitie, and lesse authoritie, is given to other Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall persons in the Church of Toled<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</p>
      <p>But the words cited in my booke, are too preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to bee avoided with such a watrish distinction, of eminent, and lesse eminent Cardinalls. For the Author having noted that some Churches, besides the Romane, had certaine Prebends which were
<pb n="150" facs="81"/> called Cardinalls, as namely, <hi>Compostella, Ravenna, Millan,</hi> and <hi>Naples:</hi> and there were two sorts of Cardinalls, <hi>viz. Papae, &amp; Episcoporum;</hi> some made by the Pope, some by Bishops; doth thereupon take occasion to make mention how <hi>Pius quintus in su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> diplomate hoc nomē in omnibus alijs Ecclesiis praeterquā in Ro. extinxit, &amp; solū Cardinalis nomē cōpetere voluit Cardinalibus S. R. E. à Papa creatis.</hi> By which is plaine, <hi>Pius</hi> 5. cried downe all Cardinals which were not of the Popes making, and by consequent which were not Cardinalls of the Church of Rome; He decreed that none but Cardinals of the Church of Rome, should be called so in proper, or improper sense.</p>
      <p>In the next instance, which you call my third ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, you say I charge your Cardinall with a lie, for saying: <hi>Nefas est, &amp;c. The Protestants hold it an heynous offense to make any man a Bishop, who is not at least the husband of one wife.</hi> But you cleere him not from lying. Onely you tell me, that he reporteth that, as the Protestants generall practise; according to their common doctrin, not allowing the vow and obligation of single life: meaning, he so said of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, because they generally teach, that it is not safe to vow to liue vnmarried.</p>
      <p>Which is a poore defence of him, for it is one thing to teach, that it is not safe to vow to liue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>married: and another thing to say, that of necessitie a man must marrie. We teach, Clergie men may marry, they need not vow against marrying: but we teach not, that Clergie men must marrie. This was <hi>Vigilantius</hi> errour, if <hi>Ierom</hi> misreport him not: from which wee are cleered by your Masters of
<pb n="151" facs="81"/>
         <hi>Rhemes, Annot. in</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 2. and by our practise, for, as I haue noted in my booke, we haue at this present, and had heretofore, many wiue-les Bishops.</p>
      <p>Neither makes it any thing to your purpose, that the farre greater part haue taken wiues; and that all hold it vnlawfull to vow perpetuall chastitie, for that is not the poynt wherewithall <hi>Bellarmin</hi> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth vs, and for which his charging of vs, I thinke he deserues the Whetstone.</p>
      <p>In my fourth Instance, you say, I charge all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes with vntruth, for saying, <hi>That all the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles were continent from their wiues after they followed Christ.</hi> Wherein you say truly, for indeed I charge them so. But you cannot answere my Argument, whereby I convince them of vntruth. Onely you say, that perhaps <hi>Petronilla</hi> (vpon whose age my Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is grounded) was but thirtie eight yeares of age, and not sixtie eight, as I say, when Count <hi>Flac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> doted on her for her beautie, there being an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in the number: but to proue an errour in the number, you neither giue reason, nor cite Authour, which argues your Answer is conceited.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>Oh, but if I may beleeue you,</hi> your Catholicke as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sertion is clearely gathered by our Saviours words, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming wiues among other things which his Apostles had left for his sake. <hi>And therfore my Argument though probable is not to be beleeved.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>The Apostles left their houses, as wel as their wiues; for they left all, saith Saint <hi>Peter, Mat.</hi> 19. 27. yet they kept their property in their houses still: else how is it written <hi>Math.</hi> 8. 14. That Iesus came to <hi>Peters</hi> house: and <hi>Ioh.</hi> 19. 27. That <hi>Iohn</hi> tooke the virgin
<pb n="150" facs="82"/>
         <hi>Mary</hi> home vnto him: and that <hi>Mathew Luke</hi> 5. 29. made our Saviour a great feast in his owne house, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven after it is written of him, that he left all and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Christ▪ Now, if they might keepe their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, notwithstanding their leaving all, why not their wiues also? vnlesse you can shew they were more strictly tyed to their houses, then to their wiues.</p>
      <p>Againe, the forsaking of all, and in speciall of wiues, whereof our Saviour speakes <hi>Math.</hi> 19. 29, is such a forsaking, as is required of all Christians: for our Saviour having told his Apostles what reward they should haue for forsaking all: hee goeth on, shewing that not onely they, but all such as leaue their wiues for his names sake, should bee bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully rewarded. But you dare not say, that all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians are so to forsake al, as that ever after they must liue continent from their wiues.</p>
      <p>Thirdly, the forsaking of all, commended by our Saviour, implies forsaking of brethren, and children, as well as of wiues, <hi>Math.</hi> 19. 29. And yet it bindes not men to refuse (when occasion serveth) perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of Offices and kindnesse to their brethren, and children. And why then should it restraine men from performance of husbandly Offices and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to their wiues, in time and place?</p>
      <p>The truth is, men are not bound to forsake all, except they cannot keepe them with performance of their dutie to God: they are not to forsake the lawfull vse of such things as they haue, vnlesse the enioyment of them may hinder them in Gods ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. Now what can living with a mans wife, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a man in Gods service, seeing the bed is vndefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led? <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 7.</p>
      <p>
         <pb n="151" facs="82"/> In my fifth obiection (as you call it) I would proue, you say, <hi>That all Bishops did not liue continent from their wiues whom they had marryed before▪ Priesthood.</hi> And in this you speake truely. But to my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment fetched out of <hi>Gregory Nazianzens</hi> discourse in verse of his owne life, to proue my assertion, you answer weakely. For to the words which I alledge, importing plainely: that <hi>Gregorie Nazianzen</hi> had not liued so many yeares (much lesse <hi>Caesarius</hi> his younger brother) as his father <hi>Gregory</hi> had lived a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop: you answer only, That <hi>he cleerely affirmes in his funerall Oration, That himselfe was borne before his father was either Priest or baptized,</hi> which you can never proue. He made one Oration, at the funerall of his father: an other, at the funerall of his brother <hi>Caesarius:</hi> a third, at the funerall of his sister <hi>Gorgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia:</hi> a fourth, at the funerall of his friend <hi>Saint Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sil.</hi> Doe me the favour to write me out the words, wherein he so cleerely affirmes that which you say, and let me know in which of these funerall Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons I may find them. In the meane, I rest perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded there is no such thing. In which perswasion I am the more confident,<note place="margin">To. 6. de ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>re. Ca. 40.</note> because <hi>S. Austin</hi> witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth, that even in his time, the Catholicke Church had many both Clergie men, and Monkes, who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with their wiues like married men. And wee reade,<note place="margin">Socrat. Hist. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> Cap. 8.</note> it was agreed vpon in the first Nicen Councel, That it should be left to every Clergie mans choise, whether hee would forbeare, or keepe company with his wife to whom he was married.</p>
      <p>And thus, Sir Priest, you haue my Reply to your Priestly Answer: which I desire you to weigh with
<pb n="152" facs="83"/> indifferency, if you haue any fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>lty in this kinde of Controversiall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, whereof I finde no shew in this your Answer. Else▪ you may thinke your owne thoughts, and follow your owne courses; and doe well to leaue these disputes to quicker wits, and to such as haue beene trained vp in these studies: for doubtlesse, by such scribblements as this you sent me, you vvill never giue anie of your ovvne friends, nor anie of my opinion, any reasonable satisfaction. And so vvishing the salvation of your soule, vvith like affection you seeme to vvish mine, I rest,</p>
      <closer>
         <signed>Yours, so farre forth as you are Gods and the Kings: ALEXANDER COOKE.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   <pb facs="83"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>