<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE VSE OF THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117106_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11886</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22186</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117106</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE VSE OF THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sacrilege sacredly handled : That is, according to Scripture onely. Diuided into two parts: 1. For the law. 2. For the Gospell. An appendix also added; answering some obiections mooued, namely, against this treatise: and some others, I finde in Ios. Scaligers Diatribe, and Ioh. Seldens Historie of tithes. For the vse of all churches in generall: but more especially for those of North-Britaine</title>
                 <author>Sempill, James, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 <publisher>Jones, William 3.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Weaver (Wever), Edmund</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 100, 52, that is 54, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE VSE OF THE READER.</head>
   <p>TWentie twelue moneths are neere spent <hi>(good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der)</hi> since I had studied this Lesson, whereof I doe heere now render thee an account: a Lesson, I say, not a <hi>Lecture,</hi> and so but to be read by entreatie, receiued as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out authoritie, and censured freely: for all are well-come that come well.</p>
   <p>Two things would I aduise thee touching it: The causes mouing me to it, and the course I hold in it. The chiefe cause was, his <hi>Maiesties</hi> both example and authoritie, (as I haue said to himselfe) who, the more Kingdomes God giueth him, the more carefull he is to see the Kingdome of heauen replenish them: and so, directing sometimes Commissioners of all sorts and Callings, for surueying Christs Sanctuary in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Scotland, I was for one. Amongst many things refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable, we found one almost incurable: Sacrilege had sealed vp Ignorance in many places: <hi>Leui</hi> was fled to his Land,<note place="margin">Nehem. 13.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he lacked his portion.</p>
   <p>Some, that had at first ioyned themselues to our Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (more for rapine sake, as appeareth, then Religion) both Atheists, Papists, and some (in shew) Protestants, (a Sacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious trinitie) as they pulled downe the Churches, so pilled they the Church-rents: laying this ground, The one shall neuer be built, and the other euer begge. The Atheist, because hee hath <hi>No Religion,</hi> he must haue <hi>All</hi> the Tithes. The Papist,
<pb facs="6"/> disliking the present Religion, thinketh in Conscience he may take Tithes <hi>in Custodiam.</hi> And the Third, renounceth <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantia est mater pietatis;</hi> but yet protesteth, that <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertas</hi> be <hi>nutrix Religionis,</hi> both blinde and beggerly rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: No skant of such Protestants.</p>
   <p>As my soule may see ioy, I sorrowed for this, being farre from all hope of gaine, for I am no <hi>Leuite,</hi> and free of all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, for I haue no priuate enemie (and I could wish, no friend) in the businesse. But when I saw their Sacrilege so confirmed, as they could picke out more texts for a pecke of Tithes, then (perhaps) for a point of saluation: and againe, seeing the Prince so perplexed to see his Churches planted: I was glad to goe to Schoole for my owne direction, finding neuer better grounds, then I receiued from our Diuine <hi>Dauids</hi> owne mouth, <hi>viz.</hi> The Church had euer an inheritance (entitled Tithes) before, vnder, and after the Law: whereupon may stand a goodly building. And this for my Motiues.</p>
   <p>Touching the course then, I hold in it: I draw the generall word <hi>(Sacrilege)</hi> to the onely point of Maintenance, and Maintenance againe, to that onely, which Scripture calleth In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, <hi>viz.</hi> Tithes. The point then to bee confirmed is, <hi>Tithes inheritance, are due to the Ministery of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, by the Law of God.</hi> Many doubt of this, as I both heare and reade: but more deliuer their iudgements, then confi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>me it by good arguments; for in such case, Custome is no Law, and Law is not humane, but dependeth onely on God: <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. And for this cause, doe I not skumme the Fathers, or Antiquities, further then I find them play vpon the text, <hi>pro,</hi> or <hi>contra.</hi> Then, as I require not my reasons to be receiued with the reuerence of a Father: so I pray thee (good Reader) reiect them not, as the raueries of a childe: for the one is neither author of lyes, nor the other of Truth. The Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher taught vs better, To conceit truely of all things, according
<pb facs="6"/> as they are▪ for they are not what they are, because such is our conceit of them. In Diuine testimonies then, we are to consider, <hi>Quis dixit,</hi> and <hi>Quid dictum,</hi> and so to <hi>acquiesce:</hi> keeping alwayes that noble Boerean custome, of <hi>Scrutamini Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras:</hi> not <hi>fide implicitâ,</hi> to beleeue all, because such a **** aid so. In humane testimonies, we are onely to weigh <hi>Quid,</hi> and <hi>quo jure dictum,</hi> not <hi>Quis:</hi> for no simple truth resteth vpon this.</p>
   <p>According to three ages foresaid, doe I treate of the questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: before, and vnder the Law, in the first part: vnder the Gospell in the second. Obiections are brought for earch Period, as I haue read or heard them, but most part namelesse, for I seek to cleare the Truth, not to be the Whetstone of Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: some obiections, from my owne priuate debating with my selfe: all which, I haue set downe heere, fearing other men might stumble at the same: for the Spirit of doubting, is an earthly guest, and common: the Spirit of true resolution, from aboue onely, <hi>Truth</hi> being but One, and <hi>Error</hi> infinite. If all doubts then be not heere peculiarly answered, yet the grounds well held, will answere all. The Towne of <hi>Abe</hi> in <hi>Phocis,</hi> was preserued by <hi>Philip Macedo,</hi> when he had destroyed all the rest, because the people of that Towne were free of Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege. Now, if that <hi>Philip</hi> were to take a suruey of our Towns, Boroughes, and Abbeyes: how many <hi>Abbees</hi> would he find? What would he leaue vndestroyed?</p>
   <p>The cause of mens carel snesse of this sin now, I take to bee, that Time and Custome, hath giuen it such authority, that it is neither feared, nor admired: where vnder the Law, and Poeda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogie of the Iewes, it was most-times, as presently punished, as children whipped at schoole: <hi>Vzza</hi> struck dead, <hi>Vzzia</hi> leaper; and <hi>Achan</hi> with his whole race, ston<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d, or destroy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d for Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege. We take all (as the prouerb is) To the long day: but then shall there neither bee place for Restitution, nor Sacrifice for purgation. Foresee (good Reader) and farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>