<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHOR TO HIS LOVING COVSIN.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117670_Fr2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12644</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22965</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117670</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHOR TO HIS LOVING COVSIN.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>St Peters complainte Mary Magdal· teares. Wth other workes of the author R:S</title>
                 <author>Southwell, Robert, saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Barrett, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>576 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_cousin">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE AVTHOR TO HIS LOVING COVSIN.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Oets by abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing their ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the follies and faynings of Loue, the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomarie subiect of their base endeuours, haue so discredited this facultie, that a Poet, a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and a Lyer, are by many reckoned but three words of one signification. But the vanity of men cannot counterpoise the authoritie of God, who deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring many parts of Scripture in verse, and by his Apostle wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vs to exercise our deuotion in Hymnes and spirituall Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, warranteth the Art to be
<pb facs="4"/> good, and the vse allowable. And therfore not onely among the Heathen, whose Gods were chiefly canonized by their Poets, and their Paynim Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie oracled in verse: but euen in the Old and New Testament, it hath bene vsed by men of greatest pietie, in matters of most deuotion. Christ himselfe by making an Hymne the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion of his last Supper, and the prologue to the first Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant of his passion, gaue his Spouse a methode to imitate, as in the office of the Church it appeareth; and to all men a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne to know the true vse of this measured and footed style. But the Diuell as he affecteth Deitie, and seeketh to haue all the complements of Diuine honour applyed to his seruice, so hath he among the rest possessed also most Poets with his idle fancies. For in lieu of solemne and deuout
<pb facs="5"/> matter, to which in dutie they owe their abilities, they now busie themselues in expressing such passions, as onely serue for testimonies to how vnworthy affections they haue wedded their wils. And because the best course to let them see the errour of their workes, is to weaue a new webbe in their owne Loome, I haue here layd a few course threeds together, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite some skilfuller wits to go forward in the same, or to begin some finer peece, wherein it may be seene how well verse and vertue sute together. Blame me not (good Cousin) though I send you a blame-worthie present: in which the most that can commend it, is the good will of the writer; neither Art nor Inuention giuing it any credit. If in me this be a fault, you cannot be faultlesse that did importune mee to commit it, and therefore you must beare
<pb facs="5"/> part of the penance, when it shall please sharpe censures to impose it. In the meane time with many good wishes I send you these few Ditties: adde you the Tunes, and let the Meane, I pray you, be still a part in all your Musicke.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>