<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL CHRISTOPHER BLACKHALL Esquire, and to the vertuous Gentle-woman, Mistris DOROTHIE BLACKHALL, his Wife, Grace, Mercy, and Peace.</title>
           <author>Crosse, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117122_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19624</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6058</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117122</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL CHRISTOPHER BLACKHALL Esquire, and to the vertuous Gentle-woman, Mistris DOROTHIE BLACKHALL, his Wife, Grace, Mercy, and Peace.</title>
                 <author>Crosse, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A lasting ievvell, for religious vvoemen : In the summe of a sermon, preached at the funerall of Mistris Mary Crosse, late wife of Mr. Henry Crosse of Barnestaple in the countie of Deuon merchant, Nouemb. 11. 1628. and now published with some additions. With a briefe description of her life and death. By William Crompton, preacher of the Word of God at Barnestaple in Deuon</title>
                 <author>Crompton, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Blount (Blunt), Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>44 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL CHRISTOPHER BLACKHALL Esquire, and to the vertuous Gentle-woman, Mistris DOROTHIE BLACKHALL, his Wife, <hi>Grace, Mercy, and Peace.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orshipfull Sir, my losse hath occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioned this gaine to the Church, the death of my dearest friend gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing life to this Monument: <hi>Iacob</hi> erects a Pillar vpon the Graue of his beloued <hi>Rachell, Gen. 35.20.</hi> my desire was, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of mine might not perish; nor her Vertues with her body, be buried in the Land, where all things are forgotten: for that end I haue at length preuailed to make that publike, which was deliuered vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a short warning (the speaker limited both for time and Text) at her funerall: neither knew I any to whom I might more fitly Dedicate the same (of right belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to her neerest Kinsman) then to your selfe, with your vertuous second: deare shee was vnto you, while
<pb facs="3"/> liuing, and I know the fragrant smell of a bruised rose, will not be vnwelcome, though dead. I could not then wish her to liue still in misery; I now desire shee may liue in memory; according to the promise of God, made vnto his Saints; <hi>Psal. 112.6. Prou. 10.7. The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the iust is blessed; and the righteous shall be had in euerlasting remembrance.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Worthy Sir, if you may hereby reape any comfort, I shall haue the more content; if God may haue any glory, the Church any benefite, religious Woemen en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement hence, the Author, I know, obtaines his expected reward: who otherwise was vnwilling to feele againe the lashes of this censuring Age. Thus, not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to finde a kinde acceptance of a good meaning; I commit all to the blessing of God, leauing you and yours to the rich mercies of God our Father in Christ, and rest now as euer,</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>Barum, <date>
            <hi>this 14.</hi> Nouemb. <hi>1629.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Worships Kinsman to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, in what I am able, HENRY CROSSE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>