<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR ARTHVR THROCKMORTON of Paulerspury Knight, one of his Maiesties Iustices of the Peace and Coram in the County of Northampton; his religious, learned and vncorrupted Patron.</title>
           <author>Sibthorpe, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117406_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12216</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22527</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117406</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR ARTHVR THROCKMORTON of Paulerspury Knight, one of his Maiesties Iustices of the Peace and Coram in the County of Northampton; his religious, learned and vncorrupted Patron.</title>
                 <author>Sibthorpe, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A covnter-plea to an apostataes [sic] pardon : A sermon preached at Paules Crosse vpon Shroue-Sunday, February 15. 1617. By Robert Sibthorpe, preacher of the Word of God at Waterstratforde in Buckingamshire</title>
                 <author>Sybthorpe, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fairbeard (Fayerbeard), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fleming, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 44, that is 55, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR ARTHVR THROCKMORTON of <hi>Paulerspury</hi> Knight, one of his Maiesties Iustices <hi>of the Peace and Coram in the County of Northampton; his</hi> religious, learned and vncorrupted Patron.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Worshipfull Sir,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the common excuse for the Presse is ouer-pressing importunity, lest the Authour should seeme inexorable; although I might set that face on it, <hi>sine fuco;</hi> yet I will rather acknowledge ingenuously, that the especiall Apollogie for my presumption is opportunity, lest I might seeme vngratefull.</p>
   <p>Wherefore as al Riuers reuert vnto the Sea from whence they come:<note place="margin">Eccles. 1.7.</note> So I returne this small spring of the Spirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the immense Ocean of your bounty whence I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it.</p>
   <p>Which fauour although I had not receyued; yet (to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse the truth without flattery: Amongst all those who
<pb facs="3"/>haue vouchsafed the Sunne shine of their fauours vpon me, I know none so blessed in his owne integritie, his Ladies vertues, and his Ofsprings innocency, from those sinnes which are here censured, as that he might equally protect it without impeachment from those muddy aspertions which Sinne-shadowing Hypocrites may contend to cast vpon it.</p>
   <p>Most humbly therefore beseeching your Worshippe to sweeten this Current with your good acceptance, and to vouchsafe a Conduct pipe for it vnto others: with my prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for encrease of your happinesse, continuance of the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of yours, and imitation of them in others, I rest.</p>
   <p>From your Worships Guift at <hi>VVaterstratford,</hi> neere <hi>Buckingham.</hi> Feb. <hi>17.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Worships euer deuoted,</hi> Robert Sibthorpe.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>