<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117166_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19252</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5665</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117166</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Worke, more vvorke, and a little more work for a masse-priest : Reviewed and augmented by the authour. VVith an epistle of an vnknowne priest remaining in London, sent to the authour, excepting against fiue points therein. With the authours answere thereunto: returned vnto the priest within twelue dayes after the receipt of the priests exceptions</title>
                 <author>Cooke, Alexander</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 153, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader, in this Pamphlet, among other things, thou shalt finde it proved, that according to Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, A man may eate his god with his teeth, as<note n="a" place="margin">Homer. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> lib. 9.</note>
      <hi>Cyclops</hi> eate <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lysses</hi> companions: and that a subiect may kill his King, as
<note n="b" place="margin">1 King. 16, 9, 10.</note>
      <hi>Zimri</hi> did his Maister: and that one man may deceiue and cozen another, as the<note n="c" place="margin">Iosua. 3. 9.</note>
      <hi>Gibeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> did <hi>Iosua.</hi> Besides, thou shalt finde it proved, that the Papists make of no sinnes grievous sinnes; and of grievous sinnes no sinnes, or at most but veniall sinnes: Yea, thou shalt finde it proved, that the Papists make of grievous sinnes rare vertues; and that their Pope
(Saint <hi>Pauls</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">2 Thess. 2. 3.</note> man of sinne) takes vpon him to forgiue sinnes past, and sinnes to come. Further, thou shalt finde it proved, that they equall the virgin <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ie</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Christ in many respects; and preferre her before him in some respects: not considering the truth of<note n="e" place="margin">Haeres co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap> Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>yridian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius speech, Par detrimentum verae Religioni affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, illi qui vilem B. Virginem habent, &amp; illi qui vltra fas eius gloriam adaugent:</hi> They are equally to blame, who vilifie the Virgin, and who deifie her. Thou shalt finde it proved, that Papists professe more dislike of Protestants, then either of Turke, Iew, or Infidell:
<pb facs="5"/> and that they esteeme of them no otherwise then of repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, of whose salvation there is no more hope then of Lucifers. These things, and some other of like stampe, thou shalt finde herein proved against the Papists, out of their owne Authours▪ which, if thou be a Protestant, may helpe to keepe thee from falling vnto Poperie: and if thou be a Papist, may helpe to recover thee from Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; which are the two onely ends <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aime at in suffering it to passe to the Presse. And this is all that by way of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face I haue to say vnto thee, besides Farewell.</p>
   <l>GOe little booke, make speed, apply the season,</l>
   <l>Propound thy Quaeres with vndanted cheere:</l>
   <l>Bid learned Priests and Cardinalls speake reason<note n="*" place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 12.</note>.</l>
   <l>The vulgar dare not reade, but make them heare.</l>
   <l>Yea giue a challenge to the Triple Crowne:</l>
   <l>Bid them reply, or cast their bucklers downe.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>