<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The preface to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Sparke, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117703_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12701</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23019</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117703</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The preface to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Sparke, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvvere to Master Iohn De Albines, notable discourse against heresies (as his frendes call his booke) compiled by Thomas Spark pastor of Blechley in the county of Buck</title>
                 <author>Sparke, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barnes, Joseph</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>76, 426, 6 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <div type="preface">
      <pb n="1" facs="8"/>
      <head>The preface to the Reader.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>
            <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Lutarch</hi> a noble Philosopher,<note n="a" place="margin">This preface for the most part of it might a prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant write a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the popis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> church, heresies, and prelates.</note> and a diligent Historici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, writeth in the life of <hi>Demetrius</hi> a king of <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donie,</hi> that whē an olde womā came to him, beseeching him to heare her speake, and he made aunswere that he had no leasure, the woman looking vpon him, saide to him againe with a loude voice: why, haue you no leasure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> rule as a king should? Which wordes so pearced the kinges heart, and so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>eatly preuailed in him, that he forthwith gaue her audience, and from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>at daie, none came to him for any matter, but gently, and with all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>gence he did heare them, and discusse their causes. Boysterously were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>se wordes spoken of a subiect, and not with that reuerence that was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>eete to be giuen to a king. Notwithstanding, as <hi>Cicero</hi> witnesseth in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>e second of his Tusculanes: <hi>Tristis res est dolor, sine dubio, aspera, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>mara, inimica naturae, ad patiendum tolerandum{que} difficilis:</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>orowe is a grieuous thing, without doubt sharpe, bitter, and an enemy to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ature, harde to suffer and forbeare. Sorowe (as I suppose) constrayned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>he seely woman to speake as shee did, <hi>&amp; veras exprimere voces,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o vtter the truth. On the other side consider, not onely the gentle na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ure of this noble Prince, but also his great wisedome, in considering <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>othing to be more seemely for a gouernour, then to heare mens causes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ndifferently, and to see all wronges redressed. <hi>Nihil</hi> (saieth the same <hi>Plutarch) tam egregium tam{que} proprium Regis esse videtur, quàm iusticiae opus,</hi> Nothing is so excellent and so properly pertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to him that is a magistrate, as iustice. I haue redde that the Tribunes, which were officers chosen for the defence of the Commons of Rome, had their gates or dores neuer shutte, neither by day, nor by night, in token that thither might bee the recourse of all them that had neede of succour. So ought euery gouernour, whether hee bee spirituall or temporall, to bee a succour, and as it were a castle and a fortresse to them that bee vnder his tuition. <hi>Dion Cassius</hi> in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ookes that he wrote <hi>de principe,</hi> amongst other precepts, willeth chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>y and aboue all things, that whosoeuer be the head of the people, be a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent worshipper and folower of God: next, that hee bee louing to his sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, if he will haue them to be faithfull to him, and loue him as subiectes should their Prince. For it is not of likelyhood, saide <hi>Dion,</hi> neither doth nature permit, but that he that loueth, should be loued, whē we see dogges
<pb n="2" facs="9"/> to fawne, and horses to neye to them, of whom they be cherished. Againe, he would haue such rulers to call themselues shepherdes and feeders of men, rather then otherwise. So <hi>Homer</hi> calleth a king <hi>pastorem populi,</hi> a shepherde &amp; a feeder of the people. And <hi>Plato</hi> in his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alogue called <hi>Minos,</hi> writeth, that <hi>Minos</hi> &amp; <hi>Radamāthus,</hi> which gaue lawes to the men of <hi>Crete,</hi> were the true shepherdes of men, which was not spoken of so noble a Philosopher without a iust cause: for nothing doth more nourish, mainteine &amp; vpholde a common wealth then law, which, as Tullie <hi>in secundo de natura deorum</hi> sayeth, <hi>est recti praeceptio, praui{que} depulsio,</hi> a commaunder of that which is good and honest, &amp; an expulser of all that is nought and vnhonest. Now, as a shepherdes care is, to see his sheepe fedde in wholsome pastures, &amp; to be kept safe from wolues &amp; al other beastes that would wery &amp; destroy them: &amp; if any in the flocke be infected with any outwarde scabbe, or inwarde maladie, to remedie it betime: or if the contagion admit no helpe, but is incureable, to haue such a one away from the flocke, that he hurt none of them that be whole: Euen so must he that will be a shepheard of men, study for the good ordering and quietnes of the multitude, ouer whom he hath charge, and that al enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that might disturbe a common wealth, whether it be spiritual or ciuill be expelled, and that all faultes be redressed with due correction, vsing le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and severity, after as hope or dispaire of amendment shall appeare. Neither hath the name of a shepheard lacked his preheminence at any time. That good Abel, <hi>ad cuius munera Deus respexit,</hi> to whose gifts and sacrifice God had respect, was a shepheard: Abraham, in whole seede God promised that all nations should be blessed, was a shepheard: so was Isaac his sonne, and Iacob his nephewe, &amp; his sonnes also. Moyses that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble captaine, and deliuerer of God his people, was a shepheard in the lande of Madian. Dauid, of whom<note n="b" place="margin">Here is Stephē named for Paul. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.</note> S. Stephen sayd, that God gaue this testimony: <hi>Inueni Dauid filium lesse, virum secundum cor meum, qui faciet omnes voluntates meas:</hi> I haue found Dauid the sonne of Iesse, a man after mine owne heart and minde, which shal doe all my will.<note n="c" place="margin">There is no mention of Stephen.</note>
         <hi>Act. 13.</hi> This noble king Dauid was a shepheard. These I suppose al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God woulde haue to be ensamples to all them that be in authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, for as Paul sayth: <hi>Quaecun{que} scripta sunt, ad nostram erudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem scripta sunt,</hi> Al thinges that are written, are written for our instruction, that as they fedde that seely innocent cattell, so should all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates that professe his sons name, learne to gouerne the people in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of his doctrine, that they might be <hi>innocētes manibus, &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro corde nec iurantes in dolo proximo suo,</hi> Innocents of their hands,
<pb facs="9"/> and of a pure heart, which vse no deceipt towardes their neighbours, but in all their doinges shewe themselues to be, <hi>veras oues pascuae Christi,</hi> the true sheepe of the pasture of Iesus Christ, who sayeth: <hi>Bonus pastor animam suam dat pro ouibus suis,</hi> A good shepheard giueth his life for his sheepe. Few words, but full of pith: And neuer could moe things be spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken more compendiously. For what will he refuse to doe? what labour, what trauaile, what paine will he forsake, which for that performance of that hee goeth about, will not spare his owne life?<note n="a" place="margin">This being true as it is, thereupon it followeth, that your popish Priests and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, who nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue skill nor will to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme this duty, are no true sheepheards.</note> If a good shepheard setteth so great store by his sheepe, if he loue them so tenderlie, that he will rather loose his life then to see them in anie daunger, what will hee not doe els for them? Howe can it be otherwise, but that hee will see his flocke fedde in wholsome pastures? howe can it bee thought, that hee will not tary with them to keepe them from wolues, from dogges that fall to bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of them, and from other like rauenous beastes? Who woulde ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine him to bee so negligent, that hee will not in the euening bring them home to the cote or folde? Will hee not, trowe you, if any be strayed, goe seeke him out, and bring him againe to his fellowes? If anie be sicke, will hee not see him holpen with all diligence? See therefore vvhat a great matter our Sauiour did comprehende and folde vp, as it were, and knit together in a bundell, all that can be desired in a good herdesman. O that gouernours whom god hath put in authoritie, <hi>per quem reges reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> by whome kinges doe raigne, who bad Peter, if hee loued him, to feede his sheepe, who hath also constitute vnder him feeders vpon the earth, some spirituall, some temporall, O, I say, that they woulde diligently looke vpon these wordes: <hi>A good shepheard giueth his life for the sheepe,</hi> and seriously ponder in their minde what a charge is hid in this short sentence, how many things, <hi>princeps pastorum,</hi> the prince of shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards, as Peter calleth him, doth require of them whom hee hath made herdsmen vnder him, whose dutie is to be good pastours and faithfull fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders like to their master. O that they would call to their minde, that they must at length depart hence, and come where it shall be said to euery one of them: <hi>Redde rationem villicationis tuae,</hi> Giue accompt of thy bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liwicke, Come forth and shew how thou hast fedde my flocke that I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to thy handes: Thou Bishop, how hast thou visited thy diocesse, what Parsons, what Ʋicares hast thou admitted? Thou Archdeacon, how often hast thou visited and seene euery curate to do his duty? how hast thou redressed al enormities &amp; slaūders within thy iurisdictiō? Thou par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, thou vicar, thou curate, how hast thou fed thy flocke with good ensā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of charity &amp; vertuous liuing, with keeping of hospitality to thy power,
<pb facs="10"/> by preaching wholsome doctrine, in reuerently ministring my Sacramēts? Thou king, how hast thou ruled thy Realme? What lawes hast thou made for the setting forth of my glory, for the extirpation of heresies, for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of equity, for punishment of wrong, for prouision, that things may be solde at a competent price, that couetous men make no dearth to their condemnation, when I giue plenty? Thou Lord, how hast thou gouerned vnder thy prince? Thou man of worship, how hast thou endeuoured to haue quietnes kept, and the princes lawes to be obeyed? Thou Iustice, how hast thou ministred right indifferently to all persons? Thou Maior or head of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer in any Citty or Towne, how hast thou kept thy selfe cleere from periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? How hast thou seene good order obserued, and all idlenes and dissolute maners to be banished? Finally, thou, whatsoeuer officer or Magistrate thou be, how hast thou regarded the common wealth, &amp; preferred it afore thy priuate lucre or commodity? O that these things were considered: for as sure as God liueth, these accōpts will he call vpon straightly. None shall escape, <hi>Cui multum datur</hi> (as <hi>S. Gregory</hi> saith) <hi>multum ab eo quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur,</hi> He that hath much giuen him, shall make a great accompt thereof, and much shall be of him required: And at that day percase he shall reckē himselfe most fortunate and happie, that had least in this worlde, and least to doe. And he peraduenture most vnfortunate, that hath most to doe in this world, vnlesse hee order it well, vnlesse hee order it righteously, iustly, and ordinately.</p>
      <p>Now, good Reader, thou hast hearde, that Christ saith: <hi>Bonus pastor animā suā dat pro ouibus suis,</hi> And to put thee out of doubt who is this good shepherde, he saieth: <hi>Ego sum pastor bonus, &amp; cognosco oues meas, &amp; cognoscunt me meae.</hi> I am the good shepherd, which will giue my life for my sheepe, by my death to purchase them life, that as I will rise, and die no more, so shall they after their bodily death arise at the last daie, neuer to die any more, but to liue alwaies with my father and me. I knowe my sheepe, not al onely that they be mine, but I so know them for mine, that I will be their succour in their tribulations, I will strengthen them in their persecutions, I will receaue them into my ioy and glory, I know them, and they know me. This is then required of their sheepe, that they knowe their shepherde. Three properties must be in euery man or woman that shall haue this worthy name to be called a sheepe of Christ.<note n="b" place="margin">These being as indeede they are the true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of christs sheepe, thereupō it must needes followe, that he hath but fewe sheepe in the popish flocke.</note> The first propertie is, that our Sauiour saieth, that his sheepe doe know him. This knowledge haue Christs sheepe of him, that by his godheade he is their father, by his manhoode he is their brother, &amp; by his benefites he is their louing Lorde &amp; master.<note n="c" place="margin">This and your doctrine of me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rits, satisfaction, and other by meanes besides Christ, to erne your saluation by cannot stand together.</note> They know it is he, &amp; none other, that hath made their peace
<pb facs="10"/> with God his father: <hi>Ipse enim est pax nostra,</hi> for he is our peace <hi>(Ad Ephesios secundo)</hi> he hath gotten vs forgeuenesse of our sinnes, he hath deliuered vs out of the bondage of the deuil, he hath purchased heauen for vs, he is to vs <hi>Turris fortitudinis,</hi> the tower of our strength. The seconde propertie of Christes sheepe is, to heare their shepheards voice, and to giue no eare to the voice of any stranger. You wil aske me peraduenture, hovv you should heare him,<note n="d" place="margin">This is more then euer all the sort of you can proue.</note> which although he be verily and bodily heere with vs in the Sacrament of the Aultar, yet in his humane forme he is ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vp into heauen, and sitteth on the right hande of his father? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto I aunswere, that we must heare his voice sounding by the mouth of his<note n="e" place="margin">True: but there by straight is not ment yours, which along time hath beene an impudent harlot.</note> Church, which is the very true spouse of Iesus Christ, <hi>Quā sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficauit, mundans eam lauacro aquae in verbo vitae,</hi> whom hee hath sanctified and purified with the bath of water in the worde of life, <hi>vt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hiberet ipse sibi gloriosam ecclesiam non habentem maculam aut rugam,</hi> to make it a glorious Church to himselfe without spot or wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle <hi>(Ad Ephesios. 5.)</hi>
         <note n="f" place="margin">Thus you take for granted that your synagogue is this church of of Christ, and that we haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from the church of Christ, both which are most false.</note> If we hear the church, we hear Christ: for as the holy Bishop &amp; Martyr <hi>Irenaeus</hi> writeth in the forty Chapter of his thirde booke, <hi>Vbi ecclesia, ibi &amp; spiritus, &amp; vbi spiritus dei, illic ecclesia &amp; omnis gratia, spiritus autem veritas</hi> where the Church is, there is the spirit of God, &amp; where the spirit of God is, there is the Church &amp; al grace, &amp; the spirit is truth. Wherefore as the same godly father writeth in the forty and three Chapter of his fourth booke, we be bounde to be obedient to the Prelates of the Church, <hi>his qui successionem habent ab Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> to them that haue their succession from the Apostles. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquos verò</hi> (saieth hee) <hi>qui absistunt a</hi>
         <note n="g" place="margin">This principall succession is suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession in truth which you are gone from long agoe.</note>
         <hi>principali successi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one, &amp; quocunq́ue loco colliguntur, suspectos habere qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>si haereticos oportet,</hi> As for all other that goe away from the<note n="g" place="margin">Which is in truth that which your synagogue long ago hath done.</note> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall succession, wee ought to suspect them as heretickes. These are Irenaeus wordes in the place nowe alleadged. And Christ saieth himselfe: <hi>Qui vos audit, me audit,</hi> Hee that heareth you, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth mee. Wherefore, if wee will heare Christ, as his father hath commaunded vs, <hi>Ipsum audite,</hi> Heare him, <hi>Matth. 17.</hi> then must wee heare the Church.<note n="h" place="margin">These things are true of the true and pure church of Christ, listening to and following the voice of her husband, and not otherwise, and therefore not of your synagogue.</note> The Church is our most holy Mother, whom we ought to haue in great reuerence, and to commit our selues wholly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, to heare her, and like obedient children, to doe what she biddeth vs. What the Church holdeth in matters of religion, that must we holde: what the Church prescribeth, it is our duetie to followe: what the Church
<pb facs="11"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb facs="11"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb facs="12"/> forbiddeth, that are we bound, vnder paine of damnation to auoyde in a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny wise.<note n="a" place="margin">Therefore is it, that we dare not beleeue your Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mish spirit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we trying it by the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, finde it contrary to the spirit that was author of them.</note> S. Iohn in the fourth Chapter of his first Epistle biddeth vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, that wee beleeue not euery spirite, but to trye the spirites, whether they be of God or not. Then, how can they be of God, which goe from the Church? S. Augustine in the exposition of this Epistle of S. Iohn, <hi>tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu primo,</hi> writeth thus:<note n="b" place="margin">This you haue done, therefore by his rule howe can you be in Christ.</note>
         <hi>Qui ecclesiam relinquit, quomodo est in Christo, qui in membris Christi non est? Quomodo est in Christo, qui in corpore Christi non est?</hi> Hee that leaueth the Church, hovv is hee in Christ, that is not in the members of Christ? how is he in Christ, that is not in the body of Christ? By the which S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine affirmeth, that the Church, which is the spouse of Christ, is also the misticall body of Christ, &amp; Christ is the heade of the Church. As many therefore, as be Christ his sheepe, they heare their shepheards voice in the Church. They wil not heare the voice of strangers,<note n="c" place="margin">You should haue exemplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in your owne doctors and thē had you said well.</note> as of <hi>Luther, Oecolampadius, Zuinglius, Caluin,</hi> and like heretikes, which for all their gay wordes, and crying still, Christ and the Ghospel, may haue euery one of thē, these verses of <hi>Persius</hi> in his fift Satyre worthily spoken to him.
<q>
            <l>Pelliculam veterem retines, &amp; fronte politus</l>
            <l>Astutā vapido seruas sub pectore vulpem.</l>
         </q>
      </p>
      <p>Thou keepest still thine olde hyde vppon thee, and bearing a faire face, thou wrappest a wyly foxe vnder thy vaporous brest.<note n="d" place="margin">euen your popes and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors for these many yeares. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.</note> These bee they, of whome Saint Peter speaketh in the seconde Chapter of his seconde Epistle: <hi>Magistri mendaces, qui introducunt sectas perditionis,</hi> Lying masters, bringing in sectes of perdition, and denying the God that bought them. Howebeit, since it is so, as Paul sayeth, There wil be alwaies rauening wolues, <hi>non parcentes gregi,</hi> not sparing the flocke, And amōg our owne selues wil men arise, speaking peruerse things, And such is our fraile nature, that as the wittie <hi>Horace</hi> sayeth:
<q>
            <note n="e" place="margin">And therefore the Romish strū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet holdes out her poyson in a golden Cup. Reu. 17.</note> Decipimur specie recti,</q>
      </p>
      <p>We be soone deceiued vnder the colour of truth. It behoueth vs to follow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> the counsel of our head &amp; principal master Iesus Christ, which teacheth vs an excellent document of heauenly philosophy, saying:<note n="f" place="margin">And therefore we had neede to take heede of you.</note>
         <hi>Attendite vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis à falsis Prophetis,</hi> take ye heede to your selues, &amp; beware of false Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phets, which come vnto you, <hi>in vestimentis ouium,</hi> in sheepes cloathing, but inwardlie they are <hi>Lupi rapaces,</hi> Rauening wolues: We must, I saie, beware, that we be not deluded, and vnder colour of Euangelical va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, bee made to receaue pernitious and damnable heresies, as alas the more pittie, hath miserably chaunced to our noble Realme of<note n="g" place="margin">This is true of Englād in respect of Qu. Maries daies, and so thē truly we might &amp; did say vnto you as you here now falsly say vnto vs.</note> Englande, vnder colour of bringing vs to truth, leading vs await
<pb facs="12"/> from the truth, to the vtter decay of all godlines, &amp; setting vp of counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aite religion.<note n="a" place="margin">Euen this is the state of your Church in deed.</note> The weede hath nowe overgrowen the corne, euill, hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ull, and soulequelling weedes of heresie haue ouergrowen, oppressed, pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d downe to the grounde, and vtterly choked the good corne of christian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eligion, and all ecclesiasticall constitutions.<note n="b" place="margin">Thus we say &amp; that iustly to our people in respect of you.</note> Al you therefore that haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>een seduced, and taken weeds for wholsome flowers, beware least with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ench of such rotten weedes, yee infect your soule to euerlasting damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n. The infallible truth is dayly opened vnto you,<note n="c" place="margin">It doth not at all appeare by the discourse that there is any falshood at all in our Religion.</note> The falshoode is mightily conuinced, as shall plainely appeare in the discourse heare fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>owing. Stande no more in the defence of that, which you may easilie know and see with your eies, if ye will not be wilfully and obstinately blinde, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o bee nothing but deceit:<note n="d" place="margin">These titles do rightly fit the po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pish Religion.</note> What doe I call it, deceit? nay, I call it a most venimous poison to the soule, yea, and an hellishe draught of endelesse <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eath.<note n="e" place="margin">This part your papists play now in England in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing recusants of all sound &amp; good meanes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them.</note> Playe not the parte of a mad man, of whome <hi>Horace</hi> vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eth in the second booke of his Epistles, that he was angry with his frends, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>or that they had caused him to bee healed of his phrensie, and restored to his wittes againe: Bee not angrye, that you may (if you will) bee brought out of the fowle miste, into the cleere ayre, from darkenesse to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ight, from an horrible phrensie to godly wisedome. Followe the whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some counsel of Saint Paule in the fourth to the <hi>Ephesians, Vt non si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus amplius pueri, qui fluctuemus, &amp; circumferamur quouis vento doctrinae, per versutiam hominum, per astutiam qua nos adoriuntur, vt imponant nobis,</hi> That we be no longer children, and fleete two and fro, caried hither and thither with euery blast of doctrine, by the wilinesse and craftinesse of men, wherewith they set vpon vs to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue vs. There haue beene a great manie<note n="f" place="margin">In deed so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny such Iesuites and Seminaries you haue sent vs</note> such sprongē vp in our Realme of late, which haue taught vs wronge Lessons: <hi>Emendemus ergò in melius,</hi> Let vs amend therefore. The thirde propertie is, that the sheepe doe follow their Shephearde: This property is of so great importance, that without it the other two cannot auaile. It is not Inough to knowe Christ to be our refuge, our helpe and succour:<note n="g" place="margin">This is true as long as the church retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the two former proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which youre long ago hath lost.</note> It is not inough with that also to heare Christ speaking to vs in his Church, except we follow Christ &amp; his Church, &amp; shew our selues willingly to doe that which the Church com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth vs: We must fast, when the Church commaundeth vs, &amp; as it biddeth vs: We must pray as the Church instructeth vs, We must do those good works that the Church teacheth vs to doe. In obeying the Church, wee obey God: if wee bee disobedient to the Church, wee disobey God. For as <hi>Chrysostome</hi> saieth vpon the first Epistle to the Corinthians, <hi>vt corpus &amp; caput vnus est homo, ita vnum est ecclesia &amp; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus,</hi>
         <pb facs="13"/> As the body and the heade is but one man, so is Christ and his Church one thing. Doe therefore as the wise man biddeth thee, <hi>Audi disciplinam patris tui, &amp; ne dimittas legem matris tuae,</hi> Heare the discipline of thy father, and forsake not the lawe of thy mother: I meane, thy mother the<note n="h" place="margin">Holy Church hold you there, for so long you say nothing for your vnholy and filthie Churche.</note> holy church, whom as many as forsake, they forsake God also. For as holy <hi>Cyprian</hi> writeth <hi>de simplicitate praelatorum: Habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re non potest Deum patrem, qui ecclesiam non habet matrem,</hi> He cannot haue God to be his father, that knoweth not the church for his mother.<note n="i" place="margin">Let this rule be followed for the questions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt vs, &amp; your church shall bee found in those pointes to haue set a broch those things that those most auncient Churches neuer were acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted withall.</note> Yee may see here euidently, that this holy man would haue vs to be obedient vnto, and diligently to keepe, the ordinances of our fathers, and not to institute euery <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>y new fashions, as men most vnconstant, and full of new fangles. The Lacedemonians are praysed, that they suffered no straunge ware to be brought into their citty, whereby the cittizens might be effeminated and corrupted in their maners, and for the same cause they extoll greatly <hi>Licurgus,</hi> which made the same law. Now, if the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedemonians were so serious obseruers of their olde lawes and customes, what a shame shall this be to vs christian men (which were not taught of <hi>Licurgus,</hi> but of Christ himselfe) daily to alter and change, not content with those rites and ceremonies that were ord yned of auncient time out of memory? <hi>Irenaeus</hi> teacheth in his third booke against the heresies of <hi>Valentine,</hi> and such other, whose wordes taken out of his fourth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the saide booke, I will briefly rehearse: <hi>Si quae de aliqua modica quaestione disceptatio esset, nonne oporteret in antiquissimas re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currere ecclesias, in quibus Apostoli conuersati sunt, &amp; ab eis de praesenti quaestione, sumere quod certum &amp; reliquidum est?</hi> If any controuersie should be of any question, were it neuer so little, must it not be meete to haue our recourse vnto the most ancient churches, in the which the Apostles were conuersant, &amp; of thē to receaue the plaine cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie thereof? It followeth, <hi>Quid autem si neque Apostoli quidem Scripturas reliquislēt nobis, nōne oportebat ordinē se qui traditio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nis, quá tradiderūt his quibus cōmittebāt ecclesias?</hi> But what if the Apostles left<note n="k" place="margin">If indeed they had left no scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures then that had beene a good course but nowe seeing they ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e, what their tradition was, is best ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by them. But the better to hide your fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in citing these wordes, you sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily translate scriptures no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing written of that matter.</note> nothing writtē of that matter, must we not follow the tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thē, to whose gouernāce they cōmitted the churches? Here haue you the minde of <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> who was neere vnto Christ his time: for as <hi>S.</hi>
         <note n="l" place="margin">Here againe the question is begged, for you take for granted that your p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates are lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called and ours not, both which we deny.</note>
         <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> testifieth in an Epistle to one <hi>Theodora,</hi> he was Disciple to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pias,</hi> who was <hi>S. Iohn</hi> the Euangelists scholler. Hee would haue men to be taught of Christ, of his Apostles and their successours, and<note n="m" place="margin">Of the same minde are we, &amp; therefore Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian men are not to listen to your prelates.</note> not of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie one, which rashly and without lawfull authority taketh vpon him to be a teacher. Christian men should be obedient to christian ordinances,
<pb facs="13"/> and followe that doctrine that is allowed by them that are lawfullie called, and haue the censure of doctrine committed to them. Such were the Apostles, called and put in authoritie by Christ. Such were they,<note n="n" place="margin">But such haue not beene your Romish teachers these many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares. Witnesse your owne writers who shewe how vnlawfully many of them came by their places.</note> to whom these againe gaue the charge ouer any faithfull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ongregation. Such are all they which haue so from time to time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eene lawefullie called by them, that haue power to put others in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and so succeeded in due order, else, <hi>Quomodo praedicabunt nisi mittantur,</hi> Howe shall they preach, except they bee sent, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t is written in the tenth to the Romanes, and sent by them which haue authoritie to sende. Did not Saint <hi>Paul</hi> for that purpose leaue <hi>Titus</hi> in Creete? Did hee not also giue <hi>Timothie</hi> charge to laye handes too quickely on no man? To these that bee thus lawefullie or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned and called to haue cure and charge of soules, yee are bounde to giue an eare: by these yee must bee ruled in matters of Religion, and as obedient children to their spirituall fathers. And this biddeth Saint <hi>Hierome,</hi> writing to <hi>Nepotian:<note n="o" place="margin">True and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie as long as the pastour is such as Paul wilde Titus to ordeine: but this helpeth yours little.</note> Esto subiectus pontifici tuo, &amp; quasi animae parentem suspice,</hi> Bee subiect to thy Bishop, and reuerence him as thy soules father. The same lesson teacheth <hi>Chrysostome</hi> in an Homylie, <hi>De recipiendo Seueriano,</hi> where hee beginneth thus: <hi>Sicuti capiti corpus cohaerere necessarium est, ita ecclesiam sacerdoti, &amp; principi populum,</hi> As it is of neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie, that the bodie cleaue to the heade, so it is likewise of necessitie, that the congregation cleaue to their Priest and spirituall ruler, and the people to their Prince. And within a fewe wordes after, hee allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth for the confirmation of this matter, the Apostle writing thus to the Hebrewes, in the thirteenth Chapter:<note n="p" place="margin">This rule is not general without exception. For Christ hath saide take heede of false Prophets &amp;c.</note>
         <hi>Obedite praepositis vestris, obtemperate eis, quia ipsi peruigilant pro vobis, quasi pro animabus vestris rationem reddituri,</hi> Obey them that haue the ouersight of you, and doe as they woulde haue you, for they watch for your sakes, as they which shall giue accomptes for your soules. This obedience doeth our Sauiour require of all men, saying: <hi>Qui vos audit, me audit,</hi> Hee that heareth you, heareth mee. This obedience to Christes Church hath continued thoroughout all Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome time out of minde. And if the authoritie of the learned and holie fathers ought to beare sway and preuaile, as of right it ought to doe indeede: <hi>Arrogantium enim hominum est, maiorum suorum authoritatem aspernari, &amp; se illis ingenio vel sapientia antepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere:</hi> For it is the manner and property of proud arrogant persons to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne the authority of their elders, &amp; to prefer themselues before thē in
<pb facs="14"/> wit or learning, If the consent of all christian Regions should be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>prob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>bilia</hi> (saieth <hi>Aristotle</hi> in the first Chapter of the first booke of his Topickes) <hi>quae videntur omnibus vel plurimis,</hi> Those things are probable, which all men, or at the least, the most part doe iudge to be so. If the long continuance of time must be of importance, <hi>In his enim</hi> (as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesseth <hi>S.</hi> Hilarie vpon the hundred and eighteene psalme) <hi>tanquàm in coelo verbum dei permanet, in quibus hoc verbum non offendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> In them doth the word of God abide, among whom that worde is not offended.<note n="a" place="margin">This is but a vaine brag that you haue these three, as shall appeare I hope sufficiētly in the answer to <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines</hi> treatise. For you haue not one of them in such sort, as that thereupon you may conclude as you doe.</note> If these three, I saie, The authority of the learned Fathers, The common consent of Christian Regions, The long continuance of time, may be a sufficient testimonie for the verity, we haue the true Gospell, &amp; the true sence of it:<note n="b" place="margin">These are but shamelesse beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings of the things in questi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, and onely your bare and therefore vaine words, for none of them you shal euer proue true.</note> Our Religion is the very Christian Religion, The order of Ceremonies that the Catholike Church doth vse, is the right or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Our fasting and praying is according to the Scriptures, Our Church is the true and lawfull spouse of Christ, from the which as many as sepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them selues, they are no sheepe of Christes folde, they are reprobate persons, they are the children of Belial, they are impes of hell.<note n="c" place="margin">What then? is the president of our next &amp; last fathers yea though for some hundred or more yeares such as we may not vary from? The vani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty of this argu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment see cap. 38. of my answere.</note> You knowe what order your fathers kept, howe they liued, and howe they beleeued: You are not ignorant, how you haue beene brought vp, instructed and tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ned in the lawes of Christ. Whosoeuer goeth about to infringe or breake any part of that<note n="d" place="margin">You must proue the order godly and lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or else your assertion is false</note> godly order, of that auncient custome and laudable vsage, he is an hereticke, an enemy to God, a murtherer to mans soule, a disturber of the common wealth, a subuerter of all honest discipline, and therefore most vnworthy to liue among men.</p>
      <p>I<note n="e" place="margin">This complaint hath most iust &amp; apparant ground especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly amongst men of your owne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, though it cannot be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where there is so lamentable cause thereof, but yet this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudiceth our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion which condemnes all imoiety, no more then you would haue it to doe yours.</note> haue heard, read and seene many things, yet can I not reade, beare, or see any world more contaminate and prone to al kinde of vices then this our age is. And howbeit afore our daies, there haue beene in all times and ages, men and women very vitious and monstrous in their liuing, yet then vertue was vertue, and vice was vice: But now in our corrupt time, wee haue lost the true names and vse of all things, and vertue with vs is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for vice, and contrarily, vice is counted for vertue. They that bee studious of modesty, obseruers of temperancie, and louers of sobrietie, they be now a daies called Pinch-pennies, and such that hunger droppeth out of their noses.<note n="f" place="margin">This is false amongst vs, if by catholique you vnderstande, as you should, sounde and true religion.</note> If any be vertuous, &amp; followers of the Catholike, which is the true Religion, they be called Pharisies &amp; papists: The discreete man he is called an hypocrite, and the small talker a foole and an ignorant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. On the other side, they that leade their liues in all kinde of riote, they be called handsome men, men of the right making, and such as can tel how
<pb facs="14"/> to keepe honest mens companie. Againe, the statelier that one goeth, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>igher that he looketh, and the stouter and malapertlier that he speaketh, be more is he praised among the worldlings for a wise man, who will not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uffer himselfe to be ouertroden and made a laughing stocke to euery ras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>all. With such vaine glorious praises be such proude <hi>Thrasoes</hi> extolled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nd magnified of the more part, and no small number are giuen to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>erie, and enhausing of Clawbackes, that neuer could that saying of <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ence</hi> be better verified then it is now: <hi>Obse quium amicos, veritas o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>odium parit,</hi> To holde vp mens yea and their naye, in holding with the bare, and running with the hounde, getteth a man frendes, but he that will laye flattery aside, &amp; tell the plaine truth, shal get nothing but hatred. Thus in these daies vice is extolled, &amp; vertue contemned: Ill rule is made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>f, and good rule neglected.</p>
      <p>O heart dissembled, which vnder coulour to be iust &amp; true, canst cloke vnto vs hipocrisie for deuotion, ambition for gentlenesse, couetousnes for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ōpetencie, cruelty for zeale, bolde babling without learning for eloquēce, florishing Rhetoricke without fruit or reasō, folly for grauity, wilines with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wit, and fleshly wanton libertie, for liberty of the Gospell. This is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els but the deuils drifte, alway couering his poison vnder some taste of suger: <hi>Fallit enim vitium specie virtutis &amp; vmbra:</hi>
         <note n="g" place="margin">This inuectiue speech we may iustly vse of you and your side.</note> For the summe &amp; ende of all their false doctrine, is nothing els but malice with murther, to the ouerthrowe of Christes Religion, and the true ministers thereof. This is their sheepes clothing, for an vnhappy reformation: <hi>Nam impia sub dulci melle venena latent,</hi> Vnder sweete honny is deadly venome hid. O blinde ignorance and ignorant blindnes! O cruell and damnable mischiefe comming from the bottomeles pit of hel! O intollerable furious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and heresie more detestable then it mate any longer be suffered! The greate d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>spleasure, the extreame vengaunce, the cruell plagues of God hange ouer our heades, if this horrible heresie be not shortly remoued frō mens mindes. O<note n="h" place="margin">These wordes iustly we maie breake out into, in respect of the infinite blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations held and maintained by your side in this point.</note> good god, how long wilt thou suffer this intollerable ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homination? It shameth me, it abhorreth me to thinke, that these shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les beastes are not ashamed to speake of the most blessed Sacramentes of Christes Church: who is able to expresse either by tongue or penne their wicked abhomination? whye haue we a pleasure to forsake the true vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing of Gods most sacred worde, and become followers and bondslaues of the deuils counterfaite and deceitfull expositions, &amp; carnall reasons set out by his ministers, who in Religion are<note n="i" place="margin">This obiection of the diuersitie of opinions, see answered at large Cap. 4.</note> so deuided, that now they dreame one thing, and now another: this day they like, tomorowe they mislike, &amp; one is against another of them, euen in the highest misterie of Christ his
<pb facs="15"/> Religion. And no meruaile, for the deuill is their chiefe head, whom they serue, and he is full of lies, variaunce, diuision, and discorde: &amp; vnder him their Schoolemasters were, <hi>Hus, Luther, Zuinglius, Oecolampadius, Bucer, Melancthon,</hi> and the Archheretike <hi>Caluin,</hi>
         <note n="k" place="margin">Therein there is no proofe that he helde any one heresy.</note> whose heresies are confuted in the Discourse hereafter ensuing.<note n="l" place="margin">This is vntrue.</note> These with the rest of that rable did neuer agree one with another, in their doings there is no v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, no certainty at all: and therefore such masters, such schollers come of them. And this diuision, this vnconstancie of doctrine, was a manifest to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, that they were not the children of our true mother the Catholike Church, nor ministers of Christ, but the children of the deuill, and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of Antichrist, yea, very Antichrists.<note n="m" place="margin">Which that you papists be is most certain, the contrari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ty of your doctrine with the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent catholic e Church conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which I haue noted cap. 17. &amp; 29 of my answer.</note> For whosoeuer (saieth <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi>) is gone from the vnitie of the Catholicke Church, hee is become an Antichrist? These Antichrists haue borne a great stroke now too long time in our Realme of England, in whom is no constancy, no stedfastnesse of religion and doctrine: These are they that haue damnably deceiued you, and haue with their damnable preachings intised you from Church to Church, from an heauenly Church to a malignant Church: from a louing mother,<note n="n" place="margin">This is false.</note> to a flattering harlot: from the condition of grace, to the state of perdition:<note n="o" place="margin">These words remaining we iustly say to, and of you.</note> from truth to falshoode, from faithfull beleeuing to carnall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soning, from sauing Christ to deceauing Antichrist. But (good Reader) beware, be not deceaued, &amp; be not ashamed to arise, that hast so shamefully fallen, be not ashamed to come home to your mother the Church, sith shee is not ashamed to receiue you: Let not folly lose the thing that grace hath so preciouslie offered and purchased: Let not wilfulnesse and blindnesse put out so great light as is now shewed vnto thee, but embrace most humblie the doctrine of our mother the catholicke church, so shall you sit in the lappe of so tender a mother, which will cherish you into life euerlasting: Choose the best, whiles choise lieth in lot.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>What were you ashamed of your preface that you put not your name to it? Indeede it is so fonde and friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, that you might well enough be ashamed to father it.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="answer">
      <pb facs="15"/>
      <head>
         <hi>An answere to the preface set before</hi> Iohn de Albines <hi>booke</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, A notable discourse against heretickes. &amp;c.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I take in hande to say any thing to <hi>Iohn de Albine,</hi> or his booke, I must craue of thee (gentle reader) whosoeuer thou art, these two things, that thou wouldest first giue me leaue to answere the long, tedious, and bragging preface, prefixed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his booke by the publisher thereof, and that then also thou thy selfe, wouldest vouchsafe before thou goest any further, either to the considering what <hi>Albine</hi> hath obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, or I answered, to take the paines to reade ouer this my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere to the saide preface. And though it seeme vnto thee of an extraordinary length, &amp; so somewhat discourages thee, yet the length of his considered likewise, I pray thee beare with me, and vouchsafe the reading of it thorow, before thou proceedest any further. His preface thou seest is long, but indeede so vaine and friuolous it is, that though it seemeth the authour thereof was some bolde and impudent Iesuite, or fugitiue of our owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, yet such care he had of his credit, that for feare of losse there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, he hath not thought good to put his name vnto it. The vanity and weakenesse thereof, may euen sufficiently appeare by those marginall notes, that I haue affixed vnto it, so that if I troubled thee with no further answere vnto it, I hope it neither could nor should much moue thee, or any other to thinke any thing the better of their Church and religion, then thou didst before: yet because, neither he, nor any of his faction, for want of a further particular aunswere vnto it, shall take occasion to persuade thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, or other, that there is further weight and matter in it then indeede there is, I will vouchsafe some more paines about it. First therefore this I would haue thee (Christian Reader) for the cōmendation of the authors great skill to obserue, that almost al of it, is spent in prouing those things which are needles, because, we teach, graunt, &amp; defende thē to be trueths, as fully and more fully then he or any of his side. For proofe whereof, cōsider, that whereas the whole preface, consists in the copie and edition that I had of his in print to aunswere, of twenty two leaues, hee spendes the first eight pages in prouing that Kinges, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and rulers both ciuill and ecclesiasticall, must carefullie administer iustice according to their callings, and so bee as good shepherdes to them, of whome they haue charge,
<pb facs="16"/> which who doubteth of, or who euer denyed amongst vs? yea we teaching as we do, that Emperours, Kings, and Queenes, in their kingdomes, are carefully to looke to the keeping of both tables amongst their people, and that they are next vnder God the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme gouernours of their people, aswel in causes ecclesiastical, in commaunding for the good of the church and religion of Christ, as in causes ciuill, in commaunding for the common weale and the good estate thereof, and they denying ciuil Magistrates any such authority in causes of the church, doe not we far more fully then they teach them, how and when they may be as good shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards to their people? Then by occasion of this former need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse discourse, hauing alleadged that <hi>Iohn</hi> 10. to proue that a good shepheard giueth his life for his sheepe, and that Christ is that good sheepheard that knowes his sheepe, and is knowen of them, marke how in as many mo pages he inferreth, that it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary that the sheepe know their shepheard, that they heare his voice, and geue no eare to the voice of a stranger, and lastly, that they follow and obey their shepheard: which are things also (tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taught and vnderstoode) which we most gladly teach &amp; em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace, and for lacke of which properties of Christes sheepe wee constantly hold &amp; aduouch that the Romish flocke these manie yeares, hath rather beene a flocke of goates, then of Christes true sheepe. For if they knowe, as they should, that the name of the sheepheard Christ were the only name whereby commeth salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Act.</hi> 4. and that in him all things are prepared already. <hi>Math.</hi> 22. they would not set vp to themselues so many names of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons and thinges besides him, nor hold that so many thinges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides those that are already prepared in him, are left to thēselues and others to that ende to prepare, as they doe. And if they did so heare his voice, and refuse to heare the voice of strangers (as Christes sheepe ought) there neither would nor could be, so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny strange doctrines, yea contrary doctrines to the voice of Christ set downe in the Canonical scriptures, receaued &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained amongst them, as ear I haue done with <hi>Albine</hi> I shall shew there are. Likewise such followers &amp; obeiers of the voice of Christ are they, &amp; haue they beene for these 4. or 500. yeares speaking vnto them in his word writtē, by the mouth of his true church &amp; aūcient sound pastours thereof, as that none euer, in a number of most weighty and materiall matters, more directly contraried
<pb facs="16"/> his voice then they. Whither I haue iust ground and proofe for my thus saying, I referre thee to that which I haue written in confutation of <hi>Albines</hi> discourse, cap. 4.17.29. &amp; 36. And yet such is the folly of this nameles preface wryter, that hauing thus noted these, to be the properties of Christs true sheepe, as though by and by without any further proofe at all, it ought of necessity to bee granted, that he and his side had all these properties, and that we of our side had neuer a one of them all, but were notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously branded with the contrary markes, he triumpheth and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulteth ouer vs, spending all the rest of his preface in railing vpon vs, and in perswading his reader to forsake vs, and to ioyne with him &amp; his. So that all the rest of his preface is builded, vppon a most shamefull and impudent begging of all these points; that they know Christ aright, heare his voice &amp; no other, obey him and follow him most orderly: and also of these (that his begging of that former may seeme the more reasonable) that their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine is sound, hauing countenāce of al auncient &amp; holy fathers, of the cōsent of al Christiā Regions, &amp; prescription of time, that their prelates are al prelates lawfully called, hauing right successi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, &amp; euery thing that they should haue, to credit them withal, &amp; therefore that they are such, as Christ hath commaunded, to to be obeyed as himselfe, and lastly, that their church is the holie Catholike church, the obedient spouse of Christ, and mother of all the faithfull, and that therefore it is damnation to depart frō her, or to refuse to obey any of her lawes and ordinances, &amp; that with vs, all things are quite contrary. All these things his reader must graunt him &amp; suppose to be true, for he hath nothing at all to proue any one of these, besides swelling words of vanity, and lofty arrogant bragging that these things are so. And therefore al these things, being the things in question betwixt vs, and such, as we all, most constantly and iustly haue alwaies denied, (as our writings of these points heretofore, &amp; now this answere of mine in sundry places thereof, make manifest to any indifferēt reader) thereupon it must needes follow, that whatsoeuer he hath allead<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged, either out of scripture or doctor to perswade his reader to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey their church, their prelates, their ordinances &amp; traditions, is shamefully abused. For compare the times when, &amp; the persons whereof those things were written, their doctrine and doings with these, and you shall finde, (witnes the scriptures thēselues
<pb facs="17"/> and all sound antiquity) as much differēce betwixt their church prelates, doctrine and ordinances, and them of whom those pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are to be truely vnderstoode, as there is betwixt light and darkenesse, the pure Church of Christ, and the impure Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of Antichrist. And also, all his exhortation vpon these grounds, to ioine with them, and all his bitter inuectiues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst vs, for refusing so to doe, is as a building in the aire with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all foundation. And therefore is thus easilye pulde downe, and laide vnderfoote, as a thing more meete to bee trampled vpon, as a thing of nothing, then by any to bee at all regarded. And yet as foule a fault as this is in him, it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to him with all wryters of his side, and most notoriously with this <hi>Iohn de Albine,</hi> before whose booke, hee hath set this his preface. It may bee, seeing his author, whom hee ment to publish, and of whom he had such an opinion, that hee accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him a notable discourser against heresies, to haue such a grace and dexterity, in stuffing out his booke almost with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else, but with this beggerly begging the maine questions alwaies, that he thought his preface should not be suteable, and fit to be set before such a learned discourse, vnlesse it were garni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed &amp; bewtified with the same popish grace. And if this were his reason (then which I am sure hee hath no better) hee is to bee borne withall, for what reason is there to the contrary, but that according to the rules of decency, the preface and the booke whereunto it is a preface shall be conformable one to the other.</p>
      <p>And yet though this be the very methode and matter (good Reader) of all this his long tedious preface, which I thus brie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flie haue laide open before thee, the poore silly man the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour thereof, seemeth to haue conceiued such a liking of his owne doings therein, especially towards the latter ende thereof, that gloriously and triumphantly hee breaketh out into wonderful complaints, amplifications, and exclamations against vs. Alas poore man that hee was, thought hee to meete with no reader, but that would graunt him all these thinges at the first asking? Or thought hee that hee had so cunningly and artificially knit those things together, that no man could espy the childish losenes of them? From his first gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall farre set and yet vnnecessary discourse of the duety of all of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers,
<pb facs="17"/> hee so suddenly falleth into the next, of the properties of Christes sheepe, that it was great maruaile that the man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ooke no great harme by it. But hauing recouered himselfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> litie, speaking belike before his wittes were well come to him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ee neuer can hit after of any thing to the purpose. For not onely all his matter and woordes, besides a fewe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked assertions of his of the trueth of certaine points of his reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and falshoode of ours, skipping in heere and there, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>here is nothing, but, the circumstances of application altered, one of vs might far more aptly and truely haue written against them. But as those things sufficiently conuince the man and his preface of grosse folly and vanitie, so if we consider, but howe he hath wilfully sought to abuse his reader, in cyting the ancient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> and others, to persuade his reader by his authoritie, to obey their prelates and traditions, we shall as plainely finde in the man palpable impiety. For page second, he cyteth his fourth booke and forty three chapter, to proue vnto vs nowe, that wee must obey their Church, now speaking vnto vs by their prelates, because then <hi>Irenaeus</hi> tolde the heretiques a thousand and foure hundred yeares agoe and more (whom indeede the pastours of the Church that then was, continued soundly in the purity of the Apostolique doctrine) that they were to obey the pastours of the Church that had succession from the Apostles. Which any mā may see, bindeth not, nor teacheth vs to do the like to theirs, vnlesse they could proue theirs to be such, as there <hi>Irenaeus</hi> spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of. Likewise whatsoeuer else in this preface of his to like pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose he hath alleadged out of <hi>Irenaeus, Augustine, Chrysostome, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priā, Hierome,</hi> or the scriptures thēselues, is abused, for that which they spake of that pure &amp; true Church of Christ, and her faithfull ministers, that he would drawe his reader to think to be spoken, euen of the Church of Rome as it is now, and hath beene of late yeares, and of her prelates, which are in nothing almost, like either the Church or ministers that they speake of. But this is not all his fault in alleadging this testimonie of <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> thus to confounde the prelates and Church with the true pastours of Christ and his pure Church, a thousande fower hundreth yeares agoe, whereunto theirs are no more like then darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse is to light, but that also wilfully (the easilier belike to beguyle the simple reader) hee concealeth that, that
<pb facs="18"/> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly followeth the former words. Which is this: <hi>Quis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap> ostendimus cum episcopatus successione charisma veritatis certum, secū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum placitum patris acceperunt,</hi> that is, which (as we haue shewed) with the succession of their Bishoppricke, according to the will and pleasure of God, haue receaued the certaine gifte of trueth, and so hee hauing skipt ouer those wordes, which hee thought, as it should seeme, in his conscience, would and might be denied, not to fit their prelats, he goeth on with that that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed these wordes, saying, <hi>Reliquos vero qui absistunt à principal successione, &amp; quocunquè loco colliguntur, suspectos habere tanquam hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticos oportet,</hi> which is in English, but the rest which goe from the principall succession, in what place soeuer they be gathered together, wee ought to suspect as heretiques. Wherein eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently it appeareth, he left out the former words (stāding in the author in the midst betwixt the former part of the sentence, and the latter here alleadged by him) to make the reader be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that Irenaeus minde was, to teach men simply to obey such prelates, without exception, as haue ordinarie, outward, and locall succession downe from the Apostles, and that that kinde of succession in place and office, is the principall succession that he speaketh of, which who so hath not, ought by and by to bee suspected of heresy. But indeede take al his words together and marke them, (especially those which craftily he had gelded the sentence of, in his quoting of them) and it is most cleare, that <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renaeus</hi> here teacheth obedience onely to such Bishops, as suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede the Apostles, in the certaine gift of trueth, that by prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall succession, he ment nothing else but succession to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, in that gift of trueth, and that therefore he would haue vs, to suspect all those to be heretiques, that lack succession vnto them in that, howsoeuer and wheresoeuer they succeede them else. Which is the very cause, why according to this rule we think no better of their popish bishops &amp; priests, then we do (what suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessiō soeuer otherwise they bragge of) for that, sure we are, that long ago they are gone from this principal succession in trueth. This he knew euery one would perceiue, if he had faithfully cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Irenaeus wordes as they lye, and therefore hee thought best, to shew how he could followe the example of that olde fox Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, who for his purpose in like māner, mangled the 91. Psalme, Math. 4. It seemeth also that these words <hi>quocun{que} loco colligūtur;</hi>
         <pb facs="18"/> in what place soeuer they be gathered together, (though he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite them in latine) he would faine haue smothered, for trāslating the rest he omits these, doubtles because without any exceptiō, yea euen of Rome it selfe, thereby <hi>Irenaeus</hi> would teach, that they ought to be suspected to be heretiques, that will not obey those pastours that succeed the Apostles in the gift of truth. Which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede the Bishops of Rome, hauing had so little care to doe this great while, if this rule of <hi>Irenaeus</hi> may bee followed, they cannot possibly escape this suspition. The credit therefore of thē waying more with the writer of this preface then his owne, he thought it was better thus to leese his owne, by thus shamefully abusing his reader in prouing this testimony after the popish manner, then once to hazard the credit of his holy fathers the popes, by right, faithfull, and honest dealing therewith. Howbeit, this kinde of dealing of his, may giue iust occasion to all that are wise euer hereafter, to looke better to the fingers of all such fellowes, then vpon their bare word to trust them any more in their quoting or citing of the fathers. But lest we should thinke that this was but a slippe of his by chance, &amp; that hee was not his craftes-master in this kinde of dealing, he hath plaide vs the very like trick againe with this same father pa. 18. &amp; where he alleadgeth the fourth chapter of the said <hi>Irenaeus</hi> third booke, to iustify their traditions not warranted by the written word. For in the beginning of the saide chapter not fiue lines before the wordes cited by him, hee speaking of the scriptures written by the Apostles &amp; Euāgelists, he saith, that they into that rich treasury most fully haue brought all things that belōg to truth, so that euery one that will, may frō thence take the drink of life. And that which he speaketh in the words alleaged by him of following of tradition, it is spoken on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by way of supposition, to shew what course had bene best for the Church, whē any questiō should haue arisen, if they had not left vs scriptures. For his words are these: if the Apostles had not left vs scriptures, must we not haue followed the order of tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which they gaue to them to whom they committed chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches? In which case (which is not our case nowe, seeing they haue left vs scripture) we grant we should haue beene, in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciding of all controuersies that could haue arisen, ouerruled by that which they deliuered by word of mouth to such, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that being the case, no better or readier way for the ending
<pb facs="19"/> of controuersies, should there haue been, then to haue recourse to the most ancient Churches wherin they were conuersant, and so by their tradition, to haue learned the certainty therein. But thus, by way of supposition, <hi>Irenaeus</hi> speaking of their tradition, in the case supposed by him, certaine it is, that by their tradition, he vnderstādeth that soūd form of doctrin, which they deliuered by their preaching, &amp; teaching, which thē would &amp; should haue been the same (forasmuch as they spoke &amp; wrot by one spirit) that now they haue left vs in writing. And therefore euē then the Romish Church, should haue been as far to seeke, as she is now, for hauing any warrant from thence, for those things that she holdeth, either contrary, or besides the word written. And that by tradition, he meaneth here no other thing, it is euident, for in the first chapter of that booke he saith plainely: <hi>Quod tum praeconiauerunt, postea, per Dei voluntatem nobis tradiderunt in scripturis, columnam &amp; fundamē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum fidei futurum,</hi> that is, that which first they preached, after by the will of god, they deliuered vnto vs in the scriptures, to be the piller and ground of faith. And in the third chapter of that book (hauing before spoken of the Apostolicke tradition) he after sheweth what he meant thereby, namely this, that god the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of heauen and earth &amp;c, as he is described in the olde testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Apostles haue taught to be the father of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, contrary to the phantasticall franticke dreame of <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinian,</hi> so plainely shewing, that they that would, euen by the scriptures themselues, might learne what the Apostolick traditiō was. Now what is this, for the authorishing, the vnwritē traditiōs of the Romish church, which are not ōly al beside the scriptures, but whereof the most are contrary thereūto? But this, gentle rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, is the right trick of all the crue of these Romanists, thus by the ambiguity of words out of the fathers, to seek to colour their absurd opinions, &amp; so er thou be a ware, to deceaue thee, if thou take not heede. As for example, to perswade a mā to like of their beggerly vnwritten traditiōs, whatsoeuer any father speaketh of traditiō, though it be neuer so plaine in the author himselfe, that thereby he meaneth nothing lesse, then such traditions as theirs, yet that must be confidently brought in, as fit, &amp; most pregnant, for their purpose. Likwise whatsoeuer any father hath said of any sacramētall chāge of the outward elements, for that therein their name, vse, &amp; estimation are chāged, though the same father in a thousād other places shew, that his iudgemēt is, that there is no
<pb facs="19"/> change at all there in substance, yet that must be quoted as a flat place for Popish trāsubstantiation. And euen so, if they find in a father speaking of the Eucharist, any mention of a sacrifice, as though there were no kind of sacrifice, but that which they dream to bee there, that must be vrged as a strong place, to proue their blasphemous sacrifice for the quick &amp; the dead. And this iugling with the fathers, and cosening of their poore simple readers, vse they in al their cōtrouersies. But at this time, thou must pardō this preface writer this fault, because herein, he doth but study to bee like him, before whose book he hath set this his preface. For chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fifth, he himselfe most grosly committeth this same fault, in the detection whereof, I haue more at large discouered this lewde dealing of theirs. In the meane time, let vs not forget that <hi>Irenaeus</hi> hath taught vs, what that church is, who those pastours be, &amp; what those traditiōs are, that we must obey &amp; be ruled by, namely, onely that Church that hath the scriptures for the piller &amp; groūd of her faith, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. those pastours that succeede the Apostles in truth of doctrine, <hi>li.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 43. &amp; those traditiōs which haue good warrant from the scriptures themselues, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. whereof it must needes follow, that all the places &amp; reasons quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him, either out of the scriptures or fathers, to binde vs to yeeld obedience to their churches ordinances, their prelates cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, &amp; to the points warranted onely by their traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, their Church hauing another foundation of her faith then the worde written, namely alwaies their popes will as it hath, &amp; the commādemēts of their prelates, &amp; traditions, being not only beside, but also often most grosly contrary to that word of God writtē (as I shal shew in sundry places, er I haue done with <hi>Albine</hi>) in <hi>Irenaeus</hi> iudgemēt, ar but so many abusings and corruptings of their holy &amp; good meanings. And yet thus, hauing to no purpose bestowed a great deale of idle paines, as one that had said inough to proue that the authority of all the learned fathers, the cōmon consēt of all Christiā regions, &amp; prescriptiō of time, were al ful &amp; fast of his side, he lustily braggeth <hi>p.</hi> 22. that if their be any weight in any, or al these together, that his side hath the true gospell, &amp; the true sence thereof. That their Religion is the very Christian Religion, their order of ceremonies the right order, and that their fasting and praying, is according to the scriptures, and that therefore their church is the lawfull and true spouse of Christ, from which, who so seperates himselfe, is in state of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.
<pb facs="20"/> This thus only said, thereupō by and by, as though there were no remedy, but that we must needs grant all this to be true, he taketh occasion to triumph, and to frame a bitter inuectiue, against our Religion and liues: so concluding his wordy preface, with an exhortation to his Reader to forsake vs &amp; our Religiō, &amp; to ioine againe with thē in theirs. All which because it is nothing, but the vaine &amp; malitious wordes of a foolish aduersary, without proofe or shadowe of proofe (which therefore I am sure the wise Reader will make no reckoning of,) I might very well let passe with this onely answere, that whatsoeuer he hath here said brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gingly, either in the commendation of his Religion &amp; Church, or to the disgrace of ours, is vtterly false, and that I haue plentifully proued it so to be, in sundry places of this my answere. Howbeit seing this is not only his brag, but the brag also a nūber of times, of <hi>Iohn de Albine</hi> in the booke following, &amp; indeed, is in effect, the only thing, by taking whereof granted, most subtily they, &amp; all their fellowes, seeke to beguile their simple readers, it shal not be amisse, because here first we meete with it, least otherwise the Reader should be too ready, to suffer his hart to be sorestald with this false principle, to the preiudice of the truth, somewhat to say to make both the vanity &amp; falshood hereof to appeare to euery one. First therefore it is worthy the marking, that the mā, though (as hee plainly sheweth, hee had here a full purpose, at least in wordes, to giue as great countenaunce as he could to his cause) that yet, he seekes to giue it credit, but by the testimonie of fathers, consent of Christian regions, and prescription of time, in the meane time, omitting that which is to be preferd before all these, namely the testimony of the vndoubted word of God, reuealed &amp; set downe in the scriptures: wherein he hath dealt but as the nature of his cause requires, which hath no counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance from thence, and as the fashion of other of his companiōs in this case is. For hereupō it is, that there is nothing more cōmon in their discourses then to labour by all meanes they can, the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of the written word of god, and to establish the credite of a word vnwritten, which they count to be the traditions or ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary practise of the Church of Rome. To this ende they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowe so much paines as they doe, at least to make shewe of proofe, that the scriptures are so darke and obscure, so insufficiēt for the direction of the Church in all matters, and of so vveake
<pb facs="20"/> authority of themselues without the authority and testimonie of the Church to countenance them, that without the foresaid vnwritten word, no man could either fully or certainly, be setled and established in the truth. So that herein this is their drift, that they indeed being without all sounde warrant out of the cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall scriptures, for those thinges which wee count erroneous in thē, they yet may make their followers beleeue, that they haue as good ground as need be for them, in that they can proue thē, by the tradition of the Church, which they call the word of god vnwritten, and which they hold to be not onely aequal, vnto the other that is written, but also far more full and certaine for the determining the trueth of all controuersies. And therefore <hi>Soto contra Brentium, Canisius cap.</hi> 5. of his Catechisme, and <hi>Lindan lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. of his panoplie are not ashamed to confesse, (reckening almost all the pointes in controuersie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them and vs) that they haue their ground and warrant from tradition, not written in the scriptures. And hereupon it is, that there is nothing more common with any of them, then when wee presse them, with this, that the opinions for the which we striue with them haue no warrāt in the scripture, yea that the scriptures rightly vnderstoode are flatte against them therein, to flye to tradition, which is the cause that this fellowe him selfe was so busie before to abuse <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> for the countenance of that onely foundation of their Religion. For this cause we may &amp; doe say of them, &amp; that iustly, by their owne confessiō, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> saide of the hereticks in his time, they cannot stand, if they be driuen once to determine al their controuersies by the scriptures, <hi>de Resurrectione Carnis cap.</hi> 3. Now as for vs (Christian reader) for all this lewde bragge of his, we appeale to these scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of god, and onely wee allowe of them, as of a most perfect touchstone whereby to trye, in all matters of Religion, the pure golde from the counterfait, crauing no further liking nor allowance in any thing, then by them wee are able soundly to proue, and confirme that which we say and teach. And the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient holy fathers, and so the Christian regions in al ancient pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of time, which are the things that he here brags of, as it appeares in all sound monuments of antiquity, euer since these scriptures were written, for the determining of controuersies in their times, haue alwaies taken this course to cōfute &amp; confound
<pb facs="21"/> all aduersaries to the truth. As for their owne authority, or the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of any other before them, no further credit they craue, then as they are foūd to agree with these scriptures, otherwise the more that haue couseted &amp; the lōger they held, the worse. This I haue made manifest by plētifull testimony of the ancient fathers thēselues <hi>cap.</hi> 3.5.23. And therfore whiles he sends vs thus to the fathers, Christian regions consent, &amp; prescription of time, he sēds vs but about the bush, for when we come to thē, they will send vs backe againe to the scriptures. But whiles they take this course in seeking rather countenance for their cause any where else, then at, or by the canonicall scriptures, in the iust iudgement of god, they plainly bewray themselues to euery simple mā, to haue but a bad cause, that they so shun the light, and refuse the most cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, &amp; most indifferent triall of it, which questionles is by these scriptures, whose neither authority nor indifferecy, without blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, may once be called in question. Indeed I read, that whē they were pressed with the authority of these scriptures, the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cionites</hi> pretēded for the defence of their heresy, their paraclet or cōforters visiōs, &amp; instructiōs: &amp; that likewise the <hi>Mōtanists</hi> did fly to their prophecy: the <hi>Valētinians</hi> to their dreams of their <hi>Aeons:</hi> the <hi>Manichees</hi> to their fundamētal Epistle: the <hi>Iewes</hi> to their <hi>Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mud:</hi> &amp; the <hi>Turks</hi> to their <hi>Alcaron:</hi> &amp; belike lest these should be foūd vnlike these their predecessors, they will thus fly from the vndoubted authority of god, speaking in the scriptures, to the vncertaine and variable authority of man.</p>
      <p>Yet if this were true that he saith, that they haue the auncient holy fathers, the common consent of all Christian regions, &amp; pre scriptiō of time of their side, it were sōewhat, &amp; some likelihood it were, that things were with thē, as he saith, I must needs cōfesse, but indeed &amp; truth, they haue neither al nor any of these, in that sort to speake for thē, as he would make his Reader beleeue. For first, there is plaine contrariety betwixt their doctrine, &amp; the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the auncient holy fathers, in a number of most weighty points, as I haue shewed at large <hi>ca.</hi> 17. &amp; 29. likewise in that both ther, &amp; also <hi>c.</hi> 39. &amp; 40. in that I shew, that they hold many things directly contrary to the ancient generall councels, I plentifully proue, that they are destitute, of the commō consent of Christiā regions. And as for the last, though it were grānted thē, that they may truly pretēd long continuāce of time, yet seing it is true, that
<pb facs="21"/>
         <hi>Tertullian de velandis virginibus</hi> hath said, <hi>Quodcun{que} aduersus veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatē sapit, heraesis est, etiā vetus cōsuetudo:</hi> that is, whatsoeuer sauoreth against the truth, is heresy, though it be an old custome: &amp; seing also it is certaine, that <hi>Cyprian ad Pompeiū</hi> saith, custome must not let truth to preuaile, for custōe without truth, is but oldnes of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, that could do thē litle good, we being alwaies able as webe, to proue by the scriptures soūdly interpreted, &amp; by al soūd antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that they are gone lōg agoe frō the trueth. But in deed though popery be too anciēt, &amp; so hath had sōe cōtinuāce of time, yet it is but a yongling, in respect of that which they pretend. And this I haue also proued <hi>cap.</hi> 17. &amp; in sūdry other places of my answere following. Yea that more is, &amp; which will goe nearer then I haue proued, that indeed we for our Religion &amp; Church, haue not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prescription of some longtime, but also of all times &amp; ages euē frō the beginning. <hi>c.</hi> 4.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17. And yet this point of antiquity, &amp; prescriptiō of time, is a thing that they so cōfidētly stād vpō, that in the offer annexed to <hi>Iohn de Albines</hi> book, that proud chalēger offreth to recāt, if we cā shew where, &amp; whē, in what yeare of the lord, &amp; vnder what Emperor, &amp; by whō, popery cāe in, &amp; by whō of our side it was gain said: which though I haue, I hope, sufficiētly shewed in the chapters last before quoted, yet because the answe rīgfully to this point, &amp; the remouig of this obiectiō, wil both blūt the edge of this his brag, &amp; greatly crack the credit of popery, I wil voutsafe sōewhat more here, to set down to the cōfutatiō of it.</p>
      <p>Hereunto therefore, whereas the foresaid offerer, and others of that side, so stand vpon the antiquity of their Church and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that they would seeme we must needes grant, that they are even as auncient, as they pretend, vnles we can shew when, where, &amp; by whō, a sodaine change frō our Religiō to theirs was made, &amp; that some of our side thē presētly espied it, &amp; withstood it, vnreasonable it is that they demaunde. For popery being not one, or two particular heresies, nor such a masse or heape of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resies, whose property is to burst in all at once of the sodaine, shewing it selfe with open and bare face at the first, but as it is tearmed, 2. <hi>Thess.</hi> 2. a mistery of iniquity, and therefore a false Religiō, creeping in cūningly by litle &amp; litle, as it were, by stealing steps, &amp; that hiddē asmuch as might bee, vnder the shew &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of holines through hypocrisy 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp; Reu.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 11. no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile though it were not only verie hard, but euen impossible, in
<pb facs="22"/> euery respect to satisfie this demaunde. And yet for al this, were popery neuer a whit the more to be liked. For as we see by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that ostentimes there is far more daunger in those disea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, that steale vppon a man by little and little, and therefore are not resisted at the first, then in those that are apparant and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent when they begin, and therefore then are they more careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly withstoode and looked vnto: euen so oftentimes also it falles out in errours and heresies, that they of al other in the end proue the most dangerous, whose beginnings haue beene most close and secret, and whose growing to their perfection hath not been of the sodaine, but in long tract of time. Indeede those diseases that come vpon the sodaine and are violent, &amp; in their fulnes at the first, men at the first may espy and complaine of, but so it is not, not cannot be alwaies in the other. We see also, that though it be an easy matter to name the father of a lawfully begotten childe, yet no man commonly can tell who is the father of the base sonne of a common woman. But to make it yet more cleare, that popery may be naught (as it is) &amp; yet this his demaunde be vnreasonable, we are to cal to mind, that Christ our sauiour, who knew best how such most dangerous cankers and diseases, would grow and come vp in his church, hath taught vs <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. that it will not alwaies be knowen &amp; espied, no not of his owne hous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde seruants, when and by whom first the tares are sowen in his field, where he had before onely sowed good seede. And there he showes vs, that notwithstanding, that it shall be sufficient to proue them tares, in that afterwards whē they are come vp, they differ as they doe from the good seed. Though therefore it were so, that we could not tel when, &amp; by whō, popery was first sowē in Gods field, yet in that now it being growen vp therein, as it is, it being compared with gods good seede taken out of the garner or barne of his holy written word, it differeth from it as it doth, that ought to be sufficient proofe vnto vs, that it is but tares, &amp; of the deuils sowing by his deuilish seedsimē, whensoeuer they did it. Doubtles the creeping of it in, not all at once, but by little and litle, &amp; that with such soft &amp; sly paces, the shew of holines &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion that it hath stolen in vnder, the trouble that the holy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient fathers had in their times otherwise, in confuting grosse he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resies that shewed themselues such at the first, and the small sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition (if they had marked the beginnings hereof, that were in
<pb facs="22"/> their times) that they could haue had, that euer they would haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rowen to this that they are now, haue beene so many great and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>peciall causes, why the first beginnings thereof haue beene no more noted &amp; resisted then they haue beene. Againe this I must <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eeds further say, that it may yet very wel be, that the beginning &amp; proceeding also thereof, haue beene both better obserued &amp; withstood by the anciēt fathers in the primatiue church, thē ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth now vnto vs in their bookes &amp; monuments: for in these parts of the world in these last 4 or 500 yeares they so raigning &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>yrānizing as they did, they hauing their books in their keeping, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>heir care and diligence being as it was, by al meanes possible to maintaine their own credit, very likely is it, that as they met with any thing to that end, they haue foūd the means to suppresse &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ase it out of their writings. Infinite proofes and examples there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e (they know wel inough) to enduce any mā to think, that loue of their owne cause, &amp; hatred of the truth, would easily prouoke them in this case to be thus bold with their labours. For in all sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries since their kingdome grew to the ful, not onely from time to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ime, it is noted, that if God raised vp any (as he did alwaies some <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s I haue shewed <hi>cap.</hi> 4.) to speake &amp; write against their corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they tooke straight such order, that if not both the men and their bookes, yet at least their bookes should be burned and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed. And they that haue had, when the times were far better, three popes one after an other, so bolde &amp; impudent thorowe an ambitious desire then of primacy, to forge a false &amp; counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faite canon of the councel of Nice, and to vrge it in the opē face of an other great &amp; famous councell of Carthage, when notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ously their forgery was espied, &amp; therefore they plainly tolde of it by epistles writtē vnto thē by that councel of purpose, no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, though when they had attained their ful desire of an vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal supremacy, they durst do and did whatsoeuer they thought good, to let as few monuments of antiquity remaine any way to their discredit, as might be. Hēce I am fully persuaded that in great part it cōmeth that we finde so litle as we do, to bewray their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning &amp; proceeding, and the withstanding thereof in the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of anciēt fathers &amp; Croniclers. And yet though we foūd in thē far lesse then we do, I say againe, that thence ariseth no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to iustifie the popish church or religion: for is there any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son that a ship that is drowned by leaking, a mā that is dead by a
<pb facs="23"/> consumptiō, &amp; a cōmō weale that is growen frō a moderate and wel ordered gouernment, to an absolute tyranny, should be said to be safe, in health, aliue, &amp; in good state, because we cannot tell whē, &amp; where, the ship began first to leake, the mā began first to fall into his consumption, and when the common weale began first to grow out of order? Likely enough also is it, that the great credit that the ancient bishops of Rome were in, for their piety and godlinesse, and the lofty estate of their successours after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, so dazeled on the one side, the eyes of the godly in ancient time, that they were not curious, in resisting the doings of their successours: and so bridled on the other side, the tongues of the worldly minded of these latter dayes, that they durst not write that which they saw: all which reasons layd together make it euident, that it ought to be no wonder, nor yet any argument, any whit at all to credit popery, though this offerers demaunde could not be satisfied. Howbeit, this onely I haue written, to shew the vnreasonablenesse of this demaunde, for indeede, Gods name be praysed for it, hovv vnreasonable soeuer it be otherwyse, vvee are able sufficiently to aunswere it. For <hi>Paul</hi> hath tolde vs, that this mystery of iniquity was vvorking in his dayes 2. <hi>Thes.</hi> 2. <hi>vers.</hi> 7. And so indeed it vvas, in that euen then, first their were false Apostles, that laboured to corrupt the article of free and full saluation, through the onely meanes and merytes of Christ Iesus, teaching that it vvas necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to saluation, for them that beleeued in Christ also to bee circumcysed, as it appeares, <hi>Actes</hi> 15. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that there vvere such, as hereupon grew a step further, namely, to vrge the necessity of the obseruing of humane traditions, as, <hi>Touch not, tast not, handle not,</hi> so making a shew of humblenesse of minde, in worshipping of Angels, and of vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary religion, in not sparing their bodies, in obseruing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: against all vvhich, <hi>Saint Paul</hi> standes foorth in the places before quoted, &amp; also in the second of the <hi>Colossians.</hi> This damnable errour also vvas considered of, and confuted in that famous Apostolike councell, <hi>Actes.</hi> 15. And amongst others, <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> also sharpely rebuketh and condemneth the teachers, of this Antichristian doctrine, calling them very Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christs, and such as vvere gone out from them, that so it
<pb facs="23"/> might appeare, that they were neuer of them, <hi>Epist.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ers.</hi> 18.19. And therefore as I shew <hi>Cap.</hi> 17. the church of Christ and the teachers therein vniuersally, for six hūdred years after Christ and more, taught directly against ioining any person or thing vvith Christ in the office of iustifying and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ing: though now there is nothing more vsuall in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ish church that nowe is, then to teach other merites and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>atisfactions in these respects to be trusted vnto besides Christs. The next Capitall poynt of Antichristianity is the nowe chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>enged supremacy of the Romane prelate, and as for that, we can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hew, both the beginning and proceeding thereof from time to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ime, and who alwaies set themselues against it. The first <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mbitious clyming that way, we may note in the mother of <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>edeus</hi> children, and her two sonnes, who comming vnto Christ, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>equire this of him, that the one may sit at his right hād, &amp; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>her at his left in his kingdome, and that vvas spyed to bee a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>owle fault in them by Christ, and therefore by him they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hecked and vvithstood <hi>Matth.</hi> 20. After we read of one <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> that so loued the preheminēce that he would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue <hi>Iohn,</hi> and such as hee was, but in his third epistle <hi>vers.</hi> 9. he shewes he spied him, and that he did vtterly dislike that ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ogant &amp; ambitious humor of his, yet by these warnings your bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops of Rome, would not take heede, but for al this, would take to much vpon them ouer their brethren, but when either they, or others haue done so, it appeares in ancient Croni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and in the writings of the ancient fathers, that they had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes some that did spie it, and set themselues against it. For when <hi>Victor</hi> bishop of Rome, about the yeare of Christ, two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derd, somewhat popelike, so farre exceeded his bounds, that he tooke vpon him to excommunicate the bishops of the East, for that they would not conforme themselues to the fashion of the church of Rome, in the keeping of Easter, not onely <hi>Polycra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> and sundry other bishops there vvithstoode him therein, out here in the west, <hi>Irenaeus</hi> bishop then of Lions (though he were of <hi>Ʋictors</hi> minde for the obseruing of Easter) yet in his ovvne name, and in the name of his brethren, wrote to <hi>Ʋictor,</hi> &amp; in that his letter rebukes him, for his so far proceeding, as you may reade in <hi>Euseb. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 22. and 23. And after this in
<pb facs="24"/>
         <hi>Cyprians</hi> time about the yeare 255. when <hi>Cornelius</hi> Bishop of Rome vnaduisedly, &amp; cōtrary to the good policy of the church, and after him <hi>Stephanus,</hi> tooke vpon them so to admitte of fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues out of Africke at Rome, that not only they receaued them into their communion, but tooke vpon them to labour their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution, they being before for their iust demerits excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, and deposed in Africke: <hi>Cyprian</hi> wrote vnto them both to <hi>Cornelius</hi> in his first booke of Epistles, Epistle 3. and to <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanus</hi> in his second booke, and first Epistle, wherein earnestly he reproueth them for so intermedling in his iurisdiction, &amp; the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdictiō of other his collegues in Africke, shewing thē that they ought not so to do, for they in Africk had as ful Pishoply autority as they at Rome, and therefore were both able and the fittest, to heare and determine such cases as fell out amongst themselues. But seeing for all this the Bishops of Rome still were too busy, in meddling further then they should, after this in the counsell of Nice cannon 6. their authority and the Patriarches of Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria are made equall about the yeare 320. And yet the better to stay and keepe the Bishops of Rome within their due limits af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, in most counsels for 300. yeares after something still was done to bridle them. For certaine it is that as it appeares dist. 99. the thirde counsell of Carthage helde about the yeare 435. <hi>cap.</hi> 26. forbad the ambitious and proud tytles of Prince, of Priests, High-priests &amp; such like, euen to the Bishops of the first see. And <hi>Concilio Mileuitano,</hi> about the yeare 420. &amp; in another of Africke held betwixt these two, as some write, about the yeare 428. <hi>cap.</hi> 92. appeales vnto them frō the Bishops &amp; counsels of Africke were forbidden. And the great generall councell of Calcedon held about the yeare 453. when the Bishop of Romes legates had done what they could to the contrary <hi>Act.</hi> 15.16. &amp; canon 28. gaue the Patriarch of Cōstantinople equal priuiledges with the Bishop of Rome. And long after this, the first generall coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell, being the third (as it is noted in the second tome of the coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celles) held at Constantinople in the time of <hi>Pope Agatho,</hi> about the yeare of the Lord 681. renuing a decree before there cōsen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto, in a councell consisting of 150. Bishops <hi>cap.</hi> 5. and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring likewise the foresaide 28. cannon of the councell of Calcedon, whereas some write there were 630. Bishops, <hi>cap.</hi> 36. ratifieth and enacteth the same. And if we go no further then to
<pb facs="24"/> the former fiue general councels, we shall finde them all to haue had a care by their decrees, to keepe the bishops of Rome within their due boūds of their owne patriarchall see. For proofe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, let any mā but read the sixt canon of the Nicene, the second &amp; third of the first of Constantinople, the eight of the Ephesme, remembring withal the twenty eight of the Calcedon, twise now immediatly before mentioned, &amp; vnderstand that the fift gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral councell solemnely confirmed those fowre former, and their canons &amp; decrees, and he cannot choose but see this to be most manifest. But amongst all the rest, notable is that that appeares to this end in that great solemne Africane councel, where <hi>Zozi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Boniface,</hi> &amp; <hi>Celestine,</hi> three popes on a rew, by their Legates vnder one of their hands alleadging a false canon of the councel of Nice, all that was determined in former councels to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary notwithstāding, shewed themselues intolerably ambitious of supremacy, thereby most egerly claiming such a preheminēce to be giuen to their see, that if any bishop or minister, were depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in any other prouince, or Patriarchal see, that vpō his appeale to Rome, the Bishop of Rome might accept thereof, &amp; therevpō either write his letters to the next prouince to determine the matter, or else to sende his Legate from his side to represent his own person, to sit in iudgement with the bishops there to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the matter. For there, as it appeares, in the 101 102 103 &amp; 105 <hi>chap.</hi> of that councell, in the first tome of the councels, this their allegation was not onely examined, by all the copies of the Nicene councell that they had there, but also by ancient copies thereof, which they sent for thither of purpose to Alexandria, Antioch, &amp; Constantinople, &amp; thereby in the open face of that councell, where 217 Bishops were assembled, their forgery was espied, &amp; therefore that allegation notwithstanding, the bishop of Romes dealing concerning <hi>Apiarius</hi> (who then gaue the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of that stur) was there openly disliked &amp; condemned, &amp; therefore to preuent the like thereafter, they in their 92 <hi>chapter</hi> there determine, that whosoeuer should so appeale any more frō the bishops, &amp; coūcels of Africke beyond the seas, should thēce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth neuer after of any in Africke be receaued into communiō. Besides, as it appears there in the 105. <hi>cap.</hi> by the common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of that councell, a letter was framed and sent to <hi>Celestine,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the latter end therof (as it should seeme by the stories about
<pb facs="25"/> the yeare foure hundred and thirty) wherein first they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monish him to admit no more such appeales, or fugitiues, but to send them backe againe alwaies to their owne prouinces and Metropolitans, and the rather, say they, because such order was taken by the Nicene councell. And after therein they pleade the equity of that ordinance, because the holy ghost is aswell in one prouince, as in an other, and there the cause is alwayes like best to bee handled, where it doeth arise, because of the neighnesse of the vvitnesses. Wherefore hauing tolde him, that they finde no such thing in the truer copies of the Nicene councell, as <hi>Faustinus</hi> sent by him alleadged, they flatly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid him the sending of his agents or legates any more, vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny such occasion amongst them. It shoulde seeme for all this, that so incident to that see, vvas this ambitious humor, that in pope <hi>Symachus</hi> time, about the yeare fiue hundred, many bishops euen in these parts, did accuse him to <hi>Theodoricus,</hi> king of the <hi>Gothes,</hi> because hee tooke vpon him to bee <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, that is, one vvho vvoulde haue his vvill to be a law, which is now professed, to bee the popes prerogatiue and not to bee controled. Dist. 40. <hi>Si papa.</hi> In <hi>Gregorie</hi> his time, in the raigne of <hi>Mauritius</hi> the Emperour, the bishop of Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople lustely chalenged the title of vniuersall bishop, but then <hi>Pelagius</hi> bishop of Rome in the yeare fiue hundred eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty three (as it appears in the ninty nine destinction of your law in <hi>Gratian</hi>) and Gregory also his successor condemned that, for an vnlawfull and Antichristian name in him, or in any other bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, the bishops of Rome themselues not excepted, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>epist.</hi> 32.38.39. And vvhereas (this notwithstanding) <hi>Boniface</hi> the next but one to <hi>Gregory</hi> (though with somewhat a doe) ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of that murderer and traitor <hi>Phocas,</hi> (who hauing cruelly slaine <hi>Mauritius,</hi> succeded him in the Empire) this Antichristian title, first to be called vniuersal bishop, or head of the church, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse <hi>Sabellicus, Marianus Scotus, Martinus Polonus,</hi> and others, yet as <hi>Platina</hi> witnesseth in <hi>vita Dom,</hi> the church of Rauēna in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly complained thereof, and vntill pope <hi>Donus</hi> time (which vvas seuenty yeares after) it coulde not bee brought to to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerate and like of it. <hi>Otho Frisingensis lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Cap.</hi> 35. an ancient historiographer, speaking of <hi>Gregory</hi> the seuenth commonly called <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> and his proceedings against the Emperour
<pb facs="25"/>
         <hi>Henry,</hi> not only to excommunicate him, but also to depose him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ith, <hi>Lego &amp; relego Romanorum regum &amp; Imperatorum gesta &amp;c.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>read and read againe the acts of the Romane kings and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and yet before this, I finde none of them of the Romane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ishop excommunicated, or depriued of his kingdome. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> we read <hi>Sigebert, Abbas Ʋrspergensis, H. Mutius,</hi> and others, vve shall finde, that the same Bishop, for this his Antichristi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n pride, and other faultes that hee had, vvas not onely won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully vvithstoode and oppugned by that Emperour, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>y councels also then held at <hi>Brixia, Mentz,</hi> and <hi>Wormes,</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>harpely rebuked, condemned, and desposed. And though hee hauing thus begunne to encroch vpon the Emperour, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his successours follovved him in his very steps, yet we read also in Cronicles that <hi>Henrie</hi> the fifte, <hi>Fredericke</hi> the first, and <hi>Fredericke</hi> the second Emperours, <hi>Philip</hi> the faire, and <hi>Carolus Caluus</hi> of Fraunce, <hi>Henry</hi> the first and second, <hi>Richard</hi> the second, and king <hi>Iohn</hi> of England, with sundry other Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and kings, did notably and openly resist them therein, and that they had alvvaies many learned fathers and Bishops to take their partes. But to leaue this matter, and to go on to others: because the author of this preface, and brag that I novv am in aunswering, in his brag maketh speciall menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as you haue heard of their order of ceremonies, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of praying, and fasting, bosting that for these, they haue the holy fathers, the consent of all christian nations, and prescription of long continuance, yea for the tvvo last the very scriptures: let vs first see if wee can finde out the originall, and vvithall the iust reproofe and condemnation of these. First for their ceremonies, none that hath but redde <hi>Platina,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther story of the liues of their popes, but he hath red when, how, and by whom they were deuised, for there is few of them, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred yeares together, that thought, as it should seeme by the vvriters of their liues, that they had worthily sate in that place, vnles they had deuised some newe rite and ceremony more then was before. But if one goe no further then to <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor de inventoribus rerum,</hi> there shall hee finde when, and by whom they had their originall, whereby also it shal appeare, that for many of thē they are of so late devising, they cannot pretend either the testimony of ancient fathers, or prescriptiō of any long
<pb facs="26"/> time, &amp; for very few of them, whatsoeuer he bragges, can they truly alleadge consent of all Christian regions, for as they haue most of them beene deuised here in these parts of the worlde by bishops of Rome, so few of them in comparison haue beene, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> yet be receaued in the other parts of Christianity, that were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the other Patriarches of Constātinople, Alexandria, &amp; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch: yea euen here in these parts, all their rites &amp; ceremonies were neuer yet vniuersally receaued of euery cuntry alike, no nor yet of euery part of any one cuntry. But they being in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber so many, in nature a number of them so childish and foolish, &amp; yet hauing beene vrged as they haue, to be vsed with such o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion and holines, S. Pauls reprehension of those that were in his time so busy with the Colossians, in vrging thē to keepe their ordinances, the keeping whereof lay in, <hi>touch not, tast not, handle not, Coloss.</hi> 2. is both a bewraying, when such like ceremonies as these that he brags of first began, and also a iust and a full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of them. Read also <hi>S. Augustines</hi> 119 epistle <hi>ad Ianua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi> and you shall finde there, how earnestly he hath enueied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the multiplying, and bringing in, &amp; so vrging of such vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necessary rites and ceremonies: shewing how few the simplicity of the gospel is contented withal. And yet as it is wel known, he liued 1000 years ago, and that since his time there are 1000. newrites &amp; ceremonies deuised in the Romish church, that he neuer had heard of, &amp; yet thē he complained that there were so many, and they so seruilely were vrged, that the Iewes state was in that respect far more tolerable, what would he haue said then, if he had liued in these daies, and had seene the curious, infinite, and foolish rites and ceremonies, but of one popish priest formal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doing his masse?</p>
      <p>Indeed fasting is a thing, and so is prayer, that hath counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of scriptures, fathers, Christian regions, and of all ages and times, but so hath not either the popish fasting or praying. For their fasting is tyed superstitiously to set daies, and also lyeth es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in abstinence from one meat, rather then from an other, their end therein being not onely to chastise the body, that it may be brought the more readily &amp; feruently to obey the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly direction of the spirit, as the word of God teacheth onely it should, but euen thereby to satisfie, either for some sin past, or to earne or deserue somewhat at the hands of God. Such fasting
<pb facs="26"/> as this was that of the hypocritical pharisies, wherof Christ warm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s disciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.16. &amp; the first fathers, &amp; teachers hereof, are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hose spirits of errour, that <hi>S. Paul</hi> speakes of 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. and so you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ay there see both, who first in the church of Christ, found out &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ractised your kind of fasting, &amp; who by &amp; by spied it, &amp; condē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ed it for hypocritical, &amp; the doctrine of deuils. But if you would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aue vs to search further, we tel you, that after Christ &amp; his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tles times, <hi>Eusebius</hi> reports in his 5 booke &amp; 16 chapter out of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>olonius,</hi> that <hi>Montanus</hi> the heretique, prescribed lawes of fasting, &amp; he is the first that we read of, that tyed fasting by law, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>cript daies &amp; times, which is there reckoned vp by that <hi>Apolonius,</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s one of his heretical deuises. This <hi>Montanus</hi> was about they eare of the Lord 145. And it appears in <hi>Augustines</hi> 2. booke &amp; 13. <hi>cha.</hi> of the manners of the church, &amp; of the <hi>Manichees,</hi> that it was the fashiō thē of those heretiques, to thinke vpon their fasting daies, that they fasted excellētly, though otherwise they had neuer so dainty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e so they abstained from flesh &amp; wine, for the which <hi>Augustine</hi> doth deride thē. And cōsequently herein <hi>Apolonius</hi> &amp; <hi>Augustine,</hi> haue shewed their dislike of that popish fasting. If yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t should be replied, as it is, by some of their side, that their fasting is not altogither like the condemned abstinence of these anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent heretiques, &amp; others, for that they abstained frō flesh vpon an opinion, that flesh was an impurer creature then fish; how will they thē excuse <hi>Durand. li.</hi> 6. <hi>ca. de ieiunijs,</hi> who giueth this as a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of their abstinence vpon fasting daies, rather from flesh, then from fish, because al flesh was accursed in the daies of <hi>Noe</hi> &amp; not all fish?</p>
      <p>Now touching their māner of praying, for al his brag, neither fathers, consent of all Christian regions, prescription of any long continuāce of time, nor scriptures giue it any credit or coūtenāce at al. For first, whereas now they pray al in Latine, a toūg not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood of most that heare, &amp; vse their prayers, it is a kinde of praying flatly condemned, because it is without edification to such, by <hi>Chrysostome</hi> &amp; <hi>Ambrose,</hi> vpō the 14. of the first to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians. Augustine</hi> also <hi>de Genesi ad literā, li.</hi> 12. <hi>Cap.</hi> 8. ioines with them herein, aduouching that no mā is edified by hearing that, which he vnderstands not. And the descriptions of al the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent lyturgies in the Church shew, that alwaies they were vsed in such a tongue, as the people vnderstood aswell as the minister,
<pb facs="27"/> there is such mentiō of intercourse of speech one to the other, as any man may see, that perused the descriptions thereof: yea wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, both old &amp; new do plainely testify, that the ancient &amp; long cōtinued vse of the church hath bene, to haue her publicke litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy in the knowen &amp; vulgar tongue of the people. For <hi>Origē cōtra Celsū lib.</hi> 8. writeth, that the Grecians name God in greeke, &amp; the Romans in the latin tongue, and euery one in their natiue and mother tongue, pray &amp; sing Psalmes vnto God. And <hi>Hierom</hi> to <hi>Eustochuim</hi> describing the solemne funeral of <hi>Pacta,</hi> &amp; elsewhere to <hi>Marcella,</hi> testifieth, that though to Bethleē there was cōcourse of very many seueral nations, yet euery one there praised god &amp; praied vnto him in their owne lāguage. Insomuch that euē <hi>Lyra</hi> vpō the 14 of the first to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> cōfesses, that in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue church, al was done in the vulgar tongue. And no lōger ago then <hi>Innocēt</hi> the thirds time, in the Laterā coūcel held in his time 1215. <hi>c.</hi> 9. order is takē, that where in one cuntrey there be people of diuers lāguages, there the Bishops should prouide them mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, to celebrate thē diuine seruice, &amp; to minister thē the sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, according to the diuersities of their rites &amp; lāguages. Yet further that thou maist see, Christian reader, in this point, that the mā blusheth at nothing, vnderstād, that by the cōfession of their own frend <hi>Eckius</hi> in his cōmō places, the South Indiās haue their liturgy in their mother tongue: &amp; by the cōfessiō of another, one <hi>Sigismūd</hi> writing of the <hi>Moscovites,</hi> that they likewise haue theirs. And <hi>Petrus Bellonius,</hi> writing of the <hi>Armonians,</hi> testifies the like of thē: yea <hi>Aeneas Siluius</hi> who after was a Pope, in his history of the <hi>Bohemiās c.</hi> 13. plainly shewes, that a Pope was admonished by a voice from heauen, to grāt <hi>Cyril,</hi> that conuerted <hi>Russia</hi> &amp; <hi>Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> to say diuine seruice amōgst thē in the <hi>Shlauon</hi> tongue which was their vulgar tongue. How haue they thē, as he bragges, these things considered, either the ancient holy fathers, consent of al regions, or such prescription of time, as he pretēds, for this maner of praying of theirs, in a tongue not vnderstoode of most? And who can read the 14 of the first to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> vnlesse he bee disposed wilfully to be blinde, but he must needes there see, that this maner of praying is directly there condemned? <hi>Chrysostome, Ambrose, Haymo, Lyra,</hi> and so expositours, both ancient and nevv, take it, howsoeuer our late <hi>Rhemists,</hi> in their notes, would faine vvrest the place from any such meaning. And in this
<pb facs="27"/> respect, suppose othervvise their prayers vvere faultles, who seeth not, that they giue God occasion againe to renue his olde complaint <hi>Esay.</hi> 29. <hi>This people drawe neare vnto mee with their lippes, but their hart is farre from mee:</hi> of most peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, vvhich through their tyranny onely pray thus. But in this poynt onely there is not vanity and falshoode in his bragge; for othervvise if vve consider vvell their maner of praying, vve shall finde both grosse vntrueth in his speech, and horrible faultes in their prayers. For how can it bee true, that consent of fathers, and the rest that he bragges of, doe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce that set forme of church-seruice, that now they are in possession of? seing neither the ancient fathers, nor yet one quarter of Christendome, vvas euer acquainted with it? There owne authours, and namely <hi>Polydor de inuentoribus rerum lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 10, doe shevv hovv it came in, and vvas de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uysed piece after piece. In the one thousand tvvo hundred yeares after Christ, it vvas not grovven eyther to that full forme or credit that it is at novv. For the forme of masse novv vsed, commonly called Saint <hi>Gregories</hi> masse, with much adoe got to be first in these westerne partes receiued in Pope <hi>Adrians</hi> time, 790 yeares after Christ, witnes <hi>Durand Nauclere,</hi> and <hi>Iaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus de voragine:</hi> and yet euen then, and long after, <hi>Millayn</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued the vse of a forme of liturgy receiued from <hi>Ambrose. Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict</hi> the 3, that succeeded next <hi>Ioan</hi> the harlot, about the yeare 857 first inuented &amp; brought in the dirge, as most authors write, though <hi>Gregory</hi> the 3 had done sōwhat about it before. The first allowance of the sequences in the masse is attributed to <hi>Nicolas</hi> the first, that succeeded this <hi>Benedict,</hi> In <hi>Alexander</hi> the 2 time, <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liluiah</hi> was first suspēded out of the church in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ēt time, which was aboue 1000 yeare after Christ. Our ordinary here in England, <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum vsum Sarum,</hi> began 1076 yeares after Christ, and that, as our stories shew, by occasion of a bloody quarel betwixt the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot of Glassenbury &amp; his monkes. The 7 canonical houres came in first by <hi>Vrban</hi> the second, in the yeare one thousand &amp; ninety. But <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth, that monstrous enemy of <hi>Fredericke</hi> the second, first brought in that blasphemous canticle <hi>Salue regina,</hi> one thousād two hūdred yeare &amp; more after Christ. And howso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer these patches, in the ende grevve in these partes to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> sovved togither, yet the other partes of the vvorld vnder the
<pb facs="28"/>
         <hi>Cyprians</hi> time about the yeare 255. when <hi>Corneliu.</hi> Bishop of Rome vnaduisedly, &amp; cōtrary to the good policy of the church, and after him <hi>Stephanus,</hi> tooke vpon them so to admitte of fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues out of Africke at Rome, that not only they receaued them into their communion, but tooke vpon them to labour their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution, they being before for their iust demerits excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, and deposed in Africke: <hi>Cyprian</hi> wrote vnto them both: to <hi>Cornelius</hi> in his first booke of Epistles, Epistle 3. and to <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanus</hi> in his second booke, and first Epistle, wherein earnestly he reproueth them for so intermedling in his iurisdiction, &amp; the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdictiō of other his collegues in Africke, shewing thē that they ought not so to do, for they in Africk had as ful Bishoply autority as they at Rome, and therefore were both able and the fittest, to heare and determine such cases as fell out amongst themselues. But seeing for all this the Bishops of Rome still were too busy, in meddling further then they should, after this in the counsell of Nice cannon 6. their authority and the Patriarches of Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria are made equall about the yeare 320. And yet the better to stay and keepe the Bishops of Rome within their due limits af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, in most counsels for 300. yeares after something still was done to bridle them. For certaine it is that as it appeares dist. 99. the thirde counsell of Carthage helde about the yeare 435. <hi>cap.</hi> 26. forbad the ambitious and proud tytles of Prince, of Priests, High-priests &amp; such like, euen to the Bishops of the first see. And <hi>Concilio Mileuitano,</hi> about the yeare 420. &amp; in another of Africke held betwixt these two, as some write, about the yeare 428. <hi>cap.</hi> 92. appeales vnto them frō the Bishops &amp; counsels of Africke were forbidden. And the great generall councell of Calcedon held about the yeare 453. when the Bishop of Romes legates had done what they could to the contrary <hi>Act.</hi> 15.16. &amp; canon 28. gaue the Patriarch of Cōstantinople equal priuiledges with the Bishop of Rome. And long after this, the first generall coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell, being the third (as it is noted in the second tome of the coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celles) held at Constantinople in the time of <hi>Pope Agatho,</hi> about the yeare of the Lord 681. renuing a decree before there cōsen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto, in a councell consisting of 150. Bishops <hi>cap.</hi> 5. and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring likewise the foresaide 28. cannon of the councell of Calcedon, whereas some write there were 630. Bishops, <hi>cap.</hi> 36. ratifieth and enacteth the same. And if we go no further then to
<pb facs="28"/> the former fiue general councels, we shall finde them all to haue had a care by their decrees, to keepe the bishops of Rome within their due boūds of their owne patriarchall see. For proofe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, let any mā but read the sixt canon of the Nicene, the second &amp; third of the first of Constantinople, the eight of the Ephesine, remembring withal the twenty eight of the Calcedon, twise now immediatly before mentioned, &amp; vnderstand that the fift gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral councell solemnely confirmed those fowre former, and their canons &amp; decrees, and he cannot choose but see this to be most manifest. But amongst all the rest, notable is that that appeares to this end in that great solemne Africane councel, where <hi>Zozi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Boniface,</hi> &amp; <hi>Celestine,</hi> three popes on a rew, by their Legates vnder one of their hands alleadging a false canon of the councel of Nice, all that was determined in former councels to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary notwithstāding, shewed themselues intolerably ambitious of supremacy, thereby most egerly claiming such a preheminēce to be giuen to their see, that if any bishop or minister, were depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in any other prouince, or Patriarchal see, that vpō his appeale to Rome, the Bishop of Rome might accept thereof, &amp; therevpō either write his letters to the next prouince to determine the matter, or else to sende his Legate from his side to represent his own person, to sit in iudgement with the bishops there to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the matter. For there, as it appeares, in the 101 102 103 &amp; 105 <hi>chap.</hi> of that councell, in the first tome of the councels, this their allegation was not onely examined, by all the copies of the Nicene councell that they had there, but also by ancient copies thereof, which they sent for thither of purpose to Alexandria, Antioch, &amp; Constantinople, &amp; thereby in the open face of that councell, where 217 Bishops were assembled, their forgery was espied, &amp; therefore that allegation notwithstanding, the bishop of Romes dealing concerning <hi>Apiarius</hi> (who then gaue the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of that stur) was there openly disliked &amp; condemned, &amp; therefore to preuent the like thereafter, they in their 92 <hi>chapter</hi> there determine, that whosoeuer should so appeale any more frō the bishops, &amp; coūcels of Africke beyond the seas, should thēce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth neuer after of any in Africke be receaued into communiō. Besides, as it appears there in the 105. <hi>cap.</hi> by the common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of that councell, a letter was framed and sent to <hi>Celestine,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the latter end therof (as it should seeme by the stories about
<pb facs="29"/> the yeare foure hundred and thirty) wherein first they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monish him to admit no more such appeales, or fugitiues, but to send them backe againe alwaies to their owne prouinces and Metropolitans, and the rather, say they, because such order was taken by the Nicene councell. And after therein they pleade the equity of that ordinance, because the holy ghost is aswell in one prouince, as in an other, and there the cause is alwayes like best to bee handled, where it doeth arise, because of the neighnesse of the vvitnesses. Wherefore hauing tolde him, that they finde no such thing in the truer copies of the Nicene councell, as <hi>Faustinus</hi> sent by him alleadged, they flatly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid him the sending of his agents or legates any more, vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny such occasion amongst them. It shoulde seeme for all this, that so incident to that see, vvas this ambitious humor, that in pope <hi>Symachus</hi> time, about the yeare fiue hundred, many bishops euen in these parts, did accuse him to <hi>Theodoricus,</hi> king of the <hi>Gothes,</hi> because hee tooke vpon him to bee <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, that is, one vvho vvoulde haue his vvill to be a law, which is now professed, to bee the popes prerogatiue and not to bee controled. Dist. 40. <hi>Si papa.</hi> In <hi>Gregorie</hi> his time, in the raigne of <hi>Mauritius</hi> the Emperour, the bishop of Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople lustely chalenged the title of vniuersall bishop, but then <hi>Pelagius</hi> bishop of Rome in the yeare fiue hundred eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty three (as it appears in the ninty nine destinction of your law in <hi>Gratian</hi>) and Gregory also his successor condemned that, for an vnlawfull and Antichristian name in him, or in any other bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, the bishops of Rome themselues not excepted, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>epist.</hi> 32.38.39. And vvhereas (this notwithstanding) <hi>Boniface</hi> the next but one to <hi>Gregory</hi> (though with somewhat a doe) ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of that murderer and traitor <hi>Phocas,</hi> (who hauing cruelly slaine <hi>Mauritius,</hi> succeded him in the Empire) this Antichristian title first to be called vniuersal bishop, or head of the church, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse <hi>Sabellicus, Marianus Scotus, Martinus Polonus,</hi> and others, yet as <hi>Platina</hi> witnesseth in <hi>vita Doni,</hi> the church of Rauēna in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly complained thereof, and vntill pope <hi>Donus</hi> time (which vvas seuenty yeares after) it coulde not bee brought to to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerate and like of it. <hi>Otho Frisingensis lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Cap.</hi> 35. an ancient historiographer, speaking of <hi>Gregory</hi> the seuenth commonly called <hi>Hild ebrand,</hi> and his proceedings against the Emperour
<pb facs="29"/>
         <hi>Henry,</hi> not only to excommunicate him, but also to depose him, saith, <hi>Lego &amp; relego Romanorum regum &amp; Imperatorum gesta &amp;c.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> read and read againe the acts of the Romane kings and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and yet before this, I finde none of them of the Romane Bishop excommunicated, or depriued of his kingdome. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>f we read <hi>Sigebert, Abbas Ʋrspergensis, H. Mutius,</hi> and others, vve shall finde, that the same Bishop, for this his Antichristi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an pride, and other faultes that hee had, vvas not onely won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully vvithstoode and oppugned by that Emperour, but by councels also then held at <hi>Brixia, Mentz,</hi> and <hi>Wormes,</hi> sharpely rebuked, condemned, and desposed. And though hee hauing thus begunne to encroch vpon the Emperour, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his successours follovved him in his very steps, yet we read also in Cronicles that <hi>Henrie</hi> the fifte, <hi>Fredericke</hi> the first, and <hi>Fredericke</hi> the second Emperours, <hi>Philip</hi> the faire, and <hi>Carolus Caluus</hi> of Fraunce, <hi>Henry</hi> the first and second, <hi>Richard</hi> the second, and king <hi>Iohn</hi> of England, with sundry other Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and kings, did notably and openly resist them therein, and that they had alvvaies many learned fathers and Bishops to take their partes. But to leaue this matter, and to go on to others: because the author of this preface, and brag that I novv am in aunswering, in his brag maketh speciall menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as you haue heard of their order of ceremonies, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of praying, and fasting, bosting that for these, they haue the holy fathers, the consent of all christian nations, and prescription of long continuance, yea for the tvvo last the very scriptures: let vs first see if wee can finde out the originall, and vvithall the iust reproofe and condemnation of these. First for their ceremonies, none that hath but redde <hi>Platina,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther story of the liues of their popes, but he hath red when, how, and by whom they were deuised, for there is few of them, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred yeares together, that thought, as it should seeme by the vvriters of their liues, that they had worthily sate in that place, vnles they had deuised some newe rite and ceremony more then was before. But if one goe no further then to <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor de inventoribus rerum,</hi> there shall hee finde when, and by whom they had their originall, whereby also it shal appeare, that for many of thē they are of so late devising, they cannot pretend either the testimony of ancient fathers, or prescriptiō of any long
<pb facs="30"/> time, &amp; for very few of them, whatsoeuer he bragges, can they truly alleadge consent of all Christian regions, for as they haue most of them beene deuised here in these parts of the worlde by bishops of Rome, so few of them in comparison haue beene, or yet be receaued in the other parts of Christianity, that were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the other Patriarches of Constātinople, Alexandria, &amp; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch: yea euen here in these parts, all their rites &amp; ceremonies were neuer yet vniuersally receaued of euery cuntry alike, no nor yet of euery part of any one cuntry. But they being in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber so many, in nature a number of them so childish and foolish, &amp; yet hauing beene vrged as they haue, to be vsed with such o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion and holines, S. Pauls reprehension of those that were in his time so busy with the Colossians, in vrging thē to keepe their ordinances, the keeping whereof lay in, <hi>touch not, tast not, handle not, Coloss.</hi> 2. is both a bewraying, when such like ceremonies as these that he brags of first began, and also a iust and a full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of them. Read also <hi>S. Augustines</hi> 119 epistle <hi>ad Ianua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi> and you shall finde there, how earnestly he hath enueied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the multiplying, and bringing in, &amp; so vrging of such vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necessary rites and ceremonies: shewing how few the simplicity of the gospel is contented withal. And yet as it is wel known, he liued 1000 years ago, and that since his time there are 1000. new rites &amp; ceremonies deuised in the Romish church, that he neuer had heard of, &amp; yet thē he complained that there were so many, and they so seruilely were vrged, that the Iewes state was in that respect far more tolerable, what would he haue said then, if he had liued in these daies, and had seene the curious, infinite, and foolish rites and ceremonies, but of one popish priest formal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doing his masse?</p>
      <p>Indeed fasting is a thing, and so is prayer, that hath counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of scriptures, fathers, Christian regions, and of all ages and times, but so hath not either the popish fasting or praying. For their fasting is tyed superstitiously to set daies, and also lyeth es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in abstinence from one meat, rather then from an other, their end therein being not onely to chastise the body, that it may be brought the more readily &amp; feruently to obey the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly direction of the spirit, as the word of God teacheth onely it should, but euen thereby to satisfie, either for some sin past, or to earne or deserue somewhat at the hands of God. Such fasting
<pb facs="30"/> as this was that of the hypocritical pharisies, wherof Christ warn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> his disciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.16. &amp; the first fathers, &amp; teachers hereof, are those spirits of errour, that <hi>S. Paul</hi> speakes of 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. and so you may there see both, who first in the church of Christ, found out &amp; practised your kind of fasting, &amp; who by &amp; by spied it, &amp; condē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it for hypocritical, &amp; the doctrine of deuils. But if you would haue vs to search further, we tel you, that after Christ &amp; his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles times, <hi>Eusebius</hi> reports in his 5 booke &amp; 16 chapter out of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polonius,</hi> that <hi>Montanus</hi> the heretique, prescribed lawes of fasting, &amp; he is the first that we read of, that tyed fasting by law, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>script daies &amp; times, which is there reckoned vp by that <hi>Apolonius,</hi> as one of his heretical deuises. This <hi>Montanus</hi> was about the yeare of the Lord 145. And it appears in <hi>Augustines</hi> 2. booke &amp; 13. <hi>cha.</hi> of the manners of the church, &amp; of the <hi>Manichees,</hi> that it was the fashiō thē of those heretiques, to thinke vpon their fasting daies, that they fasted excellētly, though otherwise they had neuer so daintyre so they abstained from flesh &amp; wine, for the which <hi>Augustine</hi> doth deride thē. And cōsequently herein <hi>Apolonius</hi> &amp; <hi>Augustine,</hi> haue shewed their dislike of that popish fasting. If yet it should be replied, as it is, by some of their side, that their fasting is not altogither like the condemned abstinence of these anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent heretiques, &amp; others, for that they abstained frō flesh vpon an opinion, that flesh was an impurer creature then fish; how will they thē excuse <hi>Durand. li.</hi> 6. <hi>ca. de ieiunijs,</hi> who giueth this as a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of their abstinence vpon fasting daies, rather from flesh, then from fish, because al flesh was accursed in the daies of <hi>Noe</hi> &amp; not all fish?</p>
      <p>Now touching their māner of praying, for al his brag, neither fathers, consent of all Christian regions, prescription of any long continuāce of time, nor scriptures giue it any credit or coūtenāce at al. For first, whereas now they pray al in Latine, a toūg not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood of most that heare, &amp; vse their prayers, it is a kinde of praying flatly condemned, because it is without edification to such, by <hi>Chrysostome</hi> &amp; <hi>Ambrose,</hi> vpō the 14. of the first to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians. Augustine</hi> also <hi>de Genesi ad literā, li.</hi> 12. <hi>Cap.</hi> 8. ioines with them herein, aduouching that no mā is edified by hearing that, which he vnderstands not. And the descriptions of al the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent lyturgies in the Church shew, that alwaies they were vsed in such a tongue, as the people vnderstood aswell as the minister,
<pb facs="31"/> there is such mentiō of intercourse of speech one to the other, as any man may see, that perused the descriptions thereof: yea wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, both old &amp; new do plainely testify, that the ancient &amp; long cōtinued vse of the church hath bene, to haue her publicke litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy in the knowen &amp; vulgar tongue of the people. For <hi>Origē cōtra Celsū lib.</hi> 8. writeth, that the Grecians name God in greeke, &amp; the Romans in the latin tongue, and euery one in their natiue and mother tongue, pray &amp; sing Psalmes vnto God. And <hi>Hierom</hi> to <hi>Eustochium</hi> describing the solemne funeral of <hi>Pacta,</hi> &amp; elsewhere to <hi>Marcella,</hi> testifieth, that though to Bethleē there was cōcourse of very many seueral nations, yet euery one there praised god &amp; praied vnto him in their owne lāguage. Insomuch that euē <hi>Lyra</hi> vpō the 14 of the first to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> cōfesses, that in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue church, al was done in the vulgar tongue. And no lōger ago then <hi>Innocēt</hi> the thirds time, in the Laterā coūcel held in his time 1215. <hi>c.</hi> 9. order is takē, that where in one cuntrey there be people of diuers lāguages, there the Bishops should prouide them mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, to celebrate thē diuine seruice, &amp; to minister thē the sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, according to the diuersities of their rites &amp; lāguages. Yet further that thou maist see, Christian reader, in this point, that the mā blusheth at nothing, vnderstād, that by the cōfession of their own frend <hi>Eckius</hi> in his cōmō places, the South Indiās haue their liturgy in their mother tongue: &amp; by the cōfessiō of another, one <hi>Sigismūd</hi> writing of the <hi>Moscovites,</hi> that they likewise haue theirs. And <hi>Petrus Bellonius,</hi> writing of the <hi>Armonians,</hi> testifies the like of thē: yea <hi>Aeneas Siluius</hi> who after was a Pope, in his history of the <hi>Bohemiās c.</hi> 13. plainly shewes, that a Pope was admonished by a voice from heauen, to grāt <hi>Cyril,</hi> that conuerted <hi>Russia</hi> &amp; <hi>Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> to say diuine seruice amōgst thē in the <hi>Shlauon</hi> tongue which was their vulgar tongue. How haue they thē, as he bragges, these things considered, either the ancient holy fathers, consent of al regions, or such prescription of time, as he pretēds, for this maner of praying of theirs, in a tongue not vnderstoode of most? And who can read the 14 of the first to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> vnlesse he bee disposed wilfully to be blinde, but he must needes there see, that this maner of praying is directly there condemned? <hi>Chrysostome, Ambrose, Haymo, Lyra,</hi> and so expositours, both ancient and nevv, take it, howsoeuer our late <hi>Rhemists,</hi> in their notes, would faine vvrest the place from any such meaning. And in this
<pb facs="31"/> respect, suppose othervvise their prayers vvere faultles, who seeth not, that they giue God occasion againe to renue his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>olde complaint <hi>Esay.</hi> 29. <hi>This people drawe neare vnto mee with their lippes, but their hart is farre from mee:</hi> of most peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, vvhich through their tyranny onely pray thus. But in this poynt onely there is not vanity and falshoode in his bragge; for othervvise if vve consider vvell their maner of praying, vve shall finde both grosse vntrueth in his speech, and horrible faultes in their prayers. For how can it bee true, that consent of fathers, and the rest that he bragges of, doe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce that set forme of church-seruice, that now they are in possession of? seing neither the ancient fathers, nor yet one quarter of Christendome, vvas euer acquainted with it? There owne authours, and namely <hi>Polydor de inuentoribus rerum lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 10, doe shevv hovv it came in, and vvas de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uysed piece after piece. In the one thousand tvvo hundred yeares after Christ, it vvas not grovven eyther to that full forme or credit that it is at novv. For the forme of masse novv vsed, commonly called Saint <hi>Gregories</hi> masse, with much adoe got to be first in these westerne partes receiued in Pope <hi>Adrians</hi> time, 790 yeares after Christ, witnes <hi>Durand Nauclere,</hi> and <hi>Iaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus de voragine:</hi> and yet euen then, and long after, <hi>Millayn</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued the vse of a forme of liturgy receiued from <hi>Ambrose. Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict</hi> the 3, that succeeded next <hi>Ioan</hi> the harlot, about the yeare 857 first inuented &amp; brought in the dirge, as most authors write, though <hi>Gregory</hi> the 3 had done sōwhat about it before. The first allowance of the sequences in the masse is attributed to <hi>Nicolas</hi> the first, that succeeded this <hi>Benedict.</hi> In <hi>Alexander</hi> the 2 time, <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liluiah</hi> was first suspēded out of the church in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ēt time, which was aboue 1000 yeare after Christ. Our ordinary here in England, <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum vsum Sarum,</hi> began 1076 yeares after Christ, and that, as our stories shew, by occasion of a bloody quarel betwixt the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot of Glassenbury &amp; his monkes. The 7 canonical houres came in first by <hi>Vrban</hi> the second, in the yeare one thousand &amp; ninety. But <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth, that monstrous enemy of <hi>Fredericke</hi> the second, first brought in that blasphemous canticle <hi>Salue regina,</hi> one thousād two hūdred yeare &amp; more after Christ. And howso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer these patches, in the ende grevve in these partes to bee sovved togither, yet the other partes of the vvorld vnder the
<pb facs="32"/> other patriarches, were litle or not at all troubled with thē. And howsoeuer he shame not to aduouch, that now their manner of praying is according to the scriptures, <hi>Gregory. l.</hi> 7. <hi>Epist.</hi> 63. writes, that, <hi>Mos Apostolorū fuit,</hi> it was the maner of the Apostles, to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>secrate onely with the Lords praier, which simplicity, who so cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares, with their stagelike dealing thereabout now, he can neuer be persuaded, that two fashiōs so differing, should both haue coū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenāce of scriptures. But to make it yet more euident, that of al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things he might worst haue made this brag, of their manner of praying, there are two great &amp; notorious faults more therein: their praying for the dead to helpe thē out, or to ease thē in the paines of purgatory, &amp; their praying, as they do, to <hi>Saintes</hi> &amp; <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</hi> For in these two points, they are not onely destitute of the testimony of the holy aūcient fathers, consent of al Christian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, prescription of so long time as he makes shew of, and the scriptures, but rather al these are indeed herein against them. For purgatory it selfe, &amp; consequently praiers made to releeue soules there, is but a very late deuise, &amp; neuer yet receiued of halfe of Christendome. For in <hi>William Rufus</hi> time, king here of England, there being a councell held at <hi>Baron,</hi> there the Greek church, in this point plainly discented from the Latin, and neuer from that day to this, could be brought herein, to be of their minde, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by any mā may gather, that it is a point, which the Latine church hath deuised, since the greek church broke of cōmuniō frō her, &amp; that neuer yet, had either consent of al christian nations, or such prescriptiō of time, to coūtenāce it, as he talkes of. And as for the scriptures, let thē be perused thorow, &amp; there shal not be foūd in them that bee of the canon, either example of prayer, or sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the dead, yea rather plainely hee shal finde them, alwaies vrging the time of this present life, to bee the onely time, to doe good in, and to seeke the Lorde for our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort euer after. And as for the other point, concerning their prayers to <hi>Saints</hi> departed and <hi>Angels,</hi> it is such a thing, for the vvhich, in all the scripture they can finde neyther precept, promisse, nor example, to leade them to vse it, but to teach them to abhor it, there they shall, or at least may learne, that inuocation, is a speciall diuine poynt of seruice, of such spirituall and high nature, as that God challengeth it one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to himselfe, &amp; that therefore neuer any holy man, mentioned
<pb facs="32"/> in the scriptures durst euer vse it to any other. Indeede a man shall easily finde that ere <hi>Epiphanius</hi> time, Sathan had taught the heretiques called <hi>Caians,</hi> to worship Angels with inuocation of them, and that likewise ere his time in Africke there were, that offred to <hi>Mary</hi> the virgin, and that in inuocating her, and other saints were verie busy, &amp; pretended great piety &amp; deuotion; but withal he shal finde, that he bitterly condemnes al that did so for heretiques, vnder the name either of <hi>Caians, Antidicomarianites,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Collyridians, Heres.</hi> 38, 78. &amp;c. &amp; that in as bitter manner as may be, vsing the same speeches &amp; reasons against them, that we doe now vsually in these daies against these. Now where, they would shift of the absurdity, &amp; blasphemy of robbing God, &amp; his sonne Christ, of their due honour herein, in saying first, that their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the souls of <hi>Saints</hi> departed, may aswel stād with their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as the requiring of our brethren aliue to pray for vs, &amp; then in affirming, that they begge nothing at their hands, but stil they conclude their praiers vnto them, with this clause, by the merites of our Lord Iesus Christ, they cannot so escape or excuse them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues. For neither doe they only desire the <hi>Saints</hi> departed, to pray to God for them, as we doe our brethren here whiles they liue, neither do they alwaies remember so to conclude their prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers vnto them. For in their office, which they call the seruice of the blessed <hi>Marie,</hi> there bee three prayers made vnto her, wherein, no lesse then eternall life is begged directly at her hands, &amp; yet there this clause is quite forgottē. The like may be obserued, in many other praiers of theirs to them, as for example, in their praier to <hi>S. Osmund</hi> confessor, in one to <hi>S. Anne,</hi> and in an other to <hi>S. Katherin.</hi> And if it were so, that they so shut vp al their praiers vnto them, what were that else, then to make Christ me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator betwixt vs &amp; them? For can we in any words, more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledge Christs effectual mediation betwixt vs and his father, then by requiring all things that wee begge of his father <hi>per dominnm nostrum Iesum Christum,</hi> by our Lorde Iesus Christ? Then what is this else, but for their pleasures to put him from his old office, of being mediator betwixt God and man, to make him nowe mediatour betwixt men and wemen aliue, and the souls of other men &amp; wemen dead? They say in their maner of praying, they neuer cause the <hi>Saints</hi> any more to incroch of his office of mediation, then wee doe when wee desire one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="33"/> being aliue, to pray to god for vs, what say they then to that prayer of theirs in the name of <hi>Thomas Becket: Tu per Thomae san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinē, quē pro te effudit, fac nos, Christe, scandere quò Thomas ascendit.</hi> That is, O thou Christ, by the bloode of <hi>Thomas,</hi> which for thee hee shed, make vs ascend thither, whither <hi>Thomas</hi> is gone. They knowe this is, or was, in their portuisse. But if this be not plaine i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, both to make it appeare that they pray otherwise to the Saints departed, then we doe to thē aliue: &amp; that in their praying to thē, most blasphemously contrary to all holy ancient fathers iudgement, consent of al Christian nations, prescriptiō of al ages, and the holy scriptures themselues, marke (Christian Reader) these further presidents. In the masse of the annuntiation they sing thus to <hi>Mary, Salue virgo virginum, mediatrix hominum,</hi> all haile virgin of virgins, the mediatrix of men: and in the masse of the conception thus, <hi>Tu spes certamiserorum, verè mater orphanorum, tu lenamen oppressorum, medicamen infirmorum, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus es omnia.</hi> That is (speaking to the same <hi>Mary</hi>) Thou art the certaine hope of the miserable, truely the mother of orphans, the helpe of the oppressed, the medicine for the sicke, to all thou art all things. Infinite such examples there be, whereby it is most cleare, that nothing can bee begged of God himselfe which they beg not of the saints, &amp; that no title cā be giuē to god but they haue giuē it to one Saint or other. Besids al this, we must cōsider that the children of God being aliue are commanded to pray one for another, &amp; that by speech, letter, or messenger, they know how to acquaint one another with their minde: whereas in praying to their soules after their death, we haue neither com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mādemēt so to doe, neither can we indeede persuade our selues, that whatsoeuer we say vnto thē, they heare and see our minds, vnles we thinke now after once they be in heauen, they are inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted in the very nature of God himselfe, &amp; so are become aswell as he, searchers &amp; scers of the harts &amp; raines: which once to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine because it is extreame blasphemy, therefore their is infinite difference, euen for these reasons betwixt desiring a Christian brother aliue to pray for vs, &amp; the desiring of his soule departed but once to doe so much for vs. Againe if that were but all they doe in praying to the Saints departed, then howsoeuer (because of our frailty that sticketh by vs whiles we liue) it were necessary one of vs to require that at the hands of another, that so the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="33"/> vve may performe the duety one to another, yet their is not the like reason, why we should so cal vpon them that are depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, though they could heare vs, for they being where they haue laide aside all frailty and forgetfulnesse of their dueties: it being supposed to be their dueties to pray for their brethren &amp; sisters in Christ aliue, we may be sure they will do it without our remē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring of them thus. But now no more of these two points here, for <hi>ca.</hi> thirty seuen, I haue spokē againe somewhat largely there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, where I haue shewed both when and how these corruptions came in, and who resisted them also.</p>
      <p>Wherefore to goe on with cōfutation of the obiectiō which I haue vndertaken to answere, concerning that point, when and by vvhom the Romish religion came in, and vvho spyed it and confuted it: besides the pointes already touched, amongst many other wherein we differ from them, these are three principall, for the which I account both them &amp; their religion Antichristi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, their doctrine of trāsubstantiation, of images, and vowed sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle life, and yet in these they bragge of fathers, consent of Christian regions, and prescription of time, as in the former. To aunswere therefore both that demaunde concerning these pointes, also and to strip them withall of that visard of antiquity and vniuersallity, that herein along time they haue deceiued the simple people vvithall, vnderstande, welbeloued in the Lord vvhosoeuer thou art, first for transubstantiation, the very archpiller of their Synagoge, that if they bee very busie to seeke out who first gaue inkling of such a matter, they shall finde indeede the originall thereof not to come from <hi>Marke</hi> the Euangelist, or anie of his fellowshippe, but from one <hi>Marke</hi> a notable Magitian, and filthie heretique of the broode of <hi>Ʋalentinian,</hi> that liued, as it seemeth by the stories, in the raigne of <hi>Antoninus Pius,</hi> about one hundred and fifteene yeares after Christ. For <hi>Epiphanius</hi> in his thirty foure heresie noteth, and when hee hath done plentifully confirmeth, it out of the first booke of <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and his ninth chapter against the heresies of <hi>Valētiniā</hi> &amp; others, that this same heretique by his enchātmēt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uīg first caused a cup of white wine to beare the colour of blood, made his followers beleeue that by his inuocation over it, it was so trāsubstantiated into blood, that seing that he had givē thāks ouer it &amp; long praied, it might be thought of them that <hi>gratiā quae
<pb facs="34"/> est super vniuersa, sanguinem suum instillâsse in illud poculum,</hi> that is, that grace that is aboue all things, had poured his bloud into that cup, by which meanes, whē he had made them in admiration of him, desirous to drink thereof, he giues it them with great deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; solemnity of words, &amp; so wonderfully bewitched many. Indeed this fellow may very wel be allowed, for the first aūcient foūder of this point of doctrin, for there being not any one point of popery, wherein Antichrist, hath more manifestly shewed him selfe cōtrary to Christ, then in this, as in truth there is not, because for the establishing &amp; vse of this, he is both spoiled of the true nature of a mā, &amp; office of the only sufficiēt priest of the new te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament, to offer himselfe once for all for the redemption of his church, who can be fitter then this auncient enchaūter <hi>Marcus,</hi> to be the first author and patrone hereof? especially seing <hi>Irenae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> speaking of him in the eight chapter of the foresaid booke (as it should seeme, secretly directed by the spirit of prophesy) saith, thas he was <hi>verè praecursor Antichristi,</hi> that is, truely Antichrists fore-runner. Yet how notably soeuer this <hi>Marcus</hi> caused ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny simple persons in his time, to beleeue his transubstātiation of wine, into the bloud of Grace, yet he was so baited, detected, &amp; confounded for his lewd and cosening dealing therein, and in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther points by <hi>Irenaeus, Epiphanius,</hi> and others, that howsoeuer in the meane time, Antichrist his successour, was busie vnder <hi>Leo</hi> the 9. in a councell at <hi>Vercellis,</hi> and after in the councell of <hi>Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran</hi> vnder <hi>Nicholas</hi> the 2. about the yeare of the lord 1060. in bringing <hi>Berengarius</hi> to recantatiō, to reuiue againe this doctrine of transubstantiation, yet as their own friends confesse, &amp; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Tonstall</hi> in his booke of the sacrament of Christs body and bloud, it could not, nor was not, decreed for a certaine and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall doctrine, before <hi>Innocent</hi> the thirds time, in another coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell at <hi>Lateran,</hi> about the yeare of Christ 1215. before which coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, the Greeke Church had separated themselues from the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, and therefore it being a point of Doctrine, not receaued as Catholike, before that diuision, neuer since could it be receaued in the Greeke Church for any Catholike truth. How can it then haue countenance of all Christian Regions and times? <hi>Bertram, Berengarius</hi> &amp; the <hi>Waldenses,</hi> in sundry places by writing &amp; spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, opposed themselues against it, as witnesseth <hi>Bertrams</hi> book of the sacramēt, the condemnation of <hi>Berengarius</hi> opinion about
<pb facs="34"/> it at <hi>Vercellis,</hi> and the articles of the <hi>Waldenses.</hi> Yea a little before, and in this Pope <hi>Innocents</hi> time, a certaine people about <hi>Iohn de Albines Tolossa</hi> called <hi>Albigenses,</hi> and that in great &amp; mighty mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes (as the French Cronicles shew) denied reall presence of Christ vnder, or with the outward elements in this sacrament, in somuch, as great warres were raised to subdue them. But of this matter also I haue spoken so much chapter eleuenth &amp; 17. that here I neede thereof say no more.</p>
      <p>Now touching Images or Idols, and the worshipping thereof: I must needes confesse that for their dealing about them, they may very well pretend both antiquity and vniuersality. For it appeares in all stories, and in the scriptures themselues, that that way, not onely all other nations, but also euen the people of the Iewes themselues, haue beene alwaies wonderfully giuen to pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and defile themselues, but withall it appeares, that god in his word writtē, against no abhominatiō hath cried out, either more often, or more vehemently, then against this. But amongst Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, the first that we reade of, that worshipped the image of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus,</hi> or any other, was <hi>Marcellina</hi> a filthy companion of the phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tasticall heretique <hi>Carpocrates,</hi> but both in <hi>Epiphanius heresi</hi> 27. and in <hi>Augustine ad Quod vult deum,</hi> we finde this, both noted &amp; condemned amongst other detestable errours of the <hi>Carpocrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> This <hi>Carpocrates</hi> liued in the beginning of the empire of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toninus Pius, Anicet</hi> then being Bishoppe of Rome, about the yeare of the lord 109. And in <hi>Origens</hi> time who died, as <hi>Spanhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mensis</hi> saith, in the yeare of Christ 261. hee in his seuenth book to <hi>Celsus</hi> noteth that then the Christians neither suffered images nor pillers to be worshipped. Likewise in <hi>Arnobius, aduersus gentes,</hi> who florished about the 300. yeare after Christ, it appeares, that the gētils obiected that, as a matter of disgrace, against the Christi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ās, that they neither had, nor worshipped any such. But so far of was it, that the christiās thē thought it any disgrace vnto thē, that <hi>Origē</hi> in the place before quoted saith, that the Iewes &amp; Christiās hearing the law <hi>Exo.</hi> 20. not only refuse images of god, choosing rather to die, then to make or worship any such, adding this as a reasō, that god is inuisible &amp; without body. And likewise <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> (who florished 100. yeares before <hi>Origen</hi>) in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to the heathen, confesses willingly this their obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be true, that Christians had no images that might be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned
<pb facs="35"/> by sence, but onely by vnderstanding, because to vse that deceitfull art, saieth he, was forbid thē. Yea and that Christians and their tēples might continue still free frō them in <hi>Constantines</hi> time, in a councel held in Spaine at <hi>Eliberis, can</hi> 36. it was decreed thus, It hath pleased vs to determine that no pictures should be suffered in churches, least that which is worshipped or adored should be painted in walles. <hi>Isid. tom.</hi> 1. <hi>cōci.</hi> And therfore <hi>Epiphani{us}</hi> 55. yeares after this councell, about the yeare of Christ 390. as it appeares in his Epistle to <hi>Iohn</hi> of Ierusalē, finding in the entrance of the church at Anablatha in that <hi>Iohns</hi> dioces, the image of a mā pictured on a cloth there hāging, puld it downe &amp; tare it asūder, &amp; writing to the foresaid <hi>Iohn</hi> about it (though as he confessed it seemed vnto him that it was made for the picture of <hi>Iesus</hi> or sōe of the Saints) yet he cōdemneth it as contrary both to the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Christian Religion, &amp; therefore perswades him not to suffer any such thing any more, for it became him to banish such superstition which was vnseemely for the Church of Christ. Yea <hi>Lactantius lib.</hi> 2 <hi>cap.</hi> 19. of his diuine institutions saieth flatly, that their can be no Religion where there is an image, he liued &amp; flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished in the yeare 320. And S <hi>Augustine</hi> who liued after al these before named, for he died not before the yeare 430. <hi>de consensu Euangelistarum lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap</hi> 2. writeth that they euen deserue to erre which seeke Christ and his Apostles, not in bookes, but in pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wals. Yea <hi>Gregory</hi> the great (as they cal him) Bishop of Rome (though thē the painting of stories for an ornamēt of the church was thought tolerable) yet he, <hi>lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Epist.</hi> 109. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 9. <hi>Epist.</hi> 9. to <hi>Serenus,</hi> slatly cōdemneth the adoring &amp; worshipping of images. And whereas by occasiō of this tolerating of historicall painting of them, through the superstition &amp; corruption of mans nature, within short time by litle &amp; litle the worshipping of thē grew to be too much vsed &amp; liked of many, especially in these Westerne parts &amp; of the Bishops of Rome thēselues: by the yeare of Christ 700. the Emperour <hi>Leo</hi> the third in a coūcell held at Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople consisting of 330. Bishops, there with the consent of that coūcell decreed, that they should be quite remoued out of chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches &amp; burnt, &amp; seuerely he punishes those which notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding would perseuere in the worshipping of them. And the same course tooke his successour <hi>Constantine</hi> by another great coūcell held their ratifying the former, &amp; two Emperours more succee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him, notwithstāding al this while the Bishops of Rome with stood thē what they might &amp; decreed as fast for the retaining &amp;
<pb facs="35"/> worshipping of thē as they could, as it appeares in <hi>Sigebert, Blōdus</hi> &amp; others. Howbeit though also in the time of <hi>Irene</hi> &amp; the nonage of her sonne <hi>Constātine</hi> in the east, through the suggestiō of <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rasius</hi> Bishop of Constantinople, they got there a councell helde at Nicea consisting of three hūdreth &amp; fifty Bishops, where to currie fauour againe with the Bishops of Rome (who vpō the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer occasiō, as it appears in <hi>Sigebert</hi> &amp; others, had bene a shrewd traiterous meanes to cause these westerne parts to reuolt frō the empire) they decreed according to their humour for the honour of images. Yet Africk &amp; Asia the greater, could neuer be brought to receiue those canōs there made, yea &amp; that more is, though by that time the Pope had made <hi>Charles</hi> the great very much behol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to him in being the means to trāslate the empire of the west vnto him, so were those canōs in this point misliked &amp; cōtradicted here in thes western parts, that a coūcel in his time &amp; by his meās, as the Emperour being called at Francford, whereunto came many Bishops of Italy, Frāce, Germāy &amp; other cūtries, yet there euē for this point was that coūcel of Nice reiected &amp; cōdēned as a wicked councell, witnes both <hi>Regino lib.</hi> 2. <hi>anno</hi> 794. &amp; also one <hi>Hinckmare</hi> not lōg after those times Archbishop of Rhemes wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting against another of his name thē Bishop of Iandune or Laue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dune as some cal it, <hi>ca.</hi> 20. where he for further proofe of this to be true writeth that the Bishops their assembled caused a booke of purpose to be writen &amp; sent to Rome, cōteining at large a cōfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiō of al the reasons vsed for images at Nicea, which in his yoūg yeares he saw, &amp; which the keeper of the Popes library <hi>Augustine Steuchus</hi> cōfesses to lie there writē in anciēt caracters <hi>de donatione Constantini lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 59. <hi>nu.</hi> 60. And <hi>Roger Houodē</hi> (who liued 400. years ago) in his cōtinuatiō of Bedeas story in the year 792. shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how <hi>Charles</hi> sēt the canōs of that coūcel of Nice hither, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in (as he saith) it was decreed that images ought to bee adored, which the church of God vtterly detesteth, reports that one <hi>Albi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rus</hi> here wrote an epistle against that determinatiō, maruelously grounded vpō the scriptures, which he caried into France (as he saith) in the name of our Bishops, by occasion whereof, the rather it should seeme, shortly after <hi>Charles</hi> thought meete to call the foresaid coūcell at Francford. All these things notwithstanding, neuer were images, pillers and crosses more idolatrously decreed to be worshipped their, nor euer were idols more grosly adored of heretiques, or the very pagans and heathen, then they haue bene &amp; yet be of superstitious Papists. For they crouch &amp; kneele
<pb facs="36"/> vnto them, present offerings before them, they run a pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage vnto them, and teach that they are to be worshipped with that honour, that is due vnto them, whose images and monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they be, though in an other manner, not for their owne sakes, but for theirs whose remembrances they be. But indeed if in worshipping of them, they did not principally respect the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages themselues, why should there not be as great deuotion, as many pilgrimages, &amp; as great offerings, presented &amp; yeelded to the image of Christ, <hi>Mary,</hi> or of any other: aswell in one place as in an other? Well, howsoeuer they will do wickedly herein, and when they haue done, seeke to colour the matter, such in truth all the worlde sees, herein hath beene their dealing, that <hi>Euthymius</hi> in his panoply had neuer more cause to name the <hi>Armenians,</hi>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, that is, Idolaters to the crosse, for their grosse and superstitious worshipping of it, then we haue generally to count, and call, the Romanists flat idolaters for their behauiour towards it, and other images also. Thus then hoping by this, that I haue said, cōcerning this point, that not onely thou maiest see (goodreader) when, and how, this point of popery first came in, but how, and by whom, it hath beene oppugned, but consequently also, that the Romish church is herein destitute both of scripture, fathers, consent of Christian regions, and al that she bragges of, let vs see if wee can shew the like, concerning the other point of forced single life vpō the clergy, which she holds to be so necessary, and holy an ordinance, as that by no meanes without deadly sin it may be transgressed.</p>
      <p>Euen in this, as in the former, if we search the monumentes of antiquity well, we shal finde that they haue very auncient here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, to be their first fathers &amp; leaders. For the <hi>Tacianists</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly cald <hi>Encratites</hi> of their abstinence from mariage, &amp; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine other thinges, who began about the yeare, one hundred forty two, were great condemners of mariage, as appeares in <hi>Aug. ad Quodvult Deum,</hi> &amp; in <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> writing of them, <hi>Heresi.</hi> 46. After them spronge vp the <hi>Manichees,</hi> who in like manner were enemies to mariage, but not so vniuersally as the former, for they permitted it to others, and restraine onely their clergy from it, whō they calde their elect, as <hi>August:</hi> witnesseth of them <hi>Epist.</hi> 74. but indeed as many as would be perfect, &amp; had in anie great reckoning amongst them, they were in any case to abstaine from
<pb facs="36"/> mariage. And as we finde, that these and other heretiques, were the fore-runners of the Papists in this point, so we finde that <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine, Epiphanius,</hi> and others, that wrote against them, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this for a doctrine of deuils in them. But I know they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, that herein we do them wrong in that we resemble them to these, for these, they say, made this the reason and groūd of their doing, that they held mariage it selfe, to be an vncleane and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy estate of life, and therefore not fit for them, that would serue the Lord, to liue in. Which, they say, they doe not hold. Indeed, thus it is their fashion, when for any of their absurd errours, they are pressed with our obiections against them, then somewhat to avoide the extremity of the foile, to set a farre better state of the questiō, then otherwise, either their commō practise or doctrine will beare: but when they finde the chase ended, and themselues by such shifting in some sort, as they think, to haue escaped, then hauing recouered their breath againe, they fall to their olde flat grosnes in the point in their life and teaching. And euen so deale they in this. For their whole and generall practise, makes it most euident, in that they rather tolerate their Priests to haue concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines, to run to the stues, yea and to commit Sodomitry, then to mary, that indeed they think mariage is more vncleane, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>files their Priesthoode more then all these. And Dist. 82. <hi>Gratian</hi> cites a saying of Pope <hi>Siritius,</hi> wherein, in plainer termes he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouches them that holdes, that ministers of the Gospell may ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and beget children as the Priests of the olde testament did, to be followers of lusts, and therein teachers of vice. Frō which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foūd diuinity it came, that the same <hi>Siritius</hi> would persuade, that therefore the ministers of the Gospell might not mary, because Saint <hi>Paul</hi> said, they that liue in the flesh cannot please god, as though to liue in the fleshe with <hi>Paul,</hi> and to liue in the state of mariage were all one: which if it had beene so, what meant S. <hi>Paul</hi> to teach 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. that he that bestowed his daughter in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage did well, that mariage is honourable <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. and that they that deny in hypocrisy, the lawfulnes thereof, are such, as haue therein giuen eare vnto doctrines of deuils, and thereby shewe, that their consciences are burnt, as it were, with an hote iron, and that they are departed from the faith 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. But they will say perhaps, they are now ashamed of this olde <hi>Siritius,</hi> &amp; of his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in this point. Doubtles if they be not, there is iust cause
<pb facs="37"/> why they should, but I haue two reasons why I thinke they are not: first, because he was Pope of Rome they know; then, because even of late one <hi>Gregory Martin,</hi> a great learned man (as they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count him) writing against our English translations <hi>Chap.</hi> 15. <hi>sect.</hi> 2. writeth of this point euen now (as though that Popes spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit still directed him) flatly, that by mariage their Priesthoode is prophaned, and made meere laicall and popular. Wherefore I see not, but that they are and may worthily still of vs herein be saied to be, the right schollers &amp; successours of the former here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques. Howbeit this I must needes further graunt them, that in perusing the writings of ancient fathers and Cronicles of times, I find euē amongst them, that otherwise yet seemed to be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians and not heretiques, and that of very ancient time, and so from time to time, that haue beene fauorers and vrgers of single life in ministers. For I finde by that that <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> hath writen of this matter in the 3. &amp; 7. booke. <hi>Stromat,</hi> who flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished within 200. yeares after <hi>Christ,</hi> that thē some earnestly vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged single life, as a life most holy &amp; fit for such. And I know that in the councell of Nice, in <hi>Constantines</hi> time, it was attēpted, that there should bee made a canon, to binde ministers vniuersally to liue single, without the vse or company of wiues: &amp; that after that <hi>Siritius</hi> before spoken of, about the yeare 390. after him <hi>Gregorie</hi> the first <hi>ann.</hi> 600. or thereabout, &amp; after that sundry other Popes, namely &amp; especially about 1000. years after Christ, &amp; after; were marueilous eger and busy, by their owne authority &amp; decrees of councels summoned by their meanes, to establish &amp; ratify this point. Whereupon (as in other cuntreies of these westerne parts, to please them withal) herein England many Bishops, as namely <hi>Lancfranke, Dūstane</hi> &amp; <hi>Anselme,</hi> Archbishops of Cāterbury, were marueilous forward in their times to further this deuice. By meās whereof, many decrees past in smodes and councels, and many great things were attēpted &amp; done to this end. But yet then vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand withall (welbeloued) that <hi>Clemens</hi> in the places before quoted, confuted &amp; withstoode notably these hypocrits, both by exāples &amp; reasons euē now vsed by vs against these their succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors: that one <hi>Paphnutius</hi> in the coūcell of Nice though vnmaried himselfe, did so effectually withstand that attēpt, that it did not there passe: that <hi>Siritius</hi> was by a Bishop of <hi>Terragon</hi> confuted &amp; withstood: &amp; that <hi>Gregory</hi> the first vpon the finding of 600. chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens heads, after the casting of certaine great ponds neare vnto
<pb facs="37"/> the aboad of many, inforced to that vow of single life, reuoked his determinatiō (as it appeareth in an epistle of one <hi>Hulricke,</hi> Bishop of Augusta, to Pope <hi>Nicolas</hi>) vpō this reasō, that it was better to let thē marry, thē to giue occasion of such murder. Further in <hi>Hilde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands</hi> time, who after he was Pope was called <hi>Gregory</hi> the seuēth, though we find that he of al that wēt before him, was herein most extreame and went furthest, yet notwithstāding we read in <hi>Sige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert, H. Muti{us}</hi> &amp; others, that he and his decrees in this point were openly &amp; stoutly resisted, not onely at <hi>Constāce</hi> &amp; <hi>Mentz</hi> in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, but also by the Bishops of France, and other cuntreies both by open preaching &amp; liuing with their wiues, doe what he could, and his successors for a great space. Hee was the first that bound Bishops &amp; Archbishops vpon their oath to admit none into the ministry, vnlesse first they would vow a single life: &amp; yet after he had done what he could, &amp; <hi>Pascalis</hi> that succeeded him, &amp; <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selme</hi> also their chaplein here, to cause that decree to take place: yet, as our Cronicles shew, <hi>Gerhardus</hi> Archbishop of Yorke, wrote to that <hi>Anselme,</hi> that those that came for orders to him would not vow single life. And howsoeuer they preuailed in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces before, <hi>Polidor</hi> saith, that the restraint of their mariages began here first to be attēpted <hi>ann.</hi> 670. <hi>hist. Ang. l.</hi> 6. <hi>&amp; de inuētorib{us} rerū l.</hi> 5. &amp; <hi>Fabiā p.</hi> 293. writeth, that Bishops &amp; Priests liued here 1000 years together with their wiues, no law being to the cōtrary. Yea <hi>Auētinus l</hi> 5. <hi>historiae Biorū</hi> saith, speaking of <hi>Hildebrāds</hi> time which was 40. years at least after this, that Priests had wiues &amp; begat chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drē as other men. And none of any learning are ignorant, that al these sturs about this matter notwitstanding, Christiā Bishops &amp; ministers in al other quarters of the world, vnder the other Patri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>arches frō the beginning vnto this day, haue bene, are maried &amp; beget childrē also, after they are entred into the ministry. This al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>so is as wel knowen of the learned, that not onely particular lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, &amp; holy fathers, as I noted before, &amp; others: but also sū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry coūcels, where multitudes of such fathers haue met, haue wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten &amp; decreed to withstād &amp; contrary the going forward of this Antichristiā ordināce. Yea they thēselues are not ignorāt hereof, as it appears by sundry things set downe both in their text and glosse <hi>dist.</hi> 81.84. &amp; elswhere in their Canon law. For in the 28. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctiō, is noted a decree of the councell of <hi>Gangra,</hi> which was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 300. yeares after Christ, whereby he is by the authority of that councell anathematized, that shall for his mariage put
<pb facs="38"/> difference betwixt a maried ministers ministry, and another, and therefore abstaine from communicating with him, and there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so is cited a canon fathered of the Apostles, whereby he is accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, that puts away his wife for Religion sake. And in the sixth generall councell held at Constantinople, these thinges are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred with other, and therefore there it was decreed, <hi>Tom. Conc.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. that he shall be deposed, that after that, should go about to debar Priests, or deacons, either of mariage, or of the vse of their wiues, yea after ordination: and there also, further it was enacted, that if they themselues being ordred, should vnder pretence of piety put away their wiues, that they shall therefore be excommunicate, and yet this was 680. yeares after Christ. Moreouer <hi>Hierom</hi> speaking of his time, saith, that then, <hi>plurum sacerdotes habebant matrimonia,</hi> that is, most Priestes were maried, <hi>aduersus Iouinianum, libro.</hi> 1. <hi>Tertullian</hi> himselfe was a maried man, as it appeareth by his writing to his wife. To holde that mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters may not mary, <hi>Ignatius ad Philadelphenses</hi> saith, comes of the deuill: And <hi>Dionysius Corinthiacus</hi> writing to the <hi>Gnosians</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suades their Bishop <hi>Pinitus,</hi> not to impose an vnnecessary, &amp; too heauy a burden of single life, or chastity vpon the brethren, as we reade in <hi>Euseb. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 22. Lastly, S. <hi>Bernard</hi> (though he liued about the yeare 1120. which was a very corrupt time for this matter,) yet euen he, in his sixty sixth sermon vppon the Canti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, thus far concerning this point hath plainely written. Take from the church honourable matrimonie, &amp; the bed vndefiled, saith he, and thou fillest it with concubine keepers, with incestu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous persons, with such as haue vncleane issues of seede flowing from them, with wantons, with Sodomites, and all kind of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane persons. But when the bright euidence of these allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, seeme to make them somewhat to bold downe their heads, yet I know they haue this shift for their last refuge, that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny not, but that such as haue been maried, or at that presēt, haue wiues, may enter into the ministry, but thē they must be such, as voluntary will vow, and performe a single life, and so thence forth abstaine: insomuch that they are so in loue with this shift, that they say, &amp; write, as is to be seen in the Rhemish notes vpō the new testamēt, that <hi>Pauls</hi> canons, touching the being of such the husbāds of one wife, are so to be vnderstood, &amp; not so, as that thē, or after once he is minister, he may continue the office of a
<pb facs="38"/> husband towardes his wife, and confidently they dare and doe brag, that we neuer read of any other that maried, or got children after they entred once into holy orders. Wherin first the practise of the Greeke Church, &amp; all other Churches, but these in these parts of the world, directly crosses them. Againe let <hi>Pauls</hi> words in deliuering of his canons cōcerning the qualities that ministers ought to haue, bee well considered, and any man shall see, that it is absurd so to vnderstād him, that he requires that they should be so qualified only <hi>de praeterito</hi> for the time past, &amp; not rather es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially for the time present and to come. Seeing they are so cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident in this, that none maried euer, or begot children after they were ministers, let them tell mee of whom Peter had his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Petronella,</hi> of whō their owne Croniclcs speake so much, had he her not of a lawful wife? And if it be true, that we read, that in the persecutiō vnder <hi>Domitian,</hi> she was of such florishing yeares, that then <hi>Flaccus,</hi> a noble Roman county would haue had her to wife, the time betwixt that and <hi>Peters</hi> entring vpon his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stleship, being at the least, fifty fiue yeares after Christ, by all likelihoode shee was got after hee was an Apostle. And well might it bee, for it being euident, that Christ had taught them, that vnlesse it were for fornication no man should forsake his wife <hi>Math.</hi> 19. and therefore that <hi>Paul</hi> hath noted, that the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of the Lord and <hi>Cephas,</hi> did cary vp and downe in the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of their Apostleshippes their wiues, being also conuerted aswell as themselues, and therefore sisters 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. taking mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for themselues &amp; then as they went, that sometime in that perigrinatiō of theirs, in the discharge of their office, this <hi>Petronel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> was borne. For it being euidēt by the Gospell of <hi>Math.</hi> 8. that <hi>Peter</hi> had a wife, and by their owne stories, that shee was a liue a little before his death, &amp; at Rome with him, &amp; that he counted not his Apostleship fornicatiō, &amp; that neither he would leaue his wiues cōpany &amp; take other women with him, nor that she came to Rome rather in the cōpany of other men, thē of him her owne husband: too too grosse and absurd is it with them to thinke, that he &amp; the rest of the Apostles that had wiues, forsooke their wiues quite and went vp and downe rather after the popish maner ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with other women. Their translating and peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the order of <hi>Paules</hi> words, a woman, a sister, will not defend their interpretation, for he placeth his wordes thus, a sister,
<pb facs="39"/> a wife, where in the later place it is absurd, the Greek word being that which sometime standeth generally for a woman, sometime for such a woman as is also a wife; to take it in the former sence, for then therein there were a needlesse tautology, for there is no sister, but shee is a woman also. But to leaue <hi>Peter</hi> with his wife and daughter, what can they say to <hi>Socrates,</hi> who in his fift booke and twentieth one Chapter of his story, writeth that <hi>omnes praesbyteri illustres,</hi> that is, all renouned ministers in the East and Bishops also, if they will, no law compelling them, may obstaine from their wiues, for not a fewe of them, whiles they are Bishops, beget childrē of their lawfull wiues. <hi>Historiae tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partitae lib.</hi> 9. <hi>ca.</hi> 38. Againe the 10. canon of the <hi>Ancyran</hi> councell testifieth of many authēticall exāples of such as maried after ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly orders. Moreouer in the daies of <hi>Iulian</hi> the apostata wee reade, that <hi>Basilius</hi> a Priest of <hi>Ancyra</hi> and <hi>Eusichius</hi> a minister at the least of Cesarea of Cappadocia, which had lately taken to wife a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman, and was but then as a bridegrome, both ended their liues in martirdome, as writeth <hi>Zozomene lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. and <hi>Balfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> long after, vpon the 10. canon of the coūcell of <hi>Ancyra,</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth a decree of <hi>Leo</hi> the Emperour, whereby it was lawfull for thē within two yeares after they were ordered to mary. And who can be perswaded, that we reading of so many famous Bishoppes that were maried, as namely of <hi>Demetrianus</hi> of Antioch, of <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dion</hi> in the councell of Nice, &amp; of <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> &amp; others, and of infinite children of these Bishops &amp; of others of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry, as we doe in all stories: that they got none of these children after their ministry, or that they left their wiues presently vpon their entring into their ministry, especially seeing the stories that tels vs they were maried &amp; names vs their childrē, mētioneth no such thing? Howsoeuer it were with these, it euidētly appeares in his 70. and 127. epistles, that there was one <hi>Synesius</hi> an excellent learned mā, Bishop of Ptolemais who was not only a maried mā, and had children, but that he begot children of his lawfull wife, being and continuing still in the execution of his office. And many more such examples might be remembred, but these are sufficient to shew the impudency of their confident assertiō, that there were neuer anie such: and this which I haue faied, I hope, also is fully sufficiēt to shew not onely the vanity of his brag that made this preface, that all is well with them and countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb facs="39"/> by fathers, consent of regions &amp;c. but also to answere the demuande or obiection which I tooke vpon mee, vpon that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion, to answere in this place, concerning the beginning and proceeding of popery, and how and by whom it was resisted. For euen, as I haue shewed, they lacke all the countinance they brag of, for those particular points that I haue here spoken of, &amp; haue made it plaine, that both their beginning and proceeding hath beene noted and withstoode: euē so is it an easy matter to deale with them, in all the rest of the points wherein they and wee differ, as ere thou hast redde this my answere to <hi>Albine</hi> thorow, I hope, I shall make vnto thee full demonstration. Wherefore thou maiest in the meane time hereby learne, to arme thy selfe against such proud brags, as notwithstanding thou hast hard the authour of this preface make. For I hope euen by this, whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he hath saied to the contrary, thou most plainely seest, that neither scripture, fathers, consent of regions, nor continuance of time can proue, that they haue, as he brags, the true Gospell, and the true sence of it, the true Christiā Religiō, &amp; the true Church &amp; spouse of Christ, who haue in these maine &amp; principall points beene controled and condemned, in all these as I haue shewed. Whatsoeuer therefore he infers or buildes vpon this false princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or whatsoeuer after, vpon the bare supposing the same to be true, thou shalt reade <hi>Iohn de Albine</hi> railingly in his triumphant &amp; arrogant maner to speake, in disgrace of vs, our Church, mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters or Religion: I hope, I say, thou wilt esteeme of it, as of vaine and foolish wordes, of proud and yet malitious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries. Yet hauing thus answered in this sort his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, somewhat the better to prepare thee to iudge of <hi>Iohn de Albine,</hi> and my answere vnto him: giue mee leaue now to say somewhat concerning his booke and his maner of dealing therein.</p>
      <p>Wherefore to proceede, hauing perused and as throughly, as I could, considered of it (gentle Reader) I protest vnto thee vpon what occasion soeuer it hath got such credit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst men of his owne consort, that it hath not onely of them beene thought worthy to be published in English, but also to be intituled, <hi>A notable discourse against heresies,</hi> I haue found it, and so shall any indifferent Reader of this my answere vnto it, not able at all to doe either good or harme, but
<pb facs="40"/> onely to such as are verie simple, vnlearned and silly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant creatures. For the principall questions in hand, either alwaies he takes for graunted, and so neuer goes about to proue them: or subtlely &amp; suddainly (seeming to haue vndertaken the proofe of them) hee slippeth into another matter, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with goeth on lustely, as though he were busy about the point in controuersy, when as indeede he hath left that quite, and chosen to himselfe some other matter more easie for him to deale in, either not at all in controuersy, or howsoeuer, to small purpose for the proofe of the thing intended. And yet thus hee seemeth vnto himselfe, and vnto his vnskilfull Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to haue wonne the cause and to carrie all before him, when indeede hee hath saied quite nothing to the purpose, and hath busied himselfe onely about that which was needelesse: which to the ende that thou maiest the better obserue thy selfe in the rest of his booke, I will giue thee a tast of, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning thereof. Vnderstand therefore, that whereas his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and principall scope is, in his whole discourse, to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace our ministry, and the whole matter thereof, our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: that so hauing once perswaded his Reader, that we haue neither lawfull ministers, nor sound Religion, hee might conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently boldely pronounce vs to bee heretiques, and our whole Church schismaticall &amp; hereticall. To effect this his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, because hee soresawe, that first it were necessarie that he should iustify their owne ministry and Religion, before hee should so call ours into question: first hee laboureth about that in the first eight Chapters, &amp; then striueth about the other in the rest. But marke now, I beseech thee, how he makes his entry into this so weighty and necessary a point. Whereas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede out of the fift to the Hebrewes wee obiect (as hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesseth) that their calling to their Priesthoode &amp; Prelacies can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be of God, because their very offices themselues were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of Gods owne ordinance, but onelie of mans owne deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing: though to answere this obiection, euery man might see, and he himselfe saw (as it appeares by his owne words <hi>ca.</hi> 1.) that it was most necessary for him first to haue proued, that their offices were of Gods institution, and not of mans inuention onely, like a cunning Sophister, hee slippes from that, promising af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in some other place to proue it, which yet though it
<pb facs="40"/> stoode him in this his discourse neuer so much vpon, he neuer so much as once remembreth or mentioneth againe. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thus onely supposing and taking this for graūted, that their Priesthoode and Prelacies are of God (which he knowes we will neuer graunt them) hee takes vpon him to proue onely their comming thereunto to bee lawfull, which he proues as slen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly also. For to proue it, hee onely saieth, that they come to them by the ordinary way, by right succession of Bishops and pastours, continuing in one Catholicke faith, downe from Christ to this present time: thus childishly begging in one piece of one short sentence these foure great points (all which in this case are betwixt vs and them in question) namely, that their officers all of them, come to their roomes by the ordinary way, that they haue right succession, right Bishops and pastours, and sounde and Apostolicke doctrine. And yet though he knew well enough, that wee constantly deny all these, yet to proue that they come lawfully to their offices, hee onely nakedly and barely affirmeth them, as though he presumed, that he was and should be such a <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> in the conceit of all his Readers, that for him once to say it, were enough and enough againe. For by and by after that thus he had onely saied, hauing vsed neither proofe nor colour of proofe to backe his saying, hee slippeth into another matter, not yet called in question: Whither a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, knowen, and alwaies a demonstrable, personall, and locall succession of Bishops &amp; pastours, be necessary for the perpetuall continuāce of the Church, and preseruatiō of the trueth therin? And thus hee windeth frō matter to matter, leauing alwaies that vnproued, which hee had most neede to haue proued, labouring &amp; sweating continually about the proofe of that, which though it were graūted him, yet he might wel enough loose his cause. As for example, hauing entred into the foresaid matter in maner before saied, in 3. or 4. whole Chapters following, he shewes how the trueth is continued in the Church by succession of pastours, how profitable their ministry is, to bring men to, &amp; to settle them in the truth, that the anciēt trodē way by Christs sheepe, downe from Christ to this day, that the ancient Catholicke faith, that the faith which in <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and <hi>Augustines</hi> time was helde and taught at Rome, &amp; had vnto their times beene continued from Christ by succession of Bishoppes and pastours, is the waie and
<pb facs="41"/> faith that a Catholicke man must liue and die in, whosoeuer saieth to the contrary. In which propositions, no maruaile though he goe on roundly, for he hath winde and weather with him, &amp; none of vs gainesaies him; yea these things being rightly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstoode, wee constantly affirme and teach the same But these things being all graunted him, what is hee nearer his cause, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as yet all the sort of them neuer could, nor shall bee able to proue, that their pastours succeed Christ, his Apostles, or the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent holy Bishops &amp; pastours, that were before <hi>Irenaeus</hi> &amp; <hi>Avgu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stines</hi> time, in teaching the same doctrine that they taught? But herein is his popish subtlely, that standing thus vpō these points, he would haue his Reader graūt him all these: that their successiō of Priests &amp; Bishops is that successiō of pastours, so profitable for the continuāce of the trueth and Church: that their Romish Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion that now is, is that ancient way that Christs sheepe haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies trod, &amp; so the ancient Catholicke Religiō which in <hi>Irenaeus</hi> &amp; <hi>Augustines</hi> time, they &amp; the holy pastours &amp; Bishops at Rome and else where had, soundly succeeding one another from the Apostles, continued in vnto that time; which are things whereof not one, the Pope and all his confederates shall euer be able in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede to proue: and therefore it seemeth <hi>Iohn de Albine</hi> thought it good policy, seeing these thinges could be got no otherwise, to trie whether he could get them thus by flatte begging of them. And it seemeth also, that hee presumed, that hee should come onely to such liberall mens dores, that all these should be graū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and giuen him, euen at the very first asking: for alwaies af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he behaues himselfe in such sort, as that without all perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture he had them all graunted him. Onely a little in his thirty seuēth Chapter, belike somewhat growing ashamed of his shamelesse begging al the while before, he begins to make shew, that if men should be so hard harted, as to deny him, that their pastours, doctrine and Church are sound &amp; Catholicke, that he is able to proue them so to bee, whither such will or no. And yet euen there, when all comes to all (though indeede hee bragge, that he could and would, but for being too tedious to his Reader, iustify the rest of their doctrine, by the testimony of a number of doctours, holy confessours and martyrs) he onely by mustering of a sort of dumbe doctours vpon the stage, makes his poore Reader beleeue, that in the places quoted by him, they
<pb facs="41"/> speake directly to iustify their ceremonies, their Auricular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, praier for the dead and to the dead, as though these were the principall matters in controuersy betwixt them and vs. But doubtles hee knew well enough, that no one of his Readers amongst an hundred, would and could turne the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and so try whither the men he name, make there so for him or no. For otherwise, for shame he would not haue quoted them so negligently, falsely and corruptly, as when I come to that place, I shall shew thee hee hath. These thinges considered (Christian Reader) thou must bee very simple and haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand thy minde wholy forestalled with his false principles, or else hee shall winne with thee little credit to his cause, or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace to ours. Howbeit, seeing both his whole drift, and his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishers in his preface, was (as it euidently thereby appeares) vnder the odious names of heretiques and schismatiques, to disgrace vs and the trueth that wee professe (as though it were not once to be called in questiō, whither they and their crue, were the onely sound Catholickes and Christians in the world) before I let thee proceede, &amp; come to the view of his declamation made to that ende, and of my answere thereunto: this vpon good and most cleare ground I protest vnto thee and assure thee, what brags so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he, or any other of his fellows make, of their popish and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish Religion, that now is prosessed amongst them: besides all other things that can or may be saied against it, it is such a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and their Church the vpholder thereof such a dame, as is the very nurse and baude of monstrous impietie, as is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerably iniurious to the right of the good estates of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Princes and their people; and as lastly (howsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it may seeme to carry a shew of holinesse) it is not so, but indeede cunningly vnder the colour thereof, ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth at no marke more, then to aduaunce the pride, pompe, and gaine of her louers. The first is euident, in that their doctrine of their Popes supermacy is such, as that for money hee may pardon any sinne (as their practise teacheth) either committed, or to be committed: yea their verie Hedge-priestes by the authority of the power of absolution giuen vnto them, vpon penaunce done, how light soeuer, if it so seeme good vnto them, haue and doe take vpon them marueilously, that way to breede immunity and impunity, by their absoluing
<pb facs="42"/> whom &amp; for what they list. Their doctrine also of satisfaction for sinne, in that they allow sprinkling of holy water, going on pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, doing of this outwarde trifling thing, or that, which easily may be done of any carnal man, to be good satisfactory meane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> to answere God withal for their sinnes: how can it be otherwise but the people measuring and iudging of sinne according there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, must needs thinke sinne, that can be satisfied for so easily and lightly, to be but a sleight matter. Their doctrine also of eare shrist, is likewise a meanes to acquaint their single priestes, with all the lewd huswiues in their parishees, and so an acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of them, with the trickes &amp; waies how, and the parties with whom, they may commit filthinesse. Yea their forced single life (as experience notoriously hath taught) hath infected earth and aire, with monstrous vncleannesse of the flesh, both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and outward, naturall &amp; vnnaturall, &amp; with infinite mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of poore infantes, the better still to hide their iniquity. And while they teach that simple fornication is not so ill in their cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, as to vse a lawfull wife, that the first inwarde motions to sinne or concupiscence not consented vnto, be no sinnes, that manie sinnes euen for their owne littlenes are veniall, &amp; not worthy of damnation: they make men secure for these, and so the fitter &amp; bolder to go on in the rest. Their doctrine and practise of dispē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sations, and pardons for money, for clergy and people almost for any thing, is, and must needs be, the roote and fountaine of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful many abhominations. Their doctrine of sanctuaries, priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, exemptiōs, and immunities of their clergy &amp; others, are very great occasions of sinne and impiety. Lastly, the ambition, pride, tyranny, pompe, gluttony, wantonnes and insatiable co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetousnes of their Popes, Cardinals and Prelats, makes al, whom they bewich with their religion, to thinke, that they are not to be blamed, if in these things they imitate then their holy fathers: &amp; marueilously are they incouraged to continue and spend their daies in these, &amp; in al other sinnes, when as by their doctrine they are put in hope, if they die (beleeuing blindly as the church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeues, providing of their goods, which they must needs leaue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them, somwhat liberally, that masses, dirges &amp; trentals may be saied and song for them, and that such other things done as thē their ghostly father shal appoint them) that in the end they shall doe well enough, how loosely and lewdly soeuer otherwise
<pb facs="42"/> they liued before.</p>
      <p>The second point also, is many waies cleare and apparent. For first by their doctrine of their Popes supremacy, where it is in the full force, Emperours, Kings &amp; Queenes, are thereby made and marde at their pleasure: they must not thinke scorne of most base seruice and subiection to them, their subiectes shall be bound to pay them tribute no longer, or to yeelde them any maner of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther duety, further then they list: yea it shall be lawfull for them, to conspire against their naturall Princes, &amp; by any meanes they can, to deuise to depriue thē both of their liues and kingdome, if so the Pope cōmaund them. Nay not onely vpon the Popes cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement and pardon, shall this of them bee counted lawfull and meritorious: but if any of his ovvne motion vndertake such a thing, of a deuout minde to his holmes and religion, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement and absolution of euery Masse-priest shall be suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, to iustifie the action, and to cause the party, that hath done it, to be canonized a Saint for his labour. Further for the establishing of this archpiller of popery, their Popes supremacy, Princes are depriued of the election of their Prelates, and they are by oath so obliged to the Pope, and so freed from the iurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of their lawfull Prince, that they may and dare beard their Princes: and howsoeuer they wil take liberty to enioy great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions vnder them, yet in effect they are no subiectes vnto them, but rather altogither stand at the deuotion of this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine Potentate. Secondly, by the pretended right of this their supremacy, for the better maintenaunce of the swelling pompe thereof, to the great weakning of Christian states, they haue taken vpon thē, and yet doe, when they may be suffred, by their annates, Peeter-pence, Paul-fees, first-fruits, tenths, lones, oppressions, taxations, impositions, and infinite such other deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, sauoring of nothing else, but of insatiable couetousnes, to cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey away the treasure, riches, and wealth of euery cuntrey, from out of it to Rome. And by this their supremacy, they haue first weakned, after rent in two, &amp; lastly brought in effect to nothing, the glorious Roman Empire, that so the better they might haue roome to grow vp in, and that for their sins in the iustice of God, Christendome might the more easily become a pray to the Turke. Thirdly, by the deuise of their Auricular Cōfession they haue, and may haue, most perfect intelligence of the secretes of
<pb facs="43"/> all states where they haue to doe, then which can any thing in these outward things bee more dangerous, to the safe and good estate of Princes? Fourthly, by the force of single life, they haue caused priuies, and ponds, &amp; such other by corners to swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe vp and destroy, in euery Christian kingdome where they ruled, as many infants, as might, being growen to be men, haue beene able, in the fielde, to defend there Prince and cuntrey a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all the enemies thereof: vvhich vvhat a vveakning to Christian Princes and their kingdomes it hath beene, vvho seeth not? These thinges therefore considered, it is to bee marueiled, that any Christian state, can or will tolerate, either them, or their religion in it.</p>
      <p>And as for the last point, that so their religion might fit the title appointed it by the Spirit of God, that is, that indeede it might proue it selfe to be,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Thess.</hi> 2.</note> a very mistery of iniquity, euen throughout vnder the shevv of holinesse and deuotion, they alvvaies haue hid, nourished, and maintained grosse iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and haue aymed at nothing more, then at their owne pompe and aduantage. For their doctrines of free-vvill, of mans a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenesse to keepe and ouer keepe the law of God, of merits &amp; satisfaction for our selues or others aliue or dead, of the mediati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Saints or Angels: and their doctrines, that the Pope cannot erre, that he hath such supremacy as they giue him, and that the scriptures haue their sence and authority from his allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance thereof, howsoeuer they paint these things with the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly shewes of care to prouoke and incourage men to good works, and with deuotion to Saint <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; the mother church: yet who is so simple or weake sighted, but that through these colours, hee may and doth discerne God &amp; his sonne Christ blasphemously robbed of that which is their right, man to be occasioned to swell with a conceyt of his owne ability: and that the final marke, that all this tēds vnto, is, by the selling of other folkes ouerplus merits and satisfactions vnder, and in the names of pardons, to enrich the Pope and his Priests, and by the rest to set vp themselues in the very seat of Antichrist? They pretend the glory of Christ, and of <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> in the doctrine of the supremacy: but it is the feeding of their owne pompous &amp; tyrānous ambition, that in trueth they seeke in it. In their swarmes of Monkeries &amp; Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eries they pretend wilfull pouerty, and an vtter forsaking of the
<pb facs="43"/> world, and yet all the world seeth, that to maintaine themselues therein in idlenes, belly-cheare, and al kinde of worldly and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal pleasure, they had houses like Princes, and reuēnues &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunces, like great Lordes of the worlde. They haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, that they vvould haue Emperours and Kinges in no case to giue Bishoprickes and benefices, to preuent Simony: whereas their practise hath made it cleare, that their Popes haue taken that into their owne hands, but to make the clergy more to stand at their deuotion, and lesse at their Princes, and that they &amp; theirs might vse that occupation and trade of Simony, as most proper vnto themselues. They pretende charity and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion in their pardons and indulgences, deuotion and care to relieue soules by their masses, dirges, and trentals, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to fray mē frō sinne by their doctrine of Purgatory: but eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mā seeth, that it is onely money, or money worth, that hereby they fish for. The vnity of the church is pretended, when they seeke to establish most their owne tyrāny: the honour and glory of the church (they say) they seeke, when it is most plaine, that it is onely their ovvne glory and honour they care for. In the maintenaunce of their doctrine of transubstantiation, they vvould seeme marueilous deuout and religious in vrging of the letter, and in captiuing their ovvne sences and reason thereunto, whereas indeede that course they take, that so their Priestes may grovve to honour and vvealth, vvhiles thereby the people are made beleeue, that they can make and offer their redeemer, for the saluation of quicke and deade. Deuotion to the Saints they pretend in teaching, that they are to bee prayed vnto and vvorshipped, but therein their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion is like vnto <hi>Demetrius</hi> his for <hi>Diana</hi> of <hi>Ephesus:</hi> for if it were not for the gaynes they get by offerings vnto their shrynes, they vvould not bee so hoate therein. Their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of penaunce caries a shevv of mortification, but it is but thereby to triumph ouer the people at their pleasures, and in the ende to make a gaine by changing their penaunce, or by making them to beleeue, that they vvill relieue them by their prayers, pardons, and masses. To conclude, I dare bee bolde to say, that there is neuer a proper point of popery, but the practise and profession of it would quickly grow very cold, if that the maintenance thereof made not, either directly to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce
<pb facs="44"/> their wordly credit with their followers, or their lucre and commodity. And therefore thou maiest see euen by this (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer they bragge of their Church and Religion) that euen for these three reasons, they, both of euery wise state, &amp; consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly also of thy selfe (Christian Reader) ought to be shunned and auoided. These things then, that I haue saied, well considered and remembred, I will now no longer detaine thee from taking a view of that, which (this notwithstanding) <hi>Albine</hi> hath writē, either in the defence of this his Religion, or to the disgrace of ours: requesting onely this at thy hands, that as thou goest, thou wouldest take the paines without partiality, to reade and confer that, which I haue writen to answere him withall, Chapter by Chapter with his booke. And thus hoping that thou wilt doe, I commend thee and thy study therein, to the direction and good protection of God, &amp; my selfe vnto thy harty praiers vnto him, in my behalfe.</p>
      <closer>
         <signed>
            <hi>Thine in the Lord,</hi> THOMAS SPARKE.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>