<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Authors Epistle, to my Ma∣sters of the Romish Church.</title>
           <author>Luyne, Motthe</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117179_Fr2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69250</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7372</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117179</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Authors Epistle, to my Ma∣sters of the Romish Church.</title>
                 <author>Luyne, Motthe</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Newes from France : containing tvvo declarations of two new conuerts from the Church of Rome to the reformed churches of France: the former made by Master M. du Tertrf [sic], Lord de la Motthe Luyne, late preacher amongst the order of the Capucins vnder the name of F. Firmin, &amp;c. at Saumur on the 27. of May last: the latter by the Marquise Boniuet, Lord of Creuecoeur, &amp;c. at Rochell on the seuenth of August last. Both translated out of the seuerall French copies into English by E.M. of Christ-Church in Oxford. Whereunto is added an English letter sent from Pari by an English gentleman to his friend in England, touching the late surprisall and imprisonment of the Prince of Conde, which happened on the 22. of August last</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 55, 5, 14 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prefatory_letter">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Authors Epistle, to my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of the Romish Church.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Irs, I haue a long while debated and disputed with my selfe, whether I should set to your view the causes and reasons of my retreate from you and your Church, and of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersion and vnion to the Reformed ones of this Kingdome, and their societie and company. On the one side, the sinceritie of my intention in this charge seemed wholly to diuert, turne, and hinder me from so doing, as ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring very little what men thought, spake, or esteemed of it; so that my actions were pleasing and acceptable to the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame and eternall maiesty of my God, conformable to his holy and diuine will, tending and redounding to his honour and glory, and aduantagious and profitable for mine owne good and saluation. And besides contenting my selfe with that which I haue spoken, treated, and declared thereof in my Profession, made in the Church of this Citie, the <hi>24.</hi> of <hi>April.</hi> But on the other side, the duties and obligations which I owe to the truth, ioyned with the most affectionate suits and opportunities, which almost an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber haue vsed towards me, and often reiterated, and the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies and slaunders, wherewith many amongst you (though vniustly and wrongfully) doe charge me, doe force and constraine me to set downe in this paper, produce to the day and bring to light, that which almost I then said of it; this only excepted, that now I will enlarge my selfe a little
<pb facs="5"/>
more, then the shortnesse of the time and discourse could at that time permit me. I haue thought and beleeued that I could not more iustly, and with better reason and equitie, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect this Treatise to any, then to those, from whom I separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my selfe, to the end I might take from them the idle and light opinions, and the bad beliefes, farre remoued from pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and honesty, and remoue the scandall which they might haue conceiued therevpon. Receiue it therefore, I pray you▪ with the same gentlenes and sincerity of affection, with the which I offer and present it vnto you. And doe mee the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to take the paines to read it; but with quietnesse, if it please you, and tranquillity of minde, without trouble and passion. And I hope, nay I am certaine, and assure my selfe that you shall finde, that there is more reason and knowledge in my action, then you thinke, and more obligation to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me, and to do that which I haue done, then you imagine. To this end I doe open all the secrets of my heart, and foulds of my soule before the Maiesty of my God: and in your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, with a solemne oath and protestation, that I will say nothing but the truth. I beseech the diuine goodnesse, to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist you with his grace and heauenly light, to make you know clearely both the one and the other. I doe pray with all my heart, and with as great affection, as I am verily, and shal be all my life, notwithstanding this change and alteration of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and departure from you, and your society &amp; company.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Sirs,</salute>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your most humble, inward, and affectionate, for your good and saluation,</hi> Dela Motthe Luyne.</signed>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From</hi> Saumur, <date>
            <hi>this 27. of</hi> May, <hi>1616.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>