<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONORABLE Sir William Parsons Knight Barronet, his Maiesties Survayour Generall, Com∣missioner in the Court of Wards, and one of his Maiesties most Honourable Privie Counsell in Ireland, &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117038_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11816</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22112</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117038</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONORABLE Sir William Parsons Knight Barronet, his Maiesties Survayour Generall, Com∣missioner in the Court of Wards, and one of his Maiesties most Honourable Privie Counsell in Ireland, &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Naturall philosophy: or A description of the vvorld, and of the severall creatures therein contained : viz. of angels, of mankinde, of the heavens, the starres, the planets, the foure elements, with their order, nature and government: as also of minerals, mettals, plants, and precious stones; with their colours, formes, and vertues. By Daniel Widdovves</title>
                 <author>Scribonius, Wilhelm Adolf</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cotes, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bellamy, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 65, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HONORABLE Sir <hi>William Parsons</hi> Knight Barronet, his Maiesties Survayour Generall, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <hi>missioner in the Court of Wards, and one of</hi> his Maiesties most Honourable Privie Counsell in <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Honourable Sir:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doe present to your view a small frame of the world, and of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures therein contained, drawne with the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>silles of iudicious <hi>Scribon,</hi> and of <hi>D. W.</hi> A worke in nature not unlike to our Survayes in <hi>Ireland,</hi> that represent most lively, vaste Countries within a small Map. I offer this to you, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heretofore given to you an account of
<pb facs="3"/> those services that I have lately done in the survey of <hi>Ireland,</hi> you being Survayor Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of that kingdome, wherein I have spent the most part of thirty yeares, in the service of my Prince and Country, <hi>Tam Marte, quam Mercurio,</hi> both by Pike and Pen, with great toyle, much hazard, and many hurts; but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle profit. Notwithstanding, your demerits and worth be such, as Gratitude hath chosen your Patronage: and Devotion wisheth all honour, health, and happinesse to you, to my good Lady, and to yours,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>At your Honours Command, I. Wyddowes, <hi>alias</hi> Woodhouse.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>