<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE KINGS MOST EXCELLENT MAIESTIE.</title>
           <author>Stranguage, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117760_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14194</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24509a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117760</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE KINGS MOST EXCELLENT MAIESTIE.</title>
                 <author>Stranguage, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of the life and death of Mary Stuart Queene of Scotland</title>
                 <author>Camden, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Whitaker, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 250, 2 pages, portraits (metal cut), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE KINGS MOST EXCELLENT MAIESTIE.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most Dread Soueraigne,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Z</seg>ENO the Philosopher, being asked how a man might attaine wisdome, answered, By draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neere vnto the dead. O the Sepulchers of our Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors, how much more doe they teach than all the studie, bookes and precepts of the learned!</p>
   <p>And herein due praise must needs be ascribed vnto Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, the life of memorie, and the mirrour of mans life, making those Heroick acts to liue againe, which otherwise would be buried in eternall forgetfulnesse, whereby the minde (a greedy hunter after knowledge) is enflamed, by affecting the seuerall perfections of others, to seeke after excellent things, and by feruent imitation to attaine to that glory which is gotten by vertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>
For these causes, (most renowned Soueraigne) when I considered <hi>Plutarke,</hi> laying aside the studie of Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phic, to thinke the time well imploied in writing the liues of <hi>Theseus,</hi> of <hi>Aristides,</hi> and of other inferiour persons; and knowing how farre the lustre and splendor of Princes shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth beyond the brightnesse of others; euery one standing for a million of the common people: And being sensible that it is infused euen by nature, euery man to desire, and to be delighted with the relation and story of his owne Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors and predecessors:</p>
   <p>For these reasons I presumed to present vnto your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse this Treatise of the life and death of your Royall Mother, the Lady <hi>MARY STVART</hi> Queene of <hi>Scotland;</hi> A History most fit for this your <hi>Meridian</hi> of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> and yet neuer published in the English tongue before: Wherein, although I confesse the slender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of my skill in the exornation and beautifying of the stile, and thereby may worthily incurre the reproofe of the learned; yet if your Maiesty vouchsafe your gracious and Princely acceptation, all faults therein shall easily bee couered and blotted out. Therefore I become your humble Orator, praying no other thing than the Sunne Diall of the Sunne, <hi>Aspice me vt aspiciar:</hi> most humbly beseeching the Almighty to blesse your most Excellent Maiestie, with a long, happie, and prosperous reigne.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Sacred Maiesties most humble subiect,
WIL. STRANGVAGE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>