<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL Mr. DOCTOR GOODWIN Deane; and to the Canons of the Colledge of CHRIST-CHVRCH in Oxon.</title>
           <author>Sprint, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117795_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12800</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23108</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117795</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL Mr. DOCTOR GOODWIN Deane; and to the Canons of the Colledge of CHRIST-CHVRCH in Oxon.</title>
                 <author>Sprint, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cassander Anglicanus : shewing the necessity of conformitie to the prescribed ceremonies of our church, in case of depriuation. By Iohn Sprint, minister of Thornbury in Glocester-shire, sometimes of Christ-Church in Oxon</title>
                 <author>Sprint, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bill, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 277, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL M<seg rend="sup">r.</seg> DOCTOR GOODWIN Deane; and to the Canons of the Colledge of CHRIST-CHVRCH in Oxon.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or dedication of this booke to you (R. w.) I had direction frō the Riuers, who <note place="margin">Eccles. 1. 7.</note> empt themselues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Seas from whence they came. To you, by whose Reuerend praedecessors I was in common consent chosen scholler into Christ-Church; by whom that small modell of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which I haue (if I haue any
<pb facs="4"/> thing in mee which may be called Learning) was deriued to me, and by whom I was of free donation, without bribe or sute first placed in my pastorall charge. Then you, I haue no greater patrones; for you, I haue no greater gift. And this I offer to your view, your censure, your memoriall. God euer graunt you so to blesse the Colledge of Christ-church, by your free electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and elocations, that the Church of Christ may euer blesse God for you, and your selues may feele the comfort of your well-doing in this life, and find the fruit thereof in the life to come. London 27 of April M. DC. XVIII.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Who am euer at your seruice in</hi> CHRIST, IO. SPRINT.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>