<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL AND ZEA∣LOVS GENTLEWOMAN MI∣stresse Borlace of little Merlow, and to the noble and learned Gentleman Sir William Borlace the elder, her sonne, of Mednam in Buckinghamshire, and to the vertuous and elect Lady, the La∣dy Marie Borlace his wife, Bezaleel Carter a weake and vnworthy Minister of Gods word, wisheth the blessings of both worlds.</title>
           <author>Carter, Bezaleel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117382_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18048</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4692</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117382</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL AND ZEA∣LOVS GENTLEWOMAN MI∣stresse Borlace of little Merlow, and to the noble and learned Gentleman Sir William Borlace the elder, her sonne, of Mednam in Buckinghamshire, and to the vertuous and elect Lady, the La∣dy Marie Borlace his wife, Bezaleel Carter a weake and vnworthy Minister of Gods word, wisheth the blessings of both worlds.</title>
                 <author>Carter, Bezaleel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Christ his last vvill, and Iohn his legacy : In a sermon preached at Clare in Suffolke, by Bezaleel Carter preacher of the word of God at Canham neere to Saint Edmunds Bury</title>
                 <author>Carter, Bezaleel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Blackmore (Blackamore), Edward</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 86 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL AND ZEA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LOVS GENTLEWOMAN MI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresse <hi>Borlace</hi> of little <hi>Merlow,</hi> and to the noble and learned Gentleman Sir <hi>William Borlace</hi> the elder, her sonne, of <hi>Mednam</hi> in Buckinghamshire, and to the vertuous and elect Lady, the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Marie Borlace</hi> his wife, <hi>Bezaleel Carter</hi> a weake and vnworthy <hi>Minister of Gods word, wisheth the blessings of both worlds.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worshipfull, I confesse that I haue had an intention to haue written of all the sufferings of our Sauiour Christ vnder <hi>Caiphas, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod, Filate</hi> and to haue beene as large vpon the whole 23. chapter of Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> as I haue beene vpon these two verses in the following Pamphlet, but so I am preuented through a numberlesse number of businesses by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of my Sabboth dayes paines, my weekeday Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, teaching children, and other imployments, that I almost wonder at my selfe, or rather I admire Gods goodnesse, that hath enabled me and carried me through all these. If God shall please hereafter
<pb facs="3"/> to rayse me vp such competency of meanes that I may without further distractions follow my priuate studies, I yet resolue (when I see a calling) to publish all my Meditations vpon that Chapter. In the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim, I haue aduentured to the light this simple Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scourse, and haue also presumed to Dedicate it to your selues, as a testimony of vnfained affection, and thankefulnesse, and as a motiue to excite you to charity &amp; constancy in Gods seruice. I say to you as <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Galathians,</hi> you haue begun well, nay I doubt not but that I may praise God for you: as the same Apostle did for the <hi>Thessalonians,</hi> because your faith growes exceedingly. My prayer for you is that as you haue beene for many yeares fruitfull trees in Gods Vineyard, bearing and bringing forth much good fruite: so also you may perseuere, florishing like the Cedar tree, that saith <hi>Plinie,</hi> beares the best &amp; the most fruite in the oldest age, in which regard the Psalmist resembles the righteous mā to the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar, <hi>Psal.</hi> 92. The righteous shall florish like a Palme tree, and spred abrode like a Cedar in Lebanon, and then it followes in his old age, he shall be fat and wel liking. Right Worshipfull these haue beene the motiues which made me bold to consecrate these my labours to your names, neither do I doubt (all weakenesse and imperfection bewrayed notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing) for the Authors sake, at the least, you will accept them, who also remaineth and shall euer.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your worship in all duty and seruice Bezaleel Carter.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>