<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117447_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16236</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3160</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117447</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The theoriques of the seuen planets : shewing all their diuerse motions, and all other accidents, called passions, thereunto belonging. Now more plainly set forth in our mother tongue by M. Blundeuile, than euer they haue been heretofore in any other tongue whatsoeuer, an that with such pleasant demonstratiue figures, as euery man that hath any skill in arithmeticke, may easily vnderstand the same. ... VVhereunto is added by the said Master Blundeuile, a breefe extract by him made, of Maginus his Theoriques, for the better vnderstanding of the Prutenicall tables, t calculate thereby the diuerse motions of the seuen planets. There is also hereto added, The making, description, and vse, of two most ingenious and necessarie instruments for sea-men ... First inuented by M. Doctor Gilbert ... and now here plainely set downe in our mother tongue by Master Blundeuile</title>
                 <author>Blundeville, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 <publisher>Bushell, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 278, 279-292, 2 pages, folded plates, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing aduertised by diuers of my good
friends, how fauorably it hath pleased
the Gentlemen, both of the Court and
Country, and specially the Gentlemen
of the Innes of Court, to accept of my
poore Pamphlets, entituled <hi>Blundeuiles Exercises;</hi>
yea, and that many haue earnestly studied the same,
because they plainly teach the first Principles, as well
of Geographie as of Astronomie: I thought I could
not shew my selfe any way more thankfull vnto them,
than by setting forth the Theoriques of the Planets,
vvhich I haue collected, partly out of <hi>Ptolomey,</hi> and
partly out of <hi>Purbachius,</hi> and of his Commentator
<hi>Reinholdus,</hi> also out of <hi>Copernicus,</hi> but most out of
<hi>Mestelyn,</hi> whom I haue cheefely followed, because his
method and order of writing greatly contenteth my
humor. I haue also in many things followed <hi>Maginus,</hi>
a later vvriter, vvho came not vnto my hands, before
that I had almost ended the first part of my booke,
neither should I haue had him at all, if my good friend
M. Doctor <hi>Browne,</hi> one of the ordinarie Physicians
to her Maiestie, had not gotten him for me, with which
<pb facs="4"/>
good Doctor I haue had in times past at Norwiche
many learned conferences, and haue receiued at his
hands many good documents, whom I take to be so
vniuersally learned in all manner of good and liberall
Sciences, as any other that I know in these daies: and
besides his great learning, I know him to be very wise
and honest, which two vertues I wish to raigne in all
learned men, because they be the greatest ornaments
that belong to learning. I haue deuided this my
booke into two parts, whereof the first part treateth
of the diuers motions of the Planets; and the second
part, of their Passions; and that so plainely, and vvith
such facilitie, as I hope that euery man of a meane ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie
may vnderstand the same. For I thought good
to collect out of the foresaid Authors no more but
that vvhich onely was meet and fit for that purpose,
praying all those that be learned, hereafter to adde to
this my booke any necessarie thing, that I through
age and vvant of cleare sight, haue negligently omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.
And so I leaue to trouble you, praying you
to take this my labour in good part, so
shall I haue iust cause to thinke
the same well bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Vale.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>