<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the gentle
Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1574</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117617_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03363</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13484</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117617</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the gentle
Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A contemplation of mysteries : contayning the rare effectes and significations of certayne comets, and a briefe rehersall of sundrie hystoricall examples, as well diuine, as prophane, verie fruitfull to be reade in this our age: with matter delectable both for the sayler, and husbandman, yea and all traueylers by sea and lande, in knowing aforehande, howe daungerous a tempest will succeede by the sight of the clowd coming ouer the head, and other matters fruitful to be read as shal appere in the table next after the preface. Gathered and englished, by Thomas Hyll</title>
                 <author>Hill, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1574</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 75, that is 76 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Preface to the gentle
Reader.</head>
   <p>Thought it good (gentle Reader) to admonishe
<hi>I</hi> thee in two or three lynes, what mine intent &amp; meaning is, in
renuing againe of this little Treatise: for although an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
reader may iudge therof, yet all mens natures not being
a like to auoyde the cauils of busie heades, and the byting speaches
of Zoylus broode, I am aduised to interpret mine owne meaning:
My purpose according to my duetie is to doe good, nature bindeth,
my countrie chalengeth, &amp; euery good man according to his talent
&amp; power ought to fulfil the same. God thretneth: the deuine to such
as will heare, cryeth repentaunce: to such as can not away wyth
that kinde of speache, but desireth sweeter and more delectable
geare, the Player with his stage matters, by an other kinde of more
pleasant meanes admonisheth, and by a plaine demonstration put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
euery man in minde of his vocation. I professing no diuinitie,
nor yet acquainted with playing inuention, haue by an other mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
(if it were possible) put thee in remembraunce of thy duetie to
Godward: we see Gods mercifulnesse, hee seldome punisheth but
sendeth before his messengers, tokens and wonders to forewarne
vs, if we were not dulheades, we might perceyue the same, but if we
had grace, we woulde indeuour our selues to amendment.</p>
   <p>Before God destroyed his owne Citie Ierusalem, he caused to
appeare in the element wonderfull and terrible visions. Before the
imperiall seate of Constantine was translated, signes and tokens
were seene in the ayre. God (as wee maye reade in Cronicles) sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
or neuer made alterations in kingdomes, but he before sent
in Ambassage, his threatning Creatures. To seeke for olde and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine
examples we neede not, seeing we haue ynough of late dayes
at home, freshe in our memories, as first he by burning his owne
house, brought a present terrour into the mindes of many, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
them to call on his name, and generally foreshewed, that as he
spared not that place, wherein his name was dayly called on, no
more would he spare the people, that despised his lawes and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces
(and soone after) it came so to passe, for when the warnin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
woould not be taken, he punished more seuerely: hee sent a gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
mortalitie, and sweeped or tooke away a great number.</p>
   <p>God is iust and mercifull, for iust he is in punishing, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull
in forgiuing. The continual bearing of monsters, the trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some
<pb facs="3"/>
Elements, these last two Summers, the vnseasonable weather:
and last of all, the late straunge and wonderfull inun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ations, doe
threaten Gods iustice, in punishing the offenders, and his clemencie
and mercie, by fauouring vs so gently. God notwithstanding, that
he threatned Niniuie, by the mouth of his Prophete, yet did hee
mercifully forgiue them, vpon their repentance. God poure out hys
spirite vpon vs, and giue vs his grace to acknowledge and bewaile
our offences, so shall we be spared with Niniuie, and the Lorde will
turne away all his threatnings, into forgiuenesse. It is high time we
repent: God threatneth, we are in daunger, compassed on euery side,
all things are readie, nothing wanteth but Gods permission.</p>
   <p>I haue bene somewhat longer (gentle Reader) than at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
I promised or purposed: yet take this (for breuitie sake)
but for an enteraunce, of a great deale more, that might
aptly be here vttered: the rest vntouched, I commit
to thy iudgement and vnderstanding. Thus
resting, I craue none other than your
friendly report, in furthering
this Treatise.</p>
   <closer>Vale feliciter.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>