<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An aduertisement to
the reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117656_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12609</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22931</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117656</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An aduertisement to
the reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Ottoman of Lazaro Soranzo : VVherein is deliuered aswell a full and perfect report of the might and power of Mahamet the third, great Emperour of the Turkes now raigning: together with the interestes and dealinges which he hath with sondrie other princes, what hee is plotting against the state of Christendome, and on the other side what we may practise and put in execution against him to his great damage and annoyaunce. As also a true description of diuers peoples, countries, citties and voyages, which are most necessarie to bee knowen, especially at this time of the present warre in Hungarie. Translated out of Italian into English, by Abraham Hartvvell</title>
                 <author>Soranzo, Lazzaro</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 <publisher>Windet, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 107, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="notice">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>An aduertisement to
the reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, if in all this discourse
you do not reade, that <hi>Mahamet Satarz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi,</hi>
(of whom mention is made pag. 9.)
is now become the General of the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kish
campe. That <hi>Sinan Cicala</hi> (pa. 6. b.)
beginneth to recouer the fauor of the Emperor <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hamet.</hi>
That <hi>Hassan Bassa,</hi> who had the gouernment
of Constantinople in the absence of the great Turk
(pag. 6.) was first created chiefe Visier, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes
put to death: And lastly, that the
Prince of Transiluania hath surprised <hi>Feulac,</hi> and
<hi>Canaal,</hi> and such other like matters. And especially,
that the Christian Emperour hath recouered the
strong Fort of <hi>Giauarino,</hi> chiefly through the grace
and fauour of God, and next by the notable valour
and labor of <hi>Adolph</hi> Baron of <hi>Schwartzenberg,</hi> most
worthy of eternall memorie: I pray you remember
how the Authour in his former Preface doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test,
that touching certaine accidents he writeth no
further then till the yeare 1597. wherein hee also
dealeth like a Politician rather then like an Historio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grapher:
&amp; therefore referreth those matters to some
other workes which he had then in hand. Farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>