<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Allegorie of the Poem.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117565_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68799</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23698</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117565</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Allegorie of the Poem.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Godfrey of Bulloigne, or The recouerie of Ierusalem. Done into English heroicall verse, by Edward Fairefax Gent</title>
                 <author>Tasso, Torquato</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Hatfield, Arnold.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jaggard (Jagger), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Matthew</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 392 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Allegorie of the <hi>Poem.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>HEroicall Poetrie</hi> (as a liuing Creature, wherein two natures are conioined) is compounded of <hi>Imitation</hi> and <hi>Allegorie:</hi> with the one she allureth vnto her the mindes and eares of men, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellously delighteth them; with the other, either in vertue or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, she instructeth them. And as the heroically written <hi>Imitation</hi> of an <hi>Other,</hi> is nothing else, but the patterne and image of humane action: so the <hi>Allegorie</hi> of an Heroicall Poeme is none other than the glasse and figure of humane life. But <hi>Imitation</hi> regardeth the <hi>Actions</hi> of man subiected to the outward senses, and about them being principally imployed, seeketh to represent them with effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and expressiue phrases, such as liuely set before our corporall eies the things represented: It doth not consider the customes, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, or discourses of the <hi>Minde,</hi> as they be inward, but onely as they come forth thence, and being manifested in words, in deedes, or working, doe accompanie the <hi>Action.</hi> On the other side, <hi>Allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> respecteth the passions, the opinions and customes, not onely as they doe appeare, but principally in their being hidden &amp; inward; and more obscurely doth expresse them with notes (as a man may say) misticall, such as only the vnderstanders of the nature of things can fully comprehend. Now leauing <hi>Imitation</hi> apart, we will accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our purpose speake of <hi>Allegorie:</hi> which, as the life of man is compound, so it represents to vs, sometime the figure of the one, sometime the figure of the other: yet because that commonly by <hi>Man,</hi> we vnderstand this compound of the bodie, soule, or minde, and then mans life, is said to be that, which of such compound is proper, in the operations whereof euerie part thereof concurres, and by working gets that perfection, of the which by her nature she is capable: sometime (although more seldome) by <hi>Man</hi> is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood, not the compound, but the most noble part, namely the <hi>Minde;</hi> According to this last signification, it may be said, that the life of man is <hi>Contemplatiue,</hi> and to worke simplie with the <hi>Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing,</hi> forasmuch as this life doth seeme much to participate of heauen, and as it were changde from humanitie, to become ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall. Of the life of the <hi>Contemplatiue Man,</hi> the Comedie of <hi>Dantes</hi> and the <hi>Odyssees</hi> are (as it were) in euerie part thereof a figure: but the ciuill life is seene to be shadowed throughout the <hi>Iliads,</hi> and <hi>Aeneids</hi> also, although in this there be rather set out a mixture of <hi>Action</hi> and <hi>Contemplation.</hi> But since the <hi>Contemplatiue Man</hi> is solita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; and the <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>Action</hi> liueth in ciuill companie, thence it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that <hi>Dantes &amp; Ulysses</hi> in their departure from <hi>Calipse</hi> are fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not to be accompanied of the armie, or of a multitude of sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, but to depart alone; whereas <hi>Agamemnon</hi> and <hi>Achilles</hi> are described, the one Generall of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Armie, the other leader of many troupes of <hi>Mirmidons,</hi> and <hi>Aeneas</hi> is seene to be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied when he fighteth, or doth other ciuill actes; but when he goeth to hell and the Elisian fields, he leaues his followers, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied onely with his most faithfull friend <hi>Achates,</hi> who neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from his side. Neither doth the Poet at randon faine that he
<pb facs="3"/>
went alone, for that in his voiage there is signified this onely <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation</hi> of these paines and rewardes which in another world are reserued for good or guiltie soules. Moreouer, the operation of the <hi>Vnderstanding speculatiue,</hi> which is the working of one only power, is commodiously figured vnto vs by the action of one alone: but the <hi>Operation Politicall,</hi> which proceedeth together from the other powers of the minde (which are as citizens vnited in one common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth) cannot so commodiously be shadowed of <hi>Action,</hi> wherein many together and to one end working, doe not concurre. To these reasons, and to these examples I hauing regarde, haue made the <hi>Allegorie</hi> of my <hi>Poem</hi> such, as now shall be manifested.</p>
   <p>The <hi>Army</hi> compounded of diuers Princes, and of other Christian souldiers, signifieth <hi>Man,</hi> compounded of soule and bodie, and of a soule not simple, but diuided into many and diuers powers. <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem</hi> the strong citie placed in a rough and hilly countrey, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto as to the last ende, are directed all the enterprises of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full armie, doth here signifie the <hi>Ciuill happines,</hi> which may come to a Christian man (as hereafter shall be declared) which is a good, verie difficult to attaine vnto, and situated vpon the top of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine and wearisome hill of virtue; and vnto this are turned (as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the last marke) all the Actions of the politicke man. <hi>Godfrey,</hi> which of all the assembly is chosen Chieftaine, stands for <hi>Vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> &amp; particularly for that vnderstanding, which considereth not the things necessarie, but the mutable and which may diuersly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, &amp; those by the wil of God. And of <hi>Princes</hi> he is chose Captaine of this enterprise, because vnderstanding is of God, and of Nature made Lord ouer the other virtues of the soule and bodie, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds these, one with ciuill power, the other with roiall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. <hi>Rinaldo, Tancredie,</hi> and the other Princes are in liew of the other powers of the soule; and the <hi>Bodie</hi> here becomes notified by the souldiers lesse noble. And because that through the imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of humaine nature, and by the deceits of his enemy, man at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines not this felicitie without many inward difficulties, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out finding by the way many outward impediments, all these are noted vnto vs by Poeticall figures. As the death of <hi>Syrenus,</hi> and his companions, not being ioined to the campe, but slaine farre off, may here shew the losses, which a ciuill man hath of his friends, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, and other externall goods, instruments of vertue, &amp; aids to the attaining of true felicitie. The armies of Affricke, Asia, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luckly battels, are none other than his enemies, his losses, and the accidents of contrarie fortune. But comming to the inward impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments, loue, which maketh <hi>Tancredie</hi> and the other woorthies to dote, and disioine them from <hi>Godfrey,</hi> and the disdaine which enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth <hi>Rinaldo</hi> from the enterprise, doe signifie the conflict and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion which the <hi>Concupiscent</hi> and <hi>Irefull</hi> powers, doe make with the <hi>Reasonable.</hi> The <hi>Diuels</hi> which doe consult to hinder the conquest of <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> are both a figure, and a thing figured, and doe here repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent the verie same euils, which doe oppose themselues against our ciuill happines, so that it may not be to vs a ladder of Christian bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sednes. The two Magitians <hi>Ismen</hi> and <hi>Armida,</hi> seruants of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, which indeuour to remooue the Christians from making war,
<pb facs="4"/>
are two deuilish temptations which doe lay snares for two powers of the soule, from whence all other sinnes doe proceed. <hi>Ismen</hi> doth signifie that temptation, which seeketh to deceiue with false beliefe the vertue (as a man may call it) Opinatiue: <hi>Armida</hi> is that temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation which laieth siege to the power of our desires, so from that proceed the errours of <hi>Opinion;</hi> from this, those of the <hi>Appetite.</hi> The inchantments of <hi>Ismen</hi> in the wood, deceiuing with illusions, signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie no other thing than the falsitie of the reasons and perswasions which are ingendred in the wood; that is, in the varietie and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of opinions and discourses of men. And since that man fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth vice and flieth vertue, either thinking that trauels and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers are euils most greeuous and insupportable, or iudging (as did the Epicure and his followers) that in pleasure and idlenesse con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted chiefest felicitie; by this, double is the inchantment and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion. The <hi>Fier,</hi> the <hi>Whirlewinde,</hi> the <hi>Darkenes,</hi> the <hi>Monsters,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faigned semblances, are the deceiuing allurements which doe shew vs honest trauels and honorable danger vnder the shape of <hi>Euill.</hi> The <hi>Flowers,</hi> the <hi>Fountaines,</hi> the <hi>Riuers,</hi> the <hi>Musicall</hi> instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the <hi>Nymphes,</hi> are the deceitfull inticemēts, which do here set downe before vs the pleasures and delights of the sense, vnder the shew of <hi>Good.</hi> So let it suffice to haue saide thus much of the impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments which a man findes as well within as without himselfe: yet if the Allegorie of any thing be not well expressed, with these be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings euerie man by himselfe may easily finde it out. Now let vs passe to the outward and inward helpes; with which the <hi>Ciuill man</hi> ouercomming all difficultie, is brought to this desired happines. The target of <hi>Diamond</hi> which <hi>Raimond</hi> recouereth, and afterward is shewed readie in the defence of <hi>Godfrey,</hi> ought to be vnderstood for the speciall safegard of the Lord God. The <hi>Angels</hi> doe signifie somtime <hi>Heauenly helpe,</hi> and somtime <hi>Inspiration,</hi> the which are here shadowed in the dream of <hi>Godfrey,</hi> &amp; in the records of the <hi>Hermite.</hi> The <hi>Hermite,</hi> who for the deliuerance of <hi>Rinaldo</hi> did sende the two messengers to the wiseman, doth shewe vnto vs the supernaturall knowledge receiued by Gods grace, as the wise man doth humane wisdome, forasmuch as of humane wisedome &amp; of the knowledge of the workes of Nature, &amp; the mysteries thereof, is bred &amp; establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed in our minds, <hi>Iustice, temperance,</hi> despising of <hi>death</hi> and mortall pleasures, <hi>magnanimitie,</hi> and euery other morall vertue. And great aid may a ciuill man receiue in euery action he attempteth, by <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation.</hi> It is fained, that this wise man was by birth a Pagan, but being by the <hi>Hermite</hi> conuerted to the true faith, becommeth a Christian, and despising his first arrogancie, he doth not much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume of his owne wisedome, but yeeldeth himselfe to the iudgment of his master, albeit that <hi>Philosophie</hi> be borne &amp; nourished amongst the Gentiles in Aegypt and Greece, and from thence hath passed ouer vnto vs, presumptious of her selfe, a miscreant bold and proud aboue measure: but of <hi>Saint Thomas</hi> and the other <hi>holy Doctors</hi> she is made the disciple and handmaid of Diuinitie, and is become by their indeuour more modest, and more religious, nothing daring rashly to affirme against that which is reuealed to her <hi>Maistres.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in vaine is the person of the wise man brought in, <hi>Rinaldo</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="4"/>
able by the onely counsel of the <hi>Hermite</hi> to be found &amp; brought backe againe) for that, it is brought in shew, that the grace of God doth not worke alwaies in men immediately, or by extraordinarie waies, but many times worketh by naturall meanes. And it is verie reasonable that <hi>Godfrey</hi> which in holines and religion doth excell all other, and is (as hath bin said) the figure of <hi>Vnderstanding,</hi> be spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially graced and priuiledged with fauours not communicated to any other. This humane wisedome, when it is directed of the supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior or more high vertue, doth deliuer the sensible soule from vice, &amp; therein placeth morall vertue. But bicause this sufficeth not, <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> the <hi>Hermite</hi> first confesseth <hi>Godfrey</hi> &amp; <hi>Rinaldo,</hi> and conuerted <hi>Tancredie. Godfrey</hi> &amp; <hi>Rinaldo</hi> being two persons, which in our <hi>Poem</hi> do hold the principall place, it can not be but pleasing to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that I repeating some of the already spoken things, do particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly lay open the allegoricall sense, which vnder the vaile of their actions, lie hidden. <hi>Godfrey</hi> which holdeth the principall place in this storie, is no other in the Allegorie but the <hi>Vnderstanding,</hi> which is signified in many places of the <hi>Poeme</hi> as in that verse,
<q>
         <l>By thee the counsell giuen is, by thee the scepter rul'd.</l>
      </q>
And more plainly in that other:
<q>
         <l>Thy soule is of the campe both minde and life.</l>
      </q>
And <hi>Life</hi> is added, bicause in the powers more noble, the lesse noble are contained: therefore <hi>Rinaldo,</hi> which in action is in the second degree of honour, ought also to be placed in the Allegorie in the answerable degree: but what this power of the mind, holding the second degree of dignitie is, shall be nowe manifested. The <hi>Irefull</hi> vertue is that, which amongst all the powers of the minde, is lesse estrāged from the nobility of the soule, insomuch that <hi>Plato</hi> (doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting) seeketh whether it differeth from reason or no. And such is it in the minde, as the chiefetaine in an assemblie of souldiours: for as of these the office is to obey their princes, which do giue directions and commandements to fight against their enimies: so is it the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the irefull, warlike, and soueraigne part of the minde, to be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with reason against concupiscence, and with that vehemencie and fiercenes (which is proper vnto it) to resist and driue awaie whatsoeuer impediment to felicitie. But when it doth not obey Reason, but suffers it selfe to be carried of her owne violence, it fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth out, that it fighteth not against concupiscence, but by concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscence, like a dogge that biteth not the theeues, but the cattle committed to his keeping. This violent, fierce, and vnbridled furie, as it can not be fully noted by one <hi>man of warre,</hi> is neuertheles prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally signified by <hi>Rinaldo,</hi> where it is said of him, that being
<q>
         <l>—Aright warrelike knight</l>
         <l>Did scorne by reasons rule to fight.</l>
      </q>
Wherin (whilest fighting against <hi>Gernando,</hi> he did passe the bounds of ciuill reuenge, and whilest he serued <hi>Armida)</hi> may be noted vnto vs, <hi>Anger,</hi> not gouerned by reason: whilest hee disinchanteth the wood, entreth the citie, breaketh the enimies array, <hi>Anger,</hi> directed by reason. His returne and reconciliation to <hi>Godfrey,</hi> noteth <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> causing the <hi>Irefull</hi> power to yeelde to the <hi>Reasonable.</hi> In these Reconciliations two things are signified, first, <hi>Godfrey</hi> with ciuill
<pb facs="5"/>
moderation is acknowledged to be superiour to <hi>Rinaldo,</hi> teaching vs, that Reason commandeth Anger, not imperiously, but curteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and ciuillie: contrariwise in that, by imprisoning <hi>Argillanus</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periously, the sedition is quieted; it is giuen vs to vnderstand, the power of the <hi>Minde,</hi> to be ouer the bodie, regall and predominate: Secondly, that as the reasonable part ought not (for heerein the Stoiks were very much deceiued) to exclude the <hi>Irefull</hi> from acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, nor <hi>vsurpe</hi> the offices thereof, for this vsurpation shoulde bee against nature and iustice, but it ought to make her her companion and handmaid: So ought not <hi>Godfrey</hi> to attempt the aduenture of the wood himselfe, thereby arrogating to himselfe the other offices belonging to <hi>Reinaldo.</hi> Lesse skill should then be shewed, and lesse regard had to the profite, which the Poet, as subiected to policie, ought to haue for his aime, if it had been fained, that by <hi>Godfrey</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, all was wrought, which was necessarie for the conquering of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem. Neither is there contrarietie or difference from that which hath been said, in putting downe <hi>Rinaldo</hi> and <hi>Godfrey</hi> for that figure of the <hi>Reasonable</hi> and of the <hi>Irefull</hi> vertue, which <hi>Hugo</hi> speakes of in his dreame, wheras he compareth the one to the <hi>Head,</hi> the other to the <hi>right Hand</hi> of the army, bicause the <hi>Head</hi> (if we belieue <hi>Plato)</hi> is the seat of Reason, and the <hi>right Hand,</hi> if it be not the seat of wrath, it is at least her most principall instrument. Finally, to come to the conclusion, the army wherein <hi>Rinaldo</hi> and the other Woorthies by the grace of God and aduise of Man, are returned and obedient to their chieftaine, signifieth man brought againe into the state of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Iustice and heauenly obedience: where the superior powers do command, as they ought, and the inferiour do obey, as they should. Then the wood is easily disinchanted, the citty vanquished, the enimies armie discomfited, that is, all externall impediments being easily ouercome, man attaineth the politike happines. But for that this <hi>Politike blessednes,</hi> ought not to be the last marke of a Christian man, but he ought to looke more high, that is, to <hi>Euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting felicitie,</hi> for this cause <hi>Godfrey</hi> doth not desire to win the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ierusalem, to haue therein onely temporall dominion, but bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause heerein may be celebrated the worship of God, and that the Holy sepulchre may be the more freely visited of godly strangers and deuout Pilgrims; and the Poem is shut vp in the praiers of <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey,</hi> it is shewed vnto vs, that the <hi>Vnderstanding</hi> being trauelled and wearied in ciuill actions ought in the ende to rest in deuotion and in the contemplation of the eternall blessednes of the other most happie and immortall life.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>