<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, And truely honorable, SIR ALEXANDER GORDON BARONET, of CLUNIE KNIGHT, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Guild, W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117899_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02358</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12490</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117899</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, And truely honorable, SIR ALEXANDER GORDON BARONET, of CLUNIE KNIGHT, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Guild, W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Popish glorying in antiqvity turned to their shame : Whereby is shewed, how they wrong, villifie, and disgrace, that whereunto they pretend to carry greateste reuerence: and are most guilty of that which they vpbraide vnto others. Collected and proued out of themselues, for the singular profit both of pastors and professors. By William Guild, minister at King Edward</title>
                 <author>Guild, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Allott, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 5-268, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="5" facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, And truely honorable, SIR ALEXANDER GORDON BARONET, of CLUNIE KNIGHT, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ever more subtily inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the <hi>Gibeonits</hi> vnder pretence of olde Furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, &amp; comming from a-farre, to deceiue the Lordes People, nor vnder the like pretence of <hi>Antiquitie</hi> novv, doeth <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels</hi>
      <pb n="6" facs="3"/>
brood intende to doe the same to <hi>Bethels</hi> Children. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more braggingly did ever the carnall <hi>Iewes,</hi> dissenting frō his Faith, yet claime a corporal descent from <hi>Abraham</hi> their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor doe the craftie <hi>Iesuits,</hi> dissenting frō their doctrine, yet claime a full consent vvith orthodox <hi>Antiquitie</hi>: accusing vs of <hi>Noveltie,</hi> as Christs ovvn doctrine, &amp; His Apostles, vvas before vs, that it may be seene true vvhich Sainct <hi>Peter</hi> fore-prophecied of such: to vvit, That in the latter times there should come false prophets,<note place="margin">Marke 1.27. Acts 17.19. 2. Pet. 1.2.</note> vvho privilie should bring in damnable heresies; and by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of vvhome the vvaye of trueth shoulde bee evill spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of.</p>
   <p>While as vve, notvvithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, adhere so to truest <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie,</hi>
      <pb n="7" facs="3"/>
as that consenting vvith <hi>Tertullian,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Te<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>. Apol. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>lt.</hi>
      </note> vvho saith, <hi>Constat id verius esse, quod prius, id prius, quod ab initio, id ab initio, quod ab Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolis,</hi> Is is manifest, that that is truest, which is first; that that is first, which hath bene from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; that that hath beene from the beginning, which hath procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the Apostles; vvee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude vvith <hi>Lyrinensis</hi> vvordes, <hi>Quod it a docemus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Lyrinens. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versiu hereses.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>vt cum dicimus nove, nont amen dicimus nova, &amp; vniversum penitus mundum saeva repentinae haereseos tempestate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culsum, adantiquam fidem, à novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la perfidia, ad antiquam sanitatem, à novitatis vesania, ad antiquam lucem, à novitatis caecitate revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus,</hi> That we so teach, that when wee speake after a new manner, yet notwithstanding wee speake not new things: and we draw back the whole worlde, affrighted with the cruell tempest of sudden heresie,
<pb n="8" facs="4"/>
from recent-broached perfidie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ancient Faith; from the mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of Noveltie, vnto sound An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiqultie; from the darknesse of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veltie, vnto the ancient Light.</p>
   <p>Yet it is no marvell, that as vnder pretence of keeping the lavve made against blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, our Head vvas condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as a blasphemer, by that <hi>Iewish High priest</hi>;<note place="margin">Iohn, 19.7.</note> So vnder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of pleading for <hi>Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> the members be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the <hi>Romane High priest,</hi> as violaters of <hi>Antiquitie.</hi> And as the <hi>Hagarenes</hi> called them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues <hi>Saracenes,</hi> so likevvise that vnder a name contrary to their nature, that <hi>Iesuitish</hi> crue, vvho seeme moste to procure for <hi>Antiquitie,</hi> practize moste against the same.</p>
   <p>This <hi>Pharisaicall</hi> brood being herein (as in other things) like
<pb n="9" facs="4"/>
to their fore-fathers, of vvhom our Saviour <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aith, <hi>Dicūt, sed non faciunt,</hi> They say, but doe not: So these men, (as <hi>Ioab</hi> did to <hi>Abner</hi>) they speake fairlie, but deale most foulie vvith vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Antiquitie</hi>: 1. Rejecting Scripture (vvhich is most pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue to vs, and Gods ovvne mouth) from being sole deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miner in Gods ovvne cause; because it is indeed that breath of consumption to their man of sinne: and, like the Arke, it plagueth those <hi>Philistimes,</hi> and over-throvveth their <hi>Dagon.</hi> Next, vvhen they haue made their recourse frō divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, to humane Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, challenging those ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Fathers of the primitiue Church, as impudentlie to bee altogether on their side, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that Whoore challenged
<pb n="10" facs="5"/>
      <hi>Athanasius,</hi> to be her associate in her filthie Whoordome. Yet notvvithstanding, vvhen they finde that vvherein they repose, so clearly and peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torly to depose against them; no more disdainfully did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>Iewes</hi> reject Christ, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring to Him <hi>Barabbas,</hi> than they reject those Ancients, and their famous testimonies, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring there-vnto the giddie Wine of their inebriating Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors: and regarding them only so farre as they seeme to make for them; as <hi>Elias</hi> sate no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger by <hi>Cherith,</hi> nor <hi>Ionas</hi> vnder the Gourd, than the one flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vved, &amp; the other flovvrished.</p>
   <p>Yea, not only dismisse they them, vvith contempt, vvhen they make not for them; but as the envious man, after the hus<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>band-mans fielde vvas sovvne
<pb n="11" facs="5"/>
vvith good seede, came craftily &amp; quietly there-after, &amp; min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled in his tares: So haue our <hi>Romanists</hi> sundry vvayes sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticated the famous vvorks of the Lords Worthies, eyther by intermingling their language of <hi>Babel,</hi> vvith the language of <hi>Bethel</hi>; and so making their Books lyke a Lincie-vvoolsie Garment: or doing to their paines, as <hi>Hanun</hi> did to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of <hi>Davids</hi> Embassadours, cutting and curtayling them; or els altering their vvords, &amp; vvhere they vvould say <hi>Shibbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth,</hi> making to say <hi>Siboleth.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And as <hi>Paul</hi> vvas accused, for bringing in Strangers and <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> in the Temple, to pollute the same; So most justly may they be accused, for vnjust in bringing of strangers (vvhich are Counterfeits, vnder the
<pb n="12" facs="6"/>
name of Fathers) into the Church of GOD, vvith such fraudfull Forgerie, to corrupt craftily; and inventing vvitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to circumvent vvickedly. And all this they doe for the <hi>Diana</hi> of the Papacie, and supporting of that glorious Whoore of their proude Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie; setting not only a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, vvith <hi>Demetrius,</hi> but the vvhole vvorld in vproare: for (as that silver smith sayd) by that Craft they haue their vvealth: &amp; if the Lords vvord prevaile, they see their Craft is in danger to be set at naught, and <hi>Dagon</hi> vvill surely dovvne before the Arke of GOD.</p>
   <p>The proofe and particulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of vvhat is formerly spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, both in their dealing vvith Fathers, Councels, and Histories, I haue summarily
<pb n="13" facs="6"/>
hereafter digested, &amp; succinctly set dovvn, &amp; dedicate the same to Your Worships Name, as a most vvorthy Patrō &amp; Pattern of Vertue, sincere in the Truth, zealous against Errour, a Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of Policie, a Map of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie, an Honour to Your Name, an Ornament to Your Countrey, &amp; a sole <hi>Moecenas</hi> of Letters amongst Your Equals in this respectlesse and clayie Age: vvhose Name, therefore, justly the Penns of the painful shal perpetuate, propagat your Fame, &amp; cōtinue your memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. And amongst many astri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to your Worship, for your Honorable &amp; vertuous parts, I shall ever approue my selfe</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships in all respectiue duetie, <hi>W. GVILD.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>