<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Middleton, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117690_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01371</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11492</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117690</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Middleton, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A watch-vvorde for warre : Not so new as necessary: published by reason of the disperced rumors amongst vs, and the suspected comming of the Spanyard against vs. Wherein we may learne how to prepare our selues to repell the enemie, and to behaue our selues all the tyme of that trouble. Compendious for the memorie, comfortable for the matter, profitable for the tyme</title>
                 <author>Gibbon, Charles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                    <distributor>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>THE mutabilitie of reports had almost dismaide mee
in proceeding: for one while there runne nothing
but rumors of vvarre, an otherwhile there passe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
speeches of peace; the same mouth that saith at one
time, the Spanyard will come, another time affirmeth, we
neede not expect his comming. There be many that wish
warrs because they cannot thriue with peace, and others
that speak of peace, because they loue not to heare of war;
but (good Reader) as there is no smoke without fire, so
there ariseth no rumor without some original, for rumors
are commonly fore-runners of warre. VVhen tydings of
vvarre were voyced in Iuda, the enemies tarried not long
after; and therefore the speeches which are giuen out of
the Spanyard, may put vs in expectation of his comming;
he which hath made so great preparation for warre, may
be suspected to weight oportunitie to effect his will.</p>
   <p>There were many false Prophets amongst the Iewes,
which perswaded them of peace for some lewd pretence,
when they knew the Assyrians were ready to assault them,
Ierem, 6, 14. I pray GOD there be not some false-harted
subiects amongst vs, that giue out reports of peace for som
ill purpose, when they are perswaded the Spanyard is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching.</p>
   <p>Howsoeuer it be, <hi>dubia timenda,</hi> things doubtful are to
be dreadfull; It is better to liue in feare then security: for
feare maketh vs to flie to God, as <hi>Iehoshaphat</hi> did when he
feared the Moabites to come vpon him, 2, Chro, 20, 3, but
securitie maketh vs forget God, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did when hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained
secure in Ierusalem. 2, Sam, 11. The feare of war
is to be doubted euen in the fruition of peace, for as the
wise-man sayth, There is a time of warre aswell as a time
<pb facs="6"/>
of peace, Eccles, 3, 8. Such euer tast the lesse troubles in
the tempest of warre, which sayle with a martiall foresight
in the calme of peace.</p>
   <p>But admit the Spanyarde hath disperced some part of
his Nauie, or hath some other crosse occasions to hinder
his cōming hether this yere, yet let vs perswade our selues,
that as God made the Amorites and others to be as pricks
and thornes to the Israelits, Iosua, 23, 13, so he hath made
the Spaniard to be as a prick &amp; thorne to Englishmen, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somuch
as we shall neuer bee so assured of peace, but wee
may alwaies liue in suspition of warre: and therefore thys
treatise of warre cannot be friuolous.</p>
   <p>I remember <hi>Cicero</hi> sayth, it is one poynt of policie in
peace to prepare for vvarre; now if outwarde furniture to
defend the body, is expedient to be in preparation, though
there be no vvarre; the inwarde Armour to asist the soule,
cannot be impertinent though there be peace.</p>
   <p>These and some other respects haue mooued me to set
forth this Treatise, considering what <hi>Seneca</hi> saith, <hi>Non vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit
qui nemini viuit,</hi> he liueth not, that liueth to none but
himselfe; therefore I thought it to bee a sinne by concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
which might turne to a more profit by publishing.</p>
   <p>Thus being loth to put any in feare of vvarre, although
it be good policie to suspect it, or in hope of peace when
the Enemie is so busie about warlike preparation, I leaue
the censuring hereof, to such as know best vnder God, and
the successe of both to him that seeth more then any man,
which is the almightie <hi>Iehouah,</hi> whom <hi>Augustine</hi> sayth to
be <hi>Totus oculus,</hi> all Eye, because hee best seeth all things,
whose purpose will take place whatsoeuer we heare,
eyther by flying reports, or by fabulous
prophecies.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>C. G.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>