<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A NECESSARIE aduertisement to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117710_Bo1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19425</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5852</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117710</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A NECESSARIE aduertisement to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>None but Christ, none but Christ : Intimating, that in Him, who is the Lord of Lords, and Prince onely, is to be found, the full and absolute cure of mans misery</title>
                 <author>Cotton, Clement</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>116 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="27"/>
   <head>A NECESSARIE aduertisement to <hi>the Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible truth, that neither a mans person,<note place="margin">Gen 4.4. Rom 8.8. Heb. 11.4. Ioh. 14.6.</note> nor acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, can please God, till himselfe be in Christ; so it is as true,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.5.</note> that a man hath neither ability of himselfe to doe good, or abstaine from euill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, vnlesse hee be as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted by the power of Christ: and this appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, both by the testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Christ himself,
<pb facs="28"/> Ioh. 15.5. For <hi>without me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> yee can doe nothing;</hi> (as also by the testimony of <hi>Paul,</hi> who saith, <hi>that by the power of Christ, he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to doe all things,</hi> Phil 4.13. Implying (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that place of <hi>Iohn</hi>) that without Christs power,<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.5.</note> he could doe nothing.</p>
   <p>Doth the power and strength of corruption then any way annoy thee,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.23.</note> and wouldest thou faine get the masterie ouer the same? flie then foorthwith out of thy selfe, and get thee direct<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly vnto Christ,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.24, 25.</note> and say
<pb facs="28"/> thus vnto him; Lord, thou biddest mee morti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fie al inordinate lusts and affections, as wrath,<note place="margin">Col. 3.5.</note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleannes, couetousnesse, &amp;c. But thou knowest there is no strength in me to mortifie these, nor any corruption of nature besides,<note place="margin">See 2 C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. 20.12.</note> further foorth than I haue assistance from thee:<note place="margin">Phil. 4.13. &amp; 2.13. Rom. 6.6.</note> apply there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to this viciousnesse of my sinfull nature, the vertue of thy precious death and buriall, by the worke of thy holy spirit,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.13.</note> which alone is able to kill sinne in me, that sin and corruption (of what
<pb facs="29"/> nature soeuer) may not as heeretofore rule nor raigne ouer me,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.12.</note> but that wageing battaile still by thy strēgth ther-against, I may yet therein haue peace,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.5</note> and expect the full victory, in the time thou hast appointed.</p>
   <p>Also, wouldest thou heare, reade, meditate, or pray profitably; thinke how insufficient thou art,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.5.</note> as of thy selfe, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme these holy exerci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ses, or any the like, with out<note n="a" place="margin">Whose pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er, in this case, must be perfected in thy weak<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nesse, or it will not be. <hi>2 Cor. 12.9.</hi>
      </note> Christ; but hasten immediately to him, and say, It is meet (Lord) that I doe these duties at
<pb facs="29"/> thy command,<note place="margin">Isai. 55 3. Reu. 1.3. 1 The. 5.17</note> for in mercy thou hast appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them for my good: but without thee,<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.5</note> thou knowest I can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: Oh let me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore feele power and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue (by the worke of thy spirit) as from thy death to mortifie and kill all sinne in me,<note place="margin">Rom 6.5.6 Col. 2 12.</note> so from thy resurrection, both to quicken and enable mee aright to performe all such duties as thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirest of mee, that the power of effecting all good, may alwaies be of thee, and not from mee, 2 Cor. 4.7.</p>
   <pb facs="30"/>
   <p>And yet euen in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard thou requirest of mee as in other things, that as a poore fraile ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssell I should put foorth all the powers of body and soule,<note place="margin">Eccle. 9.10 2 Cor. 7.1. 2 Pet. 1.2.10. Mat. 25 14. 10 30.</note> wherewith thou hast endowed me; the better heereby to serue thy diuine proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Phil. 2.12, 13.</p>
   <p>Now (good Reader) if thou approuest of this aduertisement in thy iudgement, I pray thee giue thy diligence to bring it by degrees but vnto a daily practise (for thou shalt haue need of it daily) and by goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="30"/> experience, thou shalt in the end finde, I hope, that the gaine will counteruaile the paine.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.58. Gal. 6.9.</note>
   </p>
   <div type="part">
      <pb facs="31"/>
      <head>HEREVNTO IS added, three steps to <hi>sound conuersion.</hi>
      </head>
      <div type="section">
         <head>1</head>
         <p>
            <note place="margin">Act. 26.17.18.</note>FIrst, God by his word and spirit, enlighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the vnderstanding of a sinner truely to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the doctrine of mans misery, and of his full recouery by Christ.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
         <head>2</head>
         <p>Secondly, by the same meanes he workes in his heart both such sound sorrow for his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sery, and feruent desire after Christ the remedy,<note place="margin">Act. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>7.</note>
            <pb facs="31"/> that hee can neuer be at quiet, till hee enioy Christ.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
         <head>3</head>
         <p>Thirdly, GOD so manifesteth his loue in freely offering Christ with all his benefits,<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.16.</note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him a poore sinner lost, that thereby hee drawes him in such wise to giue credit vnto God heerein, that hee gladly accepts of Christ offered vnto him.</p>
         <p>These three workes of God, whosoeuer finds to haue bin truly wrought in himselfe; may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by know certainly,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.10</note> that
<pb facs="32"/> hee hath true faith,<note place="margin">Act. 15.9.</note> and therefore sound conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</p>
         <p>Now hauing obtained this mercy at the hands of Almighty God for the merit of Christ;<note place="margin">Col. 1.12. Ephes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.5. Luke 1.74.</note> hee ought in thankefulnesse to him therefore endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour daily euer after,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.11, 12.</note> in his whole conuersation, to expresse and shew forth the vertues of him that hath thus called him out of darknesse,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.9.</note> into his maruellous light.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>