<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>
THE PROEME.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117917_Fr5_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68764</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23041</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117917</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>
THE PROEME.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The theatre of the empire of Great Britaine : presenting an exact geography of the kingdomes of England, Scotland, Ireland, and the iles adioyning: with the shires, hundreds, cities and shire-townes, within ye kingdome of England, divided and described by Iohn Speed</title>
                 <author>Speed, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Hall, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hall, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Humble, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Humble, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sudbury, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sudbury, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 146, that is 280, 10 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), maps (metal cuts), 2째</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="154"/>
   <head>
      <pb n="151" facs="154"/>
THE PROEME.</head>
   <head type="sub">TO THE LEARNED AND LOVERS OF GREAT BRITAINES GLORY.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing thus farre trauelled in the protract, and description of this famous <hi>Empire</hi> of <hi>GREAT BRITAINE,</hi> I might here haue rested, and claimed the priuiledge that yeeres and imbecillitie haue brought me vnto: had not a further desire in others vrged it a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter incident, historically to lay downe the originals of those <hi>Nations</hi> and successions of those <hi>Monarchs,</hi> which either by birth or conquest haue aspired to the <hi>Jmperiall Crowne.</hi> And albeit I finde my selfe both tired in the former, and most vnfit to prosecute this latter, yet will I endeuour to giue herein my best assayes; though as my labours, so my wants also, thereby will be made more vulgar to the world.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Heraclite.</note> For if those men were blame-worthy against whom <hi>Heraclite</hi> exclaimeth, who <hi>with long toile and great trouble finde a little pure substance in a great deale of base earth:</hi> how shall I then free me from the like imputation, that from so many <hi>mines</hi> of pure <hi>met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals,</hi> haue gotten so little <hi>Oare,</hi> and the same neither well tried in my defectiue <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace,</hi> nor yet artificially cast off through the default of the <hi>mould,</hi> wanting both skil for to fashion, and measure to performe, the true proportions that in such a <hi>proiect</hi> is to be required; and how often <hi>these</hi> my <hi>defects</hi> haue disswaded my proceedings, is best knowne to him that is the <hi>searcher of the heart.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But by what <hi>fate</hi> I am inforced still to goe forward, I know not, vnlesse it be the ardent affection and loue to my <hi>natiue Countrey;</hi> wherein I must confesse that <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> in those <hi>gifts</hi> hath bene both liberall, yea and prodigall, though <hi>Fortune</hi> as spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring &amp; fast-handed against me, euer checking the <hi>Bit</hi> with the <hi>Raines</hi> of necessity, and curbing the <hi>meanes</hi> that should illustrate my labours: which moues me some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to thinke that if the great Philosopher <hi>Theophrastus,</hi> had cause on his death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed <note place="margin">Theophrastus.</note>to accuse <hi>Nature, for giuing man so long a lesson, and so short a life;</hi> then I against <hi>Fortune</hi> may as iustly exclaime, that hath assigned me so great a <hi>labour</hi> and so little <hi>meanes.</hi> And therefore let it not seeme offensiue that I draw my <hi>waters</hi> from the <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterns</hi> of others, who am not able to fetch them at the <hi>spring-head</hi> my selfe: Neither that I strike vpon the same <hi>Anuile</hi> vnto their <hi>sound,</hi> though nothing so loud, nor with the like strength; wherein yet this <hi>fruit</hi> at least wil (I hope) redound of my <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours</hi>
      <pb n="152" facs="155"/>
that I shall incite <hi>the more learned:</hi> if not otherwise, yet in emulation of me, to free the <hi>face</hi> drawne by <hi>Apelles,</hi> from the <hi>censure</hi> of the fault or defect in the <hi>foot,</hi> and not onely to amend, but euen to new-mould the whole. Which thing though my <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 19. 35.</note>dayes are neere spent; and with <hi>Barzillai</hi> I may say that <hi>musicke to me is now vnplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Socrates.</note>yet doth my <hi>eare</hi> thirst after the set of that <hi>straine,</hi> as <hi>Socrates</hi> thoughts ranne euer on his Booke: who the night before he was to suffer death, was desirous to learne <hi>musicke,</hi> because <hi>he would die learning still something. Moses</hi> when he foresaw the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of his <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> which whilst it stood, was the glory of the <hi>earth,</hi> and a <note place="margin">
         <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 6. 7.</note>
      <hi>paterne</hi> to all <hi>kingdomes</hi> succeeding, left this for a <hi>Law</hi> among the rest, and euen to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine for euer, that <hi>the fathers should teach their children,</hi> and should <hi>commit vnto wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 32.</note>
      <hi>those things which the Lord in their dayes had done,</hi> and enioyned the <hi>children;</hi> Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise to <hi>enquire of the times that were past, euen from the first creation of man:</hi> For when as <hi>Empires</hi> and <hi>Kingdomes, Common weales</hi> and <hi>Cities,</hi> do end and perish, yet the <hi>Histories</hi> thereof do remaine and liue; And that made <hi>Cicero</hi> to say as he did, <hi>that Salamina</hi>
      <note place="margin">Thales.</note>
      <hi>should be vtterly forgotten, before the things that were done in Salamina should perish:</hi> And therefore as among the wise answeres of <hi>Thales,</hi> the <hi>Histories</hi> of <hi>Countries</hi> are to be <note place="margin">Cicero.</note>accounted for <hi>principals,</hi> either as <hi>Cicero</hi> calleth them the <hi>Mistres of life, and expositions</hi>
      <note place="margin">Simonides.</note>
      <hi>of Times;</hi> so likewise let vs from the <hi>lyricall Poet Simonides</hi> learne this further, That <hi>he</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cassidore.</note>
      <hi>is perfectly happy which knowes his natiue countrey to be truly glorious.</hi> And as <hi>Cassidore</hi> calls him <hi>a worthy Citizen that seeketh the commodity of his countrey:</hi> So contrariwise he is by <note place="margin">Bale in Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeeres gift.</note>
      <hi>Bale</hi> esteemed but a <hi>fruitles clod of earth, that sucks the sappe of his soile onely to himselfe,</hi> whose memoriall shall perish as the dispersed <hi>smoake</hi> in the <hi>clouds,</hi> though for a time he mount aloft in his swelling pride. This naturall <hi>loue</hi> and true <hi>affection</hi> to our <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Countrey,</hi> we may further learne from the ancient <hi>Patriarks</hi> and <hi>Fathers</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, who besides a desire that they had to theirs, continually to liue therein during <note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. 29.</note>life, commanded <hi>their bodies to be buried therein after death:</hi> from whose <hi>Bowels</hi> they first had assumed their <hi>breathes,</hi> and in whose <hi>bosome</hi> they layd their <hi>bones,</hi> as in their last <hi>bed</hi> of rest. Yea, of the vnreasonable creatures, the <hi>Birds</hi> and <hi>Beasts,</hi> we may learne this loue, that alwayes are willing towards their <hi>home.</hi> And if it happen that <hi>Countreys</hi> grow vnkinde as <hi>Homers</hi> did, that in his old age and blind, suffred him to <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ierem.</hi> 37. 1.</note>beg his bread; or that a <hi>Prophet</hi> in his owne <hi>countrey</hi> is not esteemed, as <hi>Jeremy</hi> felt it, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Matt.</hi> 13. 57.</note>and CHRIST IESVS taught, yet did the <hi>one</hi> for his peoples captiuity, <hi>wish his eyes a</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ierem.</hi> 9. 1. <hi>Luke</hi> 19. 41.</note>
      <hi>fountaine of teares,</hi> and the other for his <hi>countreys destruction lamented and wept,</hi> holding <note place="margin">
         <hi>Matt.</hi> 15. 26.</note>
      <hi>it vnlawfull to take the childrens bread, and to giue it vnto others.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>That this our <hi>Countrey</hi> and <hi>subiect</hi> of <hi>History</hi> deserueth the <hi>loue</hi> of her <hi>inhabitants,</hi> is witnessed euen by <hi>forraine writers</hi> themselues, who haue termed it the <hi>Court of Queene Ceres,</hi> the <hi>Granary of the Westerne world,</hi> the <hi>fortunate Island,</hi> the <hi>Paradise of pleasure</hi> and <hi>Garden of God;</hi> whose <hi>Typographicall descriptions</hi> for the whole <hi>Iland,</hi> and <hi>Geographical surueyes</hi> for the seuerall <hi>parts,</hi> exceed any other <hi>kingdome</hi> vnder the cope of <hi>Heauen;</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Habak.</hi> 2. 9.</note>that onely excepted which was <hi>conquered</hi> and <hi>diuided</hi> by <hi>Josuah;</hi> And for <hi>fruitfulnes</hi> and <hi>temperature</hi> may be accounted another <hi>Canaan;</hi> watered <hi>with riuers that doe cleaue</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Gene.</hi> 13. 10.</note>
      <hi>the earth,</hi> as the <hi>Prophet</hi> speaketh, and make the land as rich and <hi>beautiful, as was that of Aegypt.</hi> Our <hi>Kings</hi> for <hi>valour</hi> and <hi>Sanctity,</hi> ranked with the <hi>worthiest</hi> in the <hi>world,</hi> and our <hi>Nations originals, conquests,</hi> and <hi>continuance,</hi> tried by the <hi>touch</hi> of the best <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi>
      <note place="margin">Tho. Lanquet.</note>testimonies, leaue as faire a <hi>Lustre</hi> vpon the same <hi>stone,</hi> as doeth any other, and with any <hi>nation</hi> may easily contend (saith <hi>Lanquet)</hi> both for <hi>antiquity,</hi> and <hi>continuall inhabitants, from the first time that any of them can claime their originals.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And although our many <hi>Records</hi> are perished by the <hi>inuasions</hi> of <hi>strangers,</hi> through their couetous <hi>Conquest</hi> of so <hi>faire a Land;</hi> or in the <hi>ciuill dissensions</hi> of <hi>homebred aspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers</hi> that haue sought the possession of so <hi>rich a Crowne,</hi> yet <hi>Truth</hi> hath left vs no lesse beholding vnto <hi>her,</hi> then <hi>mightier Nations,</hi> and <hi>them</hi> that would be far more <hi>famous.</hi>
      <pb n="153" facs="155"/>
Neither is it to be wondred at, that the <hi>Records</hi> of GREAT BRITAINE are <hi>eaten vp with Times teeth,</hi> as <hi>Ouid</hi> speakes, when as in <hi>Times ruines</hi> lye buried their <hi>Registers,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ouid. Metam. lib. 15.</note>that haue bene kept with a stronger <hi>guard,</hi> as <hi>Titus Liuy</hi> in the entrance of his <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story</hi> affirmeth of the <hi>Romanes.</hi> As <hi>for those things</hi> (saith he) <hi>as are reported either before, or at the foundation of the City more beautified and set out with Poets fables, then grounded vpon pure and faithfull reports, J meane neither to auerre nor disproue.</hi> Of whose <hi>vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties,</hi> let vs a while heare the <hi>reporters</hi> themselues speake, before we proceed to the certaine <hi>successions</hi> of our <hi>British Monarchs:</hi> vntill which time the <hi>credit</hi> of our <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story</hi> may wel be said to <hi>waigh with</hi> (if not <hi>downe peize)</hi> many <hi>others. 틀arro</hi> (that lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Romane writer,</hi> who liued an <hi>hundred yeeres</hi> before the birth of our <hi>Sauiour Christ)</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <p>Histories vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine to the Flood, and from the Flood to the first Olympias fabulous.</p>
         <p>Plutarch.</p>
      </note> calleth the first <hi>world</hi> to the <hi>Flood vncertaine;</hi> and thence to the first <hi>Olympias fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous:</hi> Because in that time (saith he) <hi>there is nothing related (for the most part) but fables among the Greekes, Latines, and other learned Nations.</hi> And therefore <hi>Plutarch</hi> begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the <hi>liues</hi> of his <hi>worthy men,</hi> no higher then <hi>Theseus:</hi> because (saith he) <hi>what hath bene written before, was but of strange things, and sayings full of monstrous fables imagined and deuised by Poets, which are altogether vncertaine and most vntrue.</hi> And <hi>Diodorus Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus</hi>
      <note place="margin">Diodorus Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus.</note>(that liued in <hi>Augustus Caesars</hi> time, a great searcher after <hi>Antiquities,</hi> and for <hi>thirty yeeres</hi> continuance a traueller into many <hi>Countreys,</hi> for information and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther satisfaction) writing his <hi>History</hi> called <hi>Bibliotheca,</hi> conteyning <hi>forty Bookes,</hi> and <hi>yeeres</hi> of continuance <hi>one thousand, one hundred thirty and eight,</hi> of his <hi>first sixe</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe giueth this censure in his <hi>Proeme. These Bookes</hi> (saith he) <hi>contayning the Acts of ancient men, before the destruction of Troy, with the ancient Histories aswell of Grecians as Barbarians, are called fabulous:</hi> Which mooued <hi>Lucretius</hi> the Poet to demaund this question.</p>
   <q>
      <l>
         <note place="margin">Lucretius.</note> Cur supra bellum Thebanum &amp; funera Troiae,</l>
      <l>Non alias quondam veteres cecinere Poetae?</l>
   </q>
   <q>
      <l>Why haue not Poets in their workes of fained stories brought,</l>
      <l>Things done before the Warres of Thebes, or Troyes destruction wrought?</l>
   </q>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Thucydides.</note> Yea and of <hi>Troyes</hi> story it selfe, if we may beleeue <hi>Thucydides</hi> (whom <hi>Bodine</hi> commendeth for an <hi>absolute Historian) though it be ancient</hi> (saith he) <hi>yet a great part</hi>
      <note place="margin">Tully.</note>
      <hi>thereof is fabulous.</hi> And <hi>Tully</hi> out of <hi>Plato</hi> complayneth of as much: <hi>For you Grecians</hi> (saith he) <hi>as children in learning, deliuer onely things vncertaine, and haue mingled fables with the Warres of Thebes, and of Troy, things (perhaps) which neuer were, but gathered out of the scattered 틀erses of Homer and others, not digested by Aristarchus, and are yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine and obscure.</hi> And that the <hi>Greekes</hi> indeed were but <hi>babes</hi> in <hi>Antiquity, Jose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iosephus contra Appion. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
      </note>in his Nations defence against <hi>Appion,</hi> sufficiently doth proue, where he affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, That <hi>the inuention of their Letters was not so old as the siege of Troy,</hi> insomuch that <hi>the Poesie of Homer</hi> (then the which there is none more ancient among them) <hi>was not</hi>
      <note place="margin">M. Cato in a fragment of his.</note>
      <hi>committed to writing, but sung by roate.</hi> And the <hi>Latine</hi> tongue it selfe by <hi>M. Cato</hi> is said, not to haue <hi>bene in vse foure hundred and fifty yeeres before the building of Rome.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Titus Liui.</note>And <hi>Titus Liuy</hi> their famous <hi>Historian,</hi> freely confesseth, That <hi>the vse of Letters and learning among the Romanes, was rare and hard to be found before the taking of Rome by the Gaules.</hi> Yea, and of the <hi>vncertainty</hi> of <hi>Romes</hi> foundation, how lauish so euer <hi>Histori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> haue written, not onely <hi>Fenestella</hi> hath continued whole <hi>Pages,</hi> but <hi>Plutarch</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <p>Fenestella.</p>
         <p>Plutarch in the life of Romulus.</p>
      </note> likewise in the life of <hi>Romulus,</hi> hath many <hi>sayings,</hi> whereof this is one. <hi>The Historio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphers</hi> (saith he) <hi>do not agree in their writings, by whom, nor for what cause the great name of Rome (the glory whereof is blowne abroad through the world) wasfirst giuen vnto it;</hi> some affirming, that the <hi>Pelagians</hi> after they had <hi>runne ouer</hi> a great part of the <hi>world,</hi> lastly stayed themselues in that place where <hi>Rome</hi> was new built, and for their great strength in <hi>Armes,</hi> gaue name to that City <hi>Rome,</hi> which signifyeth <hi>power</hi> in the <hi>Greeke tongue. Other</hi> say, that certaine <hi>Troians</hi> after their siege, in <hi>certaine vessels sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued</hi>
      <pb n="154" facs="156"/>
      <hi>themselues by flight,</hi> and being put into the <hi>Thuscan Sea,</hi> anchored neere to the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Tyber:</hi> whose <hi>wiues</hi> being extremely <hi>Sea-sicke,</hi> through the counsell of <hi>Roma a Lady,</hi> the wisest and worthiest among them, set fire on the whole <hi>Fleete;</hi> whereupon their <hi>husbands</hi> (though sore offended) were inforced to make vse of their present necessity, and neere vnto <hi>Palantium</hi> planted this <hi>City,</hi> whose <hi>fame</hi> presently grew <hi>great,</hi> and in honour of Lady <hi>Roma</hi> named it <hi>Rome;</hi> and from hence they say the custome of <hi>kissing</hi> in <hi>salutations</hi> came, after the example of these <hi>wiues,</hi> who to appease the <hi>husbands</hi> wraths with <hi>smiles</hi> and <hi>imbracings kissed</hi> their mouths. <hi>Some</hi> will haue the name from <hi>Roma</hi> the <hi>daughter</hi> of <hi>Jtalus</hi> and of <hi>Lucaria,</hi> or els of <hi>Telephus</hi> the sonne of <hi>Hercules,</hi> and of the wife of <hi>Aeneas. Others</hi> of <hi>Ascanius</hi> the sonne of <hi>Aeneas. Some</hi> againe from <hi>Romanus</hi> the sonne of <hi>틀lysses</hi> and of <hi>Cyrce,</hi> wil haue it named <hi>Rome. Others</hi> from <hi>Romus</hi> the sonne of <hi>Emathion,</hi> whom <hi>Diomedes</hi> sent thither from <hi>Troy.</hi> There <hi>are</hi> that bring the name thereof from one <hi>Romus</hi> a <hi>tyrant</hi> of the <hi>Latines,</hi> who droue the <hi>Thuscans</hi> out of those parts. And they who thinke that <hi>Romulus</hi> (as that is most generall, and carieth the most likelihood to be <hi>Romes founder,)</hi> do not agree <note place="margin">Thucydides lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
      </note>about his <hi>auncestours,</hi> as more at large in <hi>Plutarch</hi> appeareth. And therefore with <hi>Thucydides</hi> we may well say, <hi>Jt is a hard and difficult matter to keepe a meane in speaking of things, wherein scarsly can be had a certaine opinion of trueth.</hi> And the rather, for that the <note place="margin">
         <p>Iosephus contra Appion. li. <hi>1. Hellanicus.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Acusilaus.</p>
         <p>Diodorus.</p>
         <p>Herodotus.</p>
         <p>Ephorus.</p>
         <p>Timaeus.</p>
         <p>Philistus.</p>
         <p>Callias.</p>
         <p>Thucydides.</p>
         <p>Suetonius in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Caesar. Sect. <hi>55. Tacitus.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>F. Maximus.</p>
         <p>Silenus.</p>
         <p>Antigonus.</p>
         <p>Hierome.</p>
         <p>Dionysius Hal.</p>
         <p>Bodine.</p>
      </note>
      <hi>writers</hi> themselues haue blamed each <hi>others</hi> of <hi>affectation &amp; falshood,</hi> as in <hi>Josephus</hi> we may see; who affirmeth, That <hi>Hellanicus</hi> dissented from <hi>Acusilaus, Acusilaus</hi> with <hi>Diodorus</hi> correcting <hi>Herodotus; Epherus</hi> accused <hi>Hellanicus</hi> of vntrueths; so did <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maeus</hi> reproue <hi>Ephorus</hi> of as much; <hi>Philistus</hi> and <hi>Callias</hi> dissented from <hi>Timaeus</hi> in his History of <hi>Sicily,</hi> and <hi>Thucydides</hi> accounted a lyar by <hi>some. Caesar</hi> is taxed by <hi>Asi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Pollio</hi> (saith <hi>Suetonius)</hi> to be <hi>partiall</hi> in his <hi>Commentaries;</hi> And <hi>Tacitus</hi> by <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> is blamed for vntruths; <hi>Fabius Maximus</hi> is reprehended by <hi>Polybius</hi> for defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiuely writing the <hi>Punicke warres;</hi> and himselfe againe with <hi>Silenus, Timaeus, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigonus, &amp; Hierom,</hi> as much found fault with by <hi>Dionysius Halicarnassaeus,</hi> for writing the <hi>Romane histories so vnperfectly.</hi> And a man may vse the very same speech against <hi>Dionysius,</hi> saith <hi>Bodine. These things</hi> thus standing, let vs giue leaue to <hi>Antiquitie,</hi> who sometimes <hi>mingleth falshoods with truth, to make the beginnings of Policies seeme more honourable:</hi> And whose <hi>power</hi> is farre scrued into the <hi>worlds</hi> conceit, that with <note place="margin">Hierom. in his Prolog. in Iob.</note>
      <hi>Hierome</hi> we may say, <hi>Antiquity is allowed with such generall applause, that knowne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthes many times are pleasing vnto many.</hi> Yet with better regard to reuerend <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Iob.</hi> 8. 8.</note>whom <hi>Jobs opposer</hi> wills vs inquire after, and to our owne <hi>relations</hi> in deliuering their <hi>censures,</hi> let this be considered; That <hi>more things are let slippe, then are comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in any mans writings,</hi> and yet <hi>more therein written, then any mans life</hi> (though it be long) <hi>will admit him to reade.</hi> Neither let vs be forestalled with any preiudicate <hi>opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of the <hi>reporters;</hi> that in somethings may iustly be suspected, or in <hi>affection,</hi> which <note place="margin">Titus Liui. lib. 8.</note>by nature we owe to our <hi>naturall Conntrey;</hi> nor consent (as <hi>Liuie</hi> speaketh) to <hi>stand to the ancientnesse of reports, when it seemeth to take away the certainty of truth.</hi> To keepe a meane betwixt both, my selfe with <hi>Bildad</hi> doe confesse, that I <hi>am but of yesterday, and know nothing,</hi> and therefore wil relate the <hi>originall names</hi> and <hi>Nations</hi> of this famous <hi>Jland,</hi> with the <hi>successions</hi> of her <hi>Monarches</hi> and <hi>Historicall actions,</hi> so farre only as is most approued by the best <hi>Writers,</hi> and will leaue other <hi>clouds</hi> of obscurity to be cleared by the <hi>labours</hi> of a <hi>more learned penne.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>