<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117846_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69089</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4924</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117846</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An excellent and godly sermon : most needefull for this time, wherein we liue in all securitie and sinne, to the great dishonour of God, and contempt of his holy word. Preached at Paules Crosse the xxvi. daye of October, an. 1578 by Laurence Chaderton Batcheler of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Chaderton, Laurence</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barker, Christopher</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>60 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S much reading is a wearines to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> flesh, so there is neither end nor profit, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king many bookes. True wisdome es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheweth both: but the folie of our time neuer ceaseth to write, nether can be satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with reading the new and variable inuētions of men. A fault amongst wise Philosophers much mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked, how much more ought it to be cōdemned &amp; es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewed of al learned Christians? But vaine glory, &amp; desire of popular fame in the writers, &amp; desire of fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy lucre in the Printers, haue stuffed our English studies with many superfluous &amp; vnnecessary books to the great hurt of many good wits, &amp; to the hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of cōstant iudgemēt in the soūdnes of Christiā doctrine. A matter most necessary to be reformed by such as haue receiued authority to this end, that neither our Church, nor cōmon weale shuld be hurt, but rather bettered by the writings of men. For my part, I wish with all my heart, that we had fewer bookes, &amp; greater skill in the old &amp; newe Testament of Christ, wherin are bequeathed vnto vs most hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly &amp; precious Iewels, &amp; legacies of the immortal inheritance: to which most sure word &amp; Testament, if we take heed as vnto a light that shineth in a dark place, we shalbe directed aright in the strait way that leadeth to immortalitie &amp; happines. Now touching this my Sermon, if I did thinke (deare Christian Reader) that it would quench in the mind of any, the desire of hearing the Gospell preached, &amp; not rather inflame their heart, both to hearing &amp; faithful wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, I would rather haue buried it in perpetuall si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, then committed it to writing. But being fully perswaded, that by this meanes y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Lord God in mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye wil bring into the minds of those that heard me, a fruitfull remēbrance of his mighty working by the power of his spirit, at that present, to their singular comfort: I haue in some part satisfied the earnest, &amp; importunat sute of many deare Christians and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb facs="3"/> who did both by letters &amp; word of mouth, after a sort compel me to write it. The summe and effect of al I haue set downe, not in the same words I spake (for the Lord knoweth I neuer writ it and therfore could not) but in other, so plainly as I could for the capacity and vnderstāding of al. I haue added those things, whereof then I could not, partly for lacke of time, partly for other necessary occasiōs, intreat. And albeit mine owne inabilitie in this kinde of writing, wherein I am altogether a stranger, and the feare of the seuere censure of the learned eloquent diuines, did greatly disswade me: yet my earnest desire both to leaue behind me some smal testimonie of my saith, cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, &amp; religion: &amp; also to haue my iudgement tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching faith &amp; workes approued of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> English church, did as it were violētly carie me to this dutiful worke of loue. Now my harty desire is, that this my labour may be acceptably receiued, &amp; louingly expounded of all, &amp; my prayer vnto God is &amp; shalbe, that euery one of vs, according to the measure of the gift of Christ, may be inabled by his spirit, to hold fast the sound doctrine of pure religion, in life and in death, &amp; with al ioy of the holy Ghost sincerely to practise the same, to the glory of Christ, &amp; the edificatiō of his Church. But let no man thinke, that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> reading of this can be half so effectual and profitable to him, as the hearing was, or might be. For it wāteth the zeale of the spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, the attention of the hearer, the promise of God to the ordinary preaching of his word, the mighty &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward working of his holy spirit, &amp; many other thīgs which the Lord worketh most mercifully by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of his glorious Gospel, which are not to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for by reading the written Sermons of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters. Neuerthelesse I trust that he will blesse the reading hereof, to the praise of his owne name, &amp; the cōfort of his Church. To him therefore by Christ be al praise &amp; honour in the Church for euer. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>