<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the godly Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117145_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18707</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5211</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117145</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the godly Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The true trauaile of all faithfull Christians, hovve to escape the daungers of the vvicked vvorld : VVhereunto is added a christian exercise for priuate housholders</title>
                 <author>Chub, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the godly Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F a man shoulde sit stil but a litle while and behold this pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sent last age of the worlde, and viewe the contents of this time,<note place="margin">Catastro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phe.</note> and pawse vpon it with indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent reason. It would in a maner amaze a well setled minde to consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it. But if one shold sit in an open place, wher there is daily concourse to and froe of great multitudes, and should scarse see one sound and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fite man to passe by, would you not thinke it were a crippelled worlde? and that they hadde beene among mighty enimies in a daungerous skyrmish? Surely if we consider the whole parts of a man, and weigh in conscience that he should consist of godlines, reason, and vertue, and do find that either the spirituall aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, or the worldly consort, hath
<pb facs="4"/> so grappled &amp; battelled, that some are become Heteroclites, and some Monsters. It is a very hard thing in this last age to finde a sound and perfit man, but that in one or other of these former partes hee seemeth to haue a defect, and that is percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the common society of man. For wherin wee ought to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate one with the other in godly exercises and heauenly councell we iarre, we vary, we disdaine, we enuy, backbite, and slaunder one an other yea of the same profession and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as though we were straungers to each other, and fauters to our ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uersaries, and I haue founde them most busie to speake behinde a mans backe, that haue had neuer a worde to his face, nay neuer a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter but by heeresay and surmise. I sorrow to heare it, I sigh to knowe it, and I desire God to amend it, for I dreade me in these daies in the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest Rose is sonest found a Canker.</p>
   <p>Reason that in times past hath
<pb facs="4"/> beene taken for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>age Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> in the common wealth, and a gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour as well of naturall as of morall yea and oeconomicall matters, and hath beene distributed into diuers degrees for their direction, and in all sortes of people she hath beene ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunced to the highest woman, and without the which, neither the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of a common wealth hath beene any thing worth at all, neither with out it hath man beene esteemed as a man, now she is abased like and old schoolemaster that hath taught ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good schollers, in the ende com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to teache one the poore A. B. C. For whereas shee hath beene a publique teacher of all men, both for counsell, comfort, and helpe, nowe she teacheth men to looke to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, and if they will be wise, to loue their owne selues, and to care for their owne selues, in so much, that all her schollers are become in a manner singular fellowes, neither imparting to others, neither com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating
<pb facs="5"/> with others, and yet it is a lamentable matter to see those whom they so councell, if they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe it, they are nowe called snud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and pigges, that erewhile were called beggers and bankrupts.<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uo tene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> vultus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>tantem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>tea no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> A pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull worlde, to see such a forcible doctrine, where is the lawe of God, which commaundeth all not one? <hi>Loue God, and thy neighbour as thy self</hi> where is the Law of nature? which giueth generall commaundement, <hi>Fac aliis fieri quod cupis ipse tibi.</hi> Doe to others as thou wouldest be done vnto. Where is S. Paules counsel? <hi>Doo good vnto all men,</hi> VVhat is there become of Tullies sentence? <hi>Non nobis sed patriae nati sumus.</hi> wee are not borne for our selues but for our Country. In times past, wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was accounted of, at this time wealth &amp; they that haue it, be they neuer neuer so bare and base serue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges are best esteemed, the time may come, that a man may bee had in reputation, in meane tyme, Gods
<pb facs="5"/> wyll be doone, <hi>et caetera infinita.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine if wee beholde vertue conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her noble beauty and shape, &amp; that she was a singuler braunch and member to sette foorth and adorne man, howe she is now disfigured, &amp; dismembred and defaced with infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite actions of vice, it is pittifull to see that her ornaments, namely Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, temperancy, chastity, equity, trueth, pitty, charity and such like &amp;c. are quite cut of, and the twigges little esteemed. I feare me where the mighty boughes are so often and so vnseasonably cut of, in the ende, they will hazard the whole tree and stocke, God of his mercye preserue his little flocke.</p>
   <p>For thy better preseruation (good Reader) I haue heere composed a small peece of worke,<note place="margin">The Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> in the which I haue breefely layd downe the suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient suruey of a Christian. And first he shall see himselfe what he is naturally, what sin reigneth in him. How it is nourished, howe many
<pb facs="6"/> greeuous enimies he hath by reason of sin, last of all the ease and remedy he hath against the force of sinne. VVhich I haue doone, the rather because I see a great many Trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers in opinions, and some ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rech themselues, and some ouerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor them selues, which is more for want of wit, then for lacke of wyl. And for that I pitty their weary &amp; vnprofitable trauell, doo in Christes name inuite them to this Harbour, as the best preparation I haue for mine owne part to entertaine them, beseeching the Lorde to giue them knowledge, iudgement, and a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry desire. It is but shortly compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, because it shall not bee loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some and chargable vnto thee gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Reader, a small almes is inough for this hard world. Reade it ouer with discretion, and where thou findest any thing toothsome, take it as thankfully, as I bestow it hartily, and if thou hap with any grosse or vnsauerye matter, passe it ouer as
<pb facs="6"/> freendly as I shall take it sorrowful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and if thou be one of them that loue me, thou wilt take it howsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it be, in good part, but if thou be one of them that of late condemned me of Idlenes, <hi>I</hi> sorrow no more to be slaundered, then thou dost shame to be deceiued, and yet as charitye bindeth mee, <hi>I</hi> wyll pray for thee, and byd thee hartily farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>