<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO The right wor∣shipfull, Sir Robert Heath Knight, his Maiesties Attorney Ge∣nerall: Grace and all good blessings from God the Father, and our Lord Iesus Christ.</title>
           <author>Bostock, Peter</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117350_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16479</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3395</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117350</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO The right wor∣shipfull, Sir Robert Heath Knight, his Maiesties Attorney Ge∣nerall: Grace and all good blessings from God the Father, and our Lord Iesus Christ.</title>
                 <author>Bostock, Peter</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The saints solace: or, The condition, and consolation of the saints in the earth : Deliuered in certaine sermons at Eatonbridge in Kent. By the minister there</title>
                 <author>Bostock, Peter</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bostock, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 234 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO The right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull, Sir <hi>Robert Heath</hi> Knight, his Maiesties Attorney Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall: Grace and all good blessings from God the Father, and our Lord Iesus Christ.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Worshipfull:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat <hi>the Elders of the Iewes</hi> vnto Iesus Christ,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> of the Centurious loue <hi>vnto their Nation</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">Luk 7.5.</note> might bee said vnto all, of your loue
<pb facs="3"/> and care of our <hi>Eaton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge;</hi> where by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme you were initiated, and whereof the spirituall <hi>wealth</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Esth. 10.3</note>, you haue earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sought, both by your owne bountie, and other annuall pensions procured by you, from your worthy friends *, and worshipfull alliance in the adiacent parts, vnto the Minister, which should bee there resident, to <hi>edifie</hi> the people on the <hi>most holy faith.</hi> It is not to be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of any, how you began to honour God, whew he began to honour you, and how hee hath gone on, in honouring you, as you haue him: If
<pb facs="3"/> any should, I cannot, nor will forget your great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse extended towards me (of all the Lords seruants the least and vnworthiest) since you first saw me: your counsell, countenance, and encouragement after my first entrance into that <hi>Cure,</hi> (now eleuen yeares past:) and lately your power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hand stretched out, in the happie strength thereof, to saue mee from the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of them that would haue<note n="c" place="margin">Psal. 57.3.</note> swallowed mee vp; are (if I would ingratefully be silent) most euident testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies to the vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding world. And yet vnto
<pb facs="4"/> all these (as if all these were small in your sight) it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed you afterwards to adde other fauours, when you tooke me to your house, and sent mee home, not emptie, but full of comfort and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in the worke of the Ministerie, for the time to come. As <hi>Dauid</hi> vnto the Lord, I might say vnto you; <hi>Is this the manner of man</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">2 Sam. 7.19.</note>? <hi>What shall I render vnto you, for all your benefits towards mee?</hi> My selfe I owe you, and such as <hi>I haue giue I you;</hi> These few impolished papers: But what are these? of which the acceptation
<pb facs="4"/> will be the augmentation of my debt: or why these, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than some other of my labours is that place, which some haply iudge (if I would needs to it) more worthy the presse? <hi>Nothing but pressure (God is wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse) brought me to the presse:</hi> and these (being mine immediate Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons after the Commence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my <hi>terrible trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> and the fruits of those sorrowes, or sorrowfull thoughts, which were then, in my soule) would (as I thought) vnto the people of God be acceptable; as is, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God himselfe; the <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="5"/> spirit, the broken and contrite heart</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">Psal. 51.17</note>.</p>
   <p>Nothing else, Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull but these rude lines, (which, in the dayes of my trouble, I found by enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in <hi>the Sanctuarie of God,</hi> or otherwise by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, meditation, obserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and experience,) haue I <hi>(Me penes)</hi> to present vnto you: but for you, and your honoured family, <hi>all prayers and supplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the spirit,</hi> I will (as my daily sacrifice) offer vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>golden altar</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">Reuel 8.3.</note>, vnto him who <hi>regardeth,</hi> and <hi>despiseth not the prayer of the destitute</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">Psal. 109.17</note>. The
<pb facs="5"/> Lord blessed you and assist you in your high calling: The Lord giue you the price of that other <hi>high calling of God in Christ Iesus</hi>
      <note n="h" place="margin">Phil. 3.14</note>, for which with all Saints you <hi>presse vnto the mark: The Lord make you fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in Bethlehem, and alwayes to doe worthily in Ephratah</hi>
      <note n="i" place="margin">Ruth. 4.11</note>. <hi>The Lord increase you more and more: you and your children. Blessed bee yee of the Lord which made Heauen and earth</hi>
      <note n="k" place="margin">Psal. 115.14, 15.</note>. Thus recommending this little booke, with my selfe the poore Author thereof, vnto your implored Patronage
<pb facs="6"/> and Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ection, I craue par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for my boldnesse, and rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Worships euer, and in all dutie bounden,</hi> Peter Bostock.</signed>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Eatonbridge,</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>Iune 7<seg rend="sup">th</seg>.</hi> Anno Salutis, <hi>1630.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>