<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Broade, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117363_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16916</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3807</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117363</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Broade, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A touch-stone for a Christian : Wherein is shewed, how a man may know, whether he be the Temple of the Holy Ghost, hath a sauing faith, be the childe of God, hath truly repented, and (in one word) be a Christian in deed, or in name onely. By Thomas Broade</title>
                 <author>Broad, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <publisher>Bradwood, Melchisidec.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haviland (Haveland), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 156, 4, 4, 101, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuch as all men al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most perswade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, that they are led by the Spirit of God, and are indeed Christs faithfull Disciples: howso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the Spirit hath spoken euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; <note place="margin">1. Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> that in the latter times iniquitie shall abound; and Christ himselfe complaining of these daies, hath said, <note place="margin">Luk. 18.</note>
      <hi>When the Sonne of man commeth, shall he finde faith on the earth?</hi> I haue therfore thought it labour not ill bestowed, if I could teach thee (gentle Reader) how thou mightest know, and not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued,
<pb facs="6"/> whether thou art indeede such a one, as most men vainly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine themselues to be. If thou art a strong Christian, I need not teach it thee, as one that knoweth it already. But I haue written for the weake Christians sake, that he might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue comfort, and be strengthned heereby: as also that the carelesse Christian awaking out of his sleepe of securitie, <note place="margin">Ephes. 5.</note> and standing vp from the dead, Christ might giue vnto him the light of his holy Spirit.</p>
   <p>Now, whereas this my discourse is not fraught with out landish words, and filed phrases, such as are in great request amongst many: if by my plainnesse I shall bee offensiue vnto any, my Apologie for my selfe is briefly thus. <note place="margin">Act. 18.</note> Apollos was an elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent man, as Saint Luke testifieth of him: and I see very many in all places, which in this point hold of Apollos. <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.</note> Paul shewed no such elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, as he himselfe saith of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe:
<pb facs="6"/> and it were not (I thinke) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse, that some in some places should hold of Paul also. And then, if Paul doth first plant, and Apollos afterward with his sweet showres of eloquence doth water; there is great cause to hope, that God will giue greater increase, than hitherto hee hath done in many places. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, there are too few in these daies which hold of Paul. Either we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not plant, nor teach the plaine truth plainly: or if we can, straight we goe to watering, and striue to shew our eloquence. But God of his mercie send vs some such as Paul into his vineyard, which may plant, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour more than they all: for vnlesse planting goe before watering, this kind of watering shall doe little good; <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> especially seeing not many wise men after the flesh, but God hath chosen the foolish things of the world to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the wise.</p>
   <p>Surely, when I first left the Ʋni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersitie,
<pb facs="7"/> before I might publikely so doe, I beganne to instruct some pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately: and it is altogether incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, how hardly they receiued euen milke, giuen also in the most easie and familiar manner that I could deuise. Since this time I haue bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den eloquence farewell: and mine only endeuour, and earnest praier, hath beene; that I might truly say with the Apostle, <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Cor. 11.</note>
      <hi>Though I bee rude in speaking, yet am I not so in knowledge.</hi> I hold of S. Paul▪ I would be exceeding plaine: for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, I seeke not to please thee with newfangled words and curious phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, whereby I should become a Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barian vnto some; <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Cor. 14.</note> but to haue thee please God with thy good works and plaine dealing, that so thou maist be accounted a good Christian of all. Bring not then any such mind to the reading of this Treatise: but seeing it teacheth a matter of greatest mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in these our carelesse daies,
<pb facs="7"/> reade it with good deliberation, ad in any wise beware of flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thy selfe. Truly, if thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest make a good vse heereof, I nothing doubt, but ere it were long, thou shouldest learne one good les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, which many great Doctours shall neuer bee able to learne; namely, that thou thy selfe shalt be saued. Happie is hee that hath learned this lesson perfectly, and by heart: it will not a little reioice that mans heart euer after. This happinesse (gentle Reader) God of his mercie will grant vnto thee, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse thou art mercilesse towards thy selfe, and louest thine owne mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Account it as a sure token of Gods goodwill, whensoeuer he brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth a good booke vnto thine hands: and if thou wouldest not haue this token of his good will become a meanes of his greater displeasure, reade attentiuely, meditate dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently,
<pb facs="8"/> pray continually. Reade, meditate, pray, and God shall giue a blessing.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell.</salute>
      <signed>Thomas Broade.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>