<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Carter, Bezaleel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117382_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18048</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4692</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117382</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Carter, Bezaleel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Christ his last vvill, and Iohn his legacy : In a sermon preached at Clare in Suffolke, by Bezaleel Carter preacher of the word of God at Canham neere to Saint Edmunds Bury</title>
                 <author>Carter, Bezaleel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Blackmore (Blackamore), Edward</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 86 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, it came to passe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I had furnished my selfe my selfe with matter for another congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (while these meditations follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing were fresh in my memory) that I rode through the towne where this Sermon was preached, being then the lecture day: and as God disposed of things, at that time disapointed of a sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply: what needs multitudes of words, my selfe was reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted by the carefull Pastor of that place, to speake to the people; perswasion ouercame me; but the Sermon finished, it is admirable to consider how many mouthes were ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned against me, some said that I was mis-informd against the place, other sayd that I was an hatefull enemy to such as are called professors, all concluded that I was a man of a turbulent spirit: the report of that I should speake passed with swiftnesse from man to man, molehills were made mountaines, moates were made beames: some that heard me defamed came, and louingly conferred with me: others (and such as should haue beene more charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) did not onely heare reports, but ranne current with the rest▪ trumpetting foorth what they heard, in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamest manner. Now whether there is a iust cause of offence giuen, let him iudge that reads ouer this following Discourse, which I wrote out (hearing my selfe to bee so
<pb facs="4"/> traduced) I will not say verbatim, forasmuch as my manner is not to write out all I speake, and when I haue it perfectly by heart to repeate it <hi>syllabice</hi> according as I wrote it, but as neere as I could remember (my Authors names excepted which are written in the Margent) I wrote out the same words that I preached, without take<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away or adding: onely I haue added somewhat to the sixe and twentyeth verse, that I had thought to haue vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged but could not for want of time, and I haue now ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed some of my obseruations of the 26. verse, that I then raysed out of the 27. verse, as that one where chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are commanded to honour and maintaine their parents, supplying their necessities: that other of aflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, how one crosse followes another as one waue wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes in the necke of another, &amp;c. which may be raysed naturally out of either verse the maner of handling both in preaching and writing, was the same. I know that se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall men haue seuerall aymes in printing euen as in preaching, some haue one end, some another, some preach out of lucre, others out of enuy, others out of good will. <hi>Phil. 1. 15.</hi> So in printing, some print out of malice, that they may spit out their poyson in their faces that haue dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleased them, others out of ostentation and vaineglory, like the builders of Babell to get a name. For my part I dare ayme at no other end then the aduancement of Gods glory, and the satisfaction an edification of the Church: should I ayme at mans prayse, I know I should misse of mine end, and loose my reward with God: should I ayme at reuenge, and stuffe my Booke with scoffes and froathy inuectiues, (as too many doe that write controuersies, maintaining their assertions with scoffes and taunts, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then by reason and argument) I should but disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="4"/> malice, and doe that that I must bewayle with teares, or haue my portion with the scorners. God knowes that I haue another end, and a better, <hi>viz.</hi> the satisfaction of many, and the edification of all. In others of my labours I haue seene the fruits, who knowes whether God will also blesse me in this. If such as make a trade of traducing others (shall notwithstanding that I haue sayde) yet fall a iudging and condnēing me, God I prayse him that I passe not for mans iudgement, neither doe I iudge my selfe, hee that iudges me is God, iudge nothing before the time. So be thou findest these laoburs aduantageous to thee, blesse God, pray for the Author, that ceaseth not to pray for thee, remaining</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Iesus Christ, Bezaleel Carter.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>