<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117091_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11922</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22235</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117091</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first booke of architecture, made by Sebastian Serly, entreating of geometrie. Translated out of Italian into Dutch, and out of Dutch into English</title>
                 <author>Serlio, Sebastiano</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Peake, Robert 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>3, 13, 1, 2, 26, 1, 1, 73, 71, 1, 16 leaves, illustrations (woodcuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Art and architecture</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="46"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough diuers Authors write many strange things touching Architecture, as the Egyptians, the people of Asia and Grecia, with diuers other nations, and haue left them for our example, so that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them, we may sufficiently satisfie our cares, and fill them with the greatnesse thereof, that is, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the length, bredth and depth, that certaine places haue contained; yet we can not satisfie our eyes, nor the desire we haue to see such incredible works, vnlesse it had beene our hap to haue the contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, for that the reliques of such works are almost, or for the most part vtterly defaced; or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse we might haue seene them drawne in propertion vnto our eyes, as in this Booke we may not onely read, what the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes at the last, after other nations had built, but also the same Authors haue set downe vnto vs in Figure (as you may see them here) piece by piece not only how many rods, ells feet &amp; palmes, but also the minutes thereof, and what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pas they contained, all perfectly described. And although it was no part of my intent, to translate this Booke of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquities of Rome into our mother tongue, regarding the barrennesse of our language; or peraduenture such as studie or fauour the same, are all too few to defray my charges therein: yet I haue not refrained to doe it, being thereunto com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled by the great works of the forification of the City of Andwerp, and other great places; and for this cause specially, that euery man that wondreth at the greatnes thereof, which was made with most great cost &amp; charges, may hereby see and consider, yea how much greater, &amp; needles charges (to be compared vnto this) the Romanes (not speaking of other nation) haue in time past bestowed, in making of Obelisces, Piramides, Thermes, Theaters, Amphitheaters, tryumphant Arches, and many more such like things, which serued only for pleasure &amp; tryumph: whereby it is to be presumed, that they would haue made the fortifications of such Cities or Townes, made for the safety of the Land, far better then they now are. Now it is to be noted, that all, whatsoeuer the Romanes haue made, doth not wholly agree with <hi>Vitruuius</hi> rules, so that many which haue counterfeyted these, and such like peeces of worke, haue thereby beene abused and deceiued: for some would hardly beleeue, that in those dayes (as well as at this time) all maner of workemen were one better then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which many, vnawares and vnskilfully do many things, which good Antiquities would willingly not suffer, hereof they shall find good instructions in this Booke (and they may learne, if they will read it) how to discerne good from bad; whereunto the former printed fourth Booke is specially made: for in it the whole quantity of the measures is contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as in the Epistle of the sayd Booke it is promised. So in this third Booke, you shall not onely find, first the Ichnographia, and then after the Orthographyes, with part of the Sciographies of the most famous Antiquityes of Rome, Italy, and some of other places, but also of the most excellent buyldings in our dayes, specially those that are made by <hi>Bramant.</hi> So that the Reader being well instructed in the aforesayd fourth Booke, where all the Orders are well set foorth and declared, he may of himselfe iudge what is well or ill made, that at one time a man may, without any further labour, make a good and incorrigible peece of worke.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>