<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE IVDICIOVS READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117540_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18391</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4959</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117540</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE IVDICIOVS READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Mr. Pilkinton his Parallela disparalled : And the Catholicke Roman faith maintained against Protestantisme. By Ant. Champney Sorbonist, and author of the Manuall of Controuersies, impugned by the said Mr. Pilkinton</title>
                 <author>Champney, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Boscard, Charles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Heigham, John (Roger)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>220, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="8" facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE IVDICIOVS READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the yeare 1614. (good reader) I put forth in print at the request of a friend, a briefe Enchiridion or Manuall of controuersies, proouinge the Catholike faith in 38. seuerall heades of controuersie by the text of holy Scripture it selfe; which contayninge but onlie seauen sheetes of paper, Mr. Richarde Pilkinton, who stileth himselfe doctor of Diuinitie, after fower whole yeeres, pretendeth to answre, and for that purpose hath sett forth a booke of fiftie sheetes thinkinge to couer by multitude of wordes, that which with force of argument he could not impeache nor make obscure. His booke came but to my handes the last of Februarie this present yeere, when I was both indisposed in my health, &amp; had newlie receiued a command from those who could commaunde me, to transporte myselfe from Paris, where then I liued, to Douay. So that vntill the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of May, I could not begin to thinke seriously of any reply to him, thoughe I had in the meane while runne ouer some parte of his booke, and alsoe noted some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge therein to that purpose. Where Mr. Pilkinton may peraduenture say as he saith of the Manuall, <hi>that it well appeareth to haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>e in haste, and yett not in such shorte</hi>
      <pb n="9" facs="5"/>
      <hi>tyme but another might well haue made diuers such replies in the same space; as Apelles answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to one, who sheweinge him a picture, and sayinge he had made it in one day:</hi> But be ytt that Mr. Pilkintons witt and dexteritie, coulde haue performed much more in the same tyme, yett I confesse that mine coulde doe noe better; the other imployments wherein the greatest parte of my tyme is taken vpp, lyinge vppon me. Neither doth Mr. Pilkinton neede much to bragge of his dexteritie and expedition in this kinde; seeinge he hath bestowed fower whole yeeres or verie neere in answereinge only seauen sheetes of paper, and that also so shallowly and seelily, that there is much lesse difficultie to refute his aunswere, then to Coppie out or transcribe his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. I haue replyed to all he saith as it lyeth in his booke so farr as I goe with him, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge his owne wordes, least he shoulde complayne of ill dealinge, as if somethinge of moment were lefte vntouched; And both he and the reader may likewise vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstande, that I might with as much faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie haue refuted the rest of his booke, had it been either necessarie or proffitable to haue bestowed the labour in transcribinge it, and cost in printinge it. I would wishe thee good reader to take speciall notice of the preface, which may serue thee as a key not only to this small treatise, but also to
<pb n="10" facs="6"/>
other workes of greater moment, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally to all controuersies. In the answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reinge whereof as Mr. Pilkinton hath been more laborious, so hath he also shewed himselfe more impertinent and peruerse. Reade the whole with attention if thy lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure will permitte thee, and compare dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentlie his proofes and myne together, &amp; after doe not spare to giue thy Censure thereon as thou shalt thinke good in gods name. And if thou receiuest anie proffit by my small labour, I shall thinke it well bestowed, and as fullie recompensed as I expect or desire in this worlde. God euer keepe thee and me also. This first of Iuly. 1619.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>