<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE TO the Reader.</title>
           <author>Holland, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117101_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68204</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13589</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117101</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE TO the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Holland, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Spirituall preseruatiues against the pestilence. Or Seuen lectures on the 91. Psalme : First printed in Anno. 1593. And now reuised, corrected, and published, as generally for the instruction of ignorant people: so specially for the confirmation of the weake seruants of Iesus Christ; descibing the most diuine and most soueraigne preseruatiues against the pestilence. By H. Holland. Hereunto is added a sweete prayer of M. R. Greenhams, neuer before published</title>
                 <author>Holland, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 <publisher>Browne, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jackson, Roger.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Thomas 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 194, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE TO the Reader.</head>
   <p>WE may well say (good Reader) of the men of this age, as Christ &amp; his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet spake of the people of their times: their eyes are shut and see not, their eares are heauie <note place="margin">
         <p>Mat. <hi>13. 14. 15.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Esa. <hi>6. 9.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>Fat things want sense and feeling.</hi>
         </p>
      </note> and heare not, their hearts are fat and feele not. Ignorant people swarm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> in all places, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing eyes and cannot see how the Lords iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are threatned, and otherwhiles most iust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fall vpon them: They stop their eares from the Gospell, they can at no hand be charmed to any sincere obedience to it, such effeminate, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate, and itching eares, as will not heare the charmer, charm he neuer so wisely. Their harts are fat, they cannot vnderstand how leaue their soules are, &amp; how emptie of all good graces, &amp; how stuffed &amp; farced full of rotten &amp; vnsaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie sinnes in towne &amp; country. What ignorance and blindnesse, what insidelitie and prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, what pride &amp; idlenesse, what gluttony and drunkennesse, what whoredome &amp; vncleannes, what deceit and lying, what blasphemies and all cursed speaking, what riot and all maner of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse, do raigne in most places?</p>
   <p>For these sinnes &amp; the like, many iudgements are fallen, and we haue yet escaped them. The
<pb facs="7"/>
Lords hand striueth to chasten vs, &amp; not to cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume vs: miserable people cāhear whē their bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies speak, but cānot heare whē God doth speak. Your sinnes cause the pestilence, the pestilence in time wil breed famin, great wants and penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie among you. The Lord giue you eyes to see, eares to heare, and hearts to vnderstand.</p>
   <p>Make hast to reform your selues first, &amp; then to your families. Teach &amp; correct your vnruly seruants, keepe them frō theaters and other ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominatiōs, bring them to sermons more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, teach and correct your children for lying, swearing, &amp; blasphemies. Teach al your family the holy grounds of religion, the feare of the Lord, for so ye are bound to do: if ye doubt of <note place="margin">
         <p>Deu. <hi>6. 7. 8. 9.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Gen. <hi>18. 19</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Exod. <hi>12. 26.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Iosh. <hi>24. 15</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>The godly tremble to heare &amp; see your childrē and seruants in the streets</hi>
         </p>
      </note> this, aske the Lord and he shall tell you. But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasse, most of you miserable people, neither can teach, nor will learne any good: Nay, it is to be feared, you teach your wiues, children and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, all the euill you see, heare, &amp; know, euery where practised in the world. They learn of you to sweare horribly, their wicked mouthes are full of othes: they learne of you to walke inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately: for their liues are vngodly &amp; prophane. Families are the fountains of al commō-weals, purge the fountaines and the streames shall be clean, Wherfore I warn, such as fear the Lord, loue Gods people, regard their owne welfare in
<pb facs="8"/>
this life, &amp; euerlasting saluation in that which is to come, teach, instruct, correct, &amp; by all good meanes reform your families: for assuredly our sinnes call for many iudgements from the Lord vpon vs.</p>
   <p>Purge your families I say, of vnclean persons, <note place="margin">
         <p>Ps. <hi>101. 7.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Gen. <hi>35. 2.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Ep. to Phil. Deut. <hi>21. 18. 20.</hi>
         </p>
      </note> as did <hi>Dauid &amp; Iacob,</hi> not sparing euen your owne children in their disobedience, riotous and luxurious life. And humble your selues (in this and the like calamity) in abstinence and praier: For so haue the people of god euer done in sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry afflictions, when they sought for any great blessings for thēselues, or for the church of God, Hest. <hi>4. 16.</hi> Nehem. <hi>1. 4.</hi> Act. <hi>10 30.</hi> And so did <hi>Dauid</hi> &amp; his good people in the pestilence, they rested not crying vnto the Lord, and then it is <note place="margin">
         <p>
            <hi>2.</hi> Sam. <hi>24. 25.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>Sic exoratus est Iehouah terrae.</hi>
         </p>
      </note> said: <hi>The Lord was entreated &amp; appeased toward the land, &amp; the plague ceased from</hi> Israel.</p>
   <p>Here I offer thee christian Reader, some spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall helpes &amp; cōforts, both against the pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and many other euils: if thou shalt receiue any benefit by them, giue God the praise &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Farewell in Christ, the yeare of our salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>1603.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord Iesus.
Henrie Holland.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>