<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE OF THE
TRANSLATOVR.</title>
           <author>Stapleton, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1565</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117786_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12939</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23230</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117786</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE OF THE
TRANSLATOVR.</title>
                 <author>Stapleton, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The apologie of Fridericus Staphylus counseller to the late Emperour Ferdinandus, &amp;c : Intreating of the true and right vnderstanding of holy Scripture. Of the translation of the Bible in to the vulgar tongue. Of disagrement in doctrine amonge the protestants. Translated out of Latin in to English by Thomas Stapleton, student in diuinite. Also a discourse of the translatour vppon the doctrine of the protestants vvhich he trieth by the three first founders and fathers thereof, Martin Luther, Philip Melanchthon, and especially Iohn Caluin</title>
                 <author>Staphylus, Fridericus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Laet (Latius), Hans (Jan) de</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1565</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>254, 4 leaves, folded plates, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_preface">
   <pb n="2" facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE OF THE
TRANSLATOVR.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He blessed apostle S. Paul (good Chri
sten readers) not without the instinct
of the holy ghoste and a sure fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight
off the troubles to come in
Christes church, writeth vnto the
Corinthians these wordes.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note>
      <hi>There must be heresies, to the
entent that they which are perfyt amonge you, might be kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen.</hi>
In which waighty and graue prediction of the
Apostle two things I see especially to be notised. The
one for our comfort, the other for our instruction.
For our comfort it is, that we be not dismaied or ouer
much offended when we see in the holy profession
of our Christen religion, heresies, sectes, and schismes
to arise: that we forsake not therefore the field of our
faith.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.</note>
      <hi>Wherin we warfare to god and rūne not as at an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain
thing, and fight not as one that beateth the ayre, but
rūne to obtaine, and fight to winne</hi> the reward: that we let
not go the holdfast of our hope <hi>Which we hold as the
sure and stedfast anchor of our soule:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hebr. 6.</note> but rather with the
patience of Abraham,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note>
      <hi>We beleue in hope contrary to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe,</hi>
continuing and cleauing stedfastly to the rocke
of oure faith, against the which, <hi>Hel gates shall neuer
preuaile.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Matth. 16.</note> For as we see by the verdit of the Apostle,
<hi>There must be heresies.</hi> It is now sithen the time that the
Apostle spake these wordes a thousand fiue hundred
and odde yeares, Yet neuer was there aage sence that
time but that in some part of Christendom heresies
<pb facs="3"/>
haue ben sturring. In the very first ofspring of the
Apostles there lacked not such euil wedes amonge
the corne of Christes church yet grene.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2. Apocal. 2.</note>
      <hi>Simō Magus,
Hermogenes Philetus, Hymeneus, Alexander, Nicolaus,</hi>
and such other are mencioned in holy writ to haue
swarued from the faith and <hi>after the knowledg off
righteousnes to haue turned back from the same.</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Petri. 2.</note> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side
holy writ we reade in the ecclesiastical histories
of <hi>Ebion,</hi> of <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> of <hi>Marcion</hi> and diuers other
plāters of heresies in the Apostles time. After whom
howe from age to age heresies being alwaies cutte of
and destroied haue yet spronge vp again and flouris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed
for a season as the venimous heades of Hydra. I
remitt you (to auoide prolixite) to the writinges of
<hi>Epiphanius,</hi> S. <hi>Augustin, Philaster</hi> and others, I repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te
my self also to the Chronographies of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
Sculteti</hi> and such other: which deducting the estat
of Christes church from the beginning hitherto, set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
forthe in tables seuerally the Popes and supreme
vicars of Christ, the Emperours, the generall and
prouinciall councels, the heresies of al times, haue in
no time nor age left vs bare the leafe of the heresies.
The figure of this calamite in Christes church we
see to haue gone before in the lawe of Moyses. For
at what time the children of Israel had by the mighty
hand of god entred in to the land of promis, chased
oute Idolaters and were setled in quiet possession, yet
god of a iust indignation conceiued against them suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring
the Cananites to dwell amonge them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced
by his Angell <hi>that he would not therefore cast</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 2.</note>
      <pb n="3" facs="3"/>
      <hi>those Idolaters out before them, to the entent they might ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue
them as enemies amonge them, and their gods should be as
asnare vnto them.</hi> And thereby the children of Israel
were tried as now the Christians are, they by Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
we by heretikes. Though therefore his our
present time be so entangled with schismes, seuered
in sundry sectes, and embrued with hainous heresies
as neuer at any time sence the first preaching off the
ghospel: Yea and though it haue so ouerrunne the
small plat of Christēdom that remaineth, as euer any
heresy did (except that of the Arrians) yet bicause we
see the holy ghost suffreth it so to be, and warneth vs
by the mouthe of the Apostle that is behoueth so to
be, we must yelde to the prouidence of almighty god.
and saie with the prophet <hi>Daniel.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Dan. 3.</note>
      <hi>We haue sinned with
our forefathers.</hi> Yea thousand fold more then oure fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refathers,
and therefore no maruaile if the dreadfull
wrath of god haue fallen vppon vs that we maye wel
crie and lament with the prophet Hieremy.<note place="margin">Hierem. 5</note>
      <hi>Consider
and see o Lorde our confusion: our inheritaunce is turned to
straungers.</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Ioan. 2.</note> Such surely as <hi>haue departed from vs but were
not of vs: for if they had ben of vs: they would no doubte ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue
continued with vs.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>An other lesson in the wordes of the Apostle for
our instruction is this, that heresies therefore are suf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fred
to be, to the entent that they which are perfect
amōge vs might be knowen. For by heresies the chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che
as gold by the fire is tried, and as the riuer or sea
by trouble and tēpest casteth his froth and filth awaie
(the pure water keping his bondes and course) so the
<pb facs="4"/>
churche in time of tribulation and stormes of heresy
voideth awaie the foule and vncleane membres of
her,<note place="margin">The duty of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sten man in time of heresy.</note> the sounde and faithful remaining vnder her rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe
and abiding in the receaued faith and belefe. For in
time of schismes and heresies the part of euery good
Christen man is, to do as the good souldyars in the
cāpe when a ciuil seditiō ariseth, or as the quiet passan
ger when the sea stormeth: for euen as the true and
faithfull souldyars in such a case runne all vnto their
Capitain and General, looking to be of him dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
where, howe, and when to strike, and as the wise
and sober passanger when the tempest and storme
disordreth the passage, suffreth quietly the master to
rule the sterne, medling not with that he hath no
skill of: right so when preuy rebells or open apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>statas
of Christen religion sowe seditious schismes
and preache hereticall doctrine, troubling thereby
the quiet and settled consciences of true and vpright
beleuers, euery Christen man, especially such as are
of the laye and inferiour sorte, ought to cleaue vnto
their heades and rulers in Christ his church medling
not with the determination of any point called then
in controuersy: but looke to be directed as they haue
allwaies ben by their catholike pastours and ouerse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
to whom they are commaunded by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle
to obey and submitte them selues:<note place="margin">Heb. 13.</note> truly no lesse
then the souldiar to his Capitain or the passanger
to his master.</p>
   <p>Therefore oure Sauiour biddeth the people to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware
and <hi>Take hede of false prophets,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Ioan. 4.</note>
      <hi>nor to beleue euery
<pb n="4" facs="4"/>
spirit, but trie and discern whether they be of God or no.</hi> But
this lo howe maye it be? Howe shal the ignorant
and laye man trie false doctrine from the true? It hath
ben put in to mens heads of late yeares that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
man for this purpose ought to reade holy scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,
and thereby to trie and discern truthe from fals<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.
It were perhaps to be wished (if it had so plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
God) that as holy scripture is the true triall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
so it were open and euident to all men that seke
the triall therein:<note place="margin">Scripture hard to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standed. <hi>Lib. 2. de. doctr. Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sti. Cap.</hi> 6.</note> but what haue lerned men iudged
in times past of holy scripture? <hi>Many things,</hi> saieth
S. <hi>Augustin, are darke in scriptures, and it hath so ben pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided
of God to the entent that our pridemight be tamed by
trauail and our knowledg not cloyed with facilite: which
quickely contemneth that easely hath ben lerned,</hi>
      <note place="margin">In Ezech. Cap. 45.</note> In like ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner
S. <hi>Hierom. All prophecy or interpretation of scripture
contayneth the truthe in darcknes and obscurite, to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
that the scholers and lerners within may vnderstande,
but the rude people set without may not knowe what is sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ied.
Orels we shall cast precious stones before hogges iff we
open the treasure of holy scripture to euery man.</hi>
      <note place="margin">In anchorae tu.</note>
      <hi>Epiphanius</hi>
likewise. <hi>The Scripture,</hi> saieth he, <hi>telleth all truthe: but
we haue nede of good intelligēce and perceiuerance to knowe
God and his word. There is in the ghospell,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lib. 7. in Leuiticum.</note> saieth <hi>Origen,
the letter that killeth: for the destroying letter is not only
in the olde Testament, but also in the newe Testament to him
that vnderstandeth not spiritually that which is saied. Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi>
speaketh yet more vehemently hereof. <hi>I am
not afeared,</hi>
      <note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>praescrip. haeretico<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ū</note> saieth he, <hi>to saie that the scriptures them selues
haue ben so disposed by the will of God that they mought mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister
<pb facs="5"/>
matter vnto heretikes: seing that I reade that heresies
must be which without scripture coulde not be.</hi> This is the
iudgement of the lerned fathers who haue trauailed
more in holy scripture then any new preacher of ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
time, and yet can espie no greate facilite in it,
but rather do complaine of the maruailous difficulte
thereof.<note place="margin">2. Petr. 3.</note> And doth not S. <hi>Peter</hi> write plainly that in
the epistles of S. <hi>Paule Certain thinges were very harde to
be vnderstanded which the vnlerned and inconstant depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
euen as other parts of scripture to their owne destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi>
Doth not S.<note place="margin">2. Cor 4.</note>
      <hi>Paule</hi> write that <hi>The ghospell is vailed
and couered from those that perish?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ioan. 5.</note> Are we not comma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unded
to serch holy scripture? doth not this serching
importe a diligence and difficulty more then laye
men can either attend vppon or attaine vnto?<note place="margin">Act. 8.</note> The
<hi>Eunuchus</hi> vnderstode not the prophet, vntill the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle
had expounded it vnto him, And Christ after
his Ascension <hi>opened the vnderstanding off his disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
that they might vnderstand the scriptures.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luc. 24.</note> And
thincke we oure selues able to vnderstand all that we
reade?</p>
   <p>This then being so howe shall the laye and vnler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
man perfourme the commaundement of the
ghospell bidding him, <hi>To beware of false prophetes</hi> and
<hi>to discern the sprits whether they be of god or no?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math. 7. 1. Ioan. 4.</note> Euery
secte nowe a daies chalengeth the worde of god and
the right vnderstanding thereof. The Catholike li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kewise
by prescription out of memory standeth in
possession thereof and will not be brought from it
for all the bragges the heretike maketh. Howe then
<pb n="5" facs="5"/>
shall the vnlerned man hearing bothe tales conclude
with him selfe which to folowe? Were it not nowe
good readers much to be wished that some clere and
euident doctrine were taught, by what meanes and
howe the holy worde of God maye rightly be vnder
standed, and the false prophets, preachers, and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants
of oure time might be auoided? Truly as the
sauegarde of the soule passeth all worldly interest, so
euery Christen hart ought aboue all thinges tender
the same: and with all diligence possible procure spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
remedies for the pestiferous venim off heresy
which <hi>crepeth on like a cancre,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.</note> and corrupteth the who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le
estat of our saluation.</p>
   <p>Hauing therefore sene and perused a certain boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke
of <hi>Fridericus Staphylus,</hi> writen first in the Allema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
tongue, and after translated in to Latin, wherein
he first teacheth the vnlerned laye man howe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware
of false and wrong interpretation of holy scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
which is no lesse necessary then the reading off
scripture it selfe, secondarely detecteth certain false
translations of the Bible by Luther in to his mother
tongue: laste of all declareth the maruailous dissensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
and variaunces of the Lutherans in their doctrine
and chiefest articles of our faith (which is a most eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
argument of the sprit of dissension (the diuell
him selfe) speaking in thē and a clere proufe of hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
doctrine, for the truthe is but one) I haue thought
good to translate the whole in to our mother ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue,
trusting in almighty God to profit hereby many
a Christen soule of my dere deceined countremen
<pb facs="6"/>
which (as God is my witnes) was my only respect in
this smal labour.</p>
   <p>The first part of this booke is a very necessary les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
for the vnlerned laye man.<note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie.</note> For without the true
and right interpretation of holy scripture such as the
church teacheth he can haue no right faith, and so
hazardeth his soule and euerlasting life which he
ought aboue all worldly respect tender and procure.
For as our Sauiour saieth, <hi>What auaileth it a man to wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nne
the whole worlde and lese his soule?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lucae. 9.</note>
   </p>
   <p>The second parte is a good admonition for al such
as are not sene in the tongues to beware of newe
translations of holy scripture falsely forged for a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untage.
Our english bibles sette forth these last yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res
lack not such foisting in of false termes. In the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistles
of S. Paule as ofte as the worde <hi>Idoll</hi> is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de
in the greke and latin text, so ofte they turne it <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage</hi>
as though <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> in greke, <hi>idolum</hi> and <hi>ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>go</hi>
in laten or idol and image in english were all one.
When God saieth in holy scripture.<note place="margin">Genes. 1.</note>
      <hi>Let vs make man
according to our image,</hi> will these men saie that God
hath an idoll according to the which man was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de?
and howe be they not ashamed to call couetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
worshipping of images when that S. Paule cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
it <hi>idolorum seruitus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ephes. 5.</note> that is, <hi>seruice of idols</hi> bicause
the couetous man maketh his mony his idoll? But
this shift serued them to digge vp againe the olde car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ren
heresy of the <hi>I conoclaste,</hi> image breakers, condem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned
in the seuenth generall councell and second off
Nice, and to throwe downe images out of churches
<pb n="6" facs="6"/>
setting in their places their owne and their wiues, as
in some parte of Germany it is practised. Likewise to
take away the sacrament of holy Orders,<note place="margin">Epiphani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us li. 2. cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trea har. &amp; August. ad Quoduult.</note> and to rene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we
the olde heresy of the Arrians and the <hi>Pepuziani</hi>
denieng priesthood aboue a thousand yeres past, as
the Sacramentaries and zelous Lutherans do now,
for <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> in greke and <hi>presbiter</hi> in laten, they turne
allwaies elder, not priest, as though euery <hi>presbiter</hi> in
S. Paule were an elder.<note place="margin">1. Timo. 4.</note> then Timothe was no lawfull
bishop being but young and farre from the accompt
of an elder, onles by these mens doctrine a bishop
may be younge, but the priest may be only an elder.
And these men marke not that this worde <hi>priest</hi> is
the very proper etimology of the worde <hi>presbiter.</hi> For
of <hi>presbyter</hi> in laten cometh first the frenche worde
<hi>prebstre</hi> and the dutche worde <hi>priester.</hi> Oute off
which two languages we (as in thousands of other
wordes) shortning yet more the terme, haue made of
<hi>prebstre</hi> and <hi>priester,</hi> priest. So for <hi>churche</hi> they turne
allwaies <hi>congregation,</hi> and that of a very wicked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,
meaning thereby to disanull the authorite and
estimation of Christes churche, making it to be eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
peltinge congregation of priuat heretikes: or as iff
that which we call the churche, were nought els but
the stones and morter it is made of. But as touching
the corrupted text of our common translation nowe
vsed, it is beside our purpose to make any speciall no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te
thereof: and in our Discours we shal haue occasion
to specify some other places of more importaunce:
As for these false and hereticall foistinges of <hi>Luther</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>
here noted by <hi>Staphylus,</hi> though in the cōmon trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
of our countre (thanked be God) they are not
readen, (one excepted) which when I come to the
place, I shall in the margin note you, yet it may serue
to the Lutherans of oure countre for a most euident
argument of the sprit of Antichrist speaking in Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
and of a wicked and detestable archeheretike.
For what is more conuenient for Antichrist, or more
proper for an archeheretike, then to corrupt gods ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly
worde, and geue vs in stede of it, his owne poison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous
and hereticall worde? Neither may the sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries
of oure conntre thinke that this toucheth
not them. For they are of Luthers broode no lesse
thē the other: Beside that their master, Caluin, is not
behind hand for his part, as in our Discourse we shal
by occasion declare vnto youe in diuers textes and
passages of holy scripture by him corrupted.</p>
   <p>The third part of the booke is an euident and sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible
detection of the abhominable schismes of these
protestans (what soeuer smothe countenaunces they
beare to the world) not only profitable for the laye
and vnlerned common people, but right worthy to
be read, waighed and considered of the rulers and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gher
powres: to the entent that seing euidently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
their eyes the horrible schismes, diuision, and
disordre, that these protestants haue caused in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendom,
and do foster vp and brede daily, where
they may haue their full swaie and course, they may
thinke vpon some spedy remedy for the restitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of vnite and agrement amonge them, and the
<pb n="7" facs="7"/>
church of Christ from whence they haue parted.
And truly by the example of this cōfusion in Germa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny
(where heresy hath had his free course in a state
of liberty these fourty yeares and more) we may see
as in a glasse the like inconueniences to be feared
amonge vs, if it should continew many yeares (which
God of his tender mercy forbid) as also it would ere
this haue showed it selfe amonge our protestāts at ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me,
if worldly policy had not refrained their vnruly
liberty.<note place="margin">Disagre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in doctrine among our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testans.</note> And yet amonge the pretended bishops of ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
countre it is well knowen that some allowe the or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der
of priesthood, as the ciuill Lutherans do at Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenberg,
some preache openly that all men and we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
are priestes, as the Illyricans do in Saxony and
all the flocke of the zelous Lutherans. Againe some
in the matter of the blessed Sacrament are very Zuin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glians,
as the Apologie and their articles at the laste
Cōuocation declare: some yet and that not the smal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lest
starres of the realme,<note place="margin">Caunter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury. Chi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chester. Gloce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster. Roche<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ster.</note> are in that point Lutherans,
as the trouble of certain of them after the ende off
the last parlement witnesseth. Notwithstanding (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the counsell of Melanchthon in his boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke
against <hi>Fridericus Staphylus</hi> they pretend outwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dly
agrement and vnite amonge them selues, to the
entēt that like the people of <hi>Creta</hi> (whereof such pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>testans
are called <hi>Syncretisantes</hi>) they may with more
ioyned force sett vpō their cōmon aduersaries the Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pistes,
and ouercome them the sooner. The late sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed
abhominable booke of <hi>Bernardinus Ochinus</hi>
the Apostata, Peter Martirs companyon lately prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb facs="8"/>
defending stoutely amonge other straunge he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resies
the pluralite of wiues (which began to be opēly
practised in Polevntel the Kinge banished him then<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce)
may geue vs to vnderstand, what ioyly newe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines
and heresies the scholers of Peter Martir which
are not fewe, nor of the basest sorte in our countre,
woulde plant and preach amonge vs, were it not that
matters being not yet ripe, nor thouroughly settled,
they were like to marre all the game, if they kept
not wel their countenaunces. Where in they folowe
wel and wisely the counsell of <hi>Nicolaus Amsdorffius,</hi>
which he writeth in his booke entituled <hi>Publica cōfes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sio
purae doctrinae euāgelij &amp; confutatio praesentium Suer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>merorū.</hi>
In the which complaining that <hi>Brentius</hi> and
the masters of Wittenberg being at a conference and
diet helde at <hi>Wormes</hi> would not condemne <hi>Zwingli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi>
and <hi>Osiander</hi> whose doctrine vtterly repugneth to
their Confession of Augspurg,<note place="margin">In the ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are. 1557.</note> he writeth these wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des.
<hi>In this doing they haue departed from the Confession of
Augspurg although they pretend to remaine in it, they haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
caused dissension and taken away all meanes of agrement,
for if they would (as we doe) condemne the errours of Zuinglius
and Osiander, then might we al agre together against the papi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stes.</hi>
These be the very wordes of <hi>Nicolaus Amsdorfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi>
a famous Superintendent amonge the Lutherans
well and truly obserued of our protestant preachers
and Ministers. And is this the pure worde of the gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,
so to beare two or rather twenty faces in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
hood? For although amonge our protestants bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
of the estate of our countre (where not what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer
listeth them is lawfull also to sett forth) the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
<pb n="8" facs="8"/>
semeth in this newe religion an apparent vnifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite
of doctrine, yet they vary not only amonge
them selues, as we haue before touched, but also
from their owne doinges. The order of communion
now practised in England differeth as much frō the
first order of cōmunion vsed in King Edwardes ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,<note place="margin">The dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion from the first.</note>
as the <hi>Lutherans</hi> do from the <hi>Zuinglians,</hi> and as
the <hi>Illyricans</hi> do now from the <hi>Melanchthonistes.</hi> For
the first bothe allowed the real presence in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament
as Luther did, and vsed also many olde cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies
of Christ his church as the <hi>Melanchthonistes,</hi>
and the ciuil Lutherans do yet in <hi>Wittenberg</hi> in <hi>Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi>
in <hi>Franconia,</hi> at <hi>Norimberg,</hi> at <hi>Vlmes</hi> (where pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
by of late we sawe in the churche the holy Roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de,
and aultars of stone yet standing) in the Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
of <hi>Wirtenberg,</hi> at <hi>Breslaw</hi> at <hi>Briga</hi> in <hi>Silesia</hi> and
in many other places. The last and present order off
communion denieth the reall presence, as <hi>Zuinglius,</hi>
and <hi>Caluin</hi> do, and reiecteth the ceremonies of the
Masse, as the Zuingliās and Caluinistes do in the fiue
Cantons of Suitzerland <hi>Basil, Zurich, Berna, Schafusa</hi>
and <hi>Clarona,</hi> at Geneua in Sauoye, in Scotland and
emong the seditious rebelles in Fraunce. Now Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
in his litle confession <hi>De caena Domini</hi> condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<hi>Zuinglius</hi> and his cōplices for heretikes.<note place="margin">Tomo. 6. fel. 60.</note> So do
<hi>Nicolaus Amsdorfius</hi> in the booke aboue alleaged,
and <hi>Nicolaus Gallus</hi> in his booke intituled. <hi>Theses &amp;
hypotyposes etc.</hi> Likewise <hi>Melanchthon</hi> condēneth <hi>Illy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus</hi>
and his felowes as in diuers writings, of <hi>Illyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi>
it is to be sene. By the iudgement then of Luther,
<pb facs="9"/>
of Melanchthon, and of all the ciuill Lutherans, yea
and by the iudgement of all the ghospellers in Kinge
Edwardes time, and of the stinking martirs of that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge,
our communion now practised in England is he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall,
and against the pure doctrine fo the ghospel.
It were ouer long to recite here all the variaunces in
doctrine amonge our protestants. I remitt you to the
daily experience which you may see better at home
then we which are abrode. And thus much of the
argument of this booke. What remaineth then for
our part to do, but as S. Paule commaundeth vs that
we be <hi>Solliciti seruare vnitatem spiritus in vinculo pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi>
that is,<note place="margin">Ephes. 4.</note>
      <hi>carefull and diligent to kepe vnite off minde
in the bonde off peace, being one body and one minde,
as we be called in to one hope and vocation? For the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
is but one lorde, one faith, one baptim, one God, and fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther
of all, that we hence forth be no more children wauering
and caried aboute with euery winde of doctrine by the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes
of men, and craftines laying waite to deceaue vs.</hi> It is
truly a world to see what labour and toile, what po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting
and running, what paines and charges, men su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staine
for their right in temporall traihe, in worldly
commodites and present pleasures, which we haue
renounced in our baptim, which with care being
gotten with sorow is kept, and yet soone loste, and
how colde, negligent, and careles we are, aboute
the true and sincere worshipping of God, which we
haue promised and professed in our baptim, and
which only hath his sure, certain, and euerlasting re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde.
We spare no labour, no coste, no trauail for the
<pb n="9" facs="9"/>
one, we moue not a foote, nor will not departe from
a peny for the other. but nodding and sleping in wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
ignoraunce, fuffer our selues to be lead by the no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ses
with euery tinkard and cobler prating in pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets,
and planting poisonnous doctrine. If rebells ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se
ageinst their Prince, they are with all spede possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
and force brought downe again. Well and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely.
And shall we winke at the rebelles of Christes
holy worde and his church? The thefe that robbeth
and pilleth our temporall riches, is hanged: and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely.
and will we not labour to espie oute and auoy
de heresies which bereue vs of the treasure of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
life? If we be thus recheles and careles for our sal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uation,
we perish worthely, and the plage of god ligh
teth vppon vs for our deserts. if we will not witting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
be deceiued but haue a care of our soule helth, and
think vppon the life to come, let vs in this perilous ti
mes of schismes, and abundāce off iniquite harken to
such as can teache vs to discerne the true and right in
terpretation of gods worde, from the peruerted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suasions
of heretikes. let vs beware of such guides in
matters of conscience, as stick not to corrupt the ve
ry text of gods worde, against all honesty and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science.
Let vs behold for the better assurance of our
Catholike faith, which is but one, the horrible schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes
of the Lutherās, Sacramētaries, Anabaptistes, Cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fessionistes,
and other amonge them selues, all the
which are here liuely and expressely sette forth by
<hi>Fridericus Staphylus.</hi> and we shall I trust gladly kepe
our selues vnder the wing of our mother the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb facs="10"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="9" facs="10"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="11"/>
church and geue no more eare to euery new for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
fantasie of seditious schismatikes.</p>
   <p>As touching the Author of this booke <hi>Fridericus
Staphylus,</hi> in his life time (for within these fewe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths
he departed the worlde to the great grief of all
good men) he was a vertuous, lerned, and wise, Noble
mā. His vertu wel appereth not only in the feruēt ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le
of gods worde and the truthe, for the setting forth
of the which, he toke such trade of life as bothe em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired
much the helth of his body, and procured also
greatiosse of his substaunce (as he writeth in the first
part of this worke) but also in the great patience and
modesty that he vsed alwaies against his aduersaries
writing pasquils, libels, and famous epigrams, against
him, calling him <hi>Iudas,</hi> runneagat, traitour and so
forth (as the modesty of this new ghospel vseth) by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
he forsoke their abhominable heresies after
a thourough knowledge of them, and detected their
iuggling deceites to al the worlde as especially he doth
in this worke folowing. And this only were they able
to obiect against him, which declareth well the inno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cēcy and vprightnes of his life, For as herein they spa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red
no kinde of rethorike to exaggerat his departing
from them (which was a singular grace of God and
most in him to be commended) so if they had had bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter
matter, it should not haue lacked the telling on
their part. <hi>Smidelinus,</hi> one that of all other to his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall
shame and ignominy toke vppon him to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter
with <hi>Staphylus</hi> labouring to fasten vppon
him some great blow of reproche and shame, at the
<pb n="10" facs="11"/>
lēghth for lacke of better aduauntage,<note place="margin">In Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia absolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta pag. 78.</note> entuiteth him
his naturall behauiour that he vsed commonly to lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke
downe to the grounde as he walcked, thinking
he had thereby raught him a great rappe. Which how
light a philip it is, euery wise man seeth. And that gre
at ghospeller and doctour of Gopping had forgotte it
was writen of our Sauiour that <hi>Non secundum visio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem
oculorum iudicabit He shall not iudge according to the
eye sight.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Esa. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Truly it is no small argument of his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency
that his most aduersary could laie no greuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser
matter vnto him.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>His lerning well appeareth in this and other his
workes as in his Absolut apology, his epistles and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations
against</hi> Melanchthon, Flaccus, <hi>and other: where
he showeth him selfe no lesse lerned Diuin, then elo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quent
oratour and expert of the tongues. But of his
education in lerning and prospering in the same, of
what estimation also he was amonge the protestants
them selues yow shall vnderstand by his owne wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,
being forced to declare the same by the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
reproches of Smidelinus his aduersary. In his
Absolut apology writē in the yeare 1562. thus he wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth.</hi>
Whereas Smidelinus obiecteth to me that I was Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
and Melanchthons scholer, I denie it not, for I liued in
the vniuersite of wittenberg ten yeares of my owne costes
and charges studying there vnder Luther, Melāchthon and
others. At that time also being a younge man rash and vns<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kilfull,
I was infected somwhat with the poisonnous doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
of Luther. Howbeit that was not so rooted in me, but
that it was soone driuen out again. And that I neuer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented
<pb facs="12"/>
thoroughly to the fifte ghospell of Luther, many thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
do euidently proue. First that whereas the Masters off
Wittenberg would nedes persuade me to procede Doctour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge
them,<note place="margin">Staphylus refuseth to be Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of the othe.</note> I would neuer do it. And that only bicause I
would not take the othe of the vniuersite and make open con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fession
of my belefe in that place. And this Doctour George
Maior who yet liueth can beare me witnes of. Secondarely
bicause I would neuer take vppon me the Lutheran Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery
in any church: though fewe yeares past I haue ben re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired
of certain Princes to high dignites: as to be Superin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendent
in sondry places: as at Augspurg, at Lubeck and at
Brunsuick. Thirdly this may declare how litle I fancyed
in my hart the doctrine of Luther, that being called and cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sen
of the Duke of Prussia to be a Reader in his dominions
(at Coningsberg) and a Counseller, I caused in the write of
my stipend this cōdition expresly to be put that I would be cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pelled
to no religion or doctrine that in any point repugned
with the doctrine of the primitiue, Catholike, and Apostoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
church, and of this my condition I am able to show iff
nede shall require sufficient testimonies. <hi>By these wordes
ye may see off what reputation and opinion of ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
and vertu this man was at Wittenberg, Aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spurg,
Lubeck and Brunsuick the most famous cytes
of the Lutheran profession.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>His wisedō and other noble qualites he well decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red
first in the seruice of a counseller to the Duke of
<note place="margin">Indefensio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne contra Musculum</note> Prusia from whome he was forced to depart and
that (as he writeth) to the losse of some thousands
of marks, bicause like a worthy and faithfull Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seller
he frely aduertised eftsones the Duke to bewa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
<pb n="11" facs="12"/>
of the cursed heresies of <hi>Osiander</hi> and his felowes.
Secondarely in the like seruice vnder the Catholike
and vertuous Duke of Bauaria, vnder whom he was
in such credit that he was made ouerseer and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uncelour
of the vniuersite of Ingolstad iointly with
the Bishop of Eistat. Thirdely for his wisedom, ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
and vertu he was of longe time and many yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res
Counseller to the late most worthy Emperoure
<hi>Ferdinandus.</hi> vnder whom he hath done noble serui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce
as well in the diets and conferences in Germany
as in embassages of Liflande, Pole, and other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres.</p>
   <p>As for the great labour, and diligence he besto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed
to shift him selfe oute of the captious and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious
controuersies of this time (wherein he was
nouseled in his youth) it may wel appeare in that (as
he writeth in the first part of this booke) <hi>He emploied
only the study of Diuinite and matters of Cōtrouersie about
two and twenty yeares: not medling in all that time with
any worldly or ciuill matter.</hi> And what thinck you
after so many yeares study and labour, after so great
experience and lerning, was the chiefest argument
and reason whereuppon he forsoke the Lutherans
and claue vnto the Catholikes? forsoth he declareth
it in the very same place last alleaged: and it is right
worthy to be noted. <hi>This</hi> saieth he, <hi>was the chief and
principal cause why</hi> I <hi>actōpted the diuers doctrine of Luther
and his felowes to be hereticall and for such do vtterly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake</hi>
      <note place="margin">VVhy Sta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phylus forsoke the Luthe rans.</note>
      <hi>it and detest it, this again is the cause why I esteme the
doctrine in all Christendom (which they call the Popedom)
<pb facs="13"/>
receiued, to be the only true and holesom doctrine, bicause this
doctrine is the Catholike and vniuer sally receiued interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
of holy scripture, but their doctrine is only their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uat
opinion and their priuat deprauation of holy Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</hi>
This lowas the principall reason that drew this
wise, lerned and vertuous man from the sectes of his
Masters, Luther and Melāchthō: and brought him ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me
to the perfect vnite of the Catholike faith. for he
sawe by lōg experiēce that al the doctrine of the new
ghospellers, was nought els but their owne traditiōs,
their propre inuentions, and priuat imaginations: for
ging vpon the worde of God such sence as them lis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
and telling then the people that the same was the
very worde of God: whereas the Catholikes folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed
such sence and meaning of the writen worde
as by the lerned fathers, continual tradition, and vni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uersall
consent of Christendom was receaued and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed.
And truly this only reason may be sufficient
bothe for the vnlerned and deceaued protestants to
reduce them home again to the Catholike churche
of Christ, and to kepe also within the same such as
by the grace of God, vertuous education, and good
instructions haue not yet swarued from the same.
Which I beseche almighty God it may so do.</p>
   <p>And thus much hitherto of this present Treatise
and the author thereof. Many other things there are
which I would gladly aduertise the Reader of. But
bicause we haue (I feare) ben ouerlong allready and
the Author him selfe hath prefixed a long but a ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
and profitable preface and therefore not to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted,
<pb n="12" facs="13"/>
I wil here breake of, and after the ende of the
Authors whole discourse, put for conclusion the rest
of my meaning, aduertising in the meane season
the reader of this one thing, that this our labour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
an interpretation, and bound to the inuentiō of
the Author, we haue not, ne coulde not vse the like eloquence
as the free stile geueth: beseching the not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding,
gentle Reader, to take our paines in
good part.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.
<dateline>At Louain <date>the 12. of Nouember.
1564.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Thomas Stapleton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>