<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRI∣STIAN READERS, especially those of my charge the inhabitants of Wrington in Somersetshire.</title>
           <author>Crooke, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117175_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19634</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6066</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117175</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRI∣STIAN READERS, especially those of my charge the inhabitants of Wrington in Somersetshire.</title>
                 <author>Crooke, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The guide vnto true blessednesse. Or, A body of the doctrine of the Scriptures, directing man to the sauing knowledge of God : Collected by Sam. Crooke</title>
                 <author>Crooke, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Pindley, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 250, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIAN READERS, especially those of my charge <hi>the inhabitants of Wrington in Somersetshire.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Christian Reader,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Lessednesse is the Alpha and Omega of Man, the beginning of nature, and the end of Grace. The naturall Philosopher in his inquest of Happinesse laieth this ground,<note place="margin">Arist. Ethi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>1</hi>
      </note> that, <hi>All things de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire that which either in trueth or in opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is good for them;</hi> and that onely is good, which tendeth vnto the onely good, the vttermost end and perfection of their seuerall natures. But where <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophie</hi> ends <hi>Religion</hi> begins: or rather, where <hi>Reason</hi> failes <hi>Grace</hi> supplies, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming <hi>all</hi> that nature (in the blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of Corruption) accounts excellent to be <hi>vanitie of vanities;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eccl. 1.2.</note> and the <hi>end of all
<pb facs="5"/> and whole of man,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eccl. 12.13, 14.</note>
      <hi>to be the feare of God, and the keeping of his Commandements.</hi> And that with respect to the last <hi>Iudgement,</hi> wherein all workes of men, <hi>whether good or euill, though neuer so secret, shall come to light and triall,</hi> and receiue their due reward. Yea so farre was nature in sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the matter of <hi>Blessednesse,</hi> that it could not truely define so much as the happinesse and perfection of the brute creature; which the Scripture sheweth to be the <hi>Reuelation and glorious Redemption of the Sonnes of God.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 8.19, 21.</note> Wherefore as it is euident in nature that all men seeke bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sednesse: so it is apparant in experience, that there is no man that can attaine thereto without a supernaturall guide; without which, wee see that touching <hi>Blessednesse,</hi> there are as many mindes as men, and as many waies as wits; euery one crossing another, and so all prouing that all are insufficient.</p>
   <p>For this cause I haue framed this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, for a direction to that, which all men seeke, and so few finde. Wherein from the ground of nature,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.9.</note> as of that <hi>light which enlightneth euery man that commeth into the world,</hi> I endeuor to raise the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of sauing knowledge.</p>
   <p>Although (to speake properly) the light of nature sheweth rather the necessitie
<pb facs="5"/> then the way to sauing knowledge, and is a ground rather of enquirie, then of attaining thereto. For all that nature can truely determine, and articulatelie pronounce concerning this matter, is, that Blessednesse is to bee sought, and such a blessednesse, as may sort with the nature of man the seeker; especially in regard of his better part, which is his soule. The rest well may shee stammer at; as that the soule is not onely a reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, but also a religious and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall spirit, and therefore cannot be bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed without the euerlasting fellowship and fauour of God, to whom shee is by band of conscience obliged: But plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to vtter these (more then metaphysi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call) trueths, is of such onely, whose <hi>tongue-string is loosed, and to whom the Lord hath said, Ephphata, be opened.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mar. 7.34 35.</note> And with this helpe, Reason it selfe will yet goe further, and say, that the meanes of acquaintance and fellowship with God, can be no other, then those which himselfe affordeth, and namely his Word, the onely infallible <hi>Index</hi> of the minde of the speaker; and therefore it cannot but reiect, as vncertain and vnsafe, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer the presumptuous boldnesse of flesh and blood obtrudeth against, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides this rule.</p>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <p>And yet further touching the triall of this touchstone, whether it be the word of God or no, Reason it selfe will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that (whatsoeuer induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may bee from the authoritie of those whom we credit and respect) none but God himselfe can thoroughly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solue vs of it: and that either by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant traces of diuine maiestie in the <hi>letter</hi> of the <hi>Scripture;</hi> or by the secret <hi>testimonie</hi> of the same <hi>Spirit</hi> that inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it, inclining the heart of the reader or hearer to embrace and subscribe vnto the authoritie of it. So that now the true beleeuer may say vnto the Church as those Conuerts to the woman of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria, Now wee beleeue not because of thy saying,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ioh. 4.42.</note>
      <hi>for wee haue heard him our selues.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Vnto reason thus enlightened or wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thus to be enlightened, I hope my manner of proceeding in this Treatise will seeme reasonable; wherein I haue with the vttermost of my poore abilitie faithfully endeuoured to comprise the whole bodie of the heauenly doctrine of the Scriptures: and that in such a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode, as vpon long and serious pensita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I haue iudged most meete, to bring light to the matter, and ease, both for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding and memorie, to the Reader.</p>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <p>A subiect, I grant, not of so pleasing a straine either to the writer or to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as some other treatises which afford more libertie of inuention and discourse. But I haue learned of the blessed Apostle of the Gentiles,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.1.</note>
      <hi>not to be greeued to write these same</hi> (seeming triuiall) <hi>things vnto you;</hi> knowing that euen from these things is the <hi>experience best</hi> taken <hi>of Christ spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the Minister</hi> (and therefore euen from these points doth the same Apostle auouch his <hi>vnderstanding in the mysterie of Christ</hi>) and withall being as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured, that <hi>for you it is a sure course,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Cor. 13.3.</note>
      <note place="margin">Eph. 3.4.</note>
      <hi>to be alwaies put in remembrance of these things,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.12</note>
      <hi>though yee haue knowledge, and bee esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished in the present trueth.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The experience of eleuen yeeres hath taught me, that it is not enough to teach in publike, vnlesse the auditors haue care to instruct themselues, and one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther priuately at home. For which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, I haue framed this Treatise by way of Question and answere, a waye most familiar for instruction, and whereby the spirit both of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerer, and of all that attend, is stirred vp to bethinke themselues, what might bee most aptly answered, to the Question propounded. Neither haue I done this onely in the larger Treatise; but also ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted
<pb facs="7"/> an Abridgement of the substance thereof, in a farre briefer draught, for the priuate vse of Christian families, and help of the weaker sort; that <hi>becomming all things to all men,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.22.</note>
      <hi>I might by all meanes saue some.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Wherefore as I haue <hi>out of my penurie cast in all that I had,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luc. 21.4.</note>
      <hi>euen these two mites, into the treasurie of the Church;</hi> So I ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly desire thee, Christian Reader (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially you that are of my charge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued in our Lord Iesus, to whom as my labours are principally due, and most fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar, so from you aboue others, I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect this Retaliation) to employ this our Lords talent, now in thy hands, for thine owne best aduantage, and of those that are committed vnto thee by the Lord.</p>
   <p>So shalt thou settle thy selfe, and them, vpon the ground of sauing truth. So shalt thou be prepared to <hi>giue answere to euery man,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.15.</note>
      <hi>that shall aske of thee a reason of the hope that is in thee.</hi> So shalt thou be able, to make farre greater &amp; sweeter benefite of whatsoeuer thou shalt heare out of the word preached; which vnto those that are ignorant of the grounds of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Esa. 8.6.</note> or <hi>despise these waters of Shiloah, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they runne softly,</hi> is many times vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable and vnsauourie. So shalt thou
<pb facs="7"/> not be <hi>plucked away with the errour of the wicked</hi> (whose <hi>itching eares,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.17, 18. 2. Tim. 4.3. 2. Thes. 2.10. 2. Cor. 11.3.</note> and harts <hi>not louing the truth,</hi> are easily <hi>corrupted from the simplicitie that is in Christ</hi>) and so <hi>fall from thine owne stedfastnesse: but grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ.</hi> Finally,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.16.</note>
      <hi>walking according to this rule, peace shall be vpon thee, and mercie, as vpon the Israel of God.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in the common faith, and seruice of our Lord Iesus,</hi> SAM. CROOKE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>