<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Errours of the printe, or changes.</title>
           <author>Powell, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117595_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13331</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23642</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117595</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Errours of the printe, or changes.</title>
                 <author>Powell, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The ende of Nero and beginning of Galba : Fower bookes of the Histories of Cornelivs Tacitvs. The life of Agricola</title>
                 <author>Tacitus, Cornelius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 <publisher>Barnes, Joseph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Robinson, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wright, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 17, 1, 267, 1, 80, 4 pages, illustrations (metal cut), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="171"/>
   <head>Errours of the printe, or changes.</head>
   <p>In the ende of Nero and beginning of Galba. pag. 2. direst. direct. 11. tiles. titles. 14. without. with. 16. Septinius. Septimius.</p>
   <p>In the translation of Tacitus. pag. 1. to found. to be found. <hi>in some copies onely.</hi> 5. The cuntreyes of Gallia. Those of Gallia. p. 20. puts on a brestplate. <hi>or rather</hi> a priuy coate. 22. when they shall see my enseigne. <hi>or</hi> when they shall haue my watch. word giuen them. 23. The standing in tēples and churches, <hi>or thus,</hi> The standings vpon the cōmon halles &amp; temples on euery &amp;c. 32. In higher army. In the higher army. p. 44. was honoured with a triumphal. honoured with a <seg rend="sup">82</seg> triumphal. <hi>for reference to the annotatiōs.</hi> 49. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. 53. which put vp in diuers regi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons and according. <hi>or</hi> which diuersly according. 59. fiue Paetorian. Praetorian. 60. XI. VI. 77. Po &amp; Olium. Olius, <hi>or</hi> Oglio. 78. and the sides knowing. and the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties knowing. 116. Septinius. Septimius. 243. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. <hi>In the translation for</hi> bilmen <hi>reade alwaies</hi> spearemen.</p>
   <p>In the annotations. p. 2. the last Charles. late Charles. p. 5. praedicari. praedicare. 7. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. 23. during the name of the time of. 25. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. nei- Liuy. neither Liuy. <hi>in the margin.</hi> neuer wrote to the Senate. neither wrote. 26. lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing figure. lozing-figure. 27. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> 30 <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> 30. succeede. suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded. 52. A. M. Acilio. a M' Acilio. 54. Dionysius lib. 54. repugnant places of Dionysius. <hi>reade</hi> Dio <hi>in both places.</hi> 58. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. 62. two, three, of foure-forked. or foure-forked. 69. Africanus exhibuit. Africanas. 74. point Euxini. ponti Eux. <hi>Some other smal escapes; as in the Greeke mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of an accent or spirit, an ο for ω, an ε for an η or contrary; in the Latin an υ for an η, the multitude or want of comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>es, the darke printing and sometime leauing out of a letter, as eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to euery one we haue not regarded.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>