<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Cotta, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117112_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19402</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5832</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117112</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Cotta, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cotta contra Antonium: or An Ant-Antony: or An Ant-apology : manifesting Doctor Antony his apologie for aurum potabile, in true and equall ballance of right reason, to be false and counterfait. By Iohn Cotta Doctor in Physicke</title>
                 <author>Cotta, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Cripps, Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Lichfield, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Short, James</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 108 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Antapologie (worthy Reader) was addressed vnto the Presse Anno 1616 as may be testified by letters then da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from some worthie and eminent Doctors of <hi>London,</hi> concerning the same, vpon a view thereof to them pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented. It was committed or offred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the presse, and a while pawsed in the hands of the Printer of the Ʋniversitie of Oxford, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by letters likewise from some illustrious and learned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the same famous Vniuersitie. It was thence againe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called home, and hath now by my selfe beene diuers yeares silen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vpon solicitation of some worthie Gentlemen my frends, who in the behalfe of <hi>D. Anthony,</hi> promised a faire and equall satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction from him. My indulgence vnto them hath hetherto been deluded. I doe therefore now iudge it full time no longer to tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, that so scandalous an imputation, as the Apologie doth impose vpon me falsely, should still in publike braue so impudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without as open and publike rebuke. And for this cause I haue now at last set at large this Antapologie, thus long iniuriously restrained. Vnderstand then that by the three first domesticall Testimonies, or emissarie letters of the Apologie, <hi>D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Co.</hi> (so cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally stiled by the Apologist) is charged with an vnexpected A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larum. The challenge is that <hi>Aurum potabile</hi> solely and wholy recouered the Gentleman in them mentioned, not onely without any worth or vse in <hi>D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Co.</hi> his endeauour, but rather with error and wrong thereby. The contrary hereto shall in due time and place be maintained by a discharge of <hi>D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Co.</hi> his iust defense as
<pb facs="6"/> well appointed as the enemies brauing charge, and onset in their rash and vnaduisedly giuen offense. It may be obi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cted, how can the privat quarrell against the three first Testimonies, inferre offence taken against the Apologist? The answere is, be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ause his Apologie can admit no Apologie for his vndiscreet publishing other mens private spleenes vnto D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> C. his p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eiudice, and for bringing his name vpon the stage, and there acting that part which befitteth no honest or sober man, in a cause and person vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne. D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> C. neuer infringed his <hi>Aurum,</hi> nor wronged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, notwithstanding in vaine and phantasticall dreame of a triumph, and for the idolizing of his <hi>Aurum potabile,</hi> Doctor <hi>Antony,</hi> or rather Doctor <hi>An</hi> (if I may without solecisme ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breviate him, as he in the same kinde hath first p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>esumed with me) <hi>D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> An</hi> (I say) iniuriously maketh himselfe the false trump of Doctor <hi>Co.</hi> his reproach, insinuated in the three first dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall Testimonies. They are subscribed by two Gentlemen, and a Minister (so rightly rather tearmed for ministring the occasion of such scandall, then for any eminence or noted worth in his owne function.) The Gentlemen D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>Co.</hi> will not so mainly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, perswading himselfe, that they are only transported by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers malitious instigation. His maine scope shall be at those two materially opposing markes. <hi>Marke-Antony,</hi> &amp; <hi>Antony-Marke,</hi> in this their simple conversion, not doubting to retribute a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble attenuation of their boasting follies. <hi>Antony,</hi> since in the golden flagge of the vaine-glorious praise of his <hi>Aurum pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile,</hi> he doth beare in triumph D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>C.</hi> his iniured name before the victory, hee therefore will first arme himselfe to strike at the plume of his pride, his counterfait colours, his armour of best proofe, by the generall demolition of his whole Apologie. As for <hi>Marke,</hi> since hee doth only ioyne his subsidiarie helpe by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiarie Epistle, he will only by the way buckle with him, as they shall meete in the batterie of the proofes of the fore-mentioned Testimonies. The challengers haue disgorged themselues in two Languages, for their greater boast. The Defendant will begin with the mother tongue, most fit for the satisfaction of his
<pb facs="6"/> Countrey-men. He will heereafter giue demonstration, that hee hath learned to speake as like an ancient<note n="†" place="margin">The Latine Antapologie hath diverse yeares since beene seene &amp; vewed by some learned Do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s of <hi>Oxford, London,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts.</note> Romane; as either <hi>Antony</hi> in his Apologie or <hi>Marke</hi> in his Epistolicall busie med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling out of his Apostolicall charge. In the <hi>interim</hi> (friendly Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) that thou mistake not, knowe that this Antapologie hath singled out <hi>D. Antony</hi> his Latine Apologie, as supposing it the more authenticke. The matter or substance being the same with the English, obscureth nothing thy vnderstanding thereof, though in some few things they are differing. To ease &amp; refresh thy paines in the perusing of the more serious matters, I haue here and there cast and scattered in thy way, some witty and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant sayings of some Latine Poets, and that I might exclude no mans reading, haue englished them vnto a vulgar capacitie. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the matter it selfe, deliberately view and read, embrace the truth for it selfe and for none other end. Be not preiudicate, but free and true vnto thy owne heart, and iudge sincerely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene truth and the lying visor, and impudent face of seeming truth.</p>
   <q>
      <l>
         <hi>Maxima pars vatum pater &amp; iuuenes patre digni,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Decipimur specie recti,</hi> saith <hi>Horace.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Or old or young more or lesse wise,</l>
      <l>Shadowes for truths, oft gull our eyes.</l>
   </q>
   <p>If any man deeme me ouerbold or overbitter with the Apologist let him read and ponder duly the vnciuill and rude prouocations of all honest and learned mindes, in his vilifying of all true lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, comparatiuely, or compared with his owne, as also of all wholsome medicines of all other Artists, not yeelding vnto his the sole supremacy. The summe or epitome thereof let any man view in his Preface in the beginning, and in his Appendix in the end of his Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sh Apologie. If that prowd flesh require not a corrosiue, let equall and iust men iudge; If the app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ication be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary, pardon the medicinall hand; Distinguish (gentle Reader) I hate railing or scurrilitie, which with the Apologist in his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie hath beene frequent and common. The importune prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of his ridiculous absurdities, I sometimes make merry &amp; smile at, and sometime check with free, yet ingenious<note n="†" place="margin">In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>oco qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum adh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>bet, is fest<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>vus seu vrbanus haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus. Qui mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m excedit, scurra. Quià iocis omnino ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horret, is rustici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> &amp; a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>estis. Arist Eth. lib. <hi>2</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
      </note> iest, the
<pb facs="7"/> matter and occasion so requiring. His prowd insultings onely, stupiditie, senselesse securitie, and lethargie with needfull<note n="†" place="margin">Castigare licet at{que} etiam expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, immo neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarium est. Scal.</note> gall, I also rowse and awake, not touching the person but the vice. Vnto prowd folly within moderate latitude exceeding, sufficeth a modest curb or quip discreetly falling. Obstinate and wilfull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse therein vrgeth and iustifieth a greater bitternesse, with cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it be not sordid nor impious. Thus far vpon iust incitement to proceed is not<note n="†" place="margin">Scurra is est qui risum magis qu m opo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tet mouet, &amp; risum magis mouet quam vt hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stè loquatur. Cicero.</note> scurrilitie or<note n="†" place="margin">Maledictum nihil habet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positi preter contumeliam. Contumelia pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tusantiùs iacta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta convitium, fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cetiùs vrbanitas nominatur. Cic.</note> railing (as men not discerning, or the Apologist may mistraine) scurrilitie properly including ribaldrie, vndecent iest, fowle, or vnseemely scoffing, exceeding that comely mediocritie wherein consisteth the allowed vertue of vrbanity, elegant, wittie, sportiue, close taxing, or reproofe of pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pably exposed foolery, whose insufferable ranknesse in due &amp; well husbanded time, or place, not to nip or top, is idly and dully to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, and needlesly to continue or incourage. Knowe againe, and lastly (good Reader) That in this Antapologie I intend not to meddle with the materials, or fabricke of <hi>Aurum potabile,</hi> nor with the manuarie exploration thereof by others more profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sedly therein exercised, exquisitly satisfied, but with the true touch and triall in right reason of D. <hi>Antony</hi> his promised de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstration, and of his Philosophicall and Logicall proofes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually professed, and endlesly boasted in his Apologie: which how childishly, rudely, and rawly he hath performed shall now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the Treatise following, <hi>Farewell.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy true frend warning both the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and thy priuate good from sly Imposture, IOHN COTTA.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>