<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>DEDICATED
TO THE NEITHER NOBLE OR JGNO∣BLE,
LORD OR LADY, KIND, OR CRVELL,
learned or ignorant, curteous or currish, Christian or Barbarian,
Man or Woman, rich or poore: but to all and euery one in
generall and particular.</title>
           <author>Taylor, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117734_Bo1_25_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13415</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23725</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117734</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>DEDICATED
TO THE NEITHER NOBLE OR JGNO∣BLE,
LORD OR LADY, KIND, OR CRVELL,
learned or ignorant, curteous or currish, Christian or Barbarian,
Man or Woman, rich or poore: but to all and euery one in
generall and particular.</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>All the vvorkes of Iohn Taylor the water-poet : Beeing sixty and three in number. Collected into one volume by the author: vvith sundry new additions, corrected, reuised, and newly imprinted, 1630</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Boler (Bowler), James 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Elizabeth.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 148, 2, 93, 92-200, 225-343, 1, 14, 13-146 pages, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <head>DEDICATED
TO THE NEITHER NOBLE OR JGNO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE,
LORD OR LADY, KIND, OR CRVELL,
learned or ignorant, curteous or currish, Christian or Barbarian,
Man or Woman, rich or poore: but to all and euery one in
generall and particular.</head>
   <p>MOnsieur, and Madam <hi>Hydra,</hi> to your many heads and variety of Censures I
haue made bold to dedicate, a poore, harmelesse, modest, honest, and innocent
<hi>Bawd,</hi> I know great persons of worth and honour, are daily so visited with
penurious shreds of <hi>Schollership,</hi> fragments of <hi>Hexameters</hi> and <hi>Penta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meters,</hi>
scraps of Poetry, the Scum and dreggs of wit, and the froth and lees
of wisdome: one salutes my Lords Lordship at Breakefast with a funerall <hi>Elegie,</hi> lamentably
written, and is most miserably rewarded for his kindnesse. Another bunts out his Worships vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentlemanly
Knighthood (hauing most intolerably belaboured his name with an <hi>Acrosticke</hi>
or <hi>Anagram,</hi> which out of his vacuity of worthinesse hee rewards with not a peny. A third
hath belyed such a Lady or Gentle womans beauty and qualities, in most abominable fashion,
setting her forth for faire and vertuous; for the which hee is rewarded according to the subiect
<pb n="92" facs="128"/>
hee wrote of, and his owne demerits, with as much as comes to nothing. For these and some e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
respects, I thought it not fit to desire the patronage of any one person in particular, it being
a subiect that is common to all, for all, or any. As men are dispersed uniuersally through the
world, so a <hi>Bawd,</hi> being an vniuersall creature, whose function is publikely scattered, I thought
it not pertinent or accommodating, that shee should be priuately protected by any. Therefore at
shee hath beene and is for all, so I dedicate her to all, knowing that all are better able to reward
the <hi>Poet,</hi> then one alone. And this is further to aduertise the Reader, that where I doe speake of
spirituall <hi>Bawds, Bawdry,</hi> Adultery or Fornication, that I haue auoyded prophanity, obsee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
scurrility, and all manner of inciuilitie or indecency; not meddling with religion at all, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t
with a pittifull derision, and merry reprehension explaining the abuses, soppish and sottish cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions,
that like so many Cankers or Caterpillers haue and doe daily eate, consume and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifie
both the Puritie and Pietie of that Religion which boasts it selfe to be most Primitiue and
<hi>Catholike.</hi> For the other part of this Booke, or Bawd, shee is altogether ciuill or temporall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
not troubled so much as with one good Ecclesiasticall word, but meerely Paradoxicall; set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
forth ther are and singular vertues of a <hi>Bawd;</hi> wherein if any of my Readers can picke
any pleasure, it is an apparant signe they haue some wit, and if they reape any profit, let them
either thanke me in words, or elsereward mee with silence.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours so farre, and no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
then you are mine,
IOHN TAYLOR.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>