<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Sedgwicke, Obadiah</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117037_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11850</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22151</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117037</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Sedgwicke, Obadiah</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Christs counsell to his languishing church of Sardis. Or, The dying or decaying Christian, with the meanes and helpes of his recovery and strengthening. By Obadiah Sedgwicke, B. of D. late preacher to the inhabitants of S. Mildreds Bredstreet, London</title>
                 <author>Sedgwick, Obadiah</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Badger, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawne, Luke.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Gellibrand, Samuel</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 262, 10 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F thou expectest in this Treatise what is curious and branched over with art, spare thine eye any further travell, it is not here▪ divine doctrines serve rather for the stomacke then the palate. In preaching these Sermons, I followed Saint <hi>Cyprians</hi> directions to <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> to make choise not of <hi>Diserta,</hi> but <hi>Fortia,</hi> I looked very little at harmony which might take the eare, but most of all at energy, which might reach the conscience.</p>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <p>I know well that there is a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and seasonable use of learning, I am not of his minde who would have Preachers study no booke but the Bible; onely this, Ministers (if I mistake not) must consider their auditors, and then and there, use their choiser learning, when and where it may not amaze, but profit; when all is summed up, this will be found the most comfortable truth, no Preacher is so learned, as he who can saue soules.</p>
   <p>And now if thou pleasest, reade the worke, and receiue this counsell from me; aboue all, striue for spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall life (it is thy greatest honour to be good) and when thou hast obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it, take heed of dying, the dead man and the dying Christian, are
<pb facs="8"/> two sad sights; it is wofull either to be a brand falling into hell, or to be a star falling downe from heauen: the rising sunne is more and more beautifull, but the waining moone is more full of spots and darkenesse: though all may not be lost, yet his shipwrackes are high who hath lost much in his jewels, and almost all in his comforts: no more but this, keepe heauenly things as thou wouldest keepe heauen it selfe.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in any spirituall furtherance, OBADIAH SEDGWICKE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>