<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Faults escaped partly at the Presse, partly by the default of him that copied out part of the Booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117855_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73267</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23315.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117855</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Faults escaped partly at the Presse, partly by the default of him that copied out part of the Booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The dignitie of Gods children. Or An exposition of 1. Iohn 3. 1.2.3 : Plentifully shewing the comfortable, happie, and most blessed state of all Gods children, and also on the contrarie, the base, fearefull, and most wofull condition of all other that are not the children of God</title>
                 <author>Stoughton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland (Haveland), Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 173, 184-491, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="259"/>
   <head>Faults escaped partly at the Presse, partly by the default <hi>of him that copied out part of the Booke.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>PAg. 5. l. 25. put out, vnto p. 18. l. 5. after not, r. only. and after but, r. also. p. 19. l. 32. r. all. p. 20. l. 21. r. alwaies. p. 22. l. 19. r. mediatly. p. 24. l. 3. r. euen vs. p. 29. l. 2. r. taking only. p. 41, l 15. r. alone. p. 64. l. 30. r. cleare. p. 69. l. 6. r. to beleeue it. p. 76. l. 30. r. 1. Cor. 12. 3. p. 108. l 32. r. gesture. p. 129. l. 21. after abiding r. or. p. 167. l. 23. r from. p. 169. l. 13. r. from some. p. 187. l. 3. r. Gad. p. 194. l. 4. r. giue. p. 198. l. 14. r. as. p. 208. l. 28. r. Ps. 19. 7, p. 221. l. 14. r. inueh rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding p. 223. l 5. r. Rom. 6. 3. 4 p. 236. l. 22. r. other. p. 238. l. 33. r. Iames 1. 18. p. 260. l. 11. r. high Priest. p. 271. l. 8. r. Psal. 94. p. 306. l. 34. r. euen. p. 308. l. 17. 18. r. vnspeakable. p. 312. l. 10. r. meanes. p. 324. l. 36. r. smack p. 325. l. 2. r. whom. p. 326. l. 21. r. beheld. p. 328. l. 1. r. we heard. l. 10. r. oppresse. l. 28. r. collowed. p. 335. l. 7. r. viz p. 339. l 32. r. Ps. 102. 2. p. 348. l. 33. r. Melas. 34. Rhinocurura. p. 368. l. 21. r. children of God. p. 387. l. 29. put out, one. p. 408. l. 25. r. and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. p. 412. l. 35. put out, the wicked. p. 436. l. 24. r. great. p. 467. l. 3. read com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming. p. 469. l. 32. r. Now. p. 475. l. 15. r. worke. p. 488. l. 30. r. so likewise.</p>
   <pb facs="259"/>
   <pb facs="260"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>