<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull, Reue∣rend, and iudicious Di∣uines RICHARD CLERKE Doctor of DIVINITIE one of the learned Translators of the Bible, and now Preacher of Christ Church Canterburie: and Daniel Featly Doctor of Diuini∣ty, and Rector of Lambeth, The sweet comforts of grace, and plentie of peace here, and the blessednesse of im∣mortalitie hereafter.</title>
           <author>Cobbes, Edmund</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117518_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19036</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5453</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117518</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull, Reue∣rend, and iudicious Di∣uines RICHARD CLERKE Doctor of DIVINITIE one of the learned Translators of the Bible, and now Preacher of Christ Church Canterburie: and Daniel Featly Doctor of Diuini∣ty, and Rector of Lambeth, The sweet comforts of grace, and plentie of peace here, and the blessednesse of im∣mortalitie hereafter.</title>
                 <author>Cobbes, Edmund</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Mundanum speculum, or, The worldlings looking glasse : Wherein hee may clearly see what a woefull bargaine he makes if he lose his soule for the gaine of the vvorld. A worke needfull and necessarie for this carelesse age, wherein many neglect the meanes of their saluation. Preached and now published by Edmund Cobbes, master of the Word of God</title>
                 <author>Cobbes, Edmund</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Waterhouse, Philip</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>52, 373, 19 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull, Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend, and iudicious Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines RICHARD CLERKE Doctor of DIVINITIE one of the learned Translators of the Bible, and now Preacher of <hi>Christ Church Canterburie:</hi> and <hi>Daniel Featly</hi> Doctor of Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Rector of <hi>Lambeth,</hi> The sweet comforts of grace, and plentie of peace here, and the blessednesse of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie hereafter.</head>
   <p>RIGHT Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull, and Reuerend Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, I am not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb facs="3"/> how dangerous a thing it is to present a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worke to the curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous eyes of the world, or to speake any thing vnpolished in open audience; such is the delicacie of mens eares, as experience teacheth; and so censorious are the tongues of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious, that they are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to condemne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they vnderstand,
<pb facs="3"/> and to iudge of men and their actions, not as they are indeed, but according to their own preiudicate opinions. I know and must needs confesse, that it were good reason, nothing should come before your presence, but that which were most per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and excellent; How may I then (which am neither
<pb facs="4"/> sound PHILOSO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PHER, eloquent Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, good Poet, nor learned Diuine) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume to present to your iudicious cōside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations this meane and illiterate Treatise, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>The Worldlings Looking-glasse,</hi> whose rudenesse, both for matter and method, is farre vnfit to weare the liueries
<pb facs="4"/> of your names; yet <hi>Commasculaui frontem pudoris limites transili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> I haue put courage into my bashfull na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and haue so farre presumed vpon your curtesies, as that you will pardon my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption in venturing so farre vpon your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold fauors, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend my poore paines by your patronage.
<pb facs="5"/> And the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the subiect is of so great importance, and so not vnworthy your best considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons▪</p>
   <p>Touching my own insufficiency to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle a point of so great moment, I haue the wise Heathen ready to plead for me, <hi>Not who</hi>
      <note place="margin">Non quis, sed quid di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit attendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>▪ <hi>Sen.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>is the speaker, but what he saith ought to be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/> Yet I could wish, I could act the Rhetori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians part, <hi>docendo, dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctādo, flectendo,</hi> in teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, delighting, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swading: yet seeing the first is a worke of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie, and the latter of victory and delight▪ I shall reioyce if I can performe that which is necessary, leauing the rest to those which excell therein, because
<pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>our words must rather</hi>
      <note place="margin">Non dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctent verba vestra, sed prosint. <hi>Seneca.</hi> Melius est vt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>tell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nt popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, quam vt commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matici. <hi>Amb.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>bring profit, then delight.</hi> Therefore it is a sure rule which the Father giues, that it is <hi>better so to speake, that the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est may conceiue, then for to gaine the learneds commendation;</hi> because in graue and Diuine sentences many times it proues true: <hi>That while men adde an elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent</hi>
      <note place="margin">Dum name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> adda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, pondus detrahatur.</note>
      <hi>forme of words;
<pb facs="6"/> they detract from the substance of the matter.</hi> But the best affected<note place="margin">Verum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis amant in verbis, quam ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba. <hi>Aug.</hi>
      </note> doe rather looke to the truth deliuered, then to the curiositie of the manner of deliuery.</p>
   <p>Concerning this present discourse, let it condemn or commend it selfe, for great words cannot better it, nor disabling speeces much impaire the worth of
<pb facs="7"/> it; gold is tried by the touch, and good bookes by the worth; the wise are not so skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the one, but iudgment makes them as capable of the other. But how euer it bee, it is the first Budd that grew in my garden; &amp; if it giue not that fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant smel, that others more ful grown do; yet I doubt not but that it
<pb facs="7"/> may giue some small sent, if the diligent Reader come not like <hi>Dinah,</hi> rather to feed his fancy by gazing on the lines, then to gaine by the matter. And though <hi>Elijah</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisha</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Kin. 2. 12</note> be the Chariots of Israel, &amp; the Horsemē therof, yet I doubt not but the footmen may doe some seruice in the battle: And <hi>Apollos</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/> without offence may water where <hi>Paul</hi> hath planted. And though I am not able to hold way with such strong &amp; able laborers as you are, nor worthy to be accounted in the nū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of good workmen; yet I doubt not but that by Gods assistance I may some way ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance his glory, and benefit his Church.</p>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <p>The consideration hereof hath made mee not to regard the nip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping checks, &amp; scorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful speeches of <hi>Momus,</hi> and <hi>Zoilus,</hi> and all the rabble of censorious detractors, which will like of nothing but that which is framed in their owne braines, knowing no other way to grace themselues, then by their taunting
<pb facs="9"/> tongues, which they imploy to disgrace o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and as they are carelesse to doe any good themselues; so they are ready to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage those which are carefull and willing to imploy their talents to their masters profit: like the enuious <hi>Jews,</hi> who would not build<note place="margin">Ezra 4. 4.</note> the Tēple of the Lord themselues, nor were
<pb facs="9"/> willing that any other should; but when the godly did begin to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy themselues in the worke, they scoffed,<note place="margin">Neh. 4. 2.</note> mocked, and discoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them, fearing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like that GOD might haue too much glory: yet for al this, the godly were not discouraged, but for all their reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ceased not till they had finished the
<pb facs="10"/> Worke of the Lord, whose practise shall teach mee not to bee discouraged, but with the strength of my GOD to arme my selfe with patience to endure the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures of all men. For as in all good acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">Difficile im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssibile est placere om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, nec <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>▪ ta senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>as est. <hi>Hieron.</hi>
      </note> so especially in publishing of bookes it is hard to please all men: for there is not
<pb facs="10"/> lesse varietie in mens countenances, then there is their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and therefore nothing can be so wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily spoken, but enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous<note place="margin">Nihil tam circumspec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> dici po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test, quod non rapia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ab im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probis vel in al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>quam calumni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am vel in ansam peccandi, vt vix tutum sit quicquid recte mone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. <hi>Era<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi> ad <hi>Vol.</hi>
      </note> men may find one thing or other to cauil at, if they bee disposed to depraue; though perhaps if they were put to amend, they would shew more cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticisme then abilitie;
<pb facs="11"/> yet for all this they<note place="margin">Optima queque ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnere quam discere. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>n.</hi>
      </note> thinke it better to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spise those things which are good, then to learne them. But as the scope &amp; aime of all my actions shall bee to please God, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge my owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science; so I will not trouble my self to please such mens humours; for if I should, I feare I might spend my time
<pb facs="11"/> to as little purpose as he did that would fashion<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> a Coate for the Moone: Neither doe I intend in this present discourse by adulation to praise your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships, nor my selfe by ostentation, nor my worke by admiration: the first I leaue, lest my words should im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire your worth; the second I conceale, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
<pb facs="12"/> I finde nothing in my selfe that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serues praise; and the last I refraine, for if my labour can but gaine your fauourable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance; and that you will be pleased so farre to countenance it, as that it may appeare to the world vnder your names, I haue that which I desire: and then,</p>
   <q>
      <pb facs="12"/>
      <p>
         <hi>Non ronchos metuam, non vani scommata vulgi,</hi>
      </p>
      <p>
         <hi>Censores treticos, gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticasue tribus.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>No gleering scornes Ile feare, nor spite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full gibes,</p>
      <p>Nor crabbed Criticks, nor Grammarian tribes.</p>
   </q>
   <p>And thus crauing
<pb facs="13"/> pardon for my bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, with a thankfull acknowledgement of your many vndeser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued fauours extended towards me, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend you, and yours to the protection of the Almightie, and this present Discourse to your fauourable cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, and my selfe to your seruice and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, resting alwayes
<pb facs="13"/> bound in dutie, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer deuoted in loue,</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From my study at</hi> Low Layton <hi>in</hi> Essex. <date>Ianuary 1. 1630.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Edmund Cobbes</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>