<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE VERY WORSHIPFVLL, MY EVER-HONOVRED Mother B.B. encrease of all good in him, who is the only good.</title>
           <author>B., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117366_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17130</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4008</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117366</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE VERY WORSHIPFVLL, MY EVER-HONOVRED Mother B.B. encrease of all good in him, who is the only good.</title>
                 <author>B., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Seaven sparkes of the enkindled soule : With foure lamentations, which composed in the hard times of Queene Elizabeth, may be vsed at all times, when the Church hapneth to be extreamely persecuted. Drawne out of the holy Scriptures, after the forme of Psalmes. By R.B.P</title>
                 <author>Buckland, Ralph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>—Recusant</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>156 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE VERY <hi>WORSHIPFVLL, MY</hi> EVER-HONOVRED Mother B.B. encrease <hi>of all good in him, who is</hi> the only good.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O</hi> many wee owe much, &amp; to sundry their certayne due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; to friends, kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, clyents, neighbours; to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structors, &amp; gouernors: but vnto our parentes we owe all; we owe our selues. Of which eminent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue although Christians can not be ignorant, through the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent commendation thereof in the word of God, as which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne in the
<note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 20,</note> ten Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes,
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>was by our
<note n="b" place="margin">Math 15.</note> Sauiours blessed mouth recommended; by
<note n="c" place="margin">Ephes. 6.</note>
      <hi>S. Paul</hi> noted to be the first Commaundement, hauing a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise thereunto annexed: so nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were the Heathens so desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of natures light, but that they alwayes held this as a high principle. The great reuerence of
<note n="d" place="margin">3. Reg. 3.</note>
      <hi>King Salomon</hi> towarde his mother, is to be read in the booke of Kings: and no lesse rare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample had the Gentiles of
<note n="e" place="margin">Plut.</note>
      <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obis</hi> &amp; <hi>Biton,</hi> who submitted their owne shoulders to the draw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing of their Mothers Chariot.
<note n="f" place="margin">1. Tim. 5.</note> And the Apostle expresly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded children to yeald re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall vnto their aged parents; saying that it was acceptable &amp; commendable in the sight of God so to doe. That same by way of <hi>Prouerbe</hi> drawne from the Storke, committed they to an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall
<pb n="5" facs="3"/>care and memory: glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly also at all times reciting that memorable nature of this bird, which is,
<note place="margin">Antipelar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gein.</note> that the younger fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>streth againe the elder, of whome before he was fed and bred vp. Let this litle labour of mine be in some sort to play the Storke, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in a contrary, yet most e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiualent sort of foode; such surely as in this time of my long absence from you wil be as acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptable (I doubt not) to receiue, as it was gratefull to minister it; &amp; shal prooue as cordiall in the vse, as it was paynefull in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position. Liue you to God; who also preserue you.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Sonne with all loue and duty. R. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>