<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Holme, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117238_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03481</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13601</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117238</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Holme, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The burthen of the ministerie : Gathered out of the sixt chapiter of the Epistles of S. Paul to the Galathians, the first verse. Verie profitable to be read of euery faithfull subiect, and of all that desire to be taught in the waie of truth. By Iohn Holme</title>
                 <author>Holme, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 <publisher>Danter, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Winnington, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>46 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian people straite is the gate, and narrow is the way that leadeth to eternall life, &amp; few there be that enter into it: but broad is the waye that leadeth to destruction, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny there be that finde it out, and walke in it: the one way full of pleasure and ease, the other crabbed, croked and full of sorrow. And this is the waye of the Church and chosen people of God, <hi>Israel</hi> must be vnder <hi>Egypt,</hi> the three Children in the fyrie fornace, <hi>Dauid</hi> must be persecuted in his owne kingdome, by his owne sonne, and Christ himselfe must be crucified: No maruaile therefore though the Deuill sow contentions in our mindes, now wee being at rest, for that euen in peace we should begin to warre, for the reforming of which mischiefe many and sundrie Pamphelets haue been written, but either wee are to deafe that we can not heare, or els to negligent in practising those thinges that we heare: neuer so much preaching God be praised neuer so little profitting, the Lord amend it, Some
<pb facs="4"/> of vs haue itching eares, to heape to our selues a number of teachers, and with some of vs it is mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, we care for no teachers, the one sorte be the <hi>Brownists,</hi> the other be the <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Gesuits</hi> of our time. And though our most gratious Queen whose life the Lord long continue, as the faithfull witnes in heauen, do labour and striue, to set peace betwene <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Manasses,</hi> betwene Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster and Ministery: yet we disloiall seruaunts to so good a gouernour, flee farre from this peace. Was euer any land guided so well and wisely? yet behold the enuious soweth tares in the mindes of her loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all subiects, to driue them from obedience. These &amp; such like are the trials, which persuade my hart of the trueth of the religion of England: For this cause thou haste here (gentle Reader) the burthē of the ministerie, wherin is set downe the causes of contentious and scismes, lately sprung vp amongest vs, desiring when thou knowest them to eschew thē, and now to become true to her Maiestie, if here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore thou hast not beene sound, so God will blesse thee for thy true <hi>Israëlites</hi> heart, and guide thee in all thy waies, that thy foot dash not against a stone, and at the last bring thee to euerlasting life through the merits of Christ</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours Io. Holme.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>