<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117262_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12119</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22424</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117262</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sir Antony Sherley his relation of his trauels into Persia : The dangers, and distresses, which befell him in his passage, both by sea and land, and his strange and vnexpected deliuerances. His magnificent entertainement in Persia, his honourable imployment there-hence, as embassadour to the princes of Christendome, the cause of his disapointment therein, with his aduice to his brother, Sir Robert Sherley, also, a true relation of the great magnificence, valour, prudence, iustice, temperance, and other manifold vertues of Abas, now King of Persia, with his great conquests, whereby he hath inlarged his dominions. Penned by Sr. Antony Sherley, and recommended to his brother, Sr. Robert Sherley, being now in prosecution of the like honourable imployment</title>
                 <author>Sherley, Anthony, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <publisher>Bagfet (Bagford, Barfet), Joseph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 139, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any haue beene desirous</hi> to vnderstand on what hopes, helpes, and grounds, Sir <hi>Anthony Sherley,</hi> with his brother Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Sherley,</hi> and many other friends and followers, of our Nation, could not onely be induced to vndertake to trauell into a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome so farre remote, and to liue amongst a people so farre different in Religion, Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and Manners, as that of <hi>Persia</hi> is from ours: but also he supplied of all necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries for life, in a plenteous and magnificent manner; and so highly endeare his seruice
<pb facs="3"/>
and industry to that King and State, as to bee esteemed and called a <hi>Mirza,</hi> or Prince of <hi>Persia,</hi> and to bee employed, within few monthes after his comming thither, as Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassador from so great a Potentate, in a matter of such ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne consequence and trust, to many of the greatest Princes and States of Christendome.</p>
   <p>And no lesse haue many meruailed, how, after his failing in the accomplishment of so great an enterprise, for want of due corres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondence in an Instrument, hee had taken vnto him, out of that Country for his better credence, his Brother Sir <hi>Robert Sherley,</hi> whom hee left behind him in <hi>Persia,</hi> could not onely maintaine his reputation, but win so much credite with that King, as to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with the Title of his Embassadour, to the Princes of Christendome, in the like employment newly reuiued.</p>
   <p>At his late being here in <hi>England</hi> (where
<pb facs="3"/>
hee hath beene so accepted as in the Courts of other great Princes of Christendome) a Gentleman of some vnderstanding conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing oftentimes with him, and being desirous of true information, concerning that action (whereof he had formerly heard, and read some incoherent and fabulous reports) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred with him often, concerning the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and circumstances of their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings: and thereby gaue him occasion to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course vnto him as well of the motiues of that enterprise, as of many accidents that befell him and his Brother in the conduct of that affaire. Wherein, al-be-it hee receiued good satisfaction in diuers particularities; yet, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the questions, occasioning such dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, were but incidently moued; and (by many occasions that happened) their confe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rences were often interrupted: On the en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>treaty of the said Gentleman, for the better satisfying of himselfe, and such others of
<pb facs="4"/>
his friends, as might bee desirous, out of their curiosity, to vnderstand the whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse, dependance, and prosecution of the said voyage into <hi>Persia,</hi> hee obtained of the <hi>Persian</hi> Embassadour, a Copy of this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, penned by his Brother Sir <hi>Anthony Sherley</hi> (as it seemeth) since his returne out of <hi>Persia</hi> into <hi>Europe,</hi> for the better satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of his friends, and preseruing the memory of so memorable an action.</p>
   <p>To these labours of his Brother, <hi>Sir Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Sherley</hi> himselfe as time and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity shall giue him leaue, hath promised some addition of his owne endeuours: which being not yet in such readinesse, as his friends haue wished and desired; This discourse being but the former part, yet containing the Register <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f so rare an attempt (whatsoeuer the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sse hath bene, or may bee) as hath seldome bene seene in this, or any former age, by a priuate Gentleman to haue beene enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed,
<pb facs="4"/>
the same being recorded by his owne pen who hath beene the first and chiefe Actor in it, hath bene thought by men of mature iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to whom it hath beene communicated, (besides the History it selfe which is pleasing and delightfull) to containe many fruitfull aduertisements.</p>
   <p>So that hauing in it both the eleuations of a high spirit, and the obseruations of a man experienced and versed in great affaires: it is the rather vnto thee re-commended.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>