<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ An Aduertisement to the Lerned Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1567</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117788_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12940</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23231</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117788</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ An Aduertisement to the Lerned Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A counterblast to M. Hornes vayne blaste against M. Fekenham : Wherein is set forthe: a ful reply to M. Hornes Answer, and to euery part therof made, against the declaration of my L. Abbat of Westminster, M. Fekenham, touching, the Othe of the Supremacy. By perusing vvhereof shall appeare, besides the holy Scriptures, as it vvere a chronicle of the continual practise of Christes Churche in al ages and countries, fro [m] the time of Constantin the Great, vntil our daies: prouing the popes and bishops supremacy in ecclesiastical causes: and disprouing the prince supremacy in the same causes. By Thomas Stapleton student in diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Stapleton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Fowler (Fouler), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Louvain</pubPlace>
                    <date>1567</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 542, 5 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="20"/>
   <head>¶ An Aduertisement to the Lerned Reader.</head>
   <p>TOuching certain Authors alleaged in this Reply, about mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of our own Countre, it is to be vnderstanded, that of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne writen Copies not yet printed which we haue vsed, as of Henricus Huntingtonensis, and Gulielmus Neubrigensis, or Noueoburgensis, or Neoburgensis many thinges are in the said Copies, which seme not to be writen of thē, but of Some others. As in the Copie of Henricus Huntingtonensis, certayne thinges are founde, which seme not to be writen of him, but to haue bene ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of his workes, and to haue bene writen by some other: whom we coniecture to be Simeon Dunelmensis. Also in the Copie of our Neubrigensis many thinges are added both at the beginning and at the ende, which seme not to haue ben writen by Neubrigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis him self, but by some other. And that which is added at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, was writen as we vnderstand nowe of one Alphredus Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlacensis, who liued vnder king Steuen: The additions which do followe, who wrote we yet knowe not, except it were Roger Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueden. This I warne thee of, gentle Reader, to thentent that if he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reafter the foresaid Copies come forth in printe (as this very yere Neubrigensis did) and that the printed Copies haue more or lesse then we reporte out of the writen Copies, thou may not suspect any falshood or forgery in vs, but vnderstanding the case as we haue saied, maiest take our dealing to be, as it is, true and sincere. I here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hauing conferred the printed Neubrigensis, with the writen Copie, and finding some difference: as ofte as that which I alleage out of Neubrigensis, is in the printed Copie, so ofte I haue noted in the Margent, the booke and Chapter of that Copie. And when that I alleage, is in the writen, not printed Copie, I note in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent: Neubrig. M.S. for: Manuscriptus.</p>
   <p>Againe in quoting the leaues of the Tomes of Councells, I haue alwaies in maner folowed the former Copies printed at Collen in three Tomes: Anno. 1551. Only towarde the ende of this booke I haue folowed the last edition of this present yere, quoting the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues according to that Edition, and then for perspicuites sake I hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> added in the Margent. Edit. Postr. Vale.</p>
   <q>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>.</q>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>