<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>ERRATA, CORRECTA.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117400_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12213</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22524</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117400</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>ERRATA, CORRECTA.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A reply to an ansvvere, made by a popish adversarie, to the two chapters in the first part of that booke, which is intituled a Friendly advertisement to the pretended Catholickes in Ireland : Wherein, those two points; concerning his Majejesties [sic] supremacie, and the religion, established by the lawes and statutes of the kingdome, be further justified and defended against the vaine cavils and exceptions of that adversarie: by Christopher Sibthorp, Knight, one of His Majesties iustices of his Court of Chiefe Place within the same realme</title>
                 <author>Sibthorp, Christopher, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stationers’ Society, Dublin</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Ireland--Dublin</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 114, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <head>ERRATA, CORRECTA.</head>
   <p>IN the Epistle Dedicat. pag. 1. line 12 this word (first) blotte out. In the Epist. to the Reader, pag. 1 l 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. for satisfactory, satisfactorily p. 8. l 5. for suffertus, suffenus, p 9. lin 33 for scripturiam, scripturam, p. 10. l. 14. for ingeniosly, inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuously. In the first Chapter of the Booke, p 2 l. 5. for will, soule p. 13 23. this word secondly, blotte out, &amp; in stead thereof put this figure 2 to note it to be the second section of that Chapter, &amp; so reade on forward, thus: It being then a thing very demonstratively evident, &amp;c p. 13. l. 32. for Ministers, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery, p. 15. l 6. for writeth, citeth, p. 17. l 6. for makinde, mankinde p. 24. in the margent, for 2. <hi>Sam</hi> 20 17 put 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 20 26. In p. 24 l. 31. &amp; 32, reade it thus: <hi>Aaron and his sonnes were appointed to the office of priesthood</hi> p. 26. l. 31 this word Thirdly, blotte out, &amp; in lieu thereof put the figure of 3. to note it to be the Third section of that Chap p 26. l. 33. for wisheth, wished. p. 34 l. 10. for youg, young. p. 38. l 12. for divert direct p. 39. l. 19. reade, as unto the chiefe p. 42. l 6. &amp; 7. for Iohn 9, 11, Iohn 19, 11 p. 44 l. 17. for yea, yet. p. 44 l 18 for construed, considered, p 45. l. 26 for advantagement, advantage, p. 51 l. 23 for ingeniously, ingenuously, p 52. l 10 for Aquinus, Aquinas, p. 52. 32. for cause, clause, p. 13. l. 19. betweene, as, and other Bishops, put this word, over, pag 38. l 16. for worth, worthy, p 40 l. 5 for <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> reade <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, p. 43. l. 33. this word (as) blotte out, p 57, l. 3 this word (and) blotte out, p. 66. l 2. for shall, should, p, 70, l 24, for States, seates, p. 79. l 24. for under, made, p, 82, l, 18, for how, now, p, 83, l, 7, for Episcopus, Episcopos, p, 84, l, 12, after, but, reade by, pag, 15, against l, 24, in the margent, for Novel, const, 123, Novel, const, 133, p, 19, l, 22, for hignesse, high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, pag, 100, l, vlt, for proferant, vel Apo, pag, 88, l, 26, for <hi>Airam Hira<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> &amp; in margine, for 1, <hi>Sam,</hi> 5, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, reade 2, <hi>Sam,</hi> 5, 11 p, 88. l, 8, for use, used, p, 94, l, 3, for could, would, p, 96, l, 19, betweene neverthelesse, &amp; admit, put this word (to) p, 97, l, 16, for one, on, p, 97, ly, the first (onely) blotte out, pag, 93, l, 9, for grant, reade, perceave, p. 102 l, 22, after their, reade dayes, p, 102, l, 21, for make, made p. 82 l, 11, for Bithinijs, Bithiniae.</p>
   <p>And if any other faults have escaped in the Printing, I desire the Reader to correct them with his pen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>