<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[To The Reader]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117329_Fr4_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02735</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12866</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117329</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[To The Reader]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Deaths aduantage little regarded, and The soules solace against sorrow : Preached in two funerall sermons at Childwal in Lancashire at the buriall of Mistris Katherin Brettergh the third of Iune. 1601. The one by William Harrison, one of the preachers appointed by her. Maiestie for the countie palatine of Lancaster, the other by William Leygh, Bachelor of Diuinitie, and pastor of Standish. Whereunto is annexed, the Christian life and godly death of the said gentlevvoman</title>
                 <author>Harrison, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 84, 4, 77, 19, 38 pages, folded table, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="94"/>
   <pb facs="94"/>
   <opener>
      <salute>TO THE CHRISTIAN Reader, grace and peace in Iesus Christ.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Achimaaz</hi> the sonne of <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doc</hi> requested that he might be the messenger to bring <hi>Dauid</hi> word of <hi>Absoloms</hi> death, <hi>Ioab</hi> would not suffer him: <hi>Thou shalt</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Sam 18. 19. 20.</note>
      <hi>not</hi> (saith he) <hi>be the messenger to day, but thou shalt cary newes another time, but to day thou shalt cary none; for the Kings sonne is dead.</hi> He knew <hi>Dauids</hi> affection was such, that the newes of his childs death would be most heauie to him, and the messenger him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe not welcome for his message sake.</p>
   <p>This is all our infirmity, no tidings more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous to vs then when wee heare of the death of those whom wee loue. The Parent bewayles his Child, the Husband his Wife, the Friend la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the death of his Friend, and we thinke it the losse of another friend to depart with this our griefe. <hi>Iacob</hi> mourned for <hi>Ioseph</hi> his son, <hi>that he would not be comforted</hi> of a long<note place="margin">Gen. 37 35.</note>
      <pb facs="95"/>
season, but thought he would weepe for him as long as he liued When the <hi>Amalekites</hi> had<note place="margin">1. Sam. 30. 4.</note> burned <hi>Ziklag,</hi> and led away captiue the mens wiues and their children, <hi>Dauid</hi> and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany <hi>wept, till they could weepe no more.</hi> When <hi>Lazarus</hi> dred, his sisters <hi>Martha</hi> and<note place="margin">Iohn. 11. 19.</note>
      <hi>Mary</hi> were much discomforted for him. <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory Nazianzen</hi> reports, that when <hi>Basil</hi> the<note place="margin">Moned. in Basil.</note> great died, euen the wisest men in the city stroue to exceede one another in weeping and complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for his death: <hi>And as for my selfe</hi> (saith he) <hi>now I am bereaued of the fellowship of such a man, what shall I do but either dye, or liue in miserie? Which way shall I turne me? What shall I do? What counsell shall I take, now I haue lost him that was my comfort?</hi> So heauy a thing we see it is to be se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered for a time from those that are deere vnto vs. One only thing there is, which is able in this case much to temper our affections; when we see our friend to die in the Lord; that is, in comfort of conscience, &amp; assurance of saluatiō through <hi>Christ.</hi> And this his comfort he expresseth outwardly vnto vs, by performing those duties which are required of a man when he dyes, and so he makes a ioyfull and a holy end. When our friend departeth this life in this maner, we haue iust cause to take his death the more comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably.


<pb facs="95"/>
And thus it pleaseth God many times to stirre vp some (especiallie such as in their life time haue a care to pursue Religion, and to keep themselues vndesiled of the world) at their death to expresse wonderfull comfort of spirit, and to shew forth such fruit of Religion, that we wonder at it, and acknowledge the extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary worke of Gods spirit in them. They wrastle against temptations, they confesse their faith, feele the assurance of their saluation, condemne their sinnes, exhort the beholders, praise God, sing Psalmes, wish to dye, that in their death they are better Christians then euer they were in their life.</p>
   <p>This blessed departure God giues to many, for diuers good purposes. 1. That the world may know that peace is the end of the iust, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in death is the portion of the righteous. 2. That his eternall truth in our holy profession may appeare to be able to comfort vs, not onely in our life, but in our death also, when all other comforts forsake vs. 3. That our enemies may see our faith is not in vaine. 4. That the weake by their example may be incouraged to a holy life, when they see it bring with it so happie a death, and that they may be strengthened a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the feare of death, seeing it is alwaies comfortable to those that leade a godly life.


<pb facs="96"/>
5. and finally, that the friends of the departed, by their heauēly departure, may be admonished not to mourne so much for their death, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce for their life, <hi>and to thanke God, that euer it was their lot, in any degree, to be ioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or matched with so blessed seruants of God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This Gentlewoman, <hi>Mistresse Katherine Brettergh</hi> was one of this number: her life, as long as God continued it, was deere to those a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom she was, as the life of a friend might be. Her husband, friends, kinsfolks, brethren, sisters, and all the godly that knew her, inioyed a great blessing of God of her: and her death (no doubt) was grieuous to her husband, as the death of a vertuous yoke-fellow. And if worldly affection would haue holpen it, it was the same in him that <hi>Dauids</hi> was to <hi>Absolom</hi> his sonne, when he mourned for his death: <hi>O my sonne Absolom, my sonne, my sonne Absolom;</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Sam. 18. 33.</note>
      <hi>would to God I had dyed for thee, ô Abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom my sonne, my sonne!</hi> But sure her death was such, her behauiour in her sicknes so religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, her heart so possessed with comfort, her mouth so filled with the praises of God, her spirit so strengthened against the feare of death, her conquest so happy ouer her infirmities▪ that such as loued her most haue greatest cause to reioyce


<pb facs="96"/>
in her death, and by seeing the wonderfull worke of God in her, to learne to renounce their owne affections.</p>
   <p>This is the thing I thought with profit might be presen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>d to the view of others also that knew her not: for when I had for my own priuate vse and the vse of my friends faithfully collected (out of the fresh memories of those that were present, and eye-witnesses as wel as my selfe) and set downe the manner of her sicknes and death: I considered that the knowledge thereof could not but be welcome to al those that desire to die the death of the righteous. And so the same causes that moued me to collect it, gaue me also occasion to publish it. I remembred the saying of one, <hi>That it is great pietie to set foorth the</hi>
      <note place="margin">Nazianz. Monod. Basi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> ij.</note>
      <hi>vertues of the departed, if they haue excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led therein; yea it is a meanes to increase grace in our selues.</hi> I thought so great mercie of God shewed to one among vs, ought not to be forgotten, but should remaine to vs &amp; our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre an example, to teach vs how good God is to them that loue him, and to assure vs that he will neuer forsake vs; but, in like manner as he did her, helpe and comfort vs, when we shall by death be called vnto him. I considered the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly and vncharitable tongues of the <hi>Papists</hi> abiding in our countrey, who, since her death,


<pb facs="97"/>
haue not ceased to giue it out that she died de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spairing, and by her comfortles end▪ shewed that she professed a cōfortles Religion. Wherein they bewray their malice &amp; madnes, and shew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues of what generatiō they are, euen a people (as the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> saith) <hi>which bend</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iere. 9. 3.</note>
      <hi>their tongues like bowes for lyes: and</hi> (as <hi>Dauid</hi> saith) <hi>make readie their arrowes to</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 11. 2.</note>
      <hi>shoote at them which are vpright in heart.</hi> And lastly, when I remembred the censure gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by our Sauiour Christ of the woman, that poured costly ointment on his head, a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<note place="margin">Matth. 26. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 9. 10. 11. 12. 13.</note> his Passion, though some of his Disciples vniustly blamed her for the same, saying, <hi>What needed this wast?</hi> yet he himselfe did not only excuse her for that fact, saying, <hi>she did it to bury him:</hi> but also commaunded that <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer the Gospell should bee preached throughout the worlde, there also that which she had done should be spoken of, for a memoriall of her.</hi> Euen so, seeing this vertuous Gentlewoman hath bin vniustly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused, by some popish persons, I thought it sit, that she should not onely be iustly excused, and cleered from their false and slaunderous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports: but also that a true historie of her holie life, and christian death, should be annexed to those learned Sermons which were preached at


<pb facs="97"/>
her Funerall, by two godly Preachers, and are now published in print, that where soeuer they going before as the Gospell preached; there also this briefe historie may follow after, to be seene and read for a memoriall of her.</p>
   <p>These reasons moued me both to collect and publish this treatise, the doing whereof I trust, as it will be acceptable to many, so can it bee hurtfull to none, vnlesse possible it be to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of darknes. If there be any vnsatisfied, and yet desire any other reasons, I tell them further, it is to burie her, and the last balme that euer I can powre vpon her head: it is my farewell, and the last duty which I can performe vnto her; and therefore I hope both excusable in me, and also profitable to others, because many things here spoken of her deserue imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. And this I assure the Reader, that howsoeuer I may sometimes misse the for me of words which possibly the Gentlewoman vsed in her speech; yet haue I faithfully set downe the substance of the matter, and for the most part also faithfully related the words them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, and reported nothing but that which is most true, and testified by persons of good and honest report, as they are named in the margent: out of whose fresh memories the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of that which I publish was presentlie


<pb facs="98"/>
set downe. This I humbly desire thee, good Christian Reader, to accept. I had no other odours wherewith to imbalme her, I am but the pen-man, the thing it selfe was her owne, wrought in her by Gods spirit: and therefore not costly to me, though more comfortable to me, and all that heard it, then I can now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse: and I doubt not, but it shall yeeld thee also the same comfort, and giue thee occasion both to praise God, and imitate her wel-doing, which the Lord graunt.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>