<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Preface]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117973_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13202</idno>
           <idno type="STC">235</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117973</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Preface]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A defence of the Holy Scriptures, worship, and ministerie, used in the Christian Churches separated from Antichrist : Against the challenges, cavils and contradiction of M. Smyth: in his book intituled The differences of the Churches of the Separation. Hereunto are annexe a few observations upon some of M. Smythes censures; in his answer made to M. Bernard. By Henry Ainsworth, teacher of the English exiled Church in Amsterdam</title>
                 <author>Ainsworth, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 121, that is 132 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is true of an haeretik which Solomon sayth in parable,</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 9. 13.</note> a foolish woman is troublesome: <hi>experience hereof wee have in this adversary whom I deal against. For he not content to manifest with mouth, nor to write with pen, nor to print in publik once, his owne follyand shame, with calling vpon us to</hi>
      <note n="†" place="margin">Differen. Preface.</note> justific our proceedings or repent of them; <hi>dooth in an other book the second time</hi>
      <note n="“" place="margin">Parall. p. 105.</note> require an answer, <hi>and fretting in himself that we passed over his vanitie with silence, he biddeth us battel with the third alarme in his book</hi> The character of the beast, <hi>lately published. Wherin, (to shew how near he is allyed to those which say,</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 13. 4▪</note>
      <hi>who is like unto the Beast, who is able to warr with him?) he</hi>
      <note n="†" place="margin">Charact. in the epist.</note> requireth, nay chargeth, yea challengeth us <hi>(as he saith)</hi> to the defense of our errors <hi>vawnting moreover against us, that we are</hi> guiltie in our consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of our disabilitie to defend them, <hi>and therefore</hi> subtilly draw back and pretend excuses; <hi>triumphing also over vs, as they that</hi> hitherto in craftines have withdrawn from the combat, in the matter of the translation, worship and presbyterie.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thus hath he lifted up</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Psal. 75. 5</note>
      <hi>his horne on high, and spoken with a stif neck; as if even the mightie were</hi>
      <note n="“" place="margin">Iob. 41. 16.</note>
      <hi>afraid of his majestie, and for fear fainted in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. In regard of which insolencie; all men I think may see, it is now time, if ever, to take up sheild and sword against him, and hew his hornes that so have pushed the flock of Christ, wherof not long since he professed himself to be a member with us: though now having left the truth to folow leasing, he maketh open warr with the saincts. And wheras among other</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 18.</note>
      <hi>swelling words of vanitie, he sayth,</hi>
      <note n="†" place="margin">Charact. epistle.</note> Loe we protest against them to have a false wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of reading books: we protest against them to have a false go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of a triformed Presbyterie; we protest against them to have a false Ministerie of Doctors or Teachers, &amp;c. <hi>I have taken in hand to set forth our iust defense, in these particulars, and to shew the frawd and malignitie of this boaster: leaving the other point about the constitution of our Church in baptising of infants, to others that have already begun to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince his heresie therin. And this which I have undertaken is rather for others (who may be troubled with his writings) then for his own sake, who yeeldeth smal hope of good, seing he procedeth so fast in evil; and out of a</hi>
      <note n="“" place="margin">Prov. 28. 25.</note>
      <hi>proud hart hath stirred up strife. Wherin also such hath been his ficklenes, as</hi>
      <note n="†" place="margin">Psal. 5. 9.</note>
      <hi>no constancis is in his mouth. For (not to speak of</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Princip. &amp;c. Differ. &amp;c. Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ract of the Beast.</note>
      <hi>three sundry books wherin he hath shewed himselfe of 3. several religions,) in this one book which J deal against, he say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>and unsayeth and contrarieth his own grounds for to shift and hide his blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, that litle needed him so earnestly to have caled for an other mans sword to peirce the bowels of his errour; when his own hand fighteth against himself, and the spear which he tosseth, turneth into his hart. I had much rather have folowed more cōfortable meditations, in the peaceable practise of the truth; thē thus to cōtēd with those that seek strife, &amp; that fight against the faith which themsevles once professed; having found such by experience, to be above others, most malignant enemies: but truth oppugned, may not be for saken; and</hi>
      <note n="†" place="margin">Mat. 7. 15.</note>
      <hi>wolves that would ravin, must be beaten from the fold, least the sheep be devoured or scattered. Now therefore I being to encounter this false Prophet, doe hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble my self under the good hand of God whose power is made perfect in mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie; whose mercie susteyneth in violence of the enemie; whose truth is a sheild and buckler. He blesse these my labours unto his people; that</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Psal. 107. 42.</note>
      <hi>the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous may see and reioyce, and all iniquitie may stop her mouth.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>