<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Authour, concerning his learned and pious Treatise of Gods house.</title>
           <author>Gower, E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117202_Fr1_4_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12099</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22400</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117202</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Authour, concerning his learned and pious Treatise of Gods house.</title>
                 <author>Gower, E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Five pious and learned discourses : 1. A sermon shewing how we ought to behave our selves in Gods house. 2. A sermon preferring holy charity before faith, hope, and knowledge. 3. A treatise shewing that Gods law, now qualified by the Gospel of Christ, is possible, and ought to be fulfilled of us in this life. 4. A treatise of the divine attributes. 5. A treatise shewing the Antichrist not to be yet come. By Robert Shelford of Ringsfield in Suffolk priest</title>
                 <author>Shelford, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cambridge University—Printers</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 326, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>¶ To the Authour, concerning his learned and pious Treatise of Gods house.</head>
   <l>RIch soul, and blest! for so I dare go on</l>
   <l>To voice that man, whose life's religion;</l>
   <l>Who fears not to be good, gives God his due</l>
   <l>In this our age and in the Temple too;</l>
   <l>Who scorns these lothsome times, and dares learn us</l>
   <l>To be lesse bold, lesse superstitious,</l>
   <l>Not to make God a man, joyn heav'n with earth,</l>
   <l>Use him familiarly who gave us birth;</l>
   <l>Nor man a God, by following, praising such</l>
   <l>Who neither pray nor preach, yet <hi>teach</hi> they much.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="6"/>Lord! when I view our Temples, which now be</l>
   <l>Ruin'd by time, (beauties worst enemie)</l>
   <l>Or rather by neglect crumbling to dust;</l>
   <l>Can I perswade my self, or may I trust</l>
   <l>Those ancient Fathers, those pure Saints should then</l>
   <l>Fables or fruitlesse stories write; ev'n when</l>
   <l>They praise, yea blesse their founders, and condemne</l>
   <l>Their puft up <hi>Catharists,</hi> those chair-preaching men?</l>
   <l>Can I conceive S. Pauls expression weak,</l>
   <l>Not like himself, when thus I heare him speak,</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Ye are Gods Temples?</hi> Did th' Apostle mean</l>
   <l>Our clay-like houses should be kept unclean?</l>
   <l>All cobwebd o're with vices? that a lust</l>
   <l>Should there inhabit, and that it should rust</l>
   <l>The Berill, Jasper, Amethyst, those three</l>
   <l>Celestiall graces, Faith, Hope, Charitie?</l>
   <l>Or when the Priest (the soul) must sacrifice</l>
   <l>A comely Altar, should he then despise</l>
   <l>A pure well furnisht heart? must not the place</l>
   <l>Be hung with well knit vertues, where blest grace</l>
   <l>Resides? Yes sure; and he whoe're hath done</l>
   <l>The contrary, dilapidation</l>
   <l>Of that Temple shall to his charge be laid,</l>
   <l>Because his body (Gods house) thus decayd.</l>
   <l>Now as these walking churches must be drest</l>
   <l>And purg'd from filth by all, as well as Priest;</l>
   <l>So must the other: that's Gods Temple too,</l>
   <l>Though made with hands; which carelesly if thou</l>
   <l>Profane, demolish, or perhaps abridge</l>
   <l>That of its honour, 'tis proud sacriledge.</l>
   <l>Reader, no more. That God may have his due,</l>
   <l>Turn o're this book, and it will teach thee how.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>E. Gower <hi>Coll. Jesu Soc.</hi> Raptim.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>