<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Dent, Arthur</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117456_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20217</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6640</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117456</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Dent, Arthur</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The ruine of Rome: or An exposition vpon the whole Reuelation : Wherein is plainly shewed and proued, that the popish religion, together with all the power and authoritie of Rome, shall ebbe and decay still more and more throughout all the churches of Europe, and come to an vtter ouerthrow euen in this life before the end of the world. Written especially for the comfort of Protestants, and the daunting of papists, seminary priests, Iesuites, and all that cursed rabble. Published by Arthur Dent, preacher of the word of God at South-Shoobery in Essex</title>
                 <author>Dent, Arthur</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 <distributor>Burby, Cuthbert</distributor>
                            <distributor>Waterson, Simon</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 152, 149-306 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing often requested (gentle Reader) and much importuned by sundry, both learned and godly, to publish that doctrine of the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> which diuers of them with liuely voyce heard publikely deliuered: I did at last, vpon my most mature deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yeeld vnto their reasonable request; I meane the reasons of their request. Indeed I doe ingeniously confesse, that I am the vnmeetest of many, which this age (God be thanked) doth afford, to deale in a matter of so great importance, or any wise to be imployed in so great and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable a seruice as this is. But if I doe industriously vse my small talent, and be found faithfull in a little; I hope it shall haue both chearefull and comfortable acceptation with the Church of God. For this I presume will bee granted of all, that hee which hath but a little strength, and yet putteth it forth to the vttermost to doe good withall, is more to be commended, then he which hath thrise his strength, and vseth it not to the helpe and benefit of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And true it is indeed, that sundry worthy labours of diuers excellent men vpon the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> are already extant: so as he may seeme to powre water into the Sea, or goe about to mend the crowes eyes, that will attempt to adde any thing to that which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready published. But know this (O Christian Reader) that the Lords garden is so large and plentifull of all most sweete and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant flowers, that where any one hath gathered a Nosegay most fragrant and delectable, another may come after, and gather ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not to be contemned. For the wisedome of God is such an vndrainable fountaine and head-spring, that where one hath
<pb facs="3"/>
drawne much before, another may come happely, and draw as much afterward: yea though thousands doe succeede, yet can this fountaine neuer be drawne drie. Be it farre from me to arrogate any thing to my selfe, aboue others: for I am priuy inough to mine owne meanes, and do freely confesse, that in this worke, I haue receiued much light from others: and therefore do not as a iudge, giue sentence vpon other mens workes: but as one that would furnish the same feast, bring in my dish among them. Or as one that in the same cause would come in as a third, or a fourth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to testifie and confirme the same thing. And verily through the gracious assistance of Gods spirit, my simple purpose and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor is to giue a lift to the vttermost of my power, to further that which is already happily begun, and to prouoke others of greater gifts, to come after with their great lights, and Lanternes in their hands, to discry and discouer whatsoeuer in this Prophesie is not yet fully seene into. I am not ignorant that some would not haue this booke medled withall, nor in any wise to be expounded among the common people, because (say they) it is so darke and hard to vnderstand. But let all such leaue their owne opinions, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken what the holy Ghost saith.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Apo. 1.3.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Blessed is he that readeth, and they that heare the words of this Prophecy, &amp;c.</hi> What can be said more? or more effectually to stirre vs vp to heare and reade, and with all gladnesse to embrace this booke, then to tell vs, that in so doing we shall be blessed? For the thinges contained in this booke, be no trifles: they be not things onely for a shew to mooue wonderment, or to delight the curious minds of men: but such as indeed do giue true blessednesse vnto all those that are well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed in them. What thing is greater, then to bee blessed for euermore? If we be not exceeding dull, yea, euen like stockes and stones, it must needs moue vs &amp; stir vs vp. For who will wittingly &amp; willingly loose his own blessednes, or suffer it to be taken from him when as he may haue it? If any will obiect that a man may be blessed well inough without the knowledge of this booke, and that there bee bookes inough in the Scripture, to procure our blessed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, without this: and that thousands are now in heauen, which neuer knew what this booke meant: I answere, that all this doth
<pb facs="3"/>
not take away the necessary vse of this booke: for the holy Ghost doth pronounce a blessing vpon the heads of those that reade and studie this booke, not because a man cannot be saued without it: but because of the great comfort which it ministreth vnto vs of this age, and hath ministred vnto all the Churches since the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles times. For it is the Prophesie of this age, and the Prophesie of all the ages since Christ: wherein is fully shewed what shall be the estate and conditiō of the Church in the seuerall ages thereof, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ende of the worlde. For God according to his admirable wisdome &amp; mercy, hath neuer from the beginning left his church without a Prophesie, for the great comfort thereof. For we know, that immediately after the fall of our first parents, God himselfe, for the great comfort of his Church, did foretell and foreprophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie long before of that restauration which should be made by the Messias his sonne,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen. 3. Gen. 15.</hi>
      </note> according as it came to passe in the fulnesse of time. Afterward he did foretell his people of <hi>Israel,</hi> of their great seruitude, and intollerable bondage in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and also of the ende and full determination thereof, after foure hundred and thirtie yeares. After all this he foretold by his seruants the Prophets of the captiuitie in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the full expiration thereof at the end and tearme of seuentie yeares.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ier. 25.</hi>
      </note> And yet further for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and consolation of his people,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Dan. 7. Ezech. 38.</hi>
      </note> he foretold by <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel,</hi> of the great afflictions &amp; troubles which his Church should endure by the persecutions of the diuided Greeke Empire: (I meane <hi>Alexanders</hi> posteritie,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Dan. 8.</hi>
      </note> especially the Kings of <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Siria,</hi> which descended of <hi>Ptolomeus</hi> and <hi>Seleucus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Dan. 9.</hi>
      </note>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Dan. 11.</hi>
      </note> whom the scripture calleth the Kings of the North and of the South) by the space of <hi>294</hi> yeares, and of the precise determination thereof at the comming of the Messias. Loe then what care God hath had of his Church in all ages before the comming of his sonne in the flesh, so to foretell both of the affliction it selfe, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so of the iust period and determination thereof. And shall we not thinke that God hath the like care now for his church which then he had: or hath he not as great and as prouident care for the good of his Church since the promised Messias was actually exhibited as before? Yes assuredly, and much more too: for if his care and
<pb facs="4"/>
prouidence was so great for his Church being in her ward-ship and minoritie: then much more now being come to her ripenesse and full age: If when it was lesse glorious, then much more now, being farre more glorious. Therefore now vnto vs he foretelleth by his seruant <hi>Iohn</hi> what shall be the estate of the Church vnto the end of the world: and therefore <hi>Blessed is hee that heareth and readeth this booke:</hi> sith it foretelleth of the Churches af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions in this age by the whoore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and of the full end and determination thereof. It sheweth iustly and precisely what the Church hath suffered since the Apostles times in seueral ages, and what it shall suffer: and also how all the enemies thereof shall shortly be troden vnder foote. What can be more ioyfull or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to all the people of God, then to know afore-hand that <hi>Babylon</hi> shall fall: <hi>Rome</hi> shall downe: Antichrist the great persecutor of the Church, shalbe vtterly confounded and consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in this world; notwithstanding all plottes and policies, crafts and deuises to the contrary; notwithstanding all forces &amp; armies cunningly contriued and raised vp against the Church by Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Priests, Iesuites, Pope, Cardinall, and King of <hi>Spaine</hi>? For all these in this age do very busily bestirre them, and ransacke all corners of their wits to repaire the ruines of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to make vp the breaches which are made in the walles of <hi>Babylon</hi> their great citie. But alas all in vaine, for it shall fall: It shal fall: It shal fall as <hi>Dagon</hi> before the presence of the Arke, do what they can, spight of their hearts, maugre their beards: it shall fall finally: it shall without all hope of recouery: for hath the Lord spoken it, and shall it not come to passe? or can any word of his euer fall to the ground? Sith therefore the Iesuits and Secular Priests do so fiske about, and croake in euery corner, as greatly fearing the fall of their <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the drying vp of their <hi>Euphrates,</hi> it standes vs all in hand to be as resolute for Christ, as they are for Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ; and as studious to vphold the kingdome of God, as they are to vphold the kingdome of the diuel. And for this purpose it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry requisite and necessary, that all the Lords people should be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with this booke, and armed against them with the things reueald in this Prophesie. For this booke is a most precious Iewell
<pb facs="4"/>
which God hath bestowed vpon his Church in this last age: and it is great pitie that all the seruants of God are not better acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with it, especially in these times, for now in this age is and shall be the very heate of the warre, and brunt of the battell betwixt Papists and Protestants; betwixt God and <hi>Belial;</hi> betwixt the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Christ, and the armies of Antichrist. Now this Prophesie laieth all open, and plainly telleth vs what shalbe the issue and suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse in the day of battaile: which side shall haue the victory, and which side shall goe downe. And therefore very needfull it is that it should be expounded againe and againe, and all the Lords people made throughly aaquainted with it. For in this age wherein we liue, this Prophesie can neuer be inough opened and beaten vpon, that all good Protestants may bee armed with it against future times, euen as it were with an armour of proofe. S. <hi>Iohn</hi> plainly telleth the people of his time, euen the Churches of <hi>Asia,</hi> that they should be blessed by reading and studying this booke, because they should thereby be both forewarned, and forearmed against many eminent troubles and future dangers. For saith he, <hi>The time is at hand:</hi> that is to say, some things were euen then to be fulfilled. For some matters foretold in this booke, did begin to be fulfilled, euen presently after they were shewed vnto <hi>Iohn,</hi> for the mistery of iniquitie did euen then begin to worke. The Church in the Apostles time had her conflicts. The ten great persecutions began euen then to be raised vp. Heresies shortly after beganne to spring and sprout. Afterward by degrees, the great Antichrist did approach towards his cursed seate. And after all this, S. <hi>Iohn</hi> foretelleth how hee should take possession of his abhominable and most execrable seate and sea of <hi>Rome:</hi> How he should raigne and rule for a time as the Monarche of the world: How he should pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile against the Church, and make warre against the Saintes: How he should raigne but a short time, and afterward come tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling downe, as fast as euer he rose vp, and decrease as fast as euer he increased. Therefore <hi>Blessed is he</hi> (saith S. <hi>Iohn) that dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently readeth and peruseth this booke,</hi> that thereby hee may foresee all these thinges, and bee armed against them. For as the Heathen man saith; <hi>Leuius laedit quicquid praeuideris antè,</hi> Foreseeing daungers do least hurt. Now to apply all this to our
<pb facs="5"/>
times, I say they are twise happie that are studious and painfull in searching out the true sense and meaning of this Prophesie, that thereby they may be strengthned against all the assaults of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists our professed enemies, and the enemies of Gods Church, and stick fast to the euerlasting truth of God, knowing for a certaintie that these sonnes of <hi>Belial</hi> shall not long preuaile. The date of their raigne is almost out, and the time draweth on apace, wherein both they and their king <hi>Abaddon</hi> shalbe laide in the dust. But I will now proceed to a new reasō,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Apoc. 9 11.</hi>
      </note> to proue that this booke of the Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations ought not to be concealed: but openly preached and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed to the whole Church of God in this age. My reason is taken out of the <hi>22.</hi> chapter of this booke, ver. <hi>10.</hi> in these words. <hi>Seale not the words of the Prophesie of this booke, for the time is at hand.</hi> Here is a flat commandement from God, that this booke and the doctrine of it may not be sealed vp; that is to say, kept close from the knowledge of Gods people: but it must lie alwaies vnsealed, that all men may open it, read it, and see what is in it: for it is a borrowed speech, taken from sealing of Letters. For we all knowe, that when Letters are sealed, none may open them, or reade them, but onely those whom it doth concerne: but if they be of purpose left vnsealed, then any man may reade them without daunger: So the Lorde willeth and commaundeth, that this booke of the Reuelations should of purpose be left vnsealed, that all the people of God might reade it, studie it, and knowe it. If any man doubt whether the Metaphor of Sealing be thus ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the scripture, let him reade the places quoted in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Esa. 29 11. Dan. 12.9. Apoc. 4.1. Apoc. 10.4.</hi>
      </note> and in all these places hee shall finde it taken in this sense. Whereby it doth euidently appeare, that the minde and meaning of God is, that this booke should be proclaimed and published in all the Churches. And vpon this grounde, I holde that euery Minister of the Gospell standeth bounde as much as in him ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, to Preach the doctrine of the <hi>Apocalyps</hi> to his particular charge and congregation: for euery Minister of the Gospell must shewe vnto his people all the counsell of God, and keepe backe nothing: as <hi>Paul</hi> testifieth that hee did, to the great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of his conscience. But the doctrine of the Reuelations is a part and parcell of the counsell and will of God: therefore it
<pb facs="5"/>
must not be concealed or kept backe from the knowledge of the people of God. And in these dayes I thinke it not only meete and conuenient that it should be so, but in truth absolutely neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary.</p>
   <p>But now me thinketh I heare some man say: what? must this book of the <hi>Apocalyps</hi> be preached &amp; made knowne to the commō peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? alas, what should they do with it? It is not for them to meddle withall: It is not for their diet. I answere, and yet not I, but the holy Ghost: that this booke must be made knowne to all the seruāts of God. For Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> calleth it the Reuelation of Iesus Christ which God gaue him to shew vnto all his seruants.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Apoc. 1.1.</hi>
      </note> It is plaine therefore, that al the seruantes of God, both men and women, yong and old, rich and poore, must be made acquainted with this booke. Moreouer, <hi>Iohn</hi> is commaunded by the God of heauen, to set downe all the visions which the Angell shewed him: and to write them all in a booke, and send them to the seuen Churches of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sia: that is, to people of all sortes, and conditions:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Apoc. 1.11.</hi>
      </note> And therefore this booke doth not only concerne preachers, and deep diuines; but euen all the Lords people whatsoeuer: for it doth minister great comfort and strength of faith to all the people of God, that liue in this age. But here the Papists obiect that this booke is full of darkenesse and obscuritie, and therefore not for the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to meddle withall: nay, (say they) there are as many misteries, as words in it, and therefore what should men trouble their heads about it. But no maruell though the Papists say so much, for it is the wound of their kingdom, and the battery of their <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</hi> As for others, both learned and godly, which in this point are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most of the same mind, that they will not meddle with this booke of the Reuelations: I cannot but maruell at it. The modesty and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility of some, very rare and reuerend men for learning, &amp; great variety of gifts (which notwithstanding scotch much at this book) is greatly to be commended: But if I were worthy to giue them aduice, I would wish them, in this behalfe to change their minde, and to be of another resolution: for I dare auouch it, that there is nothing in this Prophesie, which study and diligence, with prayer and humility, may not ouercome. True it is indeed, that the shell is thicke, and hard to breake: but being broken, the kernell is most
<pb facs="6"/>
sweet and pleasant. If any be discouraged with the darkenesse &amp; obscurity of it, let him hearken to these reasons following. First it is called a Reuelation, which is as much to say, as an vncouering of things which did lie hid: if it be an vncouering, and reuealing of things, then no doubt it may be knowne and seene into. For re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed thinges are for vs and our children.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Deut. 19.</hi>
      </note> If it be a Reuelation, how say some that it cannot be vnderstood? For, it is contrary to the nature of a Reuelation, to be so darke that none can vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand it. But shall we say that the holy Ghost which is the spirit of truth, hath giuen a wrong name vnto it? God forbid. For if it hide matters, or so set them forth that it cannot be vnderstood, then it is not rightly called a Reuelation. If this booke be so mysticall that it cannot be vnderstood: If the interpretation of it be vncertaine: If the common people cannot be taught to vnderstand it: how then should the holy Ghost say, <hi>Blessed is he that readeth the words of this Prophesie?<note place="margin">
            <hi>Apoc. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Apoc. 22 7.</hi>
         </note> &amp;c.</hi> Let any man iudge that hath common sense: Can any man be blessed by hearing and reading those things which he vnderstandeth not? I trow no. Then it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that this booke may be vnderstood, and no doubt is vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood of many: and might bee better vnderstood of many moe, if they would bend their wittes and studies vnto it. The holy Ghost as I said before,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Apoc. 22.10.</hi>
      </note> willeth and commaundeth that the words of this Prophesie should not be sealed vp. Whereby it is euident, that he would haue them read and made knowne to all. Then I reason thus: That which is open and vnsealed, may be read and knowne: But this booke is open and vnsealed: Therefore it may be read and knowne. If men say the matters of this Prophesie are sealed and hid, and God say they be vnsealed and open, whether shall we beleeue men or God? If any shall reply &amp; say, we feele &amp; finde by experience, that the words of this booke are hard to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood: I answere, that the fault is in our selues, because we are so negligent in the search and study thereof. For if we did with that humilitie, and reuerend care that ought to be in vs, search after the things reuealed in this booke, we should finde that they be not sealed vp, but lie open to bee read and knowne. True it is indeed, that if any man light vpon some peece, and take it by it selfe, he shall finde it very darke: But if he looke vpon the whole course of matters throughout the booke, and marke and obserue diligently
<pb facs="6"/>
how things be iterated, hee shall finde no such darknesse as he fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, for there is a notable coherence of matters, and course of times obserued in this booke, euen from the first chapter vnto the last, as God willing shall more fully &amp; plainly appeare in the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular opening and interpretation thereof. One great obiection a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this Prophesie is, that the Fathers confesse it is full of my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries, and that they could not vnderstand it. If they could not vnderstand it say some, how, how shall we vnderstand it? Is it not great arrogancy for vs to say wee vnderstand it better then they did. I answer no. For a man of meane learning in comparison, may now in these daies more easily vnderstand &amp; expound this booke, then the learnedest Doctors and Fathers in auncient time. The reason is this, we liue in an age wherein the most of the things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesied in this booke are fulfilled. Now the fulfilling of a prophesie is the best exposition of it. But as for the Fathers, they liued in a time wherein many of these things were not come to passe, nor ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, and therfore more hard for them to interprete and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand: for those things in this Prophesie which are not yet fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, are hardest for vs of this age to vnderstand and resolue of. But when a Prophesie is fulfilled, it is an easie matter to say this was the meaning of the Prophet. Some things in this booke were fulfilled before the daies of the Fathers, and some thinges in the daies wherein they liued: and both those they did clearely vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand. Some things were fulfilled after their daies, as the rising and raigning of the great Antichrist, which they did not so clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly see into. Hereupon it commeth to passe, that many things which vnto them were very obscure, are vnto vs most cleare &amp; mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest: as being already fulfilled: insomuch that all which are not wilfully blinded, may see and vnderstand them, yea the most vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned. Be not therefore discouraged (gentle Reader) at the darknesse &amp; difficultie of this booke. Doe not preiudicially resolue and set downe with thy selfe, that the naturall sense of this booke cannot be giuē, nor the true meaning found out, but that we must be faine when we haue done all that we can, to rest in vncertaine coniectures, some following one sense, and some an other, as see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth most like and probable. But no man can say confidently and precisely this is the meaning of the holy Ghost. Oh be not of that minde good Christian brother: for if we haue not an vndoubted
<pb facs="7"/>
certainty for the sense &amp; meaning of this Prophesie, we are neuer the nearer: and that is it which the Papists would driue vs vnto. But know for a certainty, that the naturall sense of this booke, is to be found out, as well as of other bookes of the Scripture. And that we might not be left to our selues in the darke, and to our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine coniectures, and doubtfull interpretations; Behold the mercifull goodnesse of God to his Church, who himselfe doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the darkest, and most misticall things in this Prophesie, or at least so many of them, and so far, as the rest are thereby laid o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and made manifest. The Lord himselfe expoundeth some things in the first Chapter, which giue cleare light to the first visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: The Angell expoundeth diuers other things. In the <hi>17.</hi> Chapter, which is the key of this prophesie, the Angel doth of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, open and interpret all the greatest doubts of this booke: as who is the Whore of Babylon, who is the beast, what be his seuen heads, what be his <hi>10.</hi> hornes, what be the waters which the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that is, the Whore of Rome, sitteth vpon. Moreouer, for the better vnderstanding of this Prophesie, we must note, that the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of <hi>Moyses</hi> and the Prophets, vnto which there bee sundry allusions, and from the which sundry things are drawne, do cleare diuers things in this Reuelation. The knowledge of antiquities, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistreth much aide to the vnderstanding of this Prophesie. The knowledge of the histories of the Church, and the particular state thereof in diuers ages, bringeth great light. The obseruation of the phrases and maner of speech, vsed by the old Prophets, doth helpe also not a little. The serious and deepe weighing of all the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of the text, &amp; conferring one thing with another the cōse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents with the antecedents, &amp; the antecedents with the conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quēts, furthereth greatly for the bolting out of the true &amp; natural sense. And furthermore, as the spirit of God is the author of this prophesie, so the same spirit is the best interpreter of it, &amp; doth opē and reueale it to all such, as vsing al other good meanes are earnest and humble suters vnto God, for the illumination thereof: whereby they may vnderstand both this, and all other the myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of his will: which the Apostle saith, God hath reuealed vnto vs by his spirit:<note place="margin">
         <hi>1. Cor. 2.</hi>
      </note> For the spirit searcheth all things, yea, the deepe things of God. To all this may be added the knowledge of artes, tongues, and the learned writings, and interpretations of sundry
<pb facs="7"/>
excellent men, which all do bring great furtherance to the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding of this Prophesie. Sith then there be so many helpes for the opening and expounding of this Reuelation: why should a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny be discouraged from the reading and study thereof? But if any man demaund a reason, why Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> writeth this Reuelation in such misticall and allegoricall maner: I answere, that there may be diuers reasons yeelded hereof. First, that the world being blinded, might fulfill the things herein specified. Secondly, because <hi>Iohn</hi> was to publish this Reuelation, in such maner and forme as he had receiued it from Iesus Christ, which was figuratiue and allegoricall. Thirdly, because it was much more wisedome, to foretel the destructiō of the Romaine Empire, which al that time bare the sway, almost ouer all the world, vnder couert and figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue speeches, then in plaine tearmes, least the Romaine Princes should rage more against the Christians, euen in that respect. The like also may be said, for <hi>Daniels</hi> darke maner of deliuering his Prophesie. For if he had vttered those things in plaine tearmes, which he spake darkely and allegorically, it might haue cost him his life. For the heathen enemies would neuer haue endured to heare that all their Empires glory and renowne should fall one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another, and one by another: and that the Iewes were the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly holy people whome God did defend, and to whome in the ende, God would not onely giue a quiet possession of their owne land and kingdome: but also a kingdome euerlasting, &amp; that through their Messias and great deliuerer. But to grow to a conclusion (gentle Reader) thou shalt find in this poore trauell: First, an exposition of the first <hi>13.</hi> Chapters: after thou shalt find the next <hi>6.</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, vnto the twentith, reduced all to one head, which is to proue the <hi>5.</hi> points propounded: and last of all the <hi>3.</hi> Chapters following briefely and plainely expounded. If any through lazinesse will not, or through want of leisure cannot read ouer this short trauel: yet for his cōfort, let him read those things only which are written vpō the <hi>14.</hi> Chapter. And thus (Christian Reader) hoping that thou wilt not neglect that which may be for thine owne good, I commēd thee to God, &amp; to the word of his grace, which is able to build fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to giue thee an inheritance among all them that are sanctified.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord, Arthur Dent.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>