<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117368_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17374</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4208</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117368</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Algiers voyage : in a iournall or briefe reportary of all occurrents hapning in the fleet of ships sent out by the King his most excellent Maiestie, as well against the pirates of Algiers, as others: the whole body of the fleete consisting of 18. sayle. Viz. Sixe of his Maiesties ships. Ten marchants ships. Two pinnaces. Vnder the command of Sir Robert Mansel knight, Vice-admirall of England, and Admirall of that fleet: and a councell of warre appointed by his Maiestie. The accidents of euery particular moneth (since the first setting forth) being in this discouery, expressed by one that went along in the voyage</title>
                 <author>I. B.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Bernard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>READER,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou shalt here receiue a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full report (by way of a Iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall) of all such occurrents as fell out in the Voyage to <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giers.</hi> Those onely that were remarkeable are in this short discourse to be found, the slight ones are not worth, nor worthy of any publicatiō. Dissigns of this nature ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged by the directions of so many noble Gentlemen, a number of valiant Captains and well experienced Nauigators, secon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the courages of the other, do for the most part fill the itching eares of the world, with more then a common expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of strange things to bee done, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the possibility of man. But if he that is so curious in his inquisition, had beene but a personall aduenturer in some of the dangers which wee ran through, I make no doubt but hee would confesse hee had
<pb facs="3"/>
seene enough, and vndergone more then willingly hee could wish himselfe to bee acquainted with againe. How our ships were furnished for men or munition; what seuerall Captaines and Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were in euery one of them are heere truly set downe: the burthen also of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ship, then the dayes and months are named in which any memorable act was performed, the townes likewise within in the Straights of <hi>Gibraltar,</hi> before which our men of Warre did any seruice.</p>
   <p>And to make this Discourse the more pleasing to thee, such Spanish ships and gallyes, besides Turkish Pirates, as we encountred with at Sea, shall appeare say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, in all their gallantry before thee. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine (as thou readest) that thou hearest the Canon playing, and Turkes by hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds tumbling into the Seas, our owne stretching out hands to saue a miserable number of poore Christians made slaues to the barbarous Turke &amp; crafty Moore, but deliuered from that seruitude by vs, God assisting our labours.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>Such men of quality as either dyed or miscarryed in this Voyage, haue here the names written downe.</p>
   <p>But least the citing of particulars in this place, should alter the property of an Epistle, which (like the first day of a Terme amongst Lawyers) should be spent onely in complement, and bidding thee welcome to this feast of newes▪ I will no longer detayne thine eye from longing for that, which my paines and obserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion haue diligently collected to giue thee content, which if here thou findest, it shall be to me some part of a recompence, for those stormy dayes and nights in which I haue beene in the voyage. So farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>