<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ANSVVERE TO THE PREFACE.</title>
           <author>Wynchester, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1567</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117788_Bo1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12940</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23231</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117788</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ANSVVERE TO THE PREFACE.</title>
                 <author>Wynchester, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A counterblast to M. Hornes vayne blaste against M. Fekenham : Wherein is set forthe: a ful reply to M. Hornes Answer, and to euery part therof made, against the declaration of my L. Abbat of Westminster, M. Fekenham, touching, the Othe of the Supremacy. By perusing vvhereof shall appeare, besides the holy Scriptures, as it vvere a chronicle of the continual practise of Christes Churche in al ages and countries, fro [m] the time of Constantin the Great, vntil our daies: prouing the popes and bishops supremacy in ecclesiastical causes: and disprouing the prince supremacy in the same causes. By Thomas Stapleton student in diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Stapleton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Fowler (Fouler), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Louvain</pubPlace>
                    <date>1567</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 542, 5 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="20"/>
   <pb facs="21"/>
   <pb facs="21"/>
   <head>AN ANSVVERE TO THE PREFACE.</head>
   <div n="Horne" type="part">
      <head>THE PREFACE OF M. HORNE.</head>
      <p>It is novve an vvhole yeare past, since I heard of a book secretly scattered abroad by M. Fekenham emong his friends: And in Aprill last, I came by a Copie therof. Vvhen I had read the booke, and perceiued both the matter and the maner of the mans doings therin: I savv his proofes so slender: and his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of dealing so shameles: that I stood in doubt vvhat to do, vvhether to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer the man by vvriting, or to shake him of vvith silence. If I had not seene a further meaning in his setting forth and publishing the book (.1.)<note place="margin">
            <hi>1. The first vntruthe slāderou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cōcernīg M. Fekē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams meaning.</hi>
         </note> thē he durst plainely vtter, or then his cunning could by any meanes ansvveare vnto: or then, that I vvith a good conscience mought haue neglected: I vvoulde haue past it ouer vvith silence, as a peece of vvoorke not vvorthy of ansvvere. But seing the (.2.)<note place="margin">
            <hi>2. His chief▪ end vvas farr other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvise, as shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.</hi>
         </note> chiefe end and principal purpose intēded, as may be iustly gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in publishing the booke, vvas, to ingrafte in the mindes of the subiectes, a misliking of the Queenes Maiestie, as though shee vsurped a povver and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie in Ecclesiasticall matters, vvhereto shee hath no right: to slaunder the vvhole Realme, as though it vvere stranged and directly against the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Churche, renouncing and refusing to haue Communion therevvith: And vnder my name to deface the mynisters of Christes Churche: I could not choose, oneles I vvould vvilfully neglect my duety to her Maiestie, shevv my selfe ouermuche vnkinde vnto my natiue Countrie, and altogeather become careles of the Churche Mynisterie, but take penne in hand, and shape him a ful and plaine ansvvere, vvithout any curiositie.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="Stapleton" type="part">
      <head>T. Stapleton.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is to be knowen (gentle Reader as I as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suredly vnderstand) that the Reuerent Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, my L. Abbat of Westmynster, M. Fekenham being prisoner in the Tower, and supposing that the othe of the supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie then passed in the Parliament hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den at Westmynster in the fifte yere of the Queenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties
<pb facs="22"/>
raigne, should foorth with (as it was probable) be ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred him and others, gathered as it were in a shedule, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain reasons and causes, why he thought he could not with safe conscience, receiue the said othe. Minding to offer the said shedule, to the Commissioners if any came. The saied shedule M. Fekenham deliuered to M. Horne at Walthā, a manour place of the Bishop of Winchester in Hamshier, he being at that time there the said M. Horns prisoner, by the committie of the Queene her highnes honourable Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel: and that vpon this occasion.</p>
      <p>In M. Fekenhams abode at Waltham, there was daylie conference in matters of Religion, namely of the principall pointes of this Treatise, betwene him and M. Horne, as him selfe confesseth. In the which space, he required M. Feken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, sundry and diuers times, that he woulde by writing, open vnto him the staies of his conscience, touchinge the othe of the Queenes highnes Supremacie, being the whole matter and cause of his trouble, with no smal promises, that he should susteine no kinde of harme or iniurie therby: And in fine, if there came no furder fruit or benefitte therof vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, the whole matter should be safly folded vppe, and left in the same estate where they beganne.<note place="margin">The cause vvhy M. Fekenhā deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise to M. Horne.</note> Wherevpon M. Fekenham, thinking verely all things by him promised, to be as truely meant as spoken, made deliueraunce to M. Horne of a small Treatise, deuised by him before his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming foorth of the Tower, entituled: <hi>The Answere made by M. Iohn Fekenham, Priest and Prisoner in the Tower, to the Queenes highnes Commissioners, touching the othe of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie.</hi> With this declaration also, made vnto the said Master Horne, that vpon the passing of the said statute, he thought to haue deliuered the said Treatise, to the Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners
<pb n="2" facs="22"/>
(if any came) as the staie of his conscience, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the refusall of the foresaid othe: And forasmuche as they came not, he being as before is said, vrged and pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by the said M. Horne to open vnto him by writing, the causes forcing him to breathe, and staie vpon the taking of the foresaid othe made deliuerance of the very same Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise deuised in the Tower, with the foresaid Title and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration. Which Treatise being afterwarde encreased as wel by M. Hornes Answers, as by M. Fekenhams Replies thervnto made: after his return back againe to the Tower, he sent one copie to the right honorable the L. Erle of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester and one other to Syr William Cicil Knight and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretarie vnto the Queenes highnes, (with the same title that the printed book conteineth) both of them being deliuered by M. Lieutenant of the Tower. This shedule or litle Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise M. Horne calleth a booke▪<note place="margin">
            <hi>Fol.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 2.</note> yea and that made with the helpe of the rest: that he might seme after two yeares and more to haue done a worthy and a notable acte in answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring six poore leaues (for thereabout in M. Hornes booke amounteth the quantitie of M. Fekenhams Treatise) and to haue made a great conqueste vpon M. Fekenham and his fellowes: woorthie for this great martiall prowes to be, if al other thinges faile, a Prelate of the Garter. This his Treatise was he forced to deliuer to the right Honorables,<note place="margin">Vvhy M. F. caused the same to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered to some of the Coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell.</note> as before for his necessary purgation concerninge suche false accusations and slaunders, as Maister Horne had made and raised vppon him, as shall heereafter in more conueniente place be specified. VVherefore this beeing done as ye haue heard so plainly, so simply, and vpon such cause sheweth that M. Fekenham had no such meaning, as M. Horne here falsly surmiseth. As one, who hadde his
<pb facs="23"/>
principall and chiefe regard, how to satisfie his owne, and not other mennes consciences, howe to saue him selfe from slaunders and vntrue accusations, and not to woorke with other men by perswasion. VVherefore this is an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true and a false surmise of M. Horne: as are the other two here also, in saying that M. Fekenhā meant otherwise, then he durst plainly vtter, or by his cūning could aunswer vnto.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="Horne" type="part">
      <head>M. Horne. The 2. Diuision.</head>
      <p>Vvherein <hi>I</hi> follovv the order of M. Fekenhams booke: I make the proofes according to his request: and besides my proofes foorth of the Scriptures, the auncient Doctours, the Generall Councels and Nationall: I make proofe by the continual practise of the Church (.3)<note place="margin">
            <hi>The third vntruth. you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer proue the like gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente Namely in al Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal things and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses.</hi>
         </note> in like gouernment as the Queenes Maiestie taketh vpon her, and that by such Authors, for a great sort of them, as are the more to be credited in this matter, for that they vvere most earnest fautors of the Romish sea, infected as the times vvere, vvith much superstitiō, and did attribute vnto the see of Rome, and so to the vvhole Clergie so much authoritie in Churche matters, as they mighte, and muche more then they ought to haue done.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="Stapleton" type="part">
      <head>Stapleton.</head>
      <p>I wil not charge M Horne, that his meaning is to ingraffe in the mindes of the subiectes, a misliking of the Queenes Maiestie, as though shee vsurped a power and autoritie in Ecclesiasticall maters, whereto shee hath no right, as he chargeth M. Fekenham withal: vnlesse perchance he were of Councell with the holy brotherhode of Geneua for the Booke, whereof we shall hereafter speake that spoyleth the Queenes Maiesty of al her authority as wel tēporal as spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and vnlesse he hath in opē sermō at VVinchester main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined, cōtrary to the Quenes ecclesiastical iniunctions, such as would not reform their disordered apparel and that, after he had put his hand (as one of the Queenes cōmissioners) to the redresse of the saied disorder. And vnlesse he hath and
<pb n="3" facs="23"/>
doth maītein many things beside, yea and cōtrary to the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes and orders of the realm late set forth cōcerning maters ecclesiasticall, as it is wel knowē and to be proued he hath don as wel in the defending of the Minister of <hi>Durley,</hi> near the Manour of Bisshops Walthā refusing the saied order, as otherwise. But this may I boldy say, and I doubt nothinge to proue it, that in al his boke, there is not as much as one worde of scripture, one Doctour, one councell generall or prouincial not the practise of any one countrey throwgh owte the worlde counted Catholike, that maketh for such kinde of regiment, as M. Horne avoucheth, nor any one manner of proufe that hath any weight or pythe in the worlde to perswade, I wil not say, M. Fekenham but any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of much lesse witte, learning and experience. I say M. Horne commeth not ones nighe the principall matter and question wherein M. Fekenhā would and of right ought to be resolued. I say further in case we remoue and sequester al other proufes on oure syde, that M. Horn shal by the very same fathers, councels, and other authorities by him felfe producted so be ouerthrowen in the chief and capital que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion (vnto the which he cometh not nighe as a man might say, by one thowsande myles) that his owne company may haue iuste cause to feare least this noble blaste so valiantly and skilfully blowen owte of M. Hornes trompet shall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gender in the harts of all indifferent and discrete Readers, much cause to mistruste, more thē they did before the whol matter, that M. Horne hath taken in hande to iustifie.</p>
      <p>Wherefore as it is mete in al matters so is it here also cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniēt and necessary to haue before thyne eyes, good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the state and principal question controuersed betwene the parties standing in variance: And then diligently to see,
<pb facs="24"/>
how the proufes are of eche party applied, for the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of their assertions.</p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">The prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stions cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stical regi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, vvhich M. Horn doth not on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che.</note>There are therfore in this cause many things to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered. Firste that Christe lefte one to rule his whole Churche in his steade from tyme to tyme vnto the ende of the worlde. Secondly that this one was Saint Peter the Apostle, and now are the Bisshoppes of Rome his succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sours. Thirdly that albeit the Bisshop of Rome had no such vniuersal gouernment ouer the whole, yet that he is and euer was, the patriarche of Englande and of the whole weste Church, and so hath as muche to doe here as any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther patriarche in his patriarkshippe. Then that all were it, that he had nothing to intermedle with vs nor as Pope, nor as patriarche, yet can not this supremacy of a ciuil prince be iustified: whereof he is not capable especiallye a woman, but it must remayne in some spiritual man. Beside this the Catholikes say,<note place="margin">No such regiment as M. Horne defēdeth among al the sectes sauing in England.</note> that as there was neuer any suche presidēte heretofore in the Catholike Churche: so at this present there is no such (except in England) neither emonge the Lutherans, the Zwinglians, the Swenckfeldians or Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tistes, nor any other secte that at this daye raygneth or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth in the worlde. None of these I saye agnise their cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil prince, as supreame gouernour in al causes spiritual and temporal: Last of al I say and M. Fekenham wil also saye that euen M. Horne him selfe in this his answere retreyteth so farre backe from this assertion of supreame gouernment in all causes spirituall and temporall,<note place="margin">M. Horne himselfe denieth this supre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>macie in al causes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>cclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stical.</note> whiche is the state and keye of the whole question, that he plucketh from the prince the chief and principal matters and causes ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall, as we shall here after plainely shewe by his owne woordes.</p>
      <p>
         <pb n="4" facs="24"/>The premisses then being true, and of owre syde abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly proued, and better to be proued, as occasion shall serue, as nothing can effectually be brought against them, so M Horne, as ye shal euidently perceiue in the processe, stragleth quyte from al these points, besetting himselfe, all his study and endeuor, to proue that which neither great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hyndereth oure cause, nor much bettereth his: and for the which neither maister Fekenham nor any other Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like will greatly contende with him: whiche is when all is done, <hi>that Princes may medle and deale with causes eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall.</hi> Which as it is in some meaning true, so dothe yt nothing reache home to the pointe most to haue bene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated vpon. And so is much labour vaynely and idlelye employed, with tediouse and infynite talke and bablinge, all from the purpose, and owte of the matter, whiche ought speciallye to haue bene iustifyed. And therefore this is but an impudente facing and bragging to say, that he hath proued the like regiment that we deny, by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by the Councels, and by the continual practise of the Churche.</p>
      <p>Now it is worthy to see the iolye pollicy of this man, and howe euen and correspondent it is to his fellowe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants.<note place="margin">The vne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the prote<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stants.</note> M. Iewel restrayneth the Catholikes to <hi>.600.</hi> yeres as it were by an extraordinary and newe founde prescrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his owne, embarringe al Later proufes. Yet he him selfe in the meane tyme runneth at large, almoste one thowsande yeares Later, shrynkinge hither and thyther, taking tagge and ragge, heretike and Catholik, for the forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of his false assertions. This wise trade this man kepeth also, and to resolue M. Fekenham, and setle his conscience, he specially stayeth him self vpon <hi>Platina, Nauclerus, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas
<pb facs="25"/>
Vrspergensis, Sabellicus, Aeneas pius, Volaterranus, Fabian, Polichronicon, Petrus Bertrandus, Benno</hi> the Cardinal, <hi>Durā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, P. Aemilius, Martinus poenitentiarius, Polidorus Virgilius.</hi> And such lyke as he him self declareth otherwhere and in this place also confesseth. Nowe all be it the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques refuse no Catholique writer, nor in this matter haue cause so to doe, yet in a matter of such importance, which beside the losse of al tēporal relief and besyde bodily death importeth also euerlasting damnation to the Catholikes, (if the case stande, as M. Horne and his fellowes beare vs in hande) reason would he should haue fetched the substance of his proufes much higher, yea within the <hi>.600.</hi> yeres wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto they strayne and binde vs: The which the Catholikes haue already performed against M. Iewel, not in the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of the matter onely, but euen in the iustifying of the precise wordes, wherein M. Iewel hathe framed to himself by a foolish wylynes, or wylye foolyshnes, the state of the question I meane for the wordes of <hi>head of the Church,</hi> and <hi>vniuersall Busshop.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>And what if M Fekenham nowe Syr would reuel with yow with lyke rhetorike, and require of yow to proue by the fathers writing within the sayde <hi>.600.</hi> yeares these ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse words:<note place="margin">A chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge to M. Horn.</note>
         <hi>Supreame heade, or gouernour in all causes spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and temporal,</hi> to haue bene geuen and attributed to any ciuil Magistrate? Againe that the temporal men without, yea and against the consent of the whole clergy, altered the state of religiō called and vsed for Catholik throughout the whole corps of Christendome one thousande yeares before with such other articles, as concerne the regiment Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticall that ye, in this your booke defende? Ye haue not, no nor ye can not, proue any such matter either by expres
<pb n="5" facs="25"/>
wordes or by any good induction or consequēt in the first and former Fathers. And yet somwhat were it, if the Later Fathers might helpe yow.</p>
      <p>But what an impudent face, as harde as any horne or stone haue ye beside your mere foly, to make the worlde belieue, that the authours aforesayde allowed such kinde of regiment of ciuill Princes, as the Catholikes now denye? Whiche assertion is so certainely and notoriously false, that M. Horne him self can not, nor doth not deny, but that his owne authours,<note place="margin">M Horns tale incre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dible,</note> were <hi>moste earnest fautours of the See of Rome.</hi> And howe then maye it ones be thoughte by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wise man that they shoulde allowe the doings of suche that forsake and abandon al maner of authority of that See, further then is the cōmen authority of al other Bisshops, yea and make the Bisshop of that Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> to whome the sayde au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors attribute so large and ample authoritye and preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue as may be, and whome they agnise as supreame iudge in matters of faith, a very Antichriste? These things be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible, these things (as the prouerbe is) hange together like germans lipps: and so shal ye, good Readers,<note place="margin">M. Horn's late bragge.</note> see the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter most euidently fal owte. And therefore, M. Horne, where you haue of late openlye sittinge at a table in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don (as I am credibly informed) bragged, that ye haue quyte cōfuted the Papists with their own papistical Doctors, how true this is, I trust it shall by this answere plainely appeare.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="Horne" type="part">
      <head>M. Horne. The <hi>3.</hi> Diuision.</head>
      <p>Their iudgements and sentences shal appeare in reading by the forme of letter: for leuing foorth the Latine to auoide tediousnes, <hi>4.</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>The 4 vntruthe For he vvrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leageth both the vvordes and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours.</hi>
         </note> I haue putte into English the Authours mindes and sentences, and caused them, for the moste parte, to be Printed in Latine letters, that the English reader may knovv and decerne the Authours sayings from mine.</p>
      <floatingText type="letter">
         <body>
            <p>If this that I haue done, vvorke that effect in the Englishe Reader, vvhich
<pb facs="26"/>
he ought to seeke, and I d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvishe, <hi>I</hi> haue vvonne that <hi>I</hi> wrought for: but otherwise, let men say and iudge what they liste, <hi>I</hi> haue discharged my consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and shewed the trueth. Anno Domini. <hi>1565.</hi> Feb. 25.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Rob. Wynchester.</signed>
            </closer>
         </body>
      </floatingText>
   </div>
   <div n="Stapleton" type="part">
      <head>Stapleton.</head>
      <p>A great vntruth. For M. Horne doth not faithfully, but most corruptly and falsly alleage the authours wordes, and vseth his owne in steade of theirs: and to suche as he truely reherseth, he geueth an vnmete and an improbable sense of his own making, as we shal particularly notifye, when the case re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>