<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READERS.</title>
           <author>H., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117705_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13759</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24058</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117705</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READERS.</title>
                 <author>H., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Eight bookes of the Peloponnesian Warre written by Thucydides the sonne of Olorus. Interpreted with faith and diligence immediately out of the Greeke by Thomas Hobbes secretary to ye late Earle of Deuonshire</title>
                 <author>Thucydides</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <distributor>Seile (Seale, Seely, Seyle), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 536, that is 535, 13 pages, 5 plates (3 folded), maps, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE READERS.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough this <hi>Translation</hi> haue already past the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of some, whose Iudgements I very much esteeme; yet, because there is something, I know not what, in the censure of a Multitude, more terrible then any single Iudgement, how seuere or exact soeuer, I haue thought it discretion in all men, that haue to doe with so many, and to me, in my want of perfection, necessary, to bespeake your Candor. Which that I may vpon the better reason hope for, I am willing to acquaint you briefly, vpon what grounds I vndertooke this Worke at first; and haue since, by publishing it, put my selfe vpon the hazard of your censure, with so small hope of glory, as from a thing of this nature can be expected. For I know, that meere Translations, haue in them this property, that they may much disgrace, if not well done; but if well, not much commend the doer.</p>
   <p>It hath beene noted by diuers, that <hi>Homer</hi> in <hi>Poesie, Aristotle</hi> in <hi>Philosophy, Demosthenes</hi> in <hi>Eloquence,</hi> and others of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, in other knowledge, doe still maintaine their Primacy, none of them exceeded, some not approached, by any, in these later Ages. And in the number of these, is iustly ranked also our <hi>Thucydides;</hi> a Workeman no lesse perfect in his worke, then any of the former; and in whom (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue with many others) the Faculty of writing History is at the highest. For the <hi>principall</hi> and <hi>proper worke</hi> of History, being to instruct, and enable men, by the knowledge of Actions <hi>past,</hi> to beare themselues prudently in the <hi>present,</hi> and prouidently towards the <hi>Future,</hi> there is not extant any other (meerely humane) that doth more fully, and natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performe it, then this of my Author. It is true, that there be many excellent and profitable Histories written since; and in some of them, there be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serted very wise discourses, both of <hi>Manners</hi> and <hi>Policie.</hi> But being discourses inserted, and not of the contexture of the Narration, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed commend the knowledge of the Writer, but not the History it selfe, the nature whereof, is meerely narratiue. In others, there bee subtile coniectures, at the secret aymes, and inward cogitations of such as fall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Penne; which is also none of the least vertues in a History,
<pb facs="5"/>
where the coniecture is throughly grounded, not forced to serue the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of the Writer, in adorning his stile, or manifesting his subtilty in coniecturing. But these coniectures cannot often be certaine, vnlesse withall so euident, that the narration it selfe may be sufficient to suggest the same also to the Reader. But <hi>Thucydides</hi> is one, who, though he neuer digresse to reade a Lecture, Morall or Politicall, vpon his owne Text, nor enter into mens hearts, further then the actions them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues euidently guide him, is yet accounted the most Politique Historio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grapher that euer writ. The reason whereof I take to bee this: He fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his Narrations with that choice of matter, and ordereth them with that Iudgement, and with such perspicuity and efficacy expresseth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, that, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> saith, he maketh his <hi>Auditor</hi> a <hi>Spectator.</hi> For he settteh his Reader in the <hi>Assemblies</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> and in the <hi>Senates,</hi> at their debating; in the <hi>Streets,</hi> at their Seditions; and in the <hi>Field</hi> at their Battels. So that looke how much a man of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, might haue added to his experience, if he had then liued, a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder of their proceedings, and familiar with the men, and businesse of the time; so much almost may he profit now, by attentiue reading of the same here written. He may from the narrations draw out lessons to himselfe, and of himselfe be able, to trace the drifts and counsailes of the Actors to their seate.</p>
   <p>These Vertues of my Author did so take my affection, that they begat in me a desire to communicate him further; which was the first occasion that moued mee to translate him. For it is an errour we easily fall into, to beleeue, that whatsoeuer pleaseth vs, will be, in like manner and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, acceptable to all; and to esteeme of one anothers Iudgement, as we agree in the liking, or dislike of the same things. And in this errour per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture was I, when I thought, that as many of the more iudicious, as I should communicate him to, would affect him as much as I my selfe did. I considered also, that he was exceedingly esteemed of the <hi>Italians</hi> and <hi>French</hi> in their owne Tongues; notwithstanding that he bee not very much beholding for it to his Interpreters. Of whom (to speake no more then becomes a Candidate of your good opinion in the same kinde) I may say this, That whereas the Author himselfe, so carrieth with him his owne light throughout, that the Reader may continually see his way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and by that which goeth before, expect what is to follow, I found it not so in them. The cause whereof, and their excuse may bee this: They followed the <hi>Latine</hi> of <hi>Laurentius Valla,</hi> which was not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out some errours, and he a <hi>Greeke</hi> Copie, not so correct as now is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant. Out of <hi>French</hi> hee was done into <hi>English,</hi> (for I neede not dissemble to haue seene him in <hi>English</hi>) in the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the sixth; but so, as by multiplication of errour, hee became at length
<pb facs="5"/>
traduced, rather then translated into our Language. Hereupon I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solued to take him immediately from the <hi>Greeke,</hi> according to the Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Aemilius Porta;</hi> not refusing, or neglecting any version, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or other helpe I could come by. Knowing that when with <hi>Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> and <hi>Leasure</hi> I should haue done it, though some error might re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maine, yet they would be errors but of one descent; of which neuerthelesse I can discouer none, and hope they bee not many. After I had finished it, it lay long by mee, and other reasons taking place, my desire to communi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cate it ceased.</p>
   <p>For I saw, that, for the greatest part, men came to the reading of Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story, with an affection much like that of the <hi>People,</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> who came to the spectacle of the <hi>Gladiators,</hi> with more delight to behold their bloud, then their Skill in Fencing. For they be farre more in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that loue to read of great Armies, bloudy Battels, and many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands slaine at once, then that minde the <hi>Art,</hi> by which, the Affaires, both of Armies, and Cities, be conducted to their ends. I obserued like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, that there were not many, whose eares were well accustomed to the names of the places they shall meet with in this Histroy; without the knowledge whereof, it can neither patiently be read ouer, perfectly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood, nor easily remembred; Especially being many, as heere it falleth out; because in that Age, almost euery City, both in <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Sicily,</hi> the two maine scenes of this Warre, was a distinct Common wealth by it selfe, and a party in the Quarrell.</p>
   <p>Neuerthelesse I haue thought since, that the former of these conside<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rations ought not to be of any weight at all, to him that can content him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe with the <hi>Few</hi> and <hi>better</hi> sort of Readers; who, as they onley iudge, so is their approbation onely considerable. And for the difficulty arising from the ignorance of places, I thought it not so insuperable, but that with conuenient pictures of the Countries it might be remoaed. To which purpose, I saw there would be necessary, especially two; a Gene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rall Mappe of <hi>Greece,</hi> and a Generall Mappe of <hi>Sicily.</hi> The latter of these, I found already extant, exactly done, by <hi>Philip Cluuerius;</hi> which I haue caused to be cut, and you haue it at the beginning of the Sixth Booke. But for Mappes of <hi>Greece,</hi> sufficient for this purpose, I could light on none. For neither are the <hi>Tables</hi> of <hi>Ptolomie▪</hi> and descripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of those that follow him, accommodate to the time of <hi>Thucydides</hi>; and therefore few of the Places by him mentioned, therein described: nor are those that bee, agreeing alwayes with the truth of History. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was constrained to draw one (as well as I could) my selfe. Which to doe, I was to rely, for the maine Figure of the Countrey, on the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne description now in reputation; and in that to set downe those Places especially (as many as the Volume was capable of) which occurre in the
<pb facs="6"/>
reading of this Author, and to assigne them that situation, which, by trauell in <hi>Strabo, Pausanias, Herodotus,</hi> and some other good Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, I saw belonged vnto them. And to shew you that I haue not played the Mountibanke in it, putting downe exactly some few of the Principall, and the rest at aduenture, without care, and without reason, I haue ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the Mappe an <hi>Index,</hi> that pointeth to the Authors which will iustifie me, where I differ from others. With these Mappes, and those few briefe notes in the Margine, vpon such passages, as I thought most required them, I supposed the History might be read with very much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, by all men of good Iudgement and Education, (for whom also it was intended from the beginning by <hi>Thucydides)</hi> and haue therefore at length made my Labour publike, not without hope to haue it accepted. Which if I obtaine, though no otherwise then in vertue of the Authors excellent matter, it is sufficient.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>T. H.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>