<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRI∣STIAN READER.</title>
           <author>P., C.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117983_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14091</idno>
           <idno type="STC">244</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117983</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRI∣STIAN READER.</title>
                 <author>P., C.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The iust and necessary apologie of Henrie Airay the late reuerend prouost of Queenes Colledge in Oxford : touching his suite in law for the rectorie of Charleton</title>
                 <author>Airay, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 <publisher>Bladen, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 44, 2, 13, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIAN READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the rule be true, <hi>Convicia spreta exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lescunt, si irascâre ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnita videntur,</hi> Iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious accusations are best answered by silence and neglect; yet then to be silent when the imputation is verie grieuous and most vniust, were both to wrong the truth, and wilfully to betray a good name. Besides, not to be sensible of deepe wounds inflicted vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our reputation, is not patience, but dull stupiditie. How much the licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
<pb facs="3"/>
tongues of some, and vnchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table conceits of others haue wronged this reuerend and worthy man (now with the Lord) will appeare by this his owne Treatise; which containes a plaine and naked declaration of that intricate controuersie, and acquaints the ignorant or scrupulous in this case vpon what grounds of Law, but espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of conscience, be first vndertooke the suite: quitting euery obiection with such a sufficient answer, as, I doubt not, will giue good satisfaction to the indifferent and impartiall. His maine purpose in composing this Treatise, was to cleare his owne innocencie (without any offence, I hope, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,) and to auoide the rash con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions of some, who are wont first to censure, and then to enquire. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto I haue suppressed it, hoping
<pb facs="3"/>
that his eminent credit in the Church of God, would quickly (of it selfe) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume the envie and vanitie of this weake exception, and so with honour outliue it. But seeing (as by many his religious friends I vnderstand) he cannot yet rest quietly in his graue, this cauill being often (vpon occasion) and odiously renewed, cast in like a dead flie to corrupt the sweete oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his blessed memorie, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed as a thicke vapour to obscure the lustre of his good name: I cannot (without palpable and irreparable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie) any longer forbeare to put forth his owne shield for protection of his guiltlesse fame, which lyes bleeding vnder the mercilesse strokes of intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate tongues, whereof some (I feare) through his sides aime at the disgrace of religion. His worthy fauourers
<pb facs="4"/>
euery where see it with commisera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but know not how to remedie it: it is high time therefore to let him speake for himselfe. For where calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious accusations are so loud and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, it were more then pittie that <hi>iust Apologies</hi> should be dumbe and smo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered. I haue therefore published it in his owne words, without the least alteration, and do commend it to Gods blessing and thy louing acceptation. Peruse it without passion, and then (I doubt not) thou wilt in iudgement acquit the Author, who for his inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie was generally and iustly reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>C. P.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>