<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>B., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1177_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08598</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1891.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1177</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>B., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The harmonie of holie scriptures : VVith the seuerall sentences of sundry learned and vvorthy vvriters. Collected for the comfort of all such as are desirous to seeke after theyr soules health. By I.B</title>
                 <author>Bentley, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                    <distributor>Ling (Lyng), Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 529, 13 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>SInce it hath beene obserued as a custome (curteous Reader) in all times heeretofore, that in the publication of bookes, some method or other of the VVriters meaning, should be expressed for the Readers better vnderstanding: I, being bound (as it were) to that ceremony, though no way distrustfull of thy kind opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and iudgement, first, wishing thy health and happinesse in Christ, and next intreating thy christianlike con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration of mee and this present la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, pray thee to take notice of these few lines following.</p>
   <p>These gathered places out of the most sacred Scriptures, marshalled in the best manner that I could deuise, concerning those nine necessarie poynts, which in the page next after this Epistle are more at large expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned;
<pb facs="5"/> likewise the graue &amp; religious Sentences of the Doctors &amp; Fathers, as also the sweete sayings of sundr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Philosophers: Though they haue cost me more paines then here I will expresse, &amp; haue proued to my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, as I pray they may to thine, yet if thy freendly acceptance aunswere but my good meaning, &amp; ouer-rash reading deliuer not as rude censu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, I doubt not but our benefite hereby will proue both alike; and all redound to his honour, in whose re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence it was vndertaken.</p>
   <p>If thou demaund a reason, why I entitle it by the name of <hi>The Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of holy Scriptures,</hi> my aunswere is, that all the sentences heerein sette downe, both in sounde, sence, and sweetnes, doe sauour of a musicall imitation, and concord together af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the nature of a diuine harmonie, as from the beginning to the end of each section thou maist easily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue.
<pb facs="5"/> Secondly, as in Musique, be there neuer so many parts, yet all must agree &amp; make a perfect Vnison: euen so do these aunswere to one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other as in report, all tending to one effect and purpose, and all at full ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing the argument handled. First the Scriptures being the ground and plaine-song, the Doctors following thereon in sweet diuine descant, and the Philosophers bearing a by part a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong to make vp the melodie, and all in one sound, sing to Gods glory.</p>
   <p>As for the Heathen authorities heerein alleaged, albeit they expresse not onely singuler wisedome, but likewise sauour of a very deuoute (though ignorant) zeale: they are not inserted with any intent in mee, that by them should be prooued the very least principle of Christian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; but rather to declare, howe neere such men as came short of any right knowledge of God, yet by the
<pb facs="6"/> bare light of Nature onely, aymed at the truth; and made a kinde of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious vse to themselues, of a further desire to know that truth.</p>
   <p>If in the first poynt handled, it shall be obiected, that I haue not so iustly obserued the order of an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, as in the other following, by vsing needles wordes of the Fathers, as saith such a one, and such a one: I did the more willingly slip from my course in that case, because the words are none of mine owne, and I could not (in my conceit) giue right enough to them that owed them, or sufficiently deliuer, howe soundlie their sentences approued euery allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged place.</p>
   <p>Now, if any nice eare, (whom no note can please, &amp; to whom the very best musique seemeth vnpleasant,) shall in this flowing age of right skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Maisters in Gods musicke, whose number (for his Names sake) may
<pb facs="6"/> hee more and more increase; if such a one I say, doe obiect what I freelie confesse, that here wanteth such arte &amp; schollarship, as such a serious sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect worthily deserued: let me thus aunswere for my selfe; As there be maister workmen in Gods buildings, so there must be some to cary stones, lime and morter, of which place nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther though I account my selfe any way worthy, yet let not the poorest labourers paines in such a seruice be despised. I did it diuers yeeres since for my owne instruction, &amp; thought to haue kept it onely for my priuate comfort, till others thinking better thereof then I my selfe can, woulde needes preuaile with mee to haue it published: which since I coulde not well denie, let this serue for all obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions whatsoeuer. The reuerend re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of Gods Name, in me both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan and finished the work, desire to benefite others as simple as my selfe,
<pb facs="7"/> was the cheefe marke I aymed at, &amp; the hope I haue that some good may ensue heereof, is the onely recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence I request for my paines. Hee then that began and ended, thou that readest and art comforted, all that see my good intent and there-with are pleased; First his blessed Name be honoured, thy comfort daily increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, &amp; all our saiths for euer through Iesus Christ established.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine</hi> I. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>