<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Stocke, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117808_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12983</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23276</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117808</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Stocke, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse, the second of Nouember. 1606. By Richard Stocke, preacher of Al-hallowes, Bread-streete, London</title>
                 <author>Stock, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Welby, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Weaver (Wever), Edmund</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 75, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>¶ To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, thou hast heere from mee a Sermon, as the Sea in a storme hath the Marchants goods, willingly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst my will. When I prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched it, manie were verie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant with mee to print it: but I was then as peremptorie in the denyall, &amp; thought neuer to haue brought it againe into viewe and sight of men. But the iniquities of the times are such, that some men for their gaine care not what preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice and iniurie they doe vnto others. Wherevpon some hauing copies of this slender labour of myne, though verie imperfect, and of some other things of farre greater quantitie in themselues, and of labour to mee, &amp; those things, whose impression would haue cost them a great summe; yet haue gone about to seek the allowance of them without my priuitie &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: and had I not had a friend in place, they had at the least obtained an allowance of them, though happely I might haue got knowledge of it, before they had printed much of them.</p>
   <p>Now this thing, being short and small, might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pely
<pb facs="8"/>some haue passed and beene speedily printed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I should haue had notice of it, &amp; that with such imperfections as would haue bene small to my credit, and as little to thy contentment. Wherefore I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solued, being importuned by some, to seeke forth my owne Copie; which in probabilitie is like to haue lesse imperfections then anie which they had. Which as in speaking, so in printing. I purpose not to make any pleasant illurement or inticement, but a remedie &amp; medicine rather, which should not so much please the cares of the idle and curious, as profite the mindes of the sickely and weake: which if I can compasse, I shall account it a great fruit of my labours. But if it happen not, I shall not thinke I haue laboured in vaine; seeing I assayed and endeuored to haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited. For happely with men, but certainely with God,<note place="margin">De duplici Martyrio.</note> it is as <hi>Cyprian</hi> speaketh, (if <hi>Cyprian</hi>) <hi>Deus non aestimat quenquā ex eventu rerum, sed ex affectu.</hi> Not the fruit of their labours, but the affection of mens hearts gets them respect with God. To whose blessing I commend thee: and this poore mite, I offer to the treasurie of the Lordes temple.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine, in Christ Iesus,</hi> Rich. Stocke.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>