<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE TESTIMONIE OF SABAEUS AMNIANUS, touching Mariano Silesio; with his judgement of his Worke, enti∣tuled, The Arcadian Princesse; or, The triumph of Iustice.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117416_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12245</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22553</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117416</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE TESTIMONIE OF SABAEUS AMNIANUS, touching Mariano Silesio; with his judgement of his Worke, enti∣tuled, The Arcadian Princesse; or, The triumph of Iustice.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Arcadian princesse; or, The triumph of iustice : prescribing excellent rules of physicke, for a sicke iustice. Digested into fowre bookes, and faithfully rendred to the originall Italian copy, by Ri. Brathvvait Esq</title>
                 <author>Silesio, Mariano</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Bostock, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 192, 191-254, 250, 8 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>THE TESTIMONIE OF SABAEUS AMNIANUS, touching <hi>Mariano Silesio;</hi> with his judgement of his Worke, enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>The Arcadian Princesse;</hi> or, <hi>The triumph of Iustice.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat pregnancy of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, and gravity of judgement, that Learned Florentine <hi>Silesio</hi> expressed, may appeare by those excellent Labours of his: wherein hee addressed his Penne to Subjects of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers natures, according to those occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sionall employments, wherein hee stood engaged. His youth hee bestowed in
<pb facs="7"/>
Poesy; wherein he shewed that vivaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and quicknesse: as the Court of <hi>Florence</hi> resounded with the fame of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>imensions. In his riper yeares, hee became employed in affaires of high consequence: being twice elected by the vote and suffrage of the whole State for an Embassador to the <hi>Genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eses:</hi> where hee demeaned himselfe in such sort, as hee was with no lesse cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious observance admired abroad, than with all honour entertained at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne home. But growing old, and wearied with the mannagement of publique affayres: hee desired to retire, and in his retirement to addresse the remainder of his dayes to some profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble workes which might live in his death, and to posterity revivè the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of his life. Amongst which, hee composed a worke (in my iudgement) of exquisite wit, entituled the <hi>Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian Princesse:</hi> wherin hoth <hi>language,</hi> and <hi>Invention</hi> discovered their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster-piece. He dyed <hi>An▪ Dom. 1368.</hi> And interred with great solemnity in the <hi>Latmian arch.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>