<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>D., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117484_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20588</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6990</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117484</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>D., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon preached in the cathedrall church of Yorke : against popish transubstantiation, and their communion vnder one kinde, the first Sunday in Lent, Ann. Dom. 1607. By Thomas Dodson, Maister of artes</title>
                 <author>Dodson, Thomas, Master of Arts</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Lownes, Matthew</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, I haue here set down (so neere as I could remember) whatsoeuer was spoken in deliuering this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: yea, and more matter then the time suffered; but not more then was purposed to bee vttered. For being gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced beyond expectation with the gratious presence of the most reuerend Father in God the Lord Archb. of <hi>Yorke</hi> his Grace, after his paines taken according to godlinesse else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in the Citie; I was in regard thereof rather contented abruptly to end, then to be troublesome: whereupon partly, but espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to profit such abroad as hauing eares to heare, and soules to saue, do want instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, I became resolued to penne this my then exercise, and to put it into print. Now iudge not rashly (gentle Reader) I most hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily desire thee, in that I being the vnworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est of many hundreths, and the vnablest of
<pb facs="4"/> many thousands, haue taken vpon me to set forth, and to publish any thing, to the open light and sight of the world: for wee knowe, that the poore Widdowes mite (where God is made Vmpire) shall not bee refused. And the Lord the searcher of the harts and reines, knoweth my purpose and affection in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and publishing this matter: wherein, if any thing be amisse (my amisse once discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the pen of the learned) <hi>Peccaui</hi> shal be my Plea: for <hi>haereticū me esse nolo.</hi> Thus I leaue thee, committing this my simple labour vnto the blessing of Gods holy spirit: who grant vs a right vnderstanding heart, with a charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble friendly Iudgement in all things.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>T. D.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>