<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE THOMAS, Earle of Exceter, Knight of the most Noble Order of the Garter, and one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuie Counsell: Grace, and Peace.</title>
           <author>Hill, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117083_Fr4_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03356</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13474</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117083</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE THOMAS, Earle of Exceter, Knight of the most Noble Order of the Garter, and one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuie Counsell: Grace, and Peace.</title>
                 <author>Hill, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pathvvay to prayer and pietie : Containing, 1 An exposition of the Lords Prayer, with an apologie for publicke, and priuate set prayer. 2 A preparation to the Lords Supper, with Ma. Zanchius confession, concerning that sacrament. 3 A direction to a Christian life, bot in our generall and particular callings. 4 An instruction to die well, and a consolation against all crosses. With diuers prayers, and thankesgiuings fit for this treatise. By Robert Hill, Doctor in Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Hill, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <distributor>Barrett, William</distributor>
                            <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40, 141, 17, 110, 8, 111-344 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="159"/>
   <pb facs="159"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE THOMAS, Earle of <hi>Exceter,</hi> Knight of the most Noble Order of the Garter, and one of <hi>his Maiesties most Honourable</hi> Priuie Counsell: Grace, and Peace.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable: Although it be appointed that all <hi>must die,</hi> yet the most put farre from them that <hi>euill day.</hi> It is certaine, we must haue an end: and the remembrance of it keepes vs from sinne. The goodliest <hi>Cities</hi> haue beene equalled with the <hi>ground,</hi> the state<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liest <hi>buildings</hi> leuelled with the <hi>earth,</hi> the greatest <hi>Empires</hi> brought to <hi>nothing,</hi> the <hi>Kings</hi> of the earth haue beene bound in <hi>chaines,</hi> and their <hi>Nobles</hi> in fetters of <hi>iron:</hi> We all waxe <hi>olde</hi> as doth a <hi>garment,</hi>
      <pb facs="160"/> wee <hi>dwell</hi> heere as in <hi>houses of clay,</hi> our breath <hi>passeth</hi> away, and wee are <hi>gone.</hi> Where is <hi>Methushelah,</hi> with all his yeeres? <hi>Sampson</hi> with all his <hi>strength? Absolom</hi> with all his <hi>beauty? Salomon</hi> with all his <hi>wisdome? Dauid</hi> with all his <hi>victories?</hi> or <hi>Croesus</hi> with all his <hi>wealth?</hi> Are wee in our <hi>yong age?</hi> till thirty, we may bee sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted with <hi>a good morrow:</hi> are we in our <hi>full age?</hi> till fifty, wee are saluted with a <hi>good day:</hi> are wee in our <hi>old age?</hi> wee must take it patiently, that we are then salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with, <hi>God send you good rest.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I haue <hi>seene</hi> (saith <hi>Dauid</hi>) an end of all <hi>perfection:</hi> and happy are they that haue <hi>Dauids</hi> eyes. But all men haue not this sight; the <hi>god</hi> of this world hath so blindfolded many, that if they bee <hi>young,</hi> they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not see death at their <hi>backes:</hi> if <hi>old</hi> they will not see it before their <hi>eies.</hi> Wee would <hi>mourne,</hi> if wee knew wee should liue but a <hi>moneth:</hi> wee <hi>laugh,</hi> when, it may bee, wee shall not liue one <hi>day.</hi>
   </p>
   <q>
      <l>
         <hi>Heu! viuunt homines tanquam mors nulla sequatur,</hi>
      </l>
      <pb facs="160"/>
      <l>
         <hi>Et velut infernus fabula vana foret.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Alas! men liue as though they should not die:</l>
      <l>And as if hell were nothing but a lie.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Ambitiosus honos, &amp; opes, &amp; foeda voluptas,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Haec tria pro trino numine mundus amat.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Vaine pompe, and wealth, and luxurie,</l>
      <l>The worldling makes his trinitie.</l>
   </q>
   <p>To the end therefore that all men might thinke of their <hi>end,</hi> I haue published this <hi>Direction to die well.</hi> And though this small <hi>mite,</hi> be not worthy to come into your rich <hi>Treasurie,</hi> yet am I bold to cast it in: and because it is all I can giue at this time, I most humbly beseech you to giue it enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment.</p>
   <p>You haue <hi>gained</hi> much in this present <hi>world:</hi> but you haue esteemed <hi>godlinesse</hi> the greatest <hi>gaine:</hi> and, with that blessed Apostle Saint <hi>Paul, You account all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hings to be but dung, to the ende you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ight winne Christ.</hi> And though it hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>leased God to giue vnto you great <hi>riches</hi> in
<pb facs="161"/> this world, yet am I perswaded, that the remembrance of <hi>death</hi> is not <hi>bitter</hi> vnto you:<note place="margin">Eccl. 41.1.</note> for as you are not <hi>ashamed</hi> to liue, so you are not <hi>afraide</hi> to die. You waite for it, because by her two Harbengers, <hi>Sickenesse,</hi> and <hi>Old age,</hi> it euer waiteth vpon you.</p>
   <p>Heere you <hi>sow</hi> liberally, that hereafter you may <hi>reape</hi> plentifully: you cast your <hi>bread</hi> vpon the <hi>waters,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eccl. 11.2.</note> after many daies you are sure to find it. And if he hath his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for a <hi>cuppe</hi> of cold <hi>water;</hi> you who deale your bread to the <hi>hungrie,</hi> who bring the wandring <hi>poore</hi> to your <hi>house,</hi> who see the <hi>naked</hi> and <hi>couer</hi> him, and hide not your <hi>selfe</hi> from your owne <hi>flesh</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Esai. 58.7.</note>: you, Right Honourable, shall not want your <hi>reward.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">2. Chr. 30.22.</note>And seeing you (with good King <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi>) speake comfortably to euery poore and painefull <hi>Leuite;</hi> how should they but speak honourably of you? The Lord grant th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> that <hi>sheafe</hi> of your family, may euer be like vnto <hi>Iosephs</hi> sheafe, and euery day grow to a greater increase of <hi>fruitfulnesse,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gen. 37.7.</note> till it be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fitted as a <hi>ricke of Corne</hi> for the Lord <hi>Barne:</hi> and he grant vnto you a <hi>long</hi> life,
<pb facs="161"/>
      <hi>godly</hi> posterity, and a <hi>peaceable end;</hi> that heere you may see your <hi>Childrens Children</hi> in great prosperity: so as you may <hi>loue</hi> yours, yours may <hi>honour</hi> you, and both you and yours bee <hi>honoured</hi> of God: and that you who are <hi>blessed</hi> in your honorable <hi>Predecessors,</hi> may euer be <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py</hi> in your future <hi>Successours,</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I doubt not, but it will please you to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don my boldnesse; and the rather peruse this <hi>Direction to die well,</hi> because your <hi>whole life</hi> is, as it ought to bee, a <hi>meditation</hi> of death. And because it is but a little Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and may bee read ouer in a few houres, giue me leaue to commend vnto you two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Bookes,</hi> in which you may reade, all the daies of your life: The one is the booke of <hi>Gods mercies;</hi> the other is the booke of <hi>Gods iudgements.</hi> In the <hi>one,</hi> you may see his <hi>goodnesse</hi> to you and yours; in the <hi>other,</hi> his <hi>iustice</hi> against his and the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches enemies. This <hi>Booke</hi> of mine hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny leaues; these <hi>other</hi> haue only two: in the <hi>one,</hi> you may reade of <hi>Mercy,</hi> in the <hi>other,</hi> you may reade of <hi>Iudgement.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="162"/>
   <p>The Lord grant vnto your Honor, with your most honorable Countesse, the Lady <hi>Francis,</hi> a second <hi>Dorothea,</hi> (giuen both as a gift to you that feare God) such a <hi>life,</hi> that at the houre of <hi>death,</hi> when your <hi>glasse</hi> shall be <hi>runne,</hi> and the <hi>Bridegrome</hi> call for you, you may both say, with that holy man;
<q>
         <l>Vixi dum volui, volui dum Christe volebas:</l>
         <l>Sic nec vita mihi, mors nec acerba fuit.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>London:</hi> From S. <hi>Martins</hi> in the fields.
<date>
            <hi>May 30. 1613.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Honors, at command: <hi>ROBERT HILL.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>