<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>DEDICATED
To all that can iudge, of what degree soeuer.</title>
           <author>Fennor, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117734_Bo1_31_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13415</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23725</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117734</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>DEDICATED
To all that can iudge, of what degree soeuer.</title>
                 <author>Fennor, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>All the vvorkes of Iohn Taylor the water-poet : Beeing sixty and three in number. Collected into one volume by the author: vvith sundry new additions, corrected, reuised, and newly imprinted, 1630</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Boler (Bowler), James 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Elizabeth.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 148, 2, 93, 92-200, 225-343, 1, 14, 13-146 pages, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <head>DEDICATED
To all that can iudge, of what degree soeuer.</head>
   <p>IVdiciall Reader, after a Supper of Slanders, giue me leaue to bestow a Banquet of Defence;
which, I hope, shall rellish with more delight in thy generous opinion. I am sorry that my
Penne is pluckt backe from better Occasions, to answere an Opposite so ignoble. But seeing
my Reputation is shot at by such a poysoned Pistoll, I thought it meete to serue out the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let
of his Infamy with my approued Honesty, before it grew ranke, or festered too farre i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
the Worlds Apprehension. But to the purpose: Master <hi>Taylor,</hi> the Gentleman-like
Sculler at the <hi>Hope</hi> on the Banke-side, at a friends house of mine, acquainted me with his Proiect; which
was as followeth: That hee the said <hi>Taylor</hi> had studied such seuerall Humors in Prose, as neuer were th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
like before: (which indeed fell out true, to his shame) wherein he would haue me ioyne; hee to play a Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>
in Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se, and I to answere him in Verse: Whereto I condiscended, on these Conditions; <hi>viz.</hi> That I might
haue halfe the Commodity thereof, Or Security for fiue pounds; Or else twenty shillings in hand, and the
rest as the Day affoorded. Next, That I might heare his Booke read (which was fit) to know on wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
ground I might build my Inuention. And last, That I should see the Manner of his Challenge bes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>
it was published, and set my Answere to it with my owne hand. To all which hee granted, and deliuered
mee fiue Shillings vpon the same: Whereupon I promised faithfully, That if all this were on his part per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed,
I would (God willing) meet him, and with my best endeauour striue to giue the Audience content.
Now, here I must en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>reat you, before you condemne mee, note but the Occasions of my Breach of Promise:
This <hi>Water-Taylor,</hi> with his Confederates, presuming he had bound mee with his Earnest-money, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
his Challenge-Bill, and my Answere annexed thereunto, without my Hand, Knowledge, or Consent:
Nay more: My Answere was by him set vp so meane and insufficient to so brauing a Challenge, that I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
disliked thereof (as I had reason) and thereupon sent my Man with the Money fiue dayes before
the Play, to certifie them, That I was otherwise employed, and would not come, in regard of the Wrong
done vnto mee, in setting vp my Answere without my Consent: My Man deliuered the Message, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
lost the Money at Play, emboldening himselfe vpon the Wrongs I had receiued; which I haue since payed.
And the same day I receiued a Letter out of Warwickeshire from my Father, That he was not well; wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
me and my wife to repayre vnto him with all possible speed. Now, you that are Parents of Children, or
<pb n="149" facs="157"/>
children to Parents, Iudge, whether I ought rather to disobay my Father; or displease <hi>Iohn Taylor;</hi> Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>se
my Fathers hate, or lose a Scullers loue; and I hope yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> will say. I had sufficient cause to keepe mee
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> the <hi>Hope.</hi> But fearing my homely Truth (though it be sufficient to plead my Honestly) is not answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> to your expectation of my Practise in Poesie; I will, as neere as I can, fit my Muse to your liking,
which is my content: And euer rest honester by Land, then <hi>Taylor</hi> by Water,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>WILL. FENNOR.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>