<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS OWNE, WORTHY MASTER GEFFE.</title>
           <author>Goodwin, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117159_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11936</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22249</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117159</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS OWNE, WORTHY MASTER GEFFE.</title>
                 <author>Goodwin, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The perfect vse of silk-vvormes, and their benefit : With the exact planting, and artificiall handling of mulberrie trees whereby to nourish them, and the figures to know how to feede the wormes, and to winde off the silke. And the fit maner to prepare the barke of the white mulberrie to make fine linnen and other workes thereof. Done out of the French originall of D'Oliuier de Serres Lord of Pradel into English, by Nicholas Geffe Esquier. With an annexed discourse of his owne, of the meanes and sufficiencie of England for to haue abundance of fine silke by feeding of silke-wormes within the same; as by apparent proofes by him made and continued appeareth. For the generall vse and vniuersall benefit of all those his countrey men which embrace them. Neuer the like yet here discouered by any</title>
                 <author>Serres, Olivier de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purset, Christopher.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sergier, Richard 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stallenge, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 81, that is 97, 5, 14, 4 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO HIS OWNE, WORTHY MASTER GEFFE.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>LEt me (of those so many of our Clime,</l>
      <l>Who stand to thee (sweet friend) in honor bound,</l>
      <l>For thy deare paines confer'd vpon the time,</l>
      <l>Who hast for vs, fame, pleasure, profit, found:)</l>
      <l>Render thee thankes, that cannot speake thy praise,</l>
      <l>Wishing all condigne honor to thy daies.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Henceforth the greedy prison shall not eate</l>
      <l>Poore wretches, wofull mappes of misery,</l>
      <l>Since in thy worke all may some liuing get,</l>
      <l>By vse of much, or little industrie,</l>
      <l>Wherein the finest wittes their power may straine,</l>
      <l>The grosser, exercise their bodies paine.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Our populous land is free from forraigne broile,</l>
      <l>These iron times but little business giue,</l>
      <l>Yet now the discontent his head may toyle,</l>
      <l>And learne a quiet vertuous life to liue.</l>
      <l>A blessed med'cine faire Imployment is,</l>
      <l>Cu'ring sicke minds that else would do amisse.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Among'st those lands which sing the memory</l>
      <l>Of their deare Children, who with pious care</l>
      <l>Haue them ennobled, by th'vtility</l>
      <l>Of Artes, that long vnto them hidden were:</l>
      <l>Faire <hi>England</hi> boast's thy birth in happy houre,</l>
      <l>Who to her garlond ad'st so rich a flower.</l>
      <closer>
         <signed>ROBERT GOODVVIN.</signed>
      </closer>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>