<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A briefe Description of Englande.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1565</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117862_Fr1_19</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13030</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23319</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117862</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A briefe Description of Englande.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A summarie of Englyshe chronicles : conteynyng the true accompt of yeres, wherein euery kyng of this realme of England began theyr reigne, howe long they reigned: and what notable thynges hath bene doone durynge theyr reygnes. Wyth also the names and yeares of all the baylyffes, custos, maiors, and sheriffes of the citie of London, sens the Conqueste, dyligentely collected by Iohn Stovv citisen of London, in the yere of our Lorde God 1565. Whervnto is added a table in the end, conteynyng all the principall matters of this booke. Perused and allowed accordyng to the Quenes maiesties iniunctions</title>
                 <author>Stow, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1565</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 159, 162-242, 241-247, 13 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb n="1" facs="13"/>
   <head>A briefe Description of Englande.</head>
   <p>BEfore I entre to abridge the factes and gestes of the kynges and other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons within this Realme frome Brutus,<note place="margin">Polydore Virgil.</note> the fyrste Kyng of the same, I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose briefely to make a description of this noble Realme gathered out of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lydore Uirgil, reported in his work of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Englishe hystorie, who saith: That all Britain, which by two names is called England and Scotland, is an Iland in the Ocean sea, sytuate ryghte ouer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynst the Region of Gallia: one parte of which Isle Englishmen do inhabite, another parte Scottes, the third parte Walshemen, and the fourth part Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish men. All they, eyther in language, conditions or lawes, doo differ amongs them selues. Englande (so called of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glishemen, whiche dyd winne the same) is the greatest part, which is deuided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to .xxxix counties, which we call shyres. Wherof ten (that is to say, Kent, Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, Surrey, Southampton, Barkshire, Wyltshire, Dorsetshire, Somersetshire
<pb facs="14"/>
Deuonshire and Cornwall, do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eine the fyrst part of that Iland: which ya<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>s bounding toward the Southe, standeth betweene the Thames and the Sea. Frome thence, to the ryuer of Trent, whiche passeth thorough the myddes of Englād be .xvi. shyres: wherof the first vi. (standyng Estward (are Essex, Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eser, Hertfordshire, Suffolke, North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke, and Cambridgeshire, the other ten which stande more in the myddle of the countrey, are these: Bedford, Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingdon, Buckingham, Oxford, North<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hampton, Rutland, Leicestre, Notyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Warwike, and Lyncolne. After these, there be .vi. whiche border weste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vpon Wales, as Glocestre, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde, Worcester, Salop, Stafford, and Chester. Aboute the myddle of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion lie Darbyshyre, Yorkshyre, Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyre, &amp; Cumbreland. On the left hande toward the west is Westmerlande. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynste the same, is the Byshopryke of Durham, and Northumberland, which boūdeth vpon the northe in the marches of Scotland. Those shyres be diuided in to .xvii. Bishop rickes, which by a greke word, be called <hi>Dioeceses.</hi> Of which <hi>Dioe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceses,</hi> Canturburye and Rochester, bee
<pb n="2" facs="14"/>
in Kēt. <hi>Essex, Middlesex</hi> &amp; part of <hi>Hertford,</hi> belongeth to the bishoprike of <hi>London.</hi> The bishop of <hi>Chicester</hi> hath Suffer. <hi>Wynchester,</hi> hathe Hampshire, Surrey, and the Isle of Wight.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Salesbury,</hi> hath Dorsetshire, Barkshyre, and Wylteshire.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Excetor,</hi> hath Deuonshire, &amp; Cornwall. <hi>Bathe,</hi> and <hi>Welles,</hi> hath Somersetshyre. <hi>Worcester,</hi> hath Glocestershyre,<note place="margin">Now at thys presente there is a byshop of Glocester.</note> Worce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stershyre, and part of Warwikeshire. <hi>Hereforde,</hi> hath parte of Shropshire, and Herefordshire.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Couentre,</hi> and <hi>Lichfelde,</hi> Staffordeshyre, and thother parte of Warwikshire. <hi>Chestre,</hi> hath Cheshire, Darbyshire, &amp; a piece of a Lancashyre, nere the ryuer of Kepel. The Diocesse of <hi>Lincolne,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ther is now a byshoppe at Peterborow.</note> which is the greatest, hath eight shyres, lieng betweene thei Thames and Humbre, as Lincolne, Northampton, Leyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, Rutlande, Huntingdon, Bedforde, Buckyngham, Oxford &amp; the residue of Hertfordshire. The byshoprike of <hi>Ely,</hi> hath Cantabridgeshire, &amp; the Isle of Ely <hi>Suffolke,</hi> and <hi>Norffolke,</hi> be in the circuite of <hi>Norwiche</hi> Diocesse. And thys is the Prouynce of the Archebyshop of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburye,
<pb facs="15"/>
whyche is the primate of all England, wyth Wales, whyche hathe iiii. diocesses, as hereafter shall be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. The byshop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> hath Yorke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyre, Notynghamshyre, and a piece of Lancastshyre. The byshop of <hi>Durham,</hi> hath the bishoprike so commonly called, and Northumberland. <hi>Carlisle,</hi> contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth Cumberlande and Westmerland: And this is the other prouince of tharch byshop of Yorke, whiche is another pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of England, &amp; was of long tyme also primate of all Scotlande: but these Diocesses take theyr names of the cities where those seas be placed. The chiefe wherof, is London, where in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng was the Archebyshops sea: but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes transposed to Canterbury, a Citie in Kent, placed in a soyle amiable and pleasant. London, standethe in Middlesex, on the northside of the Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis. That moste excellent and goodly ryuer, beginneth a little aboue a village called Winchelcombe in Oxfordshyre, styll increasyng, and passeth fyrst by the vniuersitie of Oxēford, &amp; so with a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailous quiete course by London, and and then breaketh into the frenche O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean by mayne tydes, whyche twyse in
<pb n="3" facs="15"/>
xxiiii. howers space doth ebbe and flowe more then .lx. myles, to the great cōmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie of trauailers, by whiche all kyndes of marchandise bee easylye conueyde to London, the principall store and staple for all cōmodities within this Realme. Uppon the same ryuer is placed a stone bridge,<note place="margin">London brydge.</note> a woorke very rare and meruai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, whyche brydge hathe .xx. arches made of .iiii. squared stone, of height .lx. foote, and of breadth .xxx. foote, distant one from an other .xx. foote, compacte &amp; ioyned together with vaultes and Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars. Upon bothe sydes be houses buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that it seemeth rather a continuall streete then a brydge. The Ocean sea doothe bounde Englande, the fyrst part of Britain east and South, Wales, and Cornewall west. The ryuer of Twede deuideth England and Scotland north. The length of the Island begynneth at Portsmouth in the South part, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth at Twede in the north, conteinyng 320. myles. This Realme aboue other is moste fruitfull on this syde Humbre: for beyonde, it is fuller of mountaynes. And althoughe to the beholders of that countrey a far of, it may seme playn, yet it is full of many hylles, and those for
<pb facs="16"/>
the moste part voyde of trees: the valeys wherof be very delectable, inhabited for the most part by noble men, who accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to auncient and olde ordre, desyre not to dwell in Cities, but neere vnto valleys and ryuers in seueral vyllages: for aduoidyng of vehement wyndes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause that Ilande naturally is stormye. Humbre hath his beginnyng a little on this side York, &amp; by &amp; by runneth south<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, &amp; thē holdeth his course eastward &amp; so into the mayn sea, greatly increaced by the ryuers of Dune &amp; Trent. Trent beginneth a lyttle from Stafforde, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng through Darbyshyre, and Leyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stershyre, passing by Lichfield and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyngham on the ryght hand, and Dune on the lefte: so that bothe those ryuers dooe make an Ilande, whyche is called Aurolme, and then ioynyng together on this syde Kyngston vpon Hull, a goodly marchant towne, they falle into Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre: by whych ryuer they may aryue out of France, Germanie, and Denmarke. England is fruitefull of beastes, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundeth with cattell: wherby thinha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitātes be rather for the most Grasiers, then ploughmē because they geue them selues more to fedyng, then to tyllage.
<pb n="4" facs="16"/>
So that almoste the thyrde parte of the countrey is imployed to cattell, dere red and fallow, gores (wherof there be store in the northe partes, &amp; conyes, for euery where there is ioly maintenāce of those kyndes of beastes: because it is fulle of greate woddes, wherof there ryseth pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>styme of huntyng greatly exercised, spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by the nobilitie and gentlemen.</p>
   <p>Of Scotland, an other parte of Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn, I purpose to say nothyng because I haue promised onely and briefly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre thaffaires of myne owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, as beste trauailed and acquainted with the knowledge of the same.</p>
   <p>Wales, the .iiii. part of Britayne lyeth vpon the lefte hand: whiche like a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montarie or forelande, or an Isle (as it were) on euery syde it is compassed with the mayne sea: excepte it be on the easte parte with the Ryuer of Sabrine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called Seuerne, whiche deuideth Wales from England. Although some late writers affirme Hereforde to bee a bound betwene Wales and England, &amp; say, that Wales begynneth at Chep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolle, where the Ryuer Ueye augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wyth an other ryuer called Lugge, passyng by Hereforde dooth runne into
<pb facs="17"/>
the sea: which riuer riseth in the myddle of Wales out of that hill (but vncertain whether oute of that sprynge) that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brine dothe,<note place="margin">Cornelius Tacitus.</note> whiche Corn. Tacitus cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>Antona.</hi> For euen to that place there goth a great arme of the sea,<note place="margin">This arme of the sea, as I Iudge, is nowe called Anste, where is a passage betwene the village of Anste and Chepstoll.</note> which pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syng through the land westward: on the right hande leaueth Cornewall, and on the left, Wales. Whiche Topography or description, although it be newe, yet I thoughte good to folowe. Therefore Wales is extended frome the towne of Chepstol, where it beginneth almost by a straight line a lytle aboue Shrowsbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, euē to Westchester northward. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that part, so many of the Britains as remayned alyue after the slaughter and losse of their countrey, at the length be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng dryuen to theyr shyftes, dyd repaire as ancient writings report: where part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through refuge of the mountaines, &amp; partly of the woddes and marshes, they remained in safetie: which part they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy euen to this daye. That lande after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the englyshe men dyd call Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les: and the Britaius the inhabitauntes of the same, Walshmen: for amonges the Germaynes, <hi>Walsman,</hi> signifieth a strāger, an alien, an outborn or strange
<pb n="5" facs="17"/>
man: that is, suche a one, as hath a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye language from theirs, for <hi>Wall,</hi> in their tongue is called a stranger born as an Italian or Frencheman: whyche differ in speeche from the Germane.</p>
   <p>Man, signifieth <hi>Homo,</hi> which is a mā in english. Therfore englishmen, a people of Germany, after they had wōne Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain called the Britains, which escaped after y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> destructiō of their cuntrey, after their countrey maner. <hi>walshmen,</hi> because they had an other tong or spech, besides theirs, &amp; the land which they inhabited, <hi>Wales,</hi> which name afterwardes both to the people and contrey dyd remayn. By this meanes the Britaynes with theyr kyngedome loste their name. But they whiche affirme that name to be deriued of their kyng or queene without doubte be deceiued. The countrey soyle towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the sea coaste, and in other places in the valleys and playnes, is most fertile, which yeldeth bothe to man and beaste, great plentie of fruite and grasse: but in other places for the moste parte it is ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reyne and lesse fruitfull, because it lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth tyllage: for whiche cause husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men do lyue hardly, eating Oten cakes and drinkyng milke myxte with water,
<pb facs="18"/>
and sowre whay. There be many tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and strong castels, and .iiii. Bishop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rikes, if the byshoprike of Hereforde be coūted in England, as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> late writers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare. The fyrst byshoprike is <hi>Meneue,</hi> so called of <hi>Meneua,</hi> whiche at this day they call <hi>Sainct Dauids,</hi> a Citie very auncient, situated vpon the sea coast, and boūdeth westward toward Ireland. An other is <hi>Landaeffe,</hi> the thirde <hi>Bangor,</hi> and the fourthe All <hi>Saint Asaph.</hi> whiche, be vnder Tharchbyshoppe of Canterburye. The walshmen haue a language from then<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glishmen, which as they say, that fetche their Petigree frome the Troianes, do the partly sounde of the Troian anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and partly of the Greeke. But how soever it is, the walshemen do not pronounce their speache so pleasantely and gentilly as thenglyshmen dooe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they speake more in the throte: &amp; contrary wise thenglishemen rightly fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowynge the Latines, do expresse theyr voyce somewhat within the lyps, which to the hearers semeth pleasant &amp; swete: And thus much of wales, the third part of Britaine.</p>
   <p>Nowe foloweth the fourthe and laste parte of Britayne, named Cornewall.
<pb n="6" facs="18"/>
This part beginneth on that syde whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che standeth toward Spayn westward: Toward theast, it is of bredth .iiii. score and tenne myles, extendyng a lyttle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde saynt Germains, which is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry famous village situated on the right hand vpon the sea coast, where the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test breadth of that countrey is but .xx. myles: for thys parcell of lande on the right hand is compassed with the coaste of the mayne sea: and on the left hande with that arme of the sea, whiche (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is declared) parteth the lande, and runneth vp to Chepstoll: where the coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey is in fourme of a Horne: For at the fyrst, it is narowe, and then growethe broader, a little beyonde the said towne of saint Germaine. Eastwarde it bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth vpon England, West, south, and Northe, the mayne sea is rounde about it: It is a very barreyn soyle, yeldynge fruite more through trauaile of the tyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and husband men, thē through the goodnes of the groūd. but there is great plentie of leade and tyn: in the myning and dyggyng wherof doth specially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist the liuynge &amp; sustentation of thinha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants. In this only parte of Britayn,
<pb facs="19"/>
euen to this daye continueth the nation of the Britaines, whiche in the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge brought out of Gallia occupied &amp; inhabited that Ilande, (yf credite maye be geuen to them, whyche reporte the firste inhabitantes of Britaine to come out of the Cities of Armerica.) The ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumēt &amp; profe wherof, is because y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nishmen do speake y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> langage, which the Britains vse now in France, whom the Britons do cal Britonātes. This thing to be more true, an old ancient chronicle dothe declare, wherin I found written, not <hi>Cornubia,</hi> but <hi>Cornugallia,</hi> compounded of <hi>Cornu,</hi> a horne, the forme wherof that countrey hath, and of <hi>Gallia,</hi> out of which contrey thinhabitantes came fyrst, the maner of which name is not to be mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyked. Their tongue is farre dissonant from englishe, but is muche like to the Walshe tongue, because they haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wordes cōmune to both tonges: yet thys difference there is betwene them, when a walsheman speaketh the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyshe man rather vnderstandeth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny woordes spoken by the Walshman, then the hole tale he telleth. whereby it is manyfest, that those thre people dooe vnderstande one an other in like maner
<pb n="7" facs="19"/>
as the Southerne Scottes doo perceiue and vnderstand the Northern. But it is a thyng very rare and meruailous, that in one Iland there should be such varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of speches. Cornewall or Cornugall is in the Diocesse of Excetour, whyche was ones woorthye to bee counted the fourth part of the Iland, as well for the contrarietie of language as for the fyrst inhabitantes thereof, as is beforesayde. Afterwardes, the Normans which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted a kyngdom of all those thre par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes reckned Cornewall to bee one of the counties or shires of the contrey. Thus muche of the particular descryption of Britayne, that the whole bodye of the realm (by the membres) may be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter knowen to some peraduenture that neuer heard the same before.</p>
   <p>The forme of the Iland is <hi>triquetra.</hi> or thre cornered, hauyng three corners, or three sydes: Two wherof, that is to say: The corner toward theast, and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther toward the weast: (bothe exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding northwardes) are the longest.</p>
   <p>The third syde whiche is the south syde is farre shorter then thother: for the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land is greater of length then of bredth. And as in the other two partes is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned
<pb facs="20"/>
the lengthe, euen so in the laste, the breadth. In whyche place, the breadthe begynneth: and so continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng from the South parte to the north, it is but narowe. The fyrste and ryght corner of whyche Ilande eastwarde, is in Kente, at Douer and Sandwyche.</p>
   <p>From whence to Caleys or Boloygne in France, is the dystance of .xxx. my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. From this Angle which is agaynst Fraunce to the thyrde Angle, whyche is in the Northe, in Scotlande, the mayne whereof, boundeth vpon Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, but no land seene, and there the Iland is lyke vnto a wedge euen at the very angle of the land in Scotland. The length wherof is .vii. hundreth myles. Agayne, the lengthe from this Corner at Douer in Kent, to the vttermost part of Cornewall, beynge saynt Myghels mount (whych is the west part or weste angle) is supposed to bee .300. myles.</p>
   <p>Frō this left Angle beyng the west part and thuttermoste parte of Cornewall, whiche hath a pros<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ect towards Spain, in whyche part also standeth Irelande, sytuated betwene Britayne and Spayn to the northe angle in the further parte of Scotlande, in which part the Ilande
<pb n="8" facs="20"/>
doth end, the lēgth is .viii. hundred mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, in whiche parte there be very good hauens, and saufe harboroughes for shyppes, and apt passage into Ireland, beyng not past one day saylyng, but the shorter passage is from Wales, to Wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terforde, a towne in Ireland vppon the sea coast, muche lyke to that passage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene Douer and Calaice, or som what more: but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> shortest passage of all, is out of Scotlande. From this last Angle to Hampton: (whiche is a towne vpon the sea coast, with a hauen so called toward the southe, and therefore called South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampton) betwene the Angles of Kent and Cornewall, they doo measure by a strayght lyne the whole lengthe of the Ilande, and doo say, that it conteyneth 800. myles, as the breadth from <hi>Meneua,</hi> or Saint Dauids to Yarmouth, whiche is in the vttermost part of the Iland to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the East doth conteyn .200. mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les for the breadth of the Iland is in the southe part, which part is the front and begynnyng of the Land, and endeth na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, or as it were in a straighte. So the circuit or compasse of the Iland is .xviii. C. myles, which is .200. lesse than <hi>Caesar</hi> doothe recken or accompt.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="21"/>Thus muche I haue thought good to take out of Polydore, touchynge the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uision of England, with the forme and situation of the same. Much other good matter that author doth alledge, whiche here for breuitie I doo omitte, referring those that desyre to know farther herof, to that boke: where he shall fynde the style and story bothe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant and profitable.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>