<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Reader, take this in your way.</title>
           <author>Taylor, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117734_Bo1_55_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13415</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23725</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117734</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Reader, take this in your way.</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>All the vvorkes of Iohn Taylor the water-poet : Beeing sixty and three in number. Collected into one volume by the author: vvith sundry new additions, corrected, reuised, and newly imprinted, 1630</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Boler (Bowler), James 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Elizabeth.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 148, 2, 93, 92-200, 225-343, 1, 14, 13-146 pages, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>Reader, take this in your way.</head>
   <l>A Pamphlet (Reader,) from the Presse is hurld,</l>
   <l>That hath not many fellowes in the world:</l>
   <l>The manner's common, though the matter's shallow,</l>
   <l>And 'tis all true, which makes it want a fellow.</l>
   <p>ANd because I would not haue you either guld of your mony, or deceiued in expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō,
I pray you take notice of my plaine dealing, for I haue not giuen my book a swel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
bumbasted title, or a promising inside of newes; therfore if you look for any such
matter from hence, take this warning, hold fast your mony; and lay the booke downe
yet if you do buy it (I dare presume) you shall find somwhat in it worth part of your
mony, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>roth is that I did chiefly write it, because I am of much acquaintance, and cannot passe
the streets, but I am continually stayed by one or other, to know what newes, so that sometimes I
am foure houres before I can goe the length of two paire of Buts, where such non-sence or sence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse
questions are propounded to me, that cals many seeming wise mens wisedomes in question,
drawing aside the curtaines of their vnderstanding, and laying their ignorance wide open. First
<hi>Iohn Easie</hi> takes me, and holds me fast by the fift halfe an houre; and will needs torture some newes
out of me from <hi>Spinola,</hi> whom I was neuer neere by 500.miles; for he is in the <hi>Phllatinate</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
and I was in <hi>Bohemia</hi> I am no sooner eased of him, but <hi>Gregory Gandergoose</hi> an Alderman of
<hi>Gotham,</hi> catches me by the goll demanding if <hi>Bohemia</hi> be a great Towne, and whether there bee
any meate in it, and whether the last fleet of ships be arriued there: his mouth being stop'd a third
examines me boldly, what newes from <hi>Vienna,</hi> where the Emperours Army is, what the Duke of
<hi>Bauaria</hi> doth, what is become of Count <hi>Buquoy,</hi> how sares all the Englishmen; Where lyes the
King of <hi>Bohemiaes</hi> forces, what <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> doth, what tydings of <hi>Dampeier,</hi> and such a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest
of inquisition, that it almost shakes my patience in peeces. To ease my selfe of all which, I was
inforced to set pen to paper, and let this poore Pamphlet (my harald or nuntius trauaile and talke,
whilst I take my ease with silence. Thus much I dare affirme, that whosoever he or they bee, that
doe scatter any scandalous speeches against the plenty in <hi>Bohemia</hi> of all manner of needfull things
for the sustenance of man and beasts, (of the which there is more abundance then euer I saw in any
place else) or whatsoeuer they be that report any ill successe on the Kings party, this little booke,
and I the Author, doth proclaime and proue them false Lyers, and they are to be suspected, for
coyning such falshoods as no well willers to the <hi>Bohemian</hi> prosperity. One thing I must intreat
the Readers patience in reading one hundred lines: wherein I haue kept a filthy stirre about a beast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
fellow, who was at my going from <hi>England</hi> a peece of a <hi>Graues end</hi> Constable) at which time he
did me such wrong, as might haue drawne my life in question; for he falsly said that I would haue
fired their Towne. I did promise him a ierke or two of my pen at my returne; which now I haue
performed, (not out of any malice, but because I would be as good as my word with him.) Thus
crauing you to reade if you like, and like as you lift. I leaue you a Booke much like a pratling Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sip,
full of many words to small purpose.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours, as you are mine,
<hi>IOHN TAYLOR.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>