<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the gentle Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117590_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13043</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23333</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117590</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the gentle Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The chronicles of England : from Brute vnto this present yeare of Christ. 1580. Collected by Iohn Stow citizen of London</title>
                 <author>Stow, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 879, 890-1155, 1158-1223, 1 page, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>¶ To the gentle Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongst other Bookes which are in this our learned age published in great numbers, there are few, eyther for the honestie of the matter, or commoditie which they bring to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, or for the pleasantnesse of the stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and reading, to be preferred before the Chronicles and Hystories. What examples of men deseruing immortalitie, of exploites worthy great renowne, of vertuous liuing of the posteritie to be embraced, of wise handling of weighty affaires, diligently to be marked, and aptly to be applied: what incouragement of nobilitie to noble feates, what discourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of vnnaturall subiects from wicked treasons, pernitious rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and damnable doctrines: to conclude, what perswasion to honestie, godlynesse, and vertue of all sorts, what dissuasions from the contrary is not plentifully in them to be found? So that it is as hard a matter for the Readers of Chronicles, in my fansie, to passe without some co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of wisedome, inuitements to vertue, and loathing of naughtie factes, as it is for a welfauoured man to walke vp and downe in the hot parching Sunne, &amp; not to be therewith sunburned. They there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which with long studie, earnest good will, &amp; to their great costes and charges haue brought hidden Histories from duskie darkenesse to the sight of the world, and haue bin diligent obseruers of common wealthes, and noted for the posteritie the fleeting manners of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and accidents of the times: deserue (at the least) thankes for their paines, and to be misreported of none, seeing they haue laboured for<note place="margin">Note that the backebiter slay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth three at once, himself by his ovvne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, hym that crediteth hys false tales, and him that he backebiteth.</note> all. I write not this to complayne of some mens ingratitude towardes me (although iustly I might) but to shewe the commodities which ensue of the reading of Histories, that seeing they are so great and so many, all men would (as they ought) imploy their diligence in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest, fruitefull, and delectable perusing of the same, and so to accompt of the Authors, as of men carefull for their Countrey: and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, if neede require, by whome they haue taken profite.</p>
   <p>It is now seuentene yeres since (I seing the confuse order of our late English Chronicles, and the ignorant handling of auntient affaires) leauing myne owne peculiar gaines, consecrated my selfe to the search
<pb facs="8"/>
of our famous Antiquities. What I haue done in them before time, the former editions of my Summarie of Chronicles maye wel testifie, but howe farre (be it spoken without arrogancie) I haue laboured for the truth more thā some other, this last edition wil euidently declare: wherein, that I differ from the inordinate and vnskilful collections of other men, it is no maruel, seeing that I doe not fully agree with my selfe, as some malitious persons haue fondely charged me: but lette it be considered, that there is nothing perfect at the first, and that it is incident to mankinde to erre and slippe sometime, but onelye the point of fantasticall fooles, to perseuer and continue in their errors. Wherfore, seeing that the perusing of auncient Records and best ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued Histories of all times (not without great difficultie obteined) doe not onely moue me, but for their aucthoritie driue me to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge both mine and other mens errors, and in acknowledging to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them, I truste to obtaine thus muche at your handes, that at the leaste you wil call to remembraunce a moste gentle and wise lawe of the politike Persians, wherein it was enacted, that a man accused to bee in their lawes a trespasser, and founde guiltie of the crime, should not straight waye bee condemned, but after a diligent enquirie and searche of his whole life and conuersation (no slaunder imputed vnto him as of importaunce) if the number of his laudable factes didde counteruaile the contrarie, he was full quit of the trespasse. The same lawe do I wishe the readers of these my Chronicles to put in vre, that if the errors be not so plentiful, as Histories truely alleadged, they wil beare with them: for as I promised, so haue I tried all matters worthie of immortalitie, by the certaine Touchstone of best allowed Historiographers: and yet notwithstanding, some faults by misprinting haue escaped the correction, whiche easily may be seene and amended by the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Reader.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>