<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ A Prologe whereby a man may the better perceaue the occasion and whole cause of this Booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1573</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117761_Fr3_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68831</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24436</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117761</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ A Prologe whereby a man may the better perceaue the occasion and whole cause of this Booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvhole workes of W. Tyndall, Iohn Frith, and Doct. Barnes, three worthy martyrs, and principall teachers of this Churche of England : collected and compiled in one tome togither, beyng before scattered, [and] now in print here exhibited to the Church. To the prayse of God, and profite of all good Christian readers</title>
                 <author>Tyndale, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1573</date>
                 <publisher>Day, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Day, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stationers’ Company, London</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 478, 20, 172, 12, 183-376, 4 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <head>¶ A Prologe whereby a man may the better perceaue the occasion and whole cause of this Booke.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here was a brother</hi>
      <note place="margin">Symon Fishe the maker of the booke of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plication of Beggers.</note>
      <hi>of ours named Simon Fishe (whiche nowe I trust resteth in Gods handes) whose eyes God had opened, not onely to espy the wily walkyng of hipocrites and ruyne of the realme whiche through their meanes was nye at hand: but also to marke and ponder the peril of mēs soules, and how that the ignoraunt people by their seduction was fallen into that franticke imagination that they more feared the Pope and hys De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees whiche are but vanitie, then God him selfe and his law whiche are most righteous and eternall. This man therfore of a feruent and burnyng zeale that hee bare to the wealth of the comminaltie brake out and touched these hypocrites in a litle treatise whiche hee called The Supplication of Beggers, willyng</hi>
      <note place="margin">Our riches is to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed on the poore.</note>
      <hi>that wee shoulde geue the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce of our richesse vnto the poore to whom it is due by the law of God: and that we should no len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger suffer our selues to bee dispoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and robbed of a sight of sturdy lubbars whiche vnder a false cloke of vertue and prayer deceiue the poore of their liuyng and both the poore and the riche of their soules health, if credence be geuen vnto them.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>And where these wilye Foxes</hi>
      <note place="margin">Either there is no Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, els the Pope is mercylesse.</note>
      <hi>would haue pretēded the cloke of Purgatory affirmyng that it were due vnto them because they praye for their frendes soules that they might come to rest, he aunswered vnto that poynt preuentyng theyr obiection, and proued that either there could be no such Purgatory, or els that the Pope were a mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse tyraunt which (as he saith him selfe may deliuer them from thēce and will not except hee haue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. At this point began M. More</hi>
      <note place="margin">Whereat M. More first began to fume a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynst such as denye Purgatory</note>
      <hi>to fume and tooke vpon hym selfe to bee Proctour for Purgatory (I will not say that he was hyred ther to of our spiritualtie although ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men dare sweare it (and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme his purpose hee wrested sore the Scriptures, and triumpheth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so that the very miscreantes and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters
<pb n="7" facs="260"/>
beleue that there is a Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory. He addeth thereto (to sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish his matter with all) that there is no man whiche beleueth that there is a God, and that the soule of man is immortall, but hee must nedes graunt that there is a Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory. There tooke Rastell his hold,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rastell fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth M. More.</note>
      <hi>whiche is a Printer dwellyng at Paules gate in London and of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Mores alliaunce, which also co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueteth to counterfayte his kinsmā, although the beames of his braines be nothyng so radiaunt nor his cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyaunce so commendable in the eyes of the wise. Notwithstandyng this Rastell hath enterprised to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late this matter, and hath diuided it into three Dialoges, imaginyng that two men dispute this matter by natural reason and Philosophie, secludyng Christ and all Scripture. The one of them (that should dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute</hi>
      <note place="margin">The names of the dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the matter of Purgatory</note>
      <hi>this matter) he calleth Ginge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, &amp; fayneth hym to be a Turke and of Mahometes law. The second he nameth Comingo an Almany &amp; of Christes fayth. And he maketh the Turke to teach the Christen mā what he should beleue.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The first Dialoge goeth about</hi>
      <note place="margin">The sōme and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes of Rastels iij. Dialogues</note>
      <hi>to proue by reason that there is a God, which is mercyfull and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous. The second entendeth to proue, that the soule of a man is im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mortall. Agaynst these two Dialo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues I will not dispute, partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause this treatise should not be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer long and tedious, and partly because that those twoo poyntes which he there laboureth to proue are such as no Christen man will de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny (although many of his probati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are so slender, that they may well be improued) but as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his thyrd Dialogue wherin he would proue Purgatory, it is whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iniurious vnto the bloude of Christe and the destruction of all Christen fayth, if men were so mad as to beleue his vayne persuasions. And therfore I thought expedient to cōpare this third Dialoge with all the deceitfull reasons vnto the true light and pure worde of God that at the least Rastell hym selfe might perceiue his owne blind ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunce and returne agayne into the right way. And if any man haue bene deceiued through his booke (as I trust there are but few except they bee very ignoraunt) that they may repent with hym and glorifie GOD for his inestimable mercy which hath sent his light into this world to disclose and expell theyr darke and blynd ignorauncy, that they may see his wayes and walke in them praysing the Lord eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>