<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER: Conteyning a briefe Censure vpon the Title and the front of Kellisons Suruey, and his two liminare Epistles and Praeambles.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117977_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13169</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23464</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117977</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER: Conteyning a briefe Censure vpon the Title and the front of Kellisons Suruey, and his two liminare Epistles and Praeambles.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The examination and confutation of a certaine scurrilous treatise entituled, The suruey of the newe religion, published by Matthew Kellison, in disgrace of true religion professed in the Church of England</title>
                 <author>Sutcliffe, Matthew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Weaver (Wever), Edmund</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sergier, Richard 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 113, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO <hi>THE READER:</hi> Conteyning a briefe Censure vpon the Title and the front of <hi>Kellisons Suruey,</hi> and his two liminare Epistles and Praeambles.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Deuill, as we read <hi>Iob</hi> 1. is said <hi>To compasse the Worlde, and to walke through it,</hi> and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence teacheth vs, that he is a very busie &amp; curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Surueyer. We are not therefore to thinke it strange, if his children do immitate their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and proue great compassers of the world, and contriuers of plots and surueyes, to bring men within the circle of their owne errors. Among the rest, one <hi>Kellison</hi> a cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per kettle Masse-preist, hath shewed him-selfe a great compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sser of sea and land, to winne proselytes to the Synagogue of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and a busie and captious surueyer to espye motes in our Christian faith: &amp; for this end hath set out a large volume, called <hi>The Suruey of the new Religion.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But first we say to him, as <hi>Christ</hi> said to a man of his qualitie. Hypocrita, primū eijce trabem &amp;c. <hi>Hipocrite, first cast the beame out of thine owne eye, and then thou shalt more easily see to take a mote out thy brothers eye.</hi> So we pray him to discharge his Romish re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of the just imputation of noueltie, &amp; then he may with more reason taxe others for maintayning newe religion. As for our Religion, it is vniustly and absurdly termed newe. For as <hi>Ignatius</hi> said in his Epistle to the <hi>Philippians, Christ is our antiquitie.</hi> And in religion that is most ancient, <hi>that is from the
<pb facs="6"/> Apostles,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> doth signifie. If then our Religion be from <hi>Christ,</hi> and is grounded vpon the holy Scriptures, and not vpon late Decretales, and the opinions of Popes, School-men and Canonists: how is the same reputed newe? doth not <hi>Kel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lison</hi> remember, that the somme of our whole desire is, that Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish nouelties, and the late Tridentine doctrine being aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, we may returne to the ancient, Catholike and Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like faith?</p>
   <p>Absurdly also he &amp; his consorts repute the <hi>Romish</hi> moderne religion to be ancient, seeing the same, as it differeth from the religion professed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is nothing but an hochpot of heresies, and erroneous &amp; corrupt doctrine, either deriued from late School-men, or first established by the late Conuenticles of <hi>Trent, Florence, Constance,</hi> and <hi>Lateran,</hi> or by little and little confirmed by corrupt custome. The Popish Masse (as it now standeth) is but a late patcherie. In the olde ordinall of <hi>Rome</hi> it appeareth, that neither priuate Masses, nor halfe Communions, nor Transubstantiation, nor the sacrifice of Christs body and blood contayned vnder the accidents of bread and wine, for quicke and dead, nor the adoration of the Sacrament with latria, nor prayers to Saints, and for the dead, were in vse in ancient time. The Fathers doe no where teach, that brute beasts receiuing a consecrated hoast, eate Christs flesh, or that Christs flesh is receiued downe into mens bellyes: nay they teach quite contrary. The Bishops of <hi>Rome</hi> for many yeares vsed not the temporall sworde; Neither was the Pope Lord of <hi>Rome</hi> vntill the time of <hi>Boniface</hi> the 9. <hi>Gregory</hi> the first condemned both the vniuersall authoritie of one Bishop ouer the rest, and the adoration of Images. Neuer was it imagined before the time of the Conuenticle of <hi>Trent,</hi> that euery pield Masse-priest, as ofte as he said Masse wrought three miracles. The necessitie of auricular confession, was first decreed by <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> the third. The number of 7. Sacraments albeit before talked of idly by School-men, was not by any publike autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie receiued before the Conuenticle of <hi>Florence.</hi> Finally, it is easie to shew, that the Popes doctrine concerning Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Purgatorie, the worship of Saints, and Images, extreame vnction, and other poynts of religion in controuersie betwixt the Papists and vs, is lately brought in, and more newe then
<pb facs="6"/> that religion which we professe, &amp; which by <hi>Kellison</hi> is lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and falsely called newe.</p>
   <p>Many wonder also, why he should call his Treatise <hi>A Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey of the newe Religion:</hi> seeing the poyntes which he handleth, are neither matters of religion, nor professed by vs, nor proued against them, vpon whome they are fathered by <hi>Cochleus, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phylus, Genebrard, Bolsec, Stapleton, Sanders,</hi> and such like lying parasites.</p>
   <p>He professeth him-selfe a Doctor, but his Discourse decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth him to be in the number of those of whome the Apostle speaketh 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. <hi>Which would be Doctors of the Law, and yet vnderstand not whereof they speake, nor whereof they affirme.</hi> If he haue no more knowledge, then he hath shewed in this <hi>Suruey,</hi> he is <hi>a Doctor and professor of Diuinitie</hi> of a lowe price. Little certes doth he vnderstand, what that profession meaneth, that could not distinguish his owne, &amp; his fellowes calumniations from the grounds and articles of our religion. And euill doth he deserue the title of a Doctor, &amp; professor of diuinitie, which so often speaketh against Scriptures: and <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. calleth the proofes grounded vpon them <hi>bare:</hi> and rather deriueth his diuinitie out of the sinkes of School-men, and corrupt puddles of Philosophers, then out of holy Scriptures. <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. he calleth the working of Gods spirit <hi>a fancy. Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. he blu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth not to write, that justification by fayth in Christ without workes, is a doctrine <hi>opening a gappe to all sinnes.</hi> Against <hi>Christs</hi> Priesthood, this priest of <hi>Baal</hi> talketh prophanely, as if the same were imperfect without the addition of Romish Masse-priestes. And with <hi>Christs</hi> Sacrifice he compareth, nay he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualleth the sacrifice of the Masse. Of Christian libertie he discourseth freely, but very fondly, and falsely denying, that the same consisteth any whit in the deliuerance of mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences from the cursse of the law, from the yoke of Iewish ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonyes, and humane traditions. Against the assurance, that Christians haue of Gods fauour, and of their owne saluation, he runneth out and reuelleth, as if it were a dangerous poynt of doctrine, and a cause of diuers inconueniences: all which doe argue, that he is but a kettle-doctor of diuinitie, and a professor like to those, of whome the Apostle speaking <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. sayth, <hi>When they professed them-selues wise, they became fooles.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <p>In matters in Religion and Diuinitie, he tumbleth him-selfe, as the olde Prouerb sayth, <hi>Tanquam Asinus in vnguento,</hi> that is, as an Asse smeared with a costly oyntment. For although the profession of diuinitie be honorable; yet it fitteth this Beere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawer or Tapster, that calleth him-selfe a Doctor and profess<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or of Diuinitie, no better, then it fitteth an Asse to be perfumed with Muske and Ciuet.</p>
   <p>For his deuise he chuseth these two Sētences, <hi>Doe men gather Grapes of thornes, or Figs of thistles?</hi> &amp;, <hi>They shal prosper no further, For their folly shalbe made manifest to all.</hi> The first being takē out of <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. &amp; the secōd out of 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. &amp; both seruing vs to cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude against him &amp; his consortes, whose discourses are rather like bundles of thornes, &amp; thistles, then like Grapes &amp; Figges. It seemeth when he framed them, he shooke his lippes like an Asse cropping of thistles. From a man of such a distemperd humour we are not to looke for better frutes. And certes no maruel, if such lying and rayling courses prosper not. <hi>Menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia non diu fallunt</hi> sayth <hi>Cyprian lib.</hi> 1. <hi>epist.</hi> 3. That is, <hi>Lyes doe not long deceiue,</hi> neyther doth darknesse continue, when the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to appeare. Now their lying and cogging, &amp; all their fooleryes are daily more and more made manifest. <hi>Euripides</hi> in <hi>Andromacha</hi> speaking of the <hi>Spartans,</hi> calleth them <hi>Kings of lyes and sowers of mischiefe.</hi> And <hi>Athanasius ad Constantium</hi> speaking of the <hi>Arians: Miror</hi> (sayth he) <hi>eos sine vlla abominatione aut hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rore mendacij ita falsa &amp;c. potuisse dicere. I wonder how without hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and abhomination of the fact, they could deuise thinges so false!</hi> But with far better reason we may say this of <hi>Kellison</hi> &amp; other our aduersaryes, who in lying and aequiuocating, passe both <hi>Spartans</hi> and <hi>Africans,</hi> and lay plots of mischiefe neuer heard of in anye age before. They make no Conscience what they sweare. We may not therefore thinke it strange, if he speake any thing sounding to our disgrace most falsely. As <hi>Tertullian lib. contra Hermog.</hi> sayth of that heretike, so we may say of <hi>Kel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lison. Loquacitatem faecundiam existimat &amp;c.</hi> He thinketh <hi>babling to be eloquence, and impudencye to be constancye.</hi> And these are the frutes and effectes of <hi>Kellisons</hi> labours.</p>
   <p>It resteth thē, hauing spokē of the Tytle &amp; front of his worke, that wee doe our endeauour to make this mans folly appeare most manifestly in the rest of his Suruey, &amp; that wee prescribe
<pb facs="7"/> some Triacle to such as otherwise might percase taste of his poysoned discourses. But before we passe any further, wee are first to examine his two praeambular Epistles; wherof the first is directed to the King, the second to euery other Reader.</p>
   <p>Vnto Kings, men of discretion vse not to present trifles, or else matters not pleasing their humours, or not sorting with their royall Majesties excellencie, endeuouring as much as in them lyeth, to make their giftes correspond with their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. But <hi>Kellison</hi> respected all this nothing. For albeit this Suruey be a most idle deuise, and most vnworthy to be presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to so wise, learned, pious and famous a King, as conteining nothing else but a fardle of lyes, calumniations, and fooleryes, and certaine odde fragments of olde declamations euaporated with age: Yet no inferiour person could satisfie him, then our King; such was his arrogancye and impudencie. Nay albeit he plainly perceiued incongruitie, yet could he not forbeare to prease into the Kings presence, and there to offer vp a sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of his Suruey, a fitter offring for Vulcan, then for any man of note or dignitye.</p>
   <p>He supposeth, that therein he hath committed only <hi>three inciuilities.</hi> But if he would haue spoken plainly, hee should haue named them three grosse absurdities, as indeed they are. For first, what is, or can be deuised more absurd, then for a bald idolatrous Masse-priest, to presume to present himselfe before a religious and Christian King, enimie to all Idolaters, and Priests of <hi>Ball?</hi> for a sworne slaue of King-killing Popes, and a teacher and a maintainer of their wicked &amp; disloyall doctrine, to presume to appeare before a King, whose life, he &amp; his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorts haue sougnt to take away, and whose Royall authoritie and Honour, all <hi>Papists</hi> doe empaire, and whose Crowne all Masse-priestes seeke to deliuer into the Popes hands? For a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitiue and an enimie to his Prince &amp; Country, boldly to speak to so mightie a King, and so kinde a Father to his Country and subjects? Secondly, might such an idolatrous Saltpeter-priest and a fugitiue Traytor be pardoned for his arrogant and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptuous boldnesse, daring to come into a Princes presence, that is so hardly pressed with the great weight &amp; multitude of the affayres of state, as himselfe confesseth? yet modestie might haue taught him, if any sparke of modesty had been in him, &amp;
<pb facs="8"/> we may not forbeare to tell him, that it is too great rudenesse, for fugitiues to thrust in among the Peeres of the Realme, and for base cōpanions to appeare without cōmission among the Ambassadours of great Princes, as he hath done. Thirdlie if needs he would presse into the Kings presence, and like a Ket<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle-maker stand among great men with his present, then hee should haue thought vpon some thing, that might be more gratefull, then this scurrilous Libel, containing nothing but calumniations, inuectiues, and declamations against that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which both the King and his people professeth, &amp; shall alwayes be justified to be most true and Apostolike, against him and all his partakers. At the least, if he had nothing to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, that might please so great a Prince, yet should he haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne to offer that, which both to him and all true Christians cannot chuse, but be most vngratefull and odious.</p>
   <p>Beside these absurdities, our surueyor hath runne into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers grosse errors. For first he compareth the King to an Idole, where he maketh him <hi>like a Neptune Lord of the Oceā Sea.</hi> So he is not only a worshipper of Idoles, but also would gladlie make an Idole of the King. Secondly, in setting forth the Kings prayses, he speaketh contraries, now representing his maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stye sitting <hi>in a Throne of terror:</hi> and not long after calling him <hi>the myldest Prince in Europe.</hi> But what is more contrarie, then terror and mildnesse? and what Sect in sauage crueltie can be compared to <hi>Papists,</hi> that of late haue attempted by fire and Gun-powder to destroy him, whome they confesse to bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the myldest Prince in Europe? Thirdly, he taketh from the King all authority <hi>in Ecclesiasticall causes,</hi> which he reserueth to his holy Father, and his dependants: and although in termes he doe not abridge the Kings right in his Tēporalities; yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one knoweth, that <hi>Papists</hi> make Kinges the Popes sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and giue to the Pope power to censure and depose Kings: which none can maintaine, but such as are disloyall to Princes, and slaues to Popes. Fourthly, most cunningly he doth insinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, that Kings and Princes are beholding to Priestes for their Kingdomes; because <hi>they receiue of them</hi> (as he saith) <hi>their conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration, Crownes</hi> and <hi>Scepters.</hi> So this prating Masse-priest doth not only treacherously subject Kinges to the Popes sword and censures, but also absurdly tyeth their right and inheritance
<pb facs="8"/> to the Crowne, to the rite of consecration. Finally, not content to debase the Kings Royall state, and to deminish his right, he compareth himselfe in his Priest-hood most proudly to <hi>Christ</hi> himselfe, and his holy Apostles. But none but the disciples of <hi>Antichrist</hi> make them-selues in priest-hood comparable to <hi>Christ,</hi> nor doe any but false Apostles make the Apostles sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, and aequall themselues to the Apostles.</p>
   <p>Now these errors he acknowledged not, nor can excuse. His inciuility he would gladly excuse and defend. But his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence is worse, then the offence it selfe. <hi>For the first</hi> (saith he) <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian the Emperour will excuse me, who commended vnto Minutius his proconsul of Asia, as a thing of importance: Ne nomen condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur sed crimen.</hi> He maketh also along discourse, relating vnto vs, how wrongfully Christians were hated for the name. But what affinity is there betweene the names of Christians, and the names of sacrificing Masse-priests? Againe, how can the cyclopicall priests of <hi>Baal</hi> pretend to be successors eyther of the Apostles, or of auncient Bishops? Did euer any auncient Bishop or other Doctor of the Church say, that the priest did swallowe downe Christes body whole into his bellie? againe, if that which is offered be consumed, as the <hi>Papists</hi> themselues teach; How can this priest <hi>K.</hi> defend, that hee offereth vp Christ vnder the accidents of Bread and Wine, vnlesse like the <hi>Iewes,</hi> he murder <hi>Christ,</hi> or at the least deuoure him? Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, <hi>Adrian</hi> in his Epistle to <hi>Minutius Fūdanus</hi> hath not these wordes, <hi>ne nomen condemnaretur, sed crimen.</hi> as it is euident by the wordes of this Epistle reported by <hi>Iustine Martyr</hi> in his se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Apologie. Finally we do not oppugne Masse-priests for the name of priestes, as this dreaming suruey or imagineth, but for because being made priestes beyond the Seas, they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ready at their creators the Popes cōmaund, to attempt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Princes, to trouble his state, to rayse sedition, as the late attempts of <hi>Watson</hi> &amp; <hi>Clarke,</hi> of <hi>Pearcy</hi> and his mates, set on by Priestes and <hi>Iesuites</hi> to blow vp the whole Parliament, and to make a general massacre, and Rebellion, doe plainely declare.</p>
   <p>For the second he telleth vs, <hi>that he is come from the great Monarch of heauen to salute the King;</hi> and that <hi>he is Gods Legate, and therfore not to be denyed audience, when the Ambassadors of the Kings of the earth are heard with so fauourable a countenance.</hi> But if
<pb facs="9"/> he come from the Monarch of heauen, why doth he not shewe forth his warrant, and proue his heauenly &amp; angelical mission? If he be Gods true Legat, why doth he hide his false face? If he will be respected as earthly Ambassadors, then must he shewe forth a Commission, as earthly Ambassadors doe. Otherwise he will be taken for the Legat of Sathan, set on by the Pope to write heretical discourses and scurrilous Libels, to infect the peoples mindes with a distast of truth, and with superstitious, heretical and disloyal humours, &amp; not Gods Ambassador sent to the King, to declare his will. God certes neuer gaue any man commission to perswade the Popes tyrannical authoritye, the sacrifice of the Masse for quicke &amp; dead, the 7. sacraments, the worship of Saints and Images after the Romish facion, and such like doctrines. Further he addeth <hi>That the lowest Subiect may crye, Ʋiue le Roy.</hi> But what maketh that for him, that held him-selfe for no subject of our late Queene being excōmuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate by the Pope, &amp; thinketh it not lawful to subject himselfe to the King, that now is, if the Pope should take Armes against him, and excōmunicate him? Furthermore such as he is, are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be reputed tall and stout Traytors, then low or lowlie subjects, crying not <hi>viue le Roy,</hi> with any true heart, but as <hi>Iudas</hi> cryed, al hayle to Christ, when he betrayed him: or as <hi>Squire,</hi> that was sent by the Iesuite <hi>Walpoole</hi> to empoyson the late Queene, cryed <hi>God saue the Queene,</hi> when he put poyson on the Pommell of her Saddle. If then the Pope shall once beginne to display his Banner and thunder out his excommunications against the King; then we are not to doubt, but as now <hi>Kellison</hi> cryeth, <hi>God saue the King,</hi> so then he would cry, downe with him, downe with him, and with all that followe him, and take parte with him. For such as ment to blow him vp with Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not being excōmunicat, would not I think, spare him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made subject to the Popes thundring censures.</p>
   <p>For the third, hee answeareth first, <hi>that it doth agrandise a Kinges greatnes, to accept of little presentes.</hi> And next, <hi>that he offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth himselfe as his Maiesties faithfull seruant.</hi> Lastly he standeth on stilts of high termes, and telleth vs, that <hi>he offereth the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of God, the saluation and safetie of the King and his subiects, and the peace of his people.</hi> But neyther is his Booke a little present being a large fardle of wast paper, nor can so big a lubber passe
<pb facs="9"/> for a small guift: although in truth both be of so low a price, that he might much be ashamed to make offer of either to so iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious a Prince, but that he wanteth both shame &amp; iudgemēt. Beside that, it may be a questiō how he can giue himselfe to the King, that hath already giuen himselfe bodye and soule to the Pope, whose mark he carrieth on his shauen Crowne. A faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Seruant, certes, hee cannot be to the King, seeing no man can serue two Maisters. <hi>Pearcy</hi> promised as much as he. Yet sought he the destruction of the King &amp; State, being perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereto by Iesuites, and led into treason by the rules of Popish Religion. As for the Masse and Doctrines of Poperie, which he bringeth with him, they leade to destruction, and not to saluation; they teach idolatrye, and not Gods true worship; error and Heresie, and not true Faith. The Popes obedience is a yoke in supportable. His lawes are snares, of mens consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. His Priests and Fryars are the Locustes come out of the bothomlesse pit of Hell. His Religion is neyther Catholike nor auncient, but rather a mixture of new and olde Heresies. Neither can the King looke eyther for safety or peace so long as he suffereth a generation of viperous Priests and Friars de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on an Arch-Priest to liue within the bowels of the State, and a packe of Papists to vphold the authority of his op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posites vnder colour of Religion. Take away the Gun pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Papists, &amp; such as had rather serue Antichrist, then Christ, to bow their knees to <hi>Baalim</hi> then to worship God, and then you remoue the hopes of our enemies, that seek to disturbe our peace, &amp; the firebrāds of troubles, that are the likeliest meanes to set all on a flame.</p>
   <p>To such as demaund why hee dedicated this great bale of blotting paper to the King, he giueth this answere, <hi>that hee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not want an answere, because he cannot want a reason.</hi> And no doubt, but he imagined, that therein he did pindarize, and speake ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eloquently. Yet many want answeres, that haue farre more reason and honestie then he, &amp; diuers want no ready answeres, that proceede without reason. Whatsoeuer hee pretendeth, little reason had he to offer this bundl e of papers to the King. For albeit learned men present their Bookes to Kings, suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing <hi>nothing to bee well begunne, vnlesse after God the King fauour it,</hi> as <hi>Vegetius</hi> affirmeth: yet this is nothing to this rude peece
<pb facs="10"/> of worke, that is so fraught with calumniations and idle dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses, that neither God nor man can well seeme to fauour it. Further although the King <hi>delite in Bookes,</hi> and <hi>hath set foorth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers rare monuments of his rare wit and learning:</hi> yet doth hee not take pleasure in such scurrilous surueyes. Nor may we thinke, that a man of such iudgement and learning can like or allowe such base stuffe. Thirdly we confesse that the King is indeede, <hi>the protector of Religion, the Champion of the Church, and defender of the Faith.</hi> But little doth this auaile <hi>Kellisons</hi> cause, who plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth rather for jdolatrie and superstition, then Religion; for the sinagogue of Antychrist, rather then for Christs Church; for the errors and abuses of Poperie, rather then for the faith of Christ. Fourthly it is not to be doubted, but that all the Kings true friendes did tryumph and make Bonfires at the Kings happie entrance into the Kingdome, and at his Coronation. But that sheweth that the Iesuites, Masse-priestes and their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents are not the Kings true Friends. For they tryumph but a little at the Kings prosperitie, and many of them of late haue sought insteede of Bonfires, which this <hi>K.</hi> calleth <hi>Feux de Ioy,</hi> to set the Cittie vppon a fire, &amp; to blow vp the Parliament house and places adioyning with Gunne-powder. Other their consorts are more desirous to burne the bones &amp; bodies of Gods saints, then to make bonfires, when they vnderstand of the Kinges prosperous successe. Fiftly, wee acknowledge <hi>that God by his prouidence hath reserued the King for the Crowne of England,</hi> &amp; quietly possessed him of his Crowne. But we know also that the Papists haue of late sought to depriue him of his liberty, life, and Crowne. And <hi>Parsons</hi> and the Iesuites of long time haue oppugned the Kings Title, both of them resisting not onely the Kings right, but also Gods prouidence. Finally if for all these fauours God expect at his Maiesties handes, that <hi>hee imploye himselfe in some honorable seruice</hi> for the Catholike Church, and <hi>Christes</hi> true faith, and for the deliuerance of his Realmes from Aegiptiā captiuitie, and the restoring of his sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to the Catholike faith, as <hi>Kellison</hi> desireth; then is hee to take a resolute course for the remouing of al idolatrous Masse-priestes, which seduce his Subiectes, and turne them from the Catholike faith &amp; their alleageance, to imbrace humane tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and the decretaline Doctrine of the Pope, and to prefer
<pb facs="10"/> the Pope before their King. Then is he further to ouerthrow the groues of the jdolatrous Priestes, and to prouide that his Realmes be not againe entangled with a yoake of bondage, &amp; ouer-whelmed with ignorance, &amp; <hi>Aegiptian</hi> darkenesse. Last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he is to see, that Heresies and false Doctrines bee not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vnder the colour of Romish Religion.</p>
   <p>Most grossely therefore hath this Romish Legat fayled in the proofes of his presumptuous attempt, in presenting his worthlesse and trifling discourses to the King. But hauing once passed the limits of modestie, he passeth himself in impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, afterward aduenturing to preferre a sute to the King for libertie to Papists, and for tolleration of Popish Religion. A matter, that with modestie cannot be mencioned to so pious a King, and by rules of Religion and state may not be granted: For it is impious, Idolatrous, and heretical. And therfore may not be admitted of christiās. It is factious, rebellious &amp; deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory both to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prerogatiue of Princes, &amp; liberty of Subiects. And therfore not to be endured in any wel gouerned state. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally themselues admit no Religion contrarie to their owne false groundes, if they can doe withall. Why doe they then require that of others, that they yeeld not to others thēselues? if he deny any point of these, he shall finde them iustified in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers answers framed to the importune supplycations of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistes, and wee shall alwaies be readye to prooue the same a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, as oft as the matter shall come in question.</p>
   <p>But had he reason to come to the King, yet he hath no reason to rayle on the Kings predecessor Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of famous memorie, as hee dooth, charging hir first with <hi>raysing a storme of persecution,</hi> and next <hi>with the ruine of the Catholtke faith.</hi> Nay most falsely he chargeth a most clement and mercifull Queene with persecution, and a Christian Prince of singular pyetie, with hatred of Catholike Religion. Moste falsely I say, for al her actes, and lawes doe argue an excellent moderation in her proceedings, against such as moste violentlye prosecuted her: and so farre was she vrged to doe that shee did, that the secular Priestes not onely excuse her for proceeding against Papists, but also to their vttermost defend her. Furthermore no christ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ian Prince in our time shewed more zeale in the defence of true Catholike Religion, then she. True it is, that shee fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="11"/> not Popish errors. But nothing is more different then Popery and Catholike Religion. Neither shall this <hi>K.</hi> euer prooue the contrarie.</p>
   <p>Hauing ended his idle discourse concerning the dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his book, he maketh bolde to begin his sute for a tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Popery. But his proceding is sottish &amp; intollerable. <hi>He cōmeth to the King</hi> as he saith, <hi>armed with hope, &amp; constrayned by necessitie in the name of the Kings Catholike subiects, in the name of the Catholike Church, in the name of all Catholike Princes, and of all the Christian worlde, nay in the name of the great King of heauen and earth.</hi> But as the common Prouerbe is, <hi>The hilles trauaile, and out commeth a ridiculous Mouse.</hi> For first what hope can this armed fellowe pretend, to obtaine fauourable audience either of the King, or State, that not onely rayleth on true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the Kings true subjectes, but also pleadeth for such, as of late sought to destroye both the King and State? Againe how can he and his consortes talke of comming armed with hope, when <hi>Catesbie</hi> and his followers came armed with yron, to cut the Kings throte, and to take away our liues: and when his armes are not hope, nor arguments, but bitter Inuectiues, dartes of slaunder, and malicious fictions? Thirdly, no man is compelled by necessitie to play the Vice, and that without all colour or vizor of modestie. For what is more Vice-like, then for such a pild compagnion, to pretend the name of all the Christian worlde, and all Catholike Princes, being not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to shewe commission, either from any Prince, or any part of the Christian worlde? Fourthlye, not onely all the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, but also all Catholike Princes doe disauow this presumptuous fellowes pretended Commission, renouncing his impious doctrine concerning the faith and Sacraments, his trecherous opinions concerning the Popes vsurped authority in deposing and killing Christian King's, his wicked defence of the worship of Saints and Angels, and all his idle declama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, lewd lyes, heathenish impostures, &amp; false doctrines &amp; heresies. Fiftly, the Papists of <hi>England</hi> (for the most part) doe euill deserue the name of subjectes. But were they ranked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong subjectes, yet are they not to be ranked among Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, seeing they receiue the errors of the modern Synagogue of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; erre in the faith. How-soeuer they think of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues,
<pb facs="11"/> they haue no reason to allowe their pild Proctors plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for others, who putteth them among theeues and murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers: and concludeth; that Papists are to haue a tolleration of their opinions, because <hi>Theeues and murderers are now pardoned.</hi> We say his conclusion is weake and simple: For faultes once committed, are more easily pardoned, then a lycence graunted to commit faultes euer heer-after. Further, offences against our brethern, are more easilye remitted, then offences, that are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly committed against God. Sixtly, if Princes that liue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Pope, and are his vassals, would prefer any sute to the King, they would cōmend it to wiser Agents, and not to such a balde compagnion. Seuenthly, it is a grosse conceit of a raw diuine, to thinke, that the Christiā world euer beleeued in the Popes triple Crowne, or guard of Switzers, or embraced the doctrine of the Conuenticle of <hi>Trent</hi> and Schoolmen concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Traditions, Sacraments, Purgatory, Indulgēces, worship of Saints and Angels, and such like poyntes of Popish sayth. Finally, if this counterfet Legat doe not shew his Commission vnder Seale, and plainly proue the Popes Decretales, the doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine of the Conuenticle of <hi>Trent</hi> &amp; School-men, the Popes two swordes and all the trash of Poperie; he is to be rejected as a frantike forger of newe Commissions, and disauowed by his clyents, as a foolish and simple pleader.</p>
   <p>His reasons for tolleration of Popery, are either grounded vpon false positions, or else want forme of good conclusions. That which he sayth of the Kinges Predecessors, that <hi>with Crowne, Scepter and Sword,</hi> they mainteyned the moderne doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, of the <hi>Romish</hi> Church, is vtterly false. For they neuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued, that the Pope had power to take away their Crownes, or that Christians (like Canibals) did eate Christs flesh with their teeth, and swallowe it downe into their bellyes, or other moderne Romish errors, heresies and impieties. But did any ancient Princes maintaine errors, that bindeth not their poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to continue therein. We are not to folowe the steppes of our parents, where them-selues tread awrye. <hi>Constantine</hi> left the Paganisme of his auncestors. The auncient Kinges of <hi>Spayne</hi> were <hi>Arians,</hi> yet doe the later Kinges of <hi>Spayne</hi> detest <hi>Arianisme.</hi> False it is also that the people of <hi>Scotland</hi> in time past were of the same faith, which this <hi>Kellison</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="12"/> at <hi>Doway.</hi> It may bee they built Abbeyes, worshipped Saints, &amp; vsed some popish ceremonies more then christian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiō required. But <hi>K.</hi> must prooue, that they beleeued the doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine of the Cōuenticle of <hi>Trent,</hi> &amp; al the Popes decretales, &amp; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended in jdolatrie, as grossely and obstinately, as the Papists doe now, or else hee trifleth out time in vaine. Thirdly hee speaketh not onely falsely but also absurdly, where he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth honour to such Princes, as imbrace Poperie. For what can be more dishonorable, then for Kings to become vassals, to lose halfe their Subjects, halfe their authoritye, halfe their reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues? doth <hi>Kellison</hi> suppose it honorable for Kings to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolled, deposed, killed? or can any free English man endure to be subiect to <hi>Italians</hi> and strangers? Fourthly, vainely doth this declaimer promise <hi>felicitie to the Realme,</hi> declyning to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery. There can be no greater bondage, nor miserie for mens soules, then to be entangled with popish lawes, traditions and censures. Base it is to endure the Masse-priestes extortions and pillages, greeuous to see the land deuoured by Caterpillers. Fiftly we confesse, it is honorable to conquer Heresie; but this honor belongeth not to Princes blinded with poperie: which is nothing else but a masse or compendium of diuers heresies. Contrarywise if Masse-priests were rooted out, and Gods true Religion in euerie quarter sincerely receiued; then should we neither feare the wrath of God threatned against jdolaters and contemners of Religion, nor the enmitie &amp; opposition of men hauing no meanes to hurt vs, but by the practises &amp; mutinies of Papists. Sixtly, neither is the Religion professed in England <hi>new,</hi> nor is popery <hi>old.</hi> And therein I wil ioyne issue with this Surueyor, if hee dare maintaine the contrarye. Hee braggeth much, but the surfet of popery hath distempered his wits. Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenthly it was honorable, we confesse, for <hi>Constantine</hi> to restore Christian Religion. But what maketh this for poperie, which was not in the world in the daies of <hi>Constantine,</hi> nor many ages after? Furthermore when <hi>Kellison</hi> shall be at any leysure, and not troubled with his Gunpowder plots of high treason, then we will shew and prooue to his teeth, that poperie is a corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō of faith, &amp; a declination frō Christian Religion to errors &amp; heresies. Finally, to secure the Kings life, and the peace of the State, this wise Orator offereth oathes. But Christian people
<pb facs="12"/> are too well acquainted with the practises of Papists to trust them eyther vpon oathes, bands, or pledges. Of late while they were moste forward to offer oathes, and all securitie that could be deuised, then <hi>Pearcy</hi> and his mates were sitting pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vnder the Parliament house, and laying a plot for a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral massacre of all true Christians, and for a Rebellion of al dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented Persons, and Papists. Further they teach that oathes are not to be performed to Hereticks, &amp; easily doth the Pope dispence with them. Who then is so patient as to endure this simple fellowes foolish prating? these cut-throate Priestes will murder honest men, &amp; their soules shal sue them for periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry! is not this (trow you) a goodly deuice?</p>
   <p>Whether he speake for his owne cause, or against vs, his idle talke is not much to be regarded, that either affirmeth matters nakedly vpon his owne bare word, or bringeth no better wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse then <hi>Nicol Borne, Genebrard, Baronius, Thomas Aquinas,</hi> &amp; such like, or alleadgeth Scriptures impertinently and falselye, or else belyeth his aduersaries shamefully. Against <hi>Caluin</hi> hee bringeth a place out of his Institutions, as if he taught, <hi>that by religion men might disobey Princes lawes:</hi> a matter neither taught, nor euer thought vpon by him. To what end then bringeth he allegations out of Scriptures and Fathers, to disprooue this rebellious position? would hee haue all the world to see, that Papists disobeying Princes vpon the Popes warrant repugne both to Scriptures and Fathers?</p>
   <p>His skill in Diuinitie we may easily conjecture not to be singular. For first he preferreth the will of man in his conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, before Gods grace. <hi>Religion</hi> sayth he, <hi>is not transfused with flesh and blood, but infused by God, with consent of our will, and opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of grace.</hi> Secondly, he maketh mans blood an oblation for sinne, and a mediation of others conuersion. Thirdly, he as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signeth <hi>Aureolam martyrum,</hi> that is, a degree aboue the cōmon glory of Gods Saints, as a rewarde due to Martyrs for their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssion. Fourthly, he sayth <hi>Many Ʋirgins haue liued in the flesh like Angels.</hi> But to say that man can liue without sinne, is <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gianisme.</hi> Lastly, his groundes are out of <hi>Tho. Aquinas,</hi> and the School-men. Is it then like that his Babylonian building wil long stand?</p>
   <p>His notable simplicitie is euery where apparant. For see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="13"/> king the Kings fauour, he rayleth on Religion professed by the King. Pleading for the Pope, he ouerthroweth the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the Pope. For if the authoritie of Kings be from God, then cannot Popes discharge subjectes from their dutie and obedience to Princes. Shewing him-selfe vnable to write or to dispute, yet most simply he chalengeth vs all into the field, offring to dispute with vs. Lastly, wanting other meanes, he maketh the King a petitioner vnto him-selfe.</p>
   <p>His honesty cannot be great, that rayleth against the dead, flattereth such as are able to fauour him, belyeth both the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and dead. <hi>By Popes</hi> sayth he <hi>alwayes Countryes haue beene conuerted.</hi> Yet for many yeares haue they giuē ouer preaching, and lately haue suffered the Turkish religiō to eniambe &amp; get ground vpon <hi>Christians.</hi> He saith further, <hi>That our Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan but yesterday,</hi> that <hi>our teachers want authoritie,</hi> that <hi>our doctrine hath the markes of heresie,</hi> that <hi>we pull at Christs diuinitie, make him no redeemer, spirituall Phisitian, law-giuer, Priest, nor Iudge, but make him ignorant, desperate and damned.</hi> He chargeth vs further that <hi>we haue neither Priest, Sacrifice, Sacrament, nor Prayer:</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters impudently and without all colour of truth auowched, as shall plainly appeare by our answer. If, when he commeth to dispute, he bring no more truth, Children will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>isse him out of Schooles for an impudent and lying compagnion.</p>
   <p>These being the principall poyntes and whole somme of this rude Orators pleading before his Majestie, wherein no dout he hath made the fairest shew he could of such base wares; We may easily imagine, that his speech to the common reader is more rude, harsh, and disioynted. In the beginning of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle, he rūneth out like a wilde discourser, into a long sence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse, and vnreasonable speach concerning <hi>inanimate &amp; vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable creatures.</hi> But it must needes be a dull, dead, and vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable cause, that hath such dead &amp; vnreasonable aduocates to plead for it. He turneth the Sunne into a Cocke, &amp; a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and birds into Carpenters, &amp; brute beastes into hearbists. But whereto tendeth this brutish discourse, voyde both of the light of the Sunne, and of the light of reason? doth he place his consortes among feathered fooles, or else among brute beasts? from sencelesse creatures (in which ranke we may place a good parte of this Surueyer and his consortes) he leapeth to
<pb facs="13"/> brute beastes, and frō brute beastes to man. And yet nothing he writeth, that may beseeme a sensible creature, much lesse a reasonable and discreete man. The end and marke of all his wilde vagary is this, to shewe, that <hi>because God hath giuen vs a will wholy bent to good,</hi> and an <hi>vnderstanding naturally enclined to truth, &amp; auerted from all vntruthes,</hi> he hath therfore <hi>made an exact Suruey of the new Religiō,</hi> as he saith. But first these things hang no better together then if he should say he would to <hi>Rome,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause <hi>Totnam</hi> is foure miles from <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>Doway</hi> is turned Spanish. For man may haue an vnderstanding and will, and yet frame no such false surueyes. Nay if this surueyor had either had any vnderstanding, or good purpose, he would neuer haue imployed his labour in such a lewde peece of seruice. Further neither dooth mans wil desire any good thing tending to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, or vnderstand any such thing, so long as he is vnrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate by Gods grace. The wordes of the Apostle are cleare. <hi>There dwelleth no go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d thing in my flesh.</hi> And againe, <hi>the naturall man vnderstandeth not the things that are of God.</hi> Thirdly, if mans will &amp; vnderstanding had beene so inclined, as he pretendeth; then would <hi>Kellison</hi> neuer haue liued vnder the yoke of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, nor beleeued the absurdities of popish Religion: of which we shall speake God willing, particularly heereafter. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly so farre is his suruey from exactnesse, as a surfet of foolery from sound vnderstanding and reason. Finally, nothing shall this <hi>K.</hi> bee able to alleadge in our Religion, that abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth eyther from reason, or rule of good vnderstanding. The mission and calling of our Bishops and Ministers shal be iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied against all the barking of Masse-Priestes and Iesuites. <hi>The markes of Hereticks</hi> shall be wiped from our selues, &amp; deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imprinted vpon our aduersaries. Our Doctrine shal be clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the vniust imputations of our aduersaries, and euerie indifferent man satisfied, that <hi>we neither empayre Christes honor,</hi> nor deny his <hi>Preesthood.</hi> But contrariwise the Papists commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate <hi>Christs</hi> honor to creatures, &amp; his preest-hood to Masse-Priestes. We shall also proue by plaine euidence, that we vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde <hi>the authoritie of Princes and their lawes,</hi> which the Papists ouerthowe and despise. Wee doubt not further to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate, that none of vs euer taught, <hi>that God is author of sinne,</hi> or <hi>cruell,</hi> or <hi>tyrannicall</hi> in his proceedings. Finally, we should bee
<pb facs="14"/> much ashamed, if vices and all impieties were not better censured and punished in <hi>England,</hi> then in <hi>Italy, Spaine,</hi> and other popish Countries.</p>
   <p>These matters which <hi>Kellison</hi> vanteth, that hee will make good against vs, haue been not onely formerly obiected vnto vs by <hi>William Raynoldes</hi> and <hi>D. Gifford</hi> in their rayling volume intituled <hi>Caluino-turcismus,</hi> but also answered by vs in a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise called <hi>Turco Papismus.</hi> And that so sufficiētly, that <hi>D. Gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> resteth eyther satisfied, or silent. If then this new suruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or would needes renew their slaunders and vaine obiections, he should for his credit sake haue doone wel, eyther to haue replyed to our answere, or to haue held his peace, as his betters haue done. Againe if hee had beene so wise and circumspect, as he pretendeth to bee; he would haue been well aduised be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he entred this course, least he might giue vs occasion to rip vp the deformities, fooleries, absurdities, Heresies, impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and other abuses of Popery, of which I doubt not, but his best friendes, when they are laid open, will bee much asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Himselfe being but a new vpstart Doctor, &amp; lately crept out of my Lord <hi>Vauxes</hi> Buttery, will bee much puzled to make any probable defence for them.</p>
   <p>Thus much may serue for answere to the front of his Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey and his two liminare Epistles. For the rest, I shall not neede to say much in this place. Onely this, I thought good to signifye vnto thee, good Reader, that thou looke not for any curious or long answere heereafter: to wit, that the whole vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume is nothing but a newe packe of olde calumniations and lyes. The forme of his discourse is trifling, the Subject ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. Such declamations, it should seeme hee was wont in the time of his butlerage to make ouer a canne of Beere. His proofes are fancies and bare conceites. His witnesses, fellowes of a lowe price. His conclusions weake collections. It may bee, eyther neede and hunger, or else hope and promise of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward made him so talkatiue. How be it least hee might grow proud of his owne prowesse, I haue vndertaken to shape him a short answere. In the meane while, concerning his obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and proofes, this hee may learne of mee for his instruction. First that it is a foolish thing for a man to obiect that to others, whereof they are cleare, and hee moste guiltie: and to suruey o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="14"/> mens estates, when his owne can abide no suruey. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that the bosome and domesticall testimonies of <hi>Cochleus, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebrard, Bolsec, Stapleton</hi> and such like are little to be esteemed. <hi>Fidele est testimonium quod causas non habet mentiendi. That testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> saith <hi>Hierome ad Saluinam, deserueth most credit, that hath no causes of fiction.</hi> Be not then mooued with the largenesse of <hi>Kelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi> volume, nor with his manifold leasings. Common bara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors are wont to put in longest billes, whē they haue least mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: and shallow waters make moste noise. To such lewd and long lies, this our short answere will be more then suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient. Vouchsafe therefore to compare both our discourses together, and to reade them with indifferency. And so thou shalt soone discouer the vanitie of his accusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and giue sentence for our innocency.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>