<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY NEWE, AND DEARELY Affected charge, the Diocesse of EXCETER, All Grace and bene∣diction.</title>
           <author>Exon, Joseph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117610_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02563</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12690</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117610</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY NEWE, AND DEARELY Affected charge, the Diocesse of EXCETER, All Grace and bene∣diction.</title>
                 <author>Exon, Joseph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The olde religion : a treatise, wherin is laid downe the true state of the difference betwixt the reformed, and Romane Church; and the blame of this schisme is cast vpon the true authors. Seruing for the vindication of our innocence, for the setling of wauering minds for preseruatiue against Popish insinuations. By Ios. Hall, B. of Exon</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                            <distributor>Hawkins, Richard</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>46, 199, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO MY NEWE, AND DEARELY Affected charge, the Diocesse of EXCETER, All Grace and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He truth of my heart giues mee boldnes to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, before him, who onely knowes it, that the same God, who hath
<pb facs="3"/>
cald me to the ouer-sight of your Soules, hath wrought in me a zealous desire of your saluation. This desire cannot but incite mee to a carefull preuention of those dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, which might threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the disappointment of so happie an end: Those dangers are either sinnes of practice, or errours of of Doctrine: Against both these I haue faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully vowed my vtmost indeuours. I shal labour against the first, by Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching,
<pb facs="3"/>
Example, Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures; Wherein it shall bee your choyce to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect either the rod, or the Spirit of meekenesse. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the latter, my Pen hath risen vp in this ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly assault. It hath beene assured mee, that in this time of late Vacancie, false Teachers, catching the Fore-locke of occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, haue beene busie in scattering the tares of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours amongst you: I ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily beleeue it; since I know it is not in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb facs="4"/>
of the greatest vigilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie to hinder their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of euill. Euen a full See is no sufficient barre to craftie seducers; Their suggestions wee cannot preuent, their suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse wee may: This I haue here assay'd to doe; bending my stile against Popish Doctrine, with such Christian modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as may argue zeale without malice, desire to winne Soules, no will to gall them. And since the commonest of all the
<pb facs="4"/>
grounds of Romish de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit is the pretence of their Age, and our Noueltie; and nothing doth more dazle the eyes of the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, then the name of our forefathers, and the chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge of a particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cital of our professors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Luthers</hi> reuolt, I haue (I hope) fully clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this coast, so as out of the right apprehension of these differences, my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der shal euidently see the vanitie of this cauill, and find cause to blesse God
<pb facs="5"/>
for the safetie of his stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in so pregnant, and vndeceiueable a truth.</p>
   <p>For me, I shame not to professe, that I haue passed my most, and best houres in quiet Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; wherein I needed not bend mine edge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst any Aduersarie, but Satan, and mine own corruptions: These con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersorie points I haue rather crost in my way, then taken along with me; Neither am I igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant what incomparably
<pb facs="5"/>
cleare beames (in this kind) some of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy lights of our Church haue cast abroad into all eyes, to the admiration of present, and future times; no corner of truth hath lyen vnsearcht, no plea vnargued: the wit of man can not make any essen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall additions either to our proofes, or answeres; But, as in the most per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect discouerie, where Lands and Riuers are specially descried, there may bee some small obs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
<pb facs="6"/>
in-lets reserued for the notice of following experience; So is it in the businesse of these sacred quarrels; That braine is very vnhappie which meets not with some tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of Discourse more then it hath borrowed from anothers Pen; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides which, hauing fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len vpon a methode, and manner of Tractation, which might be of vse to plain vnderstandings, the familiaritie whereof pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised to contribute, not
<pb facs="6"/>
a little, to the informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and setling of weaker soules, I might not hide it from you, to whose common good I haue gladly resolu'd to sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice my selfe: Let it bee taken with the same con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of loue, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it is tendred, and, that you may improoue this, and all other my fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing labours to a sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aduantage, giue mee leaue to impart my selfe to you a litle in this short, and free preamble.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>It is a large body, I know, and full of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate varietie, to which I now direct my words; Let mee awhile, in these lines, seuer them, whom I would neuer abide real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dis-ioyned.</p>
   <p>Yee my deare fellow-labourers (as my imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate charge) may well challenge the first place. It is no small ioy to mee to expect so able hands, vpon whom I may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably vnloade the weight of this my spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb facs="7"/>
care: If fame doe not ouer-speake you, there are not many soyles that yeeld either so frequent Flockes, or better fed; Goe on happily in these high steps of true blessed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, &amp; saue your selues, and others; To which purpose; Let mee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to you (according to the sweete experience of a greater Shepheard) two maine helpes of our sacred trade, first, the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Pastures, and second the still Waters; By the
<pb facs="8"/>
one, I meane an inuring of our People to the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of wholesome Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; By the other, an immunitie from all facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and disturbance of the publike peace.</p>
   <p>It was the obseruation of the learnedst King that euer sate hitherto in the English Throne▪ that the cause of the mis-car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of our People into Poperie, and other er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, was, their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groūdednes in the points of Catechisme; How
<pb facs="8"/>
should those soules bee but carried about with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie wind of Doctrine, that are not wel Ballasted with solid informations: Whence it was that his said late Maiestie (of happie memorie) gaue publike order for bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the later part of Gods day in familiar Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chising; then which, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could bee deuised more necessarie, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houefull to the Soules of men; It was the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and Ill-disposed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb facs="9"/>
of some cauillers, that taxed this course, as preiudicial to Preachings Since, in truth, the most vse-full of all Preaching is Catecheticall. This layes the grounds, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther raiseth the wals, and roofe; this informes the iudgement, that, stirres vp the affections: What good vse is there of those affections that runne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the iudgement? Or of those wals that want a foundation? For my part, I haue spent the
<pb facs="9"/>
greater halfe of my life in this station of our holy seruice: I thanke God, not vnpainefully, not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitably; But, there is no one thing, whereof I repent so much, as not to haue bestowed more houres in this publike Exercise of Catechisme; In regard whereof, I could quarrell my very Sermons, and wish that a great part of them had beene exchanged for this Preaching conference: Those other Diuine dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses
<pb facs="10"/>
enrich the braine &amp; the tong; this settles the heart; those other are but the descants to this plain-song; Contemne it not, my Brethren, for the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie &amp; noted homelinesse; The most excellent and beneficiall thinges are most familiar; What can bee more obuious then Light, Ayre, Fire, Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; Let him that can liue without these, despise their commonnesse: Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as we make so much more vse of the Diuine
<pb facs="10"/>
bountie in these ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie benefits, so let vs the more gladly improoue these ready &amp; facil helps to the saluation of many soules; the neglect where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of breedes instabilitie of iudgment, mesprision of necessarie truths, fashio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nablenesse of profession, frothinesse of discourse, obnoxiousnesse to all er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and seduction. And if any of our people loath this Manna, because they may gather it from vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Feete, let not
<pb facs="11"/>
their palates be humourd ic this wanton nauseati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: They are worthy to fast, that are wearie of the Bread of Angels: And if herein we bee curious to satisfie their rouing appetite, our fauour shall be no better then Iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: So wee haue seene an vndiscreete Schoole-master, whiles he affects the thankes of an ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weening Parent, marre the progresse of a forward Child, by raysing him to an higher forme, and
<pb facs="11"/>
Author, ere he haue wel learned his first rules; whence followes an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptie ostentation, and a late disappointment: Our fidelitie and care of profit must teach vs to driue at the most sure, and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall good, which shall vndoubtedly bee best at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by these safe and needfull ground-workes.</p>
   <p>From these tender pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stures let mee leade you, (and you, others) to the still Waters; Zeale in the Soule is as naturall
<pb facs="12"/>
heat in the body; there is no life of Religion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it; but as the kindliest heat, if it bee not tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with a due equalitie of moysture, wasts it selfe and the body; So doth zeale, if it be not modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with discretion, and charitable care of the common good; It is hard to bee too vehement in contending for maine and euident truthes; but litigious and immateriall verities may soone be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-striuen for; in the
<pb facs="12"/>
prosecution whereof, I haue oft lamented to see how heedlesse too many haue beene of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like welfare; Whiles, in seeking for one scruple of truth, they haue not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to spend a whole pound-weight of preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Peace.</p>
   <p>The Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, in whose mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood wee haue all iust cause to pride our selues, hath, in much wisdome, and pietie, deliuered her iudgment concerning all necessary points of religiō
<pb facs="13"/>
in so compleat a body of Diuinitie, as all hearts may rest in; These wee read, these we write vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as professing not their truth onely, but their suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie also. The voice of God our Father, in his Scriptures, and (out of these) the voyce of the Church our Mother in her Articles, is that, which must both guide and set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle our resolutiōs: What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer is besides these, is but either priuate, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necessarie and vncertain:
<pb facs="13"/>
Oh that whiles we sweat and bleed for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of these oracular truthes, we could be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded to remit of our Heat in the pursuit of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions: These, these are they that distract the Church, violate our peace, scandalize the weake, aduantage our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. Fire vpon the Hearth warmes the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but if it be mis-placed, burnes the house: My brethren, let vs bee zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for our God; Euery
<pb facs="14"/>
heartie Christian will powre Oyle, and not Water vpon this holy flame: But, let vs take heed least a blind selfe▪ loue, stiffe preiudice, and factious partialitie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose vpon vs, in stead of the causes of God; Let vs be suspicious of all New verities, and carelesse of all vnprofitable; And let vs hate to thinke our selues either wiser then the Church, or better then our superiors: And if any man thinke that he
<pb facs="14"/>
sees further then his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, in these Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall prospects, let his tongue keepe the counsel of his eyes; Least, whiles he affects the fame of deeper learning, he em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broyle the Church, and rayse his glory vpon the publike ruines.</p>
   <p>And ye worthy Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians whose soules God hath entrusted with our spirituall Guardianship, be ye alike minded with your teachers; The mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their tongues lyes
<pb facs="15"/>
much in your eares; your modest desires of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing needfull, and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some truthes, shal auoide their labour after friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and quarrelsome curiosities. God hath blessed you with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of a wise, and knowing people; In these diuine matters, let a meeke sobrietie set boūds to your inquiries. Take vp your time, and hearts with Christ and Him crucified; with those es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentiall truthes which are neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie
<pb facs="15"/>
to saluation; Leaue al curious disquisitions to the Schooles, and say of those problemes, as the Philosopher did of the Athenian shops: How many things are here that we haue no need of. Take the neerest cut yee can, yee shall finde it a side way to heauen, yee need not lengthen it with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due circuitions. I am de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued if (as the times are) yee shall not find worke enough to beare vp against the oppositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="16"/>
of professed hostility, it is not for vs to sqander our thoughts and houres vpon vse-lesse janglings; Wherewith if we suffer our selues to be still taken vp, Satan shal deale with vs like some craftie chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who whiles he holds vs at gaze with trickes of iugling, pickes our poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets.</p>
   <p>Deare brethren, what euer become of these worthlesse driblets, bee sure to looke well to the free-hold of your saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb facs="16"/>
Errour is not more busie then subtile, Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition neuer wanted sweet insinuations: make sure worke against these plausible dangers, Suffer not your selues to bee drawne into the net by the common stale of the Church; Know that outward visibilitie may too well stand with an vtter exclusion from sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. Saluation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sists not in a formalitie of profession, but in a sound<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nesse of beliefe. A true
<pb facs="17"/>
body may be ful of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall diseases: So is the Romane Church of this day; whom we haue long pitied, and laboured to cure in vaine; If she will not bee healed by vs, let not vs be infected by her; Let vs bee no lesse ielous of her Contagion, then she is of our Remedies. Hold fast that precious Truth, which hath been long taught you by faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Pastors, confirmed by cleare euidences of Scriptures, euinced by
<pb facs="17"/>
sound reasons, sealed vp by the bloud of our bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Martyrs; So whiles no man takes away the Crowne of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancie, yee shall be our Crowne and reioycing in the day of the Lord Iesus; To whose all-suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient grace I commend you al; and vow my selfe</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your common Seruant in him whom we all reioyce to serue. <hi>IOS. EXON.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>