<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right VVorshipfull Sir Edvvard PARHAM Knight, Serjeant Major of the Re∣giment of the right Honorable the Lord VAVX, in the Seruice of the King of SPAINE in the Netherlands.</title>
           <author>N., D.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117034_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14004</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13264.8</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117034</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right VVorshipfull Sir Edvvard PARHAM Knight, Serjeant Major of the Re∣giment of the right Honorable the Lord VAVX, in the Seruice of the King of SPAINE in the Netherlands.</title>
                 <author>N., D.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A tongue-combat : lately happening betvveene tvvo English souldiers in the tilt-boat of Grauesend, the one going to serue the King of Spaine, the other to serue the States Generall of the Vnited Provinces. Wherein the cause, course, and continuance of those warres, is debated, and declared</title>
                 <author>Hexham, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 104 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the right VVorshipfull</hi> Sir Edvvard <hi>PARHAM Knight, Serjeant Major of the</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment of the right Honorable the Lord VAVX, in the Seruice of the King of <hi>SPAINE</hi> in the <hi>Netherlands.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>IN my late passage downe from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Grauesend</hi> by <hi>Tilt-boate,</hi> there chanced among others, two Gentlemen at that present also to passe, being both of military profession, but indifferently disposed in their determinations, touching the Sides they went to serue on: for after some course of speech that passed among the companie, the one discouered his intention to goe ouer into the <hi>Netherlands</hi> to serue the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the other manifested his purpose to goe serue the <hi>States of Holland:</hi> but because each of them seemed fortified vvith reason for his determination, and to thinke him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe aswell able to defend it, as hee seemed willing to follow it, all the company, out of a curiositie, were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry desirous to heare what by either side could bee sayd; but yet with a prouiso, that no inconueniencie or fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling out betweene them vpon it might ensue; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they desired them, that before they began seriously to argue the matter, they should passe their words to each other vpon their honours, that without injuring one another in particular, each might haue his free speech in defence of his owne determined course; and that their arguing being ended, there should no excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be taken either by them, or any of the companie,
<pb facs="4"/> for ought that had beene spoken; but that both they, and all the rest of the companie, (their discourse beeing ended) should in ciuill and courteous manner carrie themselues, and so take their leaues of each other, when their wayes lay to be separated. To this all agreed, and these twaine gaue each other their hand vpon the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: and thereupon began betweene them a <hi>Tongue-combate,</hi> wherein neither of both were slaine or mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: and because it may be some recreation vnto you, to vnderstand how the matter passed, I thought good now at my soonest leysure, and aswell as my memorie would permit me, to pen it downe, and to present it to your view, to whom I hold my best indeuours obliged. And this kissing your hands, I take my leaue, wishing vnto you the atchieuing of all honour, answerable vnto your noble valour and courage.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>The deuoted honorer of your Vertues,</hi> D. N.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>