<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Praeface to the discourse ensuing, directed especially to euery moderate, and sober minded papist.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117866_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13159</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23453</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117866</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Praeface to the discourse ensuing, directed especially to euery moderate, and sober minded papist.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe replie to a certaine odious and slanderous libel, lately published by a seditious Iesuite, calling himselfe N.D. in defence both of publike enemies, and disloyall subiects, and entitled A temperate wardword, to Sir Francis Hastings turbulent Watchword : wherein not only the honest, and religious intention, and zeale of that good knight is defended, but also the cause of true catholike religion, and the iustice of her Maiesties proceedings against popish malcontents and traitors, from diuers malitious imputations and slanders cleered, and our aduersaries glorious declamation answered, and refuted by O.E. defendant in the challenge, and encounters of N.D. Hereunto is also added a certaine new challenge made to N.D. in fiue encounters, concerning the fundamentall pointes of his former whole discourse: together with a briefe refutation of a certaine caluminous relation of the conference of Monsieur Plessis and Monsieur d'Eureux before the French king</title>
                 <author>Sutcliffe, Matthew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Bollifant, alias Carpenter, Edmund.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hatfield, Arnold</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 237, that is 239, 7, 132, 6, 38, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="148"/>
   <pb facs="148"/>
   <head>The Praeface to the discourse ensuing, <hi>directed especially to euery moderate,</hi> and sober minded papist.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough sufficient hath bin saide alreadie, not onely to rembarre the malice of <hi>N. D.</hi> his encounters, but also to content euerie man, that is but meanely affected either to the state, or religion nowe publikely professed among vs: yet coulde I not satisfie my selfe, vnlesse I tooke a course to satisfie thee also, whose instruction and saluation I do earnestly affect and thirst after, beseeching God to touch thy hart, and reueale the truth vnto thee, and open thy eies, that are now heauie, and oppressed with a slumber and grosse darkenesse of poperie. The principall piller, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most sole foundation of al our aduersaries discourse is the pretence, which he maketh of ancient apostolike &amp; catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like religion, &amp; the vaine shew of the catholike church: &amp; vpō this he buildeth his inuectiues against vs, his defence of publike enimies, notorious traitors, and priuie malcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes, and presumeth to presse into her Maiesties pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, &amp; to present his petitions to the Lords of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties most honorable priuie Councell; as by that which hath beene spoken may easily be perceiued. Take away this colour, it must needes appeere, that he is a fauorer of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like enimies, a consort of malicious traytors, and an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettor and nourisher of men euill affected in their mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contentment. Nay albeit his colour were better cast; yet were his pleading vnsufficient, seeing true religion can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not stande with rebellion or disloyaltie, nor may true
<pb facs="149"/> catholikes be suffered to oppugne their prince and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, to practise trecherie against the state, and to nourish malcontent humours among subiects. But if it appeere, that the Romanistes are not the true church, and that their religion is neither catholike nor ancient, nor true; then must it needes be granted, that <hi>N. D.</hi> and his consorts are not onely malicious traytors, but also impious heretikes. It is also very plaine, that all his wrangling encounters are built vpon fancies and supposals, without grounde and foundation: and are no better, then malicious inuectiues degorged against good men, and idle pretenses to colour the practises of enimies, traytors and heretikes. For euery traytor can pretend, that he is a true patriot, and Catiline and his consorts, and all rebels vse to set a glosse of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good vpon their priuate wicked deseignements and treasons. <hi>All societies also of heretikes will take vpon them, as true Christians,</hi> as saith<note n="a" place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tut. cap. vlt.</note>
      <hi>Lactantius, and suppose them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to be the catholike church. Tertullian</hi> saith,<note n="b" place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> contr. Marcion.</note>
      <hi>That as waspes make honycombes, so the Marcionites pretend to make churches:</hi> albeit indeed they were no true churches. <hi>Noua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian like apes that counterfeit men,</hi> saith<note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>Epist.</hi> 73.</note>
      <hi>Cyprian, woulde challenge to himselfe the authoritie and truth of the church, albeit he be not of the church, but a rebell and enimie set vp against the church.</hi> Which fitteth our aduersary very well, who if he had his yellow ierkin, were a very ape or an apish Iebusite, entitling himselfe and his companions with the name of the church. But if he had beene a foxe as well as an ape, and had but had a foxes wiles, he would haue made b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tter proofe of his maine groundes: which not being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> is a maine maime of his whole cause.</p>
   <p>Now to the intent that thou maiest perceiue, that all his building is either without foundation, or vpon a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish ground, that will beare no such great worke, I haue thought good for thy satisfaction to challenge him once
<pb facs="149"/> more into the fielde, and to make triall of his manhood in fiue new encounters which do much concerne his cause and credite. For as before I haue shewed him and his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorts to be perfect traytors, and Recusants and malcontent papists to be verie sorie and defectiue subiects; so nowe God willing I purpose to shew first <hi>That papists are no true catholikes:</hi> secondly, <hi>That their religion,</hi> as it differeth from that which we professe, <hi>is a packe of nouelties:</hi> thirdly, <hi>That it is patched vp of many old heresies:</hi> fourthly, <hi>That the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish church is not the true church,</hi> and lastly that <hi>N. D. his consorts whether they were Iesuites or priests, or their adhae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, that haue beene executed to death according to the lawes of England, are to be esteemed traytors, and not mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs.</hi> And this in defence of her Maiesties iustice, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther clemencie. For if she woulde do them iustice, then woulde not she suffer them to liue as subiects, that will not directly acknowledge her to be their Queene, and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full souereigne, especially where the pope saith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie. If she did her-selfe right, she woulde not tolerate a faction notoriously opposite to her gouernment. If she did iustice, she woulde not suffer such to enioy wealth and honors, &amp; life, that adhere to forreine enimies, that seeke the destruction of the common-wealth, the dishonour of this state, the ruine and bloud of all that stande well affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to religion, and the state. And that <hi>Parsons</hi> and the priests, that come out of Spaine, and are sworne to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the <hi>Infantaes</hi> title, and are reconciled or adhering to the pope are all culpable of these treasons, it is so cleered by the former discourse, and by the last chapter of this, that I thinke it may be felt of blinde men, and not onelie discerned by those, that haue eies to looke into the state. The rest maketh for defence of our religion, which no m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n can reprooue, but such as haue drunke deepe of the cup of the purple harlot spoken of Apocalyp. 17. and are
<pb facs="150"/> sworne slaues to the pope, and professed enimies not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of religion and the state, but also of their owne good in this worlde, and of their eternall saluation in the worlde to come.</p>
   <p>Beware therefore my good countryman (for so I must account thee, vntill I see thee declare thy selfe open friend to popish traytors, and enimie to thy counrrey) that harkening to the Sirens songs of Iebusites and priestes, enimies to gods true religion, &amp; not onely to their prince &amp; countrey, thou be not swallowed vp in the gulfe of their heresies and treasons. They lead thee not to the rocke Christ Iesus, vpon which the church is built, but to the<note n="a" place="margin">Bellar. praefat. in lib. de pontif. Rom.</note> rocke the pope, and the bankes of his sandie inuentions, vpon which thou must needs wracke thy selfe, if thou shun them not quickly. True religion is grounded vpon Christs word reuealed to vs in the holy canonicall Scriptures, all which we professe according to the rule of the true catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like church. And for this truth we doubt not to giue our liues: so assured we are of our profession, where as thou, as long as thou continuest a papist, hast no warrant, but the popes worde, which (to say no woorse) is ignorant of true religion, and apostolike faith, and subiect to many errors and infirmities. Read therefore indifferently, and iudge syncerely and vprightly, and the God of truth guide thee into the way of iustice and truth▪</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>