<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Vertuous, and Right Worship∣full LADY, the Lady Rebecca Romeny.</title>
           <author>C., E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117277_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06030</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1642</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117277</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Vertuous, and Right Worship∣full LADY, the Lady Rebecca Romeny.</title>
                 <author>C., E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A helpe to true happinesse. Or A briefe and learned exposition of the maine and fundamentall points of Christian religion. By Mr. Paul Bayne</title>
                 <author>Baynes, Paul</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bladen, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 396 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the Vertuous,</hi> and Right Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>LADY, the</hi> Lady Rebecca Romeny.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His TREATISE falling into my hands by Gods wise and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dispensation, and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and being thought, not onely by my selfe but by diuers others of riper yeares and deeper iudgement, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be published in print for the common good of many. I haue thought good considering that the long
<pb facs="3"/> continued custome of dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating bookes to Persons of some eminencie in the Church of God, hath gotten the vpper hand to dedicate this little Treatise ensuing to your Ladiships name.</p>
   <p>I haue obserued that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many other reasons mouing such learned and godly Diuines as haue either wouen some webbe of their owne spinning, or faithfully trauelled in the fruitfull la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of other men to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate their writings: one speciall reason hath beene to testifie their thankefulnesse to the parties to whom they dedicate the same, by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing their Name both to the present age, and to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steritie for the further en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging, both of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues,
<pb facs="3"/> and others to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in piety and vertue; and especially in patroniz<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing learning and godlinesse when they shall see that such a reward remaineth for them euen in this present world.</p>
   <p>But herein I must be very sparing, considering that the neerenesse of bloud betwixt your Ladiship and my selfe, will hardly suffer mee to say the one halfe of that which I might truely say, both of your Ladiships vertues in generall, and of your speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and manifold fauours to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me: for which I will rather praise GOD, and pray for the continuance and increase thereof in the secret closet of my heart then make any publike pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation
<pb facs="4"/> of the same in the eares of men.</p>
   <p>Thus praying your Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe to accept in part of paiment, for your many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours and kindnesses, this small mite, which I bring you in another mans coine, with my humble and hearty prayers. &amp;c.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Ladiships much bounden, and louing Nephew. <hi>E. C.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>