<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117654_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12592</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22909</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117654</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A godly treatise containing and deciding certaine questions, mooued of late in London and other places, touching the ministerie, sacraments, and Church : Whereunto one proposition more is added. After the ende of this booke you shall finde a defence of such points as M. Penry hath dealt against: and a confutation of many grosse errours broched in M. Penries last treatise. Written by Robert Some Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Some, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <publisher>Barker, Christopher, Deputy of (to).</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bishop, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 36, 12, 53-200 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="23"/>
   <pb facs="23"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Did publish a short Treatise in May last. It hath pleased one M. <hi>Penry</hi> to examine part of it, and (as an other <hi>Aristarchus</hi>) to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure it. His booke was sent me. I haue viewed it, and doe finde strange things in it. Aduise was giuen me, not to vouchsafe an answere, because M. <hi>Penry</hi> is very ignorant, and his Treatise very sillie and corrupt stuffe. I considered waightely of it, but resolued to take some paines. The reasons which induced me, are: First, S. <hi>Paul</hi> vouchsafed in Gods cause to deale with <hi>Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trius</hi> the siluer, and <hi>Alexander</hi> the copper smith. The Prophet <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechiel</hi> in the like cause, did set himselfe against certaine wicked women &amp;c. <hi>Ezech. 13.</hi> Secondly, many haue beene mislead by his absurd fancies. To cure these, if God will, and to stay other, my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is not amisse. Lastly, I am personally both charged and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged by him: therefore it became me to take pen in hand. M. <hi>Penries</hi> booke is a fardle of grosse errours. None accompt of it, but such as are of the fantasticall crewe: men extremely both proude and ignorant. He hath as many learned men of his side, as H. N. the prince of the familie of Loue had of his: that is, neuer a one: therefore a little Arithmetique will serue to number them. If it had pleased him to haue considered of, and rested in the iudgement and direction of very famous men and Churches, he had not swar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from Gods booke, he had sailed by a sure compasse, he had not broched such fancies, as Gods Church with one voyce condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. <hi>Nestorius</hi> was an absurd heretike: he had some sparkles of eloquence by nature: hee was in his owne opinion learned, but in deede very ignorant: his pride was such, that he vouchsafed not to reade any interpreters. <hi>Socrat. lib. 7. cap. 32.</hi> I assure my selfe, that M. <hi>Penry</hi> is very farre from <hi>Nestorius</hi> heresie: I would he were as cleare ofpride and contempt of writers. <hi>Caluine, Beza, &amp;c.</hi> men of excellent learning, are cast off by him, euē in those waighty cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, wherein they shake hands with all the Churches of God. I doe not belie him, I charge him iustly: it shall appeare so by Gods grace in this Treatise. The question betweene him and me, is not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ignorant men may either enter into, or continue in the holy ministerie: for, my resolution is negatiue, that is, that they ought
<pb facs="24"/>not: but the question is, whether such as were and are baptized by Popish priests and ignorant ministers, haue and doe receiue a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament: and whether the godly communicant is polluted by recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the Sacrament at the hands of vnpreaching ministers. The most famous men and Churches, are peremptorie for me, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him. Yea, M. <hi>Penry</hi> himselfe ioyneth with me in many partes of his Treatise: in some other partes, I confesse, he sings an other song, absurde for matter, and out of tune for manner. This inconstancie of his proceedes from a vaine humour, which as a whirle-winde, doeth strangely carrie and ouer-carrie him. It is not in my handes to heale him: if it were, I woulde with all my heart. I will pray vnto God to cure him. <hi>Cathedram in coelo habet, qui corda docet.</hi> All that I desire of the godly Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, is, that he wil reade my Treatise before he giue sentēce. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, I may iustly charge him, to bring not <hi>iudicium,</hi> but <hi>praejudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> that is, to be very partiall. Let him, in Gods Name, compare my arguments and answeres with my aduersaries, and weigh them in equall balance: if hee doeth not see clearely, and feele sensibly his grosse errors &amp; Anabaptisticall fancies, his eyes are dimme, his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers are benummed. That he may haue present and speedie viewe of the pearles in his booke, I haue set downe in a Table, diuers strange particulers. If they seeme harsh and rough-hewen, blame <hi>M. Penry:</hi> for they come out of his forge. Yea, I dare be bolde to say, that if the Spiders webbe bee good cloth, and the Cockatrice egges holsome meate, then such points as I refute in this Treatise, are very excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Diuinitie. I am not alone of this iudgement: the worthiest Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines in this land iumpe with me, and do mislike and condemne his absurdities. It pleased God to assist mee graciously in the paines I haue taken: I thanke his Maiestie very humbly for it: I doubt not, but that he will giue a blessing vnto it. The Lord giue vs grace to see and know our ignorance, to be truely humble, to grow in godly knowledge, and not in Anabapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stical and blasphemous fancies. London. Septemb. 19. 1588.</p>
   <q>Necessaria ignoramus, quia non necessaria discimus.</q>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>