<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONORA∣ble, my all-worthy, and no lesse deare friend, Sir IOHN WENTVVORTH Knight, Baronet.</title>
           <author>Stafford, Anthony</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117802_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12820</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23128</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117802</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONORA∣ble, my all-worthy, and no lesse deare friend, Sir IOHN WENTVVORTH Knight, Baronet.</title>
                 <author>Stafford, Anthony</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Staffords heauenly dogge: or The life, and death of that great cynicke Diogenes, whom Laertius stiles Canem Coelestem, the heauenly dogge, by reason of the heauenly precepts he gaue : Taken out of the best authors, and written to delight great hearts, and to raise as high a heauen the minds that now grouell on the earth, by teaching them how to ouercome all affections, and afflictions</title>
                 <author>Stafford, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Budge, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 112, 8 pages, illustrations (metal cut), 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="43"/>
   <pb facs="43"/>
   <head>TO THE HONORA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, my all-worthy, and no lesse deare friend, Sir IOHN WENTVVORTH Knight, Baronet.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Pplause atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded mine eie, noble Friend, when I first read in a plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sing writer, <hi>Amicos primū esse deligendos, deinde dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendos,
<pb facs="44"/>
that friends are first to bee chosen, then to bee loued.</hi> Notwithstanding my applause, with mee it fell out otherwise when I first saw you, who passed through mine eye into my heart, where you shall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer sit. Yet was not my affection so sottish, but that (disdaining to haue <hi>Foolish</hi> for an Epithete,) it went to my iudgement for approbation, which in a short space satisfied it to the full of your compleate Worth. And (as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member) the foundation on which my iudgement encouraged my affection
<pb facs="44"/>
to build, was, the loue I discerned in you to those better studies, &amp; to Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, the best of men. I saw that as GOD had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you an ability of minde; so you (not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefull) sought to pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish that excellent part. Neither did you thinke it inough to beautifie your Soule, but withall tooke a course to conforme it to Reason, and to fortifie it against the forces of false Fortune. To that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose you made choyse of <hi>Seneca,</hi> and other authors that might furnish you as well with the Helmet, as
<pb facs="45"/>
with the Feather. Of the same nature, and, I dare say, of the same height is this Booke, and therefore will deserue your reading. It treateth of a strange, inimitable man, who had nothing, yet neuer knew aduersity. His happines was euer the same, and he euer himselfe. The cruell effects of Fortunes malice could neuer make him change his minde, nor his countenance. And so he liued, as if shee had stood at his award, and not hee at hers. To you I dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate this deare Dogge, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with my hart.
<pb facs="45"/>
That, which made me set your Name before it, was my ambition, the mawe of which will be full, when I shall haue the honour to be reputed your friend, which (vpon ocasion) I will proue my selfe to bee, with the hazzard of my life. In death I will professe my loue to Sir IOHN WENTVVORTH, and till then rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>His fixed friend, and seruant</hi> Antony Stafford.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>