<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PREFACE OF PRAYER: TO MINE Honourable, Worshipfull, and Chri∣stian Auditors, at Saint Martins in the Fieldes; Grace and PEACE.</title>
           <author>Hill, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117083_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03356</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13474</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117083</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PREFACE OF PRAYER: TO MINE Honourable, Worshipfull, and Chri∣stian Auditors, at Saint Martins in the Fieldes; Grace and PEACE.</title>
                 <author>Hill, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pathvvay to prayer and pietie : Containing, 1 An exposition of the Lords Prayer, with an apologie for publicke, and priuate set prayer. 2 A preparation to the Lords Supper, with Ma. Zanchius confession, concerning that sacrament. 3 A direction to a Christian life, bot in our generall and particular callings. 4 An instruction to die well, and a consolation against all crosses. With diuers prayers, and thankesgiuings fit for this treatise. By Robert Hill, Doctor in Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Hill, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <distributor>Barrett, William</distributor>
                            <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40, 141, 17, 110, 8, 111-344 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>A PREFACE OF PRAYER: TO MINE Honourable, Worshipfull, and <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Auditors, at Saint</hi> Martins <hi>in</hi> the Fieldes; Grace and PEACE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Auditors: There are three things in regard of God which euery good person must bee acquainted withall; the first is how hee must talke with God; The second, how hee must liue before God; The third, how hee must come to God, when the seale of his sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation is offered in the Sacrament. Of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hese three I am bold at this time to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent vnto you this little Manuell.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> a Law-giuer amongst the <hi>Lacedaemonians,</hi> made this one Law of sacrificing to the gods, that they should not bee presented with many things, and those
<pb facs="9"/> of either small or no great value. If things are to bee esteemed rather by weight, then worth, I haue obserued this law in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent gift. I offer vnto you but three things; the first number of which, <hi>all</hi> can bee spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. And I present vnto you but small things; for what can be contained in so few sheetes of paper? yet if it please you to giue these few sheetes the reading, you shall know better how to pray, learn better how to liue, and vnderstand better how to come to Gods table, so long as you shall either pray, liue, or receiue. And because I haue concerning the first, Preached to you of late many Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,<note place="margin">The dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of Prayer.</note> I am willing at this time in way of Preface, to commend vnto you the dignitie of Prayer.</p>
   <p>By it wee conferre and talke with God and by it we procure much good vnto man: By it we doe pierce the very cloudes, and by it we haue whatsoeuer is meete. Doe wee want any thing that is good for vs or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? Prayer is the messenger whom wee must send towards God. Haue we receiued any speciall fauour from him? Prayer is our Ambassadour to giue him thankes.</p>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <p>Are wee in the morning to begin our worke? this is the Key to open the day.<note place="margin">Clauit diei.</note> Are we at euening to shut our selues in? this is the<note n="a" place="margin">Sera no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis.</note> locke to seale vp the night. If we would bind the Almightie<note n="b" place="margin">Vincu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincibilis: <hi>Bern.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>to do vs none hurt, heere is the band by which he is tied</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">Vis Deo grata. <hi>Chrysost.</hi>
      </note>. And if we would vntie him to do vs good, heere is the porter of the gates of heauen. It is our Oedypus to dissolue our doubts, it is our commentarie to vnderstand Gods word<note n="d" place="margin">Clauis Scriptura. <hi>Origen.</hi>
      </note> It is a<note n="e" place="margin">Deo sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficium, dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolo flagel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidium. <hi>August. The praise of praier.</hi>
      </note> sacrifice to God, a scourge to the diuell, and an helpe to our selues in all our troubles. Wherefore, as the Apostle by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, commended faith to the Hebrewes, so may I by examples commend prayer to you.</p>
   <p>By it <hi>Abrahams</hi> seruant obtained a wife for <hi>Isaac,</hi> and by it <hi>Moses</hi> obtained a pardon for Israel. By this, the same <hi>Moses</hi> ouercame the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> and by this <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> interceded for the Sodomites. By prayer <hi>Iacob</hi> was deliuered from <hi>Esau; Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suah</hi> from the men of <hi>Aie; Dauid</hi> from <hi>Goliah;</hi> The Prophet from <hi>Ieroboam; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizeus</hi> from the Samaritans; <hi>Hezechiah</hi> from death; <hi>Iehosophat from the Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites;
<pb facs="10"/> Manasses</hi> from captiuitie; <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> from his aduersaries, and <hi>Daniel</hi> from the Lions: the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>seased from his lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, the Apostles from prison, &amp; the Church from persecution. By prayer <hi>Hannah</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a sonne, <hi>Dauid</hi> deliuerance, <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> wisedome, <hi>Elias</hi> the restoring of a dead child, <hi>Elizeus</hi> the opening of his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants eyes, <hi>Nehemiah</hi> the kings fauour, the Centurion his seruants health, Christ comfort in his agonie, the Apostles a suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessor to <hi>Iudas, Stephen</hi> pardon for <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Monima</hi> the conuersion of her sonne S. <hi>Austin.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">In Psal. 63</note>Thus true it is which that <hi>Austin</hi> saith, <hi>Great is the profit of pure prayer, and as a faithfull messenger, deliuers her arrand, and pierceth thither, whither flesh cannot come.</hi> And this it was which made <hi>Bernard</hi> to say; <hi>Brethren let none of vs lightly esteeme his prayer: I tell you, that hee to whom wee pray doth not lightly esteeme it: after it is out of our mouth, he writes it in his Booke: and one of these two wee may doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse expect, either that hee will grant
<pb facs="10"/> our petition, or that which hee know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be better for vs.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Call vpon me, and I will heare,</hi> saith God: <hi>aske; and you shall haue,</hi> saith Christ. <hi>Before they crie I will heare them,</hi> saith <hi>Isaiah. The Lord is nigh to all that call vpon him,</hi> saith <hi>Dauid,</hi> but to such as call vpon him in truth. And if we may belieue the Apostle <hi>Iames,</hi> the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of a righteous man auaileth much.</p>
   <p>Pray therefore, and we had need to pray.<note place="margin">Why wee ought to Pray.</note>
      <hi>Satan</hi> will deuoure thee: pray for deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. The <hi>world</hi> will allure thee: pray for assistance. The <hi>flesh</hi> will betray thee: pray for defence. The <hi>wicked</hi> will seduce thee: pray for continuance. What, belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? If God had commaunded vs a great thing, ought wee not to doe it? how much more when he saith, pray and preuaile, aske and haue, seeke and finde, knock and it shall bee opened vnto you? aske <hi>Temporall</hi> things, and haue them, seeke for <hi>Spirituall</hi> things and find them, knocke for <hi>Eternall</hi> things, and the gates of heauen shall stand as open to you, as the gates of the prison did to the Apostle <hi>Peter.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <p>By this, with <hi>Eliah,</hi> you may open and shut the verie gates of heauen, and by this with the Apostle you may shake the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the earth. O pretious praier, what could not onely wee, but euen the whole world, doe without thee! Thou <hi>increasest</hi> the earth, <hi>calmest</hi> the sea, <hi>asswagest</hi> the fire, <hi>purgest</hi> the ayre, <hi>protectest</hi> our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours, <hi>confoundest</hi> our enemies, <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruest</hi> our health, <hi>instructest</hi> our mindes, <hi>blessest</hi> our actions, <hi>encreasest</hi> our wealth, <hi>exaltest</hi> our honour, <hi>speakest but the word,</hi> and we are preserued.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Prayer in all places.</note>Pray wee therefore in all <hi>places,</hi> at all <hi>times,</hi> for all <hi>persons,</hi> and for all <hi>things.</hi> Pray wee in all <hi>places,</hi> but in euery place lifting vp pure hands vnto God. Thus, <hi>Isaac</hi> prayed in the field, <hi>Iakob</hi> in his bed, <hi>Israel</hi> in Egypt, <hi>Moses</hi> on the Mount, <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suah</hi> at <hi>Iericho, Elias</hi> in the chamber, <hi>Hezekiah</hi> on his couch, <hi>Ieremie</hi> in the dungeon, <hi>Ionah</hi> in the Whales bellie, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> in the Lions den, <hi>Christ</hi> in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, the Disciples in a ship, <hi>Peter</hi> in a Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners house, <hi>Paul</hi> at the sea side: and the Iewes at Ierusalem. Call vpon him in thy
<pb facs="11"/> priuate chamber, and crie vnto him with thy familie in thy parlour. Thou needest not to fall downe at some piller with hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, but praise him especially in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of Saints: for there many voices are Gods best melodie.</p>
   <p>Pray also at all <hi>times:</hi> at euening,<note place="margin">Pray at all times.</note> and morning, and at noone day, will I pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, yea at midnight will I rise to call vpon thee, nay seuen times a day wil I praise thee, saith <hi>Dauid. Daniel</hi> did so three times a day, <hi>Paul</hi> did it day and night, <hi>Hannah</hi> did it all the daies of her life, and the Psalmographer vowes it, I will praise the Lord as long as I liue, as long as I haue any being, I will sing praises to my God. Pray continually, not as those Heretiques,<note place="margin">Euchitae.</note> who would euer do so, but as Christians who know when to do so.</p>
   <q>
      <l>With morning prayer, the day begin:</l>
      <l>With euening prayer the night shut in.</l>
      <l>Without this prayer sit not to eate:</l>
      <l>Without Gods praise rise not from meate.</l>
   </q>
   <p>And forget not to pray for all <hi>persons,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pray for ad persons.</note> for the <hi>King</hi> as the head, his <hi>Senatours</hi> as the eyes, his <hi>Clergie</hi> as the mouth, his
<pb facs="12"/>
      <hi>Souldiers</hi> as the hands, his <hi>Subiects,</hi> to all trades, as the feete vpon which the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth doth stand. Art thou a <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster?</hi> pray for thy flocke. An <hi>Auditor?</hi> for thy Preacher. A <hi>Father?</hi> for thy child: an <hi>Husband?</hi> for thy wife: a <hi>Master?</hi> for thy seruant: or a <hi>Gouernour?</hi> pray for thy family. Is any <hi>Sicke?</hi> pray for his health: <hi>Poore?</hi> for his wealth: <hi>Impriso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned?</hi> for his libertie: <hi>Seduced?</hi> for his recouerie: <hi>Confirmed?</hi> for his constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: or in any <hi>Distresse?</hi> for his deliuerie. Pray for all men, that their <hi>bodies</hi> may be preserued, <hi>soules</hi> saued, <hi>estates</hi> maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that thy, and their thoughts may bee sanctified, your words seasoned, and your actions ordered by the Spirit of God.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">To whom we must Pray.</note>Will you know now to whom wee must pray? not to a <hi>Calfe,</hi> as the Israelites did, nor to <hi>Baal,</hi> as his Priests did, nor to an <hi>Image,</hi> as Idolaters did, nor to any <hi>Saints,</hi> as our fathers did; but as we are bound to serue God alone, so are we bounden to pray to God alone; for hee alone <hi>knoweth</hi> our wants, <hi>heareth</hi> our petitions, hath <hi>promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed</hi> to helpe vs, is <hi>able</hi> to doe for vs, and is
<pb facs="12"/> the alone <hi>present helper</hi> in the needfull time of trouble.</p>
   <p>I will draw to an end. You haue seene be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, the necessitie of this seruice,<note place="margin">How wee must Pray.</note> let mee shew you a litle the qualities of this seruice. Pray we must in <hi>knowledge</hi> with vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, in <hi>faith</hi> by beleeuing, in <hi>remorse</hi> with feeling, in <hi>zeale</hi> without cooling, in <hi>intention</hi> without wandering, in <hi>reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> without contemning, in <hi>constancie</hi> without reuolting, and in <hi>loue</hi> without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenging. Let our <hi>eyes</hi> be fastned, <hi>hearts</hi> fixed, <hi>knees</hi> bowed, mouthes opened, &amp; our <hi>hands</hi> lifted vp as to the King of Kings. And as <hi>Iacob</hi> would not let the Angell goe till he were blessed, so let not vs let him go till we be heard. Let not the woman of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> bee more earnest with Christ mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, then we will be with the same Christ triumphāt. Let neuer the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> so willingly come to <hi>Salomon,</hi> as we must willingly come vnto Christ: hee loueth most, willing and importunate suters. Wherefore, as <hi>Dauid</hi> said to <hi>Abner,</hi> neuer see my face, vnlesse thou bring <hi>Michal</hi> with thee; so I say vnto you, neuer look God in
<pb facs="13"/> the face, vnlesse you bring Prayer with you.</p>
   <p>As I haue declared to you the dutie of prayer, so should I speake somewhat of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of thankes. Many can be content to pray in troubles: but few giue thankes for deliuerance out of trouble. <hi>Multi peten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, pauci promittentes, paucissimi red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes,</hi> saith an ancient Father: there are many <hi>Petitioners,</hi> few <hi>Promisers,</hi> most few <hi>thankesgiuers.</hi> Are there not ten cleansed? where are the nine? there is none returned to giue thankes but this one, and he is a Samaritan. If euer people vnder the cope of heauen had occasion to praise God, wee are they, especially for his Word and Gospell, and for many deliuerances shewed to our Princes and people.</p>
   <p>But because at the end of this Treatise, I haue set downe a forme both of prayer and thankesgiuing, I referre you to the perusing of those two platformes.</p>
   <p>I doubt not of your patience for the length of this Preface, because I desire to leaue it as an occular Sermon, instructing you continually how to call vpon God, and
<pb facs="13"/> preparing you to the expositiō of the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> which of many through ignorance is as much prophaned, as euer God was by saying the <hi>Pater-noster</hi> in Latine, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating other <hi>Rosaries</hi> in an vnknowne language.</p>
   <p>Now hauing ended, as you see, these questions and answeres, I make question with my selfe, to whom I may commend them; and because for these ten yeares im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately past, I haue liued and preached amongst you, and that by the assignement of your Reuerend Pastor,<note place="margin">M. Doctor <hi>Montfort.</hi>
      </note> I am bold in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall to present them to you all. You haue, I confesse, known my conuersation, been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with my ministrie, countenanced me in my calling, maintained me in health, comforted me in sicknesse, and afforded vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me much more kindnesse, than can be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quited by this paper present. And since it pleaseth God to dispose of mee still in such vncertaine places, as that I could neuer yet say, heere must I rest: I blesse God that euer I came vnto you, whose loue and larges hath bin, &amp; is amongst many of you (for what le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturer for ten yeares together can please al)
<pb facs="14"/> such vnto mee, as makes mee to say of my late exile, <hi>Perijssem nisi perijssem,</hi> I had beene vndone, if others had not sought to vndoe me.</p>
   <p>Since I came vnto you, I haue <hi>preached</hi> painfully, <hi>liued</hi> honestly, and <hi>studied</hi> care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to do you seruice: with what <hi>consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> I know, with what <hi>danger</hi> you know, and with what <hi>profit</hi> God knowes. Surely this good I see done amongst you; you haue <hi>beautified</hi> the house of the <hi>liuing</hi> God; praise that worthy Knight, whose loue and labour was first in that worke; you haue <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged</hi> that house which is for the <hi>dying</hi> Saints; pray for that good King who gaue you <hi>that piece of ground;</hi> and your <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation</hi> is as the <hi>thousands</hi> of Israel. Blesse God for those trumpets of yours, who haue euer called you to such holy assemblies. Blessed be that <hi>God,</hi> who thus blesseth you: blessed be <hi>you,</hi> who thus blesse God: and blessed and <hi>billeted</hi> vp be they in heauen, who thus prouide for the liuing and the dead, and withall remember their painfull Teachers.</p>
   <p>Now though I cannot say to you, as <hi>Paul</hi>
      <pb facs="14"/> did to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> I <hi>am yours to liue and die with you:</hi> (for no Minister can say it, who dependeth vpon voluntarie contribution) yet this I will say, and say for euer, I am yours to <hi>liue,</hi> and <hi>pray</hi> for you, that you may so <hi>know</hi> God, as you may pray to him, so <hi>pray</hi> to God that you may liue before him, so <hi>liue,</hi> that you may euer be fit to receiue his Sacrament, and so both fit to know, pray, liue, and receiue, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you haue <hi>knowen</hi> him by Christ, <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> to him through Christ, <hi>liued</hi> before him in Christ, and <hi>receiued</hi> his fauour in the seales of Christ, you may in the end die in his faith, as you haue liued in his feare, and at the last day in bodies and soules, be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of eternall glorie. To the grace of this God I commend you, to your grace I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend these Treatises, doubting not but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you will be as readie to reade them, as you haue beene willing to heare them. From your Parish of Saint <hi>Martin,</hi> in the fields.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>
            <hi>Iune 10. 1613.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your seruant in the Lord, so long as it shall please God and you, ROBERT HILL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>