<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>OF THE LIFE AND HISTORY OF THVCYDIDES.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117705_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13759</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24058</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117705</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>OF THE LIFE AND HISTORY OF THVCYDIDES.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Eight bookes of the Peloponnesian Warre written by Thucydides the sonne of Olorus. Interpreted with faith and diligence immediately out of the Greeke by Thomas Hobbes secretary to ye late Earle of Deuonshire</title>
                 <author>Thucydides</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <distributor>Seile (Seale, Seely, Seyle), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 536, that is 535, 13 pages, 5 plates (3 folded), maps, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="life">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>OF THE LIFE AND HISTORY OF THVCYDIDES.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee reade of diuers men that beare the name of <hi>Thucydides.</hi> There is <hi>Thucydides</hi> a <hi>Pharsalian,</hi> mentioned in the eighth Booke of this History; who was publike Hoste of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians,</hi> in <hi>Pharsalus,</hi> and chancing to be at <hi>Athens,</hi> at the time that the gouernment of the 400 began to goe downe, by his interposition, and perswasion, kept asunder the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> then arming themselues, that they fought not in the City to the ruine of the Common-wealth. There is <hi>Thucy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dides</hi> the son of <hi>Milesias,</hi> an <hi>Athenian,</hi> of the towne of <hi>Alope,</hi> of whom <hi>Plutarch</hi> speaketh in the Life of <hi>Pericles</hi>; and the same in all probabilitie, that in the first Book of this History, is said to haue had the charge of 40 Gallies, sent against <hi>Samos,</hi> about 24 yeeres before the beginning of this Warre. Another <hi>Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cydides</hi> the sonne of <hi>Ariston,</hi> an <hi>Athenian</hi> also, of the Towne of <hi>Acherdus,</hi> was a Poet, though of his verses there be nothing extant. But <hi>Thucydides</hi> the writer of this History, an <hi>Athenian,</hi> of the Towne of <hi>Halimus,</hi> was the sonne of <hi>Olorus,</hi> (or <hi>Orolus</hi>) and <hi>Hegesipyle.</hi> His Fathers name is commonly written <hi>Olorus</hi> though in the Inscription on his Tombe, it was <hi>Orolus.</hi> Howsoeuer it be written, it is the same that was borne by diuers of the Kings of <hi>Thrace,</hi> and imposed on him, with respect vnto his descent from them. So that though our Author (as <hi>Cicero</hi> saith of him <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>De Oratore</hi>) had neuer written an History, yet had not his name not bin extant, in regard of his Honour and Nobility. And not onely <hi>Plutarch,</hi> in the Life of <hi>Cimon,</hi> but also almost all others that haue touched this point, affirme directly that he was descended from the <hi>Thracian</hi> Kings. Adducing this for proofe, that he was of the house of <hi>Miltiades,</hi> that famous Generall of the <hi>Athenians,</hi> against the <hi>Persians</hi> at <hi>Marathon</hi>; which they also proue by this, that his Tombe was a long time extant amongst the Monuments of that Family. For neere vnto the Gates of <hi>Athens,</hi> called <hi>Melirides,</hi> there was a place named <hi>Coela,</hi> and in it the Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments called <hi>Cintoniana,</hi> belonging to the Family of <hi>Miltiades,</hi> in which, none but such as were of that Family, might be buried. And amongst those was the Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Thucydides,</hi> with this inscription, <hi>Thucydides Oroli Halimusius.</hi> Now <hi>Miltiades</hi> is confessed by all, to haue descended from <hi>Olorus,</hi> King of <hi>Thrace,</hi> whose daughter another <hi>Miltiades,</hi> Grandfather to this, married, and had children by. And <hi>Miltiades,</hi> that wonne the memorable victory at <hi>Marathon,</hi> was heire to goodly possessions, and Cities in the <hi>Chersonnesus</hi> of <hi>Thrace,</hi> ouer which also hee raigne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. In <hi>Thrace</hi> lay also the possessions of <hi>Thucydides</hi> and his wealthy Mines of Gold, as he himselfe professeth in his fourth Booke. And although those riches might come to him by a Wife (as is also by some affirmed) which he married in <hi>Scapte-Hyle,</hi> a City of <hi>Thrace,</hi> yet euen by that marriage, it appeareth, that his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires had a relation to that Countrey, and that his Nobility was not there vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne. But in what degree of kindred <hi>Miltiades,</hi> and he, approached each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is not any where made manifest. Some also haue coniectured that hee was of the house of the <hi>Pisistratides</hi>; the ground of whose coniecture hath beene onely this, that he maketh honourable mention of the gouernment of <hi>Pisistratus,</hi> and his sonnes, and extenuateth the glory of <hi>Harmodius</hi> and <hi>Aristogiton</hi>; prouing that the free<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ng of the State of <hi>Athens</hi> from the tyranny of the <hi>Pisistratides,</hi> was falsly ascribed to their fact (which proceeded from priuate reuenge, in a quarrel of Loue) by which the tyranny ceased not, but grew heauier to the State, till it was at last put
<pb facs="7"/>
downe by the <hi>Lacedaemoniaus.</hi> But this opinion, as it is not so well grounded, so neither is it so well receiued as the former.</p>
   <p>Agreeable to his Nobility, was his institution in the study of <hi>Eloquence,</hi> and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophy</hi>· For in <hi>Philosophy,</hi> he was the Scholler (as also was <hi>Pericles</hi> and <hi>Socrates)</hi> of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>goras,</hi> whose opinions, being of a straine aboue the apprehension of the vulgar procured him the estimation of an <hi>Atheist,</hi> which name they bestowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all men that thought not as they did, of their ridiculous Religion, and in the end, cost him his life. And <hi>Socrates</hi> after him for the like causes, vnder▪ went the like fortune. It is not therefore much to be regarded, if this other disciple of his, were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> some reputed an <hi>Athiest</hi> to. For though he were none, yet it is not improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but by the light of naturall reason, he might see enough in the Religion of these <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, to make him thinke it vaine, and superstitious; which was enough to make him an <hi>Atheist,</hi> in the opinion of the People. In some places of his History, hee noteth the aequiuocation of the Oracles; and yet hee confirmeth an asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his owne▪ touching the time this Warre lasted, by the Oracles predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. He tax<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th <hi>Nicias</hi> for being to punctuall in the obseruation of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of their Religion▪ when he ouerthrew himselfe and his Army, and indeed the whole Dominion and liberty of his Countrey by it. Yet he commendeth him in another place for his worshipping of the <hi>Gods,</hi> and saith in that respect, hee least of all men deserued to come to so great a degree of Calamity as he did. So that in his writings our Authour appeareth to be, on the one side not superstitious, on the other side not an <hi>Ath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In <hi>Rhetorique,</hi> he was the Disciple of <hi>Antiphon</hi>▪ one (by his discription in the eighth Booke of this History) for power of speech almost a miracle, and feared by the <hi>People,</hi> for his eloquence. Insomuch as in his latter dayes he liued retyred, but so as he gaue counsell to, and writ Orations for other men that resorted vnto him, to that purpose. It was he that contriued the deposing of the <hi>People,</hi> and the set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp of the gouernment of the 400. For which also he was put to death, when the <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> againe recouered their authority; notwithstanding that he pleaded his owne cause, the best of any man to that day.</p>
   <p>It need not be doubted, but from such a Master, <hi>Thucydides</hi> was sufficiently <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, to haue become a great Demagogue, and of great authority with the <hi>People.</hi> But it seemeth he had no desire at all to meddle in the gouernment, because in those ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>s it was impossible for any man to giue good and profitable counsell for the Common-wealth and not incurre the displeasure of the <hi>People</hi> For their opinion was such of their owne power, and of the facility of atchieuing whatsoeuer acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they vndertooke, that such men onely swayed the Assemblies, and were estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se and good Common-wealths men, as did put them vpon the most dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and desperate enterprizes. Whereas he that gaue them temperate, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet aduice, was thought a Coward, or not to vnderstand, or else to maligne their power. And no maruell; for much prosperity (to which they had now for many yeeres been accustomed) maketh men in loue with themselues; and it is hard for any man to loue that counsell which maketh him loue himselfe the lesse. And it holdeth much more in a Multitude, then in one Man; For a man that reasoneth with himselfe, will not be ashamed to admit of timerous suggestions in his busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, that he may the stronglyer prouide; but in publique deliberations before a Multitude, Feare, (which for the most part aduiseth well, though it execute not so) seldome or neuer sheweth it selfe, or is admitted. By this meanes it came to passe amongst the <hi>Athenians,</hi> who thought they were able to doe any thing, that wicked men and flatterers draue them headlong into those actions that were to ruine them; and the good men either durst not oppose, or if they did, vndid them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues. <hi>Thucydides</hi> therefore, that he might not be either of them that commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or of them that suffered euill, forbore to come into the Assemblies, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to himselfe, a priuate life as farre as the eminency of so wealthy a person, and the writing of the History he had vndertaken, would permit.</p>
   <p>For his opinion touching the gouernment of the State, it is manifest that he least of all liked the <hi>Democracy.</hi> And vpon diuers occasions, hee noteth the emulation and contention of the Demagogues, for reputation, and glory of wit; with their crossing of each others counsels to the dammage of the Publique; the inconstancy
<pb facs="7"/>
of Resolutions, caused by the diuersity of ends, and power of Rhetorique in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators; and the desperate actions vndertaken vpon the flattering aduice of such as desired to attaine, or to hold what they had attained of authority and sway a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the common people. Nor doth it appeare, that he magnifieth any where the authority of the <hi>Few</hi>▪ amongst whom he saith euery one desireth to be chiefe, and they that are vnderualued, beare it with lesse patience then in a <hi>Democracy</hi>; whereupon sedition followeth, and dissolution of the gouernment. Hee prayseth the gouernment of <hi>Athens,</hi> when it was mixt of the <hi>Few</hi> and the <hi>Many</hi>; but more he commendeth it, both when <hi>Pisistratus</hi> raigned (sauing that it was an vsur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped power) and when in the beginning of this Warre, it was <hi>Democraticall</hi> in name, but in effect <hi>Monarchicall</hi> vnder <hi>Pericles.</hi> So that it seemeth that as he was of Regall descent, so he best approued of the <hi>Regall Gouernment.</hi> It is therefore no maruell, if he meddled as little as he could in the businesse of the Common-wealth, but gaue himselfe rather to the obseruation and recording of what was done by those that had the mannaging thereof. Which also he was no lesse prompt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and faithfull by the disposition of his mind, then by his fortune, dignity, and wisedome, able to accomplish. How he was disposed to a worke of this nature, may be vnderstood by this, that when being a young man he heard <hi>Herodotus</hi> the Historiographer reciting his History in Publique, (for such was the fashion both of that, and many Ages after) he felt so great a sting of aemulation, that it drew teares from him, insomuch as <hi>Herodotus</hi> himselfe tooke notice how violently his mind was set on letters, and told his Father <hi>Olorus.</hi> When the <hi>Peloponnesian</hi> Warre began to breake out, he coniectured truely, that it would prooue an Argument worthy his labour; and no sooner it began, then he began his History; pursu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the same, not in that perfect manner, in which we see it now, but by way of Commentary, or plaine Register of the Actions and passages thereof, as from time to time they fell out, and came to his knowledge. But such a Commentary it was, as might perhaps deserue to be preferr'd before a History written by another. For it is very probable that the eighth Booke is left the same it was when he first writ it, neither beautified with <hi>Orations,</hi> nor so well Cemented at the <hi>Transitions,</hi> as the former seuen Bookes are. And though he began to write as soone as euer the Warre was on foot, yet began he not to perfect and polish his History, till after he was banished.</p>
   <p>For notwithstanding his retyred life vpon the Coast of <hi>Thrace,</hi> where his owne possessions lay, he could not auoyd a seruice of the State, which proued to him af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards very vnfortunate. For whilest he resided in the Ile <hi>Thasus,</hi> it fell out that <hi>Brasidas</hi> the <hi>Lacedaemonian,</hi> besieged <hi>Amphipolis,</hi> a Citie belonging to the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians,</hi> on the Confines of <hi>Thrace,</hi> and <hi>Macedony,</hi> distant from <hi>Thasus,</hi> about halfe a dayes sayle. To relieue which, the Captaine thereof for the <hi>Athenians,</hi> sent to <hi>Tbucydides,</hi> to leuy a power and make haste vnto him, (for <hi>Thucydides</hi> was one of the <hi>Strategi,</hi> that is, had authority to raise forces in those parts, for the seruice of the Common-wealth.) And he did accordingly. But he came thither one night too late, and found the City already yeelded vp. And for this he was afterwards banished, as if he had let slip his time through negligence, or purposely put it off, vpon feare of the Enemy. Neuerthelesse he put himselfe into the Citie of <hi>Eion,</hi> and preserued it to the <hi>Athenians,</hi> with the repulse of <hi>Brasidas,</hi> which came downe from <hi>Amphipolis,</hi> the next morning, and assaulted it. The author of his banishment is supposed to haue been <hi>Gleon,</hi> a most violent Sycophant in those times, and thereby also a most acceptable Speaker amongst the people. For where affaires succeed amisse, though there want neither prouidence, nor cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in the Conduction, yet with those that iudge onely vpon euents, the way to calumny is alwayes open, and <hi>Enuy,</hi> in the likenesse of <hi>Zeale</hi> to the Publique good, easily findeth credit for an accusation.</p>
   <p>After his Banishment he liued in <hi>Scapt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>-Hyle,</hi> a Citie of <hi>Thrace,</hi> before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> writeth; but yet so as he went abroad; and was present at the Actions of the rest of the Warre as appeareth by his owne words in his fift Booke. Where he saith, that he was present at the Actions of both parts, and no lesse at those of the <hi>Peloponnesians,</hi> by reason of his exile, then those of the <hi>Athenians.</hi> During this time also, he perfected his History, so far as is now to be seene; nor doth
<pb facs="8"/>
it appeare that after his exile, he euer againe enioyed his Countrey. It is not cleere in any Author, where, or when, or in what yeere of his owne Age, he dyed. Most agree that he dyed in Banishment; yet there be that haue written, that after the defeat in <hi>Sicily,</hi> the <hi>Athenians</hi> decreed a generall reuocation of all banished persons, except those of the Family of <hi>Pisistratus</hi>; and that he then returned, and was afterwards put to death at <hi>Athens.</hi> But this is very vnlikely to be true, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse by <hi>after</hi> the defeat in <hi>Sicily,</hi> he meant <hi>so long after,</hi> that it was also after the end of the <hi>Peloponnesian</hi> Warre, because <hi>Thucydides</hi> himselfe maketh no mention of such returne, though he out-liued the whole War, as is manifest by his words in the fift Booke. For he saith he liued in banishment twenty yeeres after his charge at <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phipolis</hi>; which happened in the eighth yeere of this Warre, which in the whole, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted but 27 yeeres compleat. And in another place he maketh mention of the razing of the <hi>Long-walles</hi> betweene <hi>Peiraeus,</hi> and the Citie; which was the last stroke of this Warre. They that say he dyed at <hi>Athens,</hi> take their coniecture from his Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which was there. But this is not a sufficient Argument; for he might bee buried there secretly, (as some haue written he was) though he dyed abroad; or his Monument might be there, and (as others haue affirmed) he not buried in it. In this variety of coniecture there is nothing more probable then that which is written by <hi>Pausanias,</hi> where he describeth the Monuments of the <hi>Athenian</hi> Citie, and saith thus. <hi>The worthy Act of</hi> Oenobius, <hi>in the behalfe of</hi> Thucydides, <hi>is not without honour</hi> (meaning that he had a Statue.) <hi>For</hi> Oenobius <hi>obtained to haue a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree passed for his returne; who returning was slaine by treachery, and his Sepulchre is neere the Gates called</hi> Melirides. He dyed, as saith <hi>Marcellinus,</hi> after the seuen and fiftieth yeere of his Age. And if it be true that is written by <hi>A. Gellius,</hi> of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of <hi>Hellanicus, Herodotus,</hi> and <hi>Thucydides,</hi> then died he not before the sixty eighth yeere. For if he were forty when the Warre began, and liued (as he did, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) to see it ended he might be more when he dyed, but not lesse then sixty eight yeeres of Age. What children be left, is not manifest. <hi>Plato in Menone,</hi> maketh mention of <hi>Milesias</hi> and <hi>Stephanus,</hi> sonnes of a <hi>Thucydides,</hi> of a very Noble Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but it is cleere that they were of <hi>Thucydides,</hi> the Riuall of <hi>Pericles,</hi> both by the name <hi>Milesias,</hi> and because this <hi>Thucydides</hi> also, was of the Family of <hi>Milti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ades,</hi> as <hi>Plutarch</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>fieth in the Life of <hi>Cimon.</hi> That he had a sonne, is affirmed by <hi>Marcellinus,</hi> out of the authority of <hi>Polemon,</hi> but of his name there is no mention, saue that a learned man readeth there, in the place of <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>... (which is in the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Copie) <hi>Timotheus.</hi> Thus much of the person of <hi>Thucydides.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now for his writings, two things are to bee considered in them, <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>Eloquution.</hi> For in <hi>Truth</hi> consisteth the <hi>Soule,</hi> and in <hi>Eloquution</hi> the <hi>Body</hi> of Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story. The latter without the former, is but a picture of History; and the former without the latter, vnapt to instruct. But let vs see how our Author hath acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himselfe in both. For the Faith of this History, I shall haue the lesse to say, in respect that no man hath euer yet called it into question. Nor indeed could any man iustly doubt of the truth of that Writer, in whom they had nothing at all to suspect of those things that could haue caused him either voluntarily to lie, or ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly to deliuer an vntruth. He ouertasked not himselfe by vndertaking an Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story of things done long before his time, and of which he was not able to informe himselfe. He was a man that had as much meanes, in regard both of his dignity and wealth, to find the truth of what he relateth, as was needfull for a man to haue. He vsed as much diligence in search of the truth, (noting euery thing whilest it was fresh in memory, and laying out his wealth vpon intelligence,) as was possible for a man to vse. He affected least of any man the acclamations of Popular Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, and wrote not his History to win present applause, as was the vse of that Age, but for a Monument to instruct the Ages to come. Which he professeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, and Entitleth his Booke <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>A Posses<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ion for euerlasting.</hi> He was farre from the necessity of seruile Writers, either to feare or flatter. And whereas he may peraduenture be thought to haue beene maleuolent towards his Countrey, because they deserued to haue him so, yet hath he not written any thing that discouereth any such passion. Nor is there any thing written of them that tendeth to their dishonour, as <hi>Athenians,</hi> but onely as <hi>People</hi>; and that by the necessity of the narration, not by any sought digression. So that no word of his,
<pb facs="8"/>
but their own actions do sometimes reproach them. In summe, if the truth of a Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story did euer appeare by the manner of relating, it doth so in this History; So co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haerent, perspicuous and perswasiue is the whole Narration, and euery part therof.</p>
   <p>In the <hi>Eloquution</hi> also; Two things are considerable, <hi>Disposition</hi> or <hi>Method,</hi> and <hi>Stile.</hi> Of the <hi>Disposition</hi> here vsed by <hi>Thucydides,</hi> it will be sufficient in this place, briefly to obserue onely this. That in his first Booke, first he hath by way of <hi>Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium,</hi> deriued the State of <hi>Greece</hi> from the Cradle, to the vigorous stature it then was at, when he began to write; and next, declared the causes, both <hi>reall</hi> and <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended</hi> of the Warre hee was to write of, In the rest, in which hee handleth the Warre it selfe, he followeth distinctly and purely the order of time throughout; relating what came to passe from yeere to yeere, and subdiuiding each yeere into a Summer and Winter. The grounds and motiues of euery action, he setteth down before the action it selfe, either Narratiuely, or else contriueth them into the forme of <hi>Deliberatiue Orations,</hi> in the persons of such as from time to time bare sway in the Common-wealth. After the actions, when there is iust occasion, he giueth his iudgement of them, shewing by what meanes the successe came either to be furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or hindered. Digressions for instructions cause, and other such open conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of Precepts (which is the Philosophers part) he neuer vseth, as hauing so cleerely set before mens eyes, the wayes and euents, of good and euill counsels, that the Narration it selfe doth secretly instruct the Reader, and more effectually then possibly can be done by Precept.</p>
   <p>For his <hi>Stile,</hi> I referre it to the iudgement of diuers antient and competent Iudges. <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his Booke▪ <hi>De gloria Atheniensium,</hi> saith of him thus. Thucy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dides <hi>aymeth alwayes at this, to make his Auditor a Spectator, and to cast his Reader into the same passions that they were in, that were beholders. The manner how</hi> Demost<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henes <hi>aranged the</hi> Athenians <hi>on the rugged shore before</hi> Pylus. <hi>How</hi> Brasidas <hi>vrged the Steeresman to runne his Gally a ground; how he went to the Ladder, or place in the Gally for descent, how he was hurt, and swowned, and fell downe on the ledges of the Gally; how the</hi> Spartans <hi>fought after the manner of a Land-fight vpon the Sea, and the</hi> Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <hi>of a Sea-fight vpon Land. Againe, in the</hi> Sicilian <hi>Warre, how a battell was fought by Sea and Land, with equall fortune. These things, I say, are so described, and so euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly set before our eyes, that the mind of the Reader is no lesse affected therewith, then if hee had beene present in the Actions.</hi> There is for his perspecuity. <hi>Cicero</hi> in his Booke entituled <hi>Orator,</hi> speaking of the affection of diuers <hi>Greeke</hi> Rhetoricians, saith thus. <hi>And therefore</hi> Herodotus <hi>and</hi> Thucydides <hi>are the more admirable. For though they liued in the same Age with those J haue before named, (meaning</hi> Thrasymachus, Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius, <hi>and</hi> Theodorus) <hi>yet were they farre from this kind of delicacy, or rather indeed f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>olery. For the one without rubbe, gently glideth like a still River, and the other (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> Thucydides) <hi>runnes stronglier, and in matter of Warre, as it were, bloweth a trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet of Warre. And in these two (as saith</hi> Theophrastus) <hi>History hath rowsed her selfe, and aduentured to speake, both more copiously, and with more ornament then in those that were before them.</hi> This commends the grauity, and the dignity of his language. Againe in his second Booke, <hi>De Oratore,</hi> thus. Thucydides <hi>in the Art of speaking, hath in my opinion far exceeded them all. For he is so full of matter, that the number of his sentences, doth almost reach to the number of his words; and in his words he is so apt, and so close, that it is hard to say, whether his words do more illustrate his sentences, or his sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences his words.</hi> There is for the pithinesse and strength of his Stile. Lastly, for the purity, and propriety, I cite, <hi>Dionysius Halicarnassius,</hi> whose testimony is the stronger in this point, because he was a <hi>Greeke</hi> Rhetorician for his faculty, and for his affection, one that would no further commend him, then of necessity he must. His words are these. <hi>There is one vertue in Eloquence, the chiefest of all the rest, and without which there is no other goodnesse in speech. What is that? That the language be pure and retaine the propriety of the</hi> Greeke <hi>tongue. This they both obserue diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For</hi> Herodotus <hi>is the best rule of the</hi> Ionique, <hi>and</hi> Thucydides <hi>of the</hi> Attique <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alect.</hi> These testimonies are not needfull to him that hath read the History it selfe, nor at all, but that this same <hi>Dionysius</hi> hath taken so much paines, and applyed so much of his faculty in Rhetorique to the extenuating of the worth thereof; More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, I haue thought it necessary to take out the principall obiections he maketh against him, and without many words of mine owne, to leaue them to the consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration
<pb facs="9"/>
of the Reader. And first <hi>Dionysius</hi> saith thus. <hi>The principall, and most ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary office of any man that intendeth to write a History, is to chuse a Noble Argument, and gratefull to such as shall reade it. And this,</hi> Herodotus, <hi>in my opinion, hath done bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then</hi> Thucydides. <hi>For</hi> Herodotus <hi>hath written the ioynt History, both of the</hi> Greekes <hi>and</hi> Barbarians, <hi>to saue from obliuion, &amp;c. But</hi> Thucydides <hi>writeth one onely Warre, and that neither honourable, nor fortunate; which principally were to bee wished neuer to haue beene; and next, neuer to haue been remembred, nor knowne to posterity. And that he tooke an euill Argument in hand, he maketh it manifest in his proeme, saying,</hi> That many Cities were in that Warre made desolate, and vtterly destroyed, partly by <hi>Barbarians,</hi> partly by the <hi>Greekes</hi> themselues: so many banishments, and so much slaughter of men as neuer was the like before, &amp;c. <hi>So that the hearers will abhorre it, at the first propounding. Now by how much it is better to write of the wonderfull acts both of the</hi> Barbarians, <hi>and</hi> Grecians, <hi>then of the pittifull and horrible calamities of the</hi> Grecians, <hi>so much wiser is</hi> Herodotus <hi>in the choyce of his Argument, then</hi> Thucy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dides.</p>
   <p>Now let any man consider whether it be not more reasonable to say. <hi>That the principall, &amp; most necessary office of him that will write a History, is to take such an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, as is both within his power well to handle, and profitable to posterity that shall reade it. Which</hi> Thucydides, <hi>in the opinion of all men▪ hath done better then</hi> Herodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus. <hi>For</hi> Herodotus <hi>vndertooke to write of those things, of which it was impossible for him to know the truth; and which delight more the eare with fabulous Narrations, then satisfie the mind with truth. But</hi> Thucydides <hi>writeth one Warre, which, how it was carried from the beginning to the end, he was able certainely to informe himselfe. And by propounding in his Proeme, the miseries that happened in the same, he sheweth that it was a great Warre, and worthy to be knowne, and not to be concealed from posterity, for the calamities that then fell vpon the</hi> Grecians; <hi>but the rather to be truely deliuered vnto them for that men profit more by looking on aduerse euents, then on prosperity. Therefore by how much mens miseries doe better instruct, then their good successe, by so much was</hi> Thucydides <hi>more happy in taking his Argument, then</hi> Herodotus <hi>was wise in chusing his.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Dionysius</hi> againe, saith thus. <hi>The next office of him that will write a History, is to know where to begin, and where to end. And in this point</hi> Herodotus <hi>seemeth to be farre more discrect then</hi> Thucydides. <hi>For in the first place he layeth downe the cause, for which the</hi> Barbarians <hi>began to iniure the</hi> Grecians; <hi>and going on, maketh an end at the punishment, and the reuenge taken on the</hi> Barbarians. <hi>But</hi> Thucydides <hi>begins at the good estate of the</hi> Grecians, <hi>which being a</hi> Grecian, <hi>and an</hi> Athenian, <hi>he ought not to haue done; nor ought he, being of that dignity amongst the</hi> Athenians, <hi>so euidently to haue laid the fault of the Warre vpon his owne City, when there were other occasions enough to which he might haue imputed it. Nor ought he to haue begun with the businesse of the</hi> Corcyraeans, <hi>but at the more Noble Acts of his Countrey, which they did immediately af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the</hi> Persian <hi>Warre, (which afterward in conuenient place he mentioneth, but it is but cursorily, and not as he ought.) And when he had declared those, with much affection, as a louer of his Countrey, then he should haue brought in, how that the</hi> Lacedaemonians, <hi>through enuy and feare, but pretending other causes, began the Warre, and so haue descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the</hi> Corcyraean <hi>businesse, and the Decree against the</hi> Megareans, <hi>or whatsoeuer else he had to put in. Then in the ending of his History, there be many errours committed. For though he professe he was present in the whole warre, and that he would write it all, yet he ends with the Nauall battell at</hi> Cynossema, <hi>which was fought in the</hi> 21 <hi>yeere of the warre; whereas it had beene better to haue gone through with it, and ended his Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with that admirable, and gratefull returne of the banished</hi> Athenians <hi>from</hi> Phile, <hi>at which time the City recouered her liberty.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>To this I say. <hi>That it was the duty of him that had vndertaken to write the History of the</hi> Peloponnesian <hi>VVarre, to begin his Narration no further of, then at the causes of the same, whether the</hi> Grecians <hi>were then in good, or in euill estate. And if the iniury, vpon which the warre arose, proceeded from the</hi> Athenians, <hi>then the writer, though an</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenian, <hi>and honoured in his Countrey, ought to declare the same, and not to seeke, nor take, though at hand, any other occasion to transferre the fault. And that the Acts done before the time comprehended in the warre he writ of, ought to haue been touched but cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorily, and no more then may serue for the enlightning of the History to follow, how Noble
<pb facs="9"/>
soeuer those Acts haue beene. Which when he had thus touched, without affection to ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther side, and not as a louer of his Countrey, but of truth, then to haue proceeded to the rest, with the like indifferency, And to haue made an end of writing, where the Warre ended, which he vndertooke to write; not producing his History beyond that period, though that which followed were neuer so admirable and acceptable.</hi> All this <hi>Thucydides</hi> hath obserued.</p>
   <p>These two criminations, I haue therefore set downe at large, translated almost <hi>verbatim</hi>▪ that the iudgement of <hi>Dionysius Halicarnassius,</hi> may the better appeare, concerning the mayne and principall vertues of a History. I thinke there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer written so much absurdity in so few lines. He is contrary to the opinion of all men that euer spake of this subiect besides himselfe, and to common sense. For he makes the scope of History not profit by writing truth, but delight of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer▪ as if it were a Song. And the Argument of History, he would not by any meanes haue to containe the calamities and misery of his Countrey, (these he would haue buried in silence) but onely their glorious and splendid actions. Amongst the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of an Historiographer, hee reckons affection to his Countrey; study to please the hearer; to write of more then his Argument leades him to; and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale all actions that were not to the honour of his Countrey. Most manifest vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. He was a Rhetorician, and it seemeth he would haue nothing written, but that which was most capable of Rhetoricall ornament. Yet <hi>Lucian</hi>▪ a Rhetorician also, in a Treatise, entituled, <hi>How a History ought to be written,</hi> saith thus, <hi>That a writer of History, ought in his writings, to be a forraigner, without Countrey, liuing vnder his owne Law onely, subiect to no King, nor caring what any man will like, or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, but laying out the matter as it is.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The third fault he finds, is this That the method of his History is gouerned by the time rather then the periods of seuerall actions. For he declares in order what came to passe each Summer, and Winter, and is thereby forced sometimes, to leaue the Narration of a siege, or sedition, or a Warre, or other action, in the middest, and enter into a Relation of somewhat else▪ done at the same time, in another place, and to come to the former againe when the time requires it. This saith hee, causeth confusion in the mind of his hearer, so that he cannot comprehend distinctly the seuerall parts of the History.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Dionysius</hi> aymeth still at the delight of the <hi>present</hi> hearer; though <hi>Thucydides</hi> himselfe professe that his scope is not that, but to leaue his worke for a <hi>perpetuall possession</hi> to posterity. And then haue men leasure enough to comprehend him throughly. But indeed, whosoeuer shall reade him once attentiuely, shall more distinctly conceiue of euery action this way, then the other; and the method is more naturall; for as much as his purpose being to write of one <hi>Peloponnesian</hi> Warre, this way he hath incorporated all the parts thereof into one body, so that there is vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the whole, and the seuerall Narrations are conceiued onely as parts of that; Whereas the other way, he had but sowed together many little Histories, and left the <hi>Peloponnesian</hi> Warre (which he tooke for his subiect) in a manner vnwrltten; for neither any part▪ nor the whole, could iustly haue carryed such a Title.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, he accuseth him for the method of his first Booke, in that he deriueth <hi>Greece,</hi> from the infancy thereof to his owne time; and in that he setteth downe the Narration of the quarrels about <hi>Corcyra,</hi> and <hi>Potidaea,</hi> before he entreateth of the true cause of the Warre, which was the greatnesse of the <hi>Athenian</hi> dominion, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and enuyed by the <hi>Lacedaemonians.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For answer to this, I say thus. For the mentioning of the antient State of <hi>Greece,</hi> he doth it briefly▪ insisting no longer vpon it then is necessary for the well vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the following History. For without some generall notions of these first times, many places of the History are the lesse easie to be vnderstood, as depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpon the knowledge of the originall of seuerall Cities and Customes, which could not be at all inserted into the History it selfe, but must be either supposed to before knowne by the reader, or else be deliuered to him in the beginning, as a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary Preface And for his putting first the Narration of the Publique, and auowed cause of this Warre, and after that the true and inward motiue of the same, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension is absurd. For it is plaine that a cause of Warre, divulged and auowed, how flight soeuer it be, comes within the taske of the Historiographer, no lesse then
<pb facs="10"/>
the Warre it selfe, for without a pretext, no Warre followes. This prete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes an iniury receiued, or pretended to be receiued. Whereas the inward mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue to hostility is but coniecturall, and not of that euidence, that a Historiographer should be alwayes bound to take notice of it; as enuy to the greatnesse of another State, or feare of an iniury to come. Now let any man iudge, whether a good wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of History, ought to handle, as the principall cause of Warre, proclaimed iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or concealed enuy. In a word the Image of the Method vsed by <hi>Thucydides</hi> in this point, is this. <hi>The Quarrell about</hi> Corcyra, <hi>passed on this manner; and the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell about</hi> Potidaea, <hi>on this manner</hi>; (relating both at large) <hi>and in both, the</hi> Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <hi>were accused to haue done the iniury. Neuerthelesse the</hi> Lacedaemonians <hi>had not vpon this iniury entred into a Warre against them, but that they</hi> enuyed <hi>the greatnesse of their</hi> power, <hi>and</hi> feared <hi>the consequence of their</hi> ambition. I thinke a more cleare, and naturall order cannot possibly be deuised.</p>
   <p>Againe he sayes, that he maketh a Funerall Oration (which was solemnely done on all occasions through the Warre) for 15 Horsemen onely, that were slaine at the Brookes called <hi>Rheiti</hi>; and that for this reason onely, that he might make it in the person of <hi>Pericles,</hi> who was then liuing, but before another the like occasion hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, was dead.</p>
   <p>The manner of the <hi>Athenians</hi> was, that they that were slaine the first, in any Warre, should haue a solemne Funerall, in the suburbs of the Citie. During this Warre, they had many occasions to put this custome in practise. Seeing therefore it was fit to haue that custome, &amp; the forme of it knowne, and that once for all, the manner being euer the same, it was fittest to relate it on the first occasion, what number soeuer they were that were then buried; which neuerthelesse is not likely to haue been so few as <hi>Dionysius</hi> saith. For the Funerall was not celebrated till the Winter after they were slaine, so that many more were slaine before this solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and may all be accounted amongst the first. And that <hi>Pericles</hi> performed the office of making their Funerall Oration, there is no reason alledged by him, why it should be doubted.</p>
   <p>Another fault hee finds, is this; That he introduceth the <hi>Athenian</hi> Generals in a Dialogue, with the Inhabitants of the Ile of <hi>Melos,</hi> pretending openly, for the cause of their inuasion of that Ile, the power and will of the State of <hi>Athens,</hi> and reiecting vtterly, to enter into any disputation with them, concerning the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of their cause; which he saith, was contrary to the dignity of the State.</p>
   <p>To this may be answered; That the Proceeding of these Generals was not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to diuers other Actions, that the people of <hi>Athens</hi> openly tooke vpon them; and therefore it is very likely they were allowed so to proceed. Howsoeuer, if the <hi>Athenian People</hi> gaue in charge to these their Captaines, to take in the Iland, by all meanes whatsoeuer, without power to report backe vnto them first, the equity of the Ilanders cause, as is most likely to be true, I see then no reason the Generals had to enter into disputation with them, whether they should performe their charge, or not, but onely whether they should doe it by faire, or foule meanes; which is the point treated of in this Dialogue. Other Cauils he hath, touching the matter, and order of this History, but not needfull to be answered.</p>
   <p>Then for his phrase, he carpeth at it in infinite places, both for obscure and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious. He that will see the particular places, he reprehendeth, let him read <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nysius</hi> himselfe, if he will; for the matter is too tedious for this place. It is true, that there be some Sentences in him, somewhat long, not obscure to one that is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue; and besides that, they are but few. Yet is this the most important fault he findeth. For the rest, the obscurity that is, proceedeth from the profoundnesse of the Sentences, containing contemplations of those humane passions, which either dissembled, or not commonly discoursed of, doe yet carry the greatest sway with men, in their publique conuersation. If then one cannot penetrate into them without much meditation, we are not to expect a man should vnderstand them at the first speaking. <hi>Marcellinus</hi> saith, he was obscure on purpose, that the Common people might not vnderstand him. And not vnlikely; for a wise man should so write (thogh in words vnderstood by all men) that wise men only should be able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend him. But this obscurity is not to be in the Narrations of things done, not in the descriptions of places, or of battels▪ in all w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg>, <hi>Thucydides</hi> is most perspicuous,
<pb facs="10"/>
as <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the words before cited▪ hath testified of him. But in the Characters of mens humours and manners, and applying them to affaires of consequence, it is impossible not to be obscure to ordinary capacities, in what words soeuer a man deliuer his mind; If therefore <hi>Thucydides</hi> in his Orations, or in the Description of a Sedition, or other thing of that kind, be not easily vnderstood, it is of those onely that cannot penetrate into the nature of such things, and proceedeth not from any intricacy of expression. <hi>Dionysius</hi> further findeth fault with his vsing to set word against word, which the <hi>Rhetoricians</hi> call <hi>Antitheta.</hi> Which, as it is in some kind of speech, a very great vice, so is it not vnproper in Characters; and of comparatiue discourses, it is almost the onely Stile.</p>
   <p>And whereas he further taxeth him for licentiousnesse in turning <hi>Nownes</hi> into <hi>Verbes,</hi> and <hi>Verbes</hi> into <hi>Nownes,</hi> and altering of <hi>Genders, Cases,</hi> and <hi>Numbers,</hi> as hee doth sometimes for the more efficacy of his Stile, &amp; without <hi>Soloecisme,</hi> I leaue him to the answer of <hi>Marcellinus</hi>; who sayes, <hi>That</hi> Dionysius <hi>findeth fault with this, as being ignorant</hi> (yet he was a professed <hi>Rhetorician) that this was the most excellent, and perfect kind of speaking.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Some man may peraduenture desire to know, what motiue <hi>Dionysius</hi> might haue, to extenuate the worth of him, whom he himselfe acknowledgeth to haue beene esteemed by all men, for the best by farre of all Historians that euer writ, and to haue been taken by all the Antient <hi>Orators</hi>▪ and <hi>Philosophers,</hi> for the measure and rule of writing History. What motiue he had to it, I know not; but what glory he might expect by it, is easily knowne. For hauing first preferred <hi>Herodotus,</hi> his Countreyman▪ a <hi>Halicarnassian,</hi> before <hi>Thucydides,</hi> who was accounted the best, and then conceiuing that his owne History might perhaps be thought not inferiour to that of <hi>Herodotus,</hi> by this computation he saw the honour of the best Historiogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher falling on himselfe; Wherin (in the opinion of all men) he hath misreckoned. And thus much for the obiections of <hi>Denis</hi> of <hi>Halicarnasse.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>It is written of <hi>Demosthenes,</hi> the famous Orator, that he wrote ouer the History of <hi>Thucydides</hi> with his owne hand, eight times. So much was this Worke estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, euen for the eloquence. But yet was this his eloquence not at all fit for the barre, but proper for History, and rather to be read, then heard. For words that passe away (as in publike Orations they must) without pause, ought to be vnderstood with ease, and are lost else; though words that remaine in writing▪ for the Reader to meditate on, ought rather to be pithy, and full. <hi>Cicero</hi> therefore doth iustly set him a part, from the ranke of Pleaders, but withall, he continually giueth him his due for History. <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>De Oratore. What great Rhetorician euer borrowed any thing of</hi> Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cydides? <hi>yet all men praise him, I confesse it, as a wise, seuere, graue Relator of things done. Not for a Pleader of Causes at the Barre, but a Reporter of Warre in History. So that he was neuer reckoned an Orator, nor if he had neuer written a History, had his name therefore not been extant, being a man of Honour and Nobility. Yet, none of them imitate the gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ity of his Words and Sentences; but when they haue vttered a kinde of lame and disioynted stuffe, they presently thinke themselues brothers of</hi> Thucydides. Againe, in his Booke, <hi>De optimo Oratore,</hi> he saith thus. <hi>But here will stand vp</hi> Thucydides; <hi>For his eloquence is by some admired; and iustly. But this is nothing to the Orator wee seeke; for it is one thing to vnfold a matter by way of Narration; another thing to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse a man, or cleere him by Arguments. And in Narrations, one thing to stay the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer; another to stirre him. Lucian,</hi> in his Booke entituled, <hi>How a History ought to be written,</hi> doth continually exemplifie the vertues which he requires in an Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storiographer, by <hi>Thucydides.</hi> And if a man consider well that whole Discourse of his, he shall plainely perceiue, that the Image of this present History, praeconceiued in <hi>Lucians</hi> minde, suggested vnto him all the Precepts he there deliuereth. Lastly, heare the most true and proper commendation of him, from <hi>Iustus Lipsius,</hi> in his Notes to his Booke, <hi>De Doctrina Ciuili,</hi> in these words. Thucydides, <hi>who hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, not many, nor very great matters, hath perhaps yet won the Garland from all that haue written of matters, both many and great. Euery where for Eloquution graue; short and thicke with sense; sound in his iudgements; euery where secretly instructing, and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting a mans life and actions. In his Orations and Excursions, almost Diuine. Whom the oftner you read, the more you shall carry away, yet neuer be dismissed without appetite. Next to him is</hi> Polybius, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And thus much concerning the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>History</hi> of <hi>Thucydides.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>