<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface of the Author.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117395_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01857</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11999</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117395</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface of the Author.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A full, ample and punctuall discouery of the barbarous, bloudy, and inhumane practises of the Spanish Inquisition, against Protestants : with the originall thereof. Manifested in their proceedings against sundry particular persons, aswell English as others, upon whom they have executed their diabolicall tyrannie. A worke fit for these times, serving to withdraw the affections of all good Christians from that religion, which cannot be maintayned without those props of Hell. First written in Latin by Reginaldus Gonsaluius Montanus, and after translated into English</title>
                 <author>González de Montes, R. (Raimundo)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bellamy, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 198 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>The Preface of the Author.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N so great a hurly-burly of ciuill dissensions, wherein so many people and nations bend force against their owne companions and fellow-citizens, and furiously rush their swords and weapons into the very bowels of their owne naturall countrie, and for none other cause in very deed but for the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, it would make a wise man doubt in this case whether of them were madde: the one side, which main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the Inquisition, as a thing most holy and wholesome for the Common-wealth; or the other, which seeke not to auoide any god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Inquisition and reformation of religion, but to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues like men worthy of liberty wherein they were borne and bred, from a strange, vnworthy, and intolerable slavery. For though they be both alike ready armed, yet differing asmuch in their opinions and iudgements, as they doe in their mindes and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, it cannot be that right and equitie should bee on both parts: so that, if the one haue iustly taken weapon in hand, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (no doubt) haue done it vniustly. And to passe over the great number of inferiour estates, it is not likely that the chiefe Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes of the world, who are perswaded that they ought by all meanes possible to maintaine the same, and haue vowed the defence thereof with great deuotion and solemne o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th renued from yeare
<pb facs="10"/>
to yeare, should erre from the truth, or doe any thing against right or conscience: specially being neither the first authors there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, nor maintaining it as a thing newly deuised, or without any certaine originall, but as that, which being receiued from their forefathers, and reuerenced both for the opinion of holinesse and countenance of antiquitie, hath by a power greater then is the power of man, beene esteemed here among men as a heauenly thing. Besides these glorious titles, there be also thereunto annexed other singular commodities; to wit, a diligent endeuour to remoue the infection that might grow aswell of the Iewish and Mahometicall heresies that daily doe arise, besides the reuenues of the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer encreased hereby, and the sodaine and maruelous enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of diuers priuate persons, which though they be great matters in worldly respect, yet are they not so greatly to be accompted of in this cause. But forasmuch as by Christs owne saying, and by naturall reason, a man cannot haue a more easie or perfect iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the qualitie of a tree, whether it be good or bad, then by the fruit thereof, I may without offending of any man in the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of this matter, which is no lesse profitable then hard and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to doe, obserue the same order: since the mischiefe is now already so farre detected, and men growne to be so curious, that they feare not to call into question such things, as they haue hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto by great errour and doltishnesse worshipped and held for most holy and sacred. Now if the <hi>Inquisition</hi> be a good tree, or as they delight to terme it a <hi>Holy,</hi> I doubt not but it will be content to shew the fruits openly, by the goodnesse or holinesse whereof, it may without fraud or enuie be esteemed how good or holy the stocke it selfe is. For light loueth the light, and he that dealeth truly and vprightly is willing to come into the light, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spight of the diuell and all other darknesse, that his workes done in the feare of God may come to light. But he that worketh the things that be euill hateth the light, and hauing power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, bridleth mens tongues, couering his faults with forced si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, lest that the light should discouer them, and shew them to be repro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eable. Wherefore let all Christendome now behold these
<pb facs="10"/>
fruites of the <hi>Holy Inquisition:</hi> which being otherwise very plentifull, by the onely meanes of Gods goodnesse, wee haue here and there plucked for a say and taste of the tree, and by these let them iudge (as casily they may) whether this Holy Tree be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to stand still, or to be turned vpside downe. For herein resteth all and some concerning these matters; whether the reports that I shall make in this Treatise of the <hi>Holy Inquisition,</hi> be true or no. Secondarily, how I came to the knowledge thereof, for no man will doubt but that this tree doth worthily deserue to bee hewed downe, if there be sufficient proofe that it buddeth forth such pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stilent blossomes, and beareth like fruites as these be. Againe, it were a dangerous and inconuenient matter, if we heretickes that detest the Inquisition as a sharpe and iust plague of God, and therefore worthy to be holden suspected, should haue any credite giuen vs herein. Wherefore I haue thought it a thing worthy the trauaile, to shew the briefest and most certaine way, whereby the truth thereof might without any great trouble be vnderstood. That is to say, if the King whose office it is specially to see to the administration of justice in his owne dominion, would first bee brought to beleeue, that both he might of his absolute authoritie, and of dutie ought to call the holy Court of <hi>Inquisition</hi> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts, and that no lawes or decrees of their making, no Priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, no Bulls, no Pardons or dispensations, finally, no Oath ought to let or hinder him from the doing of his dutie herein. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condarily, if after he had appointed such a speciall Commission to examine the Inquisition, he would seeke meanes to be ensormed of such matters by men of grauitie and good consciences, who cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vnto them others, such as might be thought to haue the most knowledge and best experience in these matters, might learne out a truth, as the best custome is, in all other courts and consistories as they call them. For the which purposes those that either presently are, or haue beene heretofore fettered in the Inquisitours prisons, were first to bee sent for and examined but vnbridled in any case, hauing those worse then Iron bittes, taken from their tongues, with the which the <hi>Inquisition</hi> hath hitherto kept her tyrannie
<pb facs="11"/>
close; that is to say, their solemne swearing of them to be silent while they liue, inhibiting them the vttering of any thing by any meanes, that they either knew, or saw, or had experience of themselues touching the <hi>Holy Inquisition,</hi> or their whole manner of proceeding against them in Court or otherwise: but that they should rather repute themselues as dead persons for for that time concerning the knowledge or sense of any such matters. And as though their oath (for sooth) were not a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of force enough, they annexe thereunto terrible threatnings. By meanes where of all the trickes of the Inquisition haue hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to beene secret and hidden, and passed vnder couert to and fro, with a cloake and shadow of a zeale of godlinesse, and yet not so obscurely or secretly, but that the whole world (though confusedly and as it were a farre off) hath at the length espied and found out their outragious tyranny.</p>
   <p>And this is the onely cause that maketh all men keepe their tongues, least it might bee their happes likewise to haue experience thereof in themselues. This bridle I say must first bee remoued and taken away from them of whome these questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons should be asked, and libertie must be giuen to speake boldly and without danger, if a man would haue these secrecies come to light, that haue beene kept close so long, to the great decay and hinderance of the Common wealth, Wherefore if small credite shall be giuen to vs in this Treatise, or none at all, because wee be as it were a partie, and therefore justly to be suspected, seeing for our owne parts wee desire no credite, but referre the matter whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to diligent and orderly triall, there is no cause why any should thinke better or worse of it for vs, but judge of it indifferently by it selfe as it is.</p>
   <p>Moreouer it is as greatly pertinent to our purpose to shew how we came to the knowledge hereof. Wherein, albeit we take God to record and our conscience, that all this is true, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing wee craue no such credite to be aided thereby: neither shall any have just cause to lay that to our charge, that we haue gone from the triall of the matter, and vsed this as a shift.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="11"/>
But to passe the Kings treasuris, and the enriching of other priuate persons, howsoeuer they came by their wealth, because wee would not bee thought to enuie their prosperitie of many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and so great commodities as wee haue before rehearsed, (whereof the fauourers and maintainers of the Inquisition do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly make their bragges, that there is nothing that maketh for them, but rather for the contrary part) it is easie for any man to perceiue, that will consider with us but thus much, that of so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thousands of people, either Turkes or Iewes, or true Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans or heretikes (as they terme them) and reuolters from the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish faith, as haue come within the Inquisitours iurisdiction from the very first beginning of the Inquisition, till this day, there are to bee seene many thousands of Sambenites, as moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of some that were burned, some whom besides the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall and vnrecouerable infamie that hath red<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>unded thereby both to themselues, and to their whole posteritie, they haue bin de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of all their substance. To be short, that so many spoiles of poor soules doe remaine to be seene as haue suffred at their hands for very trifles: but of any whom they haue instructed and amen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, or withdrawn from their errors, not so much as one example <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>or any one memoriall.</p>
   <p>Now as concerning the originall of the Inquisition, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, and the glorious title that bleareth and bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>deth mens eyes now adayes (for what man is he that would bow downe and worship these sacred names and titles: <hi>The holy Inquisition. The fathers of the faith: The Inquisitors of leud heresies and apostacie?)</hi> I will speak somewhat, to the intent men may vnderstand by what right they claime and hold the same.</p>
   <p>After the warres were ended, wherin <hi>Ferdinando</hi> and <hi>Isabel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> of famous memory expelled the Turkes out of the territory and Citie of <hi>Granata,</hi> and other places in <hi>Spaine,</hi> which had vsurped there by the space of 778. yeares, from the time of <hi>Roderico</hi> the last king of <hi>Spain,</hi> that was of the race and line of the <hi>Goths,</hi> hauing restored their country into the ancient estate that it was in before, and gotten to themselues perpetuall fame and renowne, they fell from those continuall troubles and tumults of warre to
<pb facs="12"/>
reforming and purging of religion. The occasion whereof came as well by the <hi>Mores,</hi> that being conquered, had liberty to remaine in <hi>Spaine,</hi> and enjoy all their goods with condition that they should receiue the christian faith: as by the Iewes, that were in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as many as the other, who were permitted to continue still vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the same condition that the <hi>Mores</hi> did, commandement being giuen to all that were not content to admit this condition, that they should immediately depart <hi>Spaine,</hi> passing ouer the straites of <hi>Marrocke,</hi> and retyre into their owne countrey. For the <hi>Iewes</hi> (as their most ancient Chronicles doe report) did inhabite <hi>Spaine</hi> from the time that <hi>Titus</hi> Emperor of <hi>Rome</hi> destroyed <hi>Ierulalem.</hi> Who caused them to bee transported thither, there to remaine in miserie and thraldome, being notwithstanding in good case for one thing, in that they were not compelled by any to alter their religion till the time of <hi>Ferdinando.</hi> Whereupon the kings of <hi>Spaine</hi> considering, that those people were but only Christians by name and for fashion sake, submitting themselues for feare and awe, and for safegard of their riches, rather then any loue or zeal which they bare to christianitie, deuised to make prouision, and to take some order for their better instruction. A godly purpose surely, and meet for christian Princes, if euill counsellers had not maliciously peruerted their good intents. For there were alwayes about the king certaine Friers of the order of Saint <hi>Dommicke,</hi> to whom diuers well disposed Princes gaue very great care and credit, especially in matters of religion and conscience: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a proud and ambitious sect, that tooke vpon them great skill, and outwardlly professed much holinesse most arrogantly and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently; by meanes thereof, had more free acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sse to Princes pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie chambers, and thereupon growing to be of their priuie coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell, and obtaining such credit, that kings were content to bee or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and directed by them in these and such like good purposes, whereas they should haue prouided godly instructors, pastors and teachers to win and allure the counterfait christians (as it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them) by charitie and gentlenesse, labouring with all diligence to withdraw them from their errors, to embrace true christiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie sincerely and without dissimulation, they erected a new kinde
<pb facs="12"/>
of Consistorie of an Inquisition; wherein the poore wretches, in steade of better instructions, wherewith there was some hope to win them, should be robbed and spoiled of all their goods, and possessions, and either put to most cruell death, or suffer most in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable torments by whippe or otherwise, leading the rest of their life in perpetuall obloquie and ignominie, and sustaining extream pottertie by losse of lands and goods. Neither was this executed onely vpon such as had most shamefully blasph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>med Christ, but the least and most tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>g ceremonie of the <hi>Iewish</hi> or <hi>Morish</hi> law, or the smallest error in christian religion, whereof they did neuer teach them so much as their articles, had beene matter sufficient to condemne them. To the furtherance of this new deuice <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth of that name, Pope of Rome, put his helping hand by adding his confirmation, so that at the length it became of such force being ratified and established by the kings authoritie and the Popes, that were it not for that the hugenesse thereof is such, that is not able to sustaine it selfe, being a thing so burdenous to the world and so importable, a man might very well thinke it to bee impregnable. See I pray you how well these godly pastours prouided for the new increase of Christ's flocke, whom they ought to haue had greater regard to feed than their owne bellies, and should not in milking them haue drawne the very bloud to deuoure it, nor besides the hauing of their fleece, flame them also most cruelly to couer themselues with the skinnes, neither ought to haue killed the fatlings, but to cherish the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, to binde the broken, to seeke the stra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>-sheep and bring them home to the folde, like good and carefull shepheards, without vsing such force and violence, or cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>ing any iurisdiction or su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioritie ouer them: to whom they should rather submit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues and become seruants, considering that they are the folde of Christ But as for seeking, they sought indeed and daily doe, inquiring with great diligence after the wandring sheepe panting and fainting but it is to slay them, not to sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e them. But to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed. As the <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>ane</hi> were the first authors therof, so for the authoritie and estimation that they were in with Princes, they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the execution of this tyrannie vnder the pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ence of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb facs="13"/>
the true christian faith, whereof they had of long time bin accounted the patrons. But afterwards by meanes of their vnsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable couetousnesse and ambition, (for the whech two vices they are already discredited among the common people) as also for their crueltie and tyrannie which they practised, being exalted to that high estate and dignitie, they became so intolerable, that the Princes themselues who lately before had aduanced them to those estates, were enforced to displace them, pretending diuers reasonable causes and allegations, and so committed it vnto the Clergie: Whereof the ancient Churches of the <hi>Dominicans</hi> hung round about with ancients and ensignes of victorie, ouer such as they conquered during the time that they were in authoritie, is proofe sufficient.</p>
   <lg>
      <l>Ne from her heart the causes old of wrath and sore disdaine</l>
      <l>Was slaked yet, but in her brest high spight did still remaine: <note place="margin">Vrig. Aeneid.</note>
      </l>
      <l>How Paris Venus beautie praised, and hers esteem'd at nought,</l>
      <l>She abhors the stock of Ganimede, who loue to heauen had raught.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>Howbeit they retaine till this day the title and name of Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitours still with tooth and naile, and will one day no doubt haue a cast at the office againe, and claime their right. So that we may thanke these wicked counsellors and none other for the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition at this day, most diuellishly peruerting the godly purposes of Princes, which tended to the weale of the Church, and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them wholly to the aduancement of their owne commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and estimation. Or else whereto I beseech you appertained it, that they which would be accounted diligent and faithfull sow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the seede of christianitie, and the zealous furtherers of the same, should erect a new kind of <hi>Consistory,</hi> so rare and strange to the whole world, which is not set vp to informe the ignorant, or to conuince the obstinate, and bring them to the knowledge of true religion, either by perswasion of learning, or by charitable dealing, the only meanes that Christ would haue his ministers to work by, but to compell them by force and might, by rigour and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie, by commissions and authoritie, by <hi>Racks &amp; Torments,
<pb facs="13"/>
Chaines, Halters, Barnacles, Sambenites,</hi> by <hi>Fire</hi> and by <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gots:</hi> which holy <hi>Consistorie</hi> of theirs, is not assisted with men of godly conuersation, or knowne to be learned in the mysteries of holy Scripture, such as would labour painfully in the Lords vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, and set forward his haruest: but is garded with <hi>Sherifes, Treasurers, Notaries, Sum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ers, Iaylers, Proctors, Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> or <hi>Familiars</hi> (as they call them) a foule and an insinite com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. And who would not iudge think ye, that all these things were devised rather to lay new taxes and impositions vpon the people, and to encrease the reuenues of the Eschequer, than for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of religion. As for the purpose, if a man would chuse out a cunning huntsman with all his furniture, hauing his art<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery about him, his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>tres, grinnes, heyes, dogges, &amp;c. and send him thus arayed to preach the Gospel, and publish Christ's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, what man I pray you that were well advised, and should behold such a man, hauing his hands daily imbrued with the change of preyes and spoiles, would not account him a better hunter than a preacher? For (doubtlesse) the commission an dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of preaching was giuen to good and godly Bishops and pastours (if any such there were) both by the lawes of God, and constitutions of man, that they should teach and instruct, as well the young nouices as the elder schollers, to tread the path of true godlinesse. But these men being so blind, or so carelesse, or both, that either they couldnot, or wouldnot see to their office and due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in this behalfe, there was neuer a man of them all, either Bishop or Diuine, but he thought that a great part of his dutie touching his function was abbridged &amp; dispensed withall, by meanes of ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the court of Inquisition; all good and godly laws concerning christianitie, are so cleane raced out of the tables of their hearts.</p>
   <p>And this Inquisition being erected in this wise at the first, and ratisied afterwards by the greatest authoritie in the wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d, that is to say, the Kings and the Popes, though it had the opinion of holinesse to countenance it, so that it should seeme to deserue the approbation of most men, yet was it neuer generally receuied o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> all. For at what time king <hi>Ferdinando</hi> went about to establish it
<pb facs="14"/>
in <hi>Arragon,</hi> which was his owne inheritance descended from his father, the Nobles of the realme did first make humble supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that it might not be established. Afterwards, being by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence forced vpon them, they did also with force and violence withstand it, alledging that it tended rather to the impeachment of the libertie of their countrie, then to the reformation of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. In so much that it was not received (if a man may say it were receiued at all that, was forced vpon them against their wils) till the settling of it had cost many a mans life. And besides the hatred which the Nobles and Commons of that Realme beare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this their holy Inquisition at this day, it d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th well appeare by the death of <hi>Seignor Aepila,</hi> who being sent thither by the King with large commissions to execute the same, was slaine of the Noble men at <hi>Sarragoss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> in the Cathedrall Church. The which caused many of the foolish superstitious people to worship him euen as a Saint. For it is very certainely reported, that the bloud issuing out of his body, being newly slaine, sprang out in such aboundance, that it spirted to the Altar. By the which mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle (say they) God declared both the innocencie of the person, and the goodnesse of the quarrell wherein was slaine. Notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all this and that diuers other miracles are sundry times seene vpon his tombe, to confirme the same opinion and fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sie of the common people, such is the folly of men, and the power of the diuell (as <hi>Paul</hi> saith) to deceiue men which haue re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>ed the loue and zeale of the truth, he could neuer yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonized a Saint, and called <hi>Saint Aepila:</hi> forasmuch as enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prising a iust quarrell, he was not only found to haue a s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>rt of male on at the time of his death, (which thing notwithstanding they say, he might wellenough haue enioyed the holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of a Saint) but he had also vnder his other garments a short hanger by his side, and that (forsooth) only h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ndred his absolute honour.</p>
   <p>This Inquisition you will say was not brought in, to the end that any should thereby be instructed in the principles of true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but onely that heresie by meanes hereof might bee aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed. Marry so much we yeeld vnto them indeed For it appeareth
<pb facs="14"/>
plainely by the zeale that was in those good Princes, that they had a better meaning with them at the first, then that which through their wicked counsellours afterward was put in execution. The Inquisition being th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> established for the same ends and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses which I haue before mentioned (as some affirme) before the battell at <hi>Granata,</hi> which maketh nothing against me if it be so, the charge of instructing the people in the principles of religion, was first referred to I Tears and Curates, and from them transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Wardens of the Church, and afterward to the Clerkes in euery towne and parish, who taught the simple abused people their <hi>Aue Maria, Pater noster,</hi> their <hi>Credo,</hi> with <hi>Salua re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> in Latine shall I say, nay in a barbarous kinde of Latine, and that with sporting themselues, and mocking the poore silly soules, without any deuotion or zeale, not without reward neither, but very dearely and at a high price; many times besides their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wages, they were payd with the goodwi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es honestie, or the daughters virginitie. For the other fiue cōmandements of the holy Church, which they s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ad were necessarie to saluation: that is to say, the hearing of Masse on holy dayes and sundayes: The go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to shrist and holy confession: The receiuing of holy bread, the due obseruing of Fasts enioyned by the Church, and the true paying of their tithes and Church-duties, these things I warrant you were beaten into their heads in plaine words and mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tongue. By which kinde of discipline, what other thing I pray you could seeme to be sought, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n to bring men into a heape of perpetuall errours? And the court of Inquisition being erected on the other part for reformation of errours, they might be sure like good hunters to lodge the Deere, and take their stand, and so to obtaine a continuall prey. But to proceed, let vs grant them thus much, that the Inquisition was ordained to none other end, and that they be two seuerall and distinct offices, to teach the faith, and to roote out heresies, yet were it the part and dutie of good and discreet counsellours, to prouide that the authoritie committed to Bishops by the holy Scriptures of God, should not thereby be taken from them: neither should any other perswasion
<pb facs="15"/>
enter into their heads, that there were any other fire or sword to root out heresies, but only the sword of Gods word: both the which things the holy Apostle did most euidently teach in the Epistle to <hi>Titus;</hi> where among other qualities required in a Bishop, hee would haue him embrace the word of God fit for instruction, that he may be able to exhort by wholesome doctrine, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince the gainsayers and aduersaries. For surely a true and iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying faith cannot be forced, (the nature thereof is such) no more can heresie be destroyed by the heretickes death. But the word of God is most apt and sit for both purposes. For thereby faith is not only engendred, but increased and multiplyed meruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously, and whatsoeuer is not agreeable to true faith, if it be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and tried by the light of this word, shall soone be bewray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Wherefore they ought first to haue resorted to the Scriptures, and taken counsell of them, whether they had limited any punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for such as should shew themselues wilfull and obstinate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the truth, or the most cruell execution that can be by fire. For as concerning the confiscation of goods, what can be thought more wretched and couetous, or more vnjust and shamelesse, or further from the profession of a Christian man? And to let passe their open infamy, the staine whereof will hardly be spunged out againe, who can worthily speake enough against them, that vse the same kinde of punishment euen against those poore wretches, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> they haue perswaded to recant their errours? <hi>Paul</hi> in the place aboue mentioned, appointeth no penaltie, for as much as it may well be, that the partie condemned may in time be reclaimed, and therefore mercy ought rather to be practised of euery good shepheard with all gentlenesse and loue, then any such extremitie. But let vs enter further, and see what <hi>Paul</hi> appointeth for such as are obstinate persons. Auoide the company of an hereticke (saith he) after one or two admonitions. First hee would haue him charitably admonished of his error twice or thrice, and that by the Bishop, not cited into the court, not put to the torments, or otherwise punished for his erronious opinions with such extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and so continually. Then if gentle admonition will reclaime
<pb facs="15"/>
him, there is good cause why both the Bishop and the whole congregation may rejoyce of the winning of a brother, to be a member of Christ. But if such admonitions will not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, he counselleth vs to proceed to excommunication: that is to say, to cut him off and exclude him the company and fellowship of the Christians: the which notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding must not be executed in way of reuenge of his error, but ministred as a medicine for his amendment. And this judgement of the Disciple agreeth with the rule of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster: <hi>If hee wil not giue ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e to thee, nor other</hi> (saith he) that is to say, them that haue giuen him admonition the second time, <hi>Let him be thence forth accompted of as an Ethnicke or Publican.</hi> Which is as much in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, as if he had neuer receiued the faith. In this degree of seueritie, which being duely considered is sharpe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, Christs discipline stayeth, and proceedeth no further. And this is the Court, these be the lawes thereof, and the whole manner of proceeding, wherewith a true Christian man (if there had beene any such among them) should haue contented himselfe in proceeding against his brother being beside the right way; or against any heresies, of what sort or condition soeuer they be, because Christ hath thought them to be sufficient, and prouided these remedies, which the Church hath alwayes vsed from time to time to great profite, in the rooting vp of all heresies that at any time grew therein. As concerning the putting of heretickes to death, it is like altogether, as if a Phisician, to the intent to rid the patient of his disease, should for the nonce rid him also of his life. Moreouer, they that doe pretend most of all now adayes the rooting vp of heresies by such meanes, do not only not attaine thereunto, (for as yet the world is blinded, to take falshood for truth) but if it were so, then by taking away his life, they cut him off from all those meanes and possibilities where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he might attaine his owne saluation. For it might very well come to passe in time, for asmuch as Gods judgements
<pb facs="16"/>
are deepe and incomprehensible, that the partie continuing aliue, might bee brought into some better case. But it is to be feared will some say, lest he infect others. True it is, and for that consideration both Christ and his Apostle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth us to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>schue him, and to cut him off from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Church. But if they would needes proceede far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and vpon other reasonable considerations punish such obstinate persons more seuerely; were not the ordinary ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate sufficient to execute the same? Doubtlesse their answer will bee this, that the knowledge of heresies, can in no case appertaine to the secular magistrates, because they for the most part are ignorant in the holy Scriptures and Ecclesiasticall affaires: For this is a common saying with these Fathers that are so far seen in Gods secrets, that neither the knowledge nor determination of matters in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion doe appertaine to the <hi>Secular</hi> magistrate, as they terme him in despight and reproach But I pray you in what respect are they themselues chosen to supply those places, and to bee Inquisitours to determine matters of faith, whereof they are termed the Fathers, or to discusse heresies, whereof they are said to ridde the world, being neither learned in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, nor able to teach the beliefe? For they are thought men good enough for that office if they be Doctors in the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and canon lawes. As for their Diuines (and yet a silly diuinitie God knowes) truly since the time that the <hi>Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans</hi> were displaced thence, (wherof I made mention before) we haue not seen any of them execute any such office. Yea, what if since that time there hath bin an order taken by the Inquisitors, and entred into their books, that no Diuine thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth should occupy any such place? Now as concerning the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil law, surely the Inquisitors do not excell the secular magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate; and as for the canon, if a man were neuer so well seen in it, they cannot deny, but it serueth as little to the deciding of matters in religion as the ciuill. How then is it possible to be otherwise, but that when such ignorant men bee admitted
<pb facs="16"/>
to determine matters of Religion, as haue no manner of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the holy Scriptures, saue only a little poore skill in the constitutions of mans braine, they must needs turne sweet into soure, and soure into sweet: call light darkenesse, and darkenesse light? That is to say, in professing themselues to bee the Patrones of saith, roote out all faith, and maintaine monstrous errours: slea the children of God, and cherish the children of the diuell: kill the seruants of Christ, foster, maintaine, and encrease the seruants of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist.</p>
   <p>Here they will answer vs, that albeit they themselues can no more judge of matters touching faith, than a blinde man can of colours, yet they take into counsell and commission with them, to debate such matters, divers Diuines, whose pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>script rule and order they put in execution, specially <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicanes,</hi> who haue nothing now to doe with the high autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and commission of <hi>Inquisition,</hi> saue only that they are admitted to consultations, and to the <hi>Qualifications of doctrine,</hi> as they terme it.</p>
   <p>And here though we examine not narrowly with what quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Diuinitie they come furnished to this office, yet we may easily ghesse, that being remoued for the causes aforesaid, and thought vnsit for the place, they are not since growne much more apt: specially seeing besides their old infirmities, they are grieuously sicke of their ancient shame; daily renewed by beholding from a low place, the loftie Tribunall seat from whence they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ismounted, and are in a perpetuall headach and madnesse of jealous men, to see their aduersaries enioy the honour which they haue lost. Wherein we report vs to the Inquisitours themselues, for no manknoweth better then they, what tokens the poore <hi>Dominicanes</hi> giue outwardly of the great bile within their brest full of malitious matter, as oft as they are called to those graue and waightie deliberations: in-so-much that it hath perhaps beene thought on, to shut them quite out of the Inquisitours doores.
<pb facs="17"/>
But goe to, they are peradventure amended since. Why might not then the ordinary magistrate call the same Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines to the same consultations? Now to appoint any man iudge of matters which hee vnderstandeth not, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he must needs hang altogether of other mens opinions and sentences whatsoeuer they bee, what an iniquitie is this? What a peruerting of all law and iustice? Who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can maruell, if when we see the <hi>Holy Inquisition</hi> sit in her heauenly Tribunall seat, we say with <hi>Salomon, I haue seen vngodlinesse sit in the seat of iudgement, and iniquitie in the place of iustice?</hi> And yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing all this, what libertie and prerogatiue they will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low themselues, in the very same matters which they punish in others, as the highest points of herefie, you may behold in the example following.</p>
   <p>It happened a few yeares passed, in <hi>Barchinon</hi> a very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Citie in the teritory of <hi>Cathalonia,</hi> that when they should march forward in their procession on <hi>corpus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sti</hi> day to carry the Masse bread about, and all things were ready, requisite to so solemne a shew, euen as the Priest that had danced the Tragicall high Masse, should couch the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed host in the golden pixe, as the Diuell would haue it, it was too great a compasse to be put in the boxe. All men were amased: the whole shew staied: there was not a man in that great and notable assembly that knew what to doe, in a case so strange and so vnlocked for. Now surely it was a sport alone, and a iest worthy so great a company.</p>
   <p>Some perhaps of the wiser sort, saw no way but one to help at a pinch; namely to begin a new Masse in Gods name and with better lucke, and to shape a cake fit for the boxe. But that was too late: for the procession had farre to goe, and it was too too much paines to defer it any longer. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, perchance there was neuer a sir Iohn there but had broke his fast well, the better to take paine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in so great a solemnity. And tho the Diuines were of opinion that hee that
<pb facs="17"/>
sang the high Masse, might dispatch another in case of neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie, yet he good soule looking for nothing lesse then such a chance, had already supt vp the rinsing of the Chalice, as his dutie was to doe. Well sir, there was one of the Inquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, a man of <hi>Arragon,</hi> whose name was <hi>Molonio.</hi> This Gentleman being as hastie by nature, as bold by authoritie, made no more adoe, but tooke a paire of cissours, and pared his maker where he was ouergrowne, and so by a little paring, put both him in the boxe, and the people out of doubt. Some perhaps will praise this mans present wit in so great a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie: others will abhorre and detest his godlesse and rash boldnesse: others will bewaile and lament the hard fortune of their God so to be pared and circumcised by the cursed hands of a cruell Inquisitour. But good Lord, if any other had beene so saucie but an Inquisitor, specially if he had had any Iewes blood in him, how would they haue handled him trow you? Indeed <hi>Molonio</hi> was put out of office: but he tarried not many dayes ere he was sent to be Inquisitour at <hi>Siuil,</hi> for they might not lose so stout a souldier of the Inquisition for a trifle. What should we here talke of the Popes autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie? they extoll and abase him: they adore him and contemn him: they reuenge his wrong and doe him wrong, euen as hee serueth or hindreth their holy office. Wee purpose not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute these matters any further, meaning only to touch them in way of Preface, to declare by what beginnings and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions the <hi>Inquisition</hi> is growne: what antiquitie and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse it carryeth: and what profite it hath brought to the world vnder the title of reforming religion. These things being as we haue declared them, so true in deed, and such in qualitie, as no honest man can either plainely denie them, or justly excuse them, no man ought to maruell if the people, which haue otherwise hitherto beene most dutifully obedient to their Magistrates, to driue so horrible a pestilence from their countrie, haue be taken themselues to their weapons and defence of armes, as hauing none other more reasonable
<pb facs="18"/>
meanes to helpe themselues.</p>
   <p>They protest, that they seeke not to auoide the reformation of religion, which they heartily wish for, so that it be such a one as is worthy of so good a name, and bee directed by the prescript word of God, which ought to be the onely rule of religion, to all that loue true religion. And in that behalfe, what can they hope for of the Inquisition, besides that it hath already yeelded? They protest further, that they owe to their lawfull gouernours, and that by the expresse word of God, obedience, honour, and tribute, the which they are most ready to performe with their accustomed chearefulnesse and hearty good will. Only they humbly pray and beseech, that it may be taken of them without the dishonour of God, and the most miserable capti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>itie and thraldome of their consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, the which ought to bee more recommended, and deare to good and godly men, then their very liues. They protest besides, that they will not any manner of wayes shake off the yoake of just obedience to their Magistrates, but they complaine, (and that not without great cause) that besides the easie and gentle yoke which they haue hitherto borne with that meekenesse of heart that became them, they are scour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with the Iron whips of the <hi>Inquisition,</hi> which seeketh nothing but the slaughter of innocent Citizens, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiscation and spoile of their goods. They might haue in times past with some colour blamed the men of <hi>Arragon,</hi> which receiued not the Inquisition without tumult and bloudshed, for it was then couered with that goodly and fresh name, and shew of holinesse: neither as yet had it raged against all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently, but only against the <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Moores,</hi> and that also for very plausible and apparant causes. But now since it hath not ceased to bring forth such fruites, as wee haue rehearsed for these threescore and fifteene yeares: I thinke they shall not seeme to be madde, that seeke by all meanes to them possible, to driue it from their borders. Nay, they might rather be truly judged to bee madde men,
<pb facs="18"/>
if in stead of their faithfull fathers, and good shepheards and preachers of true religion they would wittingly and willingly receiue into their houses the very enemies, and most cruell destroyers of all faith and religion. And if there be any that know them not to bee such as wee terme them, let them read but part of their sleights and manner of procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings discouered in this booke, (for wee could not learne them all,) and let them well waigh and consider them, and then judge.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>