<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A briefe declaration, of the worthy Arte of Medicine, and of the inuenters of the same, and of the parts &amp; names that it is de∣uided into, and to what ende it serueth.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1586</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117692_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01410</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11531</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117692</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A briefe declaration, of the worthy Arte of Medicine, and of the inuenters of the same, and of the parts &amp; names that it is de∣uided into, and to what ende it serueth.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine vvorkes of Galens, called Methodus medendi : with a briefe declaration of the worthie art of medicine, the office of a chirurgion, and an epitome of the third booke of Galen, of naturall faculties: all translated into English, by Thomas Gale Maister in Chirurgerie</title>
                 <author>Galen</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1586</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 138 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="declaration">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <pb n="1" facs="7"/>
   <head>A briefe declaration, of the worthy Arte of Medicine, and of the inuenters of the same, and of the parts &amp; names that it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided into, and to what ende it serueth.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> famous and auncient authors, doth manifestly affirme, that the arte of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decine, was geuen to mankinde, by the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie Lord God, that it might helpe our weke and frayle nature, in the time of most greuous sicknesse, sēt vnto vs for our sinnes, for if we should alwayes remaine in health, &amp; in good and perfect state, neither should we know our selues, neither yet the great might, and power, of the Lord God, which doth both geue health, and sicknesse, neither should we seeke out the vertue of his creatures, as herbes, trées, stones, mettals, mineralls, beastes, foules, fishes, and all other things, that crepeth on the face of the earth, which hath receued of the high and mightie Lorde, both qualities, and properties, to helpe, and cure, most greuous diseases, being rightly aplied and vsed, according to reason, &amp; experience, and for as much as we doe sée, that mankinde is altered, ouerthrowen, and corrupted, through y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fraylnesse of nature, by meanes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, we cannot alwayes remaine in health, we are therefore driuen by necessitie, to séeke out those thinges, which may restore vs againe vnto health. Health is restored by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of medecines, and the vertue of medecines, was founde out by long experience: experience, and reason, being ioyned together, maketh an arte, and this arte by the common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, and testimony, of all authors, is the most worthy, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, and most profitable, in all the world: For lyke as man, which is subiect to this arte, or the matter, whervpon the artest doth worke, is most excellent amongst all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, both in the sight of God, his creature, and in the sight of the world, so is the artist, which worketh vpon his body,
<pb facs="8"/> most excellent, both in the sight of God, and in the sight of Princes, wherefore, <hi>Salomon</hi> did say, <hi>Honora medicum, pro necessitate,</hi> for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> highest Lord hath created him, for thy help and health. Here it is manifest, that this arte is most noble, for that it taketh her beginning and foundation of the om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent God, as it doth more manifestly apeare, in the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the world, for the Lord God cōmaunded the earth, to bring foorth all maner of herbes, fruitfull trées, and all other thinges, necessarie for mankinde, that he might haue the vse of them, to his sustenance, for the defence of his life, and that he might by the same thinges, put away greuous diseases: wherefore the most wise <hi>Hebrecion Iesus Sirach,</hi> did say, <hi>Medecine doth proceede from the most highest, and the auncient and most wise men of the lande, haue brought it forth, and he that is wise, will not abhorre it.</hi> What can be spoken more in the commendacion of this arte, or who dare say, that it is not worthie to be cōmended, séeing that these wordes are spoken by the spirit of God, in these holy men, Saint <hi>Paule</hi> doth saye, that the gift of healing is the gift of the holy Ghost, and <hi>Iesus Christ</hi> the sonne of God, did mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister in this Arte, and cured manie people, by meanes whereof, it doth most manifestly apeare, that it is in esti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, both with God, and man. If I shall speake of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar examples, which daylie chaunceth before our eyes, as in those which be infected with most greuous sicknesse, who hath neither comfort, nor ioye, of all their worldlie goods, neither yet hath any space, without tormēting paine, to eate their meate. The greuous and bloudie woundes, of those that be in battaile, which should perish without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent helpe, if it were not for this Arte, &amp; many other, which daylie be brought to health, of innumerable diseases. Let all these, declare the benefit of God, in receiuing the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie, of this Arte, let them testifie, I saye, what it is, to be lightned from so great euills, frō so great feare of death, and manie times, from death it selfe: how profitable, how honorable, and how worthie, this arte is, let them declare. There be diuers opinions, of the first inuention of this art, for some suppose, it was first foūd out emongst the <hi>Egiptiās,</hi>
      <pb n="2" facs="8"/> and other some saie, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the Hebrues did first inuent it, &amp; some suppose the Grecians to be the chiefe founders thereof, but if we may beléeue <hi>Herodotus</hi> or <hi>Diodorus,</hi> they saie that the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> were the first inuenters and séekers out of the nature of hearbes, and other things, to cure griefes and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases withall, and that they chalenge vnto themselues the chiefe preferment for the antiquitie of medicine, and also to be the first inuenters of the worthie art of Astronomie, as it may appeare by their bookes which they haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the course of all the Starres. And they haue brought to light what things were profitable to liuing creatures, by inuenting and exercising of diuerse artes, as Medicine, Astronomie, Musicke, and Arithmetike, and the worthie til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage of the ground was inuented by them. Also <hi>Diodorus</hi> hath giuen this honour or victory vnto <hi>Mercurie,</hi> &amp; he doeth attribute the inuenting of Medicine vnto him. <hi>Osiris</hi> the son of <hi>Saturnus,</hi> for his excellent wit, extolled him with greate honour, for the inuenting of so many noble arts, the which things <hi>Strabus</hi> doeth séeme plainelie to confirme in the last booke of his <hi>Geografie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Where as he doth also write great commendations of the fruitfull ground of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> for that it doth bring forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantlie all manner of things necessarie for the arte of medicine, which doth excell in such plentifulnesse, that no Countrie is to be compared vnto it. And he supposeth that <hi>Mercurius Trimegistus</hi> was the first that found out the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, properties, and qualities of hearbs, fruits, trées, rootes, mettalls, stones, and many other things appertaining vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the arte of Medicine, he had diuerse men appointed to be at his commandement, by the king of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> whose name was <hi>Apis,</hi> which men did continuallie trauaile in séeking of hearbes and other things throughout all <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and brought the said things vnto <hi>Mercurius,</hi> and he made expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments and trials vppon them, and did wonderful greate things by their vertues &amp; properties, &amp; afterward deuised and inuented letters, and ioyned them so together, by mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailous arte, and taught them in such sorte, vnto his disciples or schollers, that they dyd perfectlie vnderstand
<pb facs="9"/> them, and did write, and read their owne language, in such a perfect sort, that in short time, throughout all the coūtrey, they sent letters, one to an other, wherein one vnderstoode an others mynde, then <hi>Mercurius,</hi> for as much as he sawe such vertue, in herbes and other things, as is aforesaid, and how profitable they were, for mankinde, in helping of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases, woundes, pestilence, and many other things, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, many people in that countrey were afflicted, he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing compassion vpon them, and minding, to leaue a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall remembrance in writing, of the natures, and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of those herbes, and other things aforesaide, and what diseases they serued for. He called vpon the eternall Gods, to strengthen, &amp; assist him in his enterprise, with wisdome, and cunning, &amp; with length of time, that he might set forth these things, to their euerlasting praise, &amp; to the vniuersall profit, and commoditie of mankinde.</p>
   <p>And so he began to wryte, and wrote foure bookes, in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of wood, as <hi>Strabus,</hi> doth affirme: and some saith, that those tables indured to the time of <hi>Ptolome</hi> the great, who did dedicate them vnto the gods, and deliuered them vnto the Priestes of the Temple, where, afterwarde they were destroyed, by the meanes of warre.</p>
   <p>Some hold opinion, that <hi>Chiron Sentaurus,</hi> hearing of this excellent man <hi>Mercurie,</hi> went forth of <hi>Grecia,</hi> into <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt,</hi> to learne of him, and became excellent, in diuers artes, and specially, in the arte of medicine, and in knowledge of the simples, and afterwards, he returned againe into <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> his owne countrie, and in that time, there reigned in <hi>Grecia,</hi> a noble Prince named <hi>Apollo,</hi> who was of excellent wisedome, and diligent in studie, to further the common welth of his countrie, with knowledge, and he hearing of this excellent man <hi>Chiron Sentaurus,</hi> sent for him, and gaue him great rewards, and so he learned of <hi>Chiron Sentaurus,</hi> as some writers affirme, to know the natures of herbes, and other thinges, appertaining to the Arte of Medicine, &amp; hauing knowledge of them, and their natures, he put the same in vse, to the great comfort, reliefe and helpe, of the diseased and sicke people, and to his owne immortall fame,
<pb n="3" facs="9"/> for that he did help such diseases and sicknesses, which before that time coulde neuer be holpen, wherefore the people did honour him as a God, and supposed that he was a counsaile with the Gods, in that, that he did knowe the nature and propertie of these hearbes, and other thinges, which they did affirme, no man might know, except he lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it of the Gods themselues, and after the death of their king <hi>Apollo,</hi> they lamented and mourned throughout all the Countrie, thinking the art had bene vtterlie lost, but hée béeing carefull for his Countrie, had taught the same vnto <hi>Aesculapius</hi> his sonne, which when the people vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoode, and for the worthinesse of his owne good déedes, they gathered great summes of money throughout all the lande of <hi>Grecia,</hi> and builded therewithall a rich Temple, and buried his bodie in a meruailous rich Sepulcher within the same, and called it the Temple of <hi>Apollo,</hi> and dyd honour him as a God, for his most vertuous life, and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full trauaile, as concerning the common wealth of his Countrie, and speciallie for that hée dyd not disdaine to cure the most miserable diseased people, which before his time perished without remedie.</p>
   <p>And now that wée are entered in amongest the Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and for that some affirmeth <hi>Apollo</hi> to bée the first in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentour of Medicine, wée will procéede foorth to the noble men of that Countrie, which had this arte in so great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and estimation, that they most diligentlie aboue all other artes, studyed it, and in time dyd growe so excellent therein, that they excelled all other Nations in the world, as it doth most manifestlie appeare by their most worthie Bookes, lefte vnto their posteritie, for a perpetuall memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of their most vertuous and painefull trauaile, which redoundeth vnto our greate commoditie, and to the helpe and succour of those that be diseased.</p>
   <p>The most auncient of all the Grecians, I supposed to bée <hi>Apollo,</hi> who dyd cure many great and wonderfull dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases, by the helpe of the forenamed <hi>Chiron Centaurus,</hi> and some suppose, for that, that the same <hi>Chiron</hi> dyd
<pb facs="10"/> cure manie grieuous, malignant, and virulent vlcers, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst other diseases, that the name of the Arte of <hi>Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia,</hi> was first deriued from <hi>Chiron,</hi> for that hée dyd mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister medicamentes with his hands, and so cured the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and being the first that practised with medicines by the vse of the hande, it is supposed that hée gaue it that name.</p>
   <p>Then after <hi>Apollo</hi> came <hi>Aesculapius</hi> his son, who was no lesse diligent and studious in the same arte than his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and calling vnto him diuerse Philosophers, and other noble men of his Countrie, and by their aduice and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, hée dyd constitute, it an Arte, and made it lawfull for his subiectes that had studied the same, and béeing brought vp with men of greate experience and practise, to vse the same arte amongest his people, to the restoring of their health, in curing of their diseases and infirmities. By meanes whereof <hi>Aesculapius</hi> got vnto himselfe immortall fame, and was called the sonne of the Gods, and first con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituter and founder of the arte of Medicine, as you maye reade in the Historie of <hi>Tragus, Homer,</hi> and manie more of the Gréeke writers, and the same <hi>Tragus</hi> doeth saie, that those men which vsed the arte of Medicine, were named <hi>Iatroes,</hi> for that they dyd cure all manner of griefes, woundes, and sores, and in our auncient English tongue they were called Léeches, and in the Latine tongue, <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicus,</hi> which names doeth signifie no other thing, but cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and healing of mennes bodies with conuenient me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines.</p>
   <p>Then next after were <hi>Aesculapius</hi> two sonnes, called <hi>Machaon</hi> and <hi>Podalirius,</hi> who béeing well instructed in the foresayde arte by their Father <hi>Aesculapius,</hi> became wonderfull excellent, as it may appeare more at large in the Storie of the Troyan warres, by their cures which they dyd vppon the wounded, sore, and sicke men. These two noble Princes, as <hi>Tragus</hi> sayth, had manie Disciples, which they taught this arte vnto, and they and their Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, by continuall practise in proouing experiments, found
<pb n="4" facs="10"/> out manie meruailous remedies against poisons of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane meates and drinkes, and against the poyson of Hearbes, Serpents, and many other things, and against the poisoning of Swoordes, Dartes, Arrowe heades, and Speares, as it is sayd by <hi>Demosthenes</hi> and other wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
   <p>Then of their Disciples did growe a greate number, which were dispearsed into diuerse partes of the worlde, some were sent for into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> &amp; some into <hi>Persia,</hi> some to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> and some to the <hi>Scithians,</hi> whereas they were had in great estimation with the Princes and noble men of those Countries, for that they did cure and helpe their wounded and hurt Souldiers, in the time of warres, and also did reléeue and cure their people in the time of pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and other grieuous infections, to the great safegard, helpe, and comfort of their people, and to the great securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and staie of the Realme, which if their people had dyed of these contagious infections, that were saued by them, their Country should haue lien open to haue ben taken and possessed of their enimies.</p>
   <p>Now of these men, vsing this arte in diuerse Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, hauing many Disciples, or as wée may tearme them Schollers, and diuerse and sundrie sects and opinions did growe vp amongest them, by meanes whereof there was great controuersie, contention, and disputation of a long time, some suppose it was a leauen hundred yéeres, but the matter was not concluded indéede, till the time of <hi>Hyppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> which after long and manie disputations, confuted their fonde and erronious opinions, and brought this most excellent arte, vnto a most perfect waie and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode of curing, which before his time was vnperfect, and vsed onelie by Experience, without anie methode. Some of the same Experimenters affirming, that they coulde cure onelie by dyet all manner of diseases, and other some affirming, that by purging medicines they coulde doe the same, and other some were of that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that with outward medicines onelie, these might bée
<pb facs="11"/> done, vtterlie condemning the other two. Many other foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish opinions there were, which héere were too long to bée re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearsed. Now after all these commeth <hi>Hyppocrates,</hi> that most excellent and noble Philosopher, indued by the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God with such excellent wisedome and knowledge in this most worthie arte, that his lyke was neuer before or since: hée established this art and made it most perfect, that before his time was vnperfect. He wrote manie worthie Bookes of this arte, and speciallie for the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Wounds, Vlcers, Tumours against nature, Frac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and Dislocations, wherein hée shewed himselfe not onelie to bée excellent in knowledge, but also in practise, as it may most manifestlie appeare by the Methode therein contained, he did diuide the arte of Medicine into diuerse partes, that it might be the better learned and vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, declaring which ought first to be learned, which se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and so to the third and fourth, and so to the fifth, as it shall héereafter bée set foorth more at large. <hi>Soranus</hi> in the Preface of his booke, named <hi>Isagogus,</hi> did saiy that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo</hi> dyd first finde out the arte of Medicine. And <hi>Aes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culapius</hi> dyd inlarge it and constitute it an Arte, but that noble man <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> dyd finish it, and make it perfect: He sayth, that by the excellent knowledge of this arte, hée dyd driue awaie the plague out of all <hi>Grecia,</hi> and was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded with a crowne of golde of greate value, by a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crée made in the Citie of <hi>Athens,</hi> for his great paines and good deseruing toward the common wealth. After his death, the Grecians did make in a perpetuall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his Honourable déedes a most fayre Tombe, at <hi>Delfus,</hi> where they did most solempnlie burie his bodie, and wrote vppon his Tombe this Epitaph which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
   <q type="epitaph">
      <p>Hyppocrates of Thesalia, and by kinde of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of Coos, doth lie buried in this place, begotten of the seede of the immortall God Phoebus, &amp; leauing in the world manie bookes of Medicine to put awaie sicknesse, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue health, what shall we neede to saie more of this worthie
<pb n="5" facs="11"/> worthie man, there is no mannes cunning that may giue him his condigne praise.</p>
   </q>
   <p>After his tyme, there was manie in the Countrie of <hi>Grecia,</hi> which practised the Arte of Medicine, not onelye Kinges, but great learned Philosophers, Princes, Dukes, and Lordes, and by their worthie déedes, in preseruing of mennes liues, and putting away of sicknesse, they dyd obteine immortall fame, I saye such fame, did indure long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and was more estemed, then the fame of theyr Kinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes: as for their names, I let passe, for that, there be many wryters, haue spoken of them at large, there was other diuers professers of Medicine, before the tyme of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> that were of worthie fame, as you may reade more at large, in the first booke of <hi>Cornelius Celsus,</hi> wherefore we lette them passe.</p>
   <p>After all these, came that worthie manne, <hi>Galen,</hi> who was without any comparison, from the beginning of the worlde, vnto this daye, except <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> not onely for his excellent learning, in so many famous Artes, which he was perfect in, but specially for this Arte of Medicine, which he was most excellently séene in, both in the The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orike, and Practike parte thereof, his worthie Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries vppon <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> doeth well declare his excellent knowledge, wherewith he hath most bountifully garni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed the Arte of Medicine, as our latter writers doe saye, more like vnto a God, then a man.</p>
   <p>How excellent be these bookes which he hath written of the method of curing, called <hi>Methodus Medendi,</hi> some part whereof, wée haue with great trauaile, brought into the Englishe tongue, and likewise, other of his bookes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, as hereafter followeth. Well, I will saye no more of him, but what séede so euer were sowen abroad in the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall worlde, be the excellent learned men, in the Arte of Medicine, not onely of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> who was the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and fountaine of all Medicine, as <hi>Galen</hi> himselfe doeth witnesse, but the séedes of other menne, he hathe gathered together, sowne in one plaine fielde, and watered them with such diligence, that they haue so increased, that
<pb facs="12"/> at this daye, the vniuersall earth, hath receiued nourish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by them, perpetuall commoditie and pleasure, and he for his great vertue and painefull trauaile, hath wonne vnto himselfe immortall fame, which shall remaine to the worldes ende. After him came <hi>Aesius,</hi> who hath written di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers worthie bookes, in the same arte of Medicine.</p>
   <p>Also <hi>Oribasius, Actuarius,</hi> and <hi>Paulus Aegeneta,</hi> were worthie writers in the same Arte, as you may sée by their workes, which they haue written, <hi>Dioscorides</hi> also, which was before <hi>Galens</hi> time, I may not forget, for his paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful trauaile, in knowledge of the simples, as it doth apeare by a worthie booke, which he hath made thereof. All these and many more, were worthie men amongst the Grecians, and professers of the arte of Medicine, and dyd alwaies ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll and take <hi>Apollo,</hi> as the chiefe Captaine, and first be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginner of the arte of Medicine: and <hi>Aesculapius,</hi> his sonne, to be a setter forewarde of the same, and <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> did make it perfect and finish it.</p>
   <p>What shall I saye, for the worthie <hi>Arabians,</hi> as that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man of <hi>Cartage,</hi> named <hi>Aunconius,</hi> Prince <hi>Auisen, Auo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rois, Auinsor, Rasis, Mesuea, Albucasius,</hi> and many other wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie men, that spronge emongest the <hi>Arabians,</hi> who hath not a little garnished the Arte of Medicine, with a great number of most excellent bookes, which are to be séene at this daye.</p>
   <p>All these men, I saye, toke their beginning of <hi>Galen,</hi> and doeth honour him as their principall head, and doeth glory, and exalte them selues, in his name, for that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer had perfect method of curing before his time, but cured onely by experience, as they were taught of their maisters. For <hi>Hippocrates</hi> workes before <hi>Galens</hi> time, were so short and obscure, that they were vnto most men, not vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, by meanes whereof many doubtes did grow, but <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> by most worthie commentaries, made vppon the same bookes, made those doubtes most plaine and euident, vnto all people, by meanes whereof, not onely many worthie <hi>Grecians,</hi> as I haue sayde before, haue taken a courage to
<pb n="6" facs="12"/> write, but also many of these moste famous <hi>Arabians,</hi> haue followed their steppes, and examples, in setting foorth many excellent woorkes, in the same Arte of Medicine, not onely to the sauegarde of their Prince, and people, but also to their immortall fame, and perpetuall and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting honour.</p>
   <p>The noble Latinestes, haue also deserued no lesse fame, both in séeking out the knowledge of simples, and also in setting foorth of most worthie woorkes, in the Arte of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, as these worthie men, <hi>Cornelius Celsus, Plinius,</hi> and before them <hi>Cato, Verro, Alexander,</hi> and many more, which were men of worthie fame, all these, as I haue saide bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, haue taken their originall and beginning, from <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates,</hi> and <hi>Galen.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>It is also most apparant, that there are manie worthy men y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> haue written in these latter dayes &amp; no small num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in our time, and of manie Countries, some dyd wryte in Fraunce, some in Spaine, some in Germanie, and some in our owne Countrie, and many of them were famous men, and menne of great and excellent knowledge, and practise.</p>
   <p>As <hi>Lamfranke,</hi> Archbishoppe of <hi>Millon, Guido,</hi> of the schole of <hi>Mompillor,</hi> and Commissarie to the Pope <hi>Roge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> and <hi>Roulandus,</hi> of the schole of <hi>Mompilor,</hi> and Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians vnto the King of Fraunce, <hi>Rose Anglus, Gilbertus Anglus, Hugo Wiklefe, Anglus,</hi> of the schoole of <hi>Cambridge, Theodoricus,</hi> and <hi>Brunus,</hi> of the schoole of <hi>Bonane, Arnol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus de villa noua,</hi> and <hi>Plasentinus,</hi> of the schoole of <hi>Mompi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lior, Petrus de Argilat,</hi> and <hi>Gordonus:</hi> all these dyd write of the Arte of Medicine, about two or thrée hundred yeres since, and all these builded their foundation, and tooke their originall, of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> and nowe in our tyme, there hath bene famous writers, as <hi>Iohannes Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, Antonius Muse, Antonious Gallus, Nicolaus Masse, Iohannes Baptista Montanus, Iacobus Siluius, Alfonsius Ferrey, Hollerius, Leonardus Fuchius, Iohannes Tagaltius, Gabrielus Falopius, Rioldus Columnus, Antonius Calmisius Vassalius, Ioh. Fernelius, Amatus Lucitanus, Frāciscus Valleri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>olus,
<pb facs="13"/> Ieronimus Cardanus, Matthiolus,</hi> and a great many more, of learned men, who we will passe ouer, the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of tyme.</p>
   <p>All these which I haue spoken of, of what Countrie so euer they were, they tooke their originall and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, of our Father <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> although they haue founde out many thinges, appertaining to the Arte of Medicine, which we finde no mention made of, neither in <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> nor in <hi>Galen,</hi> yet they had their foundation from them, and all these men, of what coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie so euer they were, they haue dronke of the water, that flowed out of their two welles, and doe greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce therein, and who that list to reade their workes, may perceiue the truth thereof.</p>
   <p>Now my friendes, to tell you the truth, in my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, what was the cause of these mennes writinges, I take it to be chiefely, to sette forth the glory of God, in his wonderfull creatures and workes, as touching their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, qualities, and properties, which doth appertaine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this artist, which doth vse the Arte of Medicine, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider vppon, for all maner of thinges, vnder Heauen, doe serue either for mannes nourishment, or else for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of his bodie, or else for necessarie remedies in the time of sicknesse, or else for preseruatiues, to kepe him from sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and to preserue health. So carefull was the highe and mightie Lorde God, for his creature, man, that he made all these thinges, to serue his vse, as necessarie helpes, in the time of his necessitie, and placed him in the place of ioye, with great solemnitie. But alas, his frayle nature, was the cause of his sodaine ouerthrowe, from ioye to so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, from pleasure, to paine, from rest and quietnesse, to perpetuall labour and vnquietnesse, from a most tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Ayre, and pleasant place, into a miserable worlde, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with innumerable contrarie ayres, and chaunge of windes.</p>
   <p>Yea, I saye, euen from the place of health, into the worlde of sicknesse and miserie: where our bodies be altered, and weakened, euerie daye, by mixing together,
<pb n="7" facs="13"/> of contrary Elements, and we being subiect to the same, are dayly tormented, with innumerable diseases. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Adam,</hi> at the first creation, was indued with most excellent wisedome, and knowledge, by the power &amp; might, of the Lorde God, so that he dyd know all things, that were vpon the face of the earth, in the waters, and déepe partes thereof, not onely their qualities, and properties, but their substanciall formes, and figures, and gaue them names, as he himselfe thought good, for he had perfect knowledge of all thinges, by the deuine spirit of God, which dyd worke in him, according to his first creation: but when he had sinned against the Lord God, then was taken from him his diuine knowledge, and lefte here in this world, bare and naked, to take paines, and studie for all those things, that he would receiue commoditie of.</p>
   <p>Now man, as I sayde before, being wrapped about with innumerable sicknesses, diseases, and sodaine chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which bée subiect to the arte of Medicine, which Arte, I call the arte of curing and healing, was constrained to séeke for remedies, in the tyme of his necessitie. And sought out Herbes, Rootes, and manye other thinges, to helpe his diseases, and griefe withall, and by vse and longe time of practising, they dyd finde out the natures, and properties of many thinges, wherewithall, some tymes they dyd good, but by chaunce, for they obserued, neither the natures of bodyes, nor their temperatures, nor the disease, neither yet the causes thereof, but onely regarded those thinges which they dyd sée and féele.</p>
   <p>Thus farre wyde was man, from that excellent know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which was geuen him in the beeginning, for in the beginning, he was not onely indued with most beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but also with most excellent giftes of knowledge and wisedome.</p>
   <p>All other creatures, besides man, which hath not sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned against the LORD GOD, but followed the nature of their first creation, all these wée sée by experience, haue a certaine deuine nature in them, which man lacketh, for man dyd lose it through sinne, which these creatures haue
<pb facs="14"/> not done, and for the proofe héereof, we will begin with the dog, which being sicke, séeketh for a certaine grasse, &amp; eateth thereof, and with the same cureth his griefe and disease: Onelie a diuine nature teacheth him this, without anie studie. The Squirrell also prouideth her selfe nuts against Winter. The little Ant or Pismere doth gather séeds into the ground, and biteth them in the end, after such a cunning sort, that they may not grow. The Storke also being grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued or anoyed with anie vncleane thing that she hath ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, flyeth to the sea, and giueth her selfe a clister with salt water, ministring it with her bill at her neather end, by meanes whereof she purgeth and cleanseth her selfe of her griefe and sicknesse. Thus may you perceiue the diuine and wonderfull workes of almightie God, working in his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures by a diuine nature, but man lacking this diuine knowledge, and lefte onelie to reason and Experience, is constrained by greate studie to bring to passe those thinges which by imperfection of Nature dooth lacke in him: By meanes wherof, all these most worthie men afore said haue put in writing manie worthie Bookes of this arte, which arte they haue obtained by greate studie and experience, and by a reasonable method or waie, haue taught the same vnto others, not onelie to that end, that the glorie of God in his great and wonderfull workes, maye be the better knowen, as I haue sayde before, but also for the common wealth of their owne Countries wherein they did dwell. The Princes and subiects being wounded, hurt, or disea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, by their greate and painefull trauaile, and by theyr greate studie and most approued experiments might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored againe vnto their health, and the rest which bée in good health, might bée defended from most cruell plagues and sicknesses, by the helpe of this most worthie and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent arte. This art (I saie) is most worthie, for that it wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vppon the bodie of man, which is the most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellentest creature of all the world: and as the subiect is excellent, which the artist dooth worke vpon, it must néeds followe, that the artist must be most worthie which work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vppon so excellent a subiect.</p>
   <pb n="8" facs="14"/>
   <p>And furthermore, to prooue this art to bée most excellent, and most of all other to be had in honour and reuerence, I proue it by the saying of Saint <hi>Paule, That some men had the gift of wisedome, some of prophesying, and some of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling:</hi> and Saint <hi>Paule</hi> saith, <hi>That these were done by the spirit of God,</hi> that is to saie, by the holie Ghost. Therefore <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> hauing the spirit of wisedome and of the art of Medicine, most abundantlie poured into them, dyd excell all men before their times, and set forth this art so perfectlie and exactlie by the power and vertue of the same spirite, that all the vniuersall worlde hath receiued such commoditie by them, that their most excellent fame shall indure to the worlds end. All other men being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with the same spirit, and with the examples of them, to set foorth such knowledge as they are endued withall, for the helpe and maintenaunce of their common wealth, and for the reliefe and comfort of the diseased subiectes, haue bene from time to time mooued with the spirite of God, to write manie volumes of bookes to their posteritie, wherein they haue taught them the methodes of waies of curing, not onelie of grieuous wounds, great Apostumes, vlcers, fractured bones, and dislocations, but of all other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities and diseases, that chaunceth vnto the bodie of man, with their proper signes and tokens, to iudge them by their natures &amp; properties, their distemperatures, with their names and most exact diuisions, to that end that they maye bée more rightlie vnderstanded, iudged, and apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie cured.</p>
   <p>Héere may a question arise, what this arte of medicine is, and what you call him that vseth the same, for many men suppose that he is properlie named a Physition, and other some supposeth that hée shoulde bée called a Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion, by meanes wherof in times past ther hath growen some contention as perteining to the Instruments proper vnto the said arte of curing, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to saie, the vse of the hand, called <hi>Chirurgia,</hi> conuenient diet, named <hi>Dieta,</hi> and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>string of conuenient medicaments, named <hi>Phermacon.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For answere therof I haue told you my opinion before, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
      <pb facs="15"/> in the beginning the Artist was called <hi>Iatros,</hi> amongst the Grecians, and amongst the Latinists, <hi>Medicus,</hi> and in our Countrie, in our auncient tongue, he was called a Léech: which thrée wordes, that is to saie, <hi>Iatros, Medicus,</hi> &amp; Léech, signified no other thing but to cure, that is, a curer of disea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, sicknesse, and sores, wherewith mans bodie is grieued. Now, these diseases cannot be cured without cōuenient in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments, which instruments are first &amp; chieflie the hands of man, that doth make readie conuenient nourishment or medicines, and ministreth the same vnto the sicke man, or else commaundeth the same to be ministred in conuenient order. The second is diet, which is a speciall instrument, as well for the curation of Wounds, Apostumes, Vlcerations and tumours against nature, as for all other diseases which chaunceth vnto mans bodie: Both <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen</hi> doth prescribe proper diet for wounds, according to the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature of the bodie, according to the nature of the woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded part, and according to the nature of the accidents that may be ioyned with the same wound.</p>
   <p>In like manner <hi>Galen</hi> prescribeth a diet for those that hath vlcerations, not onelie in Cancers, but also in many other kinde of vlcers, which may neither be conuenientlie cured, neither yet preserued in good state, without conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent diet, and as for tumors against nature, they require no lesse helpe of diet than the residue: for it is a generall rule that we first take indication of the nature of the disease which we entend to cure, and of the effects of the same. As for example, in <hi>Phlegmon,</hi> which is an inflammation in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendered of bloud, for of nature <hi>Phlegmon</hi> is hot and moist, but his affect is to make inflammation, not onelie in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> part where it is aggregated, but by consent and affinitie, which the grieued member hath with the rest of the bodie, it doth often times moue a Feauer, which might grieue and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble all the bodie, and cause the inflammation to be more vehement in the grieued part. Therefore the Artist ought chiefelie to prouide for this mischiefe, and there is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter waie to resist the same, than by giuing of conuenient diet, which must be colde and drie, contrarie to the nature
<pb n="9" facs="15"/> of the disease which commeth of bloud, being hot and moist, for these be generall rules, taught both of <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> that euerie disease with his affects, bée cured with his contrarie.</p>
   <p>Thus I thinke, there is no reasonable man that will denie this instrument to appertaine chiefelie to the arte of <hi>Chirurgia,</hi> for reason doth approue and allowe it, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience doeth finde it most necessarie and true: Therfore I must saie, as <hi>Galen</hi> saith in his third booke <hi>Methodo Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendi,</hi> All artes are grounded vpon reason and experience, neither is there anie third thing to be added therevnto: If anie man can shew me how we may cure vlcers, tumors, and other things appertaining to the art of Surgerie, by a third waie, and with other instruments than these worthie men haue found out by reason and experience, then I will giue place, and be glad to learne it, and if I finde the same to be more profitable &amp; commodious for the common wealth and for the grieued persons, I wil not onelie endeuour my selfe to learne it, but also to followe it, extoll it, and teach it vnto other, but if no man can shew me anie other waie than reason ought to teach him, to suffer me to restore my sicke Patient to health, by the permission of God, with those instrumentes that bée most necessarie and proper for mine Arte.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, as concerning <hi>Pharmacon,</hi> which is called <hi>Medicamentum</hi> or Medicine, I thinke there be no men ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, no not so much as those that be vtterlie vnlearned, but that they knowe that medicine is an instrument to helpe to cure diseases and sicknesses withall, for who can cure a wound, a tumour against nature, or an vlcer, onelie with his handes without medicine, I thinke there is no man that is so ignorant or stupidious, that thinketh that to be true, then of necessitie it must followe, that these bée thrée instrumentes, and not thrée partes of medicine, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie men haue misconstrued both <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> both contrarie to reason and true experience, for the hands alone cannot cure without Medicine, neither can the medicines bée ministred without handes, neither yet can
<pb facs="16"/> anie man take meat or drinke, except it be ministred with the hand, then of necessitie it must followe, that these thrée cannot bée diuided, forasmuch as one is holpen by another, and the desired health brought to an end by all these thrée, and not by anie one of these alone, as <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> dyd right well prooue, in confuting of certaine sectes that were in his time, as <hi>Tragus</hi> dooth make mention by the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of that noble King <hi>Democrates,</hi> affirming that there were certaine sectes, which then dyd vse the arte of curing, some by inward medicine onelie, which they did purge the bodie withall, and some by dyet onelie, which they did vse, as it séemed vnto them good, and some by mininstring of outward medicines, to such partes of the bodie as they thought good. And euerie one of these did affirme that they would restore mannes bodie to health, what disease so euer it were affected withall, if that the saide disease were cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, onelie with one of these thrée wayes, and that the other two were superfluous, and néede not to bée vsed. By meanes whereof there did growe greate contention, and great disputation was had therein, and in conclusion they did séeme to confound all thrée partes, each of them thus confuting other.</p>
   <p>Then <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> hearing of this great contention a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongest them, they all thrée professing the curatiue parte of the Arte of Medicine, sent for them, and appointed vnto them certaine men to cure, and asked them in what space they would cure the same persons, and they appointed a certaine time, and <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> gaue them foure times so long space: Then euerie one of them with great diligence according to his owne sect and waie dyd minister. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the Patients were not made whole, so that they were constrained to leaue them vncured, when they coulde doe no more. When <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> sawe their doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges, howe farre wide it was from a reasonable methode, yet how ingenious and wittie they were in deuising and inuenting of medicines to bring their purpose to passe, hée did not a little meruaile.</p>
   <p>Then with curteous wordes he perswaded them to
<pb n="10" facs="16"/> leaue off their precisenesse and seuere sectes, and to vse a generall methode, wherein all those thrée were ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and to vse euerie one of these in his conuenient time and place, each one of them to helpe other, and then ther was no doubt but with their excellent inuentions, they would cure wonderfull griefes and diseases, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise could not bée brought to passe.</p>
   <p>Nowe when <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> had made these thrée men friendes, hée required them to goe with him to their sicke and grieued Patients, and sayde vnto them: That with the same medicines which they had ministred before, by the permission of the immortall Gods hée would make all their thrée Patients whole. So <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> ministring no other dyet, but such a diet, as hée that ministred the dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et had vsed before, neither yet anie other purging medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, than he that vsed to cure with purging medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments had vsed before, nor yet anie other plaisters or oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, than hée that vsed to cure with plaisters and oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes had vsed before, euen with the same medicines that they did vse, by vsing of them in conuenient time and place methodicallie, did cure all their sicke Patients: By meanes whereof they were perswaded to followe his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, and to vse these as common and generall instruments for the arte of curing, and all they to be exhibited and vsed with the hand.</p>
   <p>Thus it doeth appeare by <hi>Hyppocrates,</hi> that none of these may be absent from him that vseth the arte of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Galen</hi> also as concerning purging medicaments, where hée intreateth of the same, sayth, they bée verie profitable, yea, and also most necessarie in the curing of Cancers, olde, stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne, and rebellious vlcers, and also in Herpis, Herisipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>And these purging medicines were chiefelie inuented and found out by experimentes, wherewithall they dyd purge and drawe awaye these vicious and euill hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, which was the maintaining cause of all those Vlcers and grieued partes, as it is afore sayde,
<pb facs="17"/> which other wayes could not haue béene cured: <hi>Galen</hi> also in his fourth booke <hi>De Methodo Medendi,</hi> by the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Hyppocrates,</hi> doeth saie thus, That Purgations of the bellie is profitable to manie vlcers, and also to woundes of the head, of the bellie, and of the ioyntes, and where there is daunger of corruption of the bones, or where stitching behooueth in woundes or where <hi>Erosians</hi> be, or where Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis, and other affectes bée, which hindereth the curation of Vlcers, and also where rollinges must bée vsed.</p>
   <p>By these wordes it is apparant truelie, that Purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are profitable both to woundes and vlcers, at all times, when they bée greate and grieuous, I meane not onelie Purgations ministred by the vpper partes, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so Purgations ministred by the neather parts, as Clisters, and such like.</p>
   <p>Thus I doe conclude, that these thrée Instruments are most necessarie for those men that shall cure hurts, griefes, and diseases, and in no case maye bée separated or taken from them: For lyke as the Carpenter &amp; shipwright must of necessitie vse lyke instrumentes to finish and bring to passe their worke withall: euen so must the Artists in this arte, by what name so euer you will call them, haue and vse conuenient Instrumentes to bring to passe the desired health, which is the end of this art. If the Carpenter should saie vnto the Shipwright, thou maist not vse the Axe, the Saw, the pearcer, nor yet the hammer, for that they be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per instruments for my arte, then the shipwright might aunswere him and saie, they be proper for my Arte also, and without those instruments I cannot build my shippe, nor bring to passe the desired end of my Arte. Euen in lyke manner it may be sayde in the Arte of medicine, for whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be called by the name of a Phisition, or by the name of a Chirurgion, of by the name or a Léech, or by what other name you wil cal him, if ye wil admit him to cure wounds, Tumours against Nature, vlcers, or what diseases so euer they be, it is necessarie that hée haue his proper Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes apt and méete, to bring the same to passe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. But if wée shall stand vppon the names of the Arte,
<pb n="11" facs="17"/> and confound the instruments, then shal we séeme to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a vaine disputation, and spend time about those names, which are to small purpose, for the name is not the thing that doth cure, but the arte, béeing methodicallie and rightlie ministred. For <hi>Galen</hi> in his third and fourth booke, <hi>De Methodo Medendi,</hi> doth name him <hi>Medicus,</hi> that dooth cure vlcers and woundes, therefore it séemeth to mée that <hi>Mtdicus</hi> and <hi>Chyrurgus</hi> bée indifferent names for those that professeth the arte of curing, and for anie thing that I can perceiue, either by the wordes of <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> or <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> or by anie other notorious and famous writers that haue written in this arte: The Chirurgions ought not to bée forbidden neither the ministring of purgations, nor yet of dyet, for as much as they be their chiefe and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall instruments, without which they cannot bring to passe their desired scope of health: And if we shall speake of the antiquitie of names, I suppose the name of <hi>Chirurgia</hi> to be much more auncient than the name of Phisicke, for I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose Phisicke to be deriued of <hi>Phisilogia,</hi> which worde doth signifie, naturall knowledge of mannes bodie, and of all the partes and members of the same, &amp;c. And <hi>Chirurgia</hi> is deriued of <hi>Chiro,</hi> which is a hand, or as we might saie, a ministration of Medicamentes, done with the hand, vnto mannes bodie, onelie by experience. So that all those that were before the time of <hi>Hyppocrates,</hi> were accounted but as experimenters, and to followe an arte without a right methode, which that noble man <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> perceiuing, dyd lyke a most famous Philosopher, according to reason, ioyne together all these vnperfect sects, which were in his dayes verie manie, and taught them one perfect and true waie, methodicallie to worke, and also certaine rules howe they shoulde learne the same arte, and diuided it into fiue speciall partes, as we shall declare héereafter, which partes béeing perfectlie vnderstanded, is the right waie to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede to the curation of mannes bodie, and without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of these fiue partes, no man can methodicallie and rightlie cure anie Vlcers, Woundes, Apostumes, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other diseases, as wée haue sayde before, for whosoeuer
<pb facs="18"/> taketh vpon them, hauing not knowledge of these, he may be called a practiser, and experimenter, or an emperike, as the most parte of our Chirurgions may be called, that bée not learned in these partes, and doth worke onelie by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience without reason, but those y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> vnderstand these partes, and followeth a methode in their curing, whether they doe cure Wounds, Tumours against nature, Apostumes, Vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, or what other thinges so euer it bée, that doeth apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the arte of curing, that same Artist may be called <hi>Medicus, a Medendo,</hi> that is to saie, of curing, for so doeth <hi>Galen</hi> name him in his third and fourth booke <hi>De Metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do Medendi,</hi> according to the translation of that learned man <hi>Linaker.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And forasmuch as ye shall the better credit the worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of this arte of Chirurgerie, as well for the antiquitie thereof, as for the Instruments appertaining to the Artist, I haue héere set forth before your eies an Epistle made by <hi>Franciscus Valleriolus,</hi> in the commendations of the arte of Chirurgerie, which <hi>Valleriolus</hi> is one of the most notable learned men in the arte of medicine that is nowe liuing, whose wordes héereafter followeth.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>