<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Post-script to the Reader</title>
           <author>D., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117096_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69170</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6176</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117096</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Post-script to the Reader</title>
                 <author>D., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Salomons pest-house, or tovvre-royall : Nevvly re-edified and prepared to preserue Londoners with their families, and others, from the doubted deluge of the plague. Item, a laudable exercise for those that are departed, or shall depart out of the city into the country, to spend their time till they returne. A handfull of holy meditations vsefull and requisite for Gods people ... By the reuerend, learned, and godly diuine I.D. preacher of Gods word. Whereunto is added Mr Hollands admonition, and Mr Phaers prescription for bodily physicke. Also, London looke-backe: a description or representation of the great and memorable mortality an. 1625. in heroicke matchlesse lines, by A.H. of Tr. Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>I. D., preacher of Gods word</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sparke (Sparkes, Wreichionen), Michael 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 69, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="postscript">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>A Post-script to the Reader</head>
   <p>SInce God began this yeere, his Visitation, and to shake his Rod of the Pestilence ouer vs, I haue obserued an errour among the sonnes of men, <hi>viz.</hi> They haue beene and are very diligent in enquiring after the weekly Bils of mortality, and they that could first obtaine the Bill from their Parish Clarks, haue acknowledged to be most beholden vnto them: and I will not simply condemne this their diligence: But come we to enquire what vse they haue made of this their double diligence and prime-intelligence: If they haue found an <hi>increase</hi> of the number, haue they humbled themselues in Prayer, endeauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to depart from their sinnes, &amp; to trauaile to this Towre-Royall, in the sequell, for safetie? Surely no, few or none haue so done: the <hi>increase</hi> happ'ly hath deiected them, made them murmure, and proiect to flee to their Country-houses here or there, and peraduenture to send beforehand their Wiues, Children, and Houshold-stuffe: yea, very carefull they haue been, &amp; are for this their bodily safegard. Againe, on the other side, if they haue seene by the Bill a <hi>decrease</hi> in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; how many, nay how few haue returned to God by the way of thankfulnesse for such his great mercy &amp; forbearance? I feare, and it appeares, that rather they haue beene thereby encouraged to goe on in security, if not in sensualitie. I may say therefore with the Authour and Founder of our Towre-Royall. <hi>This is (also) an euill vnder the Sun,</hi> committed by the sonnes of men; Of whom I my selfe being one, &amp; ingenuously confessing. I cannot free my selfe from being tainted with the Infection of this <hi>euill,</hi> will say no more: but doe humbly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore for my selfe, and all the Israel of God, more wise, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, concrite and thankefull hearts, in obseruing his workes: <hi>Open thou my lips,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 51.15. Psal. 119.18.</note>
      <hi>O Lord, that my mouth may shew forth thy praise.</hi> And <hi>open mine eyes that I may see the wonders of thy workes.</hi> Iterum in Christo vale.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>I. D.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>