<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the friendly Reader.</title>
           <author>B., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1570</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117934_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13115</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23408</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117934</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the friendly Reader.</title>
                 <author>B., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A ritch storehouse or treasurie for nobilitye and gentlemen, which in Latine is called Nobilitas literata, written by a famous and excellent man, Iohn Sturmius, and translated into English by T.B. Gent. Seene and allowed according to the order appointed</title>
                 <author>Sturm, Johannes</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1570</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 40, 33-48 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>❧ To the friendly <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Earned and most friendlye Reader: if Bookes gaine credite or discredite by their translators, I maye iustly feare that this worthy worke by my euill handling shall be disgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and be but of small account with thee. But syth that works be not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted good, neyther are they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned as bad for their translators or reporters, but be praised for their excellencie &amp; goodnesse, or condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for their basenesse and naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. I mooue not thee to lyke thys treatise, bicause I interpreted it, but I beseeche thee to allowe it for the goodnesse and excellent matter, plentifully flowing therein. But our time (alas) is so inclined, and as it
<pb facs="4"/>were naturally bent to bestow vpon barren and vnhonest fruites, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and golden names, that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can vertuous and prayse wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy workes enioye their due and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued tytles, being forestauled and defrauded by the euill, neyther good deedes possesse their owne, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy termes being preuented by the meane. And now men rather labor to declare howe muche they can: then, what and howe much they ought to saye: yeelding themselues sooner subiectes and bondslaues to their lawlesse lustes, than truly pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishinge their vpryght iudgements, and to vtter rather in vnseasonable time painted wordes and smooth Rhetoricke, than matter good and precious, so that neyther the condici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the cause, whether it be good or badde, can moue them to saye ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more or lesse. For if the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie
<pb facs="4"/>of this small Treatise, eyther for the golden preceptes herein, the lyke whereof hath neuer earst bene taught by any, eyther for the profite hereby to thee (gentle Reader) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing shoulde with deserued com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation bee rewarded: I of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie must eyther coyne newe wordes, the auncient already being employed on lewde and peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture wicked matters, or wishe that the vulgar speache of commending might bee kept vntill some worthye matters were inuented, whereon wel and happily to bestow it. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hauing no plentie of goodlye wordes, I am enforced to keepe my iudgement to my selfe, beseeching thee to giue vnto the worthynesse of the matter due and deserued ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor. Thus doing, thou shalt not only encourage me hereafter to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture the translating of some lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb facs="5"/>matter, but in the meane time giue me iust cause to thinke my tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyle herein to bee verie well em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed: wishing that it may yeelde thee, semblable profite, that wilte vouchsafe to reade it, as it did plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to mee, that tooke the paynes to translate it: and thus as thy friend I bid thee fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, and wish thee happily to doe.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>By T.B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>