<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the noble Reader.</title>
           <author>S., A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117763_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12817</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23125</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117763</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the noble Reader.</title>
                 <author>S., A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Honour and vertue, triumphing over the grave : Exemplified in a faire devout life, and death, adorned with the surviving perfections of Edward Lord Stafford, lately deceased; the last baron of that illustrious family: which honour in him ended with as great lustre as the sunne sets within a serene skye. A treatise so written, that it is as well applicative to all of noble extraction, as to him, and wherein are handled all the requisites of honour, together with the greatest morall, and divine vertues, and commended to the practise of the noble prudent reader. By Anth. Stafford his most humble kinsman. This worke is much embelish'd by the addition of many most elegant elegies penned by the most accute wits of these times</title>
                 <author>Stafford, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Cotes, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Seile (Seale, Seely, Seyle), Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 88, 91-92, 44 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>To the noble Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath beene the manner of Ancient Times to commend their Dead, rather to testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie a good affection, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile their losse, and to hold out the Lampe of their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Lives to others left behind, then to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the deceased. Thus <hi>David</hi> commended <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Abner, Elizaeus Elias,</hi> and <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen Bazill; Ber</hi> bewailed <hi>Malachie,</hi> complaining that his very bowels were pulled from him. And J may truly averre that Death tore out my Heart, when hee bereft me of that sweetest Lord, of whose rare Gifts and Graces this ensuing Discourse is composed. That I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd till now to doe him this right, and to administer comfort to his vertuous Mother, and the rest of his Noble and deare Friends,
<pb facs="9"/>
(who still keepe warme his Ashes with their Teares) was for a wise consideration, no base neglect. A green wound abhorres the hand of the Surgeon, which after it patiently endures, nay, longingly expects: Jn like case, the Griefs of the minde, being newly entred, are not easily expelled, but at first reiect all consolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on given them; whereas afterward they become obedient to Reason, and readily admit of those Remedies, which at first they refused. There are so many reasons comprehended in this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Treatise, why his Friends should not grieve too immoderately for him, that I will onely here adde this, that they should not too violently lament his departure out of a World where Vice is naturall, Vertue but counterfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or at the best well acted. Here wee disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her, but through a Cloud. Let them apply that usuall saying of the Rabbies to their sad soules, <hi>The godly even in their Death are alive, but the wicked in their Life are dead;</hi> Jf a Heathen could boldly averre, <hi>Nunc</hi> Epaminondas <hi>vester nascitur quia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sic moritur: In so dying your</hi> Epaminon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das <hi>is now reborne,</hi> may not we with greater
<pb facs="9"/>
confidence affirme the same of him?</p>
   <p>Thus much of the excellent subiect, now to the Worke it selfe. Jn this Age (fertile in <hi>Coriats,</hi> barren of <hi>Sydneys</hi> and <hi>Raleighs.)</hi> that Booke must come into the World with a good Angell to defend it that escapes the severe censures of malevolent spirits, with whom it is a wicked custome to damne by Tradition, and traduce Authours before they peruse them. As Cankers commonly cleave to those Roses which are best grown, and spread: So these envious Detractours commonly fasten their venem<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>us Teeth on Works, to which Fame promiseth E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie. This ought not to deterre Good and Knowing Men from publishing their Labours; who herein should imitate the Sunne, which (though the Atheist, and the Jmpious, are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of his Light) shines forth still, and with his Beames glads the Earth, and all the Movers on it. The onely Recompence J desire of my ingenious Readers is, that they would vouchsafe not to reade this Treatise out, but that they would be pleased in imitation of the <hi>Sortes Virgilianae</hi> to take the <hi>Staffordian Lot,</hi> that is, to practise in their lives the first
<pb facs="10"/>
Page Chance shall direct them to, in the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it; since there is not one in this Worke which containes not some lovely Vertue or other of that deare Lord deceased: by enlarging of whose Fame, J have taken the Advantage to render my owne lesse obscure. This small favour J hope my Noble Readers will not denie their Servant,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>A. S.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>