<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Spenser, Edmund</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1586</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117423_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03718</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13843.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117423</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Spenser, Edmund</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The brutish thunderbolt: or rather feeble fier-flash of Pope Sixtus the fift, against Henrie the most excellent King of Nauarre, and the most noble Henrie Borbon, Prince of Condie : Togither with a declaration of the manifold insufficiencie of the same. Translated out of Latin into English by Christopher Fetherstone minister of Gods word</title>
                 <author>Hotman, François</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hatfield, Arnold</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1586</date>
                 <distributor>Bishop, George</distributor>
                            <distributor>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 321, 15 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, my onely drift and purpose in translating this Treatise, was, to acquaint my countriemen, who are not skilfull in the Latine toong, with such papall practises as are heerin described. The title wherof being in the Latin copie, BRVTVM FVLMEN, I was first of opinion that I might well english it, THE BRV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TISH THVNDERBOLT. But when I remembred with my selfe that words are no otherwise currant than as they are allowed by vse; and the philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher giueth good aduise when he saith, <hi>Loquendum</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Arist. Top.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>cum vulgo, sentiendum cum sapientibus:</hi> Our speech must be such as is commonly vsed, howsoeuer our thoughts be the thoughts of the wiser sort; and it hath not bin lawfull for the emperors themselues to giue as it were freedome of citie to words in Rome, when they might enfranchise what persons they listed without controlement: I would not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture to be the first coiner of so strange a terme (strange indeed in respect of that sense to which it was to be applied) without better warrant, than I haue anie; and therefore I haue expressed the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors meaning in some other maner, thus, THE FEEBLE FIER-FLASH that is <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Bruta fulmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na &amp; vana, vt quae nulla ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niant ratione naturae. Plin. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 43.</note> dull of force, vaine, and whereof no sufficient cause can be giuen in reason. For such now a daies (who knoweth not?) are those ordinarie anathematicall lightenings that breake foorth from the see of Rome, as the Poet in his <hi>Aeneis</hi> attributeth to king Salmoneus, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Virgil. Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neid.</hi> 6.</note> which may happely amaze and seduce the harts of them that haue bin all their liues long noosled vp in superstition &amp; error: but as manie as God hath
<pb facs="6"/> enabled by his grace to trie spirits, they make no more reckoning of such foolish flames, than they that walke in the night do account of that fire which is commonly called <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> by which no wise man would suffer himselfe to be misled. For the rest: I submit all my trauell to thy gentle and curteous inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="4 letters">
         <desc>••••</desc>
      </gap>on. I haue done what I might, seeing what I would, I could not, by reason of sicknes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> vpon me. In which respect, I shall the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> pardon for those sundrie ouersights which haue escaped me, for want of suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient conference with my friends. Onely I praie thee, let not the tedious narrations of Dominick and Francis setdowne almost in the first entrance, keepe thee backe from wading through the whole worke. No doubt, but the author himselfe was halfe ashamed to make recitall of such grosse stuffe, and absurd follies, sauing that he had good reason to do that he did, partly in respect of the present Pope, and partly bicause such beastly vanities are highly esteemed in the church of Rome. I confesse that the Iesuits are not altogither so palpablie grosse in outward shew, (howbeit, he that listeth to take a taste of their extreem impudencie in lying, may read <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>To which Melch. Canus applieth their common coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie prouerbe,</hi> De luengas vias, luengas mentiras.</note> their letters written from <hi>Iapan,</hi> and the <hi>Indies,</hi> with many other reports set downe in the life of their father <hi>Ignatius Lay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> full of like vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.) They haue learned to lay fairer colors on their filthie corruptions to dazell the eies of the simple and ignorant. But remooue those colours, and they will quickly appeere to be birds of the same nest. Their first Founder was neuer yet of greater name and fame, than Dominic &amp; holie S. Francis. Their doctrine, vowes, rules, &amp; profession, either the same in substance, or not very much differing. The other
<pb facs="6"/> had their time of florishing in the world, and so must these haue likewise, till they returne backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to the bottomles pit, out of the smoke wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they ascended, <hi>(Reuel.</hi> 9. 2. 3.) to giue place (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture) to some other new vpstart progenie of Locusts, by whom the light of their credit also shal be obscured &amp; quite extinguished. The Lord make vs thankfull for all his mercies towards vs, and either conuert or confound the enimies of his euerlasting truth.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy brother in Christ Christoph. Fetherstone.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>