<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHOR TO the godly Readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117489_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20606</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7005</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117489</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHOR TO the godly Readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The rockes of Christian shipwracke, discouered by the holy Church of Christ to her beloued children, that they may keepe aloofe from them. Written in Italian by the most reuerend father, Marc Ant. de Dominis, Archb. of Spalato, and thereout translated into English</title>
                 <author>De Dominis, Marco Antonio</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bill, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 171, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>THE AVTHOR TO the godly Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et this Manuell, Christian Readers, serue you onely for an essay, or rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draught of a larger worke, wherein the same Heads, which are here but briefly pointed at, as also other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters bordering thereon, are to be more particularly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted, and commodiously enlarged. And I hope, that I shall let in so much light vnto you, that you shall by God's grace be enabled to enterteine many trueths belonging to your soules health, which for long time haue bene, with no good meaning, kept out of your sight. If you please to accept these my first lineaments, you may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from me the more diligent accomplishment of the entire worke: wherein will appeare other Rockes also worthy the discouering, to the praise of our Sauiour</hi> IESVS CHRIST, <hi>to the safety of our soules, and to the confusion of the Diuell. God be with you euermore.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>