<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Peter Turner to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1568</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117784_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14059</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24367</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117784</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Peter Turner to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first and seconde partes of the herbal of William Turner Doctor in Phisick : lately ouersene, corrected and enlarged with the thirde parte, lately gathered, and nowe set oute with the names of the herbes, in Greke Latin, English, Duche, Frenche, and in the apothecarie and herbaries Latin, with the properties, degrees, and naturall places of the same. Here vnto is ioyned also a booke of the bath of Baeth in England, and of the vertues of the same with diuerse other bathes, moste holsom and effectuall, both in Almanye and England, set furth by William Turner Doctor in Phisick. God saue the Quene</title>
                 <author>Turner, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Birckman, Arnold 1, Heirs of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Cologne</pubPlace>
                    <date>1568</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 40, 37-223, 5 pages, 2, 132, 131-148, 151-171, 3 leaves, 10, 81, 3 pages, 4, 17, 1 leave, illustrations (woodcuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>Peter Turner to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the wyse Philosopher <hi>Seneca,</hi> counteth him to slay or kill, that may well saue and will not: so may I rightly iudge after the same fashion, that he is a great hindrer and hurter that may profite a man and will not. Seeing then that this my fathers Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball, which he after his long trauell, study and experience hath made, is now set forth to profit and pleasure his countrimen withall: and by the ouersight partly of the Printer, and partly of the Scribe that copied the booke out for the Printer, is now so commed forth that the Reader can not get any profite or commoditie thereof: least that I for the cause aboue rehersed bee counted a hinderer of the profite of my Countriemen, and not to set by my Fathers fame and estimation (for I am sure, many that know not that afore his death he went about to correct this booke, will blame him for letting so falsly a printed booke to come forth) I haue taken some paynes, and haue pervsed and red ouer this booke as my Father beganne, and haue conferred it with his owne hande copie, and haue so corrected it and amended it, that a diligent and a welwilling reader may easily vnderstand the meaning of the writer, and so take great profit of the same. But peraduenture some will saye, if I had minded to pleasure my Countriemen, I might haue done better if I had cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in or stayed this print, and caused the booke to haue bene printed here anew again. In dede if I had done so, I should haue eased the reader of this labour of correcting. But I should haue done against Charitie to haue caused the Printer by that meanes to lese all his labor and cost which he hath bestowed in printing hereof. Wherfore gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Reader beare a little with the Printer that neuer was much accustomed to the printing of Englishe, and afore thou reade ouer this booke, correct it as I haue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and then the profite thereof will aboundantly recompence thy paynes. And last of all, take these my paynes also in good worth at this time. Another daye when this Herball shall be printed againe (and if it please God to lend me lyfe and health, augmented and increased) I trust the reader shalbe put to no such paines in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting of the same, as in no other of my fathers bookes as yet vnprinted which hereafter as time and occasion shall serue, I entende to set forth. In the meane time vse this Herball in stede of a better, and giue all laude and prayse vnto the Lorde.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>