<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Grimeston, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117097_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11931</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22244</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117097</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Grimeston, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A general inuentorie of the history of France : from the beginning of that monarchie, vnto the treatie of Veruins, in the year 1598. Written by Ihon de Serres. And continued vnto these times, out off the best authors which haue written of that subiect. Translated out of French into English, by Edward Grimeston Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Serres, Jean de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ponsonby, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ponsonby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 209, 5, 1052, 26 pages, portraits (woodcuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Could not (Courteous Reader) neglect an vsuall complement, in the publishing of this worke, to recommend the worthines of the Author, and to excuse my weakenesse. To free my selfe from the imputation of Idlenesse, I vndertooke the Translation of this Historie of France, and to giue some con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent vnto such as either by their trauell abroad, or by their industrie at home, haue not attained vnto the knowledge of the Tongue, to read it in the originall. Where you may see the sundry Battailes woon by our Kings of England against the French, and the worthie exploits of the English, during their warres with France, whereby you may bee incited to the like resolutions vpon the like occasions. I doubt not, but those which haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersed most familiarly with the Histories of France, will concurre in that generall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of his writing, to be as fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> from affection and passion, as any one that euer treated of this subiect. He hath digested into one Worke whatsoeuer hath beene written by many, touching the French History, since the beginning of their Monarchie. And if he hath not dilated at large the great attempts of Strangers in France, employed ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for their Kings, or against them: he is not therefore to be blamed, nor to be held partiall, for that the subiest whereof he treats, being great, the time long, and his style short and succinct, he had vowed to note euery accident of State and Warre briefely and truely. Besides, you must consider, that he was a Frenchman: and although hee would not altogether smother and conceale those things, which might any way eclipse the glory of his Nation, least he should be taxed to haue fayled in these two excellent vertues required in an Historiographer, Truth and Integritie, without passion, yet hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily he hath reported them as sparingly as he could. The History of <hi>Iohn de Serres</hi> ends with the Treatie at Ueruins betwixt France and Spaine in the yeare <hi>1598.</hi> I haue been importuned to make the History perfect, and to continue it vnto these times, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto I haue added (for your better satisfaction) what I could extract out of <hi>Peter Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> and other late writers touching this subiect. Some perchance will challenge me of indiscretion, that I haue not translated <hi>Peter Mathew</hi> onely, being reputed so elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and learned a Writer. To them I answere first, That I found many things writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by him that were not fit to be inserted, and some things belonging vnto the Historie, related by others, whereof he makes no mention. Secondly, his style is so full, and his discourse so copious, as the worke would haue held no proportion, for that this last addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of seuen yeares must haue exceeded halfe <hi>Serres</hi> Historie. Which considerations haue made me to draw forth, what I thought most materiall for the subiect, and to leaue the rest as vnnecessarie. But now I come to my last, though not my least care, how this
<pb facs="4"/>
my labour shall be accepted, the which must vndergoe the censure of all humors. Some I doubt not, (regarding the content and profit they may reape thereby) will allow of mine endeauors, though others do but prie into it with a curious eye, to note what is defectiue, obseruing more the elegancie and choise of words, then the worthinesse of the Historie▪ But let me intreat as much kindnesse of these curious Surueyors, as a graue Senatour of Rome did of one of his companions, who had found him playing in his garden with his yong sonne. The Father somewhat abashed to see himselfe so surprised, requested his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Senatour not to publish his folly vntill he had a yong Sonne. Euen so I intreat them, not to detract nor to maligne that which is well meant, vntill they haue produced the like. Concluding with the Poet, <hi>Carpere vel noli nostra, vel ede tua.</hi> I must craue your patience in regard of the Presse, intreating you to supply with your iudicious reading such errors as you shall find committed: For that I my selfe could not attend it, being drawne away about other imployments. And so referring all to your kind acceptance, I rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours,</hi> Edward Grimestone.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>