<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Hart, </author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117569_Fr3_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12473</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22798</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117569</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Hart, </author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Essex doue, presenting the vvorld vvith a fevv of her oliue branches: or, A taste of the workes of that reuerend, faithfull, iudicious, learned, and holy minister of the Word, Mr. Iohn Smith, late preacher of the Word at Clauering in Essex : Deliuered in three seuerall treatises, viz. 1 His grounds of religion. 2 An exposition on the Lords Prayer. 3 A treatise of repentance</title>
                 <author>Smith, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 <publisher>Edwards, George 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Islip, Adam.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 146, 2, 142, 8, 198, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="166"/>
   <pb facs="166"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, I offer here vnto thy view a Treatise of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which I found in the stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the most worthie Author a little after his death: written in an extraordinarie small rug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged blotted coppie: which since that time with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding care and paines, was thus fitted for the publike good; hoping that thou wilt take it in good part as it is, though the exact curious hand of the Author was not to perfite it, as hee intended, if he had liued a little longer. I know the diuers Bookes already extant vpon this subiect, might haue dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged mee so, as to haue spared my paines here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: but that as diuers meates diuersly cooked and dressed, fit best diuersitie of Pala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es and queasie stomacks: So I hoped that perhaps the plaine and vnusuall handling of this Treatise, might comfort, incourage, and stirre vp some one or other, supply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="167"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="167"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="168"/>
from the storehouse and fountaine of the euer abounding Spirit, somewhat not obserued, or at least not thus cooked by any other. For which cause, and that the memorie and paines of so learned, holy, &amp; Judicious a man of God, should not be altogether buried and forgot, it hath beene thus by Gods assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance published, Let mee therefore intreate thy charitable Censure of what is done for Gods glorie and thy good, for which, I promise some other way to striue how I may best shew my selfe,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the best bonds, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. HART,</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>