<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST HONOVRABLE THE LADY MARY COVNTESSE OF Buckingham &amp;c.</title>
           <author>S., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117299_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18332</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4912</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117299</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST HONOVRABLE THE LADY MARY COVNTESSE OF Buckingham &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>S., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The life of B. Aloysius Gonzaga of the Society of Iesus : eldest sonne of Ferdinand Prince of the S.R. Empire, and Marques of Castilion. Written in Latin by the R. Fa. Virgilius Ceparius of the same society. And translated into English by R.S</title>
                 <author>Cepari, Virgilio</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 518, 10 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST HONOVRABLE THE LADY MARY COVNTESSE OF <hi>Buckingham &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAME,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>I know better with what mind, then with what words to recō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this life of <hi>B. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loysius</hi> to my Coūtrey, and principally to your HONOVR, &amp; in you to the Nobility of both sexes in this Kingdome. For if my learned Authour
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>F. Virgilius Ceparius</hi> (whome I reuerence for his piety, &amp; can sooner admire then imitate for his Eloquence) neuer satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied himselfe, in drawing this Blessed Modell to the life; what may I hope for, being but a seely Interpreter of his har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious Pen? Howsoeuer, if out of the forwardnesse of my desire to do good, I haue offered violēce to my iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I cannot but expect pardon from your HONOVR; &amp; from my Country not only pardon, but euen thanks, for so much as they may plainely see, that in respect of their profit, I haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualued my owne credit.</p>
   <p>Happily would I esteeme my selfe beggered of my reputation, if by my meanes this Blessed Cittizē of Heauen, speaking English to my Countreymen, might enrich either them, or me with any of his Vertues. And how better to accōmodate him to speake vnto them, then vnder your Honourable Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, I cannot well imagine. For wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it hath bene vsually the art of skill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Grafters, in those trees that they
<pb facs="3"/>
would haue to prosper fairely in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, and yield their fruite plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to their owners, to graft them in stocks of their owne kind (&amp; for such I take your Ladiship to be, in your affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to Blessed <hi>Aloysius,</hi> for Honour, and the prosecutiō of vertue;) most worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may I suppose, that both the humble seruice I owe vnto You in particuler, and the respect that I ought to haue to my whole Countrey in generall, exact at my handes that I dedicate this Booke vnto your HONOVR; hoping that it may both encourage and instruct you in that happy course of Vertue, which so pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perously you haue begun; and vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers your Inferiours yield those suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessefull fruits, which seriously I wish it should; who will alwayes rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours humble seruant to be commaunded. R. S.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>