<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE GHYRLOND
of the blessed Virgin
MARIE.</title>
           <author>I., B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117798_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12816</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23123</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117798</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE GHYRLOND
of the blessed Virgin
MARIE.</title>
                 <author>I., B.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The femall glory: or, The life, and death of our Blessed Lady, the holy Virgin Mary, Gods owne immaculate mother : to whose sacred memory the author dedicates these his humble endeavours. A treatise worthy the reading, and meditation of all modest women, who live under th government of vertue, and are obedient to her lawes. By Anth. Stafford, Gent</title>
                 <author>Stafford, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waterson, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>86, 249, 7 pages, illustrations (metal cuts), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="garland">
   <pb facs="22"/>
   <head>THE GHYRLOND
of the blessed Virgin
MARIE.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere, are five letters in this blessed Name,</l>
      <l>Which, chang'd, a five-fold
mysterie designe,</l>
      <l>The <hi>M.</hi> the Myrtle, <hi>A.</hi> the
Almonds clame,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>R.</hi> Rose, <hi>I.</hi> Ivy, <hi>E.</hi> sweet Eglantine.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>These forme thy Ghyrlond. Wherof <hi>Myrtle</hi> green,</l>
      <l>The gladdest ground to all the numbred-five,</l>
      <l>Is so implexed, and laid in, between,</l>
      <l>As Love, here studied to keep Grace alive.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="23"/>
      <l>The second string is the sweet <hi>Almond</hi> bloome</l>
      <l>Ymounted high upon <hi>Selinis</hi> crest:</l>
      <l>As it, alone, (and onely it) had roome,</l>
      <l>To knit thy Crowne, and glorifie the rest.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The third, is from the garden call'd the <hi>Rose,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>The Eye of flowers, worthy, for his scent,</l>
      <l>To top the fairest Lillie, now, that growes,</l>
      <l>With wonder on the thorny regiment.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The fourth is humble <hi>Ivy,</hi> intersert,</l>
      <l>But lowlie laid, as on the earth asleep,</l>
      <l>Preserved, in her antique bed of <hi>Vert,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>No faith's more firme, or flat, then, where't doth creep.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But, that which summes all, is the <hi>Eglantine,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Which, of the field is clep'd the sweetest brier,</l>
      <l>Inflam'd with ardor to that mystick Shine,</l>
      <l>In <hi>Moses</hi> bush, un-wasted in the fire.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Thus, Love, and Hope, and burning Charitie,</l>
      <l>(Divinest graces) are so entermixt,</l>
      <l>With od'rous sweets and soft humilitie,</l>
      <l>As if they 'ador'd the Head, whereon th'are fixt.</l>
   </lg>
   <div type="part">
      <pb facs="23"/>
      <head>THE REVERSE
on the backe side.</head>
      <lg>
         <l>THese Mysteries do point to three more great,</l>
         <l>On the reverse of this your circling crowne,</l>
         <l>All, pouring their full showre of graces downe,</l>
         <l>The glorious <hi>Trinity</hi> in <hi>Vnion</hi> met.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Daughter, and Mother, and the Spouse of GOD,</l>
         <l>Alike of kin, to that most blessed <hi>Trine,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Of Persons, yet in Vnion (ONE) divine.</l>
         <l>How are thy gifts, and graces blaz'd abroad!</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Most holy, &amp; pure Virgin, blessed Mayd,</l>
         <l>Sweet Tree of Life, King <hi>Davids</hi> Strength and Tower,</l>
         <l>The House of gold, the Gate of heavens power,</l>
         <l>The Morning-star, whose light our Fal hath stay'd</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Great Queen of Queens, most mild, most meek, most wise,</l>
         <l>Most venerable. Cause of all our joy.</l>
         <l>Whose chearfull look our sadnesse doth destroy,</l>
         <l>And art the spotlesse Mirrour to Mans eyes.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <pb facs="24"/>
         <l>The Seat of Sapience, the most lovely Mother,</l>
         <l>And most to be admired of thy Sexe,</l>
         <l>Who mad'st us happy all, in thy reflexe,</l>
         <l>By bringing forth GOD's onely Son, no other.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Thou Throne of glory, beauteous as the Moone,</l>
         <l>The rosie Morning, or the rising Sun,</l>
         <l>Who like a Giant hasts his course to run,</l>
         <l>Till he hath reach'd his two-fold point of Noone.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>How are thy gifts and graces blaz'd abro'd,</l>
         <l>Through all the lines of this circumference,</l>
         <l>T'imprint in all purg'd hearts this virgin sence,</l>
         <l>Of being Daughter, Mother, Spouse of GOD?</l>
      </lg>
      <closer>
         <signed>B. I.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>