<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Preface of Simon Grineus to the Reader, concerning the Profit of reading Histories.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117759_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13980</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24293</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117759</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Preface of Simon Grineus to the Reader, concerning the Profit of reading Histories.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of Iustine : Containing a narration of kingdomes, from the beginning of the Assyrian monarchy, vnto the raigne of the Emperour Augustus. VVhereunto is newly added a briefe collection of the liues and manners of all the emperours succeeding, vnto the Emp. Rodulphus now raigning. First written in Latine by that famous historiographer Iustine, and now againe newly translated into English, by G.W</title>
                 <author>Justinus, Marcus Junianus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 138, 40 leaves, illustrations (woodcuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>A Preface of Simon Grineus to the Reader, concerning the Profit of reading Histories.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho is so simple in experience, or so leane in vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that knowes not by reading Histories, and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the plentifull and fruitefull fields of them, he doth therewith make the examples and instructions left in them to grow vp in himselfe, to his aboundant profit. For what can be thought more pleasant or more desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, then sitting as it it were in the Theater and stage of mans life, (the which a History hath most exquisitely furnished in all points) to be made capable of the perils that other men haue sustained, without further daunger to himselfe: to take examples of alsorts, eyther medicynable for his ownesecure estate, or beneficiall to others: to be so ably furnished for the presence of great men, when with grauest aduice they debate of the most weyghtiest affaires, to discusse the end and sequel of their desires, by example, or answer them by argument. The companye of which worthinesse, to the worthiest is welcome, and the cogitations of the Noblest thoughts do couet.</p>
   <p>Which profit, without History (considering the shortnesse of mans life) cannot be attaind: Who can compasse in memory the times of many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years past, behold the beginings, proceedings, &amp; subuersions of great Empires, to witnes the euils they endured, either priuate or publik, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestly to discerne the ground and occasion of them. In euery difficult and daungerous matter, to haue one try the perils, and as it were tread the yce before them, neuer to bee destitute of tryed experience, and by times past which properly and peculiarly appertaineth to the duty of a wise man, poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickly to foresee what may succeed in all estates, and to iudge of them as yf they were present.</p>
   <p>Sincc then the ground of such workes are large and spacious to walk and recreat our studies in, it is requisit we prepare our thoughts to the reading of Histories, hauing first a taste of ciuill policy in our selues, which so must gouerne our affections to iudge discreetly of all actions, either pleasinge or displeasing to vs, to be as sufficiently contented with whatsoere we read, &amp; doth resist our inclination, as delighted with that motion keepes fellowship with our nature, and not by the sway of passion bee miserably led, onely with vaine imaginations, and so tosse from one place to another, to read as birds skip from bow to bough, more to prime their bils, then benefit their bodies: but like good Surgions, who search al sores thoroughly to the bottome, ere
<pb facs="5"/>
they lay <hi>Cataplasme</hi> on any, &amp; in so viewing ouer Histories, thou shalt eyther by contemplating on the vertue of good men, learne to aspire thy selfe, or by reading the infermities of the bad, blush at the remembraunce of thine own, and be taught to reforme thy condition.</p>
   <p>But it hapneth as at a royall and sumptuous feast, furnished with all sorts of delicate viands, one thing is placed before one man, some set before ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, few satisfie themselues of one restoratiue, but euery man of that hely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth best: and although there is but some one kind of measure which nature hath appointed, and one kind of meat simple and in any wise vncorrupted, that is most for the helth and the nourishment of the body, from the bounds of which whosoeuer exceedeth, and followeth his owne appetite, beyond ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther measure or the ordinance of nature, hee may receiue hurt by that was ordained for his necessary good: euen so in that great variety of Histories, wherin there is set downe a thousand counsels, directed to a thousand pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses, and after what sorte socuer the reader be ledde by fancy or stayed by iudgement, so doth he censure or apply them. Whereby oftentimes that which is ordained for meat, couerts to surfet, <hi>&amp; salutaria pharmica,</hi> the whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some medicines prepared for the recreation, infectes the mind, by which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buse it followes not, a decree be made all food to be distasted, nor any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifit despised, since there is for al men leauied a path-way to vertue, in which who so walketh aduisedly, is praise-woorthy, and who transgresseth ofselfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opinion is to be condemned for his error.</p>
   <p>Some reading Histories deceiue themselues, imagining the bare stile of the history, is of authority inough in it selfe to instruct the reader, wheras indeed it doth no more but minister matter to learne vppon, offering it selfe to all vses, according as the person is affectioned, in like case as doth the feast, for as he that draws an arrow in a bow, may draw it home or short, as his strēgth finds good for him, and as he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, so in the vse of Histories, the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise is made not according to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e vse of the words, but the inclination of the will. Some read Histories for no other delight but onely in the reading, who seeking no more but a present delectation, do loose the benefit of the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant fruites, such men gaine no more by turning ouer the leaues of a histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, then they that play vpon an instrument, taking no further delight there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, then to passe away the tediousnesse of the time present, and shottly after enter into a more tedious conflict with themselues: for it is no pleasure that hath not respect vnto vertue. Others there are whome the glittering glosse of glory pricketh so forward, and to such a mishape transformeth them, that they thinke no aduenture to great for them, nor no prehemmence aboue them, being of no ability, for the performāce of the one, nor of desert to at taine to the other; vtterly forgetting, that those glorious examples whych they read, are not set forth by writers for any other intent, then that such as ensuing vertue, may thereby learne to contemne glory being aboue their reach, or if it accompany them, not to be proud and arrogant of it.</p>
   <p>And although that none but Fooles will enterprise to aspire to the like glory, without the like virtue, yet notwithstanding it is manifest that some finding no other merit in themselues, but that they haue reade the Noble acts of others, do thinke their desert of highest worth, notsparing of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
<pb facs="5"/>
to speake, <hi>Why should not I be either a Scipio or Caesar,</hi> like vnto players of Tragedies, who when they haue put off the apparrell, wherein they haue played the part of most Noble personages, do continue to counterset them in countenance and behauiour.</p>
   <p>There are also men of rude and vulgar vnderstanding who destract from al record, which is not either newes or wonders, like Ideots that giue more to a mans gay and superfluous cote, then vnto the person or his vertuous parts; that extend large offices to the outward show, if it be gawdy, and neglect the labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red instruction within, be the worke neuer so worthy.</p>
   <p>But whereas, it is the principal commendation, apertaineth to a history, to stirre vp the mind of man from sloath fulnesse, and to fence it from all dangers by the strength of examples, (then the which there is nothing of greater po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer either to perswade or diswade) and that the ancient reseruing of them ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to that end and purpose, yet it commeth to passe through the sloathful se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of men, and the neglect of their good, being so carefully reserued and offered them, by perswading themselues, that other mens perils helpe nothing to their safty, that such acts as are most worthy of remembrance are either vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefully rebuked, or else heard with deafe and vnsetled ears. Finally their be, that out of an obstinat presumption, transgresse euen against that same part containeth the most graue and carnest matters, as though histories should be written, not as they were done indeed, but as they ought to be done, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iled phrase and fresh inuention, of set purpose onely to' please them. So that partly by meanes of that carelesse security, and partly by the surfet of rash and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduised reading, it commeth to passe that (euen as it wer of corrupt humours) a certaine corruptnesse of Iudgment and peruerse opinion is bred.</p>
   <p>There is also another of no lesse force then these a forsaid, and that is in the writer of histories, who folowing as it wer the tast of their own Palats, as thogh they wer forgers of their worke themselues, fashion their labour rather to intice the reader to spred their commendation, then to let their hand &amp; pen consent to the truth: wherin they do like Cooks, who oftentimes in seasoning their mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters meate rather please their own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ellish then their Maist, by which, two seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Iudgements are misled, the one by rash censure, the other not recording plainely and sincerly.</p>
   <p>For a <hi>Historigrapher,</hi> is no other but a reporter of things done, (with whose iudgement if there be any fault) it standeth with him as with a tun of Wine, which (of it selfe being plesant and beautiful) doth either take an euill talent of the Caske, or else is made vnrellishable by being mingled with some other compound, which is either a shameful and intollerable deceit, or a point of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame folly and ignorance.</p>
   <p>To those then that ingrosse Histories I perscribe this rule, that they write to record, not to flatter. Of those that read them (since I am of firme opinion such authors are profitable to be read) though for no other but for the great aboundance of examples that they entreate off, I request that they circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectly and carefully ouerlooke them, considering how great fruites or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodities are in them propounded: otherwise it happeneth vnto them that imagine a worke may be read ouer lightly, as with those that hold a h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e may
<pb facs="6"/>
be passed ouer vnaduisedly, without the exact obseruing &amp; executing of a mans duty, or as it doth to Souldiers who in the sacking of a Citty come to the risling of some pothycaries shop, plentiously furnished withal store belonging to their arte, and being allured with the sweetnesse of the confections, and spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which they chance first to lay their hands on, thinking the remaine to be of the same, do eat and deuorue al that they light on, in such sort that some fal sick, some run mad, some dye presently, and he scapes best, is maruailously distemepred, so that for their greedinesse their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>llowes laugh them to scorne. For euen as mans life is ful of commodities and discommodities, so is a histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which is the true image and representation of the life, and as the wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the life consisteth onely in the faire carriage and good behauiour of the life, so the profit of reading is in the applycation therof. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rwell, and enioy these things to thy most furtherance and commodity.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>