<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Hereafter followeth the Pro∣logue or Proheme of Laurence Valla Translatour of the sayde viii. bokes out of the Greke tongue into the Laten, addressed vn∣to Nicholas of that name the fyfthe Byshoppe of Rome.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1550</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117701_Fr1_8</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13758</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24056</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117701</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Hereafter followeth the Pro∣logue or Proheme of Laurence Valla Translatour of the sayde viii. bokes out of the Greke tongue into the Laten, addressed vn∣to Nicholas of that name the fyfthe Byshoppe of Rome.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The hystory writtone by Thucidides the Athenyan of the warre, whiche was betwene the Peloponesians and the Athenyans, translated oute of Frenche into the Englysh language by Thomas Nicolls citezeine and goldesmyth of London</title>
                 <author>Thucydides</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Tylle (Tylly), William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1550</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>cvi, cvi-clxxix, clxxix-cc xxiii, 1 leave, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <head>Hereafter followeth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue or Proheme of Laurence Valla Translatour of the sayde viii. bokes out of the Greke tongue into the Laten, addressed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Nicholas of that name the fyfthe Byshoppe of Rome.</head>
   <p>I Maye well saye in thys behaulf (right reuerende father) that<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> whiche Ennius the Poete, reherceth to haue bene sayde, by Eneas. In thys substāce, it is great pleasure vnto me to haue es<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aped thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ugh so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye cities of Grece, and to haue passed through the myddes of myne ennemyes. For so muche, as hauyng ended and acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mplishedde the charge, that thou hast sayde on me, it semeth well vnto me to be escaped &amp; come vnto saluetie, through the myddes of my ennemyes. For lyke as some of Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours of Rome, as Augustus Anthonius, and many other, rested them selues at Rome, to geue order to the polecie of the common welthe: and commytted the feate of warres, moued a farre of, to theyr Dukes and Lieutenantes: ryghte so thou, hauyng and takynge charge and care of holye thynges in the religyon of Goddes and mans lawes, of peace, of helthe, and of the augmentacion of the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ople Romayne, hast committed vnto me, and to many other (that haue knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laige of the Greke tongue and of the Latyne) as to thyne Dukes, trybunes and Capytaynes, that we shulde submyt holegrece to the, and to thy obeissance, by dyuers meanes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> euery one accordynge to hys charge, the most that we myght. That is to wytt, that we shulde expounde and translate for the into the Latyn tongue, all the bokes which we founde composed or made in the Greke tongue. whiche is a thynge honnorable, singulier &amp; greatly mere for a sage pers<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nage. For what thynge may be more profytable, more plentyfull and more commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyous, than to translate bokes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Truly in my Iudgement it is a marchādyse of ryght precyous wares. And I do not compare it vnto a small thynge, whan I compare it vnto marchandyse, for there is nothynge amonge men more necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry than the same: whiche fournysheth men of that, that is conuenyent for theyr lyuynge and nurriture, to theyr clothynge and deckynge, to theyr delyghtes and to all other thynges that be conuenable for them. All the whiche thy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ges, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandyse bryngeth from dyuers quarters. In so greate habundaunce, that by meane there of nothyng is lackynge in any parte, and that all thynges be euery where common, in suche sorte, as in a manner, men were (as the saying is, in the goldenne worlde. Lykewyse doth the translatyon of bokes, whiche is so muche more worthy than marchandyse, as the goodes of the soule be more worthy, thā those of the bodye. For by thynges that thys translation doth communicate vnto vs, the vnderstandynges and wyttes of men be nouryshed, clothed, repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, adourned, and by a manner of speakyng, made deuyne. Therfor there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more delectable, more healthful, more to be desyred, &amp; to comprehende a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in one worde, more profytable, then to see trāslated into our tongue all that, that is founde in the Greke, Hebrewe, Caldee or Arabique tongue, be they treaties of histories, of orators<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of philosophers, of poetes, of phisicians or of diuines. And y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
      <pb facs="15"/>
maye well and clerely perceyue by this: that yf the olde testament had not bene translated out of Hebrieu into latyne, and the newe out of Greke, we other laty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> men shulde not haue hadde any knowelayge of God, and to be shorte, yf that I had will suffycyently to laude thys arte of translatyon, I must be more longe &amp; more prolixe, than the tyme and purpose do requyre. But wythout speakynge of other languages for to come agayne to the comparasone that I haue made of the arte mylitarye, and of the warre in thys translation: I repute it no lesse to be thy glory to haue caused to be translated the bokes, whiche yet be founde not translated oute of Greke into latynne, than yf thou haddest broughte agayne into subiection of the Romayne Empyre, Asia, Macedonia and hole Grece. How beit in dystributynge thy charges and commyssyons, thou hast geuen me one, beit by chance or of sett purpose, so ryght harde: that skarce there is any that can be more<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> for thou haste commytted to me to take and to expugne by force. viii. stronge places, set in a mountaygne upon hyghe rockes well nye inexpugnable by artyllery, nor by skalynge, and skarcely to be batered by shot, and also it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry harde to make there any bastillyon nor mynes withoutfourth. And yet I w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ll not that youe impute thys maner of speakynge that I vse, more to the weakenes of myne vnderstandyng, than to the dyfficultie of the matter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> for all they that haue knowlayge of the Grek<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>he Authours confesse by one common accorde, that Thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>dides is very harde and obscure, in his orations pryncipally: wherw<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the .viii. bokes of hys hystorye be stuffed, and that doth wytnes vnto vs Cicero, whome men called the Greke of hys worlde, in his boke of Oratory, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge in this wyse. The same narrations or orations, haue so many hyd and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure sentences, that skarce one maye vnderstande them. And yf any mā woulde saye vnto me, wherfore hast thou than taken this charge vpon the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> I aunswer hym: that I have not taken it, but it hath bene geuen me, or els I woulde not for any thynge, haue demaunded it. And yf I haue accepted it, it hath bene for thys, that it semed vnto me a thyng reprehensible and vnexcusable to resist the commaundement of my Emperour and mayster. whome I knowe to be so wise and so vertuous. And sythens that it hath pleased hym to do me thys honnour (for so woll I take it) to commyt and geue me to subdewe an prouynce, that neuer man enterprysed to assaille, I had rather dye in the poursuyte, than to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake it throughe fayntnes of harte or dysobedyence. Albeit that I haue bene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued of a succoure, to whome I yll trusted. to wyt of the Cardynall of Bizan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, at whose persuasyon as I beleue, youe haue commytted thys charge vnto me. Who is, to speake the trouthe, and wythoute flaterye, an excellent Greke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge the Latyns and an excellent latenist amonge the Grekes. For that, that nowe at the hower, that I hoped that he shulde haue helped me (as he had good knowlayge, and woulde haue done) he is gone for legate vnto Bullonia, wherby I fynd me as despayred of myne enterpryse. not seynge a parsonage that would or might ayde me. By occasyon wherof thou mayest knowe (right reuerende fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) that I haue ben in such payne and trauayle, that yf thou wouldest iudge vnto me the triumphe for thys here, as thou haste done to other in lyke case, I shulde not reioyce so muche of the same, as of thys, that I am come to thende or ouercommed my labours. for that, that I founde me many tymes wythout ayde and wythoute compaygnie, in the estate wherin they be, which make my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in the earth to take a place, or for to fynde the mynes or the vaynes of quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, and whan they haue dygged very deape, they se not lowe nor hyghe, farre nor nere any thyng that they searched. Wherfore yf that by these mynes I haue taken the places, yf I haue founde by dyggynge, the vayne of stones of pure
<pb n="xiiii" facs="15"/>
marbill, and of fyne golde (as I thinke I haue done) it is not to marueylle, yf I be right ioyful to be at the ende of my labours. For, for to speake of Thucidides, he is reputed amongest the Grekes, as the Porphir amongest the marbles, or as golde among metals, for that, that there is in hys speakynge, so muche gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie, so muche vehemencye and so muche trouthe, wythoute glofynge (which is the pryncypall part in an hystorian) that they, whiche rede it, thinke and beleue that that he wryteth, holye to be true, and that he hym selfe that hath wrytton the hystorye, hath not onely sene the thynges, wherof he speaketh, but also was therin presydent or ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ef. As he was for trouth in many thynges, so as shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare hereafter by the dyscours of the hystorye, albeit that he was charged to haue to slackely comme to succoure by sea, the cytye of Antypolys wyth the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye by sea, wherof he had charge. By occasyon wherof he was bannyshed, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though vnryghtuously. Duryng whiche banyshment, he composed thys pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent hystorye, and yet coulde not fynysh it as he had determyned, bryng preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by death. And yet neuertheles thys present anthor and Herodotus haue the prayse amonge the Grekyshe hystoryans, all lyke as Saluste and Titus Lyui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us amonge the Latynes. For the one of them, to wytte Herodotus, goeth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde all playne and easy wythout any roughnes, as a ryuer, that ronneth swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely all hole together wythoute any sourge and wythout wawes. The other, to wyt Thucydides, hath hys course more impetuous and in speakyng of thynges of warre, semeth that he is at the poynte of doynge it, and that he geueth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenne to fyght. As Quyntilian the greate Oratour sayeth in thys manner. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny haue wryttone hystoryes very elegantlye, but no man putteth me in doubte, that there a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne not two, that greatly exceade the other. And albeit y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> theyr ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and excellencye be in dyuers qualyties, yet the prayse is egall, asmuch to the one, as to the other. To wytt, Thucidides, whiche is briefe and compendyous wythout interuption, and Herodotus, who is eloquent and copyous. The one is more vehemente for to moue mens hartes, the other more remys and gentle, thone is more singulier in hys orations, and the other in hys speakynge. The one is more lyuely, and the other more playsante. Thowe haste than (right re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerende father) by the testimonye of Latynes, what the hystorye of Thucydi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des in Greke is. And yf thou dyddest thinke, that it hath all the same mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>stye translated into Latynne, I wolde forget all the laboure that I haue taken to do it. But more I wyll not, but that thou despyse not my labours, consydering, that the good knyght esteameth nothynge so muche, as to be holden and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by hys heade and Emperour, to be vaillyant and hardy. Thus do I requyre you (ryght reuerende father) that you woll acknowlaige thys historye of Thucidides to be thyne aud myne. For yf thoue allowest it, and hast my worke agreable, I woll repute it common vnto vs bothe.</p>
   <p>Here followeth the translatyon of the Lorde Cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dius of Seyssell of Thucydydes into the Frenche tongue.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>