<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the right honorable Lorde Ambrose Dudley, Earle of Warwicke, Baron of Lisle, of the most honorable order of the Garter Knight, Generall of the Queenes Maiesties Ordinance, within hir highnesse realmes and dominions.</title>
           <author>Tymme, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1576</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117191_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11930</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22243</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117191</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the right honorable Lorde Ambrose Dudley, Earle of Warwicke, Baron of Lisle, of the most honorable order of the Garter Knight, Generall of the Queenes Maiesties Ordinance, within hir highnesse realmes and dominions.</title>
                 <author>Tymme, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fourth parte of Co [m] mentaries of the ciuill warres in Fraunce, and of the lovve countrie of Flaunders: translated out of Latine into English, by Thomas Tymme minister. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Serres, Jean de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Toy (Toius), Humphrey</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1576</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 35, 1, 1410, that is 150, 30 pages, folded plates, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the right honorable Lorde Ambrose Dudley, Earle of <hi>Warwicke, Baron of Lisle, of the</hi> most honorable order of the Garter Knight, Generall of the Queenes Maiesties Ordinance, within hir highnesse realmes and dominions.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is cōmonly seen (right honorable) that all men occupy them selues most in the reading of those matters, wherein they haue delight, eyther for that they are naturally disposed therevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, or else well experienced in the same. The which consideration be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ioyned with the Argument of this my booke, I coulde not deuise with my selfe a more fitte patron, to whome I might dedicate the same, than to your honour. For such no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="3"/> courage hath nature wrought in you, found out by effecte in martiall affaires, as I persuade my selfe you will delight and recreate your selfe muche, with the reading of the vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant acts, done by diuers courageous persons, in these last ciuill warres of Fraunce. Accept therefore (ryght honourable) my choyce, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don my boldnesse, which good will hath caused me to shewe, presuming vpon your honourable curtesie, by whiche I am drawne, as by the load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone, to offer this simple present to your honours handes: I wishe the same might in any part be answera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to your worthynesse. VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to staye your honour with longer speach, I take my leaue, recō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending my poore paines to your honours protection.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your honours most humble <hi>Thomas Tymme.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>