<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORA∣BLE,
MAISTER DOCTOR
WOTTON: ONE OF THE
Queenes Maiesties priuy Coun∣sayle:
Alexander Neuyle wish∣eth
Helth, vvith encrease of
Honor.</title>
           <author>Neuile, Alexander</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117108_Bo1_5_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11909</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22221</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117108</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORA∣BLE,
MAISTER DOCTOR
WOTTON: ONE OF THE
Queenes Maiesties priuy Coun∣sayle:
Alexander Neuyle wish∣eth
Helth, vvith encrease of
Honor.</title>
                 <author>Neuile, Alexander</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Seneca his tenne tragedies, translated into Englysh</title>
                 <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stationers’ Company, London</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 65, 64-217, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE,
MAISTER DOCTOR
WOTTON: ONE OF THE
Queenes Maiesties priuy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayle:
Alexander Neuyle wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
Helth, vvith encrease of
Honor.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His sixtenth yeare of myne age (righte
honorable) reneweth a gratefull memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
of your great goodnes towardes mee:
(for at Baptisme your honor vouchsafed
to aunsweare for mee): and causeth mee
thus boldly to present these greene and
vnmelowed fruicts of my first truailes vnto you: as signes
and testimonies of a well disposed minde vnto your honor.
Albeit when first I vndertoke the translation of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
Tragoedy, I minded nothing lesse, than that at any
tyme thus rudely transformed it shoulde come into the
<pb n="76" facs="82"/>
Printers hands. For I to none other ende remoued him,
from his naturall and lofty style, to our corrupt and base,
or as some men (but vntruly) affyrme it, most barbarous
Language: but onely to satisfy the instant requests of a
few my familiar frends, who thought to haue put it to the
very same vse, that SENECA himselfe in his Inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
pretended: VVhich was by the tragicall and Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous
showe vpon Stage, to admonish all men of their fic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle
Estates, to declare the vnconstant head of wauering
Fortune, her sodayne interchaunged and soone altered
Face: and lyuely to expresse the iust reuenge, and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
punishmēts of horrible Crimes, wherewith the wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
worlde in these our myserable dayes pyteously swar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth.
This caused me not to be precise in following the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,
word for word: but sometymes by addition, somtimes
by subtraction, to vse the aptest Phrases in geuing the Sēse
that I could inuent. VVhereat a great numbre (I know)
will be more offended than Reason or VVysedome woulde
they should bee. Thus as I framed it to one purpose:
so haue my frends (to whom I can not well deny any thyng
that Frendshyps ryght may seeme iustly to requyre) wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted
it to another effect: and by this meanes blowen it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade,
by ouerrash and vnaduised printing. By whych
fond deede I know vndoubtedly I shall receyue the poyso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
infamies, of a number of venemous tonges, VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
(ryght honorable) as I geue these the first Fruicts of
my trauayle vnto you: declaring therein the great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyll
and duety that I owe vnto your Honor, for the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
disposition of your vertuous mynde: so am I driuen
humbly to require your strong ayde, and assured defence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynst
<pb facs="83"/>
the sclaunderous assaults of such malicious mouths,
which obtayned: I shalbe the better encouraged agaynst
an other time, to bestow my trauaile in matters of farre
greater weighte and importaunce. In the meane season
(desiring your Honour to take these simple Attemptes of
myne in good part:) I leaue you to the tuitiō of the right
high and mighty God: VVho keepe you long in health, &amp;
graunt you many happy yeares: with encrease of Honor.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>All your Honours to commaund.
Alexander Neuile.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>