<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ TO THE WELL-AFFEC∣TED AND FAVOVRABLE READER.</title>
           <author>Speed, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117917_Fr1_13</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68764</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23041</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117917</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ TO THE WELL-AFFEC∣TED AND FAVOVRABLE READER.</title>
                 <author>Speed, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The theatre of the empire of Great Britaine : presenting an exact geography of the kingdomes of England, Scotland, Ireland, and the iles adioyning: with the shires, hundreds, cities and shire-townes, within ye kingdome of England, divided and described by Iohn Speed</title>
                 <author>Speed, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Hall, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hall, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Humble, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Humble, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sudbury, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sudbury, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 146, that is 280, 10 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), maps (metal cuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>❧ TO THE WELL-AFFEC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TED AND FAVOVRABLE <hi>READER.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O great was the attempt to assay the erection of this large and laborious <hi>THEATRE,</hi> whose onely platforme might well haue expected the readiest hand of the best Artist, that euen in the entrance of the first draught as one altogether discouraged, I found my selfe farre vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and vnfurnished both of matter and meanes, either to build, or to beautifie so stately a proiect. But how the Lord then composed my mind for the worke, or rather how his owne great power would be seene in my weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, is now in some measure made manifest by raising the frame thereof to this height; which here from the Presse sheweth his aspect vnto the world. But with what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to thy eye (gentle <hi>Reader)</hi> J stand in suspence, so many Maister-builders ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in this subiect gone before me, and I the least, not worthy to hew (much lesse to lay) the least stone in so beautifull a Building; neither can I for my heedlesse pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption <note place="margin">The principall motiues of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note>alledge any excuse, vnlesse it be this, that the zeale of my countries glory so transported my senses, as J knew not what J vndertooke, vntill J saw the charges thereof (by others bestowed) to amount so high as I held it a conscience to frustrate their designements; wherein albeit, it may be obiected that J haue put my sickle into other mens corne, and haue laid my building vpon other mens foundations (as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed who can do otherwise, especially in a subiect of this nature, seeing that the <hi>wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eccl. 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>of Kings</hi> witnesseth, <hi>that there is nothing new vnder the Sun)</hi> yet let this in part suffise for my defence, that in the worke of the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> there was more <note place="margin">Exod. 31.</note>mettals vsed then the <hi>orient gold,</hi> and more workemen imployed then <hi>Aholiab &amp; Bezaleel;</hi> neither did al the <hi>Israelites</hi> offer to that most glorious work, <hi>Gold, Siluer, Onix-stones, Purple, Scarlet,</hi> and fine <hi>Linnen:</hi> but some of thē, <hi>Brasse, Wood,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Exod. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>5.</note>
      <hi>Goates-haire, Rams-fels,</hi> and <hi>Badgers skins,</hi> as necessary implements in their <note place="margin">Mark. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>seuerall seruices. If then, with the poore widdow J cast in my mite, and by my owne trauell adde some what more then hath bene alreadie diuulged, let me craue thy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, where I haue done right, and thine assistance to correct where I misse, which J trust may as well be hoped as requested, thy loue with mine being alike obliged vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this our natiue land. VVhose beautie and benefits, not a farre off, as <hi>Moses</hi> saw <hi>Canaan</hi> from <hi>Pisgah,</hi> but by my owne trauels through euery prouince of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
      <note place="margin">Exod. 34. Things described vpon a personall suruty of all England and VVales.</note>and <hi>Wales</hi> mine eyes haue beheld: and whose Climate, Temperature, Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and Pleasures, make it to be as the very <hi>Eden of Europe</hi> (pardon me J pray if affection passe limits) for the <hi>store of corne in the champian,</hi> and of <hi>Pasturage in</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>the lower Grounds,</hi> presseth the cart vnder the sheaues to the barn, and filleth the <note place="margin">Amos. 2. 13.</note>coffers of their possessors. Neither are the faces of the <hi>Mountaines</hi> and <hi>Hils</hi> onely spread ouer with infinite heards and sorts of cattell, but their intralls also are in continuall trauell, and continually deliuered of their rich Progenies of <hi>Copper, Lead▪</hi> and <hi>Iron, Marble, Cristall, Iet, Alablaster,</hi> yea the most wonder-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Loadstone;</hi> to say nothing either of <hi>Cannol</hi> and <hi>Sea-coale</hi> as rich for profit and as needfull for vse, or of the goodly Quarries of choisest stone, as necessary for strength, as estimable for beauty. Her <hi>Seas</hi> and <hi>Riuers</hi> so stored with <hi>Fish,</hi> and her <hi>Fels</hi> and <hi>Fens</hi> so replenished with wild foule, that they euen present themselues for ready prey to their takers; briefly, euery soile is so enriched with plenty and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, as the inhabitants thinke there is no other Paradice in the earth but where <note place="margin">VVhat is perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in this worke.</note>thēselues dwell. The true plot of the whole land, &amp; that again into parts in seuerall Cards are here described, as likewise the cities and shire townes are inserted, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of some haue bene performed by others, without <hi>Scale</hi> annexed, the rest by mine owne trauels, and vnto them for distinctions sake, the <hi>Scale</hi> of <hi>Paces,</hi> accounted ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Geometricall measure, fiue foote to a pace J haue set; but in this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment I am somewhat to excuse my self from wrongs conceiued done vnto more <note place="margin">Cities and shire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>townes.</note>beautifull and richer corporatiōs, which in this suruey are in silence ouer passed, and places of lesse note &amp; frequency described. For satisfaction wherof (good <hi>Reader)</hi> vnderstand my purpose, according to the title presixed, which in this <hi>Iland</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides other things) is to shew the situation of euery city and shire town onely. So that without iniury to all, I could not insert some, though oftentimes it greeued me much to leaue such beautifull places vntouched: which notwithstanding being wel knowne so to be, giueth no little glory to the land in generall, so to be replenished with store &amp; <note place="margin">Shire-diuisions.</note>choise, as hardly can be iudged which may be omitted. The <hi>Shires</hi> diuisions into <hi>Lathes, Hundreds, Wapentakes</hi> and <hi>Cantreds</hi> according to their ratable, and <note place="margin">Tables to find all names in the maps.</note>accustomed manner J have separated, and vnder the same Title that the record bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, in their due places distinguished; wherein by the helpe of the Tables annexed, any <hi>Citie, Towne, Burrough, Hamlet,</hi> or place of note may readily be found, and whereby safely may be affirmed that there is not any one kingdome in the world so exactly described, as is this our <hi>Iland</hi> of <hi>Great Brittaine,</hi> that onely excepted which <note place="margin">Armes of the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tular Nobles.</note>
      <hi>Iosuah</hi> conquered and into Tribes diuided. The armes of such Princes and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles as haue had the dignities, and borne the titles either of Dukes, Marquesses, or <note place="margin">Places of great battels.</note>Earles, in the same Prouince, City or Place: and finally the Battels fought either by the <hi>sorraine</hi> or <hi>home-bred Conspirators,</hi> I haue also added. VVhere we from vnder our owne vines without feare may behold the prints of indured miseries, sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the blood of those times, to the losse of their liues, and liberties; our selues (as in the reigne of <hi>Augustus,</hi> when the Temple of <hi>Ianus</hi> stood shut, and <hi>Mars</hi> his hands bound with chaines of Brasse as <hi>Virgill</hi> speaketh) heare not the sound of the Alarū in our Gates, nor the clattering of armor in our campes, whose swords are <note place="margin">Mich▪ 4. 3.</note>now turned into mattockes and speares into sithes, as <hi>Micah</hi> sheweth the peaceable times vnder Christ▪ Jn shewing these things J haue chiefly sought to giue satisfactiō to all without offence to any, wherof if J faile, yet this to my self haue J gained, that <note place="margin">The benefit made of this labour.</note>whilest I set all my thoughts and cogitations hereon, J had small regard to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching pleasures, and vaine enticements of this wicked world, neither had J lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to be led by an ambitious desire to raise my statiō aboue the leuell of my equals, or with base flattery to follow, and fill the eares of <hi>Fortunes Deputies,</hi> the rains of these intents checking the bit of affection into another way. And applying my selfe wholely to the frame of this most goodly Building, haue as a poore labourer carried the <hi>carued stones</hi> and <hi>polished Pillars</hi> from the hands of the more skilfull <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitects</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>
to be set in their fit places, which here J offer vpon the altar of loue to my country, and wherein I haue held it no sacrilege to rob others of their richest iewels to adorn this my most beautifull Nurse, whose <hi>wombe</hi> was my concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whose <hi>breasts</hi> were my nourishment, whose <hi>bosome</hi> my cradle, and lap (I doubt not) shall be my bed of sweete rest, till <hi>Christ</hi> by his trumpet raise me thence.</p>
   <epigraph>
      <bibl>1. CHRON. 28. 8.</bibl>
      <q>Therefore in the sight of the congregation of the Lord, and in the audience of our God, <hi>let vs</hi> keepe and seeke for all the commandements of the Lord <hi>our</hi> God, that we may pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sesse this good land, and leaue it for an inheritance for <hi>our</hi> Children after vs for euer.</q>
   </epigraph>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ Jesus,
IOHN SPEED.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>