<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR IAMES LANCAS∣TER Knight, my sin∣gular good friend.</title>
           <author>Crooke, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117125_Fr2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19639</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6069</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117125</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR IAMES LANCAS∣TER Knight, my sin∣gular good friend.</title>
                 <author>Crooke, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Three sermons : viz. The walking sleeper, the ministeriall husbandrie, the discouerie of the heart. Preached and published by Sam. Crooke</title>
                 <author>Crooke, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 72, 12, 73-128, 60 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO</hi> THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR IAMES LANCAS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER Knight, my sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular good friend.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hese being the daies fortold by our blessed <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour,</hi> wherein men as in the daies of <hi>Noah</hi> &amp; <hi>Lot,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.26. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
      </note> do <hi>eat
<pb facs="3"/> &amp; drink, buy and build, and plant, &amp;c.</hi> vnmindfull of <hi>him,</hi> who is ready to <hi>come as a thief in the night,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Reuel.</hi> 16.15.</note> at what time <hi>he</hi> only shall be <hi>blessed, that wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth &amp; keepeth</hi> close about him the <hi>wedding garmēts</hi> of faith and holines: J haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauoured in the opening and publishing of this part of holy truth, to awaken and stir vp my selfe and others, to prepare and wait for the cōming of our Lord Jesus Christ.</p>
   <p>And because this Scripture (framed rather for an <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy</hi> of the Church in her se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall
<pb facs="3"/> members, then, as some haue supposed, for an <hi>Historie</hi> of her generall estate according to periods of time) hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded al, euen the elect in part, vnder this common disease of spirituall drowzinesse; whereby it may come to passe, that on the one side the Godly may be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged for their partaking with the wicked, and on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther side the wicked may be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldned, because they see Gods children charged with the same corruption, in which they feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesly please themselues: I haue therefore further intended to
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>take forth the precious from the vile;</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ier.</hi> 15.19.</note> by distinguishing <hi>the waking Sleeper,</hi> that is, the weake humbled Christian, who euen in sleeping waketh, from <hi>the sleeping waker,</hi> that is, the presuming Hypocrite, who seeming to be awake, is fast, yea dead asleepe.</p>
   <p>J haue made bold to offer this my poore labor to the light vnder the shadow and shelter of your worthy name.</p>
   <p>First, in regard of that light you hold forth of good example,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.27.</note> in the practise of that <hi>pure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and vndefiled before
<pb facs="4"/> God euen the Father,</hi> which approueth it selfe by your <hi>visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of</hi> so many <hi>fatherles and widowes in their affliction;</hi> a grace that infallibly <hi>accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panieth saluation,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Heb.</hi> 6 9.</note> &amp; maketh you one of those few who doe stop the mouth of Popish ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, blaspheming our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and slandering our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors as abhorring from good workes.</p>
   <p>Secondly, in regard of many particular bonds and coards of loue, whereby you haue tied me in thankefulnesse vnto your selfe; whereof therefore J am desirous, there should be extant
<pb facs="5"/> this publike, and (if it may be) perpetuall acknowledgement.</p>
   <p>And so, wishing that this may bee the beginning not of one, but of many good yeares vnto you, vntill it shall please God to translate you to date<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse and boundlesse life, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend you to <hi>his</hi> grace, who <hi>is not</hi> vnrighteous that he should forget your worke and labour of loue,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.10.</note> which you haue shewed to his Name, in that you haue ministred vnto the Saints, and doe minister; and rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Wrington Somers.</hi>
         <date>Febr. <hi>8. 1615.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Worships in the Lord Iesus, to be commanded, <hi>Sam. Crooke.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>