<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NORABLE, THOMAS, LORD Ellesmere, Lord Chancellor of England, and one of his Maiesties most Hono∣rable Priuie Counsell; Grace and Peace.</title>
           <author>Hill, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117083_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03356</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13474</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117083</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NORABLE, THOMAS, LORD Ellesmere, Lord Chancellor of England, and one of his Maiesties most Hono∣rable Priuie Counsell; Grace and Peace.</title>
                 <author>Hill, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pathvvay to prayer and pietie : Containing, 1 An exposition of the Lords Prayer, with an apologie for publicke, and priuate set prayer. 2 A preparation to the Lords Supper, with Ma. Zanchius confession, concerning that sacrament. 3 A direction to a Christian life, bot in our generall and particular callings. 4 An instruction to die well, and a consolation against all crosses. With diuers prayers, and thankesgiuings fit for this treatise. By Robert Hill, Doctor in Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Hill, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <distributor>Barrett, William</distributor>
                            <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40, 141, 17, 110, 8, 111-344 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE, THOMAS, LORD <hi>Ellesmere,</hi> Lord Chancellor of <hi>England, and one of his Maiesties most</hi> Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Priuie Counsell; <hi>Grace and Peace.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable; as it is the <hi>safetie</hi> of a <hi>Shippe</hi> to haue good <hi>Pilotes,</hi> the <hi>strength</hi> of a <hi>palace</hi> to haue sure <hi>Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars,</hi> the <hi>securitie</hi> of the <hi>body</hi> to haue <hi>cleare eyes,</hi> and the <hi>safeguard</hi> of <hi>sheepe</hi> to haue vigilant <hi>shephards:</hi> So is it the <hi>safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> of a <hi>Countrie,</hi> and <hi>safegard</hi> of a <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/> to haue many wise and watchfull <hi>Counsellors.</hi> Is this <hi>ship</hi> tossed? These <hi>Pilots</hi> will guide it. Is this <hi>palace</hi> sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken? These <hi>Pillars</hi> will <hi>vphold</hi> it. Is this <hi>body</hi> in perill? These <hi>eyes</hi> will <hi>ouersee</hi> it. Are these <hi>sheepe</hi> in danger? These <hi>shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards</hi> will <hi>defend</hi> them. And as, where there is no <hi>vision,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> is naked: So, where no <hi>counsell</hi> is, there the <hi>State</hi> is naked.</p>
   <p>Of all the miseries which befell the <hi>Israelites,</hi> this is recorded to bee one of the greatest, That either they had <hi>no King</hi> to rule them, or that their Kings were but <hi>children,</hi> who ruled them: yet as that <hi>ship</hi> is safer that hath but a bad <hi>Pilot,</hi> than no <hi>Pilot;</hi> that <hi>palace</hi> stronger that hath but woodden <hi>Pillars,</hi> than no <hi>pillars;</hi> that <hi>body</hi> securer, that hath but a squint <hi>eye,</hi> than no <hi>eye;</hi> and those <hi>sheepe</hi> better, that haue any <hi>shepheard,</hi> than no <hi>shepheard:</hi> So is that <hi>nation</hi> in farre bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter case, which hath but bad <hi>gouernours,</hi> than none at all. Is it a blessing to bee <hi>commanded</hi> by the bad? what a blessing then is it to bee <hi>gouerned</hi> by the good?
<pb facs="3"/> Haue we good <hi>Ministers?</hi> they are the <hi>horsemen</hi> and <hi>chariots</hi> of<note n="a" place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 13.14.</note>
      <hi>Israel.</hi> Haue we good Magistrates? they are the <hi>light</hi> of our <hi>eyes,</hi> the <hi>breath</hi> of our <hi>nostrils,</hi> the <hi>anointed</hi> of the <hi>Lord;</hi> and vnder their <hi>shadow</hi> we are preserued<note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.20.</note> aliue.</p>
   <p>Amongst many Right Honourable and truely honoured <hi>Senators,</hi> both <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>Commonwealth</hi> blesse God for your Honour. You are blessed of the <hi>Church</hi> as an vncorrupt <hi>Patron;</hi> you are blessed of the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> as an impartiall <hi>Iudge.</hi> In the <hi>one,</hi> you desire to plant <hi>pietie,</hi> in the <hi>other,</hi> you are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to supplant <hi>iniquitie.</hi> In the <hi>one</hi> you are <hi>carefull,</hi> that one haue not all; in the other, you are <hi>watchfull,</hi> that each may haue his owne. In the one you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for the preaching of <hi>veritie;</hi> in the other you pronounce the sentence of <hi>equitie.</hi> Are you in the one to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Iustice? I may say with <hi>Basil; Your arrow euer aimeth at the white:</hi> with <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pictetus; Your hand euer holdeth an equall ballance:</hi> and with <hi>Erasmus; Your sunne shineth alike on the poore and rich.</hi> Are
<pb facs="4"/> you to conferre <hi>Ecclesiasticall</hi> prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? You will not giue that <hi>Iaakob</hi> bleare-eyed <hi>Leah,</hi> who hath serued ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie a yeare for faire <hi>Rachel.</hi> You wil not make him a <hi>shepheard</hi> of mens soules, who is rather to bee a shepheard of mens sheepe. What good you haue done to this <hi>Church</hi> of ours, let <hi>Church-men</hi> iudge: you loue our <hi>Nation:</hi> you haue prouided for vs many decaied Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues, and put many poore Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers into the poole of <hi>Beth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sdah,</hi> who haue beene cured of their long disease of pouertie, without the descending of any one <hi>Angell.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Experience I haue had of your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to poore Ministers, in my first <hi>certaine</hi> maintenance that euer I had in our <hi>Church.</hi> For though I was <hi>afraide</hi> euen to looke vpon you, yet you were not <hi>forgetfull</hi> to prouide for mee; and without any either suing or seeking of mine, it pleased you to annex vnto my Lecture at S. <hi>Martins,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>S. Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets</hi> in Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day street.</note> that small Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, which I now haue in London, and where I am carefull to Preach euery
<pb facs="4"/> Sabbath, though I cannot liue there for want of an house.</p>
   <p>In a thankfull remembrance of your loue to our Calling, and an hopefull acceptation of this enterprised seruice, I am bold to present againe this booke to your Honor. It was penned at the first for the benefit of this Parish: and published by authoritie, for the good of the Church. This Parish of S. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> mooued mee to penne it:<note place="margin">Doctor <hi>Vaughan.</hi>
      </note> and that late Reuerend Bishop of <hi>London</hi> allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me to Print it.</p>
   <p>In regard of both these, I doubt not but your Honor will afford it your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage. You are to the one a most ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable <hi>benefactor,</hi> prouiding for the <hi>liuing,</hi> by your charitable <hi>almes;</hi> and for the <hi>dead,</hi> by procuring a new, and most needfull <hi>Church-yard.</hi> You were to the other a most honorable friend: you loued him in his life, and did vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly mourne for him at his death.</p>
   <p>Of whome, I may say (considering the encouragements I had from him in my ministerie) as <hi>El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sha</hi> said, when
<pb facs="5"/> his master <hi>Eliah</hi> was taken from his head,<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 2.12.</note>
      <hi>My Father, my Father, the Horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Israel, and the Chariots thereof.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>S. Johns</hi> in Cambridg</note>He was an honor to our <hi>Colledge,</hi> in which hee once liued a painefull stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: and an ornament to our Church, in which he was (as we haue many Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Fathers now he is gone) a prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Bishop. For his admirable lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in our Vniuersity of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> he was long since created a Doctor in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie: and for his abilitie to rule, hee was after Consecrated Bishop of <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor,</hi> and immediatly translated to the Diocesse of <hi>Chester,</hi> and after a while from thence to <hi>London.</hi> In these ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancements of his, how much hee was beholding to your Honour, I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be silent, then say little: but sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hee was worthie you should doe for him.</p>
   <p>For the gifts of his <hi>Ministerie,</hi> he was a <hi>powerfull</hi> and <hi>skilfull</hi> Preacher: for the vse of his <hi>authoritie,</hi> he was a most <hi>watchfull</hi> and <hi>temperate</hi> Gouernour. Was hee to <hi>speake?</hi> his wordes were
<pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>sententious:</hi> was hee to aduise? His counsell was <hi>religious:</hi> was hee to <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monish?</hi> his exhortations were <hi>gratious:</hi> and was hee to <hi>censure?</hi> his sentence was <hi>iudicious.</hi> Did hee <hi>obserue</hi> any Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister painefull in his calling? hee euer did <hi>encourage</hi> him to go on: did hee see any either <hi>negligent,</hi> or <hi>turbulent?</hi> the one hee would <hi>aduise</hi> to greater la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; the other <hi>bring on,</hi> to greater peace.</p>
   <p>For his <hi>iudgement</hi> in <hi>Diuinitie,</hi> what it was, the <hi>Church</hi> can iudge: hee was a <hi>profound</hi> Preacher of the <hi>truth,</hi> a <hi>zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous</hi> enemie to all <hi>superstition,</hi> and a great <hi>exhorter</hi> to all <hi>pietie</hi> &amp; <hi>godlinesse.</hi> He halted not betwixt two opinions: hee spake not with those Iewes, <hi>Nehe.</hi> 13.24. partly the language of <hi>Ashdod,</hi> and partly the language of <hi>Canaan,</hi> but euery way shewed himselfe a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant indeed.</p>
   <p>His <hi>learning</hi> was good, his life bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and his <hi>death,</hi> for himselfe, <hi>best</hi> of all. His <hi>learning</hi> was without compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison, his <hi>life</hi> without exception, his
<pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>death</hi> without suspition. By his <hi>lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> hee instructed, by his <hi>life</hi> hee shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and by his <hi>death</hi> hee yet smelleth as a sweet perfume. What his <hi>learning</hi> was, this Land knoweth; what his <hi>life</hi> was, <hi>London</hi> knoweth; and what his <hi>death</hi> was, those <hi>learned</hi> men knowe, who were about him in the time of his sicknesse.</p>
   <p>Hee was <hi>Bishop</hi> of this <hi>Diocesse,</hi> not much aboue two yeares: in which time this Citie much reioyced in him; and surely no maruaile. For hee was a <hi>Clemens</hi> to this <hi>Rome:</hi> a <hi>Polycarpus</hi> to this <hi>Smyrna:</hi> a <hi>Iustine</hi> to this <hi>Naples:</hi> a <hi>Dionysius</hi> to this <hi>Alexandria:</hi> a <hi>Cyprian</hi> to this <hi>Carthage:</hi> an <hi>Eusebius</hi> to this <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarea.</hi> a <hi>Gregorie</hi> to this <hi>Nyssa:</hi> an <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brose</hi> to this <hi>Mill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>yne:</hi> a <hi>Chrysostome</hi> to this <hi>Constantinople:</hi> an <hi>Augustine</hi> to this <hi>Hippo:</hi> and a <hi>Ridley</hi> to this <hi>Diocesse.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And as <hi>Ambrose</hi> was wont to say of his people, so questionlesse he said of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of his; <hi>Non minùs vos diligo quos genui ex euangelio, quàm si suscepissem ex contugio: gratia quippe vehementior est
<pb facs="6"/> ad diligendum quàm natura: I loue you no lesse, whom I haue begotten by the Gospell, then my owne children: For grace procures greater loue then nature.</hi> Nay it seemeth he loued them more: for hee impoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished the one, to enrich the other. But blessed bee that most reuerend <hi>Dauid,</hi> that will haue care of <hi>Ionathans</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, now he is dead.</p>
   <p>Dead hee is indeede, in regard of his presence; but aliue for euer, in regard of his remembrance: for, <hi>the righteous shalbe had in an euerlasting remembrance, when the name of the wicked shall rot.</hi> He died not rich in goods; it was an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his goodnesse: he died rich in grace; it was an argument of his godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. With <hi>Bernard</hi> he did liue <hi>in terra auri, sine auro:</hi> In a Kingdome of gold, without gold: and seemed to thinke, as <hi>Lactantius</hi> did write, that <hi>Qui apud De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um diues est, pauper esse non potest:</hi> Hee that is rich in God, cannot be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a poore man.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Did Abner,</hi> saith <hi>Dauid, die as a foole dieth?</hi> And did this <hi>Bishop</hi> of London
<pb facs="7"/> die, as that Bishop of Rome, who said, <hi>Vixi dubius, anxius morior, nescio quò va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do:</hi> I haue liued doubtfull, I die doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, I know not whither I shall goe? no hee did not. But with <hi>Ambrose</hi> hee said, <hi>I haue not so lead my life, that I was ashamed to liue: neither feare I death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I know I haue a good Lord.</hi> Hee said not with <hi>Nero, Me mortuo ruat mundus: I care not what befalle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> after I am dead;</hi> but,<note place="margin">These were almost his last words.</note>
      <hi>modo me moriente viuat &amp; floreat ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesia, fiat voluntas Domini: So that after my death the Church may flourish, the will of God be done.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thus, <hi>a good life hath the yeares num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, but a good name endureth for euer.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Not to be troublesome to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor: by his departure, his <hi>wife</hi> hath lost a louing <hi>husband,</hi> his <hi>children</hi> an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent <hi>father,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> a worthie <hi>Prelate,</hi> and I (a poore Preacher) one of the most <hi>honourable</hi> friends that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I had, hauing deserued so little of him.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Isa.</hi> 57.11.</note>Doe the righteous perish? wee must regard it. Are mercifull men taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way?
<pb facs="7"/> we must consider it in our hearts. After <hi>Ambrose</hi> was dead, <hi>Italy</hi> was troubled: after <hi>Augustine</hi> was dead, <hi>Afrike</hi> was spoiled: After <hi>Luther</hi> was dead, <hi>Germanie</hi> was distracted. After <hi>Bucer</hi> was dead, <hi>heere</hi> religion was alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And after the death of so many worthie men, as wee haue lost within these few yeeres, the Lord graunt that we be not plagued.</p>
   <p>I am no <hi>Homer</hi> to commend this <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilles:</hi> no <hi>Chrysostome</hi> to commend this <hi>Babylas:</hi> no <hi>Augustine</hi> to commend this <hi>Cyprian:</hi> no <hi>Melancthon</hi> to commend this <hi>Luther:</hi> no <hi>Parker</hi> to commend this <hi>Bucer:</hi> onely in honor to him who honoured God in his life, I presume thus to write of him being dead. Your Honor well knoweth that I haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the trueth: and the Lord knoweth I desire to write nothing but the truth.</p>
   <p>Thus crauing pardon for my bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and once againe most humbly entreating your Honorable entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of these few sheetes of Paper, as
<pb facs="8"/> they are now the fifth time enlarged, I humbly take my leaue; beseeching God to continue you long a trustie Counsellor to our Gracious King, an vpright Iudge to our Christian peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and a good Patron to the despised Clergie. From your Parish of Saint <hi>Martin</hi> in (or rather now by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of many new buildings neere) the Fields. <hi>Iune the</hi> 16. 1613.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>At your Honours seruice,</hi> ROBERT HILL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>