<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Thomas Gale vnto the friendlie Reader.</title>
           <author>Smith, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1586</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117692_Bo1_5_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01410</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11531</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117692</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Thomas Gale vnto the friendlie Reader.</title>
                 <author>Smith, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine vvorkes of Galens, called Methodus medendi : with a briefe declaration of the worthie art of medicine, the office of a chirurgion, and an epitome of the third booke of Galen, of naturall faculties: all translated into English, by Thomas Gale Maister in Chirurgerie</title>
                 <author>Galen</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1586</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 138 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="131"/>
   <head>Thomas Gale vnto the friendlie Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is requisite that euerie one that vseth this art of Medicine, in the curation of diseases or sicknesses, not onelie to know the diuisions &amp; natures of the same, but also to knowe the names, by meanas whereof, euerie one of the same may be knowen from another, and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in this part, for the better vnderstanding of Tumours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst nature, wherin Galen hath taken great paines, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in their true diuisions, but also gathering together their most apt and auncient names, giuen vnto them by the olde writers. And if anie names did lacke for such sicknesses, as raigned in his daies, he did deuise most apt and conuenient names for the same. Aristotle saith, whosoeuer is ignorant in the tearmes of his art, that he is ignorant in the whole arte. Therefore it is necessarie for those that professe so noble an art as Chirurgerie is, not onelie to know the names of sicknes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and diseases, but the name of euerie perticular medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as wel simple as compound. And also to know all other strange tearmes appertaining to this arte. Wherefore Galen in this booke of Tumours against Nature, hath taken greate paines, not onelie in setting forth of their names, but of theyr true diuisions, natures, and dispositions, with their figures, formes, and humours, by which they doe grow and are main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, without which knowledge no Chirurgion can either rightlie cure, either else vnderstand the nature of those things which he doth take in hand.</p>
   <p>Therefore I haue thought it good to set before your eies this most worthie booke, which Galen hath writtē, of tumors against nature, wherein he hath most excellently set forth not onely the most apt names, but also the humors, that the same tumors doe spring of. For like as he hath declared, in his methode of curing, the diuersitie of wounds and vlcers,
<pb n="125" facs="131"/> with their natures, formes, and properties, and also with their accedents, symptomata, and causes. Yea, I say, not onely with these, but also with the knowledge of the temperaments, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and qualities of euery medicament, proper for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, with their trew deuisions and names, to that ende, that euery one of them, may be exactly and perfectly knowen from other. And for the better vnderstanding hereof, I haue added in the ende of this booke, of Tumors against nature, an other booke of Galen, of the names of medicines, which be proper for diseases, which I haue thought very meete and conuenient, for you to vnderstand, to that ende, that you may be accounted men of knowledge in your arte, not onely to be accounted so, but to be so in deede. Thus taking my leaue of you, I desire you most hartely, to be studious herein, and so being, you shall incourage me, further to procede, in other things of this arte, which may be much for your profit. And thus I commit you to the almightie Lord, who illuminate you with knowledge, of this most worthy Arte.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your louing brother to the vttermost of my power, Thomas Gale, maister in Chirurgerie.</signed>
      <dateline>
         <date>An. Domini. 1563. Mense Septembris. 25.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>