<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The Translatour to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1576</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117191_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11930</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22243</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117191</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The Translatour to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fourth parte of Co [m] mentaries of the ciuill warres in Fraunce, and of the lovve countrie of Flaunders: translated out of Latine into English, by Thomas Tymme minister. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Serres, Jean de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Toy (Toius), Humphrey</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1576</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 35, 1, 1410, that is 150, 30 pages, folded plates, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ The Translatour to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He increasing of newe troubles and warres in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> hath also increased the matter, and giuen larger occasion of the publishing of this fourth part of Commentaries, the whiche contayneth (as the other three partes do) three bookes: the first of the three in the Latin Coppy reckoned the tenth. But bycause we haue to our third part already a tenth Booke annexed contayning the summe of those things whiche are written in the first Booke of this fourth volume. I haue thought good not to translate the same in order as it lieth, but only to gleane out those principall matters which are different from the other: for that it is super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous in one work to print one and the selfe same thing twice. This fourth parte comprehendeth the actes and gestes of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill warres, from the time of the last peace concluded in Anno 1571. vnto the death of King <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth, who dyed in Anno. 1574. In the whiche there is set before thee (righte Christian Reader) a large discourse, not only of the affayres of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> but also of the lowe countrey of <hi>Flaunders,</hi> as tyme and occasion offereth the same. Accept my good will bestowed in translating thys parte to benefyte the English reader.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>