<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR ARTHVR CAPELL Knight, his singular good Patrone, the Author wish∣eth, what the worke describeth.</title>
           <author>Crooke, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117175_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19634</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6066</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117175</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR ARTHVR CAPELL Knight, his singular good Patrone, the Author wish∣eth, what the worke describeth.</title>
                 <author>Crooke, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The guide vnto true blessednesse. Or, A body of the doctrine of the Scriptures, directing man to the sauing knowledge of God : Collected by Sam. Crooke</title>
                 <author>Crooke, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Pindley, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 250, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT <hi>WORSHIPFVLL</hi> SIR ARTHVR CAPELL Knight, his singular good <hi>Patrone, the Author wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> what the worke describeth.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O whome, vnder Christ, should I render this <hi>account</hi> of my poore <hi>labours</hi> in my charge, but vnto your selfe, Right worshipfull; by whose meanes the Lord vouchsafed mee so <hi>free</hi> and comfortable an <hi>entrance</hi> therein to? Jt is the Lord Iesus, <hi>the doore of the sheepe,</hi> of whom you haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned
<pb facs="3"/> this mercie, rather to be, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong few, a faithfull <hi>dorekeeper in his house; then to dwell,</hi> with manie, in the Simoniacall <hi>taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of wickednesse.</hi> Neither shall it euer repent you, that you haue not drunke of those <hi>stollen waters,</hi> or rather of that <hi>blood of soules;</hi> wherewith too manie, in these gold-thirstie daies, doe purchase <hi>Acelda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> vnto them and theirs. Let others enrich themselues with the <hi>wages of vnrighteousnesse;</hi> let them make their boast of their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous desire, and blesse themselues in their contempt of the Lord: but let the Lord keep this for euer in the purpose of the hearts of his seruants, to deale faithfully and vprightlie in so honourable and weightie a trust. And let such as haue found
<pb facs="3"/> this blessing, in these corrupt daies, to haue a free accesse to the worke and charge of the ministerie, thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie acknowledge the same both to God and man. Amongst whome I gladlie professe my selfe to be one; and therefore, to the honour of God, and the iust acknowledgement of your Christian integritie, I commend this worke to your worthy name and Patronage: your example to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie and imitation of posteritie: &amp; your selfe with all your Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full familie, to the holie direction and safe tuition of Almightie God.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your worships in Christ euer bounden, SAM. CROOKE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>