<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Gentlemen Readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117579_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02103</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12245</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117579</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Gentlemen Readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Greenes, groats-vvorth of witte, bought with a million of repentance : Describing the follie of youth, the falshood of makeshifte flatterers, the miserie of the negligent, and mischiefes of deceiuing courtezans. Written before his death and published at his dyeing request</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Wright, William 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 <publisher>Danter, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>46 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Gentlemen Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entlemen. The Swan sings melodiously before death, that in all his life time v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth but a iarring sound. <hi>Greene</hi> though able inough to write, yet deeplyer serched with sicknes than euer heeretofore, sendes you his Swanne like songe, for that he feares he shall nener againe carroll to you woonted loue layes, neuer againe discouer to you youths plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures. How euer yet sicknesse, riot, Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinence, haue at once shown their extremitie yet if I recouer, you shall all see, more fresh sprigs, then euer sprang from me, direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you how to liue, yet not diswading ye fro<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> loue. This is the last I haue writ, and I feare me the last I shall writ. And how euer I haue beene censured for some of my former bookes, yet Gentlemen I protest, they were as I had speciall information. But passing them, I commend this to your fauourable censures, that like an Embrion
<pb facs="3"/>
without shape, I feare me will be thrust in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world. If I liue to end it, it shall be otherwise: if not, yet will I commend it to your courtesies, that you may as well be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with my repentant death, as you haue lamented my careles course of life. But as <hi>Nemo ante obitum felix,</hi> so <hi>Acta Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itus probat:</hi> Beseeching therefore so to be deemed heereof as I deserue, I leaue the worke to your likinges, and leaue you to your delightes.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>