<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ Not vnto the veriest Ideot that euer set Pen to Paper, but to the Cynicall Bayter of Women, or metamorphosed Misogunes, Ioseph Swetnam.</title>
           <author>Speght, Rachel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117735_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12750</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23058</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117735</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ Not vnto the veriest Ideot that euer set Pen to Paper, but to the Cynicall Bayter of Women, or metamorphosed Misogunes, Ioseph Swetnam.</title>
                 <author>Speght, Rachel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A mouzell for Melastomus, the cynicall bayter of, and foule mouthed barker against Euahs sex. Or an apologeticall answere to that irreligious and illiterate pamphlet made by Io. Sw. and by him intituled, The arraignement of women. By Rachel Speght</title>
                 <author>Speght, Rachel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Archer, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 38, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>¶ Not vnto the veriest Ideot that <hi>euer set Pen to Paper, but to the</hi> Cynicall Bayter of Women, or <hi>metamorphosed Misogunes,</hi> Ioseph Swetnam.</head>
   <p>FRom standing water, which soon putrifies, can no good fish be expected; for it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth no other creatures but those that are vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous or noisome, as snakes, adders, and such like. Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blably, no better streame can we looke, should issue from your idle corrupt braine, then that whereto the ruffe of your fury (to vse your owne words) hath moued you to open the sluce. In which excrement of your roaring cogitations you haue vsed such irregularities touching con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordance, and obserued so disordered a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode, as I doubt not to tel you, that a very Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidence Schollar would haue quite put you downe in both. You appeare heerein not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like that Painter, who seriously indeuouring to
<pb facs="5"/>
pourtray <hi>Cupids</hi> Bowe, forgot the String: for you beeing greedie to botch vp your mingle mangle inuectiue against Women, haue not therein obserued, in many places, so much as as Grammer sense. But the empriest Barrell makes the lowdest sound; and so we wil account of you.</p>
   <p>Many propositions haue you framed, which (as you thinke) make much against Women, but if one would make a Logicall assumption, the conclusion would be flat against your owne Sex. Your dealing wants so much discretion, that I doubt whether to bestow so good a name as the Dunce vpon you: but Minority bids me keepe within my bounds; and therefore I onlie say vnto you, that your corrupt Heart and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Tongue, hath made you a fit scribe for the Diuell.</p>
   <p>In that you haue termed your virulent foame, <hi>the Beare-bayting of Women,</hi> you haue plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly displayed your owne disposition to be Cyni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, in that there appeares no other Dogge or Bull, to bayte them, but your selfe. Good had it beene for you to haue put on that Muzzell, which Saint <hi>Iames</hi> would haue all Christians to weare; <hi>Speake not euill one of another:</hi> and then<note place="margin">Iames 4. 11.</note> had you not seemed so like the Serpent <hi>Porphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> as now you doe; which, though full of deadly poyson, yet being toothlesse, hurteth none so much as himselfe. For you hauing gone beyond the limits not of <hi>Humanitie</hi> alone, but
<pb facs="6"/>
of Christianitie, haue done greater harme vnto your owne soule, then vnto women, as may plainely appeare. First, in dishonoring of God by palpable blasphemy, wresting and peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting euerie place of Scripture, that you haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged; which by the testimony of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3. 16.</note> is to the destruction of them that so doe. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it appeares by your disparaging of, and opprobrious speeches against that excellent worke of Gods hands, which in his great loue he perfected for the comfort of man. Thirdly, and lastly, by this your hodge-podge of heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Sentences, Similies, and Examples, you haue set forth your selfe in your right colours, vnto the view of the world: and I doubt not but the Iudicious will account of you according to your demerit: As for the Vulgar sort, which haue no more learning then you haue shewed in your Booke, it is likely they will applaud you for your paines.</p>
   <p>As for your <hi>Bugge-beare</hi> or aduice vnto Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that whatsoeuer they doe thinke of your Worke, they should conceale it, lest in finding fault, they bewray their galled backes to the world; in which you allude to that Prouerbe, <hi>Rubbe a galled borse, and he will kicke:</hi> Vnto it I answere by way of Apologie, that though eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie galled horse, being touched, doth kicke; yet euery one that kickes, is not galled: so that you might as well haue said, that because burnt folks dread the fire, therfore none feare fire but those
<pb facs="6"/>
that are burnt, as made that illiterate conclusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which you haue absurdly inferred.</p>
   <p>In your Title Leafe, you arraigne none but lewd, idle, froward and vnconstant women, but in the Sequele (through defect of memorie as it seemeth) forgetting that you had made a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction of good from badde, condemning all in generall, you aduise men to beware of, and not to match with any of these sixe sorts of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <hi>viz. Good</hi> and <hi>Badde, Faire</hi> and <hi>Foule, Rich</hi> and <hi>Poore:</hi> But this doctrine of Diuells Saint <hi>Paul</hi> foreseeing would be broached in the latter<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4. 3.</note> times, giues warning of.</p>
   <p>There also you promise a Commendation of wise, vertuous, and honest women, when as in the subsequent, the worst words, and filthiest Epithites that you can deuise, you bestow on them in generall, excepting no sort of Women. Heerein may you be likened vnto a man, which vpon the doore of a scuruie house sets this Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perscription, <hi>Heere is a very faire house to be let:</hi> whereas the doore being opened, it is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then a dogge-hole and darke dungeon.</p>
   <p>Further, if your owne words betrue, that you wrote with your hand, but not with your heart, then are you an hypocrite in Print: but it is rather to be thought that your Pen was the bewrayer of the abundance of your minde, and that this was but a little morter to dawbe vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne the wall, which you intended to breake downe.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>The reuenge of your rayling Worke wee leaue to Him, who hath appropriated venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance vnto himselfe, whose Pen-man hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded Raylers in the Catalogue of them, that shall not inherite Gods Kingdome, and your selfe vnto the mercie of that iust Iudge, who is able to saue and to destroy.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Your vndeserued friend,</salute>
      <signed>RACHEL SPEGHT.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>