<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE
to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117323_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19164</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5576</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117323</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE
to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The attestation of the most excellent, and most illustrious lord, Don Carlos Coloma, embassadour extraordinary for Spayne. Of the declaration made vnto him, by the lay Catholikes of England : concerning the authority challenged ouer them, by the Right Reuerend Lord Bishop of Chalcedon. With The answere of a Catholike lay gentleman, to the iudgment of a deuine, vpon the letter of the lay Catholikes, to the sayd Lord Bishop of Chalcedon</title>
                 <author>Coloma, Carlos</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 28, 8, 126 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Political tracts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="21"/>
   <pb facs="21"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE
to the Reader.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>GENTLE READER▪</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>Lighting of late vpon a litle writtē
Treatise intituled, <hi>The Iudgmēt of a</hi> Deuine
<hi>vpō the 3. Gentlemens Letter to my Lord
Bishop of Chalcedon,</hi> I tooke and read it,
thinking to find somewhat more then Ordinary
in it. For hauing heard much talke of that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
(being now in euery mans mouth) &amp; seene
also something written, but not to much pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose;
now finding a Booke, with the Title of a
<hi>Deuine,</hi> I presumed he would say something
more then others had done. But whē I came to
read him, I found him, but like other men of
his owne syde; and particulerly so like the Lay
Gentleman, T. M. his Iudgement vpon the
same Letter, that I began to thinke it might be
<pb facs="22"/>
the very same man; the style, discourse, and
as I may say, spirit, wherewith both are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,
being the same.</p>
   <p>And that because then, that seeming to
be but some Lay Gentlemans doing, men made
small account of it, not vouchsafing it so much
as one word of answere; Now the same party
would speake a little lowder to be heard, writing
ouer the same somewhat more dilatedly, and
inserting a little Latin in some places, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
vpon him the person of a <hi>Deuine,</hi> for the
substance of both, is the same; and accusing
worthy Catholique Gentlemen of <hi>Passion, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merity,
Pretense of daunger, Partiality
to Regulars, want of respect to Episcopal
Authority,</hi> and the like: and all this vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
with so litle reason &amp; truth on the one side,
and so much gall and bitternes on the other as
that I could not but be sorry, and ashamed to
see such a thing with the Title of a <hi>Deuine.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For if such manner of writing ill be seeme
any Christian mā, how much worse a <hi>Deuine,</hi>
who is to be a light of the world, teaching men
sobriety, and temper, by word and example, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
truth and reason with him, in what he
sayth and writeth; and deliuering it in such
sort, as the manner may not betray the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb facs="22"/>
by shewing any distempered affection. For
euen that will much derogate from his writing,
though what he writeth should otherwise be
true. For euery man knoweth what a myst Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
is wont to cast before mens eyes, and how
hard it is for a passionate man to speake truth,
and nothing but truth. And this is so much
more daungerous, where it concerneth the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit
&amp; reputation of other men: which how nice
a point it is, and how soone, &amp; how grieuously
a man may offend in it, no <hi>Deuine</hi> can be
ignorant; and especially, when the party dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couereth
but so much of himselfe as may gayne
himselfe credit, and thereby giue more force
to the slaunder, or imputation (as the wryter
doth, stiling himselfe <hi>Deuine;)</hi> and on the
other syde so concealing his particuler person,
that the partyes grieued know not of whome to
complayne, nor where to haue remedy.</p>
   <p>And whereas it was to be expected of a
<hi>Deuine,</hi> that he should handle the matter
substantially and solidly, I found no such thing
heere, but euen the very mayne Question for
the most part mistated. For the Controuersy
being of the Authority of <hi>Ordinary,</hi> as <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary,</hi>
how it may stand with the safety of
Catholiques in these tymes, and vnder these
<pb facs="23"/>
lawes; the writer flyeth from it to Episcopall
Authority in generall, Obedience to lawfull Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stours,
Gouernement of the Church, and the
like; whereof no man maketh any doubt. Or if
he happen a litle to touch the point, he doth but
touch it, and so slenderly, that any man may see
he hath not much confidence in his cause, but
seeketh rather to carry it by the Title, then rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
of a <hi>Deuine.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Wherefore finding my selfe euery way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued
of my expectation, both for the matter
and manner; and considering on the one side
the harme, which euen the bare Name, or Title
of a <hi>Deuine</hi> might do, among many that looke
not farre into things, and the wrong that it
might do to those three worthy Persons, and
zealous Catholiques in particuler, agaynst
whome this writyng is chiefly intended, and to
the cause of Catholiques in generall; I thought
best to make some answere to it, though I be
both least fit of a thousand, &amp; that this course of
writing be for the most part disallowed by wise
men, as being a thing that doth minister more
matter of dissention, and keepeth those things
longer on foot, which were better buryed.</p>
   <p>For some answere must be sometymes made,
least such men thinke they haue wonne the field:
<pb facs="23"/>
and indeed the silence of the one syde, seemeth
to haue made the other take more hart, and to
speake, and to write more freely, because per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
they thinke men will still be as temperate
of their pennes, as they haue beene, and are
still, of their tongues. But they must think that
this extreme heate of writing will force men
somewhat to alter their course: hoping that the
necessity of a iust defence may plead their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse,
&amp; that the end of this Warre wilbe Peace,
which is my desire also, &amp; intention in this my
Answere: which the God of Peace vouchsafe
to graunt vs. And so I come to the matter:
which as the <hi>Deuine</hi> diuideth into fiue Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions;
the first shewing the Letter to proceed
from passion; the 2. from Temerity; the 3. the
motiues to be humane and worldly; the 4. that
the temporall daungers are meerely pretended;
the 5. that their cause of publique disauowing
the Bishops Authority, is pretended &amp; feigned:
so shall I endeauour in so many Sections, to
shew all the Contrary.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>