<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVorshipfull Sir William Throckmorton, Knight; and to the Lady Cecilie his vertuous and beloued wife, E▪ G. wisheth continuance and increase of all heauenly and earthly happinesse, to their perpe∣tuall comfort.</title>
           <author>Graile, Edmund</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117271_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02024</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12171</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117271</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVorshipfull Sir William Throckmorton, Knight; and to the Lady Cecilie his vertuous and beloued wife, E▪ G. wisheth continuance and increase of all heauenly and earthly happinesse, to their perpe∣tuall comfort.</title>
                 <author>Graile, Edmund</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Little Timothe his lesson: or, A summary relation of the historicall part of holy scripture : plainely and familiarly comprized in meeter, for the helpe of memory, and instruction of the ignorant in the writings of God. By E.G. Mr. in Arts, and practitioner in physicke for the Kings hospitall of St. Bartholomew, in the city of Glocester</title>
                 <author>Graile, Edmond</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hall, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Jonas (Jonah)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 106 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVorshipfull Sir <hi>William Throckmorton,</hi> Knight; and to the Lady <hi>Cecilie</hi> his vertuous and beloued wife, <hi>E▪ G.</hi> wisheth continuance and increase of all heauenly and earthly happinesse, to their perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall comfort.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O none more rightly then to you I owe,</l>
      <l>this Map (for memory) of holy writ:</l>
      <l>The former part, you quickned as you know</l>
      <l>by daining grace and liking vnto it,</l>
      <l>When as in dust it lay, a birth forlorne</l>
      <l>And durst not further <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ye for feare of scorne.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And from that influence, the later budde</l>
      <l>hath sprouted out to satisfie desire:</l>
      <l>But all in priuate meant, for walles of mudde,</l>
      <l>fit countrey Cottages, but mount not higher.</l>
      <l>And that it comes with characters thus clad,</l>
      <l>Authority gaue charge they should be had.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>To presse vnto the <hi>Presse,</hi> this world in Print,</l>
      <l>where wit with wisdome vvarres, and humors hold;</l>
      <l>The raines on reason, to prescribe the stint</l>
      <l>and measures that the best, which seemes most bold,</l>
      <l>In meaner vvits I doe it madnesse deeme</l>
      <l>Since worthier works doe misse of right esteeme.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But call you that oppression of the <hi>Presse,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>when higher powers command and I obey?</l>
      <l>I rather thinke, I should be iudg'd no lesse</l>
      <l>then void of reason heerein to gaine-say.</l>
      <l>The spreading theirs, the springing is your owne▪</l>
      <l>And by the timely fruit, let tree be known.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <l>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 17. 18▪ 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. 24 2. <hi>Iohn v.</hi> 4.</note> If masters would in <hi>Abrahams</hi> steps insist,</l>
      <l>if Mothers <hi>Bathsh eha's,</hi> or <hi>Hanna's</hi> vvere,</l>
      <l>If Ladies like <hi>th'Elect,</hi> from vvhat they list,</l>
      <l>Would curbe their families to God his feare,</l>
      <l>Then should this simple plant haue place inough,</l>
      <l>Then should the fruits be seene to follow proofe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>If grand-dame <hi>Lois,</hi> her Lesson were in vse</l>
      <l>vve should not see young children from the shell</l>
      <l>To sweare, to curse, to practise all abuse,</l>
      <l>and by their parents patterne to rebell:</l>
      <l>
         <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 5. compared with cap. 3. 15</note> For from the faith that in her first did dwell,</l>
      <l>young <hi>Timothy</hi> could talke and Scriptures tell.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And for impression in that tender mould,</l>
      <l>and best those vessels nevv at first to season,</l>
      <l>This paines was meant, and by all meanes I could,</l>
      <l>made fitte for their capacity and reason.</l>
      <l>Story we know, with pleasure spendeth time,</l>
      <l>And what runnes readier on the tongue then ryme?</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Blessed be God, good <hi>Ioshua</hi> his minde,</l>
      <l>doth plenteously, your worships hearts possesse,</l>
      <l>The comforts in his sacred worde you finde,</l>
      <l>procure no doubt the fruits which shew no lesse.</l>
      <l>And that you may with grace be euer blest</l>
      <l>I humbly pray, and euermore I rest</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your worships most bounden EDMVND GRAILE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>