<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117379_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17965</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4625</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117379</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A carrier to a king. Or Doctour Carrier (Chaplayne to K. Iames of happy memory) his motiues of renoncing the protestant religio [n] : &amp; imbracing the Cath. Roman. Directed to the sayd K. Maiesty</title>
                 <author>Carier, Benjamin</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>130, 2 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>The Authour of the ensuing Discourse is <hi>M. Beniamin Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier,</hi> Doctour of Diuinity: A man (as is well knowne vnto the world) of no small Name and Credit among the Protestants whiles he liued, as hauing byn a <hi>TEACHER</hi> in their Colledges, a famous <hi>PREACHER</hi> in their Pulpittes, a <hi>DOCTOVR</hi> in their Schooles, a <hi>CHANON</hi> in their Churches, CHAPLAINE to
<pb n="4" facs="4"/> the King his most excellent Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty flowing in wealth, supported with the credit of the Court, &amp; very likely in short tyme to haue byn promoted to higher Ecclesiastical Dignities, had he persisted in the course of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour Profession.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding all these world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly allurements, which are no small cuticing-baytes to entangle, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witch an vnstayed soule; he hauing from his greener yeares, euen wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed himselfe in the choycest wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the most learned Protestants, and confronting in his mature age their wauering opinions with the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niforme and setled consent of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers, found the new so op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posite to the old, that at length (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauing light from the Father of lights) he resolued to wander no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, like a lost sheepe in the desert of Darknes, but to repayre vnto the fold of the Catholike Roman Church;
<pb n="5" facs="4"/> choosing rather a volūtarily banish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from his owne Countrey, &amp; like a zealous Moyses to be afflicted with the people of God, then to liue in the sinfull pleasures, and puddles of this world.</p>
   <p>These, and the like pregnant pointes are very learnedly, and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily debated in this Treatise; the which I wish thee, good Reader, to peruse with heedful attention, to the end the Authours paynes and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour may turne vnto thy profit, if by chance thou be alienated from the Catholike Roman Religion; togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with humble supplication vnto our Lord Iesus, that he would vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe, to illuminate thy vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in this daungerous passage of thy Eternall Saluation; that so thou mayest prefer light before Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Truth before Falshood, Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Religion, before particular opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, as <hi>Doctor Carrier</hi> did vpon
<pb n="6" facs="5"/> such sound grounds, as he hath heere briefly layd downe vnto thy view, in the ensuing discourse.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>