<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Poem]</title>
           <author>Regal, Phin. Fletcher</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117620_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00948</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11058</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117620</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Poem]</title>
                 <author>Regal, Phin. Fletcher</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Christs victorie, and triumph in Heauen, and earth, ouer, and after death</title>
                 <author>Fletcher, Giles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legge (Legg), Cantrell</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 45, 3, 47-78, 81-83, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <lg>
      <l>FOnd ladds, that spend so fast your poasting time,</l>
      <l>(Too poasting time, that spends your time as fast)</l>
      <l>To chaunt light toyes, or frame some wanton time,</l>
      <l>Where idle boyes may glut their lustfull tast,</l>
      <l>Or else with praise to cloath some fleshly shine</l>
      <l>With virgins roses, and faire lillies chast:</l>
      <l>While itching bloods, and youthfull eares adore it,</l>
      <l>But wiser men, and once your selues will most abhorre it.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But thou (most neere, most deare) in this of thine</l>
      <l>Ha'st proov'd the Muses not to Venus bound,</l>
      <l>Such as thy matter, such thy muse, divine.</l>
      <l>Or thou such grace with Merci's selfe hast found,</l>
      <l>That she her selfe deign's in thy leaues to shine:</l>
      <l>Or stol'n from heav'n, thou broughts this verse to ground,</l>
      <l>Which frights the nummed soule with fearefull thunder,</l>
      <l>And soone with honied dewes melts it twixt ioy, and wonder.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Then doe not thou malitious tongues esteeme,</l>
      <l>The glasse, through which an envious eye doth gaze,</l>
      <l>Can easily make a molehill mountaines seeme;</l>
      <l>His praise dispraises, his dispraises, praise.</l>
      <l>Enough if best men best thy labours deem,</l>
      <l>And to the highest pitch thy merit raise,</l>
      <l>While all the Muses to thy song decree</l>
      <l>Victorious Triumph, Triumphant Victorie.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Phin. Fletcher Regal.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>