<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PREFACE TO THE FOLLOWING DISCOVRSE, answering vnto some points, which concerne the matter in Common.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117745_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12768</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23073</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117745</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PREFACE TO THE FOLLOWING DISCOVRSE, answering vnto some points, which concerne the matter in Common.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Maschil vnmasked : In a treatise defending this sentence of our Church: vidz. the present Romish Church hath not the nature of the true Church. Against the publick opposition of Mr. Cholmley, and Mr. Butterfield, two children revolted in opinion from their owne subscription and the faith of their mother the Church of England. By Thomas Spencer</title>
                 <author>Spencer, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 95, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>A PREFACE TO THE FOLLOWING DISCOVRSE, answering vnto some points, which <hi>concerne the matter in Common.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> I am compelled to make a Preface to the following disputation, by a double law. The one is, perpetuall custome vsed in this case, from which I may not vary; the other is, the matter it selfe: some things (in our present Opponents) are transcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and belong vnto the whole matter, in such an vniverse, and common manner, that I could not answere them in any one particular passage: yet, it behooved me to giue thee satisfaction in them.</p>
   <p>Our present Opponents doe seeme to triumph,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> as if the cause in question were cleerly theirs, so as, even we our selves at the first sight might seeme vnreasonable, if we thought not so too.</p>
   <p>They leade vs with huge mountaines of contumelious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, and in conclusion,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> they esteem vs no better then to be <hi>Either laught, out or despised:</hi> So as, they account <hi>Their depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and defence, a thing condiscended vnto in courtesie:</hi> for themselues they haue another note, <hi>Instructers</hi> they are, and their Treatises are <hi>to giue Instruction.</hi> If you will know the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son why, they tell vs also: In them, <hi>There is a spirit, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiration of the Almighty giveth them vnderstanding.</hi> Wherefore, they dare and doe provoke, even <hi>Cato himselfe, to come in, and see, and censure, what they haue written and done.</hi> If you desire to know why they challenge to themselues these high preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, as belonging onely vnto them, they will not let you bee ignorant. <hi>Great men</hi> (say they) <hi>are not alwayes wise, neither doe
<pb facs="9"/>the aged vnderstand Iudgement, therefore I said, bearken to mee.</hi> Which reason is vtterly naught, vnlesse all are fooles but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues.</p>
   <p>Wise men doe vse both their eares,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and I hope thou wilt doe so too, especially in a cause of this high nature, and consequence. If thou wilt doe so indeed, I dare assure thee, that, thou shalt finde, that they haue not vttered one true word, to their profit, or our hurt: for the matter it selfe, I must referre thee to the body of the disputation, for things common thereunto, I will in this Preface performe my promise: and I will begin with the matter that concernes our selues.</p>
   <p>We defend the faith of our Church,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> subscribed vnto by all ours, yea, even by these our present Opponents, and will they <hi>laugh vs out, and aespise vs for that?</hi> Is it their curtesie to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>te, and defend themselues against her.</hi> We propound the question in her termes, and in a single, simple or categoricall Proposition. We explicate the termes of that question, in the words wherein our Church hath done it before vs, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to these our Opponents doe consent and agree. We conclude that question, in the same full syllogisme wherein our Church hath concluded it, and not varied, come short, or exceeded any one of her words. We further proue every part of that Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that is, or may be questioned; by the expresse word of God, or by a necessary application of the expresse word of God. We defend that Argument of hers, against all opposers: and finally, we reduce every Argument brought against her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to true forme, and shew what part we deny, and giue the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of such deniall, and that in true forme of art: and must we needs be <hi>laught out, and despised for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>?</hi> If they say, wee must be laughed out, and despised for any thing, it must be for these: for herin consisteth our greatest folly. If they will haue vs laughed out for these, then I leaue thee good Reader to be Iudge betweene vs: if thou wilt say he is a foole that does thus, <hi>Theirs be the day</hi> for this time, because we now want fit opportunity to defend our selues against them.</p>
   <p>All this while,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> we haue concealed the maine matter which they bring against vs, <hi>We write divirity without rethorick, and that is (in vs) either madnes, or impudency,</hi> But whether will
<pb facs="9"/>they <hi>laugh vs out, or dispose vs for this,</hi> wee know not their mind as yet. Is our stile horrid, and harsh, <hi>Is it not quaint, and neate enough for our Opponents pallet? Can we not delight their eares with iiggs, and tricks of wit? Surely then, we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be laughed out or despised</hi> by our Opponents: for that's their owne case, the one confesseth his stile to be such, and the stile of the other is so indeed. Moreouer these Opponents and our selues may ioy so to be vsed; because, all the schoole-men that haue liued in the world ioyne with vs, and goe hand in hand with vs the busines.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>We deale against persons better then our selues:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> and therefore we want maners, and consequently we must be laughed out, and despised for that.</hi> But is this true? Doe we oppose our selues to mens persons, or qualities and condition; Nothing lesse: the question on foote is an Article of faith. A point in Divinity wherein the divine authority rules the case; the persons, and conditions of man can beare no sway, nor be admitted any roome, or place, but for this time let the persons of men come in, and their qualities, honours, and conditions whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Yet we deale not against our betters, for (to say the least) we are in the roome and behalfe of our Church, which wee dare preferre before all her Opponents, for they haue subscri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed vnto her, and thereby they haue acknowledged and done homage vnto her Lordship, and Dominion.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Wee quarrell the persons of men in enuy to their aduancement and honours: because he that said thus now, said so long,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten before, with the approbation of our whole Church representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, and without blame of them that doo now accuse him.</hi> But is this true? our Opponents say so; but their proofe is insusfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, because in it selfe 'tis vntrue, and nought in the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, perhaps their party avouched thus much before, and yet not seene, or not regarded: for, who would suspect or mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubt such a friend as he seemed, and was accounted? If we were glasiers, or the sonnes of a glasier, perhaps he might see our secret thoughts and intentions: but, because we are not, we must not be <hi>laughed out, nor a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ised;</hi> because we oppose not vnto any mans honour, and adnancement.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>We cast a stone that hitteth our Mother.</hi> If that be so: if wee
<pb facs="10"/>haue done it, and still avow the deed; let vs be <hi>laughed out or despised,</hi> choose them whether; but this is impossible, wee cast no stones at all: by our office we hold vp our Buckler to defend our Mother, and to beare of such stones as are cast by others, if any stone hits our Mother, it is that which is cast at the Church of Rome, for that is the thing in question. If that stone hit our Mother, these Opponents must <hi>laugh her out or dispise</hi> her for her labour; for 'tis shee that cast it, we doe no more but iustifie her casting. If these Opponents will <hi>laugh her out, or dispise her</hi> let them do so to vs also, for good reason the Mother, &amp; Child should share alike, &amp; stand or fall together.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>We cause our Church to suffer,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> because we father a strange and vntrue tenant vpon her.</hi> Now we know we shall not be <hi>laughed out; nor dispised;</hi> for this: because we say of her no more, no not one word lesse, or more then she hath said vnto vs. If thus to impose deserues <hi>laughter and dispite,</hi> then to deny her to say what indeed she hath said deserues <hi>laughter and dispite;</hi> for the case is the same in both. It that be so, then our present Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents must be <hi>laughed out, and dispised;</hi> for they deny her to say, what she hath said, &amp; so much the more they deserve to bee <hi>laughed out, and dispised;</hi> because, they deny the thing wherein sence it selfe (even their owne eyes) doth avow, and cannot be deceived, thus far touching the thing which concernes our selues.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>They meane not to speake a word in behalfe of the impure Church of Rome:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> but rather, if it were not done already they would vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer her nakednesse, and abhomination.</hi> And we are content to admit their pretence; because, such deepe protestations, and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious cravings goes with it; but notwithstanding they gaine nothing, for two reasons, 1. because, their deed cries loud, and inforceth strongly to bring vs backe againe to Rome. I say to Rome, even vnto that Rome, which they call <hi>impure;</hi> for, if they haue writen truly, no man can deny to enter commons with them, even in those things which these Opponents call impure; because from them we may argue thus, the Romish Church can yeild salvation to her members, therfore it is the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest way to ioyn to her, seeing all sides agree in the Antecedent, but, vnsafe it is, to ioyn with other Churches; for 'tis doubtfull
<pb facs="10"/>and in question, whether salvation can there be had or no; and thus some of that Church haue reasoned against vs; if any say, with vs is perfection, and puritie of doctrine; with them, is he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie, and defection, he saith <hi>Nothing sufficient to keepe vs from Rome;</hi> because, if there were any power herein for that end, it is, because, their heresie, and defection, (in the event) is able to hinder salvation: but the Romish heresie, and defection, (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to these Opponents) is not able (in the event) to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der salvation; because, with them <hi>The foundation is held, which hath the property of that wine, which will not mingle with poyson, though a great quantity thereof be put vnto it, yea, such an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote it is and a thing so soveraigne, that, it will destroy much poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and at last quite overcome it.</hi> If all this be true, who would not be a Papist; seeing with them we finde enough to persuade vs; for who would not yeeld to tread the way to heaven? and nothing to disswade vs: for no wise man will be afraid of the thing that cannot hurt him: and this is the case betweene the Romish Church and vs; if these Opponents may be believed: if they say, They did not perceiue the issue of their doctrine, then must we blame them as heedlesse, and inconsiderate; what, will they be our <hi>Iustructers? Shall their I reatises serue to giue vs Instruction? Shall</hi> Cato <hi>be compelled to come in, and see, and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure:</hi> and yet such fowle, and grosse faults bee committed. Moreover, if salvation may be had in the Romish Church, and their heresies cannot hinder it, then doubtlesse, there is abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Intely nothing sufficient to bar vs their communion: seeing they doe as strongly avouch their doctrine to be pure, as these Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponents doe condemne it as impure: In this case, what shall most men living doe, if they be seduced to Popery? If a Priest should say, with vs thou maist goe to heaven, (as your owne side confesse) with vs is nothing to presse thee downe to hell: for, though we were as bad as you make vs, yet by the confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of yours, we haue an Antidote that in the event will preserue thee from the evill, and reserue thee for the good. Lastly, it can not appeare that we are blamed iustly: for, how much you say against vs, so much (if not more) we can say for vs; we haue the Records of all ages for vs, Councels, Fathers, history, are strongly on our side; we haue alledged them, and you cannot
<pb facs="11"/>gainsay vs: so as, now, either satisfie this last, or yeeld to ioyne wich vs: for, your selues doe teach the two first, and you may not deny them; now, in this case, what can a reasonable man doe? He sees nothing but doubtfull, and difficult questions to keepe him from Popery, and himselfe not able to determine those doubts; I say, who would not resolue thus? I will ioyne with them, not with you; seeing I haue nothing to debarr me, but some doubtfull questions that may be true, and may not be true; yet howsoever they cannot hurt me.</p>
   <p>If these Opponents would haue vs belieue,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> (as they greatlyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire) that, they are enemies to <hi>Rome,</hi> and friends to vs, they must haue esteemed the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to want the nature of that Church whereof Christ is the head: for, that makes all sure, that barrs the doore, and shutteth vp all entrance vnto her, no man will be so mad to joyn with that society, where he knowes the essence or nature of Christs Church is wanting; seeing in such a society, salvation cannot be had. It is a rule case in nature, <hi>No man will come to his losse; and 'tis as true in the state of grace, no man will venture where he shall lose heaven.</hi> But, because we finde not this, they must giue vs leaue to oppose them as enemies, not receiue them as friends, lest their friendship turnes to bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternesse at the last end.</p>
   <p>They would persuade vs,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> that, <hi>Their opinion of the Romish Church is burtfull vnto her, because, therein they quit her with mercy, in stead of her cruelty: she condemneth vs wholly, we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne her but in part.</hi> But, this commends their cause but little: for according to our common Proverbe, <hi>Foolish pitty spoiles a whole City:</hi> and this is their case: <hi>Foolish is their pity, because Gods word, and true reason does abhorre it, (at least) does not avow it. Spoile</hi> it doth, yea the <hi>whole City</hi> of God, (at least so farre as it is able) because it opens, I will not say a wicket, but the widest doore to Popery; and standeth also in that doore, and in the high wayes like the strumpet, to call in, adulterous lovers; as I haue already shewed: but let this pitty condemne them of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, (as for this time I am content it shall) yet the Romish Church hath no hurt by it: for, it condemnes them of a fault in the practise of good manners, wherein the nature of the Church consisteth not, it meddles not with their faith, wherein
<pb facs="11"/>the Church consisteth. The truth is, their opinion of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish Church is not loue, nor pitty: for, if it be their due, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they haue indeed that essence, and nature wherewith Christs Church is formed, then it is Iustice, (which consisteth in giving every man his due:) If it be not their due, because they want that essence or nature wherewith Christs Church is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, then it is a lye, which alwayes is committed, when a man pronounceth of a thing otherwise then it is in it selfe.</p>
   <p>They plead, <hi>That, we mistake them indeed,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> and in the thing they agree with vs; because, there is one truth naturall, and another mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall; they holde the question in the first sense, and we in the second: but, vpon advisement, and a true vnderstanding of thins, we say as they doe, and they as we; both concurring in this, that, the Romish Church hath the essence or being of Christs Church, but defiled with heresy, and idolatry.</hi> The case stands not thus, we vnderstand them to say, <hi>The Romish Church hath that essence, and nature wherewith the Church of Christ is constituted and formed.</hi> And vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and all her right bred children say the contradictory, as shall evidently appeare in the disputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it selfe, when we propound, explicate, and agree vpon, the state of the question: wherefore, let not our Opponents shrowd themselues vnder our ignorant mistaking of their meaning in the present question; for we shall depriue them thereof, and leaue them naked vnto the wide world, when we come to the place aforesaid, where the Reader shall finde, that we accept the question, even in their owne termes, and as themselues doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate, and vnfold it: wherein we doe no new thing; for our Church had vsed the like explication before them, as the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der shall perceiue in the place forenamed. These things being true, (as they are most true) it was a poore shift, to cast vpon vs, the shamefull reproach of mistaking their meaning, as if, we were ignorant, and could not, or malicious, and would not or over zealous and did not, vnderstand their writing: we vse to say, <hi>Better a bad shift, then none at all:</hi> all we may answere it with the like; <hi>A shamelesse shift, is worse then none at all:</hi> and this is the present case: when all meanes faile, we must be ignorant, malicious, or over zealous mistakers of their meaning, rather then they will be seene to meane falsely; their doings seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb facs="12"/>friends asunder, reconcileth not, nor bring them together.</p>
   <p>Hitherto we haue taken as granted,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> that, these Opponents doe maintaine a position contradictory to our Church. It may be, they will deny it, and plead thus for themselues.</p>
   <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> saith thus.</p>
   <q>The Romish Church hath not the nature of the true Church.</q>
   <p>We say thus.</p>
   <q>The Romish Church hath not the nature of a true Church.</q>
   <p>She saith, <hi>The Church:</hi> we say, <hi>A Church.</hi> I haue not found this exception made as yet by any, yet it is very needfull, that I propound it, and giue answere herevnto; Some man (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) will attempt his escape by it; for, vntruthes of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, must creepe into the poorest corner, rather then remaine without shelter. If there be no differrence betweene <hi>The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a true Church,</hi> and <hi>the nature of the true Church,</hi> then both these sentences are the same, and accordingly, they deny what our Church doth affirme; but they are the same, for Christs Church (howsoever it be taken, and with what word soever, it be donoted, and set out) is form'd and constituted, by one and the same formall essence, and being, otherwise, there should be two Churches of Christ specifically form'd, and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferenced: which yet, God never revealed, we never haue read, and no man therefore may avouch. If the word <hi>[A]</hi> and the word <hi>[The]</hi> import one specificall thing, then the Propositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in question are contradictorie: because, the same predicate is affirmed of the same subiect in the one, and so denied in the other: but, both these words import the same thing; for, a perticular Church is called <hi>[A Church]</hi> in the common vse of men; and so it is called <hi>[The Church]</hi> by the Apostle; <hi>The Church that is in thy house</hi> Moreover, though the words <hi>[A Church]</hi> did make a difference from the words <hi>[The Church]</hi> yet the predicate part of both these propositions are still the same, for, that difference can be no more, <hi>then generall or vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall, and perticuler.</hi> which in this place makes no difference in the predicates, which consisteth (cheisly) in the <hi>terme na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or essence:</hi> and that is the same in the Church, taken as a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick,
<pb facs="12"/>or vniuersall comprehension of all the members, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Church consisteth, or conceiued in perticuler, as it is bounded and limited within one Nation. This I say, the Church <hi>Catholick,</hi> and the Church <hi>Nationall,</hi> or <hi>O Econumicall,</hi> is formed and constituted by one and the same formall essence, and being, they only differ materially, whose propertie it is, to individuate the forme materiated. And sence it selfe doth teach it vs, every singuler man, and every distinct Nation and all men without exception, haue one and the same specificall, and formall being, Intelligibillitie, and Ellectuallitie, is the same in one man, &amp; in all men, herin only they differ; the one is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension of many individuall bodies, the other a comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of a few individuall bodies, so is it with Christs Church, the same thing that makes that whole societie to be Christs Church specifically, and formally, the very same thing makes a Nation, or a fewer number, to be Christs Church specifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, and formally: by reason whereof, when we deny, <hi>The Romish Church to haue the nature of the Church,</hi> we deny it to haue <hi>the nature of A Church.</hi> And contrariwise, when we say, <hi>The Romish Church hath the nature of a true Church,</hi> we giue her <hi>the nature of the true Church,</hi> and thus (I hope) I haue preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all men that would doubt whether these Opponents doe contradict our Church or not, and haue made it manifest, that they doe contradict her indeed, and accordingly we haue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, and may hereafter, rightly, and iustly, presume it as true, and take it as certeine, and thus am I well neere at an end in my answere to all their passages in common: Two onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, I will speak breifely vnto them, and then finish this matter.</p>
   <p>Amongst the rest of their hard measure offered vnto vs,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> I find one heape which may not be concealed: in 15. short lines, thus are we stiled.</p>
   <q>
      <p>Your mindes are prepossessed with preiudiced. They content themselues only to take vp opinions vpon trust, and will hold them, because they know where they had them.</p>
      <p>Whole volumes are nothing vnto them,</p>
      <p>Anuiles they are, &amp; in vaine should I spend my selfe in beating vpon them.</p>
      <pb facs="13"/>
      <p>Christians they are not ingenuous.</p>
      <p>They haue no care open for Iustice, and truth.</p>
   </q>
   <p>Doubtlesse this Opponent meant to infer something from this rabble: for, a man of wisdome, and learning will not speak words that serue to no purpose. I conceiue he would conclude thus.</p>
   <q>Therefore our adversaries cause is naught.</q>
   <p>This was once Bishop <hi>Iewels</hi> case, when he had to doe with <hi>rayling Harding;</hi> to whom he answered thus: <hi>I pray thee good Reader, thinke not our cause the worse, though these mens tongues are so ready to speake ill, content thy selfe a while, and thou shalt see all this smoake blowne away, even with one blast.</hi> In whose words I answer too. These ignominious termes are nothing to inferr such a conclusion: for evill men may speake the truth, and defend a good cause: Wherefore the naughtinesse of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son inferreth not badnesse vpon a cause, or question. The Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent is also false, we deny our selues to be guilty as he doth charge vs, he brings no proofe for his indictment, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we must be pronounced <hi>Rectius in Curia:</hi> and so every ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest man (who hath his eyes in his head) will say of vs: for, if accusation can make guilty, who shall be innocent. Thus, these pleaders Argument is come to nothing, like smoake carryed vp with the ayre.</p>
   <p>But let vs reason the case with him a little;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> Is this Authour bitter by custome? Is his nature addicted to sharpnesse? My selfe am not able to resolue the doubt: if he be, we willingly pardon the offence, we must <hi>beare one anothers burthen,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Apostles rule. Nay, we will pray in the words of the first Christian Martyr, and say, <hi>O Lord forgiue him, for he knowes not what he does:</hi> his passion was at this time his master: but if this ill language be acted, if it be taken vp to serue a turn, the case is worse for him, his account (before Gods Tribunall) is the greater and heavier; but for vs the better, his impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence shall commend our patience, his bitternesse our meeknesse; his crying in the streets, our silence; best it is to be like him, that as a lambe dumbe before the shearer, so was he, and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not his mouth. And thus much is enough for this passage.</p>
   <p>The last thing which comes in our way, is our Opponents
<pb facs="13"/>insulting and vaunting termes, conteined in the title of of his booke, and the end of his English Epistle; which I haue repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this Preface, num. 3. and these they are.</p>
   <list>
      <item>
         <hi>He is an Instructer.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>His Treatise serues to giue instruction.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>With him is the Spirit.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>The inspiration of the Almighty giues him vnderstanding, and him onely, for sometimes great men want w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>me, and the aged vnderstanding, and iudgement; therefore you must heare him.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>
         <hi>For his writings, they are such, as he may let</hi> Cato <hi>come in, and see, and censure.</hi>
      </item>
   </list>
   <p>We haue now the head, but we want the tayle: he presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs with an Antecdent, but his pocket holds the conclusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a consequent. Is he wise in that? Surely, a wise Logician I grant, for no man would doe thus, but he that excells in that art. But what say I? Doe I commend him for Logick? I doe: but 'tis my fault, and I craue his pardon: when he disputes I must extoll him, for his Rethorick: for, with him, that art is the queene of arts to serue a Disputers terme; and no doubt she was his queene and he followed her lawes when he would thus extoll himselfe. Doubtlesse, hereby he meant to abase vs, and our cause, else it had beene vaine, thus to elevate himselfe: and we will confesse (for our owne parts) that we must come vnder his see, and hide our selues vnder him from the weather shore; if all be true that he avoucheth: but I doubt of that, and so must, till I heare <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> his sentence; for, he commits the cause to him, and so will we too: because <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ato</hi> (amongst all Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophers) is held, the wisest, and gravest Statesman and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker: therefore we will present his particular braggs, and attend the sentence of <hi>Cato.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>He appeales to <hi>Cato,</hi>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> nay he invites yea provokes <hi>Cato</hi> to the search and censure of his writings. Even he, this Authour, a youth, as him elfe professeth, and all the world knowes, he is a yoncker and but a yoncker in age, and stadies: what will <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> say to this? The excellentest of many, must rise from his graue, to censure the meanest of thousands. Let him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
   </p>
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <p>An instructer he is, but will you know what degree he beares in that office; his title will tell you, even nothing infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to God himselfe: for he borrowed his whole title from <hi>Psal.</hi> 32: 1. onely God calls his worke a Psalme, this Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent names his, a treatise, but one thing he comes short in, that word MASCHIL in the Hebrew is written two se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall waies; in the one it fignifies to vnderstand, or things fit to be vnderstood, If it be written the second way, it signifies lightnesse, folly, or to be mad, as the learned in that tongue, haue observed. Thus much I baue beene informed by men of credit in that language, for my selfe am wholly ignorant that way: things standing thus, I say if he had written that word with the Hebrew Character, we should haue vnderstood his meaning, we might haue knowne the full value of his stile, and title of honour, but because he hath not, we can onely guesse at it: wherefore thus we say, if we take it to signifie things fit to giue vnderstanding, then in this office he giues God the mate, what will <hi>Cato</hi> say to this, that a Youth (not 30. yeares of age) becomes an instructer equall to God himselfe. No mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell though he dares <hi>Cato</hi> to his face, seeing he dare set his foote to Gods, and instruct in things divine equall to him: if he writes the word the second way, then folly is his name, and madnesse is with him.</p>
   <p>But,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> who is it that he offers to instruct? Not schollers in a Grammar schoole: no no: these are to meane for him to worke vpon; It is his Mother whome he must deale withall, his Mother (I say) that bred him, and nourisheth him, must be subiect now to his rod, and ferula; O happy Mother may she well say, that hath such a Child: so ripe, that in so few yeares can instruct his Mother; and thrice happy Sonne, that is growne vp with such speed, that so soone as he can but crawle, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently can sustaine and succour his Mother: I know this will be <hi>Catoes</hi> sentence, therefore <hi>Cato,</hi> speake and spare not, wee know thou wilt say as we doe, therefore we will heare and feare not.</p>
   <p>He telleth vs:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/>
      <hi>Gods Spirit dwels with him and by the inspirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, he hath vnderstanding. Therefore he must speake, you
<pb facs="14"/>you must not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eare them;</hi> If he proue the Antecedent, I grant the consequent, but that he cannot; nay 'tis impossible. <hi>Gods spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is fish</hi> of temperance, humility, meeknesse, kindenesse loue, so as, he that is taught by that Maister, hath learned these les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons; His schollers are not <hi>proud, vaine bosters of themselues, their minds are not lifted v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n them: but they esteeme others bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then themselue:</hi> If we lay our present Opponent to this rule, in what case shall we find him: agrees he with it? Does he notswarue from it? Let this title and conclusion of his Epistle giue Iudgement, I say no more: though I know <hi>Cato</hi> would say no lesse; yea we are sure, he would exceed us much, and thus am I come to an end of my answere to such things as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the disputation in common, and therefore I will proceed in the next place, to a formall dispute of the question it selfe.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>