<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>
I H S
</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117880_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14350</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24669</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117880</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>
I H S
</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The common places of the most famous and renowmed diuine Doctor Peter Martyr : diuided into foure principall parts: with a large addition of manie theologicall and necessarie discourses, some neuer extant before. Translated and partlie gathered by Anthonie Marten, one of the sewers of hir Maiesties most honourable chamber. In the end of the booke are annexed two tables of all the notable matters therein conteined</title>
                 <author>Vermigli, Pietro Martire</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 <publisher>Broome (Brome, Browne), William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Chard (Chare, Chayre), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Maunsell (Mansell), Andrew 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Middleton, Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 640, 380, that is 398, 2, 335, that is 331, 1, 4, 101-252, 165, 107 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>
      <figure>
         <head>I H S</head>
      </figure>
   </head>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong all the sundrie and manifold affaires of this short life of ours, there is nothing (good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Readers) that so neerlie toucheth man, whether we regard the end wherevnto he was first made, or the saluation, which he hath obteined by Christ, or the loue he hath to his owne kind, as dooth religion. For if man be carried with a continuall desire of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creasing mankind in the propagation of the flesh; with how much more ardent desire is he lead to mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplie the spirituall seed of soules? Bicause he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, euen by the light of nature ingraffed in his hart, and by a consideration of the power omnipotent, and prouident gouernement of all things, not onelie that man consisteth of two parts; the soule and the bodie: but that though the bodie die, and be dissolued into dust, yet the soule is immortall, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer perisheth. And therefore all people in the world, in what countrie soeuer they liue, and what maner of God soeuer they serue, doo most highlie esteeme their owne religion: whereby they thinke, of mortall and corrupt creatures, to make a long and euerlasting ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and of a dailie dissolued knot of societie, to make a perpetuall bond of friendship. And for this cause, when all other questions and debates, betweene man &amp; man, betweene state and state, betweene kingdome and kingdome, whether they concerne the bodie, or the temporall goods &amp; possessions, are easilie decided, and in processe of time are finished, and the aduersaries at the length reconciled: yet the controuersie in religion, which tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the conscience, which concerneth soules, which perteineth to eternall saluation, not of one onlie, but of innumerable others, is neuer finished, is neuer pacified, is neuer quieted. And as this happeneth generallie betweene all religions in the world; so the neerer that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions: be of likenesse, the harder it is to discerne the difference; the neerer the aduersaries be of countrie and kindred, the sharper is the contention, and the more desperate is the hope of reconciliation.</p>
   <p>Now then, if euer this position haue beene found true, betweene anie religions or anie people in the world, how cleerelie is it seene in the differences of the Christian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: but how sensiblie is it perceiued here among our owne nation? For who can with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great lamentation and greefe, yea without abundance of teares flowing from his hart, remember the endlesse strife which groweth as well by words as writing betweene the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manists and vs for the cause of religion? Or what hart dooth not melt, to fee the intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble rage &amp; vnmercifull crueltie, which the pretended Catholiks execute against the poore professors of the Gospell? Would to God that once all we, which be as it were of one faith; and for whom Christ shed but one and the selfe same bloud, and which hold the grounds of one and the selfe-same religion, and which haue but one and the selfe-same word, for the comfort of all our soules, would once condescend to one and the selfe-same doctrine! Which we might easilie bring to passe, if they that make themselues the rulers of the Lords house, would seeke not their owne, but Iesus Christs: if they would not trust in their owne righteousnesse, but in the righteousnesse of faith, which Christ hath obteined for vs: if they would iudge themselues; that they might not be iudged of the Lord: if they would once with indifferent eares, and obedient harts, giue place to the truth, when it is laid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <pb facs="6"/> them out of the holie word, or when their errors be plainlie confuted by inuincible ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments and authorities: if they would shake off the dregs of their owne vaine opinions, and the maliciousnesse of their owne cruell minds towards vs, and with a single hart and faithfull zeale towards God and his truth, would read and vnderstand, and laieng aside all the trust and confidence that they haue of their owne cause, would come and confer chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablie with vs, with all desire of true knowledge and sincere vnderstanding of the heauenlie word. Or if they that call themselues ancient and catholike, would once effectuallie shew that their doctrine was written or taught either by the apostles, or by the primitiue church. Or else when they call vs new masters, would shew where any one opinion which we hold, is newlie sproong vp and deuised of vs; and which we doo not sensiblie prooue to be deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from Christ and his apostles. Wherfore, to the intent that all ye, my beloued brethren, whose saluation in Christ I regard as mine owne, may haue continuallie before your eies, if ye be of the reformed church, how to answer your aduersaries, or if ye be of the defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med synagog, how to discerne your errors; I haue laid before your eies, in your owne mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther toong, the summe of all D. Martyrs doctrine: not your countrieman indeed; but yet one, that for your sakes passed manie dangerous brunts by sea and by land, before kings and princes, publikelie and priuatelie: that left his owne welth and quietnes, to instruct you in truth and godlinesse: that rested neither daie nor night to teach you the right waie of the Lord, and who contemned his owne life to gaine you to the Gospell of Christ. Innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble books at this daie are written by manie zealous and faithfull men, wherein the errors of the Romish church haue beene discouered; but yet in none, nor scarselie of all are so cleere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie confuted all the arguments of the aduersaries, as in this booke. Manie hard questions in the scriptures by manie haue beene assoiled, but no-where so manie and so difficult, as in this booke. Behold therefore here in the steed of all volumes one, to satisfie both the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and vnlearned, the true professor and the false worshiper, in all the waies of godlinesse, and all the principall points of true religion. If this will not suffice thee in all the controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies handled therein (and therein are handled in a maner all) of what opinion soeuer thou be, thou wilt neuer be satisfied. Fiue yeeres continuallie haue I trauelled herein: that since the Lord hath not indued me with such sufficient knowledge and vtterance, as I might be accounted woorthie the roome of a builder in the church, yet at the least-wise I might serue the seruants of the Lord, in bringing to their hands such excellent stuffe and matter, as the most skilfull artificers and messengers of Christ haue alreadie prepared for the worke. What paines, diligence, and faithfulnesse I haue vsed therein, I shall not need to be mine owne witnesse, others will testifie for me. And to shew the maner of my proceeding, and the manifold lets I had before I could atchieue to my purpose, by reason of the heape of Editions, and multitude of Additions that came foortn togither, while the worke was in hand, were ouer-long to recite. Neuerthelesse, by comparing of this booke with the last edition in Latine, printed this present yeere of the Lord 1583: which also at my speciall request and instance was in manie places amended, and greatlie increased, the same will most euidentlie appeere. Yet this must I needs shew you (good Reader) both for your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, and mine owne discharge; that if you find that the number of Common places herein, and euerie particular section in euerie place concur not in each respect with the said last Latine copie, vnderstand that we haue gained somwhat thereby: seeing you shall there perceiue, that I haue heaped more matter of Common place out of Master Martyrs Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries, than did Massonius a learned and painfull man, who gathered togither the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine booke: or else I haue placed some certeine things in a more exquisite order. All which notwithstanding I did by the aduise of verie learned and excellent men. And besides sundrie and manifold additions, which out of the Commentaries I haue inserted into the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon places, you shall find the Disputations, which he made at Oxford with certein learned aduersaries of the Gospell: and also a notable sermon of reedification of the church, and some learned epistles, neither in the Latine booke, nor before extant in print, but brought to light by mine owne industrie and diligent search.</p>
   <p>And least anie should mistrust, that I being not exercised in the studie of diuinitie, might not be able to performe so great a charge, and faithfullie to translate so notable a worke, wherein is comprehended so manifold learning, so incomparable knowledge, and so diuine <pb facs="6"/> vnderstanding; especiallie I liuing in the Court, as it were in continuall peregrination, and as a Rechabit among the children of Israel: I thought it good for the satisfieng of you (my deere and welbeloued brethren in the Lord) to let you vnderstand, that although the time of comming foorth of the booke were hereby prolonged, yet the faithfull translation of the same was nothing hindered. For by this meanes I had fit oportunitie to confer and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the same with sundrie persons of great learning and iudgment: neither did I presume to bring it into light, before I had found out the perfect sense of euerie thing, and was fullie resolued in euerie word, clause, and sentence, which was hard or doubtfull. And herewithall adde, that what want of skill soeuer might be ascribed vnto me, that hath my care and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence fullie supplied. Wherefore, all godlie Readers, being by this means persuaded, it shall be verie profitable for them to bestowe some time in the studie of this booke: whereby perhaps the better learned themselues may more readilie &amp; with greater light discerne the hardnesse and doubtfulnesse, which otherwhile appeereth in the Latine booke: especiallie, where some of the ancient fathers be cited. Whereby also the lesse skilfull and learned sort, by applieng their minds to the reading and remembring of those things, which they shall find herein, shall be fullie satisfied in the greatest matters, and be able to stop the mouthes of the most learned aduersaries, in the cheefest controuersies of religion. And for this cause would I exhort the ministers of the word, not to let passe so good an occasion. Whome in the name of Iesus Christ I exhort, that they hauing taken vpon them so weightie a charge, will not be negligent in their excellent vocation, but will wholie dedicate themselues daie and night to all maner of godlie readings necessarie for their function. For the better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance whereof, if they doo not knowe how to order their studies, and to benefit the church, I haue at the end of this Preface set downe a breefe waie and example for them to follow, with the right vse of common places of the scripture. Wherewith, if euerie one, bicause of my breuitie, shall not thinke himselfe satisfied, I refer them, which vnderstand the Latine, to Hyperius, an excellent writer to this purpose in his booke <hi>De ratione stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dij Theologici,</hi> where they shall bee fullie instructed. And when they are by this maner of meanes made fit harolds to proclame the name of the Lord in Sion, I would desire them, and all other which seeke the truth, and would gladlie haue the church of the Lord to be restored to the right forme that God hath prescribed in his holie word, that they will set to their hearts and hands to the building vp of the same: and indeuour by all meanes possible to reduce the wandring flocke vnto their owne sheepefold.</p>
   <p>And first of all ye my good Lords, whome I honour, reuerence, and obeie in my heart, with all dutie and seruice; ye to whom the seruant of God our deare Souereigne hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the sword of gouernment; ye which be the nurses, and pillers, and defenders of the English church; ye which be vnto vs, as Moses, Iosua, and Samuel to the children of Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell: continue ye the great care and zeale that ye haue alwaies borne to the true religion: and prouide that both by the faithfull execution of hir Highnes lawes, and by the vertuous example of your owne life, the church of England may be commended and well spoken of among all nations. But principallie I beseech you put to your helping hand, that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, pastours, and all others, that haue anie commission to gouerne the church and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses ecclesiasticall, be so chosen, as their godlines of life be of all men allowed, their sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of doctrine cleerelie approoued, their boldnesse in professing throughlie well tried, their gifts of edifieng of all men perceiued; and which seeke not for the desire of honour, but receiue for edification of the church, the liuings, honours, and authorities giuen vnto them: which being performed, ye shall be rid of infinit care and businesse; otherwise your labours will be no whit lessened, nor your heauie burthen lightened: but the appeales vnto you will be dailie increased, and the troubles of the church remaine vnpacified. And this will be one speciall furtherance to the building vp of the Lords temple.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, ye that be the Bishops and cheefe Prelates of the congregation; my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Lords and reuerend fathers in Christ, which haue committed vnto you the care of the Lords house, and of the ministers of the same; I beseech you for the discharge of your owne offices and consciences, for the more speedie reedification of the temple, and for the desire ye haue of the chosens felicitie, ye will haue a watchfull eie vnto your charge: and that ye will neither for fauour, nor for affection, nor for priuate commoditie, no nor at <pb facs="7"/> the speciall sute of anie mortall man, admit anie other ministers, than such as bee learned, graue, and of good report among all men: and vnto whom God hath giuen gifts to edifie in the congregation. That ye will likewise prouide by your gouernment, that all things may be doone to the glorie of God, to spirituall edification, and to a decent order in the church. That ye suffer no notorious fault to escape vnpunished, and that there be no occasion giuen to the aduersaries to speake euill of the Gospell for your sakes. That ye will by all meanes possible reconcile the diuersitie of opinions, and make that we may speake and thinke and beleeue all one thing in Christ Iesus. That ye will liue in a continuall peregrination in your diocesse: and not onelie visit all your particular churches (if it be possible by your selues, if not, by your faithfull and well chosen officers) but eftsoones also search and inquire, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your decrees be executed, and all disorders amended. Remember if anie part of the Lords house fall to decaie by your default, it shall be required at your hands; but if it be kept in good plight by your diligence and good ouersight, ye shall reape an incomparable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the kingdome of heauen. What remaineth now, when ye and other excellent men haue by your writing, and by your teaching and preaching both confirmed the true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and confuted all superstitious doctrine; but that all the aduersaries will be ashamed and yeeld, when they see your diligence in gouerning, and vnblameablenesse of liuing ioined with the godlie zeale of your preaching: if they perceiue you to contemne all things as dung in comparison of the Gospell of Christ, and to be readie, if need shall require, to laie downe your life for the brethren: finallie, if ye mortifie your selues to the world, that yee may liue vnto Christ. For vnlesse life and gouernement be ioined with preaching and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, ye labour in vaine, and withhold the truth of God in vnrighteousnesse, making the word of God of none effect. And ye shall but loose your labour in rising earlie, and in late taking rest, and in eating the bread of carefulnesse. For if all these things be not performed of you, whatsoeuer ye build vp with the one hand, ye plucke downe with the other.</p>
   <p>Againe, ye that be the heads of both the Vniuersities, haue ye a circumspect eie that there be no corrupt member within your Colleges; and where yee perceiue anie such to growe vp, let him be examined and weeded out from the good come, least he persuade Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell to commit sinne and idolatrie. Cease ye not, but declare him to the magistrates which may take further order for him, least he by his libertie infect other places in the realme.</p>
   <p>And generallie, all ye that be the common people, which liue in hope of your felicitie, and looke for the second comming of our Sauiour, be ye diligent in hearing and reading of the word. And cease not there, but if there be anie necessarie place which you doo not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>silie vnderstand, compare it diligentlie with other places of the scripture which concerne that matter. If this will not suffice, consult ye either with some godlie and learned man, or with this and such other learned bookes how that place should be trulie vnderstood. And for this cause speciallie (beloued Readers) I haue set foorth vnto you large and ample ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, whereby ye may, by the alphabet of letters, find out a full exposition of all those things, which this booke setteth foorth out of the holie scriptures necessarie to saluation. Those read, I saie, with all humilitie; but be not too curious in searching out of the mysteries, which be too high aboue you: but desire God alwaies, that ye may see what the good and acceptable will of the Lord is. For it is no woonder why a great part of the world is yet still lead in blindnesse, sith it is their owne wilfulnesse that causeth their error: it is their owne negligence that maketh their ignorance: it is their owne malignant hart that driueth the Lord to refuse them. When Augustine was conuerted from Manicheisme to the true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, hee was commanded by the spirit of God, To take vp the booke and read. And the Eunuch in the Acts, when he was diligent in searching out of a mysterie that tended to sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: God sent Philip to interpret vnto him. And thinke we that he will not send his spirit to interpret vnto vs, when we earnestlie desire him by praier to vouchsafe vnto vs the right vnderstanding of his word?</p>
   <p>Now last of all, though with griefe and lamentation of hart, I conuert my speech vnto you the pretended Catholiks of England. O ye blind guides, the leaders of the blind into the destruction of their soules! I bewaile your wofull case, howsoeuer ye your selues reioise in your euils. The God of this world hath blinded your minds, for ye disdaine the glorious Gospell of Christ, and deride the plaine sinceritie thereof; ye are enimies to the true church, <pb facs="7"/> euen to them that Christ bought with his pretious bloud; yee hate your owne flesh and bloud; ye storme and rage against your mothers children; and that more furiouslie and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouslie than against the Turks and infidels that haue no knowledge of Christ. Ye are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued and seduced in the waie of the Lord; and your ignorance is wilfull bicause ye will not take vp the booke of the holie scriptures, and labour earnestlie therein, that ye might trie and search out the truth: but ye followe your owne waies, and the deceiueable paths of your forefathers: neither will ye suffer the simple sort to read it, or the true interpretors of it. Ye knowe that there is but one true religion, and that there be assured marks to knowe the same by: but ye in so diuine a thing choose rather to trie a certeintie by such vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine marks, as the corrupt hart of man doth deuise, than by the infallible rule of the word of God. Ye knowe that all things in the world, which are out of square, must be compared by that rule and paterne from whence it was deriued. The picture of a man is examined according to that man whom it representeth, or by the first lineaments taken from him. A house to be built is set vp according to the platforme drawne for the same. A keie is sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen according to the print of the originall. Euerie offense committed against the lawe of man, is examined by the lawe prouided against that offense. If it so fare in temporal things, and that by reason of the vncerteintie of mans iudgement, humane things must be tried not by mans will, but by mens rules; how much more then must the doctrine of Gods re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be tried by the rule of Gods word, and by no other meanes? Howbeit, ye will haue no other iudges of controuersies but your selues, nor anie others to interpret the truth, but your selues: you consider not that ye be our aduersaries, and that no aduersarie parts may be their owne iudges: ye see not that we are growne of equall number with you; our bookes and volumes as manie, and as great as yours; our arguments not onelie in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as manie, but in proofe and substance more inuincible than yours. The fathers doo dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer; your selues doo varie; Councels doo erre; all men be lyers: but the word of God is true and endureth for euer. Why doo you not then confesse, that the written word is the most equall and indifferent iudge; and that the spirit of God speaking out of it to the harts of men, is the verie right and iust interpretor of the Lords will: and that no mortall man may presume to knowe his will further than he hath declared vnto him out of his holie word: but ye intermingle all, both diuine and humane things togither. Ye make the waies of the Lord to be your waies: ye thinke it vnpossible that Christ sitting in heauen can rule his church vpon the earth by his spirit, and by the gouernement of Christian magistrates, vnlesse he haue one principall prelate on the earth for his vicar: (and him onelie will you haue to be the bishop of Rome:) vnlesse the counsels of men doo establish after their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that, which the counsell of God hath alreadie decreed after his maner.</p>
   <p>Besides this, of an insatiable hatred that you beare vnto vs, and vnto the truth which we professe, ye crie out against all our translations of the bible, and ye continuallie beate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the eares of the simple, that they differ one from another, and euerie one from the truth; and for this cause ye forbid men to read them at all, vnles they be translated by your selues. We grant indeed that our translations differ in words, but verie seldome in sense: if at anie time in sense, yet neuer in matter of great importance. As for differing in words, we prooue that there was neuer yet anie mortall men, two, three, or mo, that without an apparent mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle could speake, write, and interpret one and the selfe-same thing, after one and the selfe-same maner, with the verie same words. Which interpretors notwithstanding, whilest they keepe the true sense, are not to be condemned, though they varie in words: wherefore to saie the verie truth, the difference of our translations is rather in sound of words, than in sense or meaning. And where there be anie alterations, they be seldome anie corrections, but explications. But put the case there be some few escapes of small weight in some of the first editions, &amp; perhaps some few in the latter, by reason of mistaking some Greeke, or He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue, or Syrian word or phrase: shall this make the word of God to be of none effect? Shall the people for this cause not once looke into the whole scripture for their owne comfort and edification? Shall the few small faults of an interpretor forbid a wounded conscience to seeke a medicine for his maladie, and a salue for his sore? Shall men be denied the vse of all vessels, gold and siluer, if anie cracke or flawe happen vnto them? Shall euerie pretious iewell that is not adorned with the finest gold, and with the best foiles, be cast awaie? Shall <pb facs="8"/> euerie good land that hath a bauke or bunch, be left vnmanured? Shall euerie good man that is able to do seruice in the Common-weale be abandoned, for committing one or two small offenses? If we see no pretious thing in the world, that for anie accidentall blemish is contemned &amp; cast awaie? shall the rich diamond of the word of God be kept from the vse of Christians, bicause of some few words misconstrued by some vnaduised men? Will ye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie the new testament latelie translated by your Iesuits into English, to all the English pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Catholiks, bicause some certeine words be misinterpreted therein: some childishlie affectate, &amp; some in the verie sense it selfe corrupted? You should haue dealt more charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie with vs, and not so vniustlie haue accused all our translations: but especiallie if you had spied anie thing amisse in the first Editions, which are mended in the latter; you should not so maliciouslie haue laid those things to our charge; and with more trauell you should haue learned the truth of the Greeke before you had obiected vnto vs such things, as now turne to your owne shame and reproofe. I thought to haue spoken somewhat at large in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fense of our translations: but sith that learned Diuine Master D. Fulke, whose great labour and diligence in the church I can neuer sufficientlie commend, hath so stronglie, and so latelie confuted all the causis obiected against the same, as all you that be the aduersaries shall neuer be able by all your replies to shake the credit of that booke, much lesse to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince or disprooue it; therefore I passe it ouer with a word or two: assuring you, that we haue doone nothing parciallie; but so far as God hath lent vs his talent, we haue searched out both the Latine and Greeke in all those places, wherein might be anie mistrust of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and wrong interpretation. Againe, if we according to the Greeke copies haue tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slated otherwise than your Latine translations will beare, so long as the same agreeth with the rest of the doctrine of the holie scriptures, it is warrant enough for vs to vse the same, and too great rashnesse of you to denie it. Furthermore, we confesse, that we in our translati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are not so precise, but that where the words of the Greeke, or Hebrue, or Latine be so difficult, as they cannot be liuelie expressed word for word, especiallie in the English toong, we haue sometimes added a necessarie word by the sense of the place to be vnderstood; which you haue not doone in your translation of the new testament: and therefore haue you left such vnperfect sentences, and haue giuen such absurd termes, as euerie good man dooth pitie and lament your great fruitlesse labour. Furthermore, it may be, that we haue not in euerie word kept the proper English of the Greeke or Hebrue, as neither yee haue doone altogither out of the vulgar Latine in your translation; yet neuerthelesse will the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances alwaies beare the same: and so can it not be iustlie said, that we haue anie waie altered the sense. But now would I not haue you thinke, that we haue spoken this, as though the doctrine which we teach cannot be defended, vnlesse our translations be iustified at large. For our doctrine is vnreproouable, and that which we defend is sound, and the verie same that Christ left in his word, that the apostles and all the fathers taught in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue church; that we haue receiued from them by the testimonie of their owne writings, and haue manie times sealed with our owne bloud: finallie, that we haue confirmed with innumerable books and writings, and that we will still stedfastlie defend so long as we haue breath in our bodie. Wherevpon also we conclude, that since all our translations are conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to this doctrine, consonant to the originall copies of the Greeke and Hebrue, and consonant to that, which the apostles and fathers taught in the primitiue church; they be sufficientlie authorised of themselues, without receiuing anie further defense from vs.</p>
   <p>But what doo ye of the Seminarie of Rhemes thinke, if we should receiue into our church the translation, which ye your selues latelie made (simplie I meane, and nakedlie without anie of your corrupt notes, and blasphemous glosses) would not the verie same confirme all our opinions in the cheefest matters, as much in a maner as our owne transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? For it is not your phantasticall &amp; new deuised termes, that can make Christs true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion contrarie to it selfe: that can alter the sense and meaning of the holie Ghost, that can either infeeble our true &amp; grounded positions, or strengthen your false &amp; forged obiections. Neither can the name of [Chalice] in steed of Cup, turne our Communion into your Masse; nor [Supersubstantiall] in steed of Dailie, or true bread from heauen in the Lords praier, turne naturall bread into the bodie, flesh, and bloud of Christ; nor [Hosts] in steed of Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, conuert our sacrifices of Thanks-giuing, Praier, Almes, and Mortification into the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bloudie <pb facs="8"/> sacrifice of the Masse, and hanged vp Idoll of the Altar. Nor can the name of [Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance] for Repentance, establish your Satisfactions; nor [Condigne] for Woorthie, take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie the woorthinesse of Christs death, to erect your merits of Condignitie; nor [Inuocate] for Calling vpon, establish your Inuocation of Saints; nor yet anie other of your new inkpot terms (to wit, [Impudicicitie] for wantones; [Longanimitie] for long suffering; [Praecursor] for forerunner; [Euangelize] for preaching the good tidings of the Gospell; [Azyms] for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuened Bread; [Parasceue] for the daie of Preparation; [Scandalized] for Offended; [Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state, for making Sorie; [Propiciat] for making Reconciliation [Depositum] for a thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the hands of another; [Victims] for Sacrifices: [Prepuce] for vncircumcision; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted] for Spoken against; [Resuscitate] for Stir vp; [Holocaust] for Burnt offerings; [By iuncture of Subministration] for, By ioining togither of that which serueth, &amp;c. and infinite other such obscure and new inuented words; which might easilie enough with some small Periphrasis, without hinderance of the sense, haue beene put in plaine English) that can make good anie of your heathenish superstitions. What need the common people be now set to schoole to their dieng daie, before they can learne that out of Latine, by strange and difficult words, which alreadie they knowe as perfectlie as their Pater noster in plaine Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish, with a long acquainted custome? Was this Christs &amp; his Apostles maner of teaching? Did they not speake in the plainest termes they could possiblie deuise, to make those whom they spake vnto vnderstand them? Did not babes and sucklings vnderstand that, which the Lord himselfe spake? Was not for this cause the gift of toongs sent downe to the Apostles, to the intent they might interpret euerie thing to euerie man in their owne naturall lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage? Wherefore, be ye better aduised hereafter, in accusing of our translations, before ye haue purged and perfected your owne; and before your gaines in this matter may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to the trauell that you haue taken therein. Now then, since all these translations of ours haue beene doone by faithfull, learned, and godlie men, and of a good, sincere, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie purpose, we praise God perpetuallie, and commend the good indeuours of them. And we most humblie and earnestlie desire of God, that bicause there is no perfect wisedome nor knowledge in man, vnlesse it be giuen from aboue: and that there were neuer anie mortall men, that without the assisting grace of the spirit of God, could doo anie thing so trulie and exactlie, but others after them might find some imperfection therin, it will please him for his sonnes sake to lighten continuallie the minds of men of vnderstanding, that they may dailie put to their helping hands to the perfect polishing of this excellent translation. And let vs magnifie the Lord of heauen and earth, that hath turned the enuie of you, which be our aduersaries, to the aduancement of his owne glorie, the increase of our diligence, the refutation of your errors, and benefit of his church. For ye hating vs vnmercifullie, bicause we deliuer the word of God vnto all the people indifferentlie to be read in their owne mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther toong; and yet being forced to confesse, that the same ought not to be deteined from them, haue euen against your owne wils, in some respect set foorth the glorie of God: and so by the selfe-same sword, wherewith ye thought to haue destroied vs, ye haue pearsed your owne bowels, confounded yourselues, ouerthrowne your owne counterfet and false doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, and maruellouslie established the truth of our profession. And herein moreouer are we beholding to God, though not vnto you (which ment not thereby either to pleasure vs, or to edifie the people) insomuch as by the narrow sifting which yee haue made of our opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and translations, we knowe the verie vttermost which you are able to breath and braie out against vs. And that by this meanes, if yet there remaine anie thing that lieth in our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to performe which hitherto hath beene neglected, we may run therevnto with all wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingnesse of heart, till at length we come to that principall marke, wherevnto we tend with all our desire and godlie indeuours.</p>
   <p>Moreouer, ye contend more vehementlie for all those opinions of yours which we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, than did the ancient fathers with the Montanists, Marcionites, Arrians, and other dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable sects which denied the true humanitie or diuinitie of Christ: or as though the holie scripture had as plainlie and preciselie commanded those things, as it did euerie other thing that ye and we both alike confesse. And yet Christ and the Apostles in setting downe all things in the scripture necessarie to saluation, gaue not so much as a word or signe of anie such opinion. If your opinions had beene of necessitie to beleeue, as yee pretend vnto vs
<pb facs="9"/> that they are; or if so the pleasure of God had beene, that we should imbrase them, would the holie Ghost haue passed ouer in silence so weightie matters; and for the which hee knew so great controuersie should afterward arise betweene the true church and the false? Would our mercifull God, that so tenderlie loueth his elect, and so desirouslie would haue them all to be saued; and who suffereth not his truth to faile, nor his Gospell to be hidden from anie, but from them that perish; would he, I saie, hide from his owne, anie of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie principles of religion? If he kept nothing backe from the Ephesians, but shewed them euen all the counsell of God; would he be anie thing lesse mercifull vnto vs than he was vnto them, by not shewing to vs in his written word, that which by epistles and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the spirit taught vnto them? No verelie; but what he shewed vnto them, that hath he shewed vs, that is to saie, hath plainlie taught vs in the holie scriptures. Wherfore laie aside all maliciousnesse and hatred towards vs, and discerne with a pure heart and a single eie, what the good and acceptable will of the Lord is.</p>
   <p>Againe, you would make the authoritie of your church to bee far greater, than the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of ours; bicause of a great consent of manie Prelates and Bishops. You weigh not that there is neither authoritie, nor councell, nor conspiracie, nor consent, nor custome, which is not agreeable to the will and word of God, that is of anie force. We knowe that an other foundation besides Christ Iesus, which is alreadie laid, can no man laie; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the true builders will build no other matter vpon that foundation, but such as is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued from the rocke Christ Iesus: but ye haue builded your owne vile trash vpon the same, and therfore the matter being such as neither Christ commanded to build with, nor anie of his seruants long after him vsed, nor yet is answerable to the same foundation; wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that neither your church is Christs church; nor yet the builders thereof, the Lords builders. But wee for our part haue a more certeine and assured word of prophesie for the knowledge of our church, and whereby wee take not vpon vs to woorke the Lords woorke, with anie other stuffe than the Lord himselfe hath appointed. Wee build altogither vpon the foundation of the prophets and apostles, Iesus Christ beeing the head corner stone. And we finish the temple, euen according to that paterne, which is no no lesse euidentlie set downe in the euerlasting testament of Iesus Christ, than was the Iewes temple vno Moses vpon the mount. Therefore is ours the true church, and shall continue for euer, whereas yours shall consume, perish, and come to a fearefull end.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, ye boast that the church of God hath long continued quiet without anie generall resistance till now of late, that the learned men in Germanie and else-where began to disdaine that the truth of God should so shamefullie be abused by couetous and carelesse men. Ye consider not that your forgeries crept in by little and little, now one thing and than another, whole ages betweene: that they sproong vp of deuotion; of a pretense of holines; of a wrong conceit of Gods omnipotencie; of a zeale towards religion, but yet without knowledge: that manie times your opinions either were not resisted, bicause learned men were otherwise better occupied in confuting of more grosse &amp; palpable heresies: or if they were resisted, those monuments haue perished by the enuie of your side; or else through manie barbarous nations which inuaded Christendome: that manie of your opinions grew by mistaking of councels, and misconstruing of the fathers, and of their darke and hyper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolicall speeches, and not of anie authoritie receiued from the primitiue church: that your church of Rome might more liberallie and without resistance (and therefore more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouslie) raise vp errors, hir citie being the mistresse that commanded all nations: that those errors of yours were pretended vnto the common people to be taught out of the woord of God, and that it behooued to keepe them vpon paine of damnation; that the godlie were humble and charitable: and besides the opinion they had of the authoritie and learning of bishops and councels; either for charitie they would not, or for feare they durst not find fault with anie ordinance made by them: further, that God had not as yet put into the harts of kings and great estates to defend those that should find fault with the corruptions of the church; that the professours of the Gospell had not prepared so smooth stones, nor had so apt slings for the purpose as now they haue: for God had not yet prepared the art of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, whereby the word runneth verie swiftlie into all parts of the world: that the kings of the earth had not as yet droonke the full draught of the whoore of Babylons cup, nor tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough
<pb facs="9"/> the infection thereof had shead the vniust measure of innocent bloud; bicause the mysterie of iniquitie had not yet wrought all his force, neither was that man of sinne so no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouslie reuealed; whome now the Lord dooth euerie daie more and more destroie with the spirit of his mouth. Further, that the time was not yet come, wherein God by his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall prouidence had decreed to build vp the walles of decaied Ierusalem, neither yet was the iudgement of God so neare at hand. Lastlie, that all things were not yet fulfilled, which Christ and his spirit prophesied should come to passe before the latter daie.</p>
   <p>Giue ouer therefore these insolent and vaine boastings: for the Lord dooth all things in time, in measure and in weight; his purposes are far from mens cogitations, he oftentimes maketh the vilest and basest beginnings to grow vp to the greatest advancements of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; and he knew before all eternitie, whome he had chosen to himselfe. The sinnes of your forefathers shall not excuse your wilfull obstinacie: for I saie vnto you, that not onelie they, but the cities of Sodome and Gomorrha would haue conuerted before this time, if either they had seene the wonders that haue beene doone in your daies; or else had heard the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred part of preaching, instructing, and confuting of those errors, that ye haue heard, and learned, and throughlie tried. And sith our preachers haue preached vnto you, not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, but Iesus Christ; not anie deuise of their owne, but what they haue found in the holie word: and haue taken this labour vpon them, not for ostentation of their owne learning, or for enuie they beare to your persons; but in defense of the truth, but with a zeale of the Lords house, but for reformation of Christs church, but for the manifesting of your false o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, &amp; for the earnest desire of your saluation, ye should haue imbrased them as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of God, much lesse haue persecuted them to the death. Ye should haue taken this faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full trauell of theirs, as an infallible token from heauen; that as GOD, before the first com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of his sonne, sent manie prophets betimes in the morning to rebuke the sinnes of the people, and to shew wherein the priests had violated the lawe of the Lord, and how gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouslie the false worshippers had defaced his holie sanctuarie; so now before his second comming, he hath sent heapes of these godlie and zealous preachers, to laie open the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of the church, and to gather into the sheepefold the wandering flocke, &amp; those whom he had predestinated to his kingdom before the foundations of the world were laid. If none of all these things will serue; if nothing will make ye relent; if not yet at the length ye will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the true church, for all the spirituall and supernaturall signes and wonders of your daies, for all the admonitions that haue beene giuen you, for all the arguments that haue confuted you, for all the word that preuaileth against you, for all you see the latter daie cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping towards you, and the sonne of man as a theefe in the nightstealing vpon you: if still ye will be selfe willing and obstinate; if still ye will giue more credite to your selues, than to the liuelie word of God; if no not yet ye will leaue persecuting of your brethren, by fire &amp; sword, by malicious lies and reproches, and by all maner of wicked waies ye can deuise; and that contrarie to godlines, contrarie to iustice, contrarie to all humanitie, contrarie to the law of nature, and contrarie to your owne consciences, ye will haue the iudgement of religion in your owne hands, and will haue no other interpretation, but such as your selues deuise: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I pronounce vnto you that the mightie God Iehouah commeth; he commeth, and that speedilie in his owne person, riding vpon the wings of the wind. He will not now seeke anie more reuenge vpon Pharao and Nabuchad-nezar, for his people of Israell; nor yet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Dioclesian, Iulian, and other heathen tyrants for oppressing the Christians: but hee will require the bloud of righteous Abell, at the hands of his owne brother Cain; of Lot, at his owne citie Sodome; of Iacob, at his owne brother Esau; of Zacharie, at the prince of his owne people; of Christ, at the hands of his owne Ierusalem; and of his saints and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs of England, at the hands of their owne countrimen, kinsmen, and brethren. He will not reprooue you for intermitting your vnbloudie sacrifice of the masse; and for not offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vp his sonne euerie daie to his father, which himselfe once for all offered vpon the crosse, seeing he neuer commanded you thus to doo. No, but he will condemne you for mangling his sacraments, and prophaning his ceremonies with your false seruices; for gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vnto creatures anie part of the honour that is due vnto himselfe; for turning your eares from him when he crieth vnto you out of his holie word; for refusing the congregation of his saints, and ioining your selues to Baal-Peor; for greeuing his spirit when he sounded his <pb facs="10"/> voice into your deafe eares; and for that yee haue persecuted him in his saints vpon the earth. Now the time approcheth, wherein the Lord shall preuaile against you, and shall tread all his enimies vnder his feet. Then shall ye know that the Gospell of Christ is his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer vnto saluation, to all them that beleeue: and that hee hath continuallie, since his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, spoken and interpreted to you, by his holie spirit, speaking out of his word, whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is necessarie to saluation; but ye would not harken vnto him, no more than the Iewes would vnto Christ, when he told them plainlie that he was that verie Messias. Therefore since ye will not giue credit vnto him, by the soft still noise of his spirit speaking vnto you in his word, he shall come in a mightie consuming fire, with a voice more horrible vnto you than was heard vpon mount Sina; more terrible than was there the face of his maiestie, vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouslie leading captiuitie captiue, ioifullie with all his saints; and triumphantlie with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable Angels. He shall gather his elect from all the corners of the earth: and all those, which would not hearken to his voice, he shall reiect as they that would not suffer him to reigne ouer them: they shall be cast into the vttermost darkenesse; where shall be wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and gnashing of teeth.</p>
   <p>But all vs that haue beene obedient to his word in this life, and haue sought our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse in Christ onelie: and which doo sigh and grone for his comming, he shall raise vp on high vnto him, and we shall see the saluation of our God. Let vs therefore with ioifull and true harts looke vp to heauen aboue, for our redemption draweth neere. Let vs fix our eies and minds vpon our mightie GOD, which commeth in triumph and victorie. Let vs run foorth togither with palmes in our hands to meet our bridegroome comming vnto vs. Let vs spread our garments before him in the waie, and crie; Blessed is hee that commeth in the name of the Lord, Hosanna in he highest. Then will he receiue vs gladlie and imbrase vs; and bicause we haue continued with him in his temptations, therefore shall we eate and drinke with him at his table in his kingdome, where hee reigneth euerlastinglie, and shall iudge the world with righteousnesse, and his owne peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with equitie.</p>
   <trailer>
      <figure>
</figure>
   </trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>