<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Reuerend Father in God, my very especiall good Lord and Patron, IOHN KING, Bishop of London, J. S. Wisheth all true happinesse in CHRIST IESVS.</title>
           <author>Singleton, Isaac</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117442_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12264</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22574</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117442</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Reuerend Father in God, my very especiall good Lord and Patron, IOHN KING, Bishop of London, J. S. Wisheth all true happinesse in CHRIST IESVS.</title>
                 <author>Singleton, Isaac</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The dovvnefall of Shebna : together with an application to the bloudie Gowrie of Scotland. As it was deliuered in two seuerall sermons of that occasion, in S. Maries Church in Oxford. And now published for a warning to all ill-affected Ogiluiests: vt quorum exitus perhorrescunt, eorum facta non imitentur. By I.S</title>
                 <author>Singleton, Isaac</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Bill, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 42, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Reuerend Father in God, my very especiall good Lord and Patron, IOHN KING, <hi>Bishop of London, J. S.</hi> Wisheth all true happinesse in CHRIST IESVS.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>May it please your Lordship,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue (according to the receiued cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie) made bold to recommend this Treatise of <hi>SHEBNA his Downefall</hi> to your patronage, as a testimonie of mine vnfained thankfulnesse for your many fauours and beneficence. In accepting whereof, I humbly pray you to imitate the goodnesse of Almightie God, who, as a learned Father saith, <hi>Coronat voluntatem, vbi non inuenit facultatem.</hi> For otherwise had not I this strong confidence, I so well vnderstand mine owne disabilitie, and
<pb facs="3"/>take so little pleasure in proclaiming the same, as that this liuely representation of my many defects had neuer come to your Lordships view, much lesse patronage. I know it needs a Patron; I dare not trust mine owne eie: the obiect is too neere to be well discerned. And I cannot but remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in this bookish age the complaint of <hi>Andromache.</hi> Ω <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <note place="margin">Eurip. An. drom.</note> O opinion, opinion: thou hast made many to thinke well of themselues, who were nothing indeed. Right Reuerend; let it haue your countenance, and as for others, if any man know more concerning the Subiect heere han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled, either <hi>Shebna,</hi> or <hi>Gowrie,</hi> my paines may serue to stirre vp in him a desire to profit more, that so what he knoweth, <hi>sciat &amp; alter.</hi> If any know lesse, I trust he will rather thanke me, then censure me. There is none I assure my selfe so rigid and deuoid of ingenuitie, that will denie <hi>exiguis hunc addere rebus honorem.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now the Lord that made heauen and earth <hi>blesse you out of Sion:</hi> the Lord guide and prosper you in all your waies: the Lord establish your house and familie, that you may see your childrens children, and an happy addition of many good and comfortable daies in this life, and this life ended, eternall happinesse in the kingdome of heauen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships Chaplaine in all humble dutie and seruice to be commanded, ISAAC SINGLETON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>