<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The office of a Chirurgion, and the Instruments appertaining vnto the same Art, set forth by Franciscus Valleriolus, Medi∣cus. Anno Domini. 1562.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1586</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117692_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01410</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11531</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117692</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The office of a Chirurgion, and the Instruments appertaining vnto the same Art, set forth by Franciscus Valleriolus, Medi∣cus. Anno Domini. 1562.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine vvorkes of Galens, called Methodus medendi : with a briefe declaration of the worthie art of medicine, the office of a chirurgion, and an epitome of the third booke of Galen, of naturall faculties: all translated into English, by Thomas Gale Maister in Chirurgerie</title>
                 <author>Galen</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1586</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 138 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="declaration">
   <head>The office of a Chirurgion, and the Instruments appertaining vnto the same Art, set forth by Franciscus Valleriolus, Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus. Anno Domini. 1562.</head>
   <div type="section">
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is commonlie knowen, &amp; I haue shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it before, that the other part of the Arte of Medicine, is that which cureth with the hand, which also the Gréekes doe call <hi>Ky<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgicon,</hi> for the manner of working, &amp; wée kéeping that name doe call it <hi>Chirurgia.</hi> This part as it is counted among the olde writers the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientest, so trulie both for the magnitude and for the profite
<pb n="12" facs="18"/> of the effects, it is counted the chiesect. Moreouer, <hi>Podalirius</hi> and <hi>Machaon,</hi> being the first authors of that art, as it is sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed, and the lawfull issue of <hi>Aesculapius,</hi> the father of the art of Medicine, doe declare the ancientnesse thereof, whom as <hi>Homer</hi> writeth, followed <hi>Agamemnon</hi> their Captaine in the Troyan warres, and to haue bene no small helpe to his souldiers in curing of them, not by the helpe of inward medicines onlie, but in curing diligentlie of their wounds, with yron instruments, and with other fit medicines there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto appertaining, whereby it doeth appeare, this parte of Medicine to be onelie proued of them, and the same to bée auncientest.</p>
      <p>Furthermore, the profit and vtilitie thereof, doeth of it selfe manifestlie appeare, by the curations of greate A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postumes, of wounds, of vlcers, of luxations, and of Frac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, all the which this part of Medicine doeth intreate of exactlie. And of this part we will intreate in this Chapter, and of the same we will shew forth these things what that art is, and what be the parts of it, what is the end thereof, who be the authors, what the office and dutie of a Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is, what be his instruments which he hath accustomed to vse in healing, what a one he ought for to be, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, who ought to be accounted the best Chirurgion, and thus we will finish our Chapter.</p>
      <p>Chirurgerie is defined of <hi>Galen</hi> to be a certaine order of curing, which is accomplished by accustomed incisions and adustions, and other thinges which are done by the hande. Moreouer, the author of the Introductorie, whosoeuer hée hath bene, hath defined the same after this manner (as they doe properlie call it) a taking awaie of things hurtfull, by incisions and concinations, by a certaine methode &amp; reason: In like manner it is the curation of wounds and vlcers, which is administred to mans bodie. But if anie man will set forth the order of it more curiouslie and expreslie, he wil call it the third part of the methode <hi>Therapeutichon,</hi> which doth cure diseases, by the artificialnesse of the hand, by adu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions and incisions, and by curing luxations, and by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting broken bones into their places, and such like. <hi>Guido</hi> of
<pb facs="19"/>
         <hi>Caliacensia</hi> hath so defined, that it maye be a science, which may both teach the order and qualitie of operation, chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie by adglutination and incisions, and other operations of that kinde, which bée done by the vse of the hand, resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring men to their health as much as is possible.</p>
      <p>Also, it behoueth vs to vse this name of Science more largelie in this place, and applie it vnto that parte of Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgerie which doth profit by meditation of preceptes and giuing of Methode, and not by curing with the hand. For it is manifest that Chirurgerie is an Arte, and not a Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence properlie, whose end is the bringing to effect, and not the contemplation of the veritie onelie, and for that cause <hi>Aristotle</hi> would haue the same worthelie to be an arte, and also hath thought it good to place it amongest those artes which do pertaine to the vse of the hand: But other things being put in the definition, doe kéepe their place of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in like manner, this parte is not put vnaduisedlie to the definition (that men be restored to their health) as much as is possible, for although that health is counted to a Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion, for a perpetual scope, yet that same cannot alwaies be obteined by arte, because there be many diseases vncu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, which doe chaunce, eyther because they are such by their owne nature, as <hi>Elephantiasis,</hi> or else, that as the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is taken in hand, doeth bring more discommoditie, and also a more grieuous sicknesse than that which is taken in hand to be cured. As when we goe about to cure <hi>Viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liginem, Antiquam, Lichenas, Hemorroidas, Sinuosa vlcera,</hi> and the old <hi>Fistulas,,</hi> Cancers, and to conclude, when as we haue a stubburne patient which doth giue no regard to the Surgions that gouerneth him: these are the causes why that all cannot be brought to their health by arte: In like manner Chirurgerie is diuided into two partes general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, the one is, which doth declare what things belong to the art, &amp; doth set forth the precepts, wherwith the workman be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing furnished, may worke rightly: This part the Gréeks do call <hi>Theoreticon,</hi> &amp; we do cal it <hi>Theorica,</hi> y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to saie, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or speculatiue part, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> other doth folow y<seg rend="sup">t</seg>, &amp; doth perform in effect y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> precepts of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> former, &amp; it is called in Gréek <hi>Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca.</hi>
         <pb n="13" facs="19"/> or rather <hi>Poetica,</hi> y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to say, a bringer of things to passe, for it wholy doth consist in doing and bringing to effect, and séeing that the whole Arte, doth depend of these, we maye with good cause, thinke Chirurgerie worthie to be called an arte, as whose ende, is affection and woork. For she doth exercise all her properties, either in soft mēbers, or in harde parts. The soft parts are those, which haue their beginning of bloud, and are called fleshie, and the hard parts do spring of séede. And chirurgerie doth exercise her facultie in those partes by incision, by cutting, or by taking away, by repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, and adustion. And truely of this arte, there are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine other more speciall partes, as those about the which the arte it selfe is speciallye occupied, that is to saye, Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors against nature, wounds, vlcers, fractures, and Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acions. Therefore as there be fiue parts which the art doth intreate of, so there be fiue partes of Chirurgerie, in the whole, as which doe teache vs to cure tumours, which woundes, and which vlcers, and which can put fractures and luxacions, in their proper place. But the ende where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto Chirurgerie directed all his actions, and prouisions, is the ablation, and taking away of those sicknesses, which maye be cured by ministracion of conuenient medicines with the hande, &amp; to restore the sicke, vnto his health, which ende truely the workeman cannot alwayes obtaine vnto. For those causes which we declared before, séeing that it is not in his power, to cure euery sicknesse.</p>
      <p>And this long arte, vaunteth hir selfe, vnto the famous companie of excellent and noble authors, worthie of great renowne. In whose register, that diuine man <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> the patron and defender of the noble arte of Medicine, doth of very right, challenge to him selfe, the chiefest place, by whose meane this parte of medicine, is better declared, then it was before his time, the which thing, the deuine monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which he left to his posteritie, doe witnesse, I doe meane his bookes, wherein he doth speake, of the woundes of the head, of fractures of the lyms, of vlcers, of fistules, of the emorodes, and of the furniture of Chirurgerie, and of cutting out of the Anathomies.</p>
      <pb facs="20"/>
      <p>Furthermore, Chirurgerie béeinge as it were deuided at length from the other, hath chosen vnto hir selfe a proper place, and beganne to haue hir proper professors, for in the time of olde writers, &amp; in the florishing age of <hi>Hippocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> Chirurgia was not deuided from the other parts of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, for they were then both Phisitions and Chirurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And <hi>Philoxenus,</hi> declareth it to haue florished in <hi>Egipt,</hi> which hath set foorth and garnished this Arte in many vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes. And after him <hi>Gorgias Sostratus, Hieron,</hi> and the two <hi>Apollonij, Amomus, Alexandrinus,</hi> and many other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent men, and it is certaine, that there was no meane professors of the same arte, at <hi>Rome,</hi> as the auncient. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>Tryphon, Euelpistus,</hi> and <hi>Meges,</hi> the most excellent of all, as <hi>Celsus</hi> writeth. But how much <hi>Galen</hi> excelled, in restoring, and enriching this parte of medicine, his learned Commentaries, vpon the bookes of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> wherein he doth declare of the Arte of Medicine, and vpon his booke <hi>De articulis &amp; de fracturis.</hi> And moreouer, his sixe bookes, of the first methode of curing, called <hi>Therapeuticon,</hi> and the last two of the same, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> two also, <hi>De arte curatiua ad Glau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conem,</hi> his booke, <hi>De tumoribus preter naturam,</hi> &amp; his booke <hi>De compositione medicamentorum, secundum genera,</hi> doe testifie abūdantly. Moreouer, <hi>Paulus oegeneta,</hi> ought greatly to be commended, who in a method compendious, but yet most exact, hath comprehended all Chirurgerie, both in his fourth booke, and also in his sixt.</p>
      <p>Furthermore, <hi>Auicenna, Rasius, Albucasis,</hi> and <hi>Haliabbas,</hi> being of the schoole of the <hi>Arabians,</hi> haue intreated most diligently, of the Arte of Chirurgerie, as <hi>Auicenna,</hi> in his fourth Canon, and the third, fourth, and fifte féen.</p>
      <p>Also <hi>Rasus,</hi> in his seuenth booke, to <hi>Almanser,</hi> the King, <hi>Albucasis,</hi> in a whole volume, <hi>Haliabbas,</hi> in his ninth booke, of practise of the regall disposition, neither hath she lacked hir honour, of Latines, <hi>Celsus,</hi> and <hi>Plinius,</hi> Captaines, who with great beautie, and like dignitie, haue intreated brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of this parte. Why should I passe ouer <hi>Guydo de Gauli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aco,</hi> who onely among the French, we haue knowne to haue intreated very well of Chirurgerie, if ye regard the
<pb n="14" facs="20"/> reason of the arte? We may trulie gather by his rude spéech that he wanted onelie such happie time wherein he coulde not come to the knowledge of the Gréeke tongue, nor to the pure eloquence of the Latine tongue, whilest at that time ignorance and barbarousnesse exercised tyrannie ouer good learning, which was the cause that in rehearsing the place of <hi>Galen,</hi> the truth of the author was much desired: But if God graunt me life, I will diuide those places of the Arte of Medicine, from the common place, I trust that I shall helpe <hi>Guido,</hi> and I will of a barbarous and impure writer, make him a fine and eloquent Latinist, &amp; restore him to his beutie, &amp; which our friēd <hi>Siluius</hi> hath performed in correctīg <hi>Mesueus,</hi> the same doe I faithfullie promise to the studious, to multiplie in repairing of <hi>Guido,</hi> if God prosper our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours, although perhaps without méete or equal thanks, yet shall I doe it with due labour and good will. But now I will returne to my purpose, for manie famous men, and authors most worthie of fauourable commendations, haue set forth this arte, among the which, <hi>Guido, Vigonius,</hi> and among the men of this age, <hi>Tagaltius</hi> being my fellowe in office, and my companion in my studies, haue done greate things and worthie of praise, in amplifying and garnishing this part, whereby it may be gathered, how much is vnto this art to be attributed, which so many renowmed, haue each one in his workes and monuments set forth, increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and enriched, that men might know it to be most profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and in effects most euident among all the partes of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine.</p>
      <p>Now must we show what are the duties and office of a Chirurgion, and howe he should enterprise the same, for there be thrée chiefe points which pertaineth to a Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion, wherein all the whole reason of the arte séemeth to consist.</p>
      <p>The first doth consist in loosing and separating that which is conioyned. The second is, in ioyning and bringing that to a good vnition, which is diuided. The third is in remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and taking away by incision, or otherwise, that which is superfluous. Moreouer, the Chirurgion diuideth conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuitie,
<pb facs="21"/> either by incision, by cutting off, by letting of bloud, or by scarification: That which is diuided, he conioyneth by adglutination of wounds, and by restoring, of displaced bones into their place againe, and also by curing of Frac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that is to say, broken bones. And he cutteth away su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous mattier by taking awaie tumors against nature, &amp; that by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ministration of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hand, as in extirpation diuers waies of <hi>Ganglia, Carcinonata,</hi> otherwise called <hi>Cancer, Scir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, Nodus, Strumas,</hi> &amp; other of that kind, either else in draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of water out of the bellie in Hidrops, or else in cutting off a superfluous finger, when as there be sixe or more vpon the hand, or else by taking awaie of Cataracts, which the Gréekes call <hi>Ptirigion,</hi> or the web in the eies. For truelie these be the chiefe duties of a Chirurgion, and the operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which he ought most trustelie to execute.</p>
      <p>Furthermore, that is, when he hath performed all these things, safelie, readilie, and quicklie, &amp; with as little griefe as may be, and also without all fraude and deceit, <hi>Galen</hi> estéemeth to be the dutie of a Phisition that cureth rightlie, and that onelie regardeth the vtilitie of the sicke: For these be things which cannot otherwise be done by the arte of Medicine, &amp; therefore they be most profitable in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale, and the artes thereof were had in most estima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the olde time, as the auncient writers doe declare. Therfore so profit thou, saith <hi>Hyppocrates,</hi> in diseases, that thou hurt them not. This scope must therefore alwayes be had in those things, that the Chirurgion will endeuour to doe, that he profit the sicke, and take in hand the curation of diseases with good faith and honest, and with a beneficiall will towards his neighbour, and whatsoeuer he knoweth himselfe able to cure by the benefit of his arte, that let him enterprise to doe with all diligence, but inuinsible and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable diseases, such are <hi>Oculti carni, Elephantiasis,</hi> and old Callous, hollow and fraudulent vlcers, let him not once at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to meddle with, least he get the name of an euyll Surgion.</p>
      <p>And further, because that we haue said, that a Chirurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on must safelie cure, there be thrée thinges worthie to bée
<pb n="15" facs="21"/> noted, which <hi>Galen</hi> doth mencion in his xiiii. booke, <hi>De me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodo medendi,</hi> vnto all the which the diligent Chirurgion, shal safely haue regard. The first is, that he diligently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute the perfection of his worke, which he doth enterprise, for the restoring the sick person to his health. The second is, if he may not obtein this scope, that at least he hurt not, the sicke person through his woorke: for that is the precept of <hi>Hippocrates, lib. i. Epid. textu.</hi> 50. saying, <hi>Profit thou so in sicknesse, that thou hurt not.</hi> The third and last is, that tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough diligent care, the disease do not easely returne again, for the studie of the Chirurgion is, that he by operation, may remoue all the diseases and griefes which are in mans bodie, contrarie to nature: But if he cannot bring this thing to passe, then let him take his chiefe counsail of that learned sentēce of <hi>Galen,</hi> how he should remoue these hurts. Moreouer, the cunning artist shall practise all things pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perously, if he will studie to cure diseases, by their indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which is a wittie beginning of things to be done, as <hi>Galen</hi> witnesseth in his xiiii. booke, <hi>De methodo medendi,</hi> and the first indication, is the conseruation of those thinges which are in mans body, according to nature, and the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of those which are against nature.</p>
      <p>Furthermore, those thinges which be in mans bodie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to nature, are kept by the like vse of their lyke, &amp; those which be against nature, are driuen foorth by their cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries, and that if the disease doe néede such méete curati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But notwithstāding, it is most certaine, that there are some diseases, which cannot be expelled out of the bodie.</p>
      <p>And we doe know them by this, when as the effect it selfe, of his owne nature, and whole assencie, doth refuse all or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of curing, as the disease <hi>Elefantiasis absoluta,</hi> &amp; as men commonly call it <hi>confirmata,</hi> or else when the patient (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the disease be otherwise curable) shall continue such helpes, as are to the curation necessarie, namely cutting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, as in <hi>Spaselus,</hi> or else adustion or incision, where they shalbe néedefull: and the diseases of sicke men, are made for the most part vncurable, either by the tendernesse of the patient, or yelding to the disease.</p>
      <pb facs="22"/>
      <p>In like maner we doe call such diseases vncurable, whose curation doth giue an occasion of greater euil. As when we doe studie to cure Cancer, or endeuer to helpe dayly fluxis, of the Hemordoes, except one hemorode be left open: or olde vlcers, which haue had a long issue, for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> curation of these, doe bring for the most part, more daungerous diseases in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the bodie of the patient: wherefore <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> in his sixt, xxxviiii. and xii. <hi>Apoph.</hi> doth affirme, that it is best to leaue this disease, called <hi>Cancros occultos</hi> vncured, and so of olde emorodes, except one be left vncured, for else it is more daungerous, for turning into a dropsie, madnesse, or consumpcio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> And because we haue declared before the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chirurgerie, which can not be exercised without his fit instruments. Now we will shew, what these instrumēts ought to be, by the which a furnished artist, may exercise those thinges that belongeth to this arte, and those are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally two, that is to saye, thinges medicinall, and things manuall, of the first kinde are these, order of dyet, which must be had in curing of woundes, apostumes, vlcers, frac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and luxacions: then letting of bloud, and purging, and also locall medicines, as ointments, emplaisters, fomē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacions, pouders, <hi>Cataplasmatas,</hi> and other thinges of that kinde.</p>
      <p>And séeing that great daungers doe chaunce, by appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the order of diet, by ministring, of inward medicines, and by letting of bloud, if they be not wel administred, and doe both often, bring aswell great infamie, to the Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as detrement, to the sicke patient, it shall be méete for him to vse the councell of a man learned in the arte of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, in those thinges, by whose prescription, he may as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suredly apply helpes to the health of the sick. For the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribing of wholesome dyet, the omission of bloud, and the geuing of a sollutiue medicine, belong to a maister in the arte of medicine. For these are helpes of great waight and importaunce, and such as require a man of great wisedome and iudgement, and of no lesse prudence and exercise.</p>
      <p>Wherefore I can not but be gréeued, for that I consider a great many men, to worke foolishly, let mée not say impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently,
<pb n="16" facs="22"/> greatly delighting them selues in the onely dignitie of the Arte, not knowing what it meaneth, which doe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes let bloud their poore patients, without any Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catiō, or councel, of one learned in the same arte, or of some graue and learned Phisition, but also they will geue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward medicines a gods name, a matter truely most wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, of publike punishment. For as much as I haue séene many, by such their rash, and bold enterprises, brought into daunger, yea, and some haue I séene miserably languished and depriued of lyfe. Therefore let not that young Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which would be estéemed worthie of his arte, presume to take in hande these thinges, without the councell of an auncient maister, learned in the same arte, or else a graue Phisition, such a one which is learned in the arte of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, the matter it selfe geuing also such libertie or time.</p>
      <p>But otherwise, if there be no learned maister present, or that any present necessitie doe constraine the same, then truely, the younger Chirurgions may bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>t bloud, and also if néede bée, minister a medicine, so that he haue good erudicion, iudgement and experience.</p>
      <p>Moreouer the Vnguentes, where with the Chirurgion ought to be furnished, and the same to haue alwayes in his saluetorie, as these, <hi>Vnguentum Basilicum, Vnguentum A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolorum, Vnguentum Aureum, Vnguentum Album,</hi> and <hi>Vnguentum de Althea,</hi> as <hi>Basilicon,</hi> to superate and mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and <hi>Apostolicon</hi> to mundifie and clense: <hi>Vnguentum Aureum,</hi> to incarnate and to fill, <hi>Vnguentum Album,</hi> to ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catrise, <hi>Vnguentum de Althea,</hi> to cease dolour and paine, and to make soft.</p>
      <p>Moreouer, as for emplaisters, pouders, fomentations, and such like, the expert Chirurgion, doth prescribe of them very many sortes, according to the reason of curing. And these are the medicinall instruments, pertaining to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> art of Surgerie. By y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> manual instrumēts, ye shal chiefely vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stād instrumēts of yron, very méete &amp; most necessarie, to the Chirurgiōs vse, wherof some are to make incisiō, &amp; to cut of a thing other some are to draw out, &amp; certaine are to search, also some be properly to stitch or sowe, and other some to
<pb facs="23"/> make adustion, to cut or make incision. <hi>Forfices, Nouacula, rasorius, scalpellum, Chirurgicum,</hi> for Phlebotomie, <hi>seu, lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetam, forsipes</hi> to draw out, called commōly <hi>Tenaculae vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellae, seu volcellae,</hi> which in French they call <hi>pinsettas,</hi> the crooked hooke, <hi>vncus seu vncinus,</hi> and that Yron instrument which y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Grecians call <hi>Diocleum graphiscum,</hi> is apt as <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> writeth, to draw out arrowes. For to serch, we doe fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vse a <hi>probe,</hi> for to sow, a néedell and a quill are properly vsed, and to adustion diuerse kindes of <hi>cauteries,</hi> commonly called actuall, are occupied, and for the variable meanes of their vse, they haue diuerse figures, and diuers names, for some be sharpe at the point, and other be not, and other <hi>cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris,</hi> they call <hi>myrtea, oliuaria, dactilica, cultellaria,</hi> so called of the similitude of thinges, which these instrumentes doe represent, for the <hi>cauteris</hi> called <hi>Mirtia,</hi> doe imitate the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of the leaues of Mirtills, <hi>Oliuaria,</hi> of an Oliefe, &amp; <hi>dac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilica,</hi> of the Date, as <hi>Cultellaria,</hi> doth represent the forme of a knife, these are the common instruments necessarie for Chirurgions. There are certaine other instruments pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and appointed to certaine partes of the bodie, as <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dioli,</hi> which the common Chirurgions call <hi>Trepans, malle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, scalpri,</hi> and the same are conuenient to scrape, cut, or pul out bones, as well of the head, as other parts, euen as <hi>Falx</hi> is proper to the fundament, <hi>speculum oris,</hi> to the mouth, and <hi>speculum matricis,</hi> to the matrise, there are innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble other sorts of instrumentes, conuenient to drawe out dartes, gunshots, &amp; other infixed things, whereof to speake I doe now cease, and will prepare my selfe, to set out a Chirurgion, what maner a man the best Chirurgiō should be, which thing, I often times haue declared to be the chefe effect of the matter, for wée know what <hi>Galen</hi> hath saide, of the Phisition, aswell in his booke, <hi>De institutione artis medicinalis,</hi> as also in the third booke, <hi>de naturalibus faculta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus,</hi> and in his third &amp; fourth, <hi>de methodo medendi, (Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> calleth him that cureth woundes and vlcers, <hi>medicus,</hi> that is to say, a Phisition) he saith, that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Phisition ought to be prudent and well exercised, and also he ought to be of quicke nature, and of pregnant wit, that he may promptly
<pb n="17" facs="23"/> obtaine all thinges, and verie well instructed in learning, and moreouer appointed to the best maisters to learne of, and one induring labor &amp; paine, a great louer of the truth, &amp; studious, and most déeplie vnderstanding his art, approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by much vse and long experience, and all this (saie I) must be applied to the Chyrurgion, which will bée most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, &amp; estéemed for an vndoubted Artist: but beside these, there be certaine things which doe pertaine priuatlie to a Chyrurgiō, as to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> manual Artist, &amp; do not so much pertaine to the ancient maister of the art of Medicine, for a Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ought to be a young man, or els but little past youth, that is, betwéene the same, and auncient mans estate, for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> age flourisheth most in sense &amp; strength, to exercise rightlie whatsoeuer belongeth to his art, (wherfore they which are aged men cannot so aptlie bring things to passe which arte requireth, for the imbecilitie of their senses, for they follow them rather by counsaile.) Furthermore, he must haue a sure and strong hand, and steadfast to all workes that hée shall doe, whether it be to make incision, adustion, &amp; also for the cutting awaie of a member. Also it behooueth him to haue a quicke and cléere eie, and he must not be fearefull of mind, but rather without pittie, if he do intend to cure him that he taketh in hand. Furthermore, neither let him make the more hast, neither let him cut Canteries, or cut off lesse than néede requireth, for the clamor or crying out, or for the tendernesse of the sicke Patient, but let him doe all things as though he heard not the clamors of the sicke, neither let his minde be therwith anie thing troubled: And wée haue declared that a Chyrurgion ought to excell in learning, for therein chiefelie doth his erudition manifestly appeare, if he vnderstand exactlie both the Theorike and the Practike parts, that is to saie, to know things naturall and not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, and also those that are against nature. Also if hée know what be the causes of wounds, vlcers, fractures, and luxations, with their accidents, and also what be their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient remedies, and how to remoue the same: In lyke manner he shall excell in practise, if hée haue had much and good exercise in the operations of his Arte, by working
<pb facs="24"/> spéedelie, trimlie, and readilie, &amp; consulting with the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent maisters of the same arte, in those things that pertaine to <hi>Pharmaceuticen</hi> &amp; <hi>Diateticen.</hi> And although he vse those things which be searched out by reason, &amp; confirmed by fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent vse, wherein truelie the faith and honestie of a Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion séemeth chieflie to consist: The Chyrurgion ought to be as it were, of a natural disposition, in the right &amp; easie obtaining of things w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>, that he hath to do, of a stedfast me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, of a quick remembrance, handsome in his doings, of a good iudgement, diligent and apt in searching, or inuenting remedies: but chieflie of all, as concerning manners, let him be deuout, or religious towards God, mercifull of minde, and vnfearefull in sure things, and such as must néedes bée done, and in things doubtful and perillous, he must be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and not too rash, in like maner he must be familiar, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and pleasant towards his Patients, milde &amp; tractable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the brethren of his Arte, and as the Gréekes do call him <hi>Philectairos,</hi> that is to saie, a louer of his companions. Also he must be prudent, very circumspect, and slow in prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nosticating, not a gréedie catcher, chast also and temperate, not couetous of monie, for he which doth exercise the art of Chyrurgerie rather for lucre sake &amp; desire of gaine, than for anie good wil toward his neighbour, he is no right Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but as it were, borne out of time, and thus I make an end. Thus farre I haue declared vnto you the saying of <hi>Valleriolus</hi> that learned man. But forasmuch as some men doe more regard the authorities of authors, than they doe the true iudgement of reason and experience, which two are the foundation of all Artes, and wil alleadge and saie, this is but his owne inuention, wherfore I wil not beléeue him, though it appeare neuer so much to be reasonable, shal I credit one or two mens sayings, that the art of Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie is so auncient, or that the instruments appertaining to the same art, is diet and medicaments, no I will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue it, for those instrumentes doe pertaine onelie to Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke, and not to Chirurgerie, for the instrumentes of Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgerie be onelie outward medicines, as Plaisters, Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guents, oiles, pouders, &amp;c. with a great many of yron instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="18" facs="24"/> fit for his art, wherefore I am not bounde to beléeue <hi>Franciscus Valleriolus.</hi> The answere. My friend, hast thou so soone forgotten <hi>Hyppocrates?</hi> who confuting all dispear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed sects, did conclude, <hi>That diet, wherein consisteth the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment and nourishment of the sicke man: That purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being necessarie for the euacuation of euill humours. And also outward medicines, as plaisters, vnguentes, oyles, balmes, &amp;c.</hi> That all these thrée were vnited together by the authorie of <hi>Hyppocrates,</hi> and that in no case they might be separated one from another, if we wil rightlie cure the body of man, and follow a right method, which method <hi>Hyppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> hath constituted and set forth, and willeth all men to follow the same. Then I saie, either we must breake <hi>Hyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> precepts, and by that meanes grow into ignorance againe, either else we must follow the true and right me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, set out by him, wherein he did vse all these instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments generallie and indifferentlie, as time and cause dyd require.</p>
      <p>And also <hi>Galen,</hi> as it may more at large appeare in his fourth booke <hi>De Methodo Medendi,</hi> &amp; in his bookes of purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing medicaments, where he doth confute diuerse Physiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which woulde not admit purging medicines in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward diseases, as <hi>Asclapiades, &amp;c.</hi> Saying, <hi>That purging medicaments are necessarie to be vsed, where there be great and daungerous wounds, and where there be great accidents that chanceth vnto the same, to purge &amp; draw awaie the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous quantitie of those humours, which might hurt the grieued part, or hinder the curation thereof,</hi> as he doth declare in the same booke <hi>De Methodo Medendi.</hi> And he saith in his bookes of purging medicamentes, <hi>That purgations are needfull for the curation of Cancers, Herpis, Erisipulas, Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salus, Gangrena, and many other outward griefes which chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth vnto mans bodie.</hi> And he doth affirme, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> without these things, he could not haue brought to health his diseased pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients. Thus it doth manifestly appere both by <hi>Hyppocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> &amp; <hi>Galen,</hi> that these be not onelie generall instruments, but also common instrumentes, and therefore of necessitie must be vsed, either else y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Chirurgion must leaue these euill
<pb facs="25"/> affects vncured, which he ought take first to indication off. <hi>Obiection.</hi> Yea sir, you saie verie well, for in the time of <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> the Chyrurgions were Phisitions, and were great learned men, and vnderstoode all partes of the arte, and the nature of Medicines both simple and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, wherefore it was lawfull for them to vse all these instruments generallie &amp; indifferentlie, but it is not so, for our Chyrurgions, and that I will proue by the authoritie of <hi>Tagaultius,</hi> in his institution of Chyrurgerie. The aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere. You haue sayd verie well sir, and by him I am ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie well content to be iudged, for he is both a man of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent learning, and also worthie to haue perpetuall fame, for his painfull trauaile in that excellent booke of Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie, &amp; that we may the sooner come to our purpose, I will recite a few of his sayings, whereas he declareth what the art of Chyrurgerte is, and what manner of man hée must be, and what properties he must haue, that ought to vse the same arte, how he should be trained vp in the same art, and what is the subiect of the same, and what be the things that he must cure the same subiects with, &amp; with what instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the same must be cured.</p>
      <p>Now I will recite you certaine sentences, as héereafter followeth, which are taken forth of the same booke of <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaultius,</hi> that you before haue alleadged, and I trust being well and indifferentlie construed, shall make more with my sayings than with yours.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="section">
      <head>The vvordes of Iohannes Tagaltius, declared in his booke vpon the art of Chirurgerie.</head>
      <p>TO the exact knowledge of the arte or science, which is called Chyrurgerie, it behooueth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Artist to know foure things. First, what Chyrurgerie is, what is the matter subiect to Chirurgerie, what is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> end of
<pb n="19" facs="25"/> Chirurgerie, and also what order is to be obserued &amp; kept in the learning of Chirurgerie. And we doe knowe what Chirurgerie is by thrée manner of waies. First, by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timologie of the word or name, by his definition, and by his diuision: Chirurgerie after his Etimologie, is called the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration with the hand, for it is named <hi>Apo tes chiros, cai tou ergou,</hi> that is to saie, of the hande, and his worke, because this Arte is exercised by the administration with the hand, and héereof commeth it to passe, that the minister with the hand is called <hi>Chirurgus,</hi> that is to saie, a Chirurgion: Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgerie according to the assentiall definition, is an Arte, which by the administration of the hand, doth expell &amp; driue awaie sicknesse out of mans bodie, whereof chieflie &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipallie it taketh cure and charge, or else Chirurgerie is an art, which by the cunning working with the hand, doth put awaie or remoue the sicknesses or diseases of mans bodie. The matter subiect to the art of Chirurgery, &amp; the whole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention which the Artist doth occupie himselfe about, is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie mans bodie, subiect to diseases &amp; infirmities, which disea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and infirmities requireth the help of medicaments, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistred by the hand: For all things that the art of Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie doth finde out either by reason or experience, it teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the same to be done by the administration of the hand, to the vtilitie &amp; profit of mannes bodie. Furthermore, Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgerie is diuided into two parts, that is to saie, into The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orike and Practike. The Theorike part doth teach, and is a science obteined by demonstration, &amp; by knowing the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the art. This part a man may haue, although hée neuer exercise or practise anie parte of the same, as the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Phisitions and other learned men which dailie readeth the principles of Chirurgerie: But the Practike parte of Chirurgerie, is an arte which doth rightlie and readilie, by the administration of the hand vse such things as are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented amōgst mechanical arts, which part no man can be perfect in, except he be brought vp and exercised in the same. And doth both continuallie sée other expert men worke in the same arte, &amp; diligentlie obserue such things as he dooth sée wrought.</p>
      <pb facs="26"/>
      <p>Now these two partes are commonlie exercised about these griefes, with their accidents, that is to saie, tumors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst nature, gréene wounds, vlcers, fractures, &amp; dislocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with such like, which requireth the helpe of the hand. Therefore ther are required foure things in a good Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: first, that he be learned &amp; verie skilfull in the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of his art: secondly, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he be wel brought vp vnder some cunning man, &amp; wel experienced: thirdly, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he be ingenious &amp; wise: fourthlie, that he be of good &amp; honest manners, and of a vertuous life. The erudition and learning of a Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion doth consist in knowledge of naturall things, thinges not naturall, and things against nature. The experience of a Chyrurgion doth consist in those thinges that are found out by reason, and confirmed by dailie vse and experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of them, for otherwise he will bée accounted a r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e emperike, which ioyned not reason with experience. To be ingenious and wise, it is verie necessarie, for he ought to haue a readie wit to conceiue things, and a firme memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in calling of them to remembrance, a discréete and right iudgement, an excellent perfection in working, a diligent and readie wit in inuenting and finding out of remedies to helpe his grieued Patient withall. The manners and conditions required in a Chirurgion, is boldnesse, and a minde voide of feare, in necessarie things, and in the time of necessitie, and not to be too rash in matters of doubt and perill, gentle and milde towards his Patients, and to those of his profession, to be curteous and gentle, yea, and as the Gréekes call him <hi>Philitairos,</hi> that is a louer of his fellowes, he ought also to be prudent and circumspect in prognostica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, vertuous and temperate of life, mercifull toward the poore, and not gréedie of monie, hauing these properties, hée may procéede orderlie in learning the art of Chyrurgerie: and the order to be obserued in the same, is to begin with easie things, (or as we may tearme them) common things, to perticular, or from vniuersal things, to those that be lesse vniuersall, also from things most manifest and knowen, to things more obscure, darke, and vnknowen.</p>
      <p>Hetherto we haue spoken of that part which doth apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="20" facs="26"/> to the knowledge of Chyrurgerie, and now we will intreate of the execution and operations of the same. The operations which a Chirurgion executeth about the bodie of man, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he may bring to passe his intended scope and desired end, are thrée, that is, to diuide and separate things contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to ioyne and vnite together that which is diuided, &amp; to take awaie that thing which is superfluous. We diuide and separate that thing which is contained by incision and excision, and by letting of bloud and scarification: we doe also ioyne and vnite together that which is diuided, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solidating of wounds, and restoring of members disloca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, into their proper places, and curing of fractures. Wée take awaie that which is superfluous, by remoouing of tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours against nature, as <hi>Ganglia, Nodus, Cancers, Strumas, Mirmecias,</hi> and by drawing of water out of the bellies of such as haue the Dropsie, or by cutting off such members as be superfluous, and to doe those things quicklie and readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, with a good zeale toward his patient, and not to make anie vaine promises for monie, or to take in hande those grifes which cannot be cured, and that he may more perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, readilie, and safelie, doe those things, it is requisite that he doe consider thrée speciall indications, according to the saying of <hi>Galen,</hi> y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to saie: First, the conseruation of those things which be naturall, and the expulsion of those which be against nature: The second indication sheweth whether we may bring to passe and fulfill that which the indication doth require, that is, whether we can conserue that which is natural, and take awaie that which is against nature: The third indication is that which findeth out remedie, &amp; dooth declare vnto vs with what things we may accomplish that which the first indication requireth, and the second giueth leaue to be done: touching the indication which consisteth in the conseruation of naturall things, they be sixe, that is to saie, health, or a naturall aptnesse, in doing the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
      <p>The cause of health, the effects of health, which is the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion according to nature: strength, which doth alwayes cōtend against sicknes: custōe which is like another nature:
<pb facs="27"/> Complections and temperaments which are to be conser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and kept, be their like. Nowe, for those things which be against nature, which we ought to expell and driue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie, are thrée in number, that is, sicknesse, which is an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect against nature of it selfe, and first hurteth the action, the cause of sicknesse, and the accidents, or <hi>Symptomata,</hi> which followeth the sicknesse, as the shadow doth the bodie: All these things are cured and put away by their contrarie, but forasmuch as the expulsion or curation of things doth prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipallie consist either in simple or in compound things.</p>
      <p>Note, that which is simple is cured by his contrarie, &amp; that which is compound, by their contraries.</p>
      <list>
         <item>
            <list>
               <item>Solution of vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itie.</item>
               <item>Heate.</item>
               <item>Coldnesse.</item>
               <item>Drinesse.</item>
               <item>Moistnesse.</item>
               <item>Superfluous, quantitie.</item>
               <item>Quantitie diminished.</item>
               <item>Abounding, in number</item>
               <item>Number diminished.</item>
               <item>Obstruction.</item>
               <item>Straightnesse.</item>
               <item>Inlarging.</item>
               <item>Figure altered.</item>
               <item>Luxation.</item>
            </list> by
<list>
               <item>Vnition.</item>
               <item>Coldnesse.</item>
               <item>Heate.</item>
               <item>Moistnesse.</item>
               <item>Drinesse.</item>
               <item>Diminution.</item>
               <item>Augmentation.</item>
               <item>Taking awaie.</item>
               <item>Putting to.</item>
               <item>Opening.</item>
               <item>Inlarging.</item>
               <item>Astriction.</item>
               <item>Reduction to his forme</item>
               <item>Restoring to his place.</item>
            </list>
         </item>
      </list>
      <p>In like manner in compound sicknesses, we must both consider the contrarietie of euerie simple sicknesse, and also in applying apt and conuenient medicaments for the same: But the indication for applying remedies is taken of that sicknesse, which must first be cured, and that whose cure is the curation of another, and that without whose cure, the other cannot be cured, yea, and that which most grieueth the Patient, and is most dangerous, is first to be cured. The second indication is that which sheweth whether we may bring to passe that which the first indication doth require, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
         <pb n="21" facs="27"/> is to conserue things naturall, and to expell those that be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst nature, therefore this indication is taken of thinges naturall, as whether health may be restored or not, &amp; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the strength of the patient sufficeth for life or not, and whether the cause of health may be conserued, and so of the rest. The indication taken of things against nature, is whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we may cure the sicknesse, with his accidence or not, &amp; whether we may resist the cause of these two, or not, &amp; this is to be knowen thrée waies. First, when the sicknesse of his owne proper nature is incurable, as <hi>Elephantiasis absolute,</hi> and as they tearme it, confirmed, or when the sicke patient refuseth his necessarie remedies, when the diseases are cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. As for example, the cutting awaie of a member, in which there is a Cancer, &amp;c. Or when the curation brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth a worse and more perillous disease, as olde Cancer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cured, or continuall Emorodes, for if you cure these, there is daunger of life, or of madnesse, or of consumption. Nowe, the third indication doth teach conuenient remedies for their curation, their vse, and instruments, wherewith it is brought to passe.</p>
      <p>The first of these instruments is an apt diet or regiment in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vi. things not natural. The second is, <hi>Pharmacon</hi> (which he vnderstandeth for purging medicaments.) Also letting of bloud, with plaisters, vnguents, pouders, &amp;c. But in the two first, the Chirurgion must consult with the learned &amp; graue Physition. There be many yron instruments, beside these medicinall instruments, which be both proper and common for this arte, as héereafter followeth.</p>
      <p>Thus farre we haue spoken the wordes of <hi>Tagaltius,</hi> as they be set forth in his booke of Chirurgerie, as well for his definition of Chirurgerie, as for the antiquitie thereof, and also what manner of conditions hée ought to haue, what learning he ought to be brought vp in, and what he ought to learne first, and what last, and what is the matter or sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect proper to his art, and what instruments the artist must haue, both common and proper, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> and bring to passe withall his desired scope and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> of his worke, which is the curation of mannes bodie in these thinges that hée hath
<pb facs="28"/> charge of. This is the effect of the words of <hi>Franciscus Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leriolus,</hi> as well as of <hi>Iohannes Tagaultius,</hi> as it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in their words héere aboue written Now my friend, where you did alleadge <hi>Tagaultius</hi> to proue y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> a Chirurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ought not to minister diet and Purgations, neither yet anie inward medicines, for that you saie, it doth propertie appertaine to Phisicke, it séemeth to me by the wordes of <hi>Tagaultius,</hi> that it maketh little for your purpose.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>Obiection.</hi> No sir, by your saying both <hi>Valleriolus</hi> and <hi>Tagaultius</hi> saith the contrarie, doe not they saie, that a Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion ought not to giue inward medicines, without the counsaile of a Phisition? and declareth what inconuenience hath come by the vndiscréete ministring of the same? I take this to be a sufficient proofe.</p>
      <p>The answere. No not so sir, we may not confound the instruments, which are necessarie to an Arte, because that some Artists doe abuse their instruments, neither <hi>Tagaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> nor <hi>Valleriolus</hi> meane so, but their meaning was, that those that did practise the Arte of Chyrurgerie, which dyd not vnderstand or knowe the principles of their arte, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the causes of diseases, nor yet the diseases themselues, nor how to take indication for the curation, neither yet knoweth the nature of the medicines which he doth mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</p>
      <p>These be they that <hi>Tagaultius</hi> and other learned men do reproue, which I must néeds confesse, ought not onelie to be forbiddē in inward medicines, but also outward medicines, for if I should speake of all mischiefes that hath bene done by the applications of outward medicines, how some hath bene maimed and vndone for euer, and other some brought to death, the number of them would séeme verie strange vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, and therefore we will let it passe at this time, with praier vnto almightie God for his mercifull helpe héerein, that he may moue the hart of the Prince, with the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates of this Realme, to take such order for the safegard of the people, and for the honour of this Realme, &amp; for that that learned men may be the better incouraged to studie this arte. But as concerning the instruments, there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="22" facs="28"/> these two men, neither yet anie other before their time, since the time of <hi>Galen,</hi> that hath forbidden the vse of them to the Chirurgion, for both these men doth put thē in their bookes, as most common and special instruments, affirming them as most speciall instruments pertaining to the art of Chirurgerie, that without these, those euill and vicious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours that hindereth the curation of vlcers, tumours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst nature, &amp;c. cannot be purged awaie, neither can the temperaments &amp; other naturall things of the bodie be kept in perfect state, without an apt and méete diet. But for to counsaile with the Phisition, being a graue and learned man, in the principles of this arte: In matters of waight, I take it to be verie necessarie, for what is he that is wise, that will refuse the counsaile of a wise and a learned man, and speciallie of him that professeth the principles of the same arte, for <hi>Phisiologia,</hi> whereof the Phisition taketh his name, is the first and chiefest parte, which he that worketh in the art of medicine doth proue, for that it doth consist in the knowledge of the seauen natural things, and in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidue therevnto appertaining. But yet this doth not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, that a learned an expert Chyrurgion should not vse diet and Purgations, and other inward medicines at all times when néede doth require: for if you would so vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand it, one part of their sayings should repugne against another, and so confound the whole, but their mening was, that the vnlearned Chirurgions, and these that be younge men, which be not well practised, that they shoulde take counsayle as well of the learned Physition, as of the learned Chyrurgion, for this Arte is so ioyneed togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that neyther maye the partes bée diuided, neyther yet the Instrumentes, without the ouerthrowe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of she whole Arte, for it was neuer perfect before the time of <hi>Hyppocrates,</hi> till that hée ioyned all these partes and Instrumentes together, and taught a perfect method and waie of curing, by a right vsing and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistring of the same.</p>
      <p>I for my part haue read no few authors, not onelie of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Grecians, but also of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Arabians, &amp; of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Latinists, yet could I
<pb facs="29"/> neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>nde, in any of their worke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, that they doe write of Chirurgerie, where they doe leaue out dyet and parging medicines, &amp; apointing the Chirurgion onely to cure with outward medicines, for I am certaine, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> in all their scope of curing, both of tumors against nature, of vlcers, &amp;c. That their first indication is, to take away those euell affected which may let the curatiō, (that is to say) to remoue away these euell humors, which might repaire vnto the greued part, and also to alter such distemperatures, by conuenient dyet, and other thinges, as might be hurtful vnto the same, and then to procéede with locall remedies, by outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication vnto the greued part.</p>
      <p>This is <hi>Galens</hi> doctrine also, that no strong medicine shalbe outwardly applyed, for the resoluing of inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, before the bodie be purged. And furthermore, in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulent, and malignant vlcers, which <hi>Galen</hi> nameth <hi>Cacoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the,</hi> and where the bodie is full of euill and vicious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, which humors, <hi>Galen</hi> calleth <hi>Caccochimia,</hi> these faith <hi>Galen,</hi> must be purged away, before we procéede to the cure of the vlcer, for otherwaies, the vlcer may not be cured, and if it bée, it wil come againe, either in the same place, or else in some other, or else the same humors not being euacuated, may be the cause of some other greater disease, in the body, worse then that which was cured, wherfore <hi>Galen</hi> doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue <hi>Thesalus,</hi> in his fourth booke called <hi>Therapenticon,</hi> saying, <hi>Thesalus goeth about to cut away the lippes of the vlcer, &amp; to apply his Malagma, of Mustard seede, by meanes whereof he hath inflamed all the parte, and made the vlcer worse, then it was before, not taking any indication of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, neither yet of the cause thereof, by meanes whereof, he committed great errour,</hi> as <hi>Galen</hi> doth say, and was accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for a rude emperike, and for an vnskilfull Phisition.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>Obiectiō.</hi> Why sir, it séemeth to mée by your wordes, and by the saying of these men, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> be learned in the arte, that Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke and Chirurgerie are both one arte, and I will assure you, if these woordes be true, which you recite of <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> that they were both Phisitions and Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgions, and vsed all the whole arte together, then I must
<pb n="23" facs="29"/> néedes concéeue, that the vsing of all these partes together, made them so excellent men, and of such notable fame, and that your deuiding the arte in two partes, and exercising the same seuerally, hath made you that be both Phisitiōs and Chirurgions, vnexpert, to the greate detriment, and ill report of the whole arte. Wherefore I most hartely desire you, for that y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I may know, both the art, and the artist the better, to declare the diuision of these fiue parts, which you haue spoken of before, perteining vnto these artists.</p>
      <p>Sir, I will right gladly doe the best that I can, to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie your desire, although I haue not that learning, in the Gréeke and Latine tongue, which I would wish for your sake, that I had, and also which this arte doeth require in him, that shall presisely set footh the same, yet with the little learning that I haue, and according to reasō and experiēce, which two be the foundatiōs of euerie arte, as <hi>Galen</hi> doth say in his third booke, <hi>de Methodo medendi,</hi> I will doe my indeuour, to declare vnto you these parts, in as few woords as I can, desiring you to accept my good will, and if I haue left out any thing, by the reasō of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> briefenesse of my wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, which other learned men doe finde fault with all, thē I most heartely desire them, both for curtesie, and humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie sake, to amend the faults that they shall finde, and in so doing, they shal not onely be profitable to the cōmon welth, in the furtheraunce of this arte, but also bynde mee during my life, to honor them, serue them, and loue them, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage mée to take further paines, to the vttermost of my power.</p>
      <p>Now that wée may accomplish our former talke, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning these fiue parts, pertaining to the arte of medicine, which haue bene set out, by these names, of the auncient Phisitions, long before <hi>Galens</hi> time, as I haue declared vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you before.</p>
      <list>
         <item>The parts.
<list>
               <item>Phisiologia.</item>
               <item>Pathologia.</item>
               <item>Hygiena.</item>
               <item>Semiotica.</item>
               <item>Theraputica.</item>
            </list> Partaining to the arte of medicine.</item>
      </list>
      <pb facs="30"/>
      <p>The first part called <hi>Phisiologia,</hi> is that which doth cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider the vnnaturall thinges, whereof the bodie of man is made, as Elementes, temperaments, humours, members, spirites, vertues, and operations. The Elements be foure, as Fier, Ayer, Water, and Earth. The humours be foure, also: as Bloud, Choller, Flegme, Melācholy. And the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraments be foure likewise, as hot, colde, moyst, and drye. These foure are the matter, whereby all the members of the bodie are made with, the temperamentes, and spirites, therein conteined, and he that shall cure the bodie of man rightly, must chiefely vnderstand, how to cōserue euery one of these, by their like, and to expel and remoue from them, their contraries. For the knowledge of these, it doth behoue the artist to haue long experience, and chiefely in that part, which wee call the Anathomie of mans bodie, which is the deuiding and seperating of dead bodies, that wée may ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by vnderstand all the partes of the same bodie, with theyr position, figure, number, place, nature, temperature, office, and affects, and also to know their names, and true diuisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and which be similer, and which be compound, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strumentall, for of the simuler and simple members, the compound are made.</p>
      <p>Simuler parts, be these, bones, cartilages, ligamentes, <hi>membranas,</hi> or panicles, fleshe, nerues, arteries, veines, fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and the skinne. These be called simuler parts, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the instrumentall or compound partes are made, and some requireth more of these, and some lesse, according to the necessitie of the member, for some member doth require all these, and some doth not.</p>
      <p>The compound or instrumentall members, be the head, the heart, the liuer, the legges, the eyes, and all other like. Which member both simuler, and compounde, the Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ought to know, with their natures, temperatures, and actions, and their other necessarie properties, or else he cannot rightly cure them, when they are greued, and hurt. But in the curing of them that he hurt, he shall distemper them that be quiet, for how can he conserue the right tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perament of any thing, whose temperature he knoweth
<pb n="24" facs="30"/> not, that is vnpossible, except it be by chaunce, as the blinde man shooteth at a Crowe, and hitteth one by misfortune, or as <hi>Galen</hi> doth compare him, which knoweth not the partes of mans bodie, with their nature, vnto a blinde Carpin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which cannot sée his woorke, cutting more or lesse, then is necessarie, by meanes whereof, his woorke doth neuer come to a good perfection. Therefore, who so euer is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert, as I haue saide before in the temperamentes, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of these parts, he can neither cure woūds, nor vlcers, neither yet any other thing rightly, neither can he tell by what way the vlcer, or wound shalbe cured, neither whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it may be cured, or not, neither yet, whether any cause doe remaine, that may let the curation, neither how to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue the same, nor whether nature and strength, may suffer the same causes to be remoued, nor how to maintaine the strength, and temperaments of the same bodie, for he being ignorant in these seuen naturall thinges, whereof the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of man consisteth, which bodie being subiect to the arte of medicine, he must of necessitie I say, be also ignoraunt, not onely of the preseruation of health, with his tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but also to be ignoraunt in the curation of hurtes, and diseases, which chaunceth vnto our bodies.</p>
      <p>Wherefore in fewe woordes, I haue proued here, bothe by reason and by experience, that the knowledge of this part named <hi>Phisiologia,</hi> doeth chiefely, and specially, aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein to the arte of Chirurgerie, and without the knowledge hereof, we shal neuer rightly, or methodically, cure any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of woūd, griefe, or disease, neither is he worthie to take the name of a Phisition, neither yet of a Chirurgion, but to be called by the name of an Emprike, or experimenter, curing onely by chaunce, without any reason, but euen as the blinde Carpenter, which <hi>Galen</hi> hath spoken of before, sometime cutting to much, and some time to little, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times marring all his woorke, for want of skill, ere that he beware.</p>
      <p>Now to conclude, for this first part, he that will be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther instructed herein, let him reade <hi>Hip. de natura hominis, humoribus, elamentis, de natura &amp; formatione fetus,</hi> &amp; many
<pb facs="31"/> other bookes of <hi>Hyppocrates,</hi> and chiefelie that where he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided the similer parts. As <hi>Osteotome,</hi> that is to saie, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uision of the bones, <hi>Condrotome,</hi> the Cartalages. <hi>Syndest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motome,</hi> the ligaments, <hi>Arteriotome,</hi> the Arteries, <hi>Phlebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomae,</hi> veines, <hi>Neurotome,</hi> the nerues, <hi>Miotome,</hi> diuiding of the Muscles, <hi>Tenontotome,</hi> the tendons, &amp;c. There be diuers other bookes of <hi>Galen,</hi> which be verie profitable to be read for this matter, as his bookes of Anathomie, also his bookes <hi>De temperamentis, de optima corporis constitutione, de fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultatibus naturalibus, de placitis Hippocrates, &amp; Platonis, de motu musculorum, de causis respirationis,</hi> and manie more worthie bookes of his, which we will let passe. There bée manie other bookes also, written by diuerse men, as <hi>Guido</hi> and other, which doe intreate of these naturall things, and speciallie of the Anatomie of mans bodie, and for that you may the easilier &amp; better vnderstand these naturall things which euerie Chirurgion ought to know and haue in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect memorie, to that end he may remoue those things which doth hurt them, or let them of their perfect operation, which you may easilie knowe if you vnderstand their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and properties, &amp; figures, &amp;c. Which Table followes héereafter, as you may heholde.</p>
      <pb n="25" facs="31"/>
      <list>
         <item>Naturall things.
<list>
               <item>Eelements be foure,
<list>
                     <item>Fire.</item>
                     <item>Aire.</item>
                     <item>Water.</item>
                     <item>Earth.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raments.
<list>
                     <item>Simple be foure,
<list>
                           <item>Hot.</item>
                           <item>Colde.</item>
                           <item>Moist.</item>
                           <item>and Drie.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Equall one,</item>
                     <item>Cōpound be foure.
<list>
                           <item>Hot and Drie.</item>
                           <item>Hot and moist.</item>
                           <item>Colde and moist.</item>
                           <item>Colde and drie.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Foure hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours,
<list>
                     <item>Sanguine.</item>
                     <item>Flegmatike.</item>
                     <item>Cholerike.</item>
                     <item>and Melancholie.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Members.
<list>
                     <item>Similer.
<list>
                           <item>Bones, veines, arteries, cartilage, flesh, fatnesse, pannicle, ligament, nerues, and skinne.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>cōpound
<list>
                           <item>Head, heart, liuer, lungs, armes, and legges.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Three facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.
<list>
                     <item>Animall.</item>
                     <item>Vitall.</item>
                     <item>and Naturall.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or actions.
<list>
                     <item>Animall
<list>
                           <item>Feeling.</item>
                           <item>and moouing.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Vitall.
<list>
                           <item>Beating of the pulse.</item>
                           <item>And breathing.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Naturall
<list>
                           <item>Generatio.</item>
                           <item>Auctio.</item>
                           <item>and Nutritio.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Spirites be three in nūber
<list>
                           <item>Animall</item>
                           <item>Vitall.</item>
                           <item>Naturall</item>
                        </list> In
<list>
                           <item>The braine.</item>
                           <item>The Heart.</item>
                           <item>The Liuer.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </item>
      </list>
      <pb facs="32"/>
      <p>
         <hi>Pathologia</hi> is that part of the arte, which hath the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of sicknesse against nature, with their <hi>Symptoma</hi> and accident, and they be thrée in number, that is to saie, sicknesse it selfe, the cause of sicknesse, and the accidents, which followeth after sicknesse: sicknesse it selfe may come two waies, either of outward causes, or of inward causes, we do commonlie call the outward causes primatiue, the Gréekes call them <hi>Cathertica,</hi> the inward causes, we do cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlie name Antecedent, or <hi>Internam.</hi> The affectes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlie followe these causes, and if the affectes come of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward causes, then commonlie they be wounds, contusions, fractures, dislocations, biting of mad dogs, &amp; of serpents, &amp;c. If they come of inward causes, then they make tumors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst nature, as <hi>Phlegmō, Eresipula, Oedema, Sirrhus,</hi> with many kinde of malignant and stubburne vlcers, to be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which tumours and vlcers cannot be made whole, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept their causes with their euill affects, may be remoued and taken awaie: I suppose that there is no man, but hée will iudge this part of the art chieflie to pertaine to Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgerie, for that it taketh cure of wounds, vlcers, and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors against nature, as I haue said before.</p>
      <p>Then if this part doe appertaine to the art of Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie, as it is most certaine it doeth, it behoueth the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion perfectlie and rightlie to vnderstand what kinde of sicknesses there be, with their differences &amp; names, what partes of the bodie these sicknesses may be in, and what manner of sicknesse it maketh in the same partes. As for example, euill complection maketh a distemperature in the similer parts, &amp; euil constitution, or euil cōposition, maketh a deformitie or imbecilitie in the instrumentall partes. And solution of vnitie or continuitie, chaunceth both in the similer partes, and instrumentall. And all these doe apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the Chirurgion, to haue most exact knowledge of, for he that taketh vpon him to cure an vlcer or a wound, or anie other manner of griefe, and doth not know the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the parts, neither yet what part it is in, neither yet the cause, neither how to remooue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same cause, it is vnpos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, as I haue sayde before, that he shoulde cure the same
<pb n="26" facs="32"/> griefes or diseases rightlie. And therefore these blinde em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perikes that haue neither reason nor method, to leade them to doe those things which they dailie doe, I saie, their doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are so pernitious, that many people taketh great hurt thereby (shall I saie hurte) nay rather brought to vtter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, and many times to death. The <hi>Symptoma</hi> or accidents which followeth sicknesse, is also diuided into thrée partes. The first is, the qualitie being altered, as with vehement heate in <hi>Phlegmon.</hi> The action or function hurt, but not vtterlie depriued. The action vtterlie depriued and taken awaie. For these causes aboue rehearsed, it is speciallie required, that a Chirurgion shoulde be learned, and also to haue greate experience, that hée maye rightlie iudge and discerne one disease from another, with their natures and causes, to the end, that when you come to the curation thereof, you may take right indications, what to do first, what next, and so foorth to the end, for other waies you may applie medicines nothing fit for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, but those that might doe great harme, and you might also applie those first that would be applied last, and those last which should be applyed first, and in the end marre all your workes, as the blinde Carpenter doth. Thus farre I haue proued for <hi>Phisiologia,</hi> to be one part of Chyrurgerie, or of the Art of curing, as we may tearme it, and I thinke there is no man that will count him to be a right Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that lacketh this part of the Arte, or that is not verie expert in the same. And for the further knowledge héereof, there be certaine bookes appointed of <hi>Galen,</hi> and other aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient writers, that you may reade concerning the same part as hereafter followeth.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>Libro Hippocrates, de Morbis, libro Epedimso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Hippocrates, Galen de locis affectis, Galen de Morbis &amp; Symptomatis, &amp; de 4. temporibus morborum, Galen de differentijs morborum causis &amp; Smptomatis, Galen de inequali intemperie, Galen de arte Medica, Galen de tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moribus, praeter naturam. Hippocrates de Vulneribus vlce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, &amp; Fistulis, fracturis, immorodibus, &amp;c.</hi> And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so <hi>Galen</hi> in his whole Worke called <hi>Therapeuticon,</hi>
         <pb facs="33"/> and in another worke to his Disciple <hi>Glaucon,</hi> as it is manifest to be séene. These two most excellent men béeing the patrones and fathers of the arte, haue written most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellentlie and perfectlie of many diseases, as woundes, tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours against naturne, vlcers, and many other diseases ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to the same art, as it maye more manifestly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in these bookes aboue rehearsed, and in manie other more of their workes. If I shoulde write of all men that accounteth this a proper and a principall parte of Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie, then I must néeds confesse the truth, all men learned in this art since the time of <hi>Galen,</hi> haue so written, and so taken it. Thus I conclude for this parte, that hée that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandeth it not, ye must giue him a baser name, ye may not call him a Chirurgion, that neither knoweth the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of his arte, neither yet the nature of his subiect that he worketh vpon.</p>
      <p>I remember when I was in the warres at <hi>Mutterell,</hi> in the time of that most famous Prince, King <hi>Henrie</hi> the viii. there was a great rablement there, that tooke vpon them to be Chirurgions, some were sowe gelders, &amp; some horse gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, with Tinkers and Coblers. This noble sect did such great cures, that they got to themselues a perpetual name, for like as <hi>Thesalus</hi> sect were call <hi>Thessalions,</hi> so was this noble rable for their notorious cures, called Dogge léeches, for in two dressings they did commonlie make their cures whole and sound for euer, so that they neither felt heate nor cold, nor yet no maner of paine after: but when the Duke of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> who was then general, vnderstood how the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple did die, and that of smal wounds, he sent for me and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine other Chirurgions, commaunding vs to make search how these men came to their death, whether it were by the grieuousnesse of their woundes, or by the lacke of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Chyrurgions, and we according to our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, made search throughout all the camp, &amp; found many of the same good fellowes, which tooke vppon them the names of Chirurgions, not onelie the names, but the wages also: we asking of them whether they were Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgions or no, they sayde they were, we demaunded with
<pb n="27" facs="33"/> whom they were brought vp, and they with shamelesse fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces would aunswere, either with one cunning man or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother which was dead: Then we demaunded of them what Chyrurgerie stuffe they had to cure men withall, and they wold shew vs a pot or a boxe which they had in a bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, wherein was such trumperie as they did vse to grease horse héeles withall, and layed vpon scabbed horse backes, with neruall, and such like. And other that were Coblers and Tinkers, they vsed shoomakers waxe, with the rust of olde pans, &amp; made therewithall a noble salue, as they did terme it. But in the end this worthy rablement was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Marsialsie, and threatned by the Dukes grace to be hanged, for their worthie déeds, except they would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the truth what they were, and of what occupations, and in the end they did confesse, as I haue declared to you before: wherevppon the Dukes grace gaue commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that they should auoide the Campe in paine of death, and if at anie time they came within the Campe after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, they should immediatlie be hanged, as murtherers, his Grace calling them by the name of Dogge léeches, commaunding his Captaines that they should entertaine no more such.</p>
      <p>Thus you vnderstand by what name those men were then called, which tooke vpon them vnworthilie to vse this Arte, knowing neither the principles of this arte, neither yet the nature of the diseases, nor yet the medicamentes wherewithall they could cure the same diseases.</p>
      <p>Thus we conclude with these examples before, that it is necessarie for a Chirurgion to know these partes, or else not to be admitted to so worthie an Arte, which doeth take charge, not onelie of mans health, but also of their liues and lims. And thus we end this part.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>Eugiena</hi> is the third parte, pertaining to the art of Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgerie, or Medicine, as we haue sayde before. This part doth consist in the sixe things not naturall, called <hi>Res non naturalis,</hi> which followeth.</p>
      <pb facs="34"/>
      <list>
         <item>Sixe things not naturall
<list>
               <item>In receiuing of the aire.</item>
               <item>In Meate and Drinke.</item>
               <item>In sleeping and waking.</item>
               <item>In mouing and rest.</item>
               <item>In fulnesse and emptinesse.</item>
               <item>And in affections of the minde.</item>
            </list>
         </item>
      </list>
      <p>This is also a speciall and a necessarie part to be know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en of the Chirurgion, for without this knowledge he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not giue conuenient diet, neither yet conuenient order for the gouernment of the diseased and sicke Patient, nor yet at what time he shoulde sléepe, at what time he should eate and drinke, or what manner of meates and drinkes hée should haue, and whether they shoulde bée liquide in sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staunce or grose and thicke, neither shall he knowe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the same meate and drinke maye augment the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease or not, by meanes whereof, he may giue such diet to his patients, as may confirme their diseases. As for example, in <hi>Elephantiasis,</hi> and <hi>Cancers,</hi> which by eating of melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like meates, or such meate and drinke as doth make adusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the bloud which doth confirme them. There might be many more thinges saide of meate and drinke, which is not materiall to be spoken héere, for I thinke no man doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, but that this instrument doth chieflie appertaine vnto this Arte, for it is not possible for a Chirurgion to cure his grieued patient, except he giue conuenient diet, &amp; with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient diet many greate grieuous wounds, and manie other cruell sicknesses, by the helpe of other conuenient me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines haue bene cured.</p>
      <p>And as for the gouernment by the aire, euerie man that hath anie knowledge will confesse, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> colde sicknesses which are taken by cold, are to be cured in places where y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> aire is warme, or else it ought to be made warme by art, according to the time of the yeare, for it is one of the principles and speciall rules which <hi>Galen</hi> commaundeth vs to kéepe, that we shall cure euerie thing by his contrarie, as heate by colde, colde diseases by hot thinges, drinesse by moisture, and moisture with those thinges that bée drie, fulnesse by abstinence, and euacuation by emptinesse, by things of good
<pb n="28" facs="34"/> nourishment to fill withall, watching, by thinges that moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth sléepe, &amp; ouer much sléepe, by kéeping of them waking. Thus euerie thing is ouercommed and holpen by his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, by meanes whereof the Chirurgion doth more safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and readilie restore to health, his grieued &amp; wounded pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieut, without which thinges, and their right vse, could not be done. And therefore this part is called a most necessarie and principall thing appertaining to the Artist. There is another vtilitie in this part also, which the Chirurgion of necessitie must vse, for <hi>Galen</hi> saith, that euerie Artist that will rightlie cure, must intend two thinges. The first is to conserue and kéepe euerie thing that is in good state, by his like.</p>
      <p>The second is to expell, and cure those things that bée contrary to nature, by their contraries, which we cannot do without these sixe things not naturall. Therefore it may be saide, <hi>Necessitas non legem habet,</hi> therefore there ought no lawe to bée made against that thing that must be of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie. As for example, of necessitie we must eate &amp; drinke, that we may liue. Therefore it were tyrannicall to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidde vs to eate and drinke, for they be proper things for vs whereby we doe liue. But yet the abusing of meate and drinke may be spoken against, and good and iust lawes made for the reformation thereof.</p>
      <p>In like manner for abusing the arte of Phisicke or Chirurgerie, there hath béene good and wholesome lawes made héertofore, and I trust in our Lord God shall be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after againe. But to commaund from them the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of their arte, or anie parte thereof, or other necessarie instruments or medicaments, wherewith they should cure their grieued and wounded Patients, which other wayes must of necessitie perish, or else not bée cured at all: Such commaundements or lawes were tyrannicall, and not to be well thought of, for that they should let the workes of mercie, in this most excellent arte of curing, to be ministred vnto the people orderlie for their safegard, &amp; curing of their diseases.</p>
      <p>There were much to be spoken of these sixe vnnaturall
<pb facs="35"/> things, which maketh nothing for my purpose héere in this place, for that I intend nothing but to proue that these bée necessarie instruments, for the Arte of Chyrurgerie, by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine examples, as you haue heard: for these things are spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of at large, not onelie in many worthie bookes, which are set forth by <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> but also in all other worthie mens bookes, that haue written of this art at large, as it may appeare at this present daie. Some men might héere aske a question, why these are called not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall things, for it is to be thought, that sléepe, meate, and drinke, moouing, &amp;c. should be naturall. But forasmuch as both health and sicknesse doth come by these things, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be called not naturall. They bée not called against nature: for sicknesse, the cause of sicknesse, and the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents that follow sicknesse, those be called <hi>Praeter naturam,</hi> &amp; against nature. Neither may they bée called naturall, for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> that sicknesses cōmeth by thē. But they are indifferētly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led not natural. These things are so necessary for our bodies, as I haue said before, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we do not onlie liue by them, but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> matter &amp; substanticall of our bodies, after generation, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased and mainteined by them, and also all the humours and temperaments with the spirits, and other things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the same bodie, should vtterlie cease if it were not but for those sixe thinges. Thus I conclude with these ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples aforesaid, to proue this part to be necessarie for the art of Chirurgerie, doubting nothing, but those that be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men and men of reason will so iudge, for so haue the auncient fathers before our daies, appointed it to be. Now that you may the better come to the perfect knowledge of these things, I thinke it good to declare vnto you some of the bookes which both <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen</hi> haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. <hi>Hyppocrates de elementis, Hyppo. de Aqua Aere, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionibus, Hyppo. de flatibus, Hyppo. de vrinarum differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tijs, Hyppo. de ratione victus salubris, Hyppo. de ratione vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus prauatorū, Galen de sanitate tuenda, Galen de imperica, dieta sub figuratione, Galen de aqua, Gal. de ptissana. Galen de Euchimia, &amp; Caccochimia, Galen de attenuante &amp; cras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sante victu,</hi> with many more bookes, written by most
<pb n="29" facs="35"/> excellent men, sence their times, which were superfluous, here to be rehersed, for as much as these are most necessary to be vnderstoode, and sufficient for the profe hereof: And thus I commit this part vnto your friendly iudgement, procéeding vnto the fourth part, called <hi>Semiotica.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>
         <hi>Semiotica,</hi> is an other part, perteining to the arte of Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgerie, which part doth iudge by signes, and tokēs, what the diseases are, and what be their natures, and what hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors or other things be the cause therof, and whether they may be cured easely, and in short time, or whether they be hard to be cured, &amp; must be cured in longer time, or if they cannot be cured at all. Or else whether it is not necessarie, that it be not cured at all, least worse diseases, should come by the curation of them, and specially, this part is necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, about the curatiō of wounds, to know which are dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and which are not deadly, and also which are maymed, and which are not maymed, and to foresée, daungerous and perillous accidents, which might chaunce vnto the woūded man, as <hi>paralisis, conuulsions, gangrena, spasalus,</hi> and manie other more daungerous diseases, which y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Chirurgiō ought not onely to foresée, by meanes whereof he might resist the same. But also, when any of the greuous accidēts, doe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, he might make a good and a true prognosticatiō, what might happen after these greuous, and perilous sicknesses, and also in wounds, that chaunceth in daungerous places, to prognosticate, and declare the great perill thereof, vnto the sicke and gréeued pacient, or else vnto his friendes, as it shall be thought most conuenient: for except he make a true and a iust prognostication, he shall get vnto him selfe dishonestie, and cause the worthie arte, to be euil spoken of. This parte of the Arte can not be attained vnto, without great knowledge, and long experience, and also a most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent wit. For <hi>Hyppocrates,</hi> sayth, in his <hi>Aphorismus,</hi> that this part, is the most hardest, he saith, that the lyfe of man is short, the arte of medicine long, the occasions to minister medicines many, prouing of experiments, perillous, but iudgement, and prognostication of sicknesse, to be most dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult and hard.</p>
      <pb facs="36"/>
      <p>Wherefore <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> did will all men, that would auoyde slander, and euill name, to beware, &amp; wise, in prognosticating, and not to be rashe and quicke. How many men haue gotten dishonestie, for lacke of knowledge of this parte of the Arte, and by mistaking of the <hi>Sympto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata,</hi> and accidents, it were wonderfull, to number them. And also how many sick men haue béene ouerthrowen, and vndone, for lake of knowledge of the same parte, it is not to be spoken. Wherefore this part is most necessarie, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth most diligent and exacte studie, as it doth appeare, both by <hi>Galen,</hi> and <hi>Hippo,</hi> in <hi>Galen,</hi> where he hath written vi. bookes, <hi>de differentiis &amp; causis morborum, &amp; Symptoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> which doth chiefely perteine to this parte of the Arte. And also that most excellēt and worthie man <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> hath written two diuine workes, wherein is conteined di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers bookes, the one called his <hi>Aphorismus,</hi> and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> other his prognostications, which are the most worthiest bookes that euer were written, for him that shall practise in this Arte, for therein may he learne the diuine iudgement of <hi>Hippo.</hi> And also how to prognosticate rightly, which two thinges, doe most chiefely and principally appertaine to the Art of Chirurgery. Thus I haue declared vnto you, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> foure prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall parts, or as we may tearme them, the foure principal pillers, or foundaments of this art, without the knowledge of which foure, no man may rightly, or methodically work, in the same arte. I dare not say, no man ought to worke in this Arte, that vnderstandeth not these, least I should con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempne a great sort, but I will say, as <hi>Hippocrates, Galen, Guido, Valleriolus, Tagaltius,</hi> and many other worthy men doe say, that these are the principles of the Arte, and they ought first to be learned, and trained vp, in the knowledge of these, before they be permitted to woorke in the Arte, for in the olde time, they did first learne their principles, and had them by heart, and then they were brought vp, vnder some cunning maister, where they might sée the same put in practise, and so trained vp in most exact and perfect expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riēce: And thus being brought vp, they were able to iudge in their art, &amp; so they did cōstitute &amp; builded vpō these foure
<pb n="30" facs="36"/> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, a most excellent art, which <hi>Galen</hi> calleth <hi>Therapeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticon,</hi> that is to saie, the art of curing, which part, those that are disposed to reade their works may plainlie vnderstand, and specially in a booke called <hi>Introductio, seu medicus.</hi> Thus I haue proued these foure parts, as I haue said before, to be the Theorike part of Chirurgerie, and we intend to proue <hi>Therapeuticon</hi> to be the practike part, for that it doth cure diseases &amp; griefes of mans bodie. <hi>Guido, Tagaltius,</hi> &amp; other, did not make these fiue diuisions of parts, as I haue done, but diuided the art into two parts, that is, into the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rike, and Practike: for <hi>Guido</hi> saith, that he which woulde vse the arte of Chirurgerie, must be learned in the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rike part, as wel as in the Practike part, but <hi>Guido</hi> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standeth the Theorike part to be Phisicke, and the Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike part to be Chirurgerie, as it may appeare by his words héereafter.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>Conditiones quae requiruntur in Chirurgo, sunt quatuor, prima est quod sit literatus, secunda, quod sit exper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, tertia, quod sit ingeniosus, quarta, quod sit morigeratus: Riquiritur quod sit Chirurgus literatus, non tantū in princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pijs Chirurgiae, &amp; sed etiam Phisicae tam in Theorica, quam in Practica. In Theorica, oportet quod ipse cognoscat res na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turales, &amp; non naturales, &amp; contra naturam, precipue Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thomiam, nam, sine ipsa factum est nihil, in Chirurgia.</hi> The English is this. There be foure conditions speciallie requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in a Chyrurgion: first, that he be learned: second, that he be expert: third, that he be ingenious, and fourth, that he be well mannered: It is further requisite, that the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion be not onelie learned in the principles of Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie, but also in Phisick, as well in Theorike as in Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike: In Theorike, it behooueth him to knowe thinges naturall not naturall, and things against nature.</p>
      <p>Thus it maye manifestlie appeare by the wordes of <hi>Guido,</hi> that he vnderstoode the Theorike part to be Philick, and the Practike part to be Chirurgerie, for other diuisions made he none, but vsed the art indifferently together, that is to saie, diet, purging medicaments, and all other things ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to the art of Chirurgerie. These foure partes
<pb facs="37"/> that we haue spoken off before, were accounted to be Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke, as <hi>Guido</hi> and all other later writers doe make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and euerie one of them supposeth, that a Chyrurgion ought to know these partes, either else he cannot rightlie and methodicallie worke in his arte: But when he dooth vnderstand these parts, and is well brought vp in experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the same, and hath also good vnderstanding &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge both in the simples and compounds, whereof he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his medicaments, and hath séene long experience, and vse of the same, I thinke him then a man méete and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be allowed to vse the practike parte of Chirurgerie, or else not, for otherwise he should be ignorant in the cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of many grieuous diseases, which doth appertaine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this art, that cannot be cured other waies, but by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministration of the hand, for this parte called <hi>Chirurgia</hi> is the last remedie in the arte of medicine, and cureth those things which are most hard and difficult to be cured, and therefore it is accounted amongst the auncient writers, as both <hi>Galen</hi> and <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> doe affirme, to be most profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and most worthie, as we shall declare more héereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in the Treatise of the methode of curing, called <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rapeuticon.</hi> And thus wée end this fourth parte, called <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miotica.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Now it doth behoue vs to speake of the last part called <hi>Therapeutica,</hi> and although it be last in number, yet it is chiefe in effect, and most profitable in the common wealth. For <hi>Therapeu</hi> is no other thing to be vnderstoode, than <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio,</hi> and <hi>Curatio</hi> is nothing else, but to helpe mans bodie of wounds, sicknesse, and other infirmities, as I haue sayd before.</p>
      <p>Therefore <hi>Guido</hi> doth saie, that this arte doth restore mans bodie vnto health by the curation of wounds, vlcers, tumours against nature, fractures, dislocations, and all other infirmities wherewith the same bodie is grieued.</p>
      <p>And he addeth and saith further, as much as lyeth in the Chirurgion to doe. For he saith, that it lieth not alwayes in the Artist to restore his sicke patient to health, for that that manie diseases be incurable, which the Artists ought
<pb n="31" facs="37"/> to vnderstād, and know, and to make true, and right prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nostication thereof, least he should get vnto himselfe great shame, and bring infamy and slaunder to the noble arte.</p>
      <p>Therefore, one <hi>Vego,</hi> a Spaniard, who hath made a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie commentarie vpon the prognostikes, of <hi>Hippo.</hi> sayth, that it doth behoue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> artist chiefely, to prognosticate right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and truely, of those things, which are to come, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing knowen, neither could the daunger thereof be auoided if it were possible, neither yet should y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> artist auoyd a slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous &amp; pernicious name. And therefore he deuideth this arte into thrée parts, that is, into <hi>agnostica, prognostica,</hi> and <hi>curatiua, Agnostica,</hi> he vnderstandeth to be, the knowledge of naturall things, of things not naturall, and of things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst nature. <hi>Prognostica,</hi> he vnderstandeth to be, a right iudgement, in the foresaide thinges, which he doth gather by the <hi>Symptomata,</hi> of the bodie, &amp; other excrements which nature doth auoyde. <hi>Curatiua,</hi> is that part which followeth both these and with knowledge and right iudgement, true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and rightly, prognosticating the same, he doth take vpon him, perfectly to cure mans bodie, of those griefes and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases, wherewith it is hurt, either else, if the same may not be cured, to preserue the same, from further vncōuenience, as much as is possible for this arte to doe.</p>
      <p>Thus it séemeth to mée, by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> woords of this great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man, as well as by the woords of <hi>Guido. &amp;c.</hi> That this part of the arte, called <hi>Therapeutica,</hi> or <hi>curatio,</hi> consisteth in two speciall points, (that is to say) in the curing of mans bodie perfectly, and in the preseruation of the same bodie, when the diseases are incurable, as in Cancers. &amp;c. as wée haue saide before.</p>
      <p>There be other learned men that deuide this Arte, but into two partes, that is to say, into <hi>Theorica,</hi> and <hi>Practica, Theorike,</hi> doth consist in the exact and perfect knowledge of these foure partes, which we haue spoken of before, that is to saye, in <hi>Phisiologia, Pathologia, Eugiena,</hi> and <hi>Simiotica.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>And the fiue parts named <hi>Therapeutica,</hi> doth consist in the right practising &amp; vsing of cōuenient remedies, to cure mans bodie with all, by the helpe, vnderstanding, and true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="38"/> of those things aboue specified, &amp; for as much as this part, doth bring to passe by an operation, and practise done with the hand, or ministred by the hand, therefore this part is called <hi>Practica,</hi> that is to say, practising and putting in vse all such necessarie things, as may apperteine, either for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> curatiō, or preseruation of mans bodie. And for as much, as these two thinges are brought to passe and done, by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine wayes and meanes, which reason hath inuented, and experience hath found true, and without these things, wée can not rightly cure, or bring to passe y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> desired scope or ende of our Arte, which we doe intend. Therefore, it followeth of necessitie, that wée must néedes vse them, either else wée shall not vse the practike part, which is the onely ende, and function of our vocation and Arte. And these things be cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly termed instruments, which instruments are apoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of Almightie God, to helpe vp in the time of néede, for without these, wée can doe nothing in this Arte. The first is dyet, the second is medicaments, the third is our handes, to minister the same with all, and these are named general instruments, and also speciall, for that, that all the aunciēt fathers, and most excellent men of this Arte, did alwayes so vse them.</p>
      <p>Wherefore, I thinke there is no reasonable man, or any that is learned in this Arte, that will say the contrarie, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he will wilfully, and willingly, condemne both reason and experience, and not onely experiēce and reason, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so these two most worthie and famous men, <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> and <hi>Galen.</hi> This part or those that vse it, hath also founde out many notable medicaments, with their natures, and hidden properties, which otherwayes, by the Theorike part could neuer be found out, yet by long practise and expery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the natures, qualities, and hidden properties, are foūd out, to no small helpe of the Arte of medicine, for by their natures and qualities, they are methodically vsed, and doe cure griefes, and diseases, as sicknesses, which be hot, are cured by cold thinges, those that be moyst by drye thinges, &amp;c. But those which doe cure by hidden properties, are such, as no reason can be made vnto, as for example. To expell
<pb n="32" facs="38"/> venim, either in the pestilence, or in <hi>Morbo camilliontiaci,</hi> in lepra, or in biting of any venimous beast, these are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cured, with medicaments, which doth it of propertie, rather then qualitie. Thus it doth behoue the artist, which will deale in this parte, called <hi>Therapeutica</hi> or <hi>practica,</hi> not onely to haue perfect knowledge, in all these thinges afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saide, but also to haue a very exact knowledge of all such simples, as he will make his medicaments of, or as he doth intend to minister vnto mans bodie, any maner of way, not onely as is saide before, their natures, and tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but also their qualities, and hidden properties: and also y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> times, when they should be gathered, how they should be kept, and preserued, how long they will continue in ther vertue, and strength, and whether they be of more force and vertue when they be greene, or when they be drye. All these thinges doth apperteine vnto the Artist to know, and also, to what vse he ought to minister the same, and what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie may come thereby. These things, as I haue sayde vnto you before, are knowen two maner of wayes, that is to say, by reason, and experience, neither can they be know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en by any third way, as <hi>Galen</hi> saith in his third booke, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Therapeuticon.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Therefore it is requisit, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> this Artist be not onely lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, in the Theorike part, as we haue saide before, but also, to be learned and brought vp, vnder some cunning man, which hath good knowledge in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same arte, or otherwaies, it is not possible, to come to the exact and perfect knowledge thereof, which is chiefely &amp; principally required. If I should tell you, of the vngratious witchcraftes, and of the foolish and mischiuous abuses, &amp; misuses, that haue bene in times past, and yet in our dayes continually vsed, ye would not a little maruaile thereat. But for as much, as it hath not only turned to the dishonor of God, but also, the state of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cōmon welth: I haue thought it good to declare vnto you, part of their wicked doings, that it may be vnto you which professeth this Arte, an example, to auoyde the like most wretched deeds. These things, I do not speak to you of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>say, but of mine owne knowledge. In y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> yere. 1562. I did sée
<pb facs="39"/> in the two Hospitalls of London, called S. <hi>Thomas</hi> Hospi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, and saint <hi>Bartholomewes</hi> Hospitall, to the number of CCC. and odde poore people, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> were diseased of sore legges, sore armes, féete, and handes, with other parts of the bodie, so sore infected, that a hundreth and twentie of them could neuer be recouered, without losse of a legge, or an arme, a foote or a hand, fingers, or toes, or else their limmes crooked, so that, they were either maymed, or else vndone for euer. All these were brought to this mischiefe, by witches, by women, by counterfait iauills, that tooke vpon them to vse the Art, not onely robbing them of their money, but of their limmes, and perpetuall health. And I with certaine other, diligently examining these poore people, how they came by these gréeuous hurtes, and who were their Chirurgiōs that looked vnto them, and they confessed, that they were either witches, which did promise by charmes, to make thē whole, or else some women which would make them whole with hearbes, and such like things, or else some vacabound iauil, which runneth from one countrie to an other, promising vnto them health, onely to deceaue them of their money.</p>
      <p>This fault and crime, of the vndoing of this people, were layed vnto the Chirurgions, I will not say, by part of those that were at that time maisters of the same Hospitalls, but it was saide, that Carpinters, women, weuers, coblers, and tinkers, did cure more people, then the Chirurgions. But what maner of cures they did, I haue told you before, such cures, as all y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> world may wonder at: yea, I say such cures, as maketh the diuell in hell to daunce for ioye, to sée the poore members of Iesus Christ, so miserably tormented.</p>
      <p>What shall I saie, here vnto, but lamēt and pray vnto our Lord Iesus Christ, for his precious bloud sake, that he shed vpon the crosse, to illuminate the hearts of the magistrates, for amendement hereof. And that this rablement of runa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates, with witches, baudes, and the diuells sothsaiers, with tinkers, coblers, and sow gelders, and all other their wicked coherents, of these same diuelish and wicked sectes, which doth thus abuse this noble arte of medicine, to the vtter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fasing of the same, may be reformed and amēded, and euery
<pb n="33" facs="39"/> one to get their liuing with truth, in the same arts y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they haue ben brought vp &amp; wel experiēced in, either els to be gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouslie punished, as they be in all other Countries, and as they haue bene héere in this Countrie in times past. For séeing there is lawes made for him that stealeth a shéepe, an oxe, or an horse, which is but a beast and serueth to mans vse, and hée that looseth the same, looseth no more but the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of the vse thereof, why may it not be as well conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the losse of an arme or a legge? yea, and many times of the life, which these wicked generation doe spoile, I thinke the Prince is bound in conscience, as wel to punish those false and wicked pernitious deceiuers, which doeth not onelie destroie the lims of man, but his life, as to punish these which steale shéep, oxen, or horses. Of this sort I think <hi>London</hi> to be as well stored, as the Countrie, I thinke there be not so few in <hi>London</hi> as thrée score women, that occupieth the arte of Phisicke and Chirurgerie. These wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, some of them be called wise women, or holie and good women, some of them be called Witches, and vseth to call vpon certaine spirits, and some of them vseth plaine bau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derie, and telleth Gentlewomen that cannot beare children how they may haue children. What manner of other sorts and sects there be of these, as some for sore breastes, some for the stone and Strangurie, some for paine of the téeth, some for scald heads, some for sore legges, some cunning in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Tomsons</hi> tubbe, and some to helpe maides when they haue lost their maidenhead, when their bellies are growen too great, to make thē small againe, with a thousand more. <hi>Galen</hi> in his booke of sects, did neuer make mention of the fourth part so manie, I thinke, if this worshipfull rable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were gathered together, they would make a greater profession than euer did y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Monks, the Friers, &amp; the Nuns, when they did swarme most in <hi>London.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>This vnprofitable companie haue so increased within the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> that all the Countries in <hi>England</hi> haue taken insample thereof, yea, and at this daie all the Countries in Christendome may wonder at our lawes in suffering and maintaining of them.</p>
      <pb facs="40"/>
      <p>Well I say, wée will let all these passe, with tinkers, cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, souters, and sow gelders, and a great many of occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions more, whereof, some commeth out of Fraunce, some out of Germany, and so of other countries, some for religiō, &amp; some for picking of purses. &amp;c. All these now, are become great Phisicions, and Chirurgions, to no small aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this noble Arte of Medicine, for their noble and worthie cures, doth beare witnesse thereof, and giueth so good report vnto them, that at this day, the learned Phisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions and Chirurgions, may not a little reioyce. Well, I say no more, but God amend all, and except these things be quickly amended, I thinke the diseased people, and such as haue vlcers, woundes, diseases, and sores, are like to haue small helpe, and if it shall chaunce, the prince to haue wars, then are this company that I haue spoken of, like to serue, and I doubt nothing, but that the souldiers shal haue great courage to fight, for so much, as they shal haue, such a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly companie of Chirurgions, to cure them, when they be wounded. As for other Chirurgions, there will be but a fewe left, except better order be taken, and that with spéed. Well, now wée will procéede to our matter againe.</p>
      <p>Now my welbeloued brethren, ye haue hard of this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratious company, with their damnable déedes, which may be vnto you, an example, to incourage you, to flye igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, and to learne the exact, and methodicall way of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, according to knowledge, &amp; also to know these things, that doth appertaine vnto the same, not onely these v. parts, aboue rehearsed or thrée, or two, as it séemeth good to you, to deuide them, for it is not materiall, as <hi>Galen</hi> saith, so that you vnderstād the thing. Not onely these, I say, ought to be perfectly knowen, but also, all medicines, both simple, and compoūd, with their natures and properties, their ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and right applicatiōs, and at what time the same ought to be ministred, to what partes of the bodie, and for what griefes and diseases: and also, according to right in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dications taken, what ought to be first ministred, what next, and so to the last.</p>
      <p>All these thinges, as I haue saide, doe appertaine vnto
<pb n="34" facs="40"/> the right and true Chirurgion, not onely to know, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so orderly to follow, or else he shall be accounted an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prike, and little better then one of these rude rablement, which I haue spoken of before. Wherefore, my well belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued bretheren, that vse this arte of Chirugria, I exhort you in the name of Almightie God, that you your selues, be not onely diligent in learning of all these partes, and other thinges, necessarie, appertaining vnto your arte: by meanes whereof, not onely murther, and other greuous misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, which might happen, through your ignorance, may be auoyded, but also perpetuall slander, with all other infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous report, and displeasure, may be likewise auoyded al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so. And that in like maner, your seruaunts, and children, which you doe intend to bring vp in this Arte, be learned, not onely to write and reade, but also in the tongues, that he may more exactly vnderstand these parts, as I haue said before. And so by this meanes, you shall not onely restore the Arte, againe vnto her good name, which is almost lost, at this present daye, through that foule and vgly monster, ignoraunce, but also get vnto your selues, perpetual honor, and good fame.</p>
      <p>And furthermore, by your excellēt knowledge, and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous liues, and cunning déedes, which followeth after, and are the fruites of knowledge, by these thinges, I saye, and with the helpe of the high and mightie Lord God, you shall abolish and put downe, these wicked and pernitious sectes, which are no lesse vnprofitable, vnto Gods people, in the common wealth of their countries, then caterpillers, and Grassehoppers, are vnto the fruites, and herbes of the ground, which sectes, be not onely pernitious, as I haue said before, but perillous, and selaunderous, vnto you, that be the true professers of the Arte, for they call themselues, by the name of Phisitions or Chirurgions: And the simple ignoraunt people, doe so receue them, or thinke them to be, but in déede, they be such as Christ speketh of, wher he saith, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they come in shéepes clothīg, &amp; be rauenīg wolues, so these come w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> good names, &amp; be craftie, and pernitious deceauers, which are to be driuen out of euery good common welth.</p>
      <pb facs="41"/>
      <p>Thus (most gentle Reader) I haue troubled you with a long talke, desiring you to beare with my simple and rude stile, wishing with all my heart, that it had bene bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and desiring you most humblie where you finde anie fault, curteouslie to amend the same, or else to giue mée knowledge, and I shall be as willing to amend them, as I haue bene diligent in setting it forth, praying you to leaue off slaunderous wordes and euill iudgement: by meanes whereof I haue bene greatlie impaired, not onelie in my good name, but also in the profite and commoditie of my arte, which is to my great hinderaunce: and this hath partlie risen by a booke of Chirurgerie which I haue late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie set forth, to my great cost and charge, and some men haue not let to saie, that it was onelie Doctor <hi>Cuninghams</hi> doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and none of mine. Vnto whom I answere. That <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningham</hi> was the writer thereof, and put the same booke in order, as you may now sée, for I my selfe hauing not perfect vnderstanding of the tongues, required him, for the more perfection thereof, to put in the Gréeke &amp; Latine words, in such sort as he thought good. And for the matter in the most part therein contained, you may verie well perceiue that it was mine owne practise, as the stories therin contained for the curation of diuerse people, doth declare, which I my self did cure, as it may more at large appeare in the same booke. And for the medicines y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> be written in the same booke, their names which deuised the same medicines, are put vnto thē, so y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> this is but a slaunderous, vntrue, &amp; malitious reporte, onlie to deface me of my good name, without any deseruing or cause reasonable.</p>
      <p>For it is well knowen, that Maister <hi>Cuningham</hi> neuer did anie such cures, as there is mention made of, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet is Maister <hi>Cuningham</hi> anie Chyrurgion, as yée may perceiue farther in his own Epistle written vnto the same booke, wherein he doeth not onelie declare my paines and trauaile in collecting certaine partes of Chyrurgerie, but also my great expenses and painfull labours in collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and setting forth of the same.</p>
      <p>These slaunderous and euill wordes haue caused me to
<pb n="35" facs="41"/> set pen to booke my selfe, to auoide that foule and euill fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured monster, false detraction, and also to spare my expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, which I before did l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>se amongest vnthankfull and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grate persons. And I haue taken paines now mine owne selfe, without anie other helpe of liuing men, at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent daie, but of mine owne trauaile, and collected them out of these famous authors, which I haue before rehearsed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, and although it be not in so good forme and eloquent stile, as it might haue bene, if a better learned man had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it in hand, yet the truth is not to be reiected, because of the barbarousnesse of the stile, or words. Thus I leaue off least I should be tedious vnto you.</p>
      <p>Now I will speake of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>d of this noble art, or as you will saie, to what ende this art doeth serue. The end of this art of Medicine is, to restore mans bodie to health, as much as lieth in this Artist to do, so that the end of this art consisteth in the curation of diseases, or as we may tearme it restoring of health. For man at his birth was cast into this world naked, and vncouered, requiring the helpe of other things to couer his nakednesse withall, neuer leauing crying and wéeping, till such time as reason and nature had prouided for him such necessarie thinges as dyd growe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the earth, either else vpon some other creatures, by meanes whereof, hée was both nourished and also clothed, and also by the vertue of other thinges that the Earth brought forth, restored to health in the time of his grieuous infirmities.</p>
      <p>But how was he restored to health? Truelie by Arte. And by what Arte, euen by the art of Medicine, which doth comprehend both Phisick and Chirurgerie, with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of all simple Medicines, and compound medicaments, and all other things whatsoeuer doe appertaine vnto the same. And therfore I will saie, as that worthie man <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> did. That this art is most honourable and worthy, for that it doth intend to kéepe mans bodie in health, and to remoue sicknesse. Therefore it is said, that the end of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgia,</hi> is the restoring of mans health.</p>
      <p>Now let vs consider whether this art be like vnto other
<pb facs="42"/> artes, or not. In some thinges wée saie, it is like vnto other arts, and in some things it is not. It is like vnto other arts, in that it doth consist in a multitude of principles, whose affectes are rightlie to bring to passe or finish some thing which we intend to doe, for <hi>Aristotle</hi> in his .6. <hi>Ethic. cap.</hi> 4. doth define Art to be a certaine order of doing, placed with habit and vnderstanding, working vppon some subiect, to bring to passe and finish some thing that he doth intend, by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same art, so that what thing so euer is brought to passe or done, it must néeds be done by some one art. In this the art of medicine is like vnto all other artes, for that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth in doing and bringing to passe, or as we may tearme it, in restoring health, or curing mans bodie, being subiect therevnto. But other waies it doth differ, and doth require a further knowledge than the common Artist doth. It is requisite that this Artist which intendeth to vse the arte of Medicine, should be verie well learned in the speculatiue part of his arte, as well as in practise. It is vnpossible to carrie in minde so many considerations, so many obseruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and so many inuentions as this art doth require, and therefore it is requisite, that he be not onelie well learned in the principles of his arte, but also that he be studious in the workes of other excellent men, wherein he may learne their wittie and ingenious deuises, to helpe this Artist the sooner to bring to passe his desired end. In this it doth much differ from other artes, which worketh onlie by experience, in wittie bringing of things to passe, without anie further consideration, neither doe they néed anie such excellent lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, for that theirs doth consist chieflie vppon experience and practise, and hath not so much regard vnto the life and health of man. For this art doth onelie intend to saue mans life in the time of necessitie, &amp; also to remooue awaie such grieuous sicknesses as might anoie and disquiet both bodie and minde. Wherefore this Artist is chieflie to be conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and looked vnto, not onelie to be rewarded for his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent cunning in restoring mannes bodie to health, but to bée seene vnto and throughlie examined, whether he bée learned in this arte or not, if he be not learned, neither vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandeth
<pb n="36" facs="42"/> the principles of this arte, then he is to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden this art for the worthinesse thereof, for this worthy art worketh vpon mans bodie, for whome all this worlde was made, and all things therin contained, and the almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Lord had so great care for man, that he did not onelie make these things for him, but also made him Lord of thē, and gaue vnto him straight lawes, that he shoulde foresée, that one man should not kill and destroie another, neither wilfullie, neither yet willinglie.</p>
      <p>Then I must conclude, that whosoeuer doth take vpon him to minister in this art, for the safegard of mannes life, and being ignorant in the principles thereof, as I haue said before, he taking vppon him, and the man perishing in his handes through his default, I saie, this is murther, and this is not the right end that art requireth, neither is it suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in the common wealth. And therefore it was not in vaine that this worthie man <hi>Guido</hi> did saie, that a Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion ought to be learned, not onelie in the principles of Chyrurgerie, but also in the principles of Phisicke, yea, and also in thinges both naturall and not naturall, and things against nature, without the knowledge of which, he should neither rightlie worke, neither yet bring to a good end, the desired scope which is required of the Artist. Thus you may perceiue, for this first propertie which <hi>Guido</hi> spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of, where he requireth that a Chirurgion shoulde bée learned, it is euen so necessarie for him, as the head is for the bodie, cut off the head, and sée what the bodie can doe, although the bodie hath handes and féete, and other neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie members, yet because it lacketh knowledge and the vse of reason, which was contained in the head, and should haue bene distributed to the rest of the bodie, to moue the same, and caused it to haue done the actions of the minde, thorough default héereof nothing might bée done: Euen in lyke manner, the Chyrurgion lacking knowledge of the principles of this Arte, canne doe nothing righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie nor profitablie, but hée shall alwayes bée in daunger, eyther to kill or else to mayme some man, for that hee lacketh that reasonable and methodicall knowledge which
<pb facs="43"/> this art doth require, being the head and principle thereof. It is not vnknowen vnto you what manner of seruice the Chyrurgion doth serue in, &amp; in what places, at what times, and how necessarie it is in the common wealth: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though other men haue written verie well héereof, and that I doe not doubt, but that you haue verie wel considered the same: yet forasmuch as this most excellent seruice is not to be neglected, or a light account to be made thereof: I haue thought it good, for y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it pertaineth to my matter, some thing to giue you warning therin. I haue declared vnto you in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> beginning of this proime, the noblenesse of this Art, &amp; how it is to be honored amongst men, for that it procéeded from the almightie Lord God, and was vsed and set forth by most noble and worthie Princes, and many other worthie men of most excellent vertue and learning. And now at this day either through negligence of the vncarefull Magistrates, or else through our euill natures, it is vsed by a sort of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned persons, to the great ouerthrow &amp; dishonor of this worthie Arte, yea, and almost to the vtter losse of the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodicall and true knowledge therein: which may bée no small daunger héereafter, except spéedie remedie be had héerein, and that noble persons be carefull for this so neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie an Art, which kings in times past did not onelie giue great rewards vnto those learned men which set it foorth, but also they themselues did vse it, by meanes whereof, they got vnto themselues immortall fame, in that they did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer their people by vsing of this art, from so many grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous diseases, which dailie they were brought to death withall. Thus these gratious and mercifull Princes, were not vncarefull for their subiectes, and they did not onelie build certaine Schooles, that this Arte might bée taught in, but also they did deuise medicines, and ministred the same vnto those that had néede, in such good order, and with such knowledge, that manye thousands were resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to their health thereby, and by their examples they encouraged manie other noble persons, and also excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent learned men, and men of excellent wit, to studie and practise the same, to the great comfort of their common
<pb n="37" facs="43"/> welth, and rewarded them with great rewards. But now alas, in this vnhappie time of ours, this Art is not onely neglected, and vnprouided for, but also despised, abhorred, &amp; euill spoken of, by meanes whereof noble persons, and men of great learning, doth rather hate it, then séeke meanes or other wayes, to reuiue it againe. For I saye once againe, in this our vnhappy time: that Taylours, Shoemakers, Cookes, and Carpinters, are had in more estimation, then these noble Artists bée.</p>
      <p>Yea, I thinke, Iuglers, Players, yea, &amp; Iacke foole with his fooles coate, shalbe as well estéemed &amp; placed in as néere roomes vnto the magistrates, as these most excellēt artistes shalbe.</p>
      <p>Well, I will say no more, but if that noble man <hi>Galen,</hi> were aliue, who doth say in his first booke <hi>de methodo me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendi,</hi> that drunkards and riotous persons, were more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, thē men of knowledge and learning, and also how that Cookes, Carpenters, Smithes, and many other occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions did runne from their Artes, and tooke vpon them the arte of medicine, I thinke if he were now liuing, and in our Countrey, he would not a little meruaille, to sée what a disordred company there is now at this day, which vseth this Arte: vseth this Art, nay, abuseth this Arte, most wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly and vngodly, to the great dishonor of our countrey, &amp; to the destruction and infamy of this worthie Arte. What shall I say, that these people be suffered, nay, rather main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, in this vnhappie mischiefe. For I haue knowen, not onely noble persons to maintaine them, who haue written their letters in their defence, to kéepe them from punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when they haue committed most wicked déedes, but also caused a lawe to be made, that euery one might occupy this Arte, without any punishment, not onely Shoema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, and Tailers, Carpinters, and Tinkers, and such other as <hi>Galen</hi> doth vtterly condempne, and speake against: but also witches, and baudes, coniurers, and a sort of false sooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayers. I will not speake of a multitude of strangers, as pouch makers, and pedlers, with glasse makers, and coblers, which runne out of their owne countries, and here become
<pb facs="44"/> noble Phisitions and Chirurgions, such as now is most in estimation, and ruleth all the roast in our Countrie, so that the poore English men, and such as haue serued in the time of warres, with expenses of their goods, and losse of their liues, yea, and the rest of them that be liuing, must of neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie serue at all times both by land and by sea, as well in the time of warres as in the time of pestilence: These poore men I saie, are constrained to serue, to their vtter vndoing, and when they come home againe, they, their wiues, and their children, may goe picke muscles, for this iollie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie afore spoken off, haue taken vp all their acquaintance whilest they be seruing in the warres.</p>
      <p>Come to anie of these straungers, or anie of these other people, when the Prince should be serued, and one will say, I am a Tailour, another will saie, I am a Shooemaker, and the other will saie, I am a woman, so that then they will make delaies, by meanes whereof they will not serue. And thus the Prince and the common wealth in the time of necessitie, is vtterlie vnserued, for this Companie is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to take the liuing of Chirurgions, and the names too, so long as there is no néed of seruice for the Prince, but then they haue new names, and if they be straungers, they will then trudge home againe into their owne Countries, or els hide thē out of the waie, or else retaine to some noble man, by meanes whereof, they will be defended from seruice of the Prince. And thus with this manner of disordered shifts, the Princes with their people, are not onelie euill serued, and somtimes not serued at all, but the noble arte of Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgerie is vtterlie ouerthrowen and brought to ruine, and the true professors therof at this daie, be so few in number, that it is to be wondered at. I haue my selfe in the time of king <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight, helpe to furnish out of <hi>London</hi> in one yéere, which serued by sea and by land, thrée score and twelue Chirurgions, which were good worke men, and wel able to serue, and all English men. At this present daie there are not foure and thirtie of all the whole companie of English men, &amp; yet the most part of them be in noble mens seruice, so that if we should haue néede, I doe not knowe
<pb n="38" facs="44"/> where to finde twelue sufficient men. What do I saie? suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient men: Nay, I would there were ten amongst all the companie, worthie to be called Chirurgions, and let the rest doe such seruice as they may, for if there be néede of seruice, I thinke their Chirurgerie shall appeare to some mannes griefe and paine. Thus I leaue off, and goe to my matter againe. My brethren, you that be English men, &amp; professe this noble art, remember I saie, your vocation, and be not discouraged, for that that this rablement doth flourish, &amp; that strangers are had in such estimation, which I know is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you no small discouraging, but I doe not doubt in time, God shall stirre vp the heart of the Prince, with her Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces noble Magistrates, to consider the great perill that may grow thereof, not onelie in the vtter losse of so worthie an art, which of necessitie must néeds be lost amongest vs that be English men, except prouision may bée made, that these worthie Artistes may haue sufficient liuing to maintaine them withall, but also to foresee that this common wealth may be serued with our naturall, true, and liege Countrie men, and not to preferre Straungers, which commeth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hether for their owne gaine, than for anie good loue that they doe beare vnto vs, and in the time of greatest néede doth forsake vs. Therefore I praie you remember, that ye be verie studious in this arte, and diligent and neate in the practising thereof, and also to be modest, wise, and of good manners and behauiour, and that you lacke none of these good properties that we haue spoken of before, least when you shall be called for in the time of necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to serue Princes, and other noble persons, ye doe not onelie dishonour your selues and your Countrie, but this worthie art also. Remember I praie you what great charge is committed vnto you in the time of warres, ye haue not onelie the charge of mens limmes, but also of their liues, which if they should perish through your defaulte, eyther in neglecting of anie thing that were necessarie for theyr health, which you ought to bée furnished withall, either else through lack of knowledge which ye ought to haue in your art: I saie, if these de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ults be in you, and the people perish
<pb facs="45"/> in your handes, you cannot excuse your selues of your bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers death. Therefore as you would this art should pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, remoue from it such pernitious occasions as might be hurtfull therevnto. For if we shall be bloudie murtherers, or greedie and couetous catchers, and oppressers of poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, let vs not looke for the fauour of God, neither yet to prosper in our art, or if we shall be negligent in prouiding of such necessary things as may be for the help of our disea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed patients: either else if we shall lack knowledge for the right vse and administration of the same, we shall then be slaunderous vnto this most excellent Arte, and vnworthie professors thereof, and in verie déede, accounted no better than these rude runagates and butcherlie Dogleechers are.</p>
      <p>Remember also the continuance of your art, as our fore fathers haue done before our time, which hath left no small number of worthie bookes for vs to peruse, whose diligence thereby, for the continuance of this arte, doth most mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festlie appeare. And like as they haue with most diligent studie, diuine knowledge, &amp; most willing hearts, left these their workes and labours vnto vs their posteritie, to be as it were guides, and most sure doctrine to follow: so I wold wish that we with carefull studie and louing heartes, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their precepts, as louing children ought to followe the profitable commaundementes of their carefull Fathers. And al you that be young men, I request you also, that you be diligent in séeing of other excellent mens workes, &amp; not to be too bolde &amp; presume to deale with things aboue your knowledge, but in doubtfull &amp; dangerous matters, to desire counsaile of the graue and auncient men, who hath more knowledge by long experience, &amp; able to giue better iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than you are, by meanes whereof the Patient shall not onelie be the better prouided for, but you also discharged of great blame, which might happen, if anie thing came to the sicke patient: But well, let your honest manners bée equall vnto your excellent knowledge and practise in this worthie arte, sée that ye be faithfull, trustie, and true, vnto your sicke patients honest of behauiour, sober of life, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable
<pb n="39" facs="45"/> of words. And also sée that ye serue God, and loue him, and praie vnto him at all times, that the holie Ghost may assist and strengthen you in all your workes and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprises which you doe take in hand, so that they may all turne to the commoditie of the sicke patient, and to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God, promising no health vnto them, but thy faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and painful diligence, for health lieth not in thy hands to giue, but in the might and power of the almightie Lord God, vnto whom be all honour, praise, and glorie, worlde without end, Amen.</p>
      <p>Thus most louing Reader, I beséech thée to spare mée thy good word, for my painful trauaile which I haue taken héerein, for the common weath sake, and for the furtherance of those that be young men of my Companie, and thinke not that I haue done it to teach anie learned man, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to encourage those that be better learned, to bestowe their diligence and trauaile, either for the amendement of this, or else for the setting forth of some better worke. Thus taking my leaue, I beséech the eternall God to prosper this most worthie arte, and all the true and right profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors of the same.</p>
   </div>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>