<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Furthermore</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117450_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B12273</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6038</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117450</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Furthermore</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The harmonie of the lawe and the gospel : Wherin is plainly shewed, that howsoeuer they differ in time and some other circumstances, yet in substance they are one &amp; the same. And by waie of application, the pretended antiquitie of Poperie is discouered, and found to be a meere nouelty: deliuered in a sermon at Pauls-crosse, the 9. of Aug. 1607. by George Cresvvell, minister of Gods word</title>
                 <author>Creswell, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Leake, William 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 54, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="32"/>
   <p>Vnderstand, Christian Reader, that part of the matter contained in the ninetenth and twentith pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges aforegoing, was (by him that copied out this Sermon, for the Presse) set downe in the Margent, without certaine direction for vs, where to bring it into the body of the Book. And consequently, for want of a guide, we haue somwhat failed (as we vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand since) of the due order obserued by the Authour, in his originall Copy: which was as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth;</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Symmacchus,</hi> the <hi>Gloria in excelsis Deo: Ierome,</hi> the Epistle and Gospell: <hi>Alleluia</hi> was taken out of the Church of <hi>Ierusalem:</hi> the Creed, in the Councell of <hi>Nice: Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius,</hi> the Commemoration of the dead: <hi>Leo</hi> the third, Frankincense: <hi>Innocent</hi> the first, the kissing of the <hi>Pax: Sergius,</hi> the <hi>Agnus Dei: Nicolas</hi> the first, the Sequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: <hi>Gelasius Africanus</hi> (as saith <hi>Naucle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus)</hi> the Hymnes, Collects, Responsories, Graduals, and Prefaces: <hi>Gregory</hi> the third, to the secret of the Masse, <hi>Quorum solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas hodie in conspectu tuae Maiestatis cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bratur, Domine Deus noster in toto orbe ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarū: Leo</hi> the first, &amp; so forward in order, as it standeth in the booke.</p>
   <div type="errata">
      <head>Furthermore</head>
      <p>In the 3 page, line 27, reade 430: page. 14. line 10, reade Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blatha:</p>
      <pb facs="33"/>
      <pb facs="33"/>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>