<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Breviate or short View of the whole WORKE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117796_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12952</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23245</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117796</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Breviate or short View of the whole WORKE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A bevvayling of the peace of Germany. Or, A discourse touching the Peace of Prague, no lesse unhappily than unjustly concluded at Prague in Bohemia, the 30. of May, 1635 : Wherein the subtilties and practises of the Austrians, the weakenesse of the Saxons, the dangers of the protestants, and the justnesse of the warre, deservedly set on foot by the French and Swedes, are most evidently declared. Written in Latine by Iustus Asterius, otherwise Stella, a Germane, now one of the advocates in the Court of Parliament of Paris, and historiographer to the French King. Faithfully translated out of the Latine copie. Whereunto is prefixed a briefe summarie of the treaty of peace concluded at Prague, as aforesaid, &amp;c. Published by authority</title>
                 <author>Stella, Johannes</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hunscott, Joseph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Meredith, Christopher.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stephens, Philemon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 28, 18, 129, 110-111, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb facs="19"/>
   <head>A Breviate or short View of the whole WORKE.</head>
   <p>The Treatie of <hi>Prague,</hi> concluded by the Emperour and Duke of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> against the <hi>Protestants, Swedes,</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> is proved to be of no validitie, void, and unjust, by five severall Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or generall Nullities.</p>
   <div n="1" type="part">
      <head>The first Nullitie, on the Emperours part. <hi>Pag. 1.</hi>
      </head>
      <list>
         <item>1. BEcause a Treatie or determination con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Church-Lands, exceedeth the power of the Emperour. <hi>p.</hi> 6</item>
         <item>2. Because it is founded upon the Transaction of <hi>Passaw,</hi> which is of no moment with the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strians. p.</hi> 8</item>
         <item>3. The Emperours themselves doe confesse, that it belongeth not to their power, to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine any thing in matter of Religion. <hi>p.</hi> 15</item>
         <pb facs="20"/>
         <item>4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap> by any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <hi>p.</hi> 17</item>
         <item>5. Because the Treatie of <hi>Prague</hi> it selfe is very ignominious to the Emperour and to the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes. p.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="2" type="part">
      <head>The second Nullitie, on the part of the Duke of <hi>Saxonie. Pag. 25.</hi>
      </head>
      <list>
         <item>1. Because, though he account himselfe the chiefe of the <hi>Protestants,</hi> yet by this divorce and separation from them, he utterly ruineth both his owne strength, and the strength of his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes. <hi>p.</hi> 26</item>
         <item>2. Because the treating of a common Peace, exceedeth the power of the Duke of <hi>Saxonie. p.</hi> 28</item>
         <item>3. Because this Transaction of the Duke of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> is hurtfull and deceitfull to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants. p.</hi> 31</item>
         <item>4. It springeth from a fountaine of foule in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, and horrible trecherie. <hi>p.</hi> 35</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="3" type="part">
      <head>The third Nullitie, on the part of the Protestants. <hi>Pag. 43.</hi>
      </head>
      <list>
         <item>1. Because the <hi>Protestants</hi> being instigated by the Duke of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> made Warre against the Emperour. <hi>p.</hi> 43</item>
         <item>2. Because they are enforced to consent, not to a Peace, but to a new Warre. <hi>p.</hi> 48</item>
         <pb facs="20"/>
         <item>3. The Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia</hi> is unjustly made Hereditarie to the House of <hi>Austria. p.</hi> 55</item>
         <item>4. <hi>Silesia</hi> being innocent, is stripped of her rights. <hi>p.</hi> 64</item>
         <item>5. <hi>Lusatia</hi> is unjustly dismembred from the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia. p.</hi> 66</item>
         <item>6. The Electorall dignitie of the <hi>Palatine,</hi> is unjustly translated to the <hi>Bavarian. p.</hi> 73</item>
         <item>7. The <hi>Bavarians</hi> anciently had no right to the Electorate. <hi>p.</hi> 84</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="4" type="part">
      <head>The fourth Nullitie, on the part of the <hi>Swedes. Pag. 95.</hi>
      </head>
      <list>
         <item>1. Because the <hi>Swedes</hi> making Warre in their owne name, ought also to make the accord in their owne right. <hi>p.</hi> 98</item>
         <item>2. Because the Duke of <hi>Saxonie</hi> in his owne private name oweth revenging imprecations to the <hi>Swedes. p.</hi> 101</item>
         <item>3. Because the <hi>Swedes</hi> cannot basely abandon their Leagues, nor their Troupes: Nor dare they make any agreement with the <hi>Austrians,</hi> under the faithlesse undertaking of the <hi>Saxon. p.</hi> 104</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div n="5" type="part">
      <head>The fifth Nullitie, on the part of the <hi>French. Pag. 110.</hi>
      </head>
      <list>
         <item>1. Because the <hi>most Christian King,</hi> by right of protection, preserved the <hi>Catholike</hi> Faith in the Empire. <hi>p.</hi> 111</item>
         <pb facs="21"/>
         <item>2. The protection of the Princes and States of the Empire, cannot be charged to be the <hi>French</hi> Kings fault. <hi>p.</hi> 116</item>
         <item>3. The most illustrious Elector of <hi>Trevers</hi> (or <hi>Trier</hi>) did justly and seasonably obtaine the protection of the <hi>French. p.</hi> 120</item>
         <item>4. Because the Emperour endeavoureth to make the private quarrels of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> with the <hi>French,</hi> common to the whole Empire. <hi>p.</hi> 124</item>
         <item>5. Because the cause of <hi>Lorraine</hi> doth nothing at all belong to the Emperour. <hi>p.</hi> 127</item>
      </list>
      <p>
         <hi>And therefore the conclusion is, that this Triumvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall conspiracie ought to be rejected, and a true, honest, and universall Peace to be fought for, and defended with the common Armes.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>