<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to all indifferent Readers, wherein not only the purpose of this treatise is declared, but also diuers points of the aduersaries Preface and first chapter, that fell not within the compasse of any order, examined and refuted.</title>
           <author>Sutcliffe, Matthew</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117867_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13160</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23454</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117867</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to all indifferent Readers, wherein not only the purpose of this treatise is declared, but also diuers points of the aduersaries Preface and first chapter, that fell not within the compasse of any order, examined and refuted.</title>
                 <author>Sutcliffe, Matthew</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A challenge concerning the Romish Church, her doctrine &amp; practises, published first against Rob. Parsons, and now againe reuiewed, enlarged, and fortified, and directed to him, to Frier Garnet, to the archpriest Blackevvell and all their adhærents, by Matth. Sutcliffe. Thereunto also is annexed an answere vnto certeine vaine, and friuolous exceptions, taken to his former challenge, and to a certeine worthlesse pamphlet lately set out by some poore disciple of Antichrist, and entituled, A detection of diuers notable vntrueths, contradictions, corruptions, and falsifications gathered out of M. Sutcliffes new challenge, &amp;c</title>
                 <author>Sutcliffe, Matthew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 <publisher>Harrison, John 3.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hatfield, Arnold.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 72, 93-210, 230, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Preface to all indifferent Readers, wherein not only the purpose of this treatise is declared, but also diuers points of the aduersaries Preface and first chapter, that fell not within the compasse of any order, examined and refuted.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the quarrels and cavils of false teachers and haeretikes, gentle reader, proceed from the fountaine of their malice, and are set forward by the suggestions of satan, who by all meanes endevoureth to trouble the peace of gods church, and to shake the faith of such weaklings, as are not firmely built vpon the immooueable rocke Christ Iesus: yet it pleaseth God oftentimes, by his vnsearchable wisdome, to dispose mens evill purposes and actions to his great glory, and the aduancement of religion, &amp; the great good of his church, which those men thought to ruinate. <hi>Etiam sic veris illis catholicis membris Christi malo suo prosunt</hi> saith Saint <note n="a" place="margin">Lib. 18. de ciuit. dei. c. 51.</note>
      <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> speaking of haeretickes, that contumaciously re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist the trueth, and seeke to defend their pestilent and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked opinions. Whereof although I had no great experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence before this time; yet now by the friuolous, and vaine cauils of a certaine corner-creeping disciple of antichrist against my late challenge made to <hi>Robert Parsons,</hi> disgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb facs="5"/> vnder the maske of two letters, and calling himselfe <hi>N. D.</hi> I finde to be most true. For whereas heeretofore my challenge was not knowne to many, and now beganne to be forgotten of such, as first had read it. I doubt not, but this vaine cauiller, by his vaine exceptions will cause the same to be both more diligently read, and better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, than it was like to be otherwise. for I doe not beleeue, that any man will offer me that wrong, that he will condemne me, before he hath both read, what I haue written, &amp; examined the matters wherewith I am charged.</p>
   <p>Secondly, because he hath alledged, that I deliver out matters upon mine owne credit, &amp; without proofe, I have taken occasion to peruse my former challenge, &amp; to forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the same with divers authorities and arguments, and so to publish it: assuring thee if any thing now want proofe, that it is of that nature, that it is of it selfe most euident, and needeth no proofe, being either knowen publikely, or confessed by the aduersaries themselues.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, this miserable fellow, that maketh himselfe partie against me, seemeth rather to betray the cause of the papists then otherwise. For taking vpon him to debate some matters in my late challenge, he is neither able to contradict my arguments, whereby I prooued, that the papists were neither catholicks, nor the true church, nor mainteined the old Christian faith, nor hath he abilitie to discharge his consorts of the crimes of haeresie and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, wherewith they stand charged, and now by his silence seeme to be conuicted. So that I doubt not, but if the pope may vnderstand, and be well informed of this prating fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes treacherous dealing in his cause, that he will either punish him, as a false traitor to his See, or at the least com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund him to silence as a weake ideot, and foolish plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in matter of religion.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, he doth greatly grace my writings against
<pb facs="5"/> his father <hi>Robert Parsons:</hi> for if he be not able to except against more places then sixe and twenty, or thereabout: it is cleare, that I haue said true in the rest, and that I haue argued, and alledged authorities to good purpose. For if I had offended, I doubt not but I should haue heard of it. And because you shal not suspect that these are but surmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, rather than firme conclusions; I doe before hand tell you, that this vaine bangler will not hereafter vndertake to answer my challenge from argument to argument, allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to allegation, testimony to testimony. Behold then ô miserable papists, your poore distressed proctor, and let the cacolike <hi>conuertite</hi> sisters relieue him with some good words of comfort, that in his needlesse quarrell hath ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne himselfe and his cause, and hath done me more fauour, than I shall be willing to requite him in haste.</p>
   <p>Fiftly, he doth discouer the vanitie of his owne bragges in his most miserable pleading. <hi>I require no more learning,</hi> saith <note n="b" place="margin">Detect. Ch. 1. p. 8.</note> he, <hi>then the vnderstanding of Latin; no more labour, than to open the books, &amp; view the places quoted; no more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, then that the tongue can truly report, what the heart thinketh:</hi> and yet when it commeth to the iumpe, with all that little learning he hath, and withall his labour could he not fasten any one vntrueth, or falsification vpon me; as shall sufficiently appeere by my answer. beside that, it is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous to talke of learning and vnderstanding of Latin, when in most of the places by him touched, I speake English, and alledge not the fathers words. in the rest it will appeare, that his prouision of Latin is not superabun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant. this sentence therefore he hath translated out of the pretended bishop of Eureux his discourse, although it fit not his purpose in any sort.</p>
   <p>Sixtly, He is a very vaine fellow to demand of vs such a conference, as passed in France. for well might he haue seene, if he had not wilfully shut his eies, that the case is
<pb facs="6"/> not like: and the reasons he might have vnderstood, if he had not bene sencelesse, they being so plainly laid downe in my refutation of his father <hi>Robert parsons</hi> his calumni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous relation sent vs from Rome (very wisely) of matters done in France. Further he might well haue remembred, if he had not bene forgetfull, that I offred the papists more then was demanded, for I did not onely promise to deale with <hi>Parsons,</hi> or any of his consortes in any priuate confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, but also in publicke writing, which might not onely be viewed of all men, but also remaine to posterity as a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony against those, that should be conuinced either of vntrueth or forgery, and which being extant in print nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we, nor our aduersaries should be able to alter, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or misreport any thing, that is written, as is the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry course of Popish Parasits in such conferences, and to shew, that I meant to performe as much, as I promised, I began to obiect certain epistles and canons forged not by such base thred-bare companions, as himselfe, but by the popes and church of Rome. I shewed also, that they had falsified the scriptures, and published infinit and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous lies in their legends read publickly in the church. finally I put <hi>Robert Parsons</hi> in minde of the notorious clip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and corrupting of fathers of late practised by the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists by their rubarbatif and expurgatorie indexes. but he like a wise fellow kept himselfe close and would no more heare of the matter, thinking it was better, as the old pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe teacheth, in this <hi>Carian</hi> to make triall of this hard aduenture, and <hi>to</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe, <hi>In care periculum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cito:</hi> teacheth that in base fellowes it is best to trie dangerous experiments.</note>
      <hi>thrust this asse downe headlong from the rockes,</hi> knowing well, that if we should ouercome him, or come to the taking of him up, we should finde nothing but the carcase of a dead asse. wherefore then is our adversary so desirous of a conference, that doubteth to trie his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood in iustifying his friends falshood and forgery con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning matters already laid to their charge? <note n="d" place="margin">Protrusit asinum in ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes. Horat. ep.</note> againe when he seeth our readines to answer, why is he so slow to obiect?</p>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <p>Finally where he thinketh to triumpth most gloriously and to leade my brother <hi>Willet,</hi> and me both captiues and fast chained at the taile of his chariot, there he doth most pitifully disgrace himselfe, and free vs, and marre all that he medleth withall.</p>
   <p>For first speaking of falsifications, he compareth them to <hi>Christ,</hi> and such mens incredulity, as will not beleeue him, he compareth to the incredulity of <hi>Thomas,</hi> that would not beleeue Christes resurrection, before he saw and felt manifest signes of it. <hi>the sentences alledged out of fathers and other authors,</hi> saith <note n="c" place="margin">Praes. fol. 5.</note> he, <hi>be so mangled and mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med &amp;c. as no protestant, I am sure will beleeue, vntill fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and seeing with Saint Thomas convince his incredulity.</hi> is not this a braue gallant then, trow you, that compareth trueth to falshood, the feeling of Christ to the feeling of falsifications?</p>
   <p>Secondly where the maine controuersy betwixt me and <hi>Robert Parsons</hi> in my challenge, is concerning the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and where this blinde baiard might see, that I haue alledged diuers strong reasons to prooue, that the congregation of <hi>Romanistes</hi> under the pope and cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls, is not the true church of Christ, there, all this not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding, my adversarie smoothly dissembleth the matter, and taketh that as granted, which he poore fellow can neuer prooue, and saith, <hi>that my</hi> brother <hi>Willet,</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">Fol. 1. praef.</note> and I <hi>imploy our forces in assaulting the impregnable sort of gods church, and battring that rocke, against which the gates of hell shall not preuaile.</hi> as if the congregation of the malignant, and wicked rable of antichrist could be the true church of Christ, or as if the gates of hell had not long since prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led against the pope and church of Rome. our aduersary therefore taking this for granted, that is the controuersy, if without controversy I haue not demonstrated, that the church of <hi>Rome</hi> is not the true church, sheweth, that he is
<pb facs="7"/> pregnant with folly, of which he will not be deliuered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he die, &amp; that his face is as hard as the rocke, of which he talketh.</p>
   <p>Thirdly he calleth popish religion <hi>Catholicke,</hi> and affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <note n="f" place="margin">Fol. 2. praef.</note>
      <hi>it was planted here by Gregory the great, who by suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession receiued it from Peter, &amp;c, and that it was alwaies visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble since Christ bearing still saile in the tempests of all persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> but he should doe well, to shew how true religion can be visible. for our saviour Christ saith, <note n="g" place="margin">Iohn 4.</note>
      <hi>that true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipers worship God in spirit and truth.</hi> but spirituall worship and true internall deuotion is not so easily seene. unlesse therefore our adversary suppose popish religion to consist in the popes mitre, and in coules of monkes, and such like externall matters; he shal hardly proue religion to be visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Againe, he doth greatly wrong the popish cause, if he affirme popish religion to have bene planted here in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land by <hi>Gregory,</hi> and be not able to answer my challenge, and to demonstrate those novelties, and late receiued fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, which I have mentioned, either to haue beene taught by <hi>Gregory,</hi> or at the least by his disciples to haue beene planted here in England. Furthermore, seeing in my chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge I doe prooue, <hi>that popish religion is not catholike,</hi> and giue for iustification of that point notable instances, such as our aduersary shall not be able to answer; is it not noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious impudency, to take this, as a matter either prooued, or confessed, and slily to call haeresie catholike religion? finally, I must entreat some plaine dealing papist to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish this detector, or rather detractor of ours, not to say, that <hi>Gregory</hi> receiued the popish religion, that now is mainteined by the pope of Rome, and was first established in the conuenticle of <hi>Trent,</hi> from <hi>Peter;</hi> or that all, that is taught in <hi>Gregories</hi> dialogues, or epistles came from <hi>Peter;</hi> or that the <hi>Romish</hi> church, that now is visible in the pope, cardinals, monkes, and swarmes of friers, and in Romish
<pb facs="7"/> ceremonies, <hi>hath borne saile in the tempests of all persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> for it is the pope, and his bloody inquisitors, that do persecute others, and are not persecuted. and if this be a qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ty of the church, <hi>to beare saile in tempests of persecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> certes the pope and his retinue cannot be the true church, that for many hundred yeeres have lived in all pompe, iolitie, and pleasure. but if the Romish church be so well able to beare saile in tempests, it were much to be wished, that the pope and his cardinals would saile to the Indiaes, where we might heare no more of them, and that they would take our aduersary with them, who percase would prooue a better swabber, then a disputer.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, In the beginning of his Praeface, he saith, <hi>he will present to his readers view a representation, or liuely pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of a conference, that is, notable vntrueths and falsificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp;c.</hi> and these also he auoucheth he will gather out of master <hi>Willets,</hi> and my writings. wherein I would pray all moderate papists to consider with indifferency this fond speech of this most miserable popish creature and proc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. he calleth <hi>notable untrueths and falsifications a paterne of such a conference,</hi> as he desireth. If then he desire a confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, he must needs desire vntrueths and falsifications, if his words haue any sence. I know, he hopeth to picke them out of our writings. but if he finde any, they must be such, as are vttered by himselfe, and his conforts, and not by vs. in the meane while his fellowes are sory to see him speake so foolishly of conferences, vntrueths, and falsificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
   <p>Fiftly, He <note n="e" place="margin">Fol. 1. praef.</note> talketh also verie idelly <hi>of backe dores, and deceitfull entries, such as</hi> Daniel <hi>detected in</hi> Bels <hi>idolatrous priests.</hi> which, if I did not know the mans great simplicity, I would haue imagined to haue beene foisted into his Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face by some backe friend to popish religion, to the great disgrace of Romish priests, that by backe dores, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull
<pb facs="8"/> entries play many lewd parts with their nonnes in Spaine and Italy, and with recusants wiues, maides, and daughters, where they are lodged and interteined in England, as shall be prooved by particulars, if any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> to aske me the question. These also doe worship idoles as brutishly as the <note n="f" place="margin">
         <hi>Daniel</hi> 14. in the Latin translation.</note>
      <hi>Babylonians</hi> did <hi>Bel,</hi> and set vp the images of saint <hi>Anthony,</hi> and saint <hi>Dominicke</hi> and other saints vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on altars, as the <hi>Babylonians</hi> did their god <hi>Bel.</hi> finally they burne incense to their idoles, and crouch to them, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer sacrifices before them, as the idolatrous priests did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Bel.</hi> There resteth therefore nothing to make them all like to <hi>Bels</hi> priests, but, now their fraudes and cousinages and idolatries and impieties are discouered, that some ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous prince would doe with the popish priests of <hi>Baal</hi> in England and other places, as the king of <hi>Babylon</hi> did with the priests of Bel in his country. and that would make an end both of the whole controuersy, and of this idle fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes brabling.</p>
   <p>6 Likewise under the title of his booke hee set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth downe this verse. <note n="g" place="margin">
         <hi>Hierom</hi> 14.</note>
      <hi>falsely saieth the Lord doe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets prophesie in my name. I haue not sent them, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them, nor spoken to them. they prophesie unto you a lying vision, and diuination, and fraud, and the deceipt of there owne heart.</hi> whereby it seemeth he was hired, to speake shame and reproch of his owne most lewd companions, comming directly from antichrist, and not from Christ; of the church of Rome, that in liew of Gods word readeth fables and lying legends; and of the pope, that in his lying decretales brocheth the deceits of his owne heart, neither can this prophesie be expounded of any so fitly, as of the false priests of <hi>Baal,</hi> that come with faculties from the pope without any one word of authority, or lawful mission from God; and that prophesie lying visions of the restoring of the idolatrous religion of papists, and preach the fancies
<pb facs="8"/> and deceits of there owne hearts, out of their masters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>turall and false dictates. I know he aimeth at vs. but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing chosen this sentence for an ornament of the front of his lying pamphlet, he must be content to take it to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, and must for any helpe he shall haue of vs, necessarily be forced to apply it to his friends, where it is best deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
   <p>7 Talking of suposed falsifications he saith, <hi>three things make a falsary: first changing of the trueth into falshood, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly craft and malice, and lastly domage or hurt.</hi> and to proue his words true, he alledgeth the names of <hi>Hostiensis and Panormitan:</hi> two ancient canonistes. but vnlesse he acquit himselfe the better, in talking of falsification it will be proued, that he hath falsely alledged these two authors. no man certes euer talked more simply of falsity, and falsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, then this falsary. for, not either change of trueth into falshood, is falsity, no albeit it be craftily done, &amp; with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment to some person (for then should euery malicious and hurtfull liar be a falsary also; and the authours and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouers of the Romish legends and breuiaries should also be notorious falsaries, hauing told many grosse malicious lies to the great slander and hurt of religion) nor hath our aduersary rightly defined a falsary. for a falsary is he, that in writings addeth or detracteth, or altereth any thing fraudulently, as appeareth by the glosse <hi>in c. in memoriam. dist.</hi> 19. and as the Romanistes shew themselves to be by their expurgatory indexes. but saith our detractor in the margent, <hi>in the french copy printed by Hierome Verdussen</hi> it is so. but this is contrary to the text. beside that, we are no more ro beleeue the print of <hi>Hierome Verdussen,</hi> then of <hi>Iulian Greenesleue.</hi> if our aduersary will make such crakes, he must bring vs better authours then <hi>Hierome Verdussen,</hi> or the popish reporter of the conference betwixt M. <hi>Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>su,</hi> and <hi>Eureux.</hi> is it then likely, that our aduersary should
<pb facs="9"/> conuince vs of falsification, that albeit himsefe commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth many grosse falsifications, yet knoweth not what this word meaneth? which may also appeare in this, that he chargeth me with falsification in the first and second place noted page. 47. &amp; 51. where I doe not so much as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge any writing, or any mans words, but onely quote <hi>Augustin</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius</hi> in the margent, to shew that my assertion may be proued out of their writings.</p>
   <p>8 His metaphors, and profound allegoricall speeches he vseth to draw from womens rocks. <hi>as though</hi> saith he, <hi>he had not towe inough to his rocke.</hi> which sheweth that this companion is better seene in womens rockes and frockes, then in any point of diuinity. beware therefore you of the cacolicke crew, that such gallants come not neere your wiues, daughters, nor maids, that they play not with you a tricke of their cacolicke religion, if you beleeue not me, beleeue <hi>Palingenius,</hi> that would haue such mates excluded out of mens houses, that meane to keepe their women chast.</p>
   <p>9 And although this is the mans great simplicity and weaknesse; yet would he needs incounter at one time M. <hi>Willet,</hi> and me both together. nay, as if we were nothing in this giants hands, with great arrogancy he setteth also vpō M. <hi>Thomas Bell,</hi> a man while he was yet a popish priest, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them accounted the most learned, sufficient and graue man among their company, and now well knowen by his learned workes not answerable, at the least not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, to haue much profited since. but what is it, that our wise aduersary obiecteth, that he should cry out so loud against Master <hi>Bell?</hi> what is the <hi>Gordian knot,</hi> that he supposeth <hi>to be insoluble?</hi> forsooth, because he saith, <hi>that the bishops of Rome, vntill the daies of Saint Augustine, and long after, were very godly men, and taught the same doctrine, that Saint Peter had done before them: and yet affirmeth also,
<pb facs="9"/> that pope Syricius was seduced by Sathan, published wicked doctrine &amp; taught the flat doctrine of the divel; &amp; that pope Sozimus brought in superstition, and falsified the decrees of the Nicene councell. so to mainteine the vsurped primacie of the Church of Rome.</hi> as if M. <hi>Belles</hi> propositions might not well stand together. for he saith not, that <hi>all the bishops of Rome were good and godly men, and taught true doctrine vntill S. Augustines time;</hi> but speaketh indefinitly of the bishops of Rome without adding, <hi>all;</hi> which maner of speech <hi>in materia contingenti,</hi> is not to be taken absolutely and vniuersally, but for the most part. and so no doubt saint <hi>Augustine</hi> speaking of the bishops of Rome vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood it, knowing that <hi>Marcelline</hi> sacrificed to idoles, and that <hi>Liberius</hi> was an Arrian. and we may say also, that the apostles of <hi>Christ</hi> were good men, although <hi>Judas</hi> was a traitor, and lanterne bearer to the Iewes, as some popish writers say, that betraied <hi>Christ,</hi> and much of the nature and condition of this <hi>detectour</hi> of falsifications, and detractor from honest men, and a very lanterner of Antichrist, and a traitour to his countrey. let him therefore beware he be not taken passing through backe dores, like the idolatrous priests of <hi>Bel,</hi> and so for his gordian knot, be taken tied in a <hi>Tyburne</hi> knot.</p>
   <p>10 I need not say much of our adversaries forme of writing, or frame of sentences. for it appeereth euery where, that he did not know the difference of <hi>pneuma,</hi> and <hi>periodus;</hi> nor could distinguish betwixt <hi>colons</hi> and <hi>periodes, commaes</hi> and <hi>colons.</hi> his whole discouse is liker to nothing that I can imagine, then to the way betweene <hi>Chard</hi> and <hi>Honiton</hi> in the west countrey, that is, rude and rugged, vp hill and downe hill, and very vnequall. but to let that passe, yet may I not passe in silence, that <note n="a" place="margin">Praefat. fol. 1.</note> speaking <hi>of the great commanders and princely pilots, that sit at the sterne of the common wealth,</hi> he seemeth to communicate her Maiesties
<pb facs="10"/> souereigne authority to inferior persons, and doth not once vouchsafe to acknowledge her princely power, or to name her among the governors of this state. and yet such disloiall traitors, that acknowledge the popes supreme au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and deny her Maiesties power, as being excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate by the popes <hi>scuruinesse,</hi> (our fellow percase would say <hi>holinesse</hi>) are not sought out, nor brought to such a triall, as their offences deserue.</p>
   <p>By this therefore it may appeare, that, as our aduersary hath no ability to disproue any point of religion, which we hold, so he hath vtterly shamed his consorts, and the crew of papists, that hitherto haue made great brags of this their champion, &amp; of his inuincible arguments, all hard &amp; knot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, like the haft of a dougeon dagger. he hath also vtterly shamed himself in medling with these matters, being a mā not read, nor any way fit to discourse, or handle matter of cōtrouersy: the which, that it may further appere, I purpose, god willing, not only to iustify my former chalenge, which this poore menowe would nibble at, but also to discharge my selfe honestly of all those vntruthes and falsifications, which the detractor maliciously goeth about to charge vpon me. Wherein, that I may proceed more formally, &amp; not onely skin this dead dog, whose ouerthrow shall helpe vs nothing, but handle somewhat else, that may make for the aduantage of true religion, and the instruction of the ignorant; <note place="margin">The order and chiefe propositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; chapters of the discourse ensuing.</note> I wil, God willing, declare, first <hi>that the church of Rome that now is, and which embraceth the doctrine of the pope and conuenticle of Trent, is not the true church of Christ Iesus.</hi> and secondly, <hi>that the doctrines and traditions of the Romish church, which the church of England refuseth, are meere nouelties and late deuised fancies, for the most part.</hi> thirdly, <hi>that the papists are no true catholikes, nor hold the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike faith,</hi> and that it is a great wrong offred to Christes church to call them <hi>catholikes,</hi> vnlesse it be, as we call dead
<pb facs="10"/> carcases, men. fourthly, <hi>that papists mainteine many both old &amp; new haresies and points of doctrine contrary to the word of God, and to the catholike faith.</hi> fifthly, that they are idolaters. finally, <hi>that such as haue died in the popes quarrell in England were vnnaturall traitors, and no true martyrs, and that such priests also as come from Rome with commission and faculties from the pope, are traitors and enemies to their prince and countrey, and so to be reputed and taken, and not otherwise.</hi> All which points, one or two excepted, I handled in my last challenge, this challenge thus iustified, I shall God willing presently encountre our detractor, and answer first his obiections concerning <hi>vntruthes:</hi> secondly his quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels concerning supposed <hi>falsifications:</hi> thirdly his vaine &amp; childish <hi>obseruations.</hi> and to shew the vanitie of our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries pleading, and how much the papists are to shunne all conferences, and disputes concerning lies, and falsificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; I will also for further euidence against them set down, first certeine notorious lies, and forgeries committed by the popes and church of Rome: and next such lies and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geries, as are committed by their principall agents. and heerein first I will declare <hi>Bellarmine</hi> to be most guiltie in this point. the next place shall conteine <hi>Baronius</hi> his cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall leasinges. after them I will note certeine notorious lies and forgeries conteined in the writings of other pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists, yea of <hi>Parsons</hi> himselfe, and of this <hi>Momus,</hi> in his new nothing, which he calleth <hi>a detection of lies and falsificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> finally to answer his obseruations, I will also discourse of such things as in our aduersaries, and their writings seeme woorthy to be obserued. and all this, to let our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries know, that they had more need to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, then to presse vs; and to take the beames out of their owne eies rather, then to espie motes in our eies.</p>
   <p>As for his railing words, &amp; rustical &amp; vnciuil behauiour, I leave to be censured by the archpriest in his next gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb facs="11"/> synod: which if he doe not, I will referre him over to be answered by master <hi>Kempe</hi> vpon the stage. and if he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist not his railing and rusticalitie either vpon the arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priests admonition, or master <hi>Kempes</hi> censure; I assure him, I will set a fellow to answer him, that shall so currie him and his consorts the papists, and that shall in such sort tippe vp their vilanies, that the whole fraternitie of asses shall curse him for braying so vnciuilly. I hope also, that some odde priest or other, out of his grammer dictates will admonish him, to looke better to his grammer rules, and tell him, that he hath falsified a verse out of <hi>Horace,</hi> and made a grosse fault in it. <note place="margin">This is the onely verse in the booke.</note> for where <hi>Horace</hi> saith, <hi>quid dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num tanto feret hic pro missor hiatu:</hi> our wise <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Pag.</hi> 4.</note> aduersarie hath, <hi>quid dignum tanto proferet promissor hiatu:</hi> both alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his authors words, and committing a fault in the verse, and marring the sence.</p>
   <p>His reprochfull termes omitted, and his small errors pardoned, there is nothing in his pamphlet, which I haue not answered, and, I hope in that sort, that he shall not be able to take iust exception against any thing I haue said or done. it may be, that he will be offended, for that not being able to speake by letters, and finding his name to be <hi>E. O.</hi> I doe name the baby somtime <hi>detector,</hi> or <hi>detractor,</hi> somtime <hi>ectaticall owliglasse.</hi> I haue great reason to doe it. for I doe perceiue, that he is a desciple of <hi>Robert Parsons,</hi> who in his pamphlet <hi>of reasons, for not going to church,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth himselfe <hi>Iohn Howlet.</hi> what then can be more conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, then that his disciple, that goeth about to imitate him in his pride, railing, and phrase of speech, though very vnhandsomly, should be called <hi>Owliglasse</hi> alias Howly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glasse, and ectaticall, that is leapt out of his wit into a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle fit of foolery? if he like not this name, then let him set downe his owne name, and for my part he shall not heare worse then his name, vnlesse his faults deserue it.</p>
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <p>Both this challenge, and the answere to the detractors ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, presuming vpon thy indifferency I recommend to thy reading. much I will not request at thy hands, and small fauours are easily granted. Examine, I pray thee, both my answere, and my aduersaries obiections, and yeeld to neither side more then is prooued: compare his great brags, with his poore talent of writing, and his scornefull termes with his slender matters, and thou shalt easily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that short answeres may serue such simple argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. it may be, that thou and I differ in opinion. yet neuer refuse to yeeld to trueth; nor resolue to defend dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loialty or errour.</p>
   <p>I haue, as thou maiest see, dealt plainly, and professe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly, that I will not mainteine any error, whereof I can be conuinced. if the aduersarie would take the same course, there might be an end of this contention. <hi>Rob. Parsons</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne this quarrell, albeit he hath first giuen it ouer. the ground of his pleading standing principally vpon the title of <hi>ancient and catholike religion,</hi> and the innocency of mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing priests, and friers, and their consorts, I gaue him a short issue in my former chalenge, and offered to proue, that popish religion established in the conuenticle of <hi>Trent,</hi> and now receiued by the church of Rome, is neither ancient, catholicke, nor true. if they cannot proue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to be catholicks, why doe they entitle themselues ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes? if their relsgion be new, why doe they bragge of antiquity? if they be haeretickes, why are they not asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, to take to themselues the praerogatiues of the true church? if the Iebusites and rheir consorts be combined with forrein enimies, what reason haue they to challenge the fauour due to subiects?</p>
   <p>Vpon occasion of an ecstaticall fellowes importunity, I doe renew the same challenge againe, and by all meanes prouoke <hi>Robert Parsons</hi> to answere. and because percase
<pb facs="12"/> he is busie comploting of matters against his country at Rome, I addresse it also to Frier Garnet and the archpriest Blackewell, that are neerer at hand, and not vnaquainted with the worthy volume of exceptions lately published a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst me. If <hi>Parsons</hi> haue not laisure, let one of them an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere. it is a shame to begin a quarrell, and to giue it ouer first. for one bout they haue no reason to refuse me. if they pretend want of books and laisure, they know <hi>Doway</hi> is not farre off. They haue begon to crie out of falsifications and untruthes, let them therefore make triall, how they can answere for themselues. <hi>Parsons</hi> was woont to be ready to plead for others. now therefore he hath no reason but to plead for himselfe. In time past he and that false traitor <hi>Allen</hi> filled mens eares with their clamours, <hi>contra persequu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores Anglos.</hi> let them therefore defend their consorts, that are <hi>preditores Angliae,</hi> &amp; enimies to their country. no man hath greater cause to defend traitors, then traitors. If they refuse to answere for themselues, or to satisfie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, I hope for modesty sake hereafter, they will neither arrogate to themselues the title of the church, nor the shelter of catholicke religion, neither can they with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestie vant of antiquity, or accuse true men of heresie, whereof themselues are most guilty. finally if shame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straine not their tongues, yet feare of punnishment may keepe them in temper, being declared to be professed eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to their prince and country, &amp; a packe of rinegned english cōspiring with the enimies of this state, &amp; combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together for the ouerthrow of religion &amp; the realme.</p>
   <p>If my aduersary and his consorts shall no way be able, though otherwise willing inough, to cleare themselues of most malitious libelling, lying, and forging, I trust they wil hereafter spare me, a plaine fellow, and one that no way standeth in need of such poore shifts for the iustification of my cause. And I doubt not, but with shame inough
<pb facs="12"/> they will for euer hereafter cease to make any challenge concerning lies and falsifications, hauing so euill successe in this first incounter.</p>
   <p>If I haue cleared this state from all imputation of iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice in the proceeding against Iesuites, seminary priests, popish rebels and their adherents; neither haue the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates reason to suffer <hi>Robert Parsons</hi> his libels to flie abroad to the slander of the state, nor any good subiect to allow of his calumniations, and most wicked libels.</p>
   <p>If it doe clearely appeare, that <hi>Robert Parsons</hi> and his trecherous consorts are linked and combined with foraine enemies, and by no meanes will submit themselues to her Maiesties lawes and authoritie, those that haue the custo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and execution of her lawes, committed vnto them, I doubt not, will haue a watchfull eie ouer the proceedings of such slippery companions, and with great constancie and resolution mainteine hir Maiesties authority, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute her lawes against such as wilfully impugne it. the late edict published against this vermine, doth shew that the state is not onely well acquainted with their leud prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises, but also resolute to punish such wicked practisers, and plotters, as hitherto haue abused her Maiesties great clemency toward them.</p>
   <p>If it appere that the Iebusites and priests teach haeresie, and lies, it behooveth all true christians to auoid them. Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> in his second epistle doth giue vs warning not to haue any familiaritie with them, or so much as once <hi>to bidde them God speed.</hi> the church <note n="c" place="margin">Apocal. 2.</note> of <hi>Thyatira</hi> is reproo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for permitting a wicked false prophet <hi>to teach and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Gods people.</hi> and our sauiour <note n="d" place="margin">Matth. 7.</note> Christ giueth vs war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of false prophets, <hi>that come vnto vs in sheepes clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and inwardly are rauening woolues.</hi> these false masse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priests deuoure many widdowes houses, and abuse the
<pb facs="13"/> simplicity of many yoong youthes to their vtter ruine and destruction. and yet that is not the woorst. for they do not onely ouerthrow their worldly states, but also destroy their soules, and lead them headlong into hell.</p>
   <p>If the popes agents vnder pretence of religion haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled their folowers in diuers practises of faction and treason, I hope all English, albeit otherwise fauorers of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, wil better looke, how they engage themselues in trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. they come from forreine enemies, and depend vpon them; and though they talke of religion, yet their intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is wholy for the pope and Spaniard, and their course is irreligious and factious.</p>
   <p>If popish religion founded in the conuenticle of <hi>Trent,</hi> and taught by late popes and their proctors be catholike, and ancient, then will it be an easie matter to shew it, and to answer our obiections, where we prooue the contrary. if our aduersaries flie triall, and will not ioine with vs, and directly answere; then haue all papists and others, reason to flie from such false teachers, and heretikes, and to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don all their wicked haeresies. there is no agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Christ and Belial,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.</note> betwixt trueth and error, light and darknes. if they can shew themselues, that they are no ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, they will cleere themselues: if not, why do they seeke to erect altars of <hi>Baal</hi> in euery corner? and why doe not all Christians auoid to communicate with the priests of <hi>Baal</hi> in their idolatrous masse? <note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.</note>
      <hi>there is no agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the temple of God and idoles,</hi> neither <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note>
      <hi>can any drinke the Lords cuppe, that doth participate at the table of diuels,</hi> or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelish masse. but what should I talke of the Lords cup, when these idolatrous priests take the Lords cup from all that follow them?</p>
   <p>If the aduersaries be cleare of lying and falsification; then will they answer plainly and directly, as I haue answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="13"/> them. if their lies and forgeries be made notorious to the world, he is not very wise, that will trust such lying and forging companions.</p>
   <p>But what should I need to declare that briefely, which at large is prooued in the discourse following? reade onely diligently, and examine carefully, and iudge indifferently. and so leauing thee to thy meditations, and referring thee to the touch of both our aduersaries accusations, and our answers, I beseech God to giue thee true vnderstanding of his sauing trueth. and that hee will giue thee grace, if thou knowest the trueth, to perseuere constant vnto the end: if thou cariest a preiudicate affection towards pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, then to see into the deformities, impostures and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of popish religion: and that in the end it will please him, to discouer all fraudes, impostures, conspiracies, trecheries and vilanies of the popish faction, and to let thee see the damnation of the great whore, and the abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Babylon. Adieu.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in all Christian affection, MATTH. SUTCLIFFE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>