<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117710_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19425</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5852</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117710</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>None but Christ, none but Christ : Intimating, that in Him, who is the Lord of Lords, and Prince onely, is to be found, the full and absolute cure of mans misery</title>
                 <author>Cotton, Clement</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>116 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongst the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miseries that haue light vpon vs by the fall of our first parents, those of the soule are chiefest; and amongst them, this is not the least, that though we be conuinced by the Word and Spirit, to be forlorne crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, yet we naturally shun to take any knowledge thereof.</p>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <p>No man is rocked so fast asleepe in the cradle of secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, but at one time or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, this alarum rings in his eares:<note place="margin">Rom. 3.19, 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Eccle 11 9. &amp; 12.14.</note>
      <hi>Thou hast sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and therefore must come to iudgement.</hi> But who trembleth in himselfe at the sound thereof, that he might finde rest in the day of trouble?<note place="margin">Hab. 3.16.</note>
   </p>
   <p>It cannot bee, but <hi>these troubled thoughts</hi> will now and then fasten vpon the most hard-hearted and impenitent sinner;<note place="margin">Dan 5.6.</note>
      <note place="margin">Act. 24.26.</note>
      <hi>surely all things are not wel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene</hi> God <hi>and me;</hi> and, <hi>what will become of me another day?</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.10.</note> And yet
<pb facs="7"/> where is he for all that, who will presently fall to <hi>sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching</hi> &amp; <hi>iudging</hi> of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe,<note place="margin">Lam. 3.40.</note>
      <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.3.</note> that he <hi>might not be iudged of the Lord?</hi> No, the heart of man is natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly swolne with such a diuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish pride,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.7, 8.</note>
      <note place="margin">Isai, 65.2.</note> that though hee know God is, and will bee, <hi>his Iudge,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 2.16.</note> yet will hee not make <hi>supplication to his Iudge.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iob 9.15. 1 Pet. 5.5, 6</note> And albeit we know that GOD <hi>resisteth the proud,</hi> and hath decreed in himselfe to staine all the glory thereof;<note place="margin">Isa. 23.9. Dan. 4.34.</note> yet <hi>walke we on still in our pride, against him. But who was euer fierce against him and prospered?</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.22. Iob 9.4.</note>
   </p>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <p>Thou then that art as yet in thy naturall estate, I wish thee in the name of GOD, speedily to examine thy selfe vpon thy bed:<note place="margin">Psal. 6.4. Zeph. 2.1.</note> and betweene the Lord and thee, propound these que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions to thy soule; <hi>Soule, what saist thou to the guilt of</hi> Adams <hi>sinne?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 5.12.</note>
      <hi>It is imputed to thee, I pray thee how shall wee answer it? Thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est that this guilt binds vs ouer to eternal death,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 5.16. &amp; 6.23. Psal. 139.7. 2. Cor. 5.10.</note>
      <hi>there is no fleeing for vs, from the face of the Iudge, what shall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of thee and me,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Act. 17.31.</note>
      <hi>in the day of the Lords
<pb facs="8"/> wrath? Thou knowest, that all our righteousnes is but as filthy clouts,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Isai. 64.6. Iob 14.4. Psal. 67.7.</note>
      <hi>&amp; how shall wee be able to stand before the Lords pure eyes,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hab. 1.13.</note>
      <hi>which can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold no impurity? Thou knowest also that our sinnes are aboue mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure sinfull, yea,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ezra 9.6.</note>
      <hi>farre exceeding the sands of the sea,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom 7.13.</note>
      <hi>both for weight and number;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 40.11. Psal. 38.4.</note>
      <hi>must they not needs then sinke vs to hell, without recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? For Gods sake (O my soule) let vs looke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout vs, &amp; whilst space,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Reuel. 221.</note>
      <hi>place, and meanes are allotted vs,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Isai. 55.6.</note>
      <hi>ponder wee
<pb facs="9"/> seriously these things in time. Let vs, I pray thee, take vnto vs words, and now,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hos. 14.2.</note>
      <hi>euen now turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vnto the LORD, from whom wee haue too too long,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Isa. 53.6.</note>
      <hi>most wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully erred: Beseech we him, that he would take away all iniquity and receiue vs graciously, that wee may eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>r here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after render him the calues of our lips.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thus or in the like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, should euery one that meane to escape <hi>the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of GOD,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom 2.30</note> and the iust <hi>damnation of hell,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 23.33.</note> question and reason with
<pb facs="9"/> his owne soule. For it is not the <hi>guiltlesse,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luk. 15.18, 19. &amp; 18.13.</note> but the <hi>guiltie,</hi> that prizeth a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don; it is not the <hi>whole,</hi> but the <hi>sicke,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat 9.2.</note> that is glad of the Physician: So, if sin make thee not sicke at the very heart,<note place="margin">Act. 2.37.4.38.</note> thou wilt not esteeme of Christ, nor of the saluation which hee hath brought for all <hi>broken-hearted sinners,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luk. 4.18.</note>
      <hi>no more than of a rush.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math. 22.5.</note>
   </p>
   <p>A little to helpe thee then, that hast not yet felt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> spirituall sicknesse (and also somewhat to refresh the memory of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se who haue) here is in a short summe dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered vnto thee, some of
<pb facs="10"/> the maladies of thy soule, shewing thee how Christ is both the Physician, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine of them seuerally, as the title giuen to the Booke, <hi>None but Christ, none but Christ,</hi> giues thee to vnderstand.</p>
   <p>Touching the which, if thou wouldest I should yeeld thee a reason; then know, that I tooke it not vp at randome; but as I found them the words, and those the last words of a constant Martyr of Christ, <hi>Iohn Lambert</hi> by name; which (as I conceiue) beeing vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by him, as the trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant voice of faith, after
<pb facs="10"/> that hee had, through the power of Christ, put to flight the feare of Hell, Sinne, and Death, &amp;c. (as by dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of them may appeare) So by way of imitation, I thinke them (not tying any to sillables) well beseeming the thoughts, and speeches also of euery Christian, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on safe and sure grounds, as in their dayly, so euen in their last conflicts to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp and vsed. Not as if heereby it were my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to exclude,<note place="margin">See Ioh. 3.16. Titus 3.5.</note> or shut out either the Father, or the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost, from hauing an hand in the worke of our sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, as well as Christ:
<pb facs="11"/> but attributing the same to him onely,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.34</note> as to the sole meritorious cause thereof: And so I bid thee hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ, C.C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>