<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Shelton, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117258_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12102</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22403</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117258</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Shelton, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A centurie of similies. By Thomas Shelton</title>
                 <author>Shelton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, John 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 62, 10 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Reatures inanimate, though they have motion, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, yet they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of the knowledge of what they doe, The sea ebbs, and flowes, the sunne shines, heates and moves continually: The winde goeth his circuits, the fire burnes, the trees and plants grow, yet none of them have intelligence that they doe so, but are all carried by a secret impres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the first mover, Creatures that are brutish, all the knowledge they have is bounded in the satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying
<pb facs="3"/> of sensuall appetite. Man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indued with a reasonable soule, with an indefatigable motion, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth after knowledge of things, humane and divine, and is then best apaid, when his knowledg is at once divers wayes enriched, when severall things concurre to adde to his stock. Beautie is delightfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a mixture of different colours; proportion is comely being a fit composure of different members: Musicke is pleasant being a harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of different sounds.</p>
   <p>Now that man might at once both vnderstand things that are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, (and therefore in their owne knowledge above his reach) and might also reape both profit and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>light God hath delivered truths in
<pb facs="3"/> the old testament vnder types, and figures; in the new by similitudes &amp; comparisons. There is nothing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in nature either in heaven or earth, but God hath made vse of it to set forth the excellency of Christ, and the good things wee have by him. Christ himselfe is compared to the <hi>sunne,</hi> to <hi>water,</hi> to <hi>bread,</hi> to a <hi>vine,</hi> &amp;c. Grace by Christ, to <hi>garments,</hi> a <hi>feast, gold, eye-salve.</hi> Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to <hi>Throns, Crownes, Kingdomes,</hi> &amp;c▪ that together vpon the sight, or thought of these things, we might be raised up to contemplate the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies, in and by him. And as the best so also the worst things are this way conveyed to our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension. Sinne is compated to <hi>filthinesse, vomit, rags,</hi> &amp;c. Sinners to <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>tigers, beares, serpents</hi> &amp;c. The pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment of sin to <hi>chaines, prison,</hi> &amp;c. that by these sensible evills wee might the better conceiue of those which are unutterable,</p>
   <p>And for this purpose I have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured these few similies to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like view, that the reader at once might have profit with pleasure. I intended a far greater number; but considering how vntowardly the left-handed world reacheth things, I thought fit to pauze a while and for the present only send a few for a tast, &amp; as I see them relished, I shall (God willing) either increase their number, or wish them in my closet againe.</p>
   <p>I thought it not very needfull to observe a method in placing them
<pb facs="4"/> vnder severall heads, being so few in number that they all require no long time to peruse; yet those that will not be at that paines may ease themselves by a small table annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. I have also to each simile set downe a text of scripture agreeable to the scope of it, by all which that thou mayst be benefited, shal be the desire of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>THOMAS SHELTON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>