<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO
The Noble Company of Cordwainers, the worshipfull Company
of Sadlers and Woodmongers: To the worthy, honest and laudable Com∣pany
of Watermen; And to the Sacred Societie of Hackney-men; And finally, to
as many as are grieued and vniustly impouerished, and molested
with the Worlds running on Wheeles.</title>
           <author>Taylor, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117734_Bo1_37_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13415</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23725</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117734</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO
The Noble Company of Cordwainers, the worshipfull Company
of Sadlers and Woodmongers: To the worthy, honest and laudable Com∣pany
of Watermen; And to the Sacred Societie of Hackney-men; And finally, to
as many as are grieued and vniustly impouerished, and molested
with the Worlds running on Wheeles.</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>All the vvorkes of Iohn Taylor the water-poet : Beeing sixty and three in number. Collected into one volume by the author: vvith sundry new additions, corrected, reuised, and newly imprinted, 1630</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Boler (Bowler), James 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Elizabeth.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 148, 2, 93, 92-200, 225-343, 1, 14, 13-146 pages, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <head>TO
The Noble Company of Cordwainers, the worshipfull Company
of Sadlers and Woodmongers: To the worthy, honest and laudable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
of Watermen; And to the Sacred Societie of Hackney-men; And finally, to
as many as are grieued and vniustly impouerished, and molested
with the Worlds running on Wheeles.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>GEntlemen</hi> and <hi>Yeomen,</hi> maruell not that I write this Pamphlet in Prose now, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
beforetimes set forth so many Bookes in Verse: The first reason that moued me to
write thus, was because I was Lame, and durst not write Verses, for seare they should be infected
with my Griefe, and be lame too. The Second Reason is, because that I finde no good rime for
a <hi>Coach,</hi> but <hi>Broach, Roach, Encroach,</hi> or such like. And you know that the <hi>Coach</hi> hath
ouer-throwne the good vse of the <hi>Broach</hi> and Broach-turner, turning the one to <hi>Rackes,</hi> and
the other to <hi>Iackes,</hi> quite through the Kingdome. The <hi>Roach</hi> is a dry bish, much like the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable
profit of a <hi>Coach;</hi> it will cost more the dressing and appurtenances then tis worth.
For the word <hi>Encroach,</hi> I thinke that best befits it, for I think neuer such an impudent proud,
sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cie Intruder or Encroacher came into the world as a <hi>Coach</hi> is; for it hath driuen many
honest Families out of their Houses, many Knights to Beggers, Corporations to pouerty, Almes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> to all misdeedes, Hospitality to extortion, Plenty to famine, Humility to pride, Compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
to oppression, and all Earthly goodnes almost to an vtter confusion.</p>
   <p>These haue beene the causes why I writ this Booke in Prose, and Dedicated it to all your good
Companies, knowing that you haue borne a heauie share in the Calamitie which these hyred
Hackney bell-Carts haue put this Common-wealth vnto; For in all my whole Discourse, I
doe not enueigh against any <hi>Coaches</hi> that belong to persons of worth or qualitie, but onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
the Carter piller swarme of hyrelings; they haue vndone my poore Trade, whereof I
am in Member, and though I look for no reformation yet I expect the benefit of an old prouerbe,
<hi>(Giue the losers leaue to speake.)</hi> I haue imbroadered it with mirth, Quilted it with
materiall stuffe, Lac'd it with similitudes; Sowed it with comparisons, and in a word, so plaid
the Taylor with it, that I think it will fit the wearing of any honest mans Reading, attention,
and liking; But howsoeuer, I leaue both it and my selfe to remaine.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours as you are mine,
<hi>Iohn Taylor.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>