<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE IVDI∣cicus Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117528_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18238</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4859</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117528</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE IVDI∣cicus Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cato translated grammatically : directing for vnderstanding, construing, parsing, making, and proouing the same Latine: and so for continuall practice of the grammaticall analysis and genesis. Done for the good of schooles, and of all desirous to recouer, or keep that which they got in the grammar-schoole, or to increase therein</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 32, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>TO THE IVDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cicus Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Earned Reader, if you perceiue the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of this kinde of translating, help louingly to amend vvhat is amisse. Future editions (God willing) shall supply what is wanting, and bring to more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
   <list>
      <head>To the Learner.</head>
      <item>1. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> carefull firs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> to be ready in the Grounds of your Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Grammar, at least to haue the perfect vnderstanding
<pb facs="7"/>
of them; and to bee very cunning in the examples of Nounes and Verbes, also to haue very readily the Rule of construing. For your better direction heerein, see the questions of the Accidence and Grammar, called <hi>The Posing of the Parts,</hi> gathered of purpose to help thereto.</item>
      <item>2. In vsing these translations, labour euer, first, to vnderstand fully the matter of euery sentence which you would construe, by oft reading ouer the English, to get it (as it were) without book.</item>
      <item>3 Then learne to construe the Latin according to the rule of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struing, vsing the book where you doubt, and to the end to goe sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and speedily.</item>
      <item>4 Next, to parse as you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strue, being helped by the Latin and English together.</item>
      <item>
         <pb facs="7"/>5. After, trie to construe and parse out of the English alone, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king only on it: whereby you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually make Latin.</item>
      <item>6. Lastly, prooue whether by oft reading-ouer the Latin out of the English (first, according to the order of the translation; after, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the order of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour) both Latin and matter will not most speedily bee made your owne.</item>
   </list>
   <closer>Vnderstand the matter perfectly; and the Latin will flow most easily, as of the owne accord.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>