<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the wel-willers of Architecture.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117091_Fr4_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11922</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22235</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117091</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the wel-willers of Architecture.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first booke of architecture, made by Sebastian Serly, entreating of geometrie. Translated out of Italian into Dutch, and out of Dutch into English</title>
                 <author>Serlio, Sebastiano</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Peake, Robert 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>3, 13, 1, 2, 26, 1, 1, 73, 71, 1, 16 leaves, illustrations (woodcuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Art and architecture</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="120"/>
   <head>To the wel-willers of Architecture.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>VItruuius</hi> sayth, that such as haue built without learning or instruction (although workemen) could neuer make any famous or commendable pieces of worke: no more can others, being no workemen, such as haue followed the letter or writing onely, and made no proofe: of which, some haue presumed to father their doings vpon <hi>Vitru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius:</hi> yet in diuers places of their writings, which are found, they could not close vp their rules orderly, but haue left ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things doubtfull, and (more) haue esteemed that to be good and commendable, which in worke is not to bee endured. The cause of this errour, is, that the last Booke of the sayd <hi>Vitruuius,</hi> wherein the Figures are, was lost: whereby men might haue knowne and sound out his meanings: so that hereby it appeareth, that some Antiquities haue beene very bare in their workes, and especially, in their Orders of Dorica, because <hi>Vitruuius</hi> nameth no Dorica Bases: but in stead thereof, speaketh of an Attica. Now it may be, regarding that he there speaketh not of any Order of Attica, therefore they durst not make any Dorica Bases or Columnes: on the contrary, others possibly contemning the darknesse of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, (or for want of knowledge) haue so far exceeded their Author in many things, that they haue not onely forsaken and left the examples and reasons of good Antiquities, but also (more then that) haue made their workes vnseemely, and ridiculous to mens eyes, as may be seene in diuers antient works: whereby, gentle Reader, many workmen, well seene in both, haue beene cumbred therein, and especially in this our time. <hi>Bramant</hi> of <hi>Castle Durant, Balthazar</hi> of <hi>Scienne,</hi> and many others, for that (not onely by meanes of <hi>Iulius</hi> the <hi>2.</hi> Pope, but) also by others good Architecture was bettered in their times: who, after long disputation and searching of many, aswell Authors and Commentaries, together with the examples of good Antiquities, haue with authority (to make an end of all doubts) not only added this Spira Attica, of the Dorica, but also as many orders as now are vsed, beginning at the Thuscan, as the grossest and slenderest of all the rest, and haue reduced the same into a certaine and common forme, together with their ornaments and measures: which vnles <hi>Sebastian Serlius,</hi> a workeman and scholer of the sayd <hi>Balthazar,</hi> hath written, and set out in figures; so that, leauing the obscurities of <hi>Vitruuius,</hi> we may make an incorrigible worke. And for that all those that loue workemanship, vnderstand not the Italians, therefore (in my opinion) I haue translated the most certayne and best rules out of Italian into Dutch, and out of Dutch into English; onely the names of all Procels, Bases, Capitals, Cornices, &amp;c. which are not named in Dutch nor English, for that <hi>Bastian,</hi> by <hi>Vitruuius</hi> termes, vseth the common and moderne Italian words, which by some should be as hardly vnderstood as the Latine. But I would commend him, that seeing we take vpon vs to follow <hi>Vitruuius</hi> writings, that we giue him the name of <hi>Vitruuius,</hi> that the learned might bee vnderstood of the workeman, and the workeman also vnderstood of the learned. And for that the worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man might the better read it, I haue printed it in our ordinary Dutch letter. And although this fourth Booke of seuen was first set out, because it is the best, yet the other also are no lesse fit and conuenient to further Architecture or Art of Building, as in the ensuing Epistle you shall see.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>