<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>DEDICATED
To the Honourable, well approued, and accomplisht Souldier,
Sir ANDREVV GRAY Knight, Colonell of the Forces
of Great Britaine, in this Noble Bohemian
Preparation.</title>
           <author>Taylor, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117734_Bo1_57_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13415</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23725</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117734</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>DEDICATED
To the Honourable, well approued, and accomplisht Souldier,
Sir ANDREVV GRAY Knight, Colonell of the Forces
of Great Britaine, in this Noble Bohemian
Preparation.</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>All the vvorkes of Iohn Taylor the water-poet : Beeing sixty and three in number. Collected into one volume by the author: vvith sundry new additions, corrected, reuised, and newly imprinted, 1630</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Boler (Bowler), James 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Elizabeth.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 148, 2, 93, 92-200, 225-343, 1, 14, 13-146 pages, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <head>DEDICATED
To the Honourable, well approued, and accomplisht Souldier,
Sir ANDREVV GRAY Knight, Colonell of the Forces
of Great Britaine, in this Noble Bohemian
Preparation.</head>
   <head type="sub">SIR ANDREVV GRAI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>.
Anagramma,
I GARDE IN WARRES.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Honourable Knight:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>THere are two especiall Causes that haue moued me most boldly to thrust
these rude lines into the world: The first is my heartie affection to the
generality of the cause you vndertake, (which I beleeue God and his best
seruants doe affect:) and the other is my loue and seruice which I owe to
your worthy Selfe in particular, for many vnde serued friendships which I
haue receiued from you, and many of your noble friends for your sake.
Ingratitude is a Deuill, so farre worse them all the deuils, that if I should
craue harbour of me, in the likenesse of an Angell of light, yet it would
neuer by perswaded to entertaine it. My thankfull acknowledgement of
your goodnesse towards me is my prayers and best wishes, which shall euer
be a poore requitall towards you, not forgetting my thankes in the behalfe of all the worthy Ladies and
others of that Angelicall sex that are maried and resident in <hi>London,</hi> whose chast honours you(as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
a true Knight) defended, when an audacious <hi>Frenchman</hi> most slaunderously did (without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion)
sweare there was not one honest Women dwelling within the bounds of this populous Citie, but that
they had all generally abused the bed of Mariage: then did your noble selfe inforce the pestiferous pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant
to swallow his odious calumny, and in humilitie to comfesse there were fifty thousand or a greater
number that neuer had wronged their Husbands in that vnlawfull act. I haue made bold to speake of
this matter here, because the abuse was so generall, and your quarrell so Honourable, which I thinke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
to be buried in silence or forgetfulnesse: howsoeuer, I craue your pardon and worthy acceptance, whilst
I most obsequiously remaine,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Euer to be commanded by you,
IOHN TAYLOR,</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>