<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           <author>S., M.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117720_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12698</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23017.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117720</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 <author>S., M.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The poore orphans court, or Orphans cry. By M.S. Being a wel-wisher for a speedy helpe of their misery, and an eye-witnesse of their present calamitie</title>
                 <author>Sparke, Michael</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Anne.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sparke, Michael 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16 pages, illustrations (metal cut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   
   <pb facs="2"/>
   
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that shal undertake at all times to speake truth in this age (freely from his heart) shall be accounted a med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling fellow, not worthy to live in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny society, but to be sequestred from men. We all know some be in feriour, and those men ought not to be so little respected, as not to be called men, because they have no authority: For there is as well the common Sailer as the Pilot, and hee sees the storme before it comes, and gives notice to the Pilot how to steare his course for their best safegard. So I living this many yeeres, and observing this wel-governed Citty, have seene as in most things something which I thought amisse, and might be rectified, which is the great neglect of the poore of this Cittie. I meddle no further, for by my fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent going in all parts earely and late, I have these many yeeres observed the misery of the poore but most of all of children, young boyes and girles, which for many yeeres I beheld, hoping ever God would open some honest Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens heart that died rich, that they would doe something to beginne to raise a stocke. And seeing S. <hi>Pauls</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, though not sufffciently, as also Morefields, Aldersgate, Allgate, Newgate, and other good deeds done and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
<pb facs="3"/>
      yet this neglecte<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, I caused a Booke to be printed some <hi>16.</hi> yeeres agoe, called, Grievons groanes for the Poore. But I being then in the country the booke (whether at the Booke sellers or at the Printers I know not) lost the life, and reason how the poore should be provided for, by which meanes it lost all respect, and I my good intention; not many yeeres after this, there was a collection for imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the poore, but which way that stocke went I have nothing to doe to examine; Not many yeeres after that, that worthy Sir <hi>T. M.</hi> his project came forth, which no doubt had it beene seconded, it had taken good effect, for I am perswaded hee aimed at the generall good of all, but this vanished as a shadow; since which I have observed and finde the last remedy is for the children used in the weekely Bills, <hi>Dead</hi> in the <hi>Street,</hi> or <hi>starved.</hi> And this is all the remedy I finde for these poore silly witlesse creatures. Those that be able to helpe themselves, I speake not for, but for these poore <hi>Orphans,</hi> whose Court is kept in a <hi>Cage,</hi> or under a <hi>Stall,</hi> or in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> amongst the formes, the more is the pittie. Wee have an Orphans Court well guided and governed (God be thanked for it) long may it continue, and what trudging and going is there if the rich die and leave wealth to their children, but the poore die and no <hi>Orphans Court</hi> can be found. <hi>Outinam,</hi> thereit is, and not else to be found or seene. But these few lines it may be will be laughed at, I care not though they be; I give my selfe content, and wish but that may be done here, as is at this present in <hi>Dorchester, Norwich,</hi> not one seene to begge: let us learne of them or of the Dutch, as in the Vniversity of LEYDEN: where <hi>800.</hi> Orphans are daily fed and set at worke, and well provided
<pb facs="3"/>
      for, how doe the Dutch or French parishioners in <hi>LONDON;</hi> can they doe so, and not wee? It is nothing but our hard hearts; for mee thinkes I heare some say, I have but <hi>500.</hi> pounds in my estate, I would give one to it, nay I am perswaded there be <hi>500.</hi> of this minde in this Citie, but either cowardize, or feare of being accounted a vaine-glorious person makes them desist, nay, mee thinkes I heare some <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> say, We will keepe all our poore and well some may, if all things were looked into; but these Orphans with good looking to would keepe themselves, witnesse the willingnesse of some, who you shall have of the bigger sort in Fleet-steet in the evenings, with linkes ready to earne a penny to light men, nay, in Smithfield standing by day to sweepe cleane the waies, how ready are many of them? but the weakest goe to the wall, as wee see by woefull experience, many whose <hi>Toes</hi> and <hi>Legges</hi> are ready to rot off, and worser mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series, which make many a man blush to see that they are no better provided for. It may be I am de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, would I were. I am verily perswaded, that many spend more in the Taverne idlely than they give the poore willingly. Will not many a Lady spend ordinarily day by day five shillings to see an idle play, or five pounds at a Rere Banquet rather tha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> give five shillings, I beleeve five tokens, to help these poore miserable children. If they heare of a new Play, on goes all the best clothes, the Coach-horses must be fetched, and that they may hurry from the poore, the Coach-man shall have his charge, to drive away when hee commeth amongst them; and whats the word? Away with these <hi>Stinking-beggers,</hi> but
<pb facs="4"/>
      when they come home, they will call to the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to see the dogge have his dinner, but the poore shall goe supperlesse to bedd under a stall, or in a Porch, <hi>dying</hi> with <hi>misery,</hi> or <hi>starving</hi> with <hi>cold,</hi> and <hi>hunger.</hi> These are reasons able to draw a man into a serious consideration for a speedie remedy, and I leave them to those in authority, and rest ever wishing, but not obtaining my desire, that there were a Court for the poore Orphans as well as the rich.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>A wel-wisher of the poore. <hi>M. S.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>