<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PITHIE DIS∣COVRSE OF OVR COMMVNION WITH CHRIST.</title>
           <author>Hill, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117083_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03356</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13474</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117083</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PITHIE DIS∣COVRSE OF OVR COMMVNION WITH CHRIST.</title>
                 <author>Hill, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pathvvay to prayer and pietie : Containing, 1 An exposition of the Lords Prayer, with an apologie for publicke, and priuate set prayer. 2 A preparation to the Lords Supper, with Ma. Zanchius confession, concerning that sacrament. 3 A direction to a Christian life, bot in our generall and particular callings. 4 An instruction to die well, and a consolation against all crosses. With diuers prayers, and thankesgiuings fit for this treatise. By Robert Hill, Doctor in Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Hill, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <distributor>Barrett, William</distributor>
                            <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40, 141, 17, 110, 8, 111-344 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="97"/>
   <head>A PITHIE DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COVRSE OF OVR COMMVNION WITH CHRIST.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough the <hi>word</hi> of life, in it self causeth <hi>peace,</hi> yet by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of <hi>Satan</hi> it occasioneth <hi>warre:</hi> and though the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of life shew our <hi>commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> with Christ, yet by the corruption of <hi>man</hi> it is made an instrument of <hi>combustion.</hi> The <hi>Vbiquiterian Lutheran</hi> is zealous on the one side for his <hi>consubstantiation,</hi> and with the bread and wine he will chap vp his <hi>sauiour:</hi> The <hi>Artolatrian Romanist</hi> is as zealous on the other, for his <hi>transubstantiation,</hi> and after the repetition of fiue Latine words will deuoure his <hi>creator.</hi> And if varieties of opinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Lords Supper, should but heere be repeated; as a <hi>great ship</hi> would not hold the the Reliquian pieces which the Papists haue of <hi>Christs crosse:</hi> so a <hi>large volume</hi> would but hold the opinions which are about <hi>Christs Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</hi> Is it the falt of this <hi>blessed banquet</hi>
      <pb facs="97"/> that so many are distracted about feeding vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it? no it is not.</p>
   <p>It is reported that one in a lightsome house being <hi>stricken blinde,</hi> complained exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the darknesse of the chamber, where as the salt was in the want of his sight. When the <hi>eye</hi> is diuine, it must not complaine of the <hi>sunne</hi> if it see not: when <hi>stomake</hi> is corrupt, it must not complaine of the <hi>meate</hi> if it digest not: and when the <hi>fantasticall</hi> wit of man is wedded to <hi>reason,</hi> no meruaile if it perceiue not the <hi>things</hi> of God. The <hi>preaching</hi> of Christs crosse was a <hi>scandale</hi> to the <hi>Iewes:</hi> their owne corrupt heart caused it to bee offensiue: The <hi>administoation</hi> of Christs <hi>Sacrament</hi> is a stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling block to the <hi>curious:</hi> their owne carnall conceit makes them to fall. If wee could in our iudgements subscribe vnto the <hi>written word</hi> of God, and of <hi>spirituall</hi> things conceit after a <hi>spirituall</hi> manner, our <hi>Capernaiticall</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries would not looke heere for a <hi>breaden God,</hi> and our <hi>carnal</hi> gospellers would look for more heere than common bread. It is, euen to the <hi>wicked</hi> the <hi>bread</hi> of the Lord, and to the <hi>godly,</hi> that <hi>bread</hi> which is the Lord.</p>
   <p>By comming to the <hi>Lordes table,</hi> (if wee come as wee should) wee reape much good: for heere we may behold the <hi>loue</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> to vs, who, as a louing friend, by this <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancer,</hi> desires euer to liue in our mindes, and
<pb facs="98"/> memories: and the <hi>prouidence</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> for his beloued friends, that his <hi>benefits</hi> bestowed might truly profit, &amp; being kept in memorie, might enioy their end, <hi>euer to shew forth his death till he come.</hi> Yea by thus comming we <hi>testifie</hi> our <hi>spirituall</hi> nourishment by his body and blood: we <hi>seale</hi> to our selues the <hi>pardon</hi> of our sinnes: Christ <hi>couenants</hi> with vs to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue</hi> vs gratiously: we <hi>condition</hi> with him to <hi>obey</hi> him principally, and if we desire either to testifie our desire of the <hi>first</hi> resurrection, out of the <hi>graue</hi> of sinne, or our hope of the <hi>second,</hi> out of the <hi>graue</hi> of death: wee shall do both these, so often as we come to the <hi>holy commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</hi> In a word, it is a <hi>testimonie</hi> of our <hi>profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,</hi> and <hi>consent</hi> to Gods Religion: a <hi>token</hi> of our <hi>separation</hi> from all the tents of Satan: an <hi>obligation</hi> of our constancie in the <hi>profession</hi> of the Gospel: a <hi>sinew</hi> and <hi>conseruation</hi> of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique meetings: a <hi>caueat</hi> to take heede of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapse</hi> into sinne: a <hi>comforter</hi> in the middest of any Temptation: and a <hi>seale</hi> of that <hi>communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> which is betwixt <hi>Christ</hi> and <hi>Christians.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The cup of blessing which wee blesse, is it not the Communion of the bloud of Christ? and the bread which we breake;</hi>
      <note place="margin">i. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.6.</note>
      <hi>is it not the Communion of the body of Christ?</hi> as the <hi>preaching</hi> of the Gospell is Gods <hi>powerfull</hi> instrument to <hi>signe</hi> our saluation: so the <hi>sacrament</hi> of the Lords Supper is an <hi>effectuall</hi> instrument to <hi>seale</hi> this
<pb facs="98"/> coniunction. Now that wee may more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently <hi>communicate</hi> with <hi>Christians,</hi> I am bolde to entreate of our <hi>communion</hi> with <hi>Christ.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In the first <hi>Adams</hi> innocencie, there was an <hi>act</hi> of <hi>assotiation</hi> betwixt God and man: but with <hi>condition</hi> of mans loyaltie to God. The <hi>condition</hi> is <hi>broken,</hi> man is <hi>exiled</hi> from Gods <hi>presence,</hi> and becomes an <hi>enemie</hi> both to God and man. Gods <hi>iustice</hi> can not admit sinfull man into <hi>fauor:</hi> mans <hi>infidelitie</hi> hinders him from suing to God for <hi>fauor. Christ</hi> our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, the<note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>diuine</hi> Sonne of God, and <hi>humane</hi> Son of man, satisfieth Gods <hi>Iustice,</hi> acquaints man with Gods <hi>mercie:</hi> and in the fulnesse of time, <hi>this seede of the woman breakes the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents head.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But vnlesse man haue communion with <hi>Christ,</hi> his al sufficient satisfaction will do him no good. What then may this <hi>communion</hi> be? it is a <hi>spirituall societie of mutuall loue betwixt Christ and his Church.</hi> A <hi>societie,</hi> like vnto that of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Heuah,</hi> when they twaine became <hi>one</hi> flesh: <hi>spirituall,</hi> like vnto that of the <hi>soule</hi> and the <hi>bodie,</hi> where they by the <hi>spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites,</hi> become <hi>one</hi> man: of mutuall loue, like a paire of Turtle Doues, who neuer know any other but one mate: of <hi>Christ and his Church,</hi> like that of the <hi>head</hi> and the <hi>members,</hi> when they, by certaine <hi>iunctures,</hi> become <hi>one</hi> body.</p>
   <pb facs="99"/>
   <p>
      <hi>Christ</hi> communicated with our nature in his <hi>incarnation,</hi> when hee tooke vnto him the <hi>seede</hi> of <hi>Abraham:</hi> hence comes that <hi>vnion</hi> which we call <hi>Hypostaticall:</hi> and he is become <hi>Flesh of our Flesh.</hi> We communicate with the person of <hi>Christ,</hi> when we are <hi>incorporated</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: Hence comes that <hi>vnion,</hi> which wee call <hi>mysticall,</hi> &amp; wee now become <hi>Flesh of his Flesh.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If we consider the <hi>things</hi> vnited together, this vnion is <hi>substantiall</hi> and <hi>essentiall:</hi> if the <hi>bond</hi> by which they are vnited, it is <hi>spirituall</hi> and <hi>secret.</hi> And as we haue feeling of Christ dwelling on our hearts, so the more shall wee haue feeling of this blessed societie: by which we haue <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> an <hi>vnion,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>fellowship,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>participation</hi> with whole Christ and his merits, and <hi>meet altogether in the vnitie of faith and knowledge of the sonne of God, vnto a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man, and vnto the measure of the age of the fulnesse of Christ.</hi> Ephes. 4.13.5.30. But as in our <hi>separation</hi> from God, by the spirit of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, our <hi>mindes, heart,</hi> and <hi>wils</hi> were first se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered and then followed the <hi>whole</hi> man: so the first thing in this <hi>coniunction</hi> which must be ioyned with God by his spirit, is the <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding</hi> by <hi>knowledge,</hi> the <hi>heart</hi> by affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, the <hi>will</hi> by <hi>obedience,</hi> after which will follow all the <hi>new</hi> man.</p>
   <p>By the <hi>humanitie</hi> of Christ we are conioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="99"/> to <hi>him:</hi> and by his <hi>Spirit</hi> he is ioyned to <hi>vs.</hi> Not, either by an <hi>actuall</hi> falling of Christs flesh into <hi>ours,</hi> or a <hi>naturall</hi> contiguitie or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion of our <hi>persons,</hi> or <hi>essentiall</hi> comixtion of his body with <hi>ours:</hi> but by a copulation and connexion altogether <hi>spirituall,</hi> felt by <hi>grace</hi> in this life, and seene by <hi>glorie</hi> in the life to come, when Christ and his Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Gods iudgement seate, shall appeare as <hi>one Christ.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But Christ is in <hi>heauen,</hi> and we vpon <hi>earth.</hi> Send thy <hi>faith</hi> into <hi>heauen,</hi> and <hi>hee</hi> in heauen is ioyned to thee heere vpon <hi>earth.</hi> Thy <hi>sight</hi> in a moment can visiblie touch the <hi>starres</hi> of heauen, much more may thy faith touch that <hi>morning starre,</hi> and <hi>sunne of righteousnesse</hi> which is in heauen. Say that the <hi>wife</hi> bee in <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>husband</hi> in <hi>India:</hi> the <hi>head</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the <hi>feete</hi> below: the <hi>branches</hi> on the top the <hi>roote</hi> in the ground: the <hi>spring</hi> in one place, the <hi>riuers</hi> in an other: the <hi>foundation</hi> on the earth the <hi>building</hi> in the ayre, is there not notwithstanding an <hi>vnion</hi> betwixt them? Surely there is. <hi>Christ</hi> is our <hi>husband,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> is his <hi>spouse: Christ</hi> is our <hi>head,</hi> ech <hi>Christian</hi> is a <hi>member: Christ</hi> is the <hi>roote,</hi> the righteous are <hi>branches: Christ</hi> is the <hi>fountaine,</hi> the <hi>Religious</hi> are <hi>riuers: Christ</hi> is the <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, belieuers</hi> are Gods <hi>building.</hi> Be hee neuer so <hi>high</hi> euen in the highest <hi>heauens,</hi>
      <pb facs="100"/> we <hi>vpon earth</hi> are so ioyned vnto him, that by <hi>vertue</hi> of this vnion, our <hi>soules</hi> do receiue the life of <hi>grace</hi> in this world, and our <hi>bodies</hi> shall receiue the life of <hi>glorie</hi> in the world to come. Heere, this coniunction appeares in the <hi>vnitie of spirit:</hi> for in it there is neither a <hi>commixtion</hi> of <hi>persons</hi> nor an vnion of <hi>substances,</hi> but a <hi>confederation</hi> of our <hi>affections,</hi> and <hi>concatenati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of our <hi>wils:</hi> there it shall appeare in the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sociation</hi> of our <hi>persons.</hi> For wee shall <hi>enioy</hi> there, a most <hi>holy,</hi> and <hi>comfortable</hi> conuersati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Christ, <hi>see</hi> him as he is, <hi>conferre</hi> with him face to face, and as in this sacrament, (as by a <hi>marriage ring</hi>) wee are <hi>espoused</hi> to him heere: so there wee shall be solemnly <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried</hi> to him for euer.</p>
   <p>And all this comes vnto vs, because the <hi>word</hi> was made <hi>flesh:</hi> not because that <hi>Flesh</hi> hath any such <hi>vertue</hi> in it selfe <hi>(it is the spirit that quickneth the flesh profiteth nothing)</hi> but in that it is caro verbi, <hi>flesh vnited to the word,</hi> to that <hi>word,</hi> which is the <hi>fountaine</hi> of life <hi>quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> all things, and causing the <hi>death</hi> of that flesh to obtaine for vs eternall life. <hi>The flesh is not quickning in it selfe, but in the word, Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>statically vnited vnto it,</hi> saith <hi>Cyrill.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This <hi>word</hi> by <hi>personall</hi> vnion, <hi>quickneth</hi> Christs humanitie, and giueth it, for our sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, <hi>merite</hi> and <hi>efficacie:</hi> and by <hi>mysticall</hi> vnion <hi>quickneth</hi> Christian consciences, and
<pb facs="100"/> ioyneth them in loue and life vnto God: so that now there is a mutuall <hi>giuing</hi> and <hi>recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing</hi> betwixt <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Church.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>From <hi>Christ</hi> wee <hi>receiue,</hi> first him <hi>selfe,</hi> which the <hi>Father,</hi> and their <hi>Spirit,</hi> to become <hi>our</hi> portion. Secondly <hi>Adoption,</hi> to be <hi>actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally</hi> made the children of God. Thirdly a <hi>title</hi> and <hi>right</hi> to <hi>Christs righteousnesse</hi> in his suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, and with all to his <hi>fulfilling</hi> of the whole law. Lastly, a <hi>right</hi> to the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, which now is made the <hi>inheritance of the Saints.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And what doth he now receiue from vs? surely <hi>drosse</hi> for <hi>gold, euil</hi> for <hi>good, shame</hi> for <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, sorrow</hi> for <hi>solace,</hi> and a <hi>curse</hi> for this <hi>bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing.</hi> For he receiues ftom vs, first, our <hi>sinnes,</hi> with the <hi>punishment</hi> thereof made his by <hi>impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> and <hi>suertie-ship.</hi> Secondly our afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which hee accounts his <hi>owne,</hi> so long as we suffer for righteousnesse sake. And this is our communion which we haue with Christ.</p>
   <p>But because we are all <hi>members</hi> of one <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,</hi> and are all <hi>baptized</hi> into one <hi>Spirit,</hi> and after do <hi>eate</hi> of one <hi>bread,</hi> there is also a <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> with all Christians, <hi>one</hi> with an <hi>other?</hi> Art thou a <hi>liuing</hi> saint vpon earth? thou art in regard of <hi>minde</hi> of one <hi>iudgement</hi> in the grounds of pietie, <hi>affection</hi> of one <hi>heart</hi> alike affected to <hi>God, Christ Iesus,</hi> and euery good <hi>Christian,</hi> though thou wast neuer acquainted
<pb facs="101"/> with them. And in regard of the <hi>gifts</hi> of the <hi>spirit,</hi> like a good candle thou wilt <hi>spend</hi> them al to the good of others; &amp; be ready to <hi>serue</hi> thy brother in loue; and both by <hi>example, admonition, exhortation, consolation</hi> &amp; <hi>prayer,</hi> to conuey all graces in thee to an other; yea not to be wanting to him in <hi>communicating</hi> thy <hi>goods.</hi> And for our <hi>communion</hi> with the <hi>dead</hi> they in <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> do pray <hi>generally</hi> for al vs, and we on <hi>earth</hi> do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire our <hi>dissolution</hi> to be with them.</p>
   <p>But, that we may enioy this <hi>blessed</hi> societie, we must <hi>walke</hi> in the light. For, <hi>if we say that we haue fellowship with him &amp; yet walke in darknesse, we lie: but if we walke in the light as hee is in the light, then haue wee fellowship one with an other</hi> 1. Ioh. 1.7. (that is God with vs, &amp; we with God and godly people) <hi>and the blood of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ his Sonne purgeth vs from all sinne.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thus then <hi>Christ</hi> in heauen, by his <hi>spirit,</hi> is so vnited to vs, &amp; <hi>we</hi> on earth, by our <hi>faith</hi> are so vnited to him, that without him we can do <hi>nothing,</hi> &amp; with him we are able to do <hi>al</hi> things: <hi>Of his fulnesse we receiue grace for grace.</hi> And as by the <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>sunne</hi> in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond heauen, all things are made <hi>fruitfull</hi> heere vpon earth: so by the <hi>power</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> in the third heauen, all men become <hi>sanctified</hi> in the Church; yet not by the alone <hi>inward</hi> operation of his <hi>spirit,</hi> without the <hi>outward</hi> vse of the <hi>word</hi> and <hi>sacraments.</hi> By the word <hi>alone,</hi> when the <hi>sacraments</hi> are not admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred: and both by word and <hi>sacraments</hi> when they are ioined together. Is the <hi>word</hi> preached? in it Christ <hi>speaketh</hi> by his spitit to vs. Are the <hi>sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi>
      <pb facs="101"/> administred? by <hi>baptisme</hi> we are receiued in to the <hi>communion</hi> of Gods couenant, and by the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charist,</hi> wee are more confirmed in the same. By the <hi>word</hi> God enters by <hi>one gate</hi> into vs, namely by the <hi>eare:</hi> by the <hi>Eucharist</hi> he knocks at <hi>al</hi> the <hi>gates</hi> of our <hi>soule,</hi> and seekes entrance by euery <hi>sense.</hi> Are they both conioyned? our vnion becomes more <hi>effectuall</hi> vnto vs. By the word <hi>without</hi> the sacraments, Christ may come vnto vs: by the sacraments <hi>without</hi> the word, he will not come vnto vs. <hi>Adde the word vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the element and it becomes a sacrament.</hi> This I write against such as thinke, that <hi>Christ</hi> doth after a <hi>farre</hi> better sort communicate himselfe to vs in the <hi>sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> than hee doth in the <hi>word,</hi> whereas the <hi>sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> hath all their efficacie from the <hi>word,</hi> euen the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>institution,</hi> deliuered by <hi>Christ,</hi> &amp; vnderstood of <hi>Christians.</hi> Yet note that in the <hi>sacraments</hi> Christ communicates himselfe more <hi>particularly</hi> to vs then in the <hi>word.</hi> The end of both is to ioyne <hi>vs</hi> to <hi>him</hi> &amp; <hi>himself</hi> to vs: that we being thus <hi>one</hi> with him, might <hi>grow</hi> vp together with him, till that he at the last be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>all</hi> in all of vs; hee (by this <hi>matrimoniall</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction) to <hi>loue</hi> vs as his <hi>spouse,</hi> we to <hi>reuerence</hi> him as our <hi>husband</hi> and both he and we together to bee <hi>honored</hi> of God the Father in the resurrection of the iust with complete glory.</p>
   <p>Consider what I say, and the Lord giue thee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding in all things. <hi>Iune</hi> 16. 1613.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in the Lord.</hi> ROBERT HILL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>