<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the right noble Lord, the Lord Edward Earle of Bedford, grace and peace from the Lord.</title>
           <author>S., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117490_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B15838</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22768</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117490</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the right noble Lord, the Lord Edward Earle of Bedford, grace and peace from the Lord.</title>
                 <author>S., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tvvo sermons preached by Master Henry Smith: with a prayer for the morning thereunto adioyned. And published by a more perfect copy then heeretofore</title>
                 <author>Smith, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hall, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Leake, William 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>136 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="21"/>
   <pb facs="21"/>
   <head>¶ To the right noble Lord, the Lord Edward Earle of Bedford, <hi>grace and peace from the Lord.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the little Bee gathereth not hony for her selfe alone, but for others; so right Honourable, I am bold to present your good Lordship with my Choice, my Care, and the Issue. The first, your hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable selfe, and in this, as you are the <note place="margin">The Choice.</note> hope of the reuiuing of your vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted noble Grand father and Father: so my hearty well wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing (together with the prayers of all the godly) is, that what the Almighty graced thē with, in you may be redoubled. The second is, the Fountaine whence the first had his streame, and <note place="margin">The Care.</note> being in me (as a member of the Church) what I wish to the same assured assembly of Gods people, I leaue to the alone de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminer of all Controuersies whatsoeuer. The last I commēd to the onely direction of the Lord. Now as the faithfull dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poser <note place="margin">The Issue.</note> of Gods truth, was a man linked vnto mee in assured friendship whilst he liued: so I hauing with care long fithence collected these his Sermons together, doe now with singlenesse of heart present the same to your Lordship, and heerewith am prest to performe all such duties to your honour, as God shall enable me vnto, both in prayer for your health, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of zeal to the maintenance of his poore flocke, which I hope is the onely aime and end of all your honourable purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses. Thus with all other graces, I most heartily desire that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of light to enrich you in this life, and after this to blesse you with immortality in that place of rest for euer.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, W. S.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>