<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To Mr. George Abbat, called by some, Archbishoppe of Canturbury.</title>
           <author>Champney, A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117540_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18391</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4959</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117540</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To Mr. George Abbat, called by some, Archbishoppe of Canturbury.</title>
                 <author>Champney, A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Mr. Pilkinton his Parallela disparalled : And the Catholicke Roman faith maintained against Protestantisme. By Ant. Champney Sorbonist, and author of the Manuall of Controuersies, impugned by the said Mr. Pilkinton</title>
                 <author>Champney, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Boscard, Charles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Heigham, John (Roger)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>220, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <epigraph>
      <q>Wee wish that those would departe from their owne frowardnes, who against Christ, carry the ensigne of Christ, and against the Gospel, bragge of the Gospel which they vnderstande not.</q>
      <bibl>Aug. ep. 61. ad Dulcit. Cited by Mr. Pilkinton against himselfe.</bibl>
   </epigraph>
   <head>To Mr. George Abbat, called by some, Archbishoppe of Canturbury.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is now three whole yeeres I appealed to your iudgment in a matter of difference and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie betwixte a minister of your owne makinge, or allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wance att least, Mr. Francis Mason, and my selfe; concerninge the vocation and consecration aswell of your owne person,
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>
as of all the rest of the protestant Bishops and ministers in England. And thoughe hitherto I haue receiued no notice of anie Sentences geuen by you in this Controuersie (because for seeinge as I suppose, that you cannot passe your Sentēce thereupon, without preiudice either of your owne interest, or reputation, you willinglie dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble the matter) yett am I moued to demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de your iudgment in another difference, betwixt another minister of yours, Mr. Richarde Pilkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and my selfe. For where as I sett forth fiue yeeres a goe a briefe Manuall of Controuersies, contayninge onlie seauen sheetes of Paper, proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge all the cheefest heades of controuersie by Scriptures only; he, this last yeare, to crosse the same, hath printed a fowle great booke of fifty sheetes, callinge it, <hi>Parallela.</hi> Which booke he dedicateth to you. In whose Epistle Dedicatorie, thoughe there be as manie falsities and imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencies, as there are in so manies lines of the rest of his booke; yet shall they passe without other touch in particular, then this generall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension (as either refutinge themselues, or not worthy refutinge of purpose) only I cannot omitte these brauinge wordes of his which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe. <hi>This popish agent (he meaneth the author of the Manual) I haue vndertaken, and stripped him of his armour, which he hath vsurped, shewinge his proofes to be as weake, as his positions are wicked, that his blinde religion may appeare vnto all to be nothinge but an heape of vntruthes</hi>
      <pb n="5" facs="3"/>
      <hi>without patronage of holy Scriptures. Which encounter I nowe offer vnto the viewe of the world, vnder the shield of your graces protection, who first encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged mee to this battell, and canne best of all men iudge (as the most experienced ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall in this sacred warfare) on which side the truth propendeth.</hi> In which wordes he doth not onlie vainlie bragge of the victorie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie achieued, but also acknowledgeth to haue receiued this taske from you, and perferringe your iudgment of his trauells before all other mens, offereth his booke vnto you, nothinge doubtinge either of your approbation or protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Therefore haue I made free choice of you for vmpiere betwixt him and me, to iudge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he hath indeede stryped me of myne Armour, as he braggeth, &amp; whether his proofes or myne be stronger, and more pertinent to the purpose for which they are produced. I say of the proofes onlie, for of the positions themselues, I houlde you not a fitt or competent iudge. And were it not, that I am verie confident in the clearenes of my cause, and am also persuaded that you will not preiudice your reputation with the world so farre, as to giue your iudgment against a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest truth, I would not be so vnaduised as to put my cause into so vnequall and partiall a iudge his handes, as all men knowe you to be, betweene me and myne aduersarie. Neuertheles the premis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses beinge considered I will not refuse your iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement in this cause: Only I will request of you
<pb n="6" facs="4"/>
to peruse that which hath been sayd on either parte, before you geue your iudgment of the cause it selfe; And this I thinke I may iustlie demaunde of you, without incurringe anie spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall obligation of particular grace or fauour: which beinge performed, I freelie permitt you to passe your opinion of the difference, as you shall thinke most conformable to equitie, and important for your owne reputation. Whereof, I maruell not a litle, you had so smal reguarde, as to lett goe foorth into the viewe of the worlde, with so much testimonie of your allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wance and approbation, such a peece of stuffe as Mr. Pilkinton hath sett to sale in this booke. Which (to speake without preiudice of others that may seeme to contēd with him for the price of ignorance, impertinencie and peruersitie) I thinke is one of the seeliest and shallowest thinges that hath seen sunne in this age▪ And therefore a iudicious friende (hauinge looked a litle into it) tould me I was not to expect anie honour by vndertakinge such an aduersarie. Wherefore I aduise you for your owne credit sake, to be more warie hereafter, then to lett such birdes flye abroade with your name in their forehead. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>r the blemishe and staine which they bringe with them, will sticke as faste in your face, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>th in that of the author, yea by so much the faster, by howe much more eminent your name and authoritie is, or ought to be aboue his. And so wishinge you from my verie hearte more loue and affection to the
<pb n="7" facs="4"/>
Catholike truth and veritie, then hitherto you haue sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>wed, without which your parte will infalliblie be with the Father of all falshoode: For, <hi>qui non credit iam iudicatus est,</hi> he<note place="margin">Ioan. 3. 18</note> that beleeueth not is alreadie iudged; I leaue you to his disposition whose prouidence is neuer deceiued; thoughe his will whereby he wisheth vs well, be not allwayes fulfilled, we our selues only beinge in faulte thereof.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>Doway <date>this last of Iune 1619.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your true friende, thoughe enemie to your errours, A. CHAMPNEY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>