<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PLOT OR DISSEINE OF THE WHOLE HISTORIE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117097_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11931</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22244</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117097</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PLOT OR DISSEINE OF THE WHOLE HISTORIE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A general inuentorie of the history of France : from the beginning of that monarchie, vnto the treatie of Veruins, in the year 1598. Written by Ihon de Serres. And continued vnto these times, out off the best authors which haue written of that subiect. Translated out of French into English, by Edward Grimeston Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Serres, Jean de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ponsonby, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ponsonby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 209, 5, 1052, 26 pages, portraits (woodcuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary_of_work">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>A PLOT OR DISSEINE OF THE WHOLE HISTORIE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y meaning is to represent in this discourse, what is most re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable in the Historie of <hi>France,</hi> and (with a simple, faithfull, and liuely breuitie) to report all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t hath succeeded in the <hi>French</hi> Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, worth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e of memorie, to make our <hi>Frenchmen</hi> see a modell of this great building, reducing it to the first foundation, according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of the subiect, and the order of times, the certaine light of truth; and by the changes of the greatest and most famous fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>reine States, to the end, that this our <hi>Inuentorie</hi> may serue the learned for a memoriall, and learners for a direction. The enterprise is not small, although the worke be little, but as it must bee valued by the fruit, so the proofe will appeare to such as shall vouchsafe to reade what my desire was able to performe. And for a ground of this goodly and excelent <hi>Historie,</hi> so worthy of knowledge, we must set downe in generall termes what shalbe handled in particular throughout the whole discourse, and lay before your eyes (as in a table by the most cleere and soundest proofes that may be drawne from likelyhoods of so obscure antiquitie) the beginning and continnuance, with the greatest apparance of truth, the increase with the diuers euents and successe of this s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ate such as now it is.</p>
   <p>It were to seeke truth in vanitie, following the common error, to search for the originall of the <hi>FRENCH,</hi> in the ruines and ashes of <hi>Troy</hi> or in the fennes of <hi>Meotides,</hi> for in the most auncient Histories of the <hi>Trojans,</hi> there is no mention of <hi>FRANCVS</hi> or <hi>FRANCI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON,</hi> sonnes of <hi>Hector,</hi> who had but one sonne named <hi>Astianax</hi> slayne at three yeares of age in the sacke of <hi>Troy.</hi> There is also no likelyhood to find the stemme of our <hi>FRENCH</hi> nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the sennes of <hi>Meotides,</hi> where they were first called <hi>SICAMBRES,</hi> hauing built a Citty by imagination named <hi>SICAMBRA</hi>: And that they issued from thence in great troups. There is no more proofe that they are come from these marishes, then from the desarts of <hi>Affricke.</hi> It appeares the <hi>SICAMBRIANS</hi> were a different people from the <hi>FRENCH,</hi> and that the wales of <hi>SICAMBRIA</hi> are yet to build. But the newe presumption of a certaine writer is yet more admirable, who com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s frō far to aduertise the <hi>FRENCH</hi> of their originall, the which he findes beyond the Moonne, and with so great an assurance as he setts downe nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> by name the kings of the house of <hi>SICAMBRIA</hi> and of <hi>FRANCE,</hi> their r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ce, ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ners▪ deeds, aduentures, and that in so good ern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st (as reporting a thing but of yesterday, or as being a Counsellor to these supposed kings) seeming with reason to reprehend such as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ll not take his word for present payment, vnder the authoritie of certaine old Registers produced by him, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he names these kings one after one, like in presumption to the <hi>Castilians,</hi> the inuentors of the fabulous Historie of <hi>Amadis:</hi> or the deuisors of the ofspring of the <hi>Panim</hi> Gods, or of the <hi>Roman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> of the <hi>Rose,</hi> hauing forged names at their pleasure; leauing therefore all these Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinations and Fopperies, let vs search (as neere as wee may) what is most likely by the traces of
<pb facs="8"/>
Truth, vntill it may guide vs to the firme land, not plunging our selues any further in the boggs and vnknowne desarts, of an imagined Antiquitie.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>The French are come out of Germ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>nie.</hi>
      </note>What then? doubtlesse we shall no where find a more certaine originall of our <hi>FRENCH</hi> Nation then in <hi>Germany.</hi> This is most apparant; <hi>FRANCONIE</hi> beares yet the name of the old Inhabitants, and the markes of their auncient possession: The Cities of the one and the other side of the <hi>Rhine</hi> are full of their Antiquities. We can no way doubt by these markes, but they haue inhabited in those parts, and it is likely they were dispersed betwixt the Riuers of <hi>Rhine</hi> and <hi>Danubius,</hi> vnto the Ocean. Whether the had their beginning there, or came from any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part, it auailes not to dispute, seeing the search is altogether vnprofitable, for that in deed it is impossible.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Of the name of Frenchmen.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>The originall of the name</hi> is verie difficult, being wholly vnknowne to the first Antiquitie: for we reade not in any auntient Histories of the name of <hi>French-men</hi> among the nations of <hi>Germany,</hi> yet carefully obserued by the most auntient. But who sees not the change of auntient names to new. <hi>Alemaigne</hi> is now called <hi>Germanie: Heluetia, Suisse: Brittaine, England:</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out seeking vnnecessary proofes in so apparant a matter. The <hi>FRENCH</hi> therefore being an auncient people of <hi>Germany,</hi> haue changed their name with the whole country vpon diuers subiects, but when, how, by whome and wherefore, it cannot be certainely defined, but by conie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, more easie to be refuted then mainteined. It appeares only that <hi>FRANCE</hi> is a <hi>Germane</hi> word, which signifieth Free, and that their auncestors eyther hauing shakt of the yoke of the <hi>Romane</hi> seruitude, and recouered their auntient libertie, or remayning free amongst so many neighbours, subiect to that great Empire were called <hi>French-men</hi> in token of their libertie.</p>
   <p>There are learned men which write that <hi>FRANCE</hi> was the name of a Communalty of diuers people, assembled and vnited together, to preserue their libertyes, hauing taken that name as a marke of their generous resolution, and not of any certain Nation: Although <hi>Tully</hi> (a witnesse aboue all exception) notes the name of <hi>FRANCONS</hi> among the nations of <hi>Germany,</hi> which had offered obedience to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> whilest their commonweale florished, before the Empire began, which shewes that we cannot talke of so obscure Antiquitie but doubtfully, so as it is boot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse to pronounce Oracles vpon a subiect so disputable. Truely to referre the first memories of theire name to the Empire of <hi>Valentinian,</hi> and the beginning of their liberty to the defeat of the <hi>Ala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s,</hi> and to the bountie of this Emperor, hauing freed them in recompence of so worthye a seruice: that were to ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e a leape of aboue an hundred and thirtie yeares, to confound thinges and to be ignorant of the estate of our Auncestors, who at the time of this memorable defeate, did in nothing acknowledge the <hi>Romaines;</hi> But rather for a particular fruite of the victorie gotten by them in common with <hi>Valentinian,</hi> they had possession of a great part of the <hi>Gaules,</hi> not holding it of any but of their Sword, nor doing homage but to their owne Valour. It were in briefe not to haue obserued the originalls of true Histories. Seeing then the auntient habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>FRENCH</hi> was in that part of <hi>Germany</hi> which lay near<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st vnto <hi>Gaule,</hi> who can with reason deny but the are issued from thence, and that in taking <hi>Gaule</hi> they made it to change both Master and Name: This is in breise what may bee spoken with most apparancie of truth concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the originall of our <hi>FRENCH</hi> nation, if wee will not vrge more then may well bee iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>By what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and when they entred Gaule</hi>
      </note>As for their estate and gouernment there is great likelyhood that it was a great nation growne warlike by meanes of desending themselues and succoring others with their owne forces. I adde that they were led and commaunded by a king, for the most auntient Histories represent them vnder a royall authority, as I will shew els where. Doubtles they had no meanes to buyld this great Monarchy in <hi>Gaule</hi> without force and order, yet did they not erect it all at one instant, but slipt into <hi>Gaule</hi> at sundry times, eyther imployed to succor the <hi>Romaines,</hi> or they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, seeking their fortune, and good aduentures: And as they grew familiar by diuers sommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, so they got footing by little and little, vntill that hauing not only expelled the <hi>Romains,</hi> but all other tributarie Lords; they became Masters and possessors of this goodly country: so
<pb facs="8"/>
this Monarchy was buylt vpon the ruines of the Empyre, and the end of the one was the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the other. The <hi>Romane</hi> Empyre had not only seazed vpon all <hi>Gaule</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s the eye of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> (hauing reduced it into the forme of Prouinces) but did long inioe it by their Gouernours and Lief<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>nants generall. This authoritie and <hi>Romane</hi> power was in a maner dispersed ouer the whole world. But as this Empyre was framed of diuers peeces, and built by Iniustice and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rany, so God a iust iudge &amp; reuenger of iniquties, raysed them vp great &amp; pourefull enemies from all parts of the world, is it were hyred to teare in sunder this Cloake, to dismember this Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die by peecemeales, and to punish their vnciuill rigor, by a barbarous cruelty, and their greedy iniustice, bn the rauishing extortion of others. The Empire then which had robbed was sackt it selfe, and hauing taken anothers good, lost their owne, being skarce able (and that by meanes of the <hi>FRENCH</hi>) to retaine any show of this great and vast body. The fury of <hi>Mahomet</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaded <hi>Asia,</hi> and <hi>Affricke,</hi> with a part of <hi>Europe,</hi> like a violent flame, with an incredible swift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, <hi>Spaine</hi> was se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>zed on by the <hi>Vandales, Alanes, Sueues</hi> and <hi>Gothes, Italy</hi> by the <hi>Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dales, Hunnes, Gothes</hi> and <hi>Lombards, Gaule</hi> wanted not sundry guests: the <hi>Gothes</hi> seazed on that goodly <hi>Gaule Narbo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ise,</hi> called for the exelencie a second <hi>Italy,</hi> and left their name to this goodly Prouince, which they enioyed long and called it by their name, first <hi>Gothia</hi> and after <hi>Languedoc,</hi> as it were the language of <hi>Gothe,</hi> although they giue other reasons of this name more subtile then true. The <hi>Burgognons</hi> seazed of the country which they called by their name <hi>Bourgougne,</hi> and erected a kingdome which contained the one &amp; the other <hi>Burgongne</hi> with the Prouince of <hi>Lionois, Daulphine, Sauoy,</hi> and <hi>Prouence.</hi> The <hi>Normans, Brittons</hi> and <hi>Picts,</hi> tooke euery one their tickett to lodge in <hi>Gaule,</hi> according to the diuers occurrents of affayres which presented themselues in this generall dissipation of the <hi>Romaines</hi> Empyre, who amiddest these confusions did with great difficulty retaine the least portion: knowing not how to oppose themselues against so great and victorious enimies. So the <hi>FRENCH</hi> hauing like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise in the begining seazed on their quarter, were so fauoured by the prouidence of God, that through their vallour they layed the foundation of a newe estate, so as hauing expelled out of <hi>Gaule,</hi> both the old and new vsurpers, in the end they became Masters, and buylt this goodlie Monarchy, the which since hath giuen a lawe to neighbour Nations, settled the <hi>Romaine</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, stopt the violence of these cruell and barbarous Nations, and (which is the greatest honour of this estate) hath maintayned the Christiā Church in Europe, the which God hath appointed for an habitation amidest the furious confusions of <hi>Asia</hi> and <hi>Affricke,</hi> where the deluge of <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets</hi> blasphemies hath horriblely exceeded: Wherein the greatnesse and power of <hi>Gaule</hi> is to be admired, by the which <hi>Iulius Caesar</hi> could first alter the common weale of <hi>Rome</hi> his country, into the newe forme of an Empyre, and after when as all the most furious nations did flocke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to cast downe this great masse; <hi>Charlemayne</hi> with the same force cold preserue a great part of the West from that cruell shipwracke which ruened all the Est.</p>
   <p>And as this spoyle was not generall at one instant ouer all <hi>Gaule,</hi> but by fits like vnto a Riuer which ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es her course in a newe quarter; so the <hi>FRENCH Monarchie</hi> was built by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees. The <hi>FRENCH</hi> being first imployed by the <hi>Romaines</hi> for their valour in notable oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations. We begin to reade of their Name with some show and state, vnder the Empyre of <hi>Galli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s,</hi> about the yeare of Christ two hundred seuenty. <hi>Posthumus</hi> gouernour of <hi>Gaule</hi> armed them against his Master and with the helpe of their forces &amp; the consent of the <hi>Gaules,</hi> he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed <hi>Gaule</hi> the space of seauen yeares, with the Title of Emperour. It is likely this first aboad caused them to taste the fertile sweetnesse of this goodly and rich Country. Thus both the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Posthumus</hi> and the proofe of their owne forces gaue them courage to attempt for themselues, Wee reade that vnder the Emperours <hi>Aurelian, Probus, Dioclesian</hi> and <hi>Constantius</hi> father to <hi>Constantine</hi> the great, they haue often returned without any other subiect then to seeke their aduantage: so were they often repulsed by the <hi>Romaines</hi> with great losse.</p>
   <p>These fruitelesse striuinges might well haue cooled the heate of their attemptes, but
<pb facs="9"/>
not their desire to seeke for means: But they continued m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st obstinately theyr practize in Arms, and mayntained their reputation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uen with the <hi>Romaynes</hi> themselues, who were glad to haue them for friendes and to imploy them in their warres, as <hi>Constantine</hi> against <hi>Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>inius</hi> a greate enimie to the Christians: and <hi>Constantius</hi> his sonne against the <hi>Germaines</hi> and <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apostata, against the <hi>Persians.</hi> Trulie aswell the Historie of the Church as <hi>Saint Hierome</hi> in particular (one of the most famous Doctors) spake of the <hi>FRENCH</hi> as of a very renowned people, who might both hurt and helpe, by their multitudes and their valour of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Armes. The style of this desseine, which I haue vndertaken, doth only note the thing for your vnderstanding, without spending time in longer proofes. This Apprentiship of the <hi>FRENCH</hi> by their many voyages into <hi>Gaule,</hi> contynued a hundred and thirtie yeares, for so much it was from <hi>Gallienus</hi> to <hi>Honorius,</hi> vnder whome they began to sett footing into <hi>Gaule,</hi> vpon this occasion. Those of the Citty of <hi>Treues</hi> tyred with the Tyranie of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines,</hi> were infinitely grieued that <hi>Lucius</hi> their Gouernour a <hi>Romaine,</hi> had by force taken the wife of a notable Cittizen. This excesse ministred a subiect to call the <hi>French-men</hi> to their ayde, who expelled the <hi>Romaines,</hi> seased quietly on the Citty with the consent of the Inhabitants, and so (proceeding in their conquest) they possessed their neighbour Countries, and in time, became Maisters of all that lyes beyond the Riuers of <hi>Escaut,</hi> and <hi>Some</hi>: and in the end hauing woone <hi>Paris,</hi> and the territories about, they gaue their name to the conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Country. I doe briefely touch what shall be represented in particular in euery place, and sett downe truelie the originall of the <hi>FRENCH</hi> in this Realme.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>PHARAMOND</hi> layd the first stone in the buylding of this estate, <hi>CLODION</hi> followed in this desseine▪ <hi>MEROVE</hi> made it appeare aboue ground, in a more goodly forme, hauing purchased credit among the <hi>Gaules,</hi> both by his valour and the happy succeesse of his Armes. <hi>CLOVIS</hi> (adding the profession of Christ to his Predecessors valour and his owne) did so winne the hartes of the <hi>Gaules,</hi> (who were for the most part Christians) as by their hearts he got their voluntary obedience, and the assured possession of these newe Conquestes. Two nations vnited in one by the Conquerour, giuing lawe to the Conquered, with so wise and mylde a discretion, as they held him worthy of this Alliance, and Name: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd the fruite of this mariage was to happy as the n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>we name of <hi>FRANCE</hi> was generally receiued in <hi>Gaule.</hi> Thus this newe estate increased dayly in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ce of <hi>PHARAMOND</hi> by diuers oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currentes during the space of three hun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>d yeares. But i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> was much more augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the famous race of <hi>PEPIN.</hi> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>d the Author of all good order in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; giuing him to Sonne <hi>CHARLEMAIGNE</hi> to preuent the ruine of the Empire, inriched him with singular graces, and confirmed in him that great authoritie and power of the King of <hi>FRANCE,</hi> and Emperour of <hi>ROME,</hi> which greatnesse God would make profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to all Christendome. But his race Inheritor of these great honours did not inherite his valour and happinesse, hauing sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rce continued <hi>237.</hi> yeares: but degenerating from his vertues, they lost both Authoritie and Crowne, so much augmented and beautified by him and <hi>CHARLES MA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>TELL.</hi> So this second race, vnworthy of the blood and name of their Grandfathers, was spoyled of their Kingdome by their negligence. But God the Guardian of Monarchies (who changing the persons, would preserue the State) r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed vp <hi>HVGH CAPET</hi> a wise and modest Prince, arming him with wisedome and dexteritie fitt for the preseruation of his Crowne, accompanying his Armes with lawe, and his royall authoritie with well gouerned Iustice. It is to <hi>HVGH CAPET</hi> that the Realme of <hi>FRANCE</hi> standes most ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ted for the establishment of those goodly Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, by the which (together with the vallour and fidelitie of the <hi>FRENCH</hi>) this great Monarchy halfe withstood the stormes of so many ages, and maintaines euen vnto this day, the lawfull heire in the same race, for the space of fiue hundred and thirtie yeares. So as gathering the summe of all these yeares, they reckon from <hi>PHARAMOND</hi> to <hi>HENRY</hi>▪ the fourth that now Raignes, <hi>1175.</hi> yeares.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="9"/>This is the Plot or desseigne of the whole History of France, the which being thus laid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we raise this great building in euery part, according to the true meas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>res and iust propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, let vs make a <hi>Diagramme</hi> as a liuely figure, which may conteine nakedly, and without circumstance, the names of our Kings, according to the order of these three royall Races. To the which we will adde a particuler Chronologie,<note place="margin">
         <hi>The order &amp; forme of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap> Inuentorie.</hi>
      </note> which shall be proued by the discourse of our <hi>Inuentorie,</hi> I haue distinguished it into three parts, according to the order of the three roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Races. In the front of euery part I note the names of Kings, and the time they haue reigned, that at my first entrance you may obserue all that is represented in this p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rticuler discourse▪ wherein the wise Reader (that shall take the paines to conferre this modell with the whole Historie) will iudge that I haue omitted nothing that may concerne the sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ect of the History▪ with all principall circumstances, to the end the truth in this short, simple, and vnseemly weed, appointed for euery day, may serue aswell as that which the Learned and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent writers shew forth in open Theaters at Festiuall times. To Actions carefully described, I adde sometimes my Iudgement, for the vse of the History, examined by the Maximes of State. To actions I say generally aduowed, as for the rest I leaue them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>emembring that I am a Witnesse and no Iudge, to do seruic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to such as could not see the Originals. I note in the beginning the Elections, the Birthes, Liues, Aduentures, Intents, Desseignes, Maners and Complections of our Kings, the Motiues, Actions, Alterations, Crosses, Issues and Successe of their affaires, both in Warre and Peace: their Enterprises, taking of Citties and Countries, Battels, Encounters, Victories, Ouer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hrowes, Aduantages, Disaduantages, and other things remarkeable in State: Finally I obserue their ends in their death, as the <hi>Catastrophe</hi> of their Life, and closing vp of their Reigne. But to make this dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ourse more proportionable for the knowledge of our Monarchie, it was necessary to explaine it by that which hath chanced of most import in forreine Estates, especially in the Church &amp; Empire, the most famous Theat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rs of the world, by reason wherof I haue added a most carefull Collation of the one and the other with our Realme. I intreate the wise Reader to way with iudgement what I shall report con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning matters most subiect to comptroule, as those of the Church. I doubt not but that hee shall finde that I haue conteined my selfe within the limits of State, talking nothing of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, nor medling with the diuerse humors of this age. I haue onely treated of the politique gouernment of <hi>Rome,</hi> with as much modesty as the subiect would permit. I know likewise that making profession to write a History, no man will wish mee eyther to disguise or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale the truth, the which will warrant it selfe, and free me from reproche, in making knowne to iudicious and modest wits, that I haue no other passion but my duty, whereof I can giue no better proofe, thē in iustifying my discourse with the Original, if there appeare any difficulty. I protest I haue only had a true desire to serue the publique, whose profit is the only scope of my labours. As for the Computations, as they be very necessary for the well vnderstanding of the History (which is the Register of times) so hath it much troubled me, being altogether negl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the most ancient Writers, borne in the first obscure ages. The learned which haue hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily handled this subiect before me, finding plainly this notable difficultie, haue held it expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to make litle or no accompt to obserue the dates, which was i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> my conceipt (vnder cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection be it spoken) to cut the knot a sunder insteed of vnloosing it. But it hath made me more carefully to labour in this search, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o finde out some meanes amidst these extremities. And therefore I haue distinguished the most n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>table cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ges, not onely from one Race to another, but in the Races themselues▪ placing the dates i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ront of the whole discourse, as a Bound<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ston to limit the Lands. Moreouer I haue faithfully collected in grosse the yeares of euery reigne, and haue deuided them as I thought most likely, by the continuance of publike and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate actions. It is all I could do i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the most ancient reignes, being vnable to deuine further, but in those that approach neerer to our age, the Reader shall see the vniting of things from yeare to yeare by degrees, whereby he may mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nly in so goodly a light without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>▪ The <hi>Diag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>mmes</hi> shall supply the particuler default of times, which we cannot otherwise distinguish. But let vs first see the whole patterne of our Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>y c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lour or f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="4 letters">
         <desc>••••</desc>
      </gap>ish whatsoeuer.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>