<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTY PRINCE IAMES, BY THE GRACE OF GOD King of Great Britaine, France, and Ireland, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Tillesley, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117059_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13775</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24073</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117059</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTY PRINCE IAMES, BY THE GRACE OF GOD King of Great Britaine, France, and Ireland, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Tillesley, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Animaduersions vpon M. Seldens History of tithes, and his reuievv thereof : before which (in lieu of the two first chapters purposely pretermitted) is premised a catalogue of seuenty two authours, before the yeere 1215. Maintaining the ius diuinum of tythes or more, to be payd to the priesthood vnder the Gospell: by Richard Tillesley Doctor in Diuinity, and archdeacon of Rochester</title>
                 <author>Tillesley, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bill, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44, 236 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTY <hi>PRINCE</hi> IAMES, <hi>BY THE GRACE OF GOD</hi> King of <hi>Great Britaine, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the <hi>Faith, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the duty of a Subiect and <hi>seruant,</hi> were not a most sufficient reason to consecrate all labours &amp; endeauors to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and protection of his Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster: yet to whom are <hi>Animaduersions</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/> more proper then to the Magistrate? Or to whom should the defence of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Tythes be dedicated, but to the Defendour of the Faith? All these rights in your sacred Maiesty are su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme; and therefore haue emboldened me your poore vnworthy yet faithful sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect and seruant, to implore your sacred patronage of these animaduersions on the History of Tythes, that so the defence of faith may extend it selfe to the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the preachers of the faith, and the temporall food of their bodies may be established by diuine and humane autori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who prepare, the spirituall foode of soules.</p>
   <p>But more especially, that pious deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and zealous affection, wherewith your gracious Maiesty embraceth and vpholdeth the Ancient doctrine and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scipline
<pb facs="3"/> of the true primitiue Church, to whom,<note place="margin">Beda in ho. Infra Octau. Ascens.</note>
      <hi>perfectum est vitae magisteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Ecclesiae primitiuae actus imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri,</hi> The imitation of Reuerend and sound antiquity, is the perfect schole of faith and life, by which patterne your sacred pen and sword hath suppressed all schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall and turbulent paritie, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded all Jdolatrous superstition, and treasonable practises. This is that which hath most encouraged me,<note place="margin">Conc. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thag. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> &amp; passim in Concil.</note>
      <hi>postulare ab Imperatore defensorem,</hi> to implore your Royall and religious patronage, who are the aduocate and nursing father of Gods portion the Church, and of the Churches portion, that is Tythes, due to God himselfe in acknowledgement of his supreame right and dominion, and giuen by God himselfe, to them that serue at his Altar. And so much the rather for that
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>Kings</hi> as they are in their power <hi>the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God,</hi>
      <note place="margin">August in qu. ex V. Test. c. <hi>106.</hi>
      </note> who sayd, <hi>The Tythe is mine:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Leu. 27.30. 1. Sam. 8. v. 15.17.</note> so in the right of their sustenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion haue the proportion of God, <hi>Tenths:</hi> which quantity in Tribute was so vsuall amongst the Grecians,<note place="margin">Hesychius in Ʋerb. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> that <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> to tithe and pay Tribute, were as properly <hi>Synonymaes,</hi> as <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> to tythe and consecrate, So that to assume the protection of Gods challenged Tenth as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed to his ministers, is indeed to streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the reason of that right of Tribute allowed to your selfe. And surely this number <hi>Tenth,</hi> or <hi>Tithe,</hi> is sacred and very mysticall; and communicated onely to sacred and consecrated persons that are Gods Ʋicars vpon Earth, that is Kings and Priests; <hi>decima Regis, &amp; decima Sacerdotis,</hi> who both stand in Gods place and receiue this portion as
<pb facs="4"/> Gods vpon earth; and this number is so acceptable and familiar to God,<note place="margin">Lib. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress. quaerēd. eruditionis causa.</note> as <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo</hi> speakes, that it doth properly belong to him, and by his assignement to those who resemble him.</p>
   <p>It was the saying of an Ancient in S. <hi>Augustine:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Epist.</hi> 20.</note>
      <hi>Quibus satis persuasum esset, vt nihil mallent se esse quam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros bonos, his reliquam facilem esse doctrinam,</hi> To those, who only inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to be good men, all other instruction is easie, and among them this doctrine of Tithes need no enforcement nor defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. But couetousnesse hath so blinded religion, and custome so hardned consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and might so abetted sacrilege, that vnlesse,<note place="margin">Isidor. sent. lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>51.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Quod non praeualet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdos efficere per doctrinae sermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, potestas hoc imperet per disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinae terrorem,</hi> The magistrate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb facs="5"/> what the Minister cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade, Religion must giue way to sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, and Christ to Mammon. Jt was the complaint of <hi>Goffridus</hi> Abbot of <hi>Vendosme</hi> to <hi>Goffridus</hi> Bishop <hi>of Chartres,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>ep.</hi> 24</note>
      <hi>Quod seculares homines sua consuetudine sanctae Ecclesiae authoritatem conantur adnullare,</hi> That secular men by custome would abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate the Churches authority, which is too true now. And it is the Church of Englands petition to her foster-father, to her Soueraigne, <hi>vt reddantur quae sunt Dei, Deo.</hi> And since, <hi>Res Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticae quia diuini iuris sunt,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iuo ep. <hi>112.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>in nullius bonis sunt,</hi> Church-goods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause Gods right, are not to be accounted any mans possessions; <hi>Non suntinter res mundi deputari credendae sed Dei,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lib. de vita contemplat. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>16</hi>
      </note> as saith <hi>Prosper:</hi> Why should
<pb facs="5"/> men who may not couet their neighbours goods, couet that which is Gods, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe against diuine right, making cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome and humane practise, and positiue law, the basis, or <hi>maior</hi> proposition of their syllogisme or conclusion, which they call conscience; that so they may lay sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious hands vpon Gods portion, that is tythes, which surely must all be voyd and vniust, as <hi>M. Selden</hi> ingeniously confesseth pag. <hi>150.</hi> if tithes be due by diuine right vnto the Ministers of the Gospell. Wherein although I hope the <hi>Authours harty submission</hi> hath cleered his iudgement concerning any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation intended by him against the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine right of Tythes, yet because I am afrayd this History of Tythes hath af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorded premisses to some, and to others great surmises of religious practise of sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege,
<pb facs="6"/> while they see, and heare, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine not) manifold quotations of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, heathen writers, Rabbines, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Councels, Jmperiall Lawes, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Chartularies, and many vncouth and vnusuall marginall notes, whereby they hope, nay resolue their owne desires are vnanswerably defended.<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> ad Monymum.</note> Yet, I hope, as <hi>Fulgentius</hi> saith of Heretikes and their Arguments, <hi>Nouum non est vt Haeretici illis propositionibus se veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem superaturos arbitrentur, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus facillime superantur,</hi> so in this Historian, his owne authorities being faithfully discouered, do easily ouerthrow the credit of all his consequences.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>ep.</hi> 6.</note>Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> sayd to <hi>Childebert, Esse Regem quia sunt &amp; alij, non mirum; sed esse Catholicum quod alij non merentur; hoc satis.</hi> Giue me
<pb facs="6"/> leaue to applie it: Your Maiestie is a great King, and a mighty Monarch, whom God hath crowned with many Kingdomes aboue your Ancestours, and made you the vniter of Crownes: and this is common to many others with your Maiesty. Your Maiesty is a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Catholike King, Defender of the true, Ancient, Catholike and Apostolike faith, which is almost <hi>proper</hi> to your selfe; they that boast to be called <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> &amp; <hi>Catholike,</hi> may not compare with your Maiestie in this stile. But J must adde another word out of the same Saint <hi>Gregory: Regiam,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Lib.</hi> 9. <hi>ep.</hi> 57</note>
      <hi>quod maioris lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis est, ornatis sapientia potestatem.</hi> This is your owne proper and peculiar, no King can share with you in this honour; you are a most learned &amp; iudicious King, who with your great knowledge and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable
<pb facs="7"/> pen, haue, and doe dayly adorne your Regall power with your singular wisdome &amp; learning: <hi>Rex Theologo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> a King of many excellent &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Diuines, and <hi>Rex Theologus,</hi> a King, a Diuine, who are <hi>Antesigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> a leader among your great Bishops and worthy writers: And which is hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie for my Argument, a <hi>founder,</hi> a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storer,</hi> &amp; an <hi>endower of Bishopricks</hi> with Tithes, I beseech your sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty, let me, and this poore worke of mine, march vnder your Banner, it will stand against all enemies if it may but carry your Maiesties name &amp; protection. And so I will end with the prayer of those Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the <hi>12. Toletan</hi> Councel, to God for their Prince,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Can.</hi> 13.</note>
      <hi>Vt det amatori Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sti Serenissimo Domino nostro at{que} amantissimo</hi> Iacobo <hi>Principi, impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare
<pb facs="7"/> clemēter, regnare foeliciter, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere de clementia fructum, obtine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re de iustitia praemium, de pietate Trophaeum, quo &amp; hic inuictus vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor hostiū semper appareat, &amp; post diuturna huius seculi curricula, ad regnum aeternum cum suis omnibus coronandus perueniat: praestante Deo, &amp; Saluatore nostro Domino Iesu Christo, qui cum patre &amp; san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto spiritu in Trinitate, viuit &amp; reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat Deus in secula seculorum.</hi> Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties most humble seruant and Chaplaine, <hi>RICHARD TILLESLEY.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>