<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE NOBLE, AND POTENT LORD IAMES MARQVIS OF HAMILTOVN, EARLE OF ARANE, AND CAMBRIDGE, LORD AVEN, AND INNERDAILL, MASTER OF HIS MAIE∣STIES HORSES, AND ONE OF HIS MAIESTIES PRIVIE COVNSELL.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117283_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16540</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3448</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117283</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE NOBLE, AND POTENT LORD IAMES MARQVIS OF HAMILTOVN, EARLE OF ARANE, AND CAMBRIDGE, LORD AVEN, AND INNERDAILL, MASTER OF HIS MAIE∣STIES HORSES, AND ONE OF HIS MAIESTIES PRIVIE COVNSELL.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Two orientall pearles, grace and glory, published by Mr. Zacharie Boyd, preacher of Gods word, at Glasgovv</title>
                 <author>Boyd, Zacharie</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wreittoun (Scribonius), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>152 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="1"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE NOBLE,</hi> AND POTENT LORD <hi>IAMES</hi> MARQVIS OF HAMILTOVN, <hi>EARLE OF ARANE, AND</hi> CAMBRIDGE, LORD <hi>AVEN,</hi> AND <hi>INNERDAILL,</hi> MASTER OF HIS <hi>MAIE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIES HORSES, AND ONE</hi> OF HIS MAIESTIES <hi>PRIVIE COVNSELL.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MY most Honorable good Lord,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Great GOD who honoureth these that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him, hath honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red your Lo. with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny graces both spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and temporally: As for the spirituall, of the loue of the trueth, and courage for the same,
<pb n="4" facs="2"/> your L. hath already given a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine proofe: wee all looke for more as occasion shall serue: In whomsoever the spirit of <hi>IESVS</hi> truely is, that man will goe from grace to grace: <hi>He</hi> (said our Master,<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.5.</note>) <hi>that abideth in mee, and I in him, the same bringeth foorth much fruite.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>As for the <hi>TEMPORALL,</hi> your L. is the first of the Royall blood in this Land after his <hi>MAIESTIE:</hi> You are the Sonne of the most wise and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Father, who in his lyfe was a most fast friend both to <hi>CHVRCH</hi> and Commoun-wealth.</p>
   <p>The Lord also hath made you the Sonne of a most Religious and Noble Lady, even of a Lady <hi>LYDIA, whose heart the LORD in great mercy hath opened,</hi> for to let in and lodge the KING of GLORY. After my six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene yeeres absence in <hi>Fraunce</hi> at my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne I arrived at <hi>KINNEILL,</hi> where her Ladiship received mee with such courtesie, that shall never want my most heartly and humble thankes.</p>
   <p>In testimonie of my great desire to serue your L. I present you with these two m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st precious <hi>ORIENTALL
<pb n="5" facs="2"/> PEARLES,</hi> viz. <hi>GRACE</hi> and <hi>GLO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RY,</hi> which are from him,<note place="margin">Luk. 1.78.</note> whom <hi>ZA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHARIE</hi> in his Song calleth <hi>ORI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ENS ab alto, the day spring from on high:</hi> In this sermon you will see whose Counsell you should cheefly seeke: All the counsell of men with the counsell of <hi>Achitophell</hi> may easily <hi>bee turned into follie;</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.31.</note> but heere is the counsell that failed never, even the <hi>COVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SELL</hi> of <hi>GOD:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Note.</note> When ever your Lo. is for to deliberate vpon any graue and weightie matter, let this secreet ejaculation first goe before, LORD guide mee with thy Counsell, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward receiue mee to Glory.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Note.</note> The whole Church of Britaine most humbly intreats your L. to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in your <hi>good course and courage</hi> for GODS glory: Read often these words of good <hi>MORDECAI</hi> to Ester. <hi>Thinke not with thy selfe that thou shall escape in the Kings house:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Esth. 4.13.14.</note>
      <hi>For if thou altogether holdest thy peace at this tyme, then shall there enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and deliverance arise to GODS people from another place, but thou and thy Fathers house shall bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed:
<pb n="6" facs="3"/> And who knoweth whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou art come to such honour for such a tyme as this?</hi> Your Lo. sitteth at the common-sterne; Helpe vs with <hi>your power,</hi> and wee will helpe you with <hi>our prayers.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Let it please your L. to take this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in good part, though it be but litle.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Note.</note> At the making of the Tabernacle not only were the great and rich presents acceptable, as <hi>PVRPLE, SCARLET,</hi> and <hi>BLVE SILK,</hi> but also <hi>RAMMES SKINNES,</hi> and <hi>GOATES HAIRE,</hi> which the poorer sort was able onely to affoord.</p>
   <p>For to make an end by humble prayers to GOD for your L. I intreat the most high,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Thess.</hi> 3.13.</note> the God of Maiestie and mercie, <hi>to make your heart stable and vnblameable in holinesse,</hi> till hee hath in you crowned his graces with glorie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lo. <hi>Most humble and</hi> obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Servant. <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. ZACHARIE BOYD</hi> Preacher of GODS <hi>WORD, at</hi> GLASGOW.</signed>
      <dateline>
         <hi>At</hi> Glasgow <date>
            <hi>the 13 of Februar 1629.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>