<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL MAI∣ster Erasmus Dryden Esquier, grace, and peace be multiplied.</title>
           <author>Winston, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117481_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20540</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6950</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117481</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL MAI∣ster Erasmus Dryden Esquier, grace, and peace be multiplied.</title>
                 <author>Winston, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Three godlie and fruitful sermons; the two first preached by Maister Iohn Dod: the last by Maister Robert Cleauer. Whereunto are annexed, fiue propositions, or points of doctrine, comprehended in three other sermons, by the same author</title>
                 <author>Dod, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Welby, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 184 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL MAI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Erasmus Dryden Esquier, grace, and peace be multiplied.</head>
   <p>SIR, it is a point well knowne vnto your Worship, that in duties of absolute necessity we must regard what God doth commande and enioyne, not what men doe approue and like of: and that we must still offer vp our seruice in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the Almighty, whatsoeuer men do thinke or speake of vs. As for this worke of publishing the labours of such faithfull and painefull Ministers, as desire rather to spend their time in preaching, than in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, I take it not to be a duty of that kind:
<pb facs="3"/> but of an inferiour nature; wherein the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance or disallowance of those that are godly wise, should haue a great stroke, either for incouragement to proceed in it, or for discouragement to desist from it Herein ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing made some tryal, I haue (through Gods blessing) found successe beyond my expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: which as it ministreth vnto me mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of much reioycing, in regard there are many thousands in Israel, who desire and embrace the sincere and plaine doctrine of the Gospell; so doth it set an edge on my desires to take vp some vacant houres in this imployment: being right glad, if by any meanes I may be an helper to the truth, and an instrument of refreshing hunger-bitten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soules, by conueying vnto them some bas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets full of such fragments, as may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated without any detriment or disad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage to my selfe, or to any else. These Sermons I haue made bolde to recommend vnto your fauourable acceptance and patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, not onely in regard of the interest which you haue in them, and that incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which I haue often receiued from your
<pb facs="3"/> Worship in businesses of this nature; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so because I perswade my selfe that your ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry countenancing of them, wil adde, though not vnto their goodnesse, yet vnto their good esteeme, among many that are religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously affected.</p>
   <p>I haue annexed vnto these Sermons, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine select points of doctrine, without any speciall texts of Scripture prefixed thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: and that because I found the rest of the doctrines that were deliuered with those, either very briefly handled, and so vnfit to be printed, or else treated of in some of the Sermons already extant. And thus nothing doubting of your Worships fauour in taking in good worth this my bold attempt, I leaue you to the safe tuition of God almighty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeching him to enrich you and yours with all manner of corporall and spirituall bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings in Christ Iesus; and to adde vnto your life, as also vnto the life of your faithfull and gracious yoake-fellow, many happy and comfortable daies.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships much indebted, and in what I may, to be commanded, IOHN WINSTON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>