<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Translators Epistle to the Indifferent Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117343_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03451</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13575</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117343</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Translators Epistle to the Indifferent Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Nevves out of Holland : of the East Indie trade there. Containing a true copie of a Dutch treatise there published, of the grosse abuses of their maiors, the managers of their trade. Shewing that not withstanding the extreame wrongs they doe to the English nation, trading i the Indies, yet it is the iustice of God, they thriue not with it themselues. Printed this 26. of Iune. 1622</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <distributor>Archer, Thomas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 14 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Translators Epistle to the <hi>Indifferent Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>GEntle Reader, This</hi> Pamphlet following, came by meanes of a friende to my hand, in <hi>Dutch</hi> lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage out of <hi>Holland</hi> from the City of <hi>Amster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> which when I had throughly perused, I suppose my labour could not be lost in translating it into our <hi>English</hi> tongue, because the <hi>English</hi> my Countrie-men, may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand <hi>2.</hi> especiall considerations thereby: First the small gaine the <hi>Hollanders</hi> make by trading into the <hi>East Indies.</hi> Secondly the misse-governement and iniurious dealing of the <hi>Maiors,</hi> and such as are appointed <hi>Governours</hi> for the trade of the <hi>East Indies</hi> by the <hi>Hollanders.</hi> If the <hi>Maiors</hi> and <hi>Governours</hi> be those, who Substitute vnder them <hi>Committies</hi> and <hi>Commissioners</hi> for the
<pb facs="3"/>governement of the Trade. They being in this <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet</hi> touched by their owne Countrie-men, of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honest and vnconscionable dealing themselues, what <hi>Substitutes, Maiors</hi> &amp;c, will they appoint? but such who shall correspond with them in little Honesty and lesse Conscience: so that it is to bee considered. in how dangerous an estate our <hi>English Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi> of the <hi>East Indian</hi> Companie remaine, to stand to the curtesie of such persons, against whom their owne Countrie-men doe so heavily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, it is apparant generally, that the <hi>English</hi> are wronged extreamely by the <hi>Hollanders</hi> in the <hi>East Indies;</hi> and there is small hope of any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresse in <hi>Holland,</hi> for where Covetousnes at home, make choyce of Officers in forraigne parts abroad, Covetousnes will rather maintaine the extortions and oppressions committed by his Officers, then either redresse them or correct them: As by this Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation following may plainly appeare, which I leaue to the reading and consideration of the indifferent Reader.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>