<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Rich. Saint George Norrey King at armes, in fauour of this worke.</title>
           <author>Goldwell, Charles</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117917_Fr1_8</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68764</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23041</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117917</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Rich. Saint George Norrey King at armes, in fauour of this worke.</title>
                 <author>Goldwell, Charles</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The theatre of the empire of Great Britaine : presenting an exact geography of the kingdomes of England, Scotland, Ireland, and the iles adioyning: with the shires, hundreds, cities and shire-townes, within ye kingdome of England, divided and described by Iohn Speed</title>
                 <author>Speed, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Hall, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hall, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Humble, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Humble, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sudbury, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sudbury, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 146, that is 280, 10 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), maps (metal cuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>
      <hi>Rich. Saint George Norrey</hi> King at armes, in fauour of this worke.</head>
   <p>IT is farre from my purpose, to commend without cause, or by ouer curious florish to make a shadow seeme a substance, this worke needs no such <hi>deceptio visus;</hi> The subiect is of it selfe honorable, and able to stand without such weake proppes. The glory of our nation being almost buried in the pit of obscurity, is herein reuiued, the continuance of Christianity traced from age to age, the antiquity and situation of our Townes, Castles, Religious Houses, Nobility, and all other memorable matters so liuely portraied, as in a glasse we may rightly discerne the true shape, quality and condition of each of them in particular. This worke therefore being now brought vpon the publike stage and view of the world, may in my poore censure giue satisfaction to the learned Reader, and abide the touch of the malignant opposer; which being effected without hope of gaine or vaine ostentation with so great care both of body and mind, is the more precious, for, <hi>difficilia quae pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chra.</hi> Wherein Gods power is made knowne in this his weake, but worthy instrument: and the glory of <hi>Great Britaine</hi> made more famous to the world as well in the Geographicall demension of the Lands situation as in the historicall relations of her most famous monarchsand glorious actions; no Kingdome hitherto so particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly described, nor nations History by true record more faithfully penned: In honor whereof I sacrifice these lines of my loue vpon the Altar of this worke, and celebrate the Authors remembrance to future posteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>