<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ADMONITION SENT BY GERARD TO THE READER touching the former epistle.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117527_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68555</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19406</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117527</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ADMONITION SENT BY GERARD TO THE READER touching the former epistle.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An epistle of the persecution of Catholickes in Englande : Translated ovvt of frenche into Englishe and conferred vvithe the Latyne copie. by G.T. To whiche there is added an epistle by the translator to the right honorable lordes of her maiesties preeuie councell towchynge the same matter</title>
                 <author>Parsons, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Fr. Parsons’ Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>167, 17 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="85"/>
   <head>AN ADMONITION SENT BY GERARD TO THE READER touching the former epistle.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Vhen I imparted vvith some of my familiars this epistle, vvhich vvas sent vnto me from a fryend ouer the Alpes: vpo their earnest request and certein kinde of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoute <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. I vvas comēt to let it pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se further in to the hands of some noble and principall persones, by vvhole persuasion, or rather commaundement it vvas put in printe. For I thought it to be muche auailable to the common estate of Christendome, that this so notable a persecution of Catholiques in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland should be not onlie communicated to the knovvleige of this present age, but put ouer allso to the mynde and memorie of oure poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. For it hathe matter enough to sturre vp them novv liuing to compassion and pitie, and to instruct them that are to come, of vvhat thīgs they ought to take hede &amp; bevvare. But of one thing I vvoolde aduertise the reader (as my freēde in other letters hath aduertised me) that among many matters not mētioned in the other parts of his Epistle this one in the rehearsall of lavves he hathe vvillinglie omitted: that is, hovv by many statuts, and proclamations such order is taken in England as no Catholique, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by exile, or by forsaking of his countrie,
<pb facs="85"/>
can escape, or vvith dravv hym selfe from tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se paines or persecutions vvhiche folovv hym for religiō For it is prouided (to this effect) that no Catholique may goe forth of the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thout leaue and licence first obteined And that yf anie do go forth vvithoute licence he shall forfait all his possessions during his life was and further, that none before his departure forth of the realme may geue avvay his possessions no not to his vvyfe, childeren nor fryend <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> doe: it shall be taken as done of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraude the quene of her for<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> for such forfaitures, they <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> by information of couen. But this statute of fugitiues (for so it is called) is so strictlye and seuerelie obserued against Catholiques, as none vvithin the realm, dare by anie vvay or mean help, succoure, or releeue eyther father, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, husband, bretheren, or children, vvhich are Catholiques, and vvithoute licece abyding ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of England. And as for this licence to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent oute of the realme, as it is hardlie obteined for others: so is it neuer or seldome, and vvith verie muche difficultie graunted to Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques. Yea further, (vvhiche is more seuere) all those parents (vvhose childeren are abyding in these parts, or else vvhere oute of England, for studie sake, are compelled to enter in bond, vvith good assurance, eyther to dravve their childeren home again by and by vvithoute ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieng, or to depriue them vtterlie of all exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and releefe. All vvhiche things do tende to this ende, that no part nor portion of anie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loose
<pb facs="86"/>
or comfort, be it neuer so litle, might fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye come to the English Catholiques, either at home or abroad. And these be the matters vv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here of I thought good to admonish yovv, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are not spoke of in the epistle. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re remaineth novv no more but that all true Christians vvold thorovvlie vevve and cōsider the great distresses of their bretheren &amp; of their ovvne <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, and vvith moste feruent pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yere, for the common bond sake of Charitie, vvhiche passeth thorovvgh the vvhole corps of Christendome, to commend their case to the common <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> ouer all.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>