<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE LIFE OF LVCIVS ANNAEVS SENECA, DE∣SCRIBED BY IVSTVS LIPSIVS.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117063_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11899</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22213</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117063</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE LIFE OF LVCIVS ANNAEVS SENECA, DE∣SCRIBED BY IVSTVS LIPSIVS.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The workes of Lucius Annæus Seneca, both morrall and naturall : Containing, 1. His bookes of benefites. 2. His epistles. 3. His booke of prouidence. 4. Three bookes of anger. 5. Two bookes of clemencie. 6. His booke of a blessed life. 7. His booke of the tranquilitie of the minde. 8. His booke of the constancie of a wiseman. 9. His booke of the shortnesse of life. 10. Two bookes of consolation to Martia. 11. Three bookes of consolation to Heluia. 12. His booke of consolation to Polibius. 13. His seuen bookes of naturall questions. Translated by Tho. Lodge, D. in Physicke</title>
                 <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 <publisher>Blount (Blunt), Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 324, 335-915, 914-917, 23 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="biography">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>THE LIFE OF LVCIVS ANNAEVS SENECA, DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SCRIBED BY <hi>IVSTVS LIPSIVS.</hi>
   </head>
   <div n="1" type="chapter">
      <head>CHAP. I. Of his Countrey and Parents.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath beene an olde custome to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish the liues of worthy men, and those whose wisedomes, writings and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we admire it doth not a little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent vs to know such other things as concerned or appertained vnto them. I will therefore speake of <hi>Seneca</hi> as farre as may be, and will collect and dispose all those things that concerne this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, both out of himselfe and diuers other writers. It appeareth that he mas borne in Corduba, an olde and flourishing Colony in Andalouzill in Spaine, and besides that, the chiefest in those Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions. This doth <hi>Strabo</hi> testifie in these wordes: <hi>Amongst all other Cities of Hispania, Batica, or Andalouzie, Corduba i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> enlarged both in glorie and power by</hi> Marcellus <hi>meanes:</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>Lib.</hi> 3.</note>
         <hi>as also the Citie of Gaditana, the one by reason of Nauigations, and the societies o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> the Romanes: the other, because of the goodnesse and greatnesse of the country; the riuer Babs like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise conferring much hereunto.</hi> They praise it, and therewithall proue it to be auncient, because it was <hi>Marcellus</hi> worke: which of them, was it his that was Praetor, or the other that was Consull? For <hi>Marcus Marcellus</hi> the Praetor gouerned Spaine, as <hi>Pliny</hi> testifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="12"/>
in the yeare of the Citie DLXXXV. although,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Lib.</hi> 43.</note> as it seemeth, in peace and quietnesse; by which means the rather this Colony of his countrimen was drawne thither, and happily the Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ie both increased and adorned. For that it was not built anew, it appeares by <hi>Siluius,</hi> who euen in <hi>Hanibals</hi> time called it Corduba. I had rather therfore ascribe it to him, then to the Consul <hi>Marcell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>s,</hi> who in the yeare DCI gouerned the hither part of Spain, as it appeares in the Epitome, and thou mayest gather out of <hi>Appian</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing worthily executed his charge in that place, triumphed Celti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rs. He had therefore at that time nothing to do with Baetica, or our Corduba, which is in the farther part of Spaine. But <hi>Strabo</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth more, The most chosen Romanes and Spaniards inhabited this Corduba from the beginning, and into these places did the Romanes send their first Colonie. Note this word Chosen; for it was so indeed: and thereupon afterwards, as I suppose, it obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this priuiledge, that it was called <hi>Colonia Patricia. Pliny</hi> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifieth it most plainly; Corduba (saith hee) named the Patrician Colonie, and in <hi>Augustus</hi> stampe of money, <hi>Permissu Caesaris Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gusti,</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> with his head on the one side, and then on the other side, <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia Patricia.</hi> The cause of which title, in my opinion, is, because that being both a faire and a rich Citie, it supplied the Roman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Common-wealth with Fathers and Senators. For now in <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus</hi> age they made choice of men out of euery Prouince to make vp the Senate. Furthermore, <hi>Strabo</hi> saith, That the first Colonie was sent thither, which reade thou with circumspection. For Carteia in the same countrey of Bae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ica, before this time had a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonie planted in it by <hi>Lucius Canuleius</hi> Praetor: but because they were not of the better sort, it was called <hi>Colonia Libertinorum,</hi> or the colonie of the Libertines. Thou shalt reade it in <hi>Liuy,</hi> in the beginning of his 43. booke: yet mayest thou, and happily oughtest thou to defend <hi>Strabo,</hi> that those inhabitants were not sent from Rome or Italie, but that they were begotten by the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane souldiers vpon the Spanish women; and by the permission of the Senate the Bastards had their libertie giuen them and were planted in a colonie. But <hi>Strabo</hi> expresly writeth, that a colonie was sent thither. Enough of Corduba, and this was his countrie; but who were his parents? It appeareth that they were of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naean race, whose name seemeth to be giuen them in way of good fortune, <hi>ab Annis.</hi> The sirname of <hi>Seneca</hi> likewise was fortunate. For the first, in my iudgment, had this name giuen him, although
<pb facs="12"/>
         <hi>Isidore</hi> thinke, that hee who was at first so called, was borne grey headed. Vndoubtedly <hi>Seneca,</hi> or as the Auncients write, <hi>Senica:</hi> (for <hi>Senecis</hi> is deriued <hi>à Sene</hi>) signified <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, as <hi>Senecio</hi> doth. Let <hi>Nonius</hi> be seene in <hi>Senica.</hi> Hereunto I adde that in another kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred also I finde this sirname; as in Accia in an ancient stone <hi>M. Accio Seneca. Manlio Plauta</hi> 11. <hi>virg. Quinq.</hi> But whether those of the race of <hi>Annaea</hi> were of the Spanish race, or were sent out of Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in a Colony, I dare not affirme; this onely I say, that they were of the order of Knights: for so <hi>Seneca</hi> himselfe speaketh of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe in <hi>Tacitus.</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>Lib.</hi> 14.</note> Am I he that sprung from the order of knight, and in a prouinciall place, numbred amongst the chiefest Peers of the Citie? Can it be amongst the Nobles, that boast themselues of their long worthinesse and antiquitie, that my noueltie should shine? his father therefore, and happily his grandfather were Knights, and not aboue. For he presently maketh mention of his noueltie; which he would not haue done, if any of his Ancestors had attained vnto honours. But his father was known both by himselfe and his writings, to be <hi>Lucius Annaeus Seneca,</hi> whom for the most part, they distinguish from the sonne by the title of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimer, in which kinde he excelled. Diuers Declamations are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, which were not his own but another mans, digested by him, which he distinguished by some titles and Annotations, and by this meanes sufficiently expressed his milde &amp; happy wit: he had to wife one <hi>Heluia</hi> a Spanish Ladie, a woman of great constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and wisedome as her sonne sufficientlie describeth her in his Consolatorie booke vnto her. The father came to Rome in <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustus</hi> time, and presently after his wife with her children follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him; amongst which was this our <hi>Seneca,</hi> as yet but verie yong. In that place liued he long, and followed his af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>airs with the fauor and good report of all men, and I thinke that hee liued till about the later time of <hi>Tiberius</hi>; and hereunto am I perswaded, because he maketh mention of <hi>Seianus</hi> conspiracie in his bookes, and of other things that appertaine hereunto. I let him passe, and returne vnto his sonne, of whom I haue intended to speake.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="2" type="chapter">
      <pb facs="13"/>
      <head>CHAP. II. Of <hi>Lucius Annaeus Seneca</hi> himselfe and his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, where he was borne, and when he was brought to Rome.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N Corduba was he borne, and was translated from thence to Rome when hee was a childe;<note place="margin">
            <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s. ad Hel. cap.</hi> 16.</note> which hee himselfe testifieth thus, where hee praiseth his Aunt: By her hands was I brought into the Citie, by her pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and motherly noursing I recouered my selfe after my long sickenesse. If he were carried in her armes, it must needs be that he was but an infant, and thou seest that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e was sicke at that time likewise and was recomforted by her care and diligence. This thinke I hapned in the fifteenth yeare or thereabouts, before <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustus</hi> de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>th, the argument whereof i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Senecaes</hi> young yeares in <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius</hi> time, whereof I must speake hereafter. The father therfore not long before that time came to Rome: he had two brothers, and no sisters; which appeareth by his wordes vnto his mother; Thou bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>iedst thy dearest husband, by whom thou wert the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of three children.<note place="margin">
            <hi>Ad Hel. c.</hi> 2.</note> And these three were <hi>M. Annaeus Nouatus, L. Annaeus Seneca, L. Annaeus Mela;</hi> all borne in such order as I haue set them downe. This appeareth by the inscriptions of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s, where they are so set down, althogh by their sirnames. But the eldest of these brethren presently changed his name, and was c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lled <hi>Iunius Gallio,</hi> because hee was adopted by him. Which <hi>Gallio</hi> is oftentimes named by <hi>Seneca</hi> the father in his declamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and is called ours, either by reason of their common countrie Spaine, or of that friendship which was betweene them<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> were they not likewise allied and a kin? I know not, yet suspect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, by reason of this adoption. And this <hi>Gall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>o</hi> it is who is called Father by <hi>Quintilian</hi> and <hi>Tacitus</hi> likewise, in the sixt of his Chronicles. But this our adopted <hi>Gallio</hi> in the Eusebian Cronicle is called <hi>Iunius Annaeus Gallio, Senecaes</hi> brother, and a worthy Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. Was it by the name of both the Families (which was rare amongst the Auncients; nay more, neuer heard of) that it might appeare into what familie hee entered by adoption, and in what hee was borne by nature? It appeareth mani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>estly, if the name
<pb facs="13"/>
and title bee true. He it is to whom our <hi>Seneca</hi> both sent and wrote his bookes of Wrath, in which he calleth him <hi>Nouatus</hi>: yet the same man in his title of blessed life calleth he his brother <hi>Gallio,</hi> and likewi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e in his Epistles his Lord <hi>Gallio</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> and that honestly as him that was his elder brother. Obserue this therefore that he see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med not to be adopted at such time as his bookes of Anger were written, that is, when <hi>Caius</hi> was aliue, but afterwards, and that then he changed his sirname: but his yongest brother was <hi>Annaeus Mela,</hi> so called by <hi>Tacitus Dion</hi> and <hi>Eusebius,</hi> who was onely a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Knight (for he that was the elder was a Senator) who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat <hi>Lucan</hi> a great accesse to his greatnesse, as <hi>Tacitus</hi> saith. These therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e were the three brothers, of whom <hi>Martiall</hi> witnesseth,
<q>
            <l>And learned <hi>Senecaes</hi> house,</l>
            <l>That is thrice to be numbred.</l>
         </q>
He calleth him learned, (I meane, the Orator) his treble-house; his three sonnes called his families.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="3" type="chapter">
      <head>CHAP. III. His youth, his Masters and studies.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ee came therfore to Rome when he was a childe,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Epist.</hi> 113.</note> and in that place ripened he his excellent wit in the best stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: his youth hapned in the beginning of <hi>Tiberius</hi> gouernment, as he himselfe confesseth, and about that time, when forraine sacrifices were remoued and abolished. This was in the fift yeare of <hi>Tiberius,</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>Lib. Annal.</hi> 14. <hi>in fine.</hi>
         </note> &amp; of that of the Citie Dcclxx<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. which appeareth manifestly by <hi>Tacitus,</hi> who writeth, that the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of the Egyptians and Iewes were abolished. <hi>Seneca</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore about that time grew to mans estate, &amp; was about som twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or two and twentie yeares olde. For that he was well stept in yeares in <hi>Augustus</hi> time, hereby it appeareth; because he obserued a Comet or a flame before his departure;<note place="margin">
            <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> of which he saith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> We saw before the death of <hi>Augustus</hi> such a kinde of prodigie, which chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren could not so curiously obserue. His father, in my opinion, was he that first instructed him in eloquence<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> &amp; this do his books of Controuersies &amp; their Praefaces testifie. For why shold not this worthy olde man, who both directed &amp; taught others, direct and instruct his owne children in that kinde. Hee did it, and left
<pb facs="14"/>
two of them most excellent &amp; exercised in eloquence, Gallio, and this our <hi>Seneca,</hi> for I haue red nothing of <hi>Mela.</hi> This is that Gallio whom <hi>Status</hi> commendeth for his sweet discourse.
<q>
            <l>And thus much more, that from his happy line</l>
            <l>He blest the world with <hi>Seneca</hi> diuine,</l>
            <l>And brought to light that <hi>Gallio,</hi> whose grace</l>
            <l>And fluent speech the commons did embrace.</l>
         </q>
He that was the author of the booke <hi>Of the causes of corrupted elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,</hi> said, that hee had a certaine resounding and pleasing elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, which he calleth the resounding of Gallio, meaning it by the sonne and not by the father. But our <hi>Seneca,</hi> besides his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence, addicted himselfe to Philosophie with earnest endeuor, and vertue rauished his most excellent wit, although his father were against it. He himselfe diuers times saith, that hee was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne from Philosophie, and that his wife was shee that dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded him; yea, and that she hated it, hee openly writeth in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place: yet did the sonnes desire and forwardnesse get the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hand, so that hee diligently and carefully heard the most fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and serious Philosophers of that age, and namely, <hi>Attalus</hi> the Stoicke, <hi>Sotion</hi> one of the same sort, although he seemed to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Pythagoras</hi> and <hi>Papirius Fabius,</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st.</hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>9.</note> which he names likewise, and praiseth with a g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>atefull memorie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> he was <hi>Sotions</hi> scholler in his yonger yeares, and he writeth, <hi>And now, though a childe, I sate and heard</hi> Sotion. Moreouer, he admired and honoured <hi>Demetrius</hi> the Cinique, conuersing oftentimes with him in his elder dayes, and at such time as he serued in Cour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, both priuately and publiquely. For he made him his companion both in his walks and trauailes. Such was his forwardnesse in honest studies, yet his father broke him off, and in the interim caused him to follow the Courts and to pleade causes: which course, as it appeareth he continued long, yea, euen in <hi>Caius</hi> time, being greatly fauoured and famed for his eloquence.<note place="margin">
            <hi>Epist.</hi> 49.</note> Vndoubtedly there are no Philosophicall treatises ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, that were his before that time.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="4" type="chapter">
      <pb facs="14"/>
      <head>CHAP. IIII. His honours and ciuill life.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Is father likewise perswaded him to affect gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to make sute for honours: he therefore first of all was Threa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>orer, in obtayning which office, hee acknowledgeth what helpes his Aunt had procured him:<note place="margin">
            <hi>Cons. ad Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. cap.</hi> 16.</note> She (saith he) tried all her friends in my suite for the Threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ership, and she that scarcely would endure to be confer'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, or publikely saluted in my behalfe, ouercame her modestie by her loue towards me. What woman this was, and what husband she had thou shalt learne by my notes: but when he was Threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorer I doe not certainly know: for his yeares, it might haue been vnder <hi>Tiberius,</hi> or it might be vnder <hi>Caius,</hi> but I intend not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine the matter. This had I rather say, that by <hi>Agripinals</hi> meanes presently after his exile he got and exercised the Praetorship. For thus saith <hi>Tacitus: Agripina</hi> got at her husbands hand, not onely a release of <hi>Annaeus Senecaes</hi> banishment, but also the Praetorship, supposing that it would be pleasing to the common sort by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the fame of his studie,<note place="margin">12. <hi>Annalls.</hi>
         </note> and to the end that <hi>Domitius</hi> childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood might be the better ripened by such a master, and that hee might vse his counsailes, vnder hope to attaine the soueraigntie. Thou see<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t that hee was suddenly made Praetor, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>earest what praises and endowments <hi>Tacitus</hi> vnfainedly honoureth him with. The loue of the commons was gotten by that meanes. Because <hi>Seneca</hi> now was accompanied with euery mans good words and fauours, by reason of the excellencie of his studies, and was desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous that vnder such and so great a Master, that their <hi>Domitius</hi> should be brought vp, and should be addressed (and herein note his ciuill prudence) both to obtaine the Empire, and to gouern it. He was therefore Praetor the yeare of the Citie DCCII. and was hee not afterwards Consull? The Law bookes affirme the same to <hi>S.C. Trebellian,</hi> as <hi>Vlpian.</hi> In the time of <hi>Nero</hi> in the Octaues of the Calends of September, when <hi>Annaeus Seneca</hi> and <hi>Trebellius Maximus</hi> were Consuls, it was made irreuocable. The same is written in the elements of <hi>Iustinians</hi> institutions. But they that made our holy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>daies, make these substitute Consuls (for ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie they were not) the yeare of the Citie DCCCXV. which should
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb facs="15"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb facs="15"/>
         <pb facs="16"/>
be the yeare, and some few moneths before <hi>Senecaes</hi> death. Some men perhaps will doubt of the whole matter, because <hi>Ausonius</hi> in his thankesgiuing s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ith openly, The rich man <hi>Seneca,</hi> but yet not Consull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Seneca</hi> likewise himselfe neuer maketh mention of this honour, although he wrote many Epistles at that time. I answer, for <hi>Ausonius</hi> it is to be vnderstood, that it seemed to him to bee an ordinarie Consulate; for our <hi>Seneca,</hi> that a silence is no deniall. Furthermore, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> adde this likewise, that the Chronicle-makers seem to haue digested their relations badly; for in that yeare vndoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly he was not. For see here in the very beginning of the yeare, how <hi>Tacitus</hi> maketh mention of his cold entertainement by <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro,</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>Annal.</hi> 14.</note> and how his detractors had diuersly iniuried him, and how he himselfe with a confident Oration came vnto the Prince, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired <hi>viaticum,</hi> and resigned his substance: yet <hi>Caesar</hi> permitted it not, &amp; yet <hi>Seneca</hi> from that time forward, as <hi>Cornelius</hi> saith, chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the prescripts of his former power, forbiddeth intercourse of Courtiers, auoydeth attendants, is sildome seene in the Citie, and as if ouer-tired with sickenes, keepeth himselfe at home, intending onely the studie of wisedome. These are no proper actions of a new made Consull or a Candidate, and his death that followed presently afterwards, forbiddeth vs to consent hereunto. But what was it that learned men suspected thus? That which <hi>Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> writeth in that yeare was done by the consent of the Senate, lest a fained adoption should in any sort further a publique Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, &amp; least in vsurping heritages, it should profit. But this apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth nothing to that of <hi>Trebellian,</hi> it hath another reference: if a man doe examine those things likewise that are in <hi>Tacitus.</hi> I therefore consent that he was Consull, but in another and a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time, the certaintie whereof I will not set downe. But the perpetuall honour of this man, and how hee was both the teacher and gouernour of a Prince, vndoubtedly worthy as long as he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted himselfe to his counsailes and admonitions<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Tacitus</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealeth not, and nameth two, to whom the Prince was well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined for his owne profite. Murthers had preuailed except <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Burrus</hi> and <hi>Annaeus Seneca</hi> had withstood them. These were the Gouernours of the Emperour in his yonger yeares, and con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>formed in that equall societie they had in gouernement, and in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rs sorts they had equall power. <hi>Burrus</hi> in his cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ge, in regard of warlike affaires and seueritie in his manners. <hi>Seneca</hi> in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of eloquence and honest affabilitie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> assisting one another,
<pb facs="16"/>
whereby they might more easily restraine the tender yeares of the Prince if he despised vertue, by granting him ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sures<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> O laud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble endeuour and consent, which is too ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e in Court, where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one for the most part will desire to be so eminent that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sireth no second. But to <hi>Seneca.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div n="5" type="chapter">
      <head>CHAP. V. His priuate life, his wife, his children, his banishment.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether he acted any other thing in publique, I know not;<note place="margin">
            <hi>Consola<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. ad Helu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>am. cap.</hi> 21.</note> but priuately I find, or at least wise I collect, that during his yonger yeares hee was in Egypt vpon this occasion; because his Vncle was P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ect t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ere: for he writeth of his Aunt to his Mother, Shee will shew th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, whereof I was an eye-witnesse. An eye witnesse? he ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore associated his Aunt in that Nauigation (of which he speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in that place) when as his Aunt returned from Egypt. And how could this be, except he himselfe likewise had beene in AE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt? Vndoubtedly it was thus: and this is the cause why he cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously intermixeth many things of AEgypt and Nilus, especially in his bookes of Naturall Questions.<note place="margin">
            <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 17.</note> Perchance he trau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>iled out of AEgypt into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ndia by the red Sea, and therefore would hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ndia, vpon that which was written by <hi>Pliny.</hi> But now he married a wife at Rome, which though it be vncertain to be so, yet the reason he had children do approue it: for he maketh mention of <hi>Marcus</hi> a wanton lad, with much praise and affection to his mother <hi>Heluia:</hi> neyther is it to be doubted but that he was his sonne, at least wise his owne verses will approue it, where a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst his vowes,
<q>
            <l>So may yong <hi>Marcus,</hi> who with pleasing prate</l>
            <l>Contents vs now, in eloquent debate,</l>
            <l>Prouoke his vncles, though in being yong</l>
            <l>In wit, in wisdome, and in fluent tong.</l>
         </q>
For should I giue way to those who attribute this to <hi>Marcus Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus,</hi> I finde no reason for it; yet maketh hee no mention o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> his
<pb facs="17"/>
former wife: not in these books, I confesse; what then? nor o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> his brother <hi>Annaeus Mela</hi> by name, had hee not therefore a brother? Notwithstanding thou art to consider whether thou vnderstand not this by his first wife: Thou knowest that <hi>Harpastes</hi> my wiues foole remained as an hereditary burthen in my family:<note place="margin">3. <hi>de Ira. c.</hi> 1.</note> what wife? his first wife? for the books of Anger seem to be written in a place well known to vs. But he married <hi>Paulina</hi> after his exile, a woman of great Nobility, which, as I tell thee, married him when he was old &amp; powerful in the Court: which very thing <hi>Dio</hi> likewise, or whatsoeuer he were in <hi>Dion,</hi> thought good to obiect against <hi>Dion</hi>; which is, that being s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ept in yeares he had married a yong wench. Such were both of them, and <hi>Seneca</hi> himselfe, testifieth it. This said I to my <hi>Paulina</hi> which commends my health vnto me:<note place="margin">
            <hi>Epist.</hi> 104.</note> it came into my mind, that in this old man there is a yong one that is forborn. A yong one? he meanes <hi>Paulina</hi> her selfe: for vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly she loued her husband, as there in many places he boasteth, and that vnfainedly, which she expressed in his death, when in as farre as in her lay, she sought to accompanie his soule with hers. Hereafter we shall see it. And these were his wiues. The rest of his life quiet, and without offence, excepting onely that grieuous accident of his exile. For vnder <hi>Claudius</hi> the first yeare of his reigne, when <hi>Iulia</hi> the daughter of <hi>Germanicus</hi> was accused of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterie (Gods and Goddesses by <hi>Messaline</hi>?) and was driuen her selfe into banishment: and <hi>Seneca,</hi> if he had beene one of the adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, was exiled and sent into Corsica; I will not say whether it were vpon a iust cause, I could wish it were not, and happily <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus</hi> with me, who when hee speaketh of his banishment. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi> was angrie with <hi>Claudius,</hi> it was supposed by reason of the iniurie that was done him. Note this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>niurie: hee therefore had receiued some. For who would otherwise be ignorant to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete the accusations of that impudent Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lot (I meane <hi>Messa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line</hi>) and that my sonne beast <hi>Claudius</hi>? For, for the most par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e they practised no mischiefe but against good and innocent persons. Hee liued about some eight yeares or thereabouts in exile, I, and constantly too; yea, if wee may beleeue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, happily intending onely the best st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>dies, and the wholsom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est meditations. For thus writeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e to his mother; That hee is blessed amongst those things which are wont to make other men wretched. And afterwards (but I pray thee obserue him) he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily Philosophieth, he addeth in the end, and rowseth himselfe;
<pb facs="17"/>
Conceiue what thou shouldest, thinke mee to be ioyfull and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dressed as it were in the best fortunes.<note place="margin">
            <hi>Cap.</hi> 4.</note> But they are the best, when as the minde, deuoide of all thought intendeth himselfe, and som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times delighteth himselfe in lighter studies, and somtimes moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth into the consideration of the nature of himselfe, &amp; the whole world being desirous of truth. O man, O honest wordes, which the Author of <hi>Octauia's</hi> Tragedie would imitate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> for it was not he (God forbid) in these Verses in the person of <hi>Seneca</hi>;
<q>
            <l>Farre better lay I hid: remoued farre</l>
            <l>From enuies stormes amidst the Corsicke shores,</l>
            <l>Whereas my minde was farre from any iarre,</l>
            <l>Fixt on my studies, not on earthly powres:</l>
            <l>O what content had I? (For neuer nature</l>
            <l>Mother of all things, Mistris of each creature</l>
            <l>Could grant no more) then to behold the heauen,</l>
            <l>The Sunnes true motion, and the Planets seuen.</l>
         </q>
These are better, yea, farre truer then he hath written in his conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latorie booke to <hi>Polybius,</hi> ouer-basely and humbly. And is it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible that our <hi>Seneca</hi> should write it? Oftentimes haue I doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it, and almost durst forsweare it. Howsoeuer, he was a man, and happily that writing was enlarged and published by his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and happily they corrupted it: yet note this in <hi>Senecaes</hi> words abouesaid; That there he delighted himselfe in more slighter stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies likewise, which I suppose should be Poesie: &amp; amongst them is <hi>Medea,</hi> which I am halfe assured was written in his exile, at such time as <hi>Claudius</hi> conquered Britanie; and therfore made he choice of that argument of <hi>Iason,</hi> that he might intermixe somewhat of the Ocean that was subdued. Is it possible that those verses in the <hi>Chorus</hi> should haue relation to any but <hi>Claudius</hi>?</p>
      <q>
         <l>Spare me, O gods, I doe intreat for grace,</l>
         <l>Long let him liue secure that hath subdude.</l>
      </q>
      <p>And againe,
<q>
            <l>The Seas—</l>
            <l>Enough already O you gods, you haue</l>
            <l>Reuengd you on the Seas, now spare the Powre.</l>
         </q>
         <pb facs="18"/>
Which he applied to <hi>Cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>dius,</hi> although he were liuing, and will haue the gods to spare the god in his Poeticall fiction.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="6" type="chapter">
      <head>CHAP. VI. His riches, his granges, his lands, his vsurie.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt presently after he returned from his exile, hee grew a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into reputation, being both at that time, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his aduancement in Court plentifully enstated, for his father had left him rich:<note place="margin">
            <hi>Cap.</hi> 2.</note> neyther oweth he all his wealth to his industrie and forwardnesse. Hereupon to his mother; Thou being the daughter of a family, didst freely bestow thy bounty on thy welthy children. And he praised her liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie the rather, as he saith, because she bestowed it on her wealthy sons, and not such as were needie. This before he came to Court; but when he liued there he got mightie riches, or rather admitted them which thrust themselues vpon him before he sought them. For he got much by the Princes beneficence; for thus speaketh he vnto <hi>Nero</hi> in our <hi>Tacitus</hi>: Thou (said hee) hast giuen mee great grace, and innumerable treasure; so that oftentimes I my selfe turn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t oftentimes by my selfe: where is that minde which contented himselfe with a little? Doth he plant such Gardens, and doth he walke about these mannors without the Citie? and is hee stored with so many acre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> of land, and with such mightie vsu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ie? Note Gardens, Mannors, Granges, Fields, and Vsurie, &amp; all these boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully and abundantly. Will you heare <hi>Tacitus</hi> words once more, but from another mans mouth, and in another sense:<note place="margin">
            <hi>Lib.</hi> 14.</note>
         <hi>Senecaes</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumners, saith he, accuse him of diuers crimes; as that he, as yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased his mighty riches, which were raised aboue any priuate fortune, that he won and drew the Citizens hearts vnto him, and as it were exceeded the Prince likewise in the annuity of his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and the magnificence of his Mannor houses. And <hi>Suillus</hi> in the same <hi>Tacitus</hi> expresseth the measure of his riches likewise, with what wisedome, with what precepts of the Philosophers during th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>se foure yeares that he was in the Princes fauour, had hee got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten three thousand <hi>HSS.</hi> that in Rome, whole Testaments and Inheritances were taken and got holde on by his cunning and search;<note place="margin">
            <hi>Lib.</hi> 13.</note> that Italy and the Prouinces were exhausted by his imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surable
<pb facs="18"/>
vsurie. His estate amongst vs should be seuentie fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth thousand crownes. These riches were almost regall, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse it, but I condemne that which he annexeth, that it was gotten by vnlawfull meanes and deceit. Before he came to Court, as I said, he had a great reuenue, and what wonder is it that he increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the same in so mightie a Court, and so great felicity of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane state? But hee saith likewise that Italie and the Prouinces were exhausted by his vsurie: his meaning is, that he had money at vse in diuers places, and I suspect it likewise in AEgypt. This ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I by his Epistle,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Epist.</hi> 77.</note> wherein hee writeth that the Alexandrian Fleete suddenly arriued, and that all men ranne vnto the hauen and to the shore; but I, saith he, in this generall hastie running of all men, found great pleasure in my slackenesse, that being to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue my Letters from my friends I made not hast to knowe in what estate my affaires stood in that place, and what they had brought. For this long time I haue neyther wonne or lost any thing. He had there his Brokers or Factors, who followed his businesse; it was therefore in some great stocke of money or in lands. For to haue possessions beyond the Seas was no new mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in that age wherin he liued, and in so great abundance. Verily <hi>Dion</hi> amongst the causes of the warre in Brittaine, reckoneth this vp likewise, That when as <hi>Seneca</hi> had vpon great interest trusted the Brittaines with foure hundreth <hi>HSS.</hi> which in our recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning amounteth to the sum of ten hundreth thousand crownes: he called in for that whole summe of money at one time. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he spake this truely or no I know not; for euery wayes he was a mortall and professed enemy of our <hi>Seneca.</hi> Yet telleth hee no vntruth, for there likewise had hee money. Why now Gardens and houses of pleasure? he had diuers, and differently bewtified. <hi>Iuuenall</hi> toucheth it, The Gardens of most wealthy <hi>Seneca.</hi> Hee himse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>fe likewise maketh mention of his houses; Nomentanum, Albanum, and Baianum, and without question hee had manie. He likewise had a house within the Citie, which continued the name for many yeares after, and was called <hi>Senecaes</hi> house in the Region <hi>P. Victor.</hi> His houshold-stuffe also was enuied at, and <hi>Dio</hi> obiecteth, that he had fiue hundreth tables of Cedar with I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorie feete, all of them alike and equall. This was a great matter if truely great (for this alwaies ought we to be warie in <hi>Dions</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections) that he had so many tables, whereof any one is vsually taxed and prised at the rate of an ample possession: for they must
<pb facs="19"/>
not haue beene so choice and so rare; but what if they were not? I denie not but that it was the custome of dissolute and lauish men to haue such: for thus speaketh <hi>Martial</hi> of one of these:
<q>
            <l>A hundreth Moorish tables stand about,</l>
            <l>With Libique teeth, and golden plates do crackle</l>
            <l>Vpon our beddes.</l>
         </q>
For in great banquets they set a Table before euery seuerall man, (which is elsewhere to be noted) and to this end therefore they had diuers. I doe not therefore say I denie or doubt hereof. But because <hi>Seneca</hi> himselfe toucheth and reprehendeth this madnesse oftentimes, yea, at such time as he was in Court, and in his olde age, in those bookes of Benefits which he then wrote. What doth he not in his booke of Tranquilitie, about the beginning, openly denie that he tooke no pleasure in those Tables that were conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous through varietie of spots. Nor was wont to vse them? Wonderfull is this impudence, in a matter so euident and obiect to the eyes of that age, to dissemble or to lie so openly. I cannot think it; especially if <hi>Dion</hi> report the same, or any other to whom <hi>Dion</hi> assigneth this office. For in another place haue I noted, that these things seeme to be deduced and vrged against him in some inuectiue Oration; and there by the way haue I acquit him of the crime of his riches, which any man may reade if he please. But rather let him reade <hi>Seneca</hi> himselfe, who about this time publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his booke of Blessed life, in which his proiect is to defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe from those aspersions, wherewith his enemies would haue attainted him. O excellent, O wise booke, and more allowed in this behalfe was the reproofe, that was the meane to bring it to light.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="7" type="chapter">
      <pb facs="19"/>
      <head>CHAP. VII. His Manners, and first his Abstinence, his Truth, his Safetie, and Pietie.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt his very manners refu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e this obiection of his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and iustifie his vse, and not ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>se of them. For what hath he offended in pride, excesse, and pompe? Let them tell vs it, and wee will be silent. What was he happily lauish, eyther in his diet or feasting? Let vs heare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe professing openly; When as I heard <hi>Attalus</hi> declayming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst vices,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Epist.</hi> 108.</note> errours, and the infirmities of life, oftentimes ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e I had compassion of mankinde, and haue bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>ed that hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> sublimed and raised aboue human<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>each. When he beganne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> traduce our pleasures, to praise a chaste bodie, a sober <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>able, a pure minde; not onely from vnlawfull pleasures, but al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> superfluous, I tooke a liking to temper mine appetite and bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> Of these instructions some haue sithence dwel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> with me my <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillius</hi>; for I came with a great alac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>itie to all thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Afterwards being reduced to a ciuill life, I stored vp som<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> few of these <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hy good beginnings. Hereupon for all my life time after, I renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced all Oysters and Mushromes. Euer since for my whole life time I haue abstayned from iniunction; since that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>me my sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke hath wanted wine, neyther haue I euer since, vouch sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ed to bath my selfe. Where was euer any such frugalitie in any other place, or by what name is it called? And this haue I written of, in my commendation of <hi>Seneca,</hi> so let vs no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> repea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e it he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>re, now as touching the rest of his life it was both serious and seuere.<note place="margin">11. <hi>de Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
         </note> The Court corrupted him not, neyther inclined he v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>o flatterie, a vice almost familiar, and allied to such places. No: hee vnto <hi>Nero.</hi> Suffer me to stay here a little longer with thee, not to flatter thine eares, for this is not my custome: I had rather offend thee by truth, then please thee by flatterie. And beeing now readie to die, in <hi>Tacitus</hi> hee willed them to make knowne to the Prince,<note place="margin">15. <hi>Annal.</hi> 3. <hi>de Ira.</hi>
         </note> That his minde was neuer inclined vnto flatrerie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d that this was knowne to no man better then to <hi>Nero</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o had more
<pb facs="20"/>
often made vse of <hi>Senecaes</hi> libertie then hee had experience of his seruitude. Moreouer, what exaction and examination of his manners and life? Againe he himselfe, I vse this power, and daily examine my selfe when the light is out and my wife is silent, which is now priuie to my custom. I examin the whole day that is past by my selfe, and consider both mine actions and wordes. I hide nothing from my selfe, I let nothing slip: for why should I feare any of mine errours? When as I may say, See that thou doe this no more, for this time I pardon thee. Can the studie of wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome appeare eyther more greatly or more cleerely? Finally, how often appeareth his pietie and submission towards God? I will set downe one thing that I gathered from him.<note place="margin">
            <hi>Epist.</hi> 96.</note> If thou beleeuest me any waies, when I discouer my most inward affections to thee, I am thus formed in all occurrents, which seeme either diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult or dangerous. I obey not God, but I assent vnto him; I fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him from my heart, and not of necessitie. There shall no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing euer befall mee that I will grieue at, or change my counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for when it happeneth. I will pay no tribute vnwillingly, and many such like obserued by me in my Manuduction or Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siologie. Yea, some of that vnstained pietie that <hi>Tertullian</hi> and the Auncients call him Ours. I haue in my Fragments set downe some of his counsailes, let them make vse of them. Furthermore, <hi>Otho Frigensis</hi> affirmed, that <hi>Lucius Seneca</hi> was not onely worthie to be reputed a Philosopher, but also a Christian. And for these his eminent vertues sake, euen in that age there was a great good opinion held of him, yea and they destinated him to the Empire. <hi>Tacitus</hi> plainly writeth that this was set abroach,<note place="margin">15. <hi>Annal.</hi>
         </note> that the Empire should be deliuered to <hi>Senecaes</hi> hands, as to one that was guiltles, being chosen, by reason of the excellency of his vertues, to the highest dignitie. O Rome thou wert vnworthy of this felicitie; neyther did God respect thee so well otherwise.
<q>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Iuuenal Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note>If all the people might haue leaue to speake,</l>
            <l>What one of them (how desolate soeuer)</l>
            <l>Would feare or doubt to honor <hi>Seneca</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Farre more then <hi>Nero.</hi>
            </l>
         </q>
Yet some there are that doubt of the realitie of his vertues, and thinke them rather words and ostentation. Did he not therefore
<pb facs="20"/>
in his death make it manifest how slightly hee esteemed all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane things, how he addicted himselfe to God?</p>
   </div>
   <div n="8" type="chapter">
      <head>CHAP. VIII. His Manfull and Constant life, set downe out of <hi>Tacitus.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND let vs see the commoditie thereof, but from whence should we gather it rather then from <hi>Tacitus,</hi> the most faithfullest of all other Writers? Beholde, I set thee downe his owne wordes: Hereafter followeth the slaughter of <hi>Annaeus Seneca,</hi> most pleasing to the Prince, not because he had manifestly found him guiltie of treason, but to the end he might confound him by the sword, since his attempt in poysoning him, so badly succeeded. For onely <hi>Natalis</hi> discouered no lesse. That he was sent to <hi>Seneca</hi> at such time as hee was sicke to visite him, and to complaine why he barred <hi>Piso</hi> of accesse vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, that it would be better for them if they should exercise their friendship with familiar entercourse. And that <hi>Seneca</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, that mutuall discourse and often conference would bee profitable for neyther of them both, yet that his safetie depended on <hi>Pisoes</hi> securitie. This was <hi>Granius Siluanus,</hi> the Tribune of the Praetoriall Band, commanded to relate vnto him, and to enquire whether he knew these speeches of <hi>Natalis,</hi> and acknowledged his owne answers. He eyther by chance or wittingly had retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that day out of Campania, and remained in a house of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of his in the Suburbes, aboue foure miles off. Thither came the Tribune about the euening, and beset the Village with a troupe of his souldiers. There discouered he vnto him whilst hee sate at supper with <hi>Pompeia Paulina</hi> his wife, and two other of his friends, what the Emperours commaund was. <hi>Seneca</hi> answered, that <hi>Natalis</hi> was sent vnto him, and that he complained in <hi>Pisoes</hi> behalfe, that he had bin debarred from visiting him, &amp; that he by reason of his infirmity, &amp; loue of his quiet, had excused himselfe. But why hee should preferre a priuate mans securitie before his owne, hee had no cause; nor that his minde was inclined to flatterie, and that the same was best knowne vnto <hi>Nero,</hi> who had
<pb facs="21"/>
more oftentimes made proofe of <hi>Senecaes</hi> libertie then seruice. When as this answer was related by the Tribune, in the presence of <hi>Poppea</hi> and <hi>Tigillinus,</hi> which were inward Counsailors to this mercilesse Prince, he asked him whether <hi>Seneca</hi> had prepared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe for a voluntarie death. Then did the Tribune confirme, that he discouered no signe of feare, nor appearance of dismay, eyther in his words or countenance. He is therefore commanded to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, and to tell him of his death. <hi>Fabius Rusticus</hi> reporteth, that he returned not by the same way he came, but that he stept aside to <hi>Fenuis</hi> the Praefect, and told him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> what <hi>Caesar</hi> had commanded, and asked his counsaile whether he should obey him, and that he was aduised by him to execute his charge, which was the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall cowardlinesse of them all. For both <hi>Siluanus</hi> was one of the Conspirators, and increased their hainous offences, to whose reuenge he had consented; yet spared hee both his speech and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, and sent in one of the Centurions to <hi>Seneca,</hi> to signifie vnto him the fatall sentence. He no waies dismayed hereat, called for the tables of his Testament, which being denied him by the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion, turning himselfe towards his friends, hee testified vnto them, that since it was not permitted him to remunerate their kindnesse towards him, yet testified he, that he left them yet that which of all others he esteemed most worthy, namely, the image of his life, wherof if they were mindfull, they should carrie away the fame of good learning, and of so constant friendship. And therewithall recalleth their teares, and calleth them to constancie now by speeches, now by expostulations, after a more intended manner; asking them, where are the precepts of wisedome? where that premeditated resolution, which you haue studied for so many yeares against imminent dangers? For to whom was <hi>Neroes</hi> crueltie vnknowne? Neyther remained there any thing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the murther both of his mother and brother, but to annex the death of his Gouernour and Master? When as he had in generall said these or such like words, he embraced his wife; and hauing somewhat tempered her against the present feare, he prayeth and intreateth her to moderate her griefe, and not to make it continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. But in contemplation of her life that was vertuously ledde, to endure the lacke of her husband with honest solaces. She con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwise alleaged that her selfe was sentenced to die also, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth for the executioners helpe. Then <hi>Seneca</hi> loath to obscure her glorie, and louing her intirely, least he should leaue her to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries
<pb facs="21"/>
of others, whom he so deerely loued, said, I haue shewed thee the proportions and images of life, but thou hadst rather haue the glorie of de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> I will not enuy thy example. Let the constancie be equall in vs both in this so short a death, but thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne will be farre greater. After which wordes, both of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ut their veines at on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> time. <hi>Seneca</hi> in that his bodie was old and leane, by reason of his sparing diet, and that by this meanes his bloud flowed more slowly; cut the veines of his legges and hams likewise. And being wearied with cruell torments, lest by his paine he should weaken his wiues courage, and he by beholding her torments should fall into some impatience, he perswaded her to step aside into another chamber. And in the last moment being no waies disfurnished of his eloquence, calling his writers about him, he deliuered manie things, which being discouered to the world in his owne wordes, I intend not to alter. But <hi>Nero</hi> that had conceiued no priuate hatred against <hi>Paulina,</hi> and being affraid lest th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> odiousnesse of his crueltie should increase the more, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> her death to be hindered. By the exhortations of the souldiers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>er slaues and bond-men binde vp her armes, and stop the bloud, the matter being yet vncertaine whether it was with her consent. For amongst the common sort (who are readiest to speake the worst) there wanted not some that beleeued, that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time that shee feared that <hi>Nero</hi> was implacable, shee sought to accompanie her husband in the same of his death: but when more apparant hopes were offered, that then she was ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with the sweetnesse of life, whereunto shee added a fewe yeares after, with a laudable memorie towards her husband. But her face and other partes of her bodie were growne so pale and discoloured, that it easily appeared that her vital spirits were much spent. In the meane while <hi>Seneca</hi> seeing the protraction and slownesse of his death, besought <hi>Statius Annaeus,</hi> a man well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued vnto him, both for his faith in friendship, and skill in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke, to hast and bring him that poison which in times past was prouided, and by which they were put to death who were by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like iudgement condemned amongst the Athenians; and hauing it brought vnto him he drunke it, in vaine, by reason that his lims were already colde, and his body shut vp against the force of the venome. At last he entered into a Bath of hot water, besprinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling those his slaues that stood next about him, saying that he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vp that liquor to <hi>Ioue</hi> the deliuerer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Then put into the Bath,
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb facs="22"/>
         <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
            <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb facs="22"/>
         <pb facs="23"/>
and stifled with the vapour thereof, hee was buried without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny solemnitie of his Funerall: for so had hee set it downe in his Will. Euen then when as being very rich and mighty, he dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed of his last Will. Hitherto <hi>Tacitus.</hi> Neither will I repent my selfe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> I insist lightly, and examine and illustrate his sayings: He saith, that this slaughter of his was most pleasing to the Prince. For of long time he was aggrieued against this Master &amp; Teacher of his in goodnesse and equitie, and his intent was to shake off that Raine of reuerence once whereby he was restrained against his will, by cutting him off; yet had he otherwise sworne, as <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius</hi> witnesseth: Hee compelled <hi>Seneca</hi> his Master, saith hee, to chuse his death, although when he oftentimes sought for a <hi>via<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum</hi> at his hands, and surrendred vp all his goods vnto him: hee had solemnly sworne that he was suspected without cause, and that he had rather die then that hee would hurt him. He swore, that is, he deluded the gods also: hee saith, When as his intent to poyson him succeeded not: for he had attempted it; for so saith the same <hi>Tacitus</hi> in a former place, Some deliuered poy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>on vnto <hi>Seneca</hi> by <hi>Neroes</hi> command, prepared by the handes of one of his free men, called <hi>Cleonicus,</hi> but that it was auoyded by <hi>Seneca,</hi> by the discouerie of his Libertine, or through his owne feare, whilst he sustained his life with a spare diet with wilde apples, and if he were athirst with running water. He goeth forward: Or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it; as if he had knowledge of the conspiracie, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed time. Likewise, he returned out of Campania, from some Lordship of his there. And there truely oftentimes before his death liued he solitarie, and in that place wrote many of his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles to <hi>Lucillius.</hi> Foure miles off, in some Mannor of his likewise, what was it <hi>Nomentanum</hi>? This did <hi>Xitho Polentinus</hi> write, but vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon meere coniecture, as I thinke. Neither doth <hi>Tacitus</hi> admit it, who speaketh of some foure miles off the Citie; but <hi>Nomentum</hi> is at least twelue miles off. No signes of feare. Behold a death both worthy of a Philosopher and a Stoicke, which those things that follow commend. The image of his life: if <hi>Seneca</hi> I pray you were so absurd a fellow, as <hi>Dion</hi> speaketh, should this be spoken of his life in the shutting vp? Would hee thus dallie and deceiue his friends, and delude his familiars? Sometimes with speech, that is, gently and familiarly, Being hardned against present feare, I write it not againe rashly, yet some man may doubt, should it not be <hi>Molitam</hi> that she was mollified, hauing relation to his wife?
<pb facs="23"/>
That which followeth seemeth to inferre the same, when hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth her to temper her sorrow; and that which he annexeth: Thou seest, saith he, the portra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ture of life. These, and diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are <hi>Senecaes</hi> owne words, or very like vnto them, which were extant and well knowne, as presently after hee saith: his aged bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. By my reckoning he was some threscore and three, or foure yeares olde. For that he was not elder, <hi>Neroes</hi> wordes to <hi>Seneca</hi> conuince, not spoken long time before that in <hi>Tac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>tus.</hi> But thou art both ripe in yeares, and sufficient for affaires, and the fruite of them, which thou canst not truely speake of the elder. Calling his writers about him. O man. O mightie minde? To dictate that when he was a dying that might helpe posteritie. For it is not to be doubted but that they were such, and meere precepts both of constancie and wisedome. The argument is, because they were published; which should not be except they had been excellent. And because they were published, <hi>Tacitus</hi> omits them. O improuidently done? O that we likewise had but a touch of these Swan-like songs. A Bath of hot water: hee meaneth some Bathing-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ub, and then first vsed he colde water when he should vse it no more. Carried into his Bath; that is, into his Stoue or drie Bath, as I thinke: for hee sheweth that by the vapour and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimonie of the heate, he was strangled. Euen then when he was most rich and mightie: this is somewhat wherin <hi>Tacitus</hi> seemeth to carpe at him, yet, if I conceiue him rightly, <hi>Tacitus</hi> meant his funerall, and that he forbad the solemnities thereof, but how in that He made his last Will. What, would <hi>Ner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> haue broken his Testament? who happily was appointed heire of the greatest part thereof, and would suffer himselfe to loose nothing through neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence. Or doth he touch <hi>Senecaes</hi> parsimonie herein? But dead wordes passe not farre. Another man may finde it.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="9" type="chapter">
      <head>CHAP. IX. His body, his sickenesses, his forme.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue ended, except it please you that I write somewhat of his bodie: for men delight, if I may so speake it, to take notice of the habitations and receptacles of great wits: his bodie from his childehood was but weake. This saith he of his Aunt, after he was brought into the Citie. By
<pb facs="24"/>
her pious and motherly care,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Cons. ad Hel cap.</hi> 16. <hi>Epist.</hi> 54.</note> after I had beene long time sicke I recouered my health. And in a certaine Epistle: Sicknesse had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me a long safe conduct, and suddenly inuaded me. In what kinde, sayest thou? And not without cause doest thou aske mee this, since that there is not any one that is vnknowne to me. But to one kinde of sickenesse I seeme as it were destinated; which why I should call by a Greeke name I know not, for it may aptly enough be called <hi>Wheosing</hi> or <hi>Astine.</hi> And presently after he addeth, All the incommodities or dangers of the bodie haue past by me. Behold an olde man well exercised, when likewise being a young man, was exercised with Distillations and Rhumes, by meanes whereof he seemed to be inclined to a consumption. Himselfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: That thou art troubled with often distillations &amp; agues: it grieues me the more, because I haue had proof of that kind of sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, which in the beginning I contemned;<note place="margin">
            <hi>Epist.</hi> 78.</note> for at first my youth could weare out the iniurie, &amp; oppose it selfe boldly against infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, at last I was masterd, and was brought to that passe, that I my selfe was consumed by distillations. I was brought to an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame leanenesse, and oftentimes had I a minde to shorten my daies, but my carefull and louing fathers olde yeares restrained me. He writeth expresly enough of his leanenesse and consump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Neither is it to be wondred at, that <hi>Caligula</hi> was so perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by a woman: for <hi>Dio</hi> writeth, When as <hi>Seneca</hi> had worthily and happily handled a certain cause in the Senate, that this Prince waxed mad red with anger, who onely would seeme to be elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, and bethought himselfe of taking away <hi>Senecaes</hi> life, which he had done if one of his Concubins had not tolde him this, That in vaine prepared he a death for him that was alreadie dying, and was spent with a consumption. He gaue credite to her; and this was the meanes of <hi>Senecaes</hi> safetie. So true is that which he (what was a looker on?) wrote. Many mens sickenesse deferred their death, and it was a meanes of their securitie, that they seemed rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to die. But till his last houre he had but a drie and decayed bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, why wonder we when either it was thorow his infirmities or his studies?<note place="margin">
            <hi>Epist.</hi> 45.</note> And <hi>Tacitus</hi> likewise addeth a third cause, That his bodie was attenuated by a slender diet. And that it was not bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, <hi>Seneca</hi> himselfe expresseth in another place, That thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirest my bookes,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Epist.</hi> 104.</note> I doe not therefore thinke my selfe more elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, no more then I should iudge my selfe faire because thou requirest my picture. He toucheth that he was not, and that i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage,
<pb facs="24"/>
which is discouered of him by <hi>Fuluius Vrsinus,</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 7</note> sheweth not a countenance worthy that minde; yet confirmed he his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, though weake, with more harder exercises, as in tilling the fields, and in digging of Vineyards, whereof he maketh mention in a certaine Epistle of his, and in his naturall Questions, where he called himselfe A diligent digger of Vineyards, and generally likewise of Gardens,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Epist.</hi> 112.</note> which he termeth his cunning.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="10" type="chapter">
      <head>CHAP. X. Those bookes of his that are extant.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hus of the body onely; neyther had we any fruite by it, but great from his minde, and let vs see them by an <hi>Index.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>His Verses and Poems, which vndoubtedly and plen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ifully he wrote, he himselfe sheweth that he penned them in his exile:<note place="margin">
            <hi>Lib.</hi> 14.</note> and <hi>Tacitus</hi> then likewise when he was stept in yeares, and liued in Court. For thus do his calumners obiect against him to <hi>Nero</hi>; For they obiected against him that hee got the praise of eloquence to himselfe only, and wrote verses very often, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ter that he knew that <hi>Nero</hi> was in loue with them.</p>
      <p>Orations of Declamations he made many &amp; worthy one, yea, euen in the Senate, besides those which he wrote to the Prince, to be receiued likewise in the Senate; neyther doubt I but that the Edicts vnto the people, and the grauer Epistles were written or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctated by him.</p>
      <p>His booke of Earth-quake, which, as he testifieth, he wrote when he was yong, in the sixt of his Naturall Questions, chap. 4 Thou shalt not want, for he hath handled the same matter againe in the same Questions.</p>
      <p>That of Matrimonie, whether it were a booke or an Epistle I know not, but S. <hi>Ierome</hi> citeth it against <hi>Iouinian, lib.</hi> I.</p>
      <p>His History or <hi>Compendium</hi> out of <hi>Lactant.</hi> the 7. and 15. Chap.</p>
      <p>His bookes of Superstition was vndoubtedly one of his best ones, S <hi>August.</hi> in his booke <hi>de Ciuitate Dei</hi> praiseth it, and culleth somewhat out of it, and <hi>Tertullian</hi> maketh mention thereof in <hi>Apologetico.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>His Dialogues, which <hi>Fabius</hi> nameth, and no more.</p>
      <p>His Morall books, <hi>Lactantius</hi> citeth them in his eleueth booke,
<pb facs="25"/>
         <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. and in other places, and <hi>Seneca</hi> himselfe in his hundreth and sixt Epistle in the beginning, and his Epistle 109. he wrote it in his later time, as it appeareth there. O worthy worke? And it grieues me that it is obscured.</p>
      <p>His bookes of Exhortations: for there were many of them, as may be gathered out of <hi>Lactantius,</hi> and see our Fragments. Who thinketh that this likewise is not to be numbred amongst his best works? There are other, yet such that thou maist not confidently ascribe to this man, as his bookes of notes, which seeme rather to be his fathers. Likewise of Causes; for so an vnknowne Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cler among the Brittaines testifieth; He maketh mention of <hi>Seneca de Causis,</hi> wherein he saith that <hi>Cato</hi> defined the office of an Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor thus: An Orator is a good man that is, exercised in eloquence. But this belongeth to the father also, and they are the bookes of Controuersies; in the first booke wherof, and in the very Praeface thou shalt finde that this of <hi>Catoes</hi> is cited there: and except I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get my selfe, thou shalt finde it likewise in my Fragments, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though these smaller things doe not so much ouerslip me, as I suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to passe by me.</p>
      <p>But harke you Sir, make wee no reckoning of his Epistles to S. <hi>Paul</hi>?</p>
      <p>Those that are now extant are not so much worth, nay, it is most certaine, that they haue all of them the same authour, and that they were written, but by some scarce learned Clerke in our disgrace. He trauelleth and attempteth to speak Latin, whosoeuer it was that was the Author: did they not therefore write one vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another? <note n="a" place="margin">
            <hi>De scripto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib. ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticis.</hi>
         </note> S. <hi>Ierome,</hi>
         <note n="b" place="margin">
            <hi>Epistola</hi> 53 <hi>ad Maced. &amp; de Ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Dei. cap.</hi> 10.</note> S. <hi>Augustine,</hi> and Pope <hi>Linus</hi> more ancient then them both auerre it, and it is a passiue opinion. And <hi>Iohn</hi> of Salisbury likewise confidently writeth, They seeme to be foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish, who reuerence not him who, as it appeareth, deserued the familiaritie of the Apostle.<note place="margin">
            <hi>De passione Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i Pauli. Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car. cap.</hi> 13.</note> I therefore dare not wholly reiect and contemne this; it may be there were som, but others then these, if these<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> I required the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the best Fathers.</p>
   </div>
   <trailer>The end of <hi>Senecaes</hi> life, written by <hi>Lipsius.</hi>
   </trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>