<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117604_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13333</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23644</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117604</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The annales of Cornelius Tacitus. The description of Germanie</title>
                 <author>Tacitus, Cornelius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Norton, Bonham</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 <publisher>Hatfield, Arnold.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 271, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which most men alleage (courteous Reader) as a cause of publishing vnto the world their commendable endeuours; as commaundement of superiours, intreatie of friends, or such like: causes yeelding some excuse, if things well done by them needed any; that can I no way pretend: though no man hath iuster cause to inuent somewhat to excuse that, which (well knowing and confessing my owne insufficiencie) I should by no inducements haue beene drawen vnto. For I wanted not iudgement to know, that to performe this I vndertooke as I ought, was a matter beyond the compasse of my skill: yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthelesse my will ouercomming my owne iudgement and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son in vndertaking, I haue ventured my credit to the wide sea of common opinion, and dangerous censure; and knowing the best haue followed the woorst. A fault perhaps pardonlesse, in the rigoroust censure, and which bred in my selfe a long time distrust and feare: yet at last, incouraged by hope to find some milder iudges for my boldnes, I ventured this labour, and performed it thus meanely as thou seest: trusting the courteous Reader, if in ought I haue pleasured him, will affoord me his good woord for my good will, and in that I haue done amisse pardon, and a fauourable construction for my paines. And although in reason it seemeth, I should most of all feare the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of the learned (if any such vouchsafe to read this tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation) in regard they best can, and with quickest insight pearce into my want of skill, iudgement, and vnderstanding;
<pb facs="4"/>
yet in those is my greatest hope, because they be learned. Cause sufficient to feare no captious or carping constructions, as a propertie ill beseeming their good qualitie and education. I was well assured that he who best might, would take no further paines in this kind: nor hearing of any other which would, I thought some could be contented to haue it rather il done, than not at all. Friendly Reader, I craue pardon for my faults, and desire thou wouldest fauourably beare with my ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sights.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>