<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A iust defence of the late L. Bish. of Carliles honour, sent to the iudicious Reader.</title>
           <author>Blechynden, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117131_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11918</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22230</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117131</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A iust defence of the late L. Bish. of Carliles honour, sent to the iudicious Reader.</title>
                 <author>Blechynden, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Foure sermons preached at the court vpon seuerall occasions, by the late reuerend and learned diuine, Doctor Senhouse, L. Bishop of Carlile</title>
                 <author>Senhouse, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Dawlman (Dolman), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 141, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>A iust defence of the late L. Bish. of Carliles <hi>honour, sent to the iudicious Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hose ancient Fathers, on whom came daily<note n="a" place="margin">2. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>1.28.</note>
      <hi>the care of all the Churches,</hi> seeme no way better to perfect, no way so wel to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate that vniuersall care, as by wakening mens consciences with their quills,<note n="b" place="margin">Vid. T. Liv. l. 5. c. 47.</note> whose wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings saued the Capitoll, and<note n="c" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Clem. Alex. l. 1. strom. <hi>Euangelizo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu &amp; scriptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, &amp;c.</hi> 1. Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nold. l. de Rom. eccles. idol. <hi>Antipater cala mo vociferans</hi> Cael. l. 19. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>5.</note> speaking with their pennes vnto the whole Church; by causing their sanctified Labours, trauell, like so many holy pilgrims, to the liuing after their death, and in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to our Sauiours command,<note n="d" place="margin">Mark. 16.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>Goe,</hi> euen thus vpon their very hands, <hi>into all the world to preach the Gospel;</hi> that so by a strange kinde of midwifrie, they may assist at the new birth of many thousand soules they neuer knew, giue a spirituall deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to many members of the Church they neuer saw, after their owne bodies are gone downe with hope into the chambers of the graue, &amp; those taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles of flesh resolued into sacred dust; dust that lies expecting glory. Now that this religious inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of spreading himself into a Catholique good,
<pb facs="3"/> and communicating the diffusiue blessings of God, and great measures of his Grace vnto posteritie, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the late Lord Bishop of Carlile, Doctor <hi>Senhouse</hi> that was—I am vnto you an vnworthy witnesse, and yet a witnesse; who presume not to giue any other attribute to that neuer sufficiently honoured Name, all attributes that can fall from my dwarft expression, falling beneath those tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scendent parts, those vnparalleld gifts, those accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulated heapes of worth, which lodg'd in Doctor <hi>Senhouse;</hi> to whose<note n="d" place="margin">Vir calamo potens &amp; viri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis eloquentiae Hieronymus. <hi>Verul. hist. vit. &amp; mort. l. 1.</hi>
      </note> masculine and soule-begetting discourses, I had the happinesse of many yeeres accesses; and in his later times heard him often to my comfort professe, and I neuer heard him but to my comfort, that his Lectures on King <hi>Dauids</hi> first and second Psalmes, were by himselfe (for who else could doe it?) perfected for the presse; that so what was his Maiesties in the dutie of his originall seruice,<note n="f" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Clem. Alex. l. 1. Strom.</note> those children of his soules best strength, might now, when it ceaseth to be with him after the manner of men, inherit the fauour of kissing that great <hi>Masters</hi> sacred hand, and liuing in his Royall heart too, and in the harts of other Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. And therefore being casually enformed by a friend, that some Sermons of his Lordships, had more than seene the Presse, were ready to be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched againe to as many as would<note n="g" place="margin">Prou. 23.23.</note>
      <hi>buy the truth;</hi>
      <note n="h" place="margin">Cyprianus quotidie Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullianum lege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, notario Paulo dicens, da magistrum. <hi>Hieron. cat. vir. illust.</hi>
      </note> Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> call'd not oftner for his learned-strong-phras'd<note n="i" place="margin">Tertullianus homo doctissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus—haereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum errores fortiter contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. <hi>Trith. l. de script. eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siast.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Tertullian,</hi> than I enquired with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, for this my iudicious Christian <hi>Gamaliel;</hi> at whose reuerent feete I often sate, and learned to speake by silence; and now began to comfort that
<pb facs="3"/> losse with this fresh hope, that as<note n="k" place="margin">Dixit Chryso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomus se con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cionare nosse, quod D. Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum quotidie manu versaret. <hi>Keck. eccles. rhet. l. 2. c. 3.</hi>
      </note> S. <hi>Chrysostome</hi> attained to an admired excellency of preaching, by hauing the great Doctor of the Gentiles, blessed <hi>Paul,</hi> alwayes in his hand; so I might improue that gift to a conscionable discharge of my duty, by laying the laborious workes of this<note n="l" place="margin">Saluianus to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius orbis Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiani magister. <hi>Rittershus. vit. Saluian.</hi>
      </note> Master-Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, a Preacher that had<note n="m" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Greg. Nazianz. ep. 140 <hi>Romani voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant Proaresium</hi>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Cressol. theat. rhet. l. 1. c 9.</note> a royaltie of speech, and commanded all mens attentions, euer before mine eyes. But when I opened this booke with that reuerence which belonged vnto his name, and read with greedinesse a line, a leafe, or two, and more; I found the order of his worke so inuerted, the periods in some places so vnperfected, the sense by those periods so disioynted, the Greeke here and there where the sense was good, so negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, that I doe not say ignorantly, corrupted, and the entire frame so stript of those accessions vpon the by, which would haue giuen much satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to this learned age, the more learned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he once was in it; that whereas<note n="n" place="margin">Basil. Mag, ep. 1.</note> Saint <hi>Basil</hi> knew <hi>Nazianzenes</hi> Epistles, as men know the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of their friends, by their likenesse to their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; these seemed in many things so vnlike that Reuerend Father, whose name they beare, that at the first sight I hardly knew them to bee his. But when I viewed once, and againe<note n="o" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Basil. Mag. ep. 41.</note> these images of his soule, though in some places too much sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed, in some places much defaced, in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces set to a false light; yet my memorie perswaded mine eyes, that they were copies drawne from his originals. And least, induced by the like reasons, you might suspect them to be some spurious sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posititious
<pb facs="4"/> pieces christened with his Name, to giue them a fairer entertainement in the world and your good opinion; I craued so much leaue from Authoritie, as to prefixe this Epistle, and to let you know they are indeed his; but so his, as a man that's rob'd and wounded, &amp; hath his tongue taken out, is himselfe: For first, they want that which could best speake them his, that which next the efficacious cooperating of GODS Spirit with his owne, was the soule of euery Sermon, the strong and powerfull elocution of his diuiner Tongue; and this they must for euer want. Next, they are wounded many wayes; wounded grama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically in the words, wounded logically in the methode, and wounded intellectually in the sense; wounds which might easily haue been cured by his owne prescripts. Lastly, they are rob'd of those many rich apparellings, with which they might haue been compleately furnisht too, out of his owne Wardrope, and shall be supplyed in the next Impression, and those wounds some way healed by him, who hauing, with much difficultie, obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his owne Originals of these foure Sermons, will study nothing more in them, than the glory of his mercifull GOD, the seruice of his Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church, the honour of his Reuerend friend, and the satisfaction of his iudicious Reader.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thomas Blechynden.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>