<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Sprint, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117795_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12800</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23108</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117795</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Sprint, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cassander Anglicanus : shewing the necessity of conformitie to the prescribed ceremonies of our church, in case of depriuation. By Iohn Sprint, minister of Thornbury in Glocester-shire, sometimes of Christ-Church in Oxon</title>
                 <author>Sprint, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bill, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 277, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very part of Trueth is precious, euen the least: (as the least graine of muske is sweete.) Because it is the Trueth; Because Gods Truth; and because small errors intertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned against small Trueths, haue often euill, sometimes pernicious effects. Which last appeareth in the controuersie of our Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies; the sparkles of which difference haue growen vnto great flames in this our Church. Where the fault is, as God knoweth, so the day will try, and God will one day iudge. But difference of appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensions hath brought foorth difference of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and difference of iudgements, hath brought forth difference of practise, and disagreement in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. The difference of practise hath mooued Authority to silence and suppresse refusers of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie: The disagreement in affection, hath moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Ministers depriued to speake euil of persons in authority, and of Conformers: Whereby in the euent, the course of the Gospell is interrupted, and
<pb facs="7"/> of Popery enlarged; the friends of <hi>Sion</hi> are grieued, the enemies reioyced, the Deuill gratified, and God not pleased. The Church is rent with Schisme, the Trueth scandalized by dissention, &amp; the Ministers vndone by losse of liuing, and the vnitie of brethren liuing in the same house, professing the same Faith, and reioycing in the same Hope, is pulled in pieces: And this like to continue God knowes how long; but all men know, the longer the worse.</p>
   <p>For which cause I haue vndertaken this seruice to Gods Church, to vnfold the state of this question, which as yet hath not been so directly and distinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handled, in my opinion, as it might, by any that I know. The Ministers haue heretofore laboured to proue the Ceremonies euill to be vsed, and fit to be abolished; but they neuer went about to prooue, whether in case of Depriuation they ought to haue conformed; which is the question directly concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their case. This is performed in this tractate, and resolued by reason drawen from God and man, from Scripture and Authority of all sorts, which thou (good Reader) mayest perceiue, if thy desire allure thee, or thy patience will giue thee leaue to reade.</p>
   <p>The occasion of my penning it was this: At <note place="margin">The occasion of penning this Treatise.</note> first, being of aduersary iudgement to the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, I laboured (as men doe that are sicke of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice) to gather all I could against them, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stained from the practise of them, as from things simply euill: But after, hauing been indicted at a
<pb facs="7"/> quarter Sessions for refusing to conforme, by some of my Parish for my fidelity in opposing their dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered life, I was occasioned to looke more neere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the state of this question, whether I might vse them with my peace in any case, or not; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of necessity, &amp; Depriuation. I asked of my selfe two things, whether I would rather suffer death, then vse them in a Church professing the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and vrging them as things indifferent, not pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing them, as binding Conscience in themselues, or as needfull to saluation? And whether the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my Ministery (which was pressed on my Conscience with a woe, if I neglected it) should not be as deare vnto me, as my life? Which questions, when they put mee to a stand, and that I could not well resolue vnto my selfe, for the ill conceit I had against the Ceremonies, I beganne to search in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the iudgement of our best latter writers, and the practise of reformed Churches, from whence I went vnto antiquitie of primitiue and purer times; where with one consent and harmonie of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I found them for the practise of farre more, and more offensiue Ceremonies then ours may bee supposed, and chiefely in this case. This was a ground to stay my iudgement, and build my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution: From which when once I found it, in con-conscience I could not, in modestie I durst not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part in haste. For with what shew or conscience should any man turne his backe in dislike, or his face in opposition to the iudgement and
<pb facs="8"/> practise of all Churches of Christ since the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles? And from all those worthy Lights, those Spirituall persons, the Teachers of the Churches, the champions of the Trueth, the Masters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, by whom, and by whom onely, God had in all ages propagated his Gospell, conuerted soules, confirmed Veritie, confuted Heresies and Errors, builded Christes Church, discouered and ouerthrowne the Church of Antichrist? Chiefly, seeing it is the iudgement not of one or two, nor of some against some other, but euen of All, not One excepted which is of note, or classicall authority: And none against this iudgement, excepting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted and condemned Hereticks and Schisma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, such as Donatists, Anabaptists, and our latter Brownists. From thence I looked into the reasons mouing them vnto this iudgement, &amp; that practise, which in this Tractate are set downe: So that here is no nouelty broached, or fancy of mine owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to thy view (Christian reader) but Antiquity and Vniuersality; not Papall, but Euangelicall, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scripture; not of Carnall, but Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall persons, which may bee to thy Conscience as an <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
   <p>The causes of publishing are principally three, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specting <note place="margin">Causes of publishing.</note> the trueth, the Ministers my brethren, and my selfe. The publication of this booke concerneth the trueth in two respects: First, because it is a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stioned trueth, which may not bee concealed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iniury to God, and to his Church: and it is a sin
<pb facs="8"/> of no light nature, to withhold the trueth in vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse: <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 18.</note> next, it is a profitable trueth, which may occasion some Ministers to enter, which dare not for conformitie, and others to returne which are depriued for not conforming to the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, both tending to the benefit and edification of Gods Church. For what greater profit may there be, then that which is opposed to the greatest mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe? For as it pleaseth God to saue them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 21. prou 29. 18.</note> by preaching: so where no vision is, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple perish. Secondly, it respecteth the ministers of two sorts. First, such as are depriued, on whom these reasons doe inforce a sinne for not confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the case of depriuation: and it is very scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous for Ministers, professing sinceritie of Christ his Gospel to haue begunne, and to continue in a wrong course; neither can they approoue their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science before God or man, to beginne and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in error and not amend when they see a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter way. Then, it concerneth the Ministers that haue conformed in this case: both because it serueth to cleere the innocencie of sundry godly teachers, that haue conformed to preuent their depriuation, which are hardly thought of, and traduced as back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sliders, and betrayers of Gods cause. And if this trueth were knowen, they would not haue condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned innocents: As also because it is meete that the hearts of such as haue conformed of feare, and are wounded with griefe, should bee relieued: this trueth seruing to quiet their afflicted conscience,
<pb facs="9"/> which must not bee neglected. Lastly, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specteth my selfe, and that two wayes. First, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause by suppressing of this veritie, I should wrap my selfe in the guilte of a two fold sin; namely, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulnesse to God, &amp; vnrighteousnesse to man. For why hath God opened my eyes to see this truth, but to that end I should reueale it vnto others?</p>
   <p>And it were vnrighteousnesse, and hatred to my <note place="margin">Leu. 19. 17.</note> brethren to suffer them to sin, and not to shew them of it, to see them to wander, and not to point vnto the right way. Lastly, it were iniquitie to my selfe, to suffer my Ministerie to be euill spoken of, for practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the trueth; there being scandall taken farre and neere at the alteration of my iudgement, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of my purpose to conforme, rather then to suffer depriuation, which I may lawfully, and must also of some necessitie preuent. To this I adde the respect I haue vnto our Schismatickes, the Brown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ists, whose errors are hereby discouered, and their false conclusions ouerthrowne.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
      <note place="margin">Obiections answered.</note>But it will bee said I am in error: If so, it shall the easier be confuted. And when any man hath shewed it to be error, hee may the more safely call it so: And I shall bee the rather induced to confesse it so to be. It will be well, and more agreeing to the comfort of mens consciences, and more fitted to the rekconing they must giue, to bee aduised before they so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude it. Howbeit, if I erre, it is with such company, with whom in some case I had rather erre (as one speaketh) then thinke or know the trueth with some
<pb facs="9"/> other. Neither can I bee perswaded, neither will any man proue easily, that all true Churches of Christ, of all ages, agreeing in a pointe, haue agreed in an error.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> But thus good men receaue disgrace that stand against the Ceremonies. To this I say that no man can, no good man will esteeme the trueth to bee his owne disgrace. It is a grace by seeing error to acknowledge it. It is an honour vnto God to disgrace our selues, by gracing and embracing of his trueth. Can any man preferre his credit to Gods dishonour, and redeeme it with the ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke of the trueth?</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> O, but I lay a sinne vnto the charge of all the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters depriued: And to this I say, they lay a sinne vpon their brethren not inferiour to themselues, that haue conformed to the Ceremonies (by their account) in nature euill. Nay they lay a sinne vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all Churches and godly Teachers since the time of Christ: should any man indure so great indignity, or swallow such absurditie by sparing them? And admit they be prooued to be found in sinne, it is no newes that hath beene taught from the beginning, <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 4 23. Iam. 3. 2. 1. Cor. 13. 9, 10</note> that all men are liers, and that all haue sinned; yea, in many things wee offend all: Wee know but in part, and difference will bee among the best, and with difference, error on one side or another in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters circumstantiall, vntill perfection come. Our <note place="margin">Psal. 19▪ 12.</note> comfort is, that all sinnes, especially vnknowne to such as are in Christ, are pardoned, as being inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="10"/> in the compasse of their generall repentance. Though reason accuse them of a sinne, yet grace in <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1. 7.</note> Christ his blood cleanseth from all sinne, neither can any man condemne where God hath iustified. <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 33, 34.</note> And what I thinke of them in charitie, that to my comfort I thinke of my selfe and all that holde this iudgement albeit it prooue an error.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Yet againe good mindes will be offended at this, which I haue written. But either it is Truth or error. If error, I confesse they haue iust cause, and I will confesse it when I see it. But if it bee the Trueth: what? will the children of the light bee offended at <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 16. Luk. 7. 35.</note> the light? or am I their enemie because I tell them the Trueth? wisedome is iustified of all her children. And euery one that is of the Trueth heareth the <note place="margin">Iohn 18. 37.</note> voice thereof.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> And wicked men, with such as are the enemies of our Church, such as Papists, Brownists, Anabaptists, will triumph and reioyce, that such as haue stood out against Conformitie, doe now defend it: But when was it otherwise, when will it, how can it bee, but that weake eyes should be offended at the light? It is a griefe to raigning sinnes to see others to amend. They triumph in our conforming, but will they not much more in our eiection? they reioyce in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming to the Ceremonies, and wee will grieue at their conforming to the world.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Lastly, some haue obserued, how certaine of the <note place="margin">Modest offer. fol. 19.</note> Ministers which stood against Conformitie, haue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter yeelding, euidently lost the grace and power of
<pb facs="10"/> their gifts, some fallen to idlenesse, neglect of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke and priuate duties, yea to prophane and scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous life &amp; conuersation. And so (say I) haue sundry done vpon my knowledge, that haue holden out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Conformitie, euen to suspension &amp; depriuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; whose zeale in that behalfe, hath either been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postrous, more insisting on the lesser then the weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier matters of the Law, or ioyned with grosse ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, themselues not able to haue giuen a reason of their doings before God or man: It being iust with God to punish them on either side, who without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science or ground of Faith, do either conforme or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse Conformitie. For otherwise none can be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, but that on either side, sundry haue remained in the constant euidence of Gods best gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and in the blessing of a sanctified estate. To teach vs that it is not the zeale, for or against the Ceremonies, but an heart established in grace, that <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 9.</note> can keepe men from the markes and badges of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie.</p>
   <p>Now, for the manner of my handling these my <note place="margin">The manner of handling.</note> reasons, I trust it shall appeare to euery person fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God, that as I haue written these things with a good conscience, as in the sight of God: so I haue performed it with due respect to my Brethren, as it becommeth Truth. I know with whom I hold this controuersie, not with enemies but brethren, and I haue not learned the language of fowle speech. If any man be moued to reply, I wish him to performe it in the spirit of meekenesse, and in the euidence of <note place="margin">Iames 3. 17.</note>
      <pb facs="11"/> heauenly wisedome; for that our passions are great hinderances of finding out the Truth: And no man breaketh out into inordinate affection in any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie, chiefly of this nature, but hee hazardeth the losse of a better thing then that he seeketh. Hee seeketh Truth, and loseth Charitie and power of godlinesse; whereas he should seeke Truth in Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie: For Charitie reioyceth not in iniquitie, but in <note place="margin">Ephes 4. 15. 1. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 13. 6.</note> the Truth. God needeth not our lies to defend his Truth: I leaue such practise for my part to Papists and to Brownists, who by vnablenesse to leaue their rayling formes and bitternesse, do manifest the foule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of their heart and falsehood of their cause, that cannot bee defended but by weapons borrowed from corrupted nature, and the diuill; And in a word declare themselues vnprofitable in the Truth they know, &amp; vncapable of any Truth they know not, and quite vnworthy of respect. Wee haue had contentions enough about circumstances and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies. The yeeres should teach vs how smally the Lord doeth blesse the dissentions of Brethren: And the times approach wherin it must be knowne, <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 17.</note> that the kingdome of God stands not in meate and drinke, nor godlinesse in Ceremonialls, but in the power of a regenerated state: And that sauing grace wil stand, though men neuer write or preach against a Bishop, or suffer depriuation for refusall of a Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony: And that the grace of God doth teach vs to seeke resolution of euery doubt, and to witnesse our dislike of things to bee disliked in wisedome and
<pb facs="11"/> proportion; but neuer to contend about any thing, but for the faith once giuen to the Saints. If any man <note place="margin">Iude v 3. Phil 3. 15.</note> bee otherwise minded, God shall reueale the same vnto him. If any man bee ignorant, let him be <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14 38.</note> ignorant still. If any man will be contentious, we <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11. 16.</note> haue no such custome, nor the Churche of God. In the foundation we all agree. Time and day will <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3 11. 12. 13. 15▪ 10.</note> try the hay and stubble from the gold and siluer: And the fire of Gods triall will surely sindge delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents. Let euery man take heede how hee builds. <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. 5.</note> Let vs iudge nothing before the time, vntil the Lord come, who will bring to light the things hidden in darkenesse: <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 16.</note> But whereunto we haue attained, let vs walke by the same rule, and let vs minde the same thing. <note place="margin">Iude v. 20.</note> Let vs edifie our selues in our most holy Faith, and pray one for nother. And the in their hearts. <note place="margin">Iames 5. 16.</note> Lord doe good to those that are good, and to them that are vpright <note place="margin">Psal. 125. 4.</note>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>IOHN SPRINT.</signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="12"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>