<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE CHIEFE HEADS AND CONCLVSIONS OF THE TREATIE OF Peace held at Prague, are contained in the three Ex∣tracts ensuing.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117796_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12952</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23245</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117796</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE CHIEFE HEADS AND CONCLVSIONS OF THE TREATIE OF Peace held at Prague, are contained in the three Ex∣tracts ensuing.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A bevvayling of the peace of Germany. Or, A discourse touching the Peace of Prague, no lesse unhappily than unjustly concluded at Prague in Bohemia, the 30. of May, 1635 : Wherein the subtilties and practises of the Austrians, the weakenesse of the Saxons, the dangers of the protestants, and the justnesse of the warre, deservedly set on foot by the French and Swedes, are most evidently declared. Written in Latine by Iustus Asterius, otherwise Stella, a Germane, now one of the advocates in the Court of Parliament of Paris, and historiographer to the French King. Faithfully translated out of the Latine copie. Whereunto is prefixed a briefe summarie of the treaty of peace concluded at Prague, as aforesaid, &amp;c. Published by authority</title>
                 <author>Stella, Johannes</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hunscott, Joseph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Meredith, Christopher.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stephens, Philemon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 28, 18, 129, 110-111, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="1" facs="2"/>
   <head>THE CHIEFE HEADS AND CONCLVSIONS OF THE TREATIE OF Peace held at <hi>Prague,</hi> are contained in the three Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts ensuing.</head>
   <list>
      <item>I. <hi>A</hi> Summarie Extract out of the Treatie of Peace made and concluded betwixt the Emperour and the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> at <hi>Prague,</hi> the <hi>30.</hi> day of May, <hi>1635.</hi>
      </item>
      <pb n="2" facs="3"/>
      <item>II. An Extract of the Agreement made betwixt the Emperour and the said Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ioyning of their Armes together.</item>
      <item>III. An Extract translated word for word out of the said Treatie, touching the <hi>Palatinate</hi> in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</item>
   </list>
   <div n="1" type="part">
      <pb n="3" facs="3"/>
      <head>
         <hi>I.</hi> An Abridgement of the Treatie of the Peace.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Revenues of th Church, which were pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed by the <hi>Protestants,</hi> before the Treatie of <hi>Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saw,</hi> shall remaine entirely in the same state they were setled in by the said Treatie of <hi>Passaw.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>The Church-Revenues possessed by them since the said Treatie, shall be left unto them for the space of fortie yeeres, upon the conditions more specially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and expressed in this agreement, as well for the Spirituall, as for the Temporall.</p>
      <pb n="4" facs="4"/>
      <p>And ten yeeres before the expiration of the said Terme, the best endeavour shall be used to make a finall accord, for so much as concerneth the said Possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Church, and that which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth of them: But if that cannot be done, it shall then be in the power of the Emperour to make a decision of the difference: And in the meane time, there shall no more Church-Possessions be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from the <hi>Catholikes.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>The Archbishoprick of <hi>Magdebourg</hi> shall remaine to Duke <hi>Augustus,</hi> sonne to the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> during his life, upon such conditions as are expressed in this agreement as well for the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, as for the Spirituall.</p>
      <p>The Elector of <hi>Saxonie</hi> shall have the Seignories and Bayliwickes of <hi>Querfurt, Iuterbock, Dama,</hi> and <hi>Borck;</hi> which Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he shall hold in Fee of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishoprick of <hi>Magdebourg.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>The Marquis <hi>Christian William,</hi> shall have 12000 Rix-Dollars given him by the yeere out of the Revenues of the said
<pb n="5" facs="4"/> Archbishoprick, during his life, for his entertainment.</p>
      <p>The Archduke <hi>Leopold William,</hi> the Emperours sonne, shall have, amongst other things, the Bishoprick of <hi>Halber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stadt.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>The Nobilitie and Gentrie of the Empire shall be left to their free exercise of the Confession of <hi>Auspurgh;</hi> as shall also those Imperiall Cities, which shall conforme themselves to this Treatie: But those which before the conclusion of the said Treatie, shall have accorded alreadie in any other manner with the Emperour, shall hold themselves to that accord.</p>
      <p>The Citie of <hi>Donawerth</hi> shall remaine in the hands of the Duke of <hi>Baviere,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he be re-embursed his charges.</p>
      <p>The free exercise of the Confession of <hi>Auspurgh</hi> shall no more be tolerated for the time to come in the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> nor in the other Hereditarie Countries of the Emperour.</p>
      <p>As for <hi>Silesia,</hi> the Emperour hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="6" facs="5"/> his resolution by it selfe, and hath made a particular accord with the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> for <hi>Lusatia.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>The propositions made by the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> That the Imperiall Chamber may from henceforth be divided, and composed of persons of both Religions, equall in number; are put off unto the first generall Assembly, which shall be holden hereafter: In the meane time, the order shal be observed which is practised in the said Imperiall Chamber. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause there hath been no Visitation since the yeere 1600, there shall be one as soone as possibly may be extraordinarily.</p>
      <p>The instruction of the Assessors and Presidents of the Court <hi>Aulike,</hi> or of the <hi>Councell</hi> following the Emperors person, shall be submitted to the advice of all the Electors but the said Assessors shall not be of both Religions, in equall number.</p>
      <p>The <hi>Protestant</hi> Electors, Princes, and States, shall be permitted to have their Agents and Sollicitors in the said <hi>Aulike</hi> Court.</p>
      <pb n="7" facs="5"/>
      <p>The <hi>Palatine Electorate,</hi> and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries belonging to it, shall remaine unto the Duke of <hi>Baviere,</hi> and to the Line of Duke <hi>William</hi> his father, according as the Emperour hath ordered: And that which his Imperiall Majestie hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed touching the estates of some of the <hi>Palatines</hi> servants, shall remaine entire as it is.</p>
      <p>The Widow of the Elector <hi>Frederick</hi> the fourth, Count <hi>Palatine,</hi> shall enjoy her Iointure, for so much as she can make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be due unto her.</p>
      <p>An entertainment of a Prince shall be given to the children of <hi>Frederick</hi> the proscribed, if they doe in due manner humble themselves towards the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour: But this not to be done as a thing due, but of his Imperiall grace.</p>
      <p>The heires of the Count <hi>Tilly</hi> deceased shall have 400000 Rix-Dollars out of the Revenues of the Duchy of <hi>Brunswick,</hi> payable in eight yeres, with interest after five in the hundred, untill it be fully payd: and in the meane time, they shall keepe that which is morgaged unto them.</p>
      <pb n="8" facs="6"/>
      <p>If the Dukes of <hi>Meckelburgh</hi> doe accept these Articles of Pacification, they shall be received into the <hi>Amnestia,</hi> according as is contained in the particular Order made concerning that matter.</p>
      <p>The Electors, Princes, and States of the Confession of <hi>Auspurgh</hi> shall restore to the Emperour, and to the <hi>Catholike</hi> Electors, Princes, &amp; States, his assistants, as also unto the Duke of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> their Countreyes, Lands, Seignories, Cities, Townes, Castles, and all that belongs unto them. Yet neverthelesse, they shall not be tyed to make restitution of the Revenues received, nor of their charges expended in the Warre; but they shall not carry away the Ordnance, nor their moveable goods, out of the places which they shall give up.</p>
      <p>Ayde and assistance shall be given, by a conjunction of Armes and Forces, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover that which the Crowne of <hi>France,</hi> the Crowne of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and the States of the Empire, which will not conforme themselves to this present Treatie, doe possesse within the Empire.</p>
      <pb n="9" facs="6"/>
      <p>The Emperour and his assistants shall restore the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and those of his party, their subjects, vassalls, men, and servants, to the possession of their estates, if they accept of this Treatie; excepting those, whom the Emperour hath expressely excluded from it: And the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and those of his party, shall doe the same reciprocally to the Emperour and his assistants.</p>
      <p>The places possessed by the <hi>Catholikes,</hi> since the yeere 1625, (amongst which, <hi>Wolfenbottle</hi> and <hi>Newburgh</hi> are intended to be of the number) shall be restored to their proprietarie Lords, without resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them the Revenues of them, and without carrying away the Ordnance.</p>
      <p>The Elector of <hi>Saxonie</hi> shall restore within ten dayes, that he yet holdeth in <hi>Bohemia;</hi> and shall give ayde towards the dislodging of the Souldiers of the other party, which shall be found with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that Kingdome.</p>
      <p>The said Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and the rest of the <hi>Protestants</hi> of his party, shall
<pb n="10" facs="7"/> ayde the Emperour and his assistants, for the recoverie of their Possessions, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie to this Treatie: And the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, with his assistants, shall ayde the said Elector and his, in the recoverie of that which belongeth unto them.</p>
      <p>If the Elector of <hi>Brandenbourg,</hi> who is not excluded from the <hi>Amnestia,</hi> will accept of this Peace, he shall be invested in the Duchie of <hi>Pomeranie.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>All labour and endeavour shall be joyntly used, to deliver <hi>Pomeranie,</hi> the upper and nether Circle of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and the whole Empire in generall, from strange Souldiers.</p>
      <p>When this shall be done, and the House of <hi>Brunswick</hi> shall have accepted this Treatie, rid away his Souldiers, and shall have conformed it selfe, then <hi>Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenbottle</hi> and other places shall be resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto him.</p>
      <p>When the Emperour, the <hi>Catholikes,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Lorraine</hi> shall be resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the <hi>Protestants</hi> to that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth unto them, in the upper and
<pb n="11" facs="7"/> nether Circle of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and in the Circles of <hi>Suaube, Bavaria,</hi> and <hi>Franconia,</hi> so as they may fully and peaceably en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it; the said <hi>Protestants</hi> shall also fully enjoy and have the benefit of this Peace.</p>
      <p>If the Emperour doth still entertaine Garrisons in some places within the said Circles; that shall not prejudice the said <hi>Protestants,</hi> nor shall hinder them from returning thither, and enjoying their Right.</p>
      <p>And as it is provided, that the Duke of <hi>Lorraine</hi> shall be restored to the pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session of all his Countries, and the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purtenances; so it shall not be suffered, that from henceforth any thing more whatsoever be taken from him.</p>
      <p>The Emperour reserveth unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe the Fort of <hi>Philipsbourg,</hi> to dispose of it hereafter, as shall seeme good unto himselfe.</p>
      <p>The Prisoners, and their Principalls, to whom they belong, which shall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme themselves to this Treatie, shall
<pb n="12" facs="8"/> be released within one moneth after the publication of the Peace: Yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse, those who have alreadie promised their ransome, shall pay it, with the charges which they have expended.</p>
      <p>There shall be a generall <hi>Amnestia</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Emperour, the <hi>Catholike</hi> Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, Princes, and States, his assistants, and the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and those which have beene of his partie in this Warre; in such manner and sort, that all which hath beene done and committed hostilely, since the yeere 1630, untill this time, shall be abolished and forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, if they doe accept of this Peace within ten dayes: Which <hi>Amnestia</hi> shall be extended also unto their Heires, Lands, Countries, People, and Subjects, their Officers of Warre, Souldiers, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellors, Servants, and Ministers.</p>
      <p>The Emperour hath excluded out of this <hi>Amnestia,</hi> the Affaires and Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and of the <hi>Palatinate:</hi> For since that his Imperiall Majestie, for the quieting of them, hath been constrained
<pb n="13" facs="8"/> to put himselfe to very great charges; he will seeke for reparation of his Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages upon them, who have beene the causers of them, and upon their Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Assistants.</p>
      <p>He doth also exclude from this <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestia,</hi> all the persons and estates, which are specified in a Schedule, which hath been exhibited of them unto the Elector of <hi>Saxonie:</hi> Which exclusion and excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the said persons and their estates, expressed in the said Schedule, shall be held as firme and availeable, to be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected and put in execution, as if the spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification of them were here inserted word for word.</p>
      <p>The States, which have already made their accommodation with the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, shall hold themselves to their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, and shall have no power to make any pretence to any further matter, by vertue of this.</p>
      <p>Those which have hitherto remained Neuters, and will accept of this Pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, shall enjoy the said <hi>Amnestia.</hi>
      </p>
      <pb n="14" facs="9"/>
      <p>The forraine Potentates, which have interessed themselves in this Warre, since the yeere 1630, shall be also comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded within the said <hi>Amnestia,</hi> if they will conforme themselves to this Treatie.</p>
      <p>The Emperour will take it to his charge, to publish, notifie, and also to advance, promote, and confirme by his Edicts and Commandements, this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Treatie, and that which depends of it: He will exhort and stirre up every one to joyne his Armes to those of his Imperiall Majestie, and to signifie in what state, condition, and posture hee findes himselfe, and what his Forces are: Which signification, or advertisement, every man shall give, either to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour himselfe, or (if he cannot doe that, by reason of the dangerousnesse of the Wayes) to the King of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> or to the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> or to the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of <hi>Mentz, Collen, Bavaria,</hi> or to the generall and principall Officers.</p>
      <p>The end or ayme of this Pacification, is, to restore the Empire to her ancient
<pb n="15" facs="9"/> tranquillitie and libertie: And to this purpose, the Emperour shall continue armed; and the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and the other Electors, Princes, and States, shall joyne their troupes to those of his Imperiall Majestie: And of all their Armies, shall be made one principall one, which shall be called, <hi>The Armie of his Imperiall Majestie, and of the sacred Empire.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>The Elector of <hi>Saxonie</hi> shall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the fourth part of the said Armie, in a Body by it selfe; and the King of <hi>Hungarie</hi> shall command the other three parts, in another Body, or in divers, as it shall be found expedient.</p>
      <p>The said Armie shall be employed against all those that shall oppose this Treatie of Pacification, or that shall not be willing to give use that they possesse.</p>
      <p>All the Bodies of their Armies, and all their Generalls and Officers, shall sweare allegeance to the Emperour.</p>
      <p>Yet notwithstanding, the King of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garie,</hi> and the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> when
<pb n="16" facs="10"/> they shall command in person, shall not be summoned to take their corporall Oath; but it shall suffice, that they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage their Word, Honour, and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, Royall and Electorall, respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively.</p>
      <p>The Emperour will cause the Instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Capitulations (Articles briefe) to be framed, as neere as may be confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to the Lawes and Statutes of the Empire.</p>
      <p>The whole Body of the Empire shall contribute to the entertainment of the said Imperiall Armie; and the States shall make no difficultie to furnish and pay, presently after the publication, 120 moneths of the contribution of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, called <hi>Romertzug.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>The charges and expences of quarte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Armie, shall be defalked out of the said contribution, in such sort, that those who have beene at the charge of quartering and lodging the Souldiers, shall abate out of their taxation so much as they have expended that way.</p>
      <pb n="17" facs="10"/>
      <p>The Emperour will call an Imperiall Dyet as soone as possibly can be, as well for the setling and advancing of the said contribution of the Empire, as for the other publike affaires of the Empire.</p>
      <p>When the Peace shall be fully re-established, then all lodging of Souldiers and all sorts of arming shall cease.</p>
      <p>No forraine Forces shall be suffered to enter into the Empire, for any cause whatsoever, nor for the difference concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Palatinate.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>By vertue of this Pacification and Agreement, all other Vnions, Leagues, and Alliances within the Empire, shall be disannulled and made void; except the Agreements and Contracts of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, made betwixt Noble Houses.</p>
      <p>The Emperour will hold good intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence with his neighbour Kingdomes, which doe no oppression upon the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</p>
      <p>His Imperiall Majestie will reigne and governe the Empire with mildnesse and clemencie.</p>
      <pb n="18" facs="11"/>
      <p>On the other side, the Electors, Princes, and States, will render him all the respect and obedience they owe him.</p>
      <p>Also good amitie shall be maintained betwixt the parties.</p>
      <p>For the advancement of the Peace, and of Iustice, the Electors, Princes, and States shall hold good correspondence with the Emperour.</p>
      <p>The Constitutions of execution, and that which is ordained by this Treatie, shall be observed against those that shall keepe themselves armed, in prejudice of this Pacification.</p>
      <p>Whatsoever shall be done and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted against the tenor of this Treatie, shall be held void <hi>ipso facto,</hi> and of no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liditie.</p>
      <p>The Emperour doth promise, by his Imperiall Dignitie, to observe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever is concluded by this Treatie; and the Elector of <hi>Saxonie</hi> doth the same.</p>
      <p>If then the Electors, Princes, and States of the Empire, or the greater part
<pb n="19" facs="11"/> of them, doe accept this Pacification and Agreement; it shall be held for a common resolution, and fundamentall Law of the Empire: in conformitie whereunto, the Iudges of Courts of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice shall give sentence against those that shall infringe the same.</p>
      <p>The Emperour and the Elector of <hi>Saxonie</hi> have called to minde, that a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion of so high importance, which concerneth the whole Body of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, ought not to have beene made, but in a Dyet of the Empire, or in an Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Deputation: But for as much as the urgent necessitie hereof, could not give leave to stay for the occasion of such an Assembly; it is by way of precaution declared, that this resolution shall not prejudice the right and libertie of the Empire, for the time to come.</p>
      <p>Three severall Exemplifications in Parchment have beene made and signed of this present Treatie, and all of one and the same tenor: whereof, one was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the Emperour; the other, to the
<pb n="20" facs="12"/> Elector of <hi>Mentz,</hi> as Arch-Chancellor of the Empire, to register it amongst the publike Acts and Records of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; and the third, to the Elector of <hi>Saxonie.</hi>
      </p>
      <closer>
         <dateline>
            <hi>Given at</hi> Prague, <date>
               <hi>the</hi> 30. <hi>of May,</hi> 1635.</date>
         </dateline>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div n="2" type="part">
      <head>
         <hi>II.</hi> An Extract out of the particular Accord made betwixt the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> touching the ioyning together of their Armes.</head>
      <p>ALL the Forces shall be reduced into one <hi>Armade,</hi> which shall be called, <hi>The</hi> Armade <hi>of his Imperiall Majestie, and of the sacred Empire;</hi> and a good part of it shall be left to the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> to be commanded. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion shall be this: If the Armie doe
<pb n="21" facs="12"/> amount unto 80000 men, the Emperour shall have 60000 of them; which he shall cause to be commanded by the King of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> his Sonne: and the Elector of <hi>Saxonie</hi> shall have 20000 to command; and if the said Elector have foure or five thousand over and above that number, he shall be suffered to have them. All these Souldiers shall be entertained with the contributions of the Empire; and the Receivers generall shall be tyed to furnish to every Generall his rate, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the proportion of the Body of the Armie which he shall command. If the Emperour happen to depart this life, the King of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> his Sonne, and he whom it shall please him to ordaine, shall continue the command of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of his Armie. And if the Elector of <hi>Saxonie</hi> happen to dye, his Sonne, who is to be his Successour in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorate, shall succeed his Father also in his place of Generall. If the said Elector, or his Sonne, doe desire to be discharged of the Bodie of his Armie,
<pb n="22" facs="13"/> he shall be so; and the Emperour will entrust the Command of Generall of that Body of the Army, to some other of the Confession of <hi>Auspurgh;</hi> such as the said Elector, and the Elector of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgh</hi> shall advise him unto. When any execution shall be commanded, and committed to one of the said Bodies of Armies, it shall be obedient, to undertake it; without any disturbance to be given unto them, in the said execution, by the other Bodies of Armies: and if that Body be not found sufficient for the action, the others shall readily and willingly assist it: To the effecting whereof, the Generalls and Directors shall hold a carefull cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>respondence together, and shall direct all their actions to one and the same end. They shall as soone as possibly may be, and at the furthest, within foure or sixe weekes after the publication hereof, take their Oath of Allegeance unto the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour and the Empire, as is mentioned in the Treatie of Pacification. In the places where <hi>Catholikes</hi> and <hi>Protestants</hi>
         <pb n="23" facs="13"/> dwell, the quarters shall be equally di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stributed, without any distinction of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. If any Warre doe happen to be made in the Circles of high and low <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> as being neighbour unto it, have a desire to doe execution rather then another, or to quarter himselfe there, the Emperour will grant him leave to doe it, before ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. In case, that the Elector of <hi>Saxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi> or his Sonne, should not be in person in the Campe, and that necessitie did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, that they should joyne the Bodies of the Armies together; then the King of <hi>Hungarie</hi> shall have the direction of the Body of the Armie of the said E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector: and the levyes of Souldiers, and their quartering, shall be proportioned according to the Bodies of the Armies. The Receivers generall of the Empire shall be bound by Oath, to pay and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the contribution-Mony to each Body of the Armies proportionably, that is to say, to the King of <hi>Hungarie</hi> for 60000, and to the Elector of <hi>Saxonie</hi> for 20000 men.
<pb n="24" facs="14"/> When it shall please God to re-establish the Peace, and that the Troupes shall come to be disbanded, this proportion shall be observed; That as the Elector shall disband 2000 men, the King of <hi>Hungarie</hi> shall disband 6000. Whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is not found to be comprehended nor expressed in this Schedule or Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Agreement, is to be sought for in the Contents of the Treatie of Peace at large, which ought to be invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lably observed.</p>
      <p>Of this Schedule there have beene made two Exemplifications in Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of one and the same tenor: The one, for the Emperour; the other, for the Elector of <hi>Saxonie.</hi>
      </p>
      <closer>
         <dateline>
            <hi>Given at</hi> Prague, <date>
               <hi>the</hi> 30. <hi>of May,</hi> 1635.</date>
         </dateline>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div n="3" type="part">
      <pb n="25" facs="14"/>
      <head>
         <hi>III.</hi> An Extract out of the said Treatie of Peace, for so much as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the <hi>Palatinate.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>TOuching the businesse of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine,</hi> as being that for which in these yeeres last past many horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Commotions, Troubles, and Oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions have beene raysed; His Electorall Highnesse of <hi>Saxonie</hi> did very stiffely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist upon it, to have it fully setled and accommodated, as well in point of the Electorall Dignitie, as for that which concerneth his Countreyes: But for as much as it is notoriously knowne, (and the most laudable College of Electors judged it to be so at <hi>Mulbausen,</hi> in the yeere 1627) that the proscribed <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, Frederick,</hi> hath beene the Author
<pb n="26" facs="15"/> and Promoter of all the Mischiefes hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> an Hereditarie King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of his Imperiall Majestie, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after in the Empire; and that his Imperiall Majestie, together with his most honourable House, findes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to be in debt for this occasion many Millions, and to have sustained divers other great Damages; and namely, that he hath beene constrained to leave some part of his Hereditarie Countreyes in ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reare, to furnish the expences of the Warre: His Majestie would by no meanes depart from his resolution, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his Electorall Highnesse of <hi>Saxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi> did seriously bestow his labour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And therefore that remained firme and setled, which his Imperiall Majestie had ordained and determined, touching the said Electorall Dignitie, and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes; as well on the behalfe of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorall Highnesse of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and the Line of the late Duke <hi>William</hi> his Father, as otherwise; and also, touching the estates of some of the <hi>Palatines</hi> Servants.
<pb n="27" facs="15"/> Yet neverthelesse, the Widow of the late Elector, <hi>Frederick</hi> the fourth, Count <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine</hi> of <hi>Rhine,</hi> shall have her Iointure allowed her, so farre forth as she can make appeare what belongeth to her. Also the entertainment of a Prince shall be ordered to be allowed to the Children of the proscribed <hi>Palatine,</hi> if they will duely humble themselves towards his Imperiall Majestie. And all this to be done of his Imperiall grace, not as any thing of due.</p>
      <div type="subpart">
         <head>Below.</head>
         <p>HIS Imperiall Majestie doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressely exclude and cut off from this <hi>Amnestia,</hi> the Affaires and Differences of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and of the <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate.</hi> And because, for the appeasing and quieting of them, his Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie hath brought himselfe and his House into great and heavie Expences;
<pb n="28" facs="16"/> and that he hath (as hath beene formerly said) beene constrained to leave in Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reare some part of his Hereditarie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes, of the profits whereof he remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth yet frustrate, and unsatisfied; his Majestie hath reserved unto himselfe the seeking of restitution of the Charges ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended by him, and the reparation of the Damages sustained by him, from them who have beene the causers thereof, and from their assistants and promoters; and especially from as many of them as can be found, that have not yet by other Accords accommodated and reconciled themselves to his said Imperiall Majestie.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>