<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the reuerend man of God, and faithfull Preacher, M. William Leygh, Bachelor of Diuinity, and Pastor of Standish in Lancashire: William Brettergh wisheth increase of all good graces, for the gathering of Gods Saints, and buil∣ding vp of his Church, and for his owne euerlasting saluation in Iesus Christ.</title>
           <author>Brettergh, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117329_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02735</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12866</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117329</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the reuerend man of God, and faithfull Preacher, M. William Leygh, Bachelor of Diuinity, and Pastor of Standish in Lancashire: William Brettergh wisheth increase of all good graces, for the gathering of Gods Saints, and buil∣ding vp of his Church, and for his owne euerlasting saluation in Iesus Christ.</title>
                 <author>Brettergh, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Deaths aduantage little regarded, and The soules solace against sorrow : Preached in two funerall sermons at Childwal in Lancashire at the buriall of Mistris Katherin Brettergh the third of Iune. 1601. The one by William Harrison, one of the preachers appointed by her. Maiestie for the countie palatine of Lancaster, the other by William Leygh, Bachelor of Diuinitie, and pastor of Standish. Whereunto is annexed, the Christian life and godly death of the said gentlevvoman</title>
                 <author>Harrison, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 84, 4, 77, 19, 38 pages, folded table, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="52"/>
   <pb facs="52"/>
   <head>To the reuerend man of <hi>God, and faithfull Preacher, M.</hi> William Leygh, <hi>Bachelor of Diuinity, and</hi> Pastor of <hi>Standish</hi> in Lancashire: <hi>William Brettergh</hi> wisheth increase of all good graces, for the gathering of Gods Saints, and buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vp of his Church, and for his owne euerlasting saluation in Iesus Christ.</head>
   <p>GOod Sir, after I had read with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that which I gayned from you with much intreaty, I meane a copie of your Sermon, preached at my wiues Funerall; I was so ful and pregnant of the birth, that I could beare no longer, but must needs bring foorth the same, and lay it in the lap of Gods children: which how euer I vse it in the nursing, was from your selfe a per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>est birth. Happily you will deem I do you wrong, to publish the same without your futher warrantie: indeede you may and my selfe should thinke none other; but that fearing vpon a second intreaty you might either perswade me in your loue, or ouer-awe me by your authority▪ to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist from printing the same: I haue thought good rather to venture vpon all carthly replies, thē to hazard the want of so heauenly a solace.


<pb facs="53"/>
Good sir pardon my boldnes, for and if you would giue me your house full of gold, I cannot keepe in, what God will haue out: nor can I bee silent where God will speake: The best is, I lacke no priuiledge: The Lord hath giuen good success: The Examiner full allowance: The Learned good approuall: And my conscience is cleare within: I doe it neither to your praise, or my own, but with a single heart to set out the Lords glory. And for the wantonnes of the world, the iniquitie of the time, and the multitude of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious wreslers, of whom you speake; let them alone, whilest they but pine themselues in feeding vpon our best things. The Lord giue you grace, countenance, and continuance in the bleshed worke of the Ministery, for his <hi>Sions</hi> sake.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>London <date>this 20. of Nouember 1601.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your assured in Christ Iesus,
William Brettergh.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>