<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Peter Martyr to the Christian reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117880_Bo2_3_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14350</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24669</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117880</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Peter Martyr to the Christian reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The common places of the most famous and renowmed diuine Doctor Peter Martyr : diuided into foure principall parts: with a large addition of manie theologicall and necessarie discourses, some neuer extant before. Translated and partlie gathered by Anthonie Marten, one of the sewers of hir Maiesties most honourable chamber. In the end of the booke are annexed two tables of all the notable matters therein conteined</title>
                 <author>Vermigli, Pietro Martire</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 <publisher>Broome (Brome, Browne), William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Chard (Chare, Chayre), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Maunsell (Mansell), Andrew 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Middleton, Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 640, 380, that is 398, 2, 335, that is 331, 1, 4, 101-252, 165, 107 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>Peter Martyr to the Christian reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here be two causes that haue moued me to write of the Eucharist: namelie, the slanders of euill men, and the desires of my freends. The one whereof to contemne had beene a point of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curtesie, and the other to neglect were vngodlie: since I perceiued, that thereof depended no small hinderance to the religion of GOD. For if one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie mine owne cause were heere dealt withall, I might easilie haue contemned these things: sith I make not so great an account of mine owne esti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, that I thinke I ought to be mooued with the slanders of aduersaries, and with the vaine ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors of enimies. I knowe it is a wise mans part to dissemble verie manie things, and especiallie such as be of this sort, and that Christian charitie endureth all things: that it seeketh not his owne, but those things that be Iesus Christs: howbeit, not mine owne cause, but Christs is here in hand: not my name, but the word of God is ill reported of. For the danger of the authoritie of the ministerie is so ioined with the word of God, as it reacheth euen to himselfe: for so we see it come to passe, that albeit good and godlie things be neuer so godlie and learnedlie handled, yet if he that handleth them shall want authoritie, speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie if he be defaced or disgraced by anie blemish, they proceed with little or no fruit at all. But what the impudencie of some hath spred abroad, as concerning the disputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had by me at Oxford the summer last past, and how they slandered me to all sorts of men, both princes, noble men, commonaltie, citizens, and countrie men, I will not saie: for they haue doone nothing in secret, but euerie corner, street, house, shop, and tauerne doo still sound of their lieng, triumphs, and victories. And I doubt not, but that these ill reports are come also into other nations. Wherefore, one cause that vrged mee to set foorth these disputations was this: and another, as I said at the beginning, is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests of freends, which in verie deed I denied vntill this present time: as well for that I knew there were bookes enow extant of this matter, wherein euerie godlie man might be sufficientlie instructed, as also for that no man knoweth mine owne dooings better than my selfe: which hitherto I haue so accounted of, as I would not (gentle reader) hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thee by them from the reading of better bookes. But now these my freends being mooued, and that not a little, with the false reports of euill men, haue so vrged me, that granting to the requests of some, &amp; compelled by the authoritie of others, at the length <pb n="174" facs="754"/> I yeelded. For what could I denie vnto the most reuerend Archbishop of Canturburie, vnto whom I am most of all beholding? Or what could I denie to the kings visitors, which were not onelie present at these disputations, but were also presidents thereof? Wherfore I deliuer vnto thee this disputation,
<note place="margin">Looke this treatise be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore part. 4, chap. 10.</note> togither with a treatise of the same mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for the plainer declaration thereof. All which things I haue written in simple sort, and as I may saie, without anie stile; neuerthelesse faithfullie. For as concerning the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, I compared mine owne with the examples of the aduersaries. Which, when I had diligentlie read, those things which I sawe I had omitted, that were of some im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, I indeuoured, as much as the truth of the matter would suffer, to restore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine out of their writings: and whereas I perceiued them otherwhile to haue expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their reasons more largelie, and in writing to haue handled them more artificiallie, than they were vttered in the time of disputing; I also, reteining the truth of the matter haue expounded the same somewhat more largelie, which neuerthelesse happeneth verie seldome. But as concerning the effect, the principall points and substance of the arguments, and of the confutations or answers, I haue not, so far as I knowe, changed or inuerted anie thing, wherein I might doo wrong to them, which disputed with me: yea and I haue caused that oftentimes, and in a maner alwaies, the selfe-same words might be set downe, which we vsed on either side, when we disputed togither, so far as either my memorie would serue me, or their notes which gathered would giue me to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand. Whosoeuer therefore was present at our disputation, shall perceiue, that in truth there was no argument omitted, nor added; and shall vnderstand, that I haue no where fled from the summe and sense of those things that were spoken. But and if anie ill dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed persons shall (for such is their nature) complaine that I haue omitted or wrested anie thing, those things let them put in writing, and let them not deale against me by words, which maketh no matter if they be spent in vaine, but let them deale by written reasons: which, sith men may both read and well consider, this kind of disputation shall not be without fruit. For words (said Homer) are but wind; but those things which are put in writing, cannot be so easilie misreported. This if they will doo, euen as I was then bold to deale with them by liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie voice, so will I now prepare my selfe to answer those things which they shall write. In the meane time fare yee well, and take this in good part.</p>
   <trailer>
      <figure>
</figure>
   </trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>