<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Thomas Gale Maister in Chirurgerie, vnto those young men which are desirous of knowledge, and are studious in the Art of Chirurgerie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1586</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117692_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01410</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11531</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117692</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Thomas Gale Maister in Chirurgerie, vnto those young men which are desirous of knowledge, and are studious in the Art of Chirurgerie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine vvorkes of Galens, called Methodus medendi : with a briefe declaration of the worthie art of medicine, the office of a chirurgion, and an epitome of the third booke of Galen, of naturall faculties: all translated into English, by Thomas Gale Maister in Chirurgerie</title>
                 <author>Galen</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1586</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 138 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>Thomas Gale Maister in Chirurgerie, vnto those young men which are desirous of knowledge, and are studious in the Art of Chirurgerie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the name of the blessed <hi>Trinitie,</hi> I for the health of mankinde, haue with great paines and trauaile, collected and gathered together certaine parts of the Arte of Medicine, and haue put the same into sūdry bookes, for that ende, they might be the better vnderstanded, and for as much as there be many young men desirous of knowledge in this Arte, and fewe of them learned in the Latine or Gréeke tongue. Therefore, I with the help of my friends, haue set foorth these bookes in English. This part which I haue set foorth, is commonly called Chirurgerie, for that it doth cure by the ministring of conuenient medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines with the hand. And for as much as diuers and sundry persons, taketh vpon them to vse the same Arte, hauing lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle skill in the principles or right vse thereof, and some of the same doe dwell farre from Cities and good Townes, wherefore they cannot haue such counsaile as is needefull to be had, when great and daungerous cures chaunceth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their hands.</p>
   <p>Therefore I haue set forth and published abroade, both for your better vnderstanding, and also safegard of Gods people, these woorks, desiring you most hartely to giue God the praise and thanks therefore, and as for my part, I haue done but my dutie, in furthering of the common welth in this my profession and Arte, requiring you in the name of Almightie God, that when great &amp; daungerous cures hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth into your hands, not onely to be circumspect to trust in your owne doinges, but also to take counsaile of other auncient and graue men that haue had good experience, for in so doing, it shall not be onely a helpe vnto the Patient, but also vnto your owne selues, for in seeing of other cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="6"/> mens woorkes, you shall learne and sée those thinges, which you did neuer know nor sée before: &amp; further more, the common people shal haue a good opinion in you, for that you disdaine not to take counsaile of other expert men.</p>
   <p>Thus I leaue to trouble you any further, committing this my doing vnto your iudgement, desiring you to take it in as good part as I offer it vnto you, and diligently to reade all these bookes often times ouer, and then I trust you shal finde such commoditie and profit thereby, as shall redound vnto your perpetuall good name and fame, and to the safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of many people, which other wayes through your ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and lacke of knowledge, might vtterly perish.</p>
   <p>Thus I besech the eternall God to blesse vs all, &amp; to giue vs grace to honour and praise his holy name, and to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile in this our vocation and Arte, truely, rightly, and without deceit, so that it may be to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God, to the common welth, and your further knowledge: and finally, to the health and safegard of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, through <hi>Iesus Christ</hi> our Lord.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>