<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader, concerning the Errata.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117936_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13118</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23411</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117936</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader, concerning the Errata.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Metallica. Or The treatise of metallica : Briefly comprehending the doctrine of diuerse new metallicall inuentions, but especially, how to neale, melt, and worke all kinde of mettle-oares, irons and steeles with sea-coale, pit-coale, earth-coale and brush-fewell. Also a transcript of his Maiesties letters pattents of priuiledge, granted vnto Simon Sturteuant for the said metallicall businesses, for one and thirty yeares. Published in print before the last day of this present Easter terme, as the said Simon Sturteuant was by his Highnesse inioyned</title>
                 <author>Sturtevant, Simon</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 112 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>To the Reader, concerning the <hi>Errata.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>TO pretermit the correction of the lesser literare faults, read and place, I pray you, the foure first lines. pag. 73. immediately before the 61. question, for they are misplaced.</p>
   <div type="errata">
      <head>Errata.</head>
      <p>Pag. 17. l. 12. 31. parts, <hi>for</hi> 33. parts. pag. 45. l. 11. Ignime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallica, <hi>for</hi> In-ignimetallica. pa. 56. l. 17. Instruments <hi>for</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreuticks. <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 21. Instrument, <hi>for</hi> Emporeutick. pa. 73. l. 13 consisteth, <hi>for</hi> consisting. pa. 76. l. 7. diuers meanes <hi>for</hi> diuers things. pag. 77. l. 11. bee incroached, <hi>for</hi> bee not incroached. pa. 93. l. 26. edge, <hi>for</hi> edge-toole. pa. 94. l. 3. fier, colouring, <hi>for</hi> fier-colouring. pa. 108. l. 10. alter-slagge, <hi>for</hi> after-slagge.</p>
      <p>In the Epistle to the Reader, in some copies, pag. 1. of A. l. 11. <hi>Dibere</hi> for <hi>Dibre.</hi> l. 12. <hi>Aucomaton,</hi> for <hi>Automa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi> l. 18. <hi>Hubla,</hi> for <hi>Lubla.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>