<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>S., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117670_Fr4_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12644</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22965</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117670</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>S., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>St Peters complainte Mary Magdal· teares. Wth other workes of the author R:S</title>
                 <author>Southwell, Robert, saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Barrett, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>576 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="113"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any, suiting their labours to the popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar vaine, and gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the gale of vulgar breath, haue diuulged diuerse patheticall dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses, in which if they had shewed as much care to profit, as they haue done desire to please, their workes would much more haue honored their names, and auailed the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. But it is a iust complaint a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the better sort of persons, that the finest wits lose themselues in the vainest follies, spilling much Art in some idle fancie, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing their workes as witnesses how long they haue beene in trauaile, to be in fine deliuered of a fable. And sure it is a thing greatly to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, that men of so high conceit,
<pb facs="114"/> should so much abase their habili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that when they haue racked them to the vttermost endeuour, all the praise that they reape of their employment, consisteth in this, that they haue wisely told a foolish tale, and carried a long lye very smooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the end. Yet this inconuenience might find some excuse, if the drift of their discourse leuelled at any vertuous marke. For infables are often figured morall truths, and that couertly vttered to a common good, which without a maske would not find so free a passage. But when the substance of the worke hath neither truth nor probability; nor the purport thereof tendeth to any honest end, the writer is rather to be pitied than praised, and his bookes fitter for the fire than for the presse. This common ouersight more haue obserued, than endeuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to salue, euery one being able to reprooue, none willing to redresse such faults, authorised especially by generall custome. And though if
<pb facs="114"/> necessitie (the lawlesse patron of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced actions) had not more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed than choise, this worke of so different a subiect from the vsuall vaine, should haue bene no eye-sore to those that are pleased with worse matters. Yet sith the copies thereof flew fo fast, and so false abroad, that it was in danger to come corrupted to the print, it seemed a lesse euill to let it fly to common view in the natiue plume, and with the owne wings, than disguised in a coat of a bastard feather, or cast off from the fast of such a corrector, as might hapily haue perished the sound, and imped in some sicke and sory fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of his owne fansies. It may be that curteous skill will reckon this, though course in respect of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers exquisite labours, not vnfit to entertaine wel-tempered hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, both with pleasure and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, the ground thereef being in Scripture, and the forme of enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging it, an imitation of the ancient Doctors, in the same and other
<pb facs="115"/> points of like tenour. This commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity at the least it will carry with it, that the Reader may learne to loue without improofe of puritie, and teach his thoughts either to temper passion in the meane, or to giue the bridle onely where the excesse can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be faulty. Let the worke defend it selfe, and euery one passe his cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure as he seeth cause. Many Carps are expected when curious eyes come a fishing. But the care is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready taken, and patience wayteth at the cable, ready to take away, when that dish is serued in, and to make roome for others to set on the desired fruit.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>R.S.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>