<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Guild, W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117899_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02358</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12490</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117899</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Guild, W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Popish glorying in antiqvity turned to their shame : Whereby is shewed, how they wrong, villifie, and disgrace, that whereunto they pretend to carry greateste reuerence: and are most guilty of that which they vpbraide vnto others. Collected and proued out of themselues, for the singular profit both of pastors and professors. By William Guild, minister at King Edward</title>
                 <author>Guild, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Allott, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 5-268, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="14" facs="7"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Iewish People ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Burials of the ancient Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, as honourers of their memories; but in the meane time rejected that Great <hi>Prophet</hi> fore-tolde by them, and persecuted their successors: or, as that <hi>Romane</hi> Band; who crucified our Head, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever by wordes of salutation they seemed to giue Him honour &amp; cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesie; yet they shew by their deeds they meant disgrace and crueltie. Even so the <hi>Romish</hi> brood of that
<pb n="15" facs="7"/>
lamed souldior, howsoever by words they would seeme to pleade for <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie,</hi> yet their practises doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime, that they are the defacers &amp; defamers thereof in veritie. So that amongst them, (as <hi>Lyrinensis</hi> saith) <hi>Dum pro coelesti dogmate humanae superstitiones introducun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, bene fundata antiquitas scelesta novitate subruitur, &amp; nova cōtagio non tantū portiunculam, sed totam pariter Ecclesiam invasit</hi>: that is, While as humane superstitions are broght in for an heavenly point of Faith, well grounded <hi>Antiquitie</hi> is overthrowne by wicked <hi>Noveltie</hi>; and a new contagion hath broken in, not vpon a little part, but vpon the whole Church alyke.</p>
   <p>As the <hi>Ephesians</hi> therefore tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuously cried out,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Acts 19.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Great is Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na of Ephesus</hi>; so howsoever they in like manner crye, and appeale (as <hi>Paul</hi> did to <hi>Caesar</hi>) to <hi>Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> to Fathers and Doctors of the primitiue Church; yet when they
<pb n="16" facs="8"/>
are brought thither whither they haue appealed, they are seene evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentlie as much to reject their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox doctrine, as ever the <hi>Ievves</hi> did the Prophets, whose Tombes they were decoring; and as much to abuse them in their holie pains, as ever their truest successours were in their harmlesse persons;<note place="margin">
         <hi>Genesis</hi> 38.</note> and (like <hi>Iudah</hi> to <hi>Tamar</hi>) to be most guiltie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues of what they vp-braide to others; straining out the Gnat, but swallowing the Camell.</p>
   <p>Yea, as <hi>Salomō</hi> judged between the two Women, which of them was the mother of the living child; or as <hi>Saul</hi> confessed of <hi>David,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. <hi>Samuel</hi> 24.</note> that hee was more righteous than he: So eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie judicious discerner may easilie here-by perceiue, which of vs more righteouslie, or reverentlie dealeth with <hi>Antiquitie</hi>: for (beside the particulars ensuing in this Treatise) they thinke it no fault to appeale frō
<pb n="17" facs="8"/>
the <hi>Fathers,</hi> to the <hi>Popes</hi> judgement, and so to mans mouth<note n="*" place="margin">Plus uni pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tif<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>i crederem, qu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m mille Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustinis. Corn. Mus, in Rom. <hi>3.4.</hi>
      </note>. But wee never appeale from <hi>them,</hi> but to <hi>Scripture,</hi> and so to <hi>GODS</hi> Mouth.</p>
   <p>Againe, to reject <hi>their</hi> say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges, when they are contrarie to <hi>Scripture,</hi> is thought <hi>piaculum</hi> in vs: But to reject <hi>them,</hi> when they are contrarie to the <hi>Popes</hi> Decrees, is thought onelie <hi>pium</hi> to them <note n="†" place="margin">Turre<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>r. sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>107 Also</hi> Stapicton, lib. <hi>7.</hi> de doct. prin. c. <hi>10.</hi> nec concilia, nec pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres, nec ullus alius, nisi papa controversiarū <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>ex est.</note>. In like manner, wee sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject <hi>Councels,</hi> and their dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, onelie to <hi>Scripture,</hi> and so vnto <hi>GOD</hi>: But they subject <hi>Councels,</hi> and their direction, to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and so to fraile man <note n="‡" place="margin">Bellar. l. <hi>2.</hi> de pont. c. <hi>27.</hi> in fine.</note> Wee esteeme likewise no man to bee exeemed from the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of a lawfull <hi>Councell,</hi> nor no flesh to bee aboue the same: But they advance their <hi>papall</hi> Dignitie aboue <hi>Councels</hi> in authoritie,
<pb n="18" facs="9"/>
and exeeme the same there-frae; not only in suffering &amp; correction, but also (as <hi>Terrecremata</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <note n="*" place="margin">Turrecr. sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>52. §. 9.</hi>
      </note>) in matter of doing and direction.</p>
   <p>The other particulars of their dealing with <hi>Antiquitie,</hi> I haue in some measure heere-after manisted more amplie; and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie cleared the same succinctlie out of their Grand <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> to avoyde thy distraction about ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie <hi>Bookes,</hi> and that <hi>(Gentle Reader)</hi> thou mayest haue the evidence out of one of best account with them, and moste obvious to vs, <hi>Et ut ex ungue Leonem,</hi> That thou mayest know the <hi>Lyon</hi> by his Paw, and rightlie consider, if so great evidence may bee had in one, or a fewe, how much more ample may bee had in the Writs of manie.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="19" facs="9"/>These paynes then, taken by mee heere-in for thine avayle, and excitation of others, accept thou graciouslie, censure charitablie, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>use profitablie, applie prudentlie, and the <hi>LORD</hi> giue thee the good, and His owne Name the Glorie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in CHRIST IESUS,</hi> W. Guild.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>