<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Christian READER.</title>
           <author>Stocke, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117806_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12980</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23273</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117806</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Christian READER.</title>
                 <author>Stocke, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The churches lamentation for the losse of the godly : deliuered in a sermon, at the funerals of that truly noble, and most hopefull young gentleman, Iohn Lord Harington, Baron of Exton, Knight of the noble order of the Bath, and his Maiesties lieutenaunt of the county of Rutland, at Exton in Rutland, the last day of March 1614. Together with a patterne of piety, and the power of godlinesse expressed in his life and death, who yeelded to nature the 27. of February, 1613. when he wanted two moneths of 22 yeeres of his age. By Richard Stock, pastor of Alhallowes-Breadstreet in London</title>
                 <author>Stock, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 105, 7 pages, illustrations, portraits (woodcuts), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <head>¶ To the Christian READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristiā reader who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer thou art, whether one that was an auditor of this sermon, or one that otherwise knowes me and my practise in this kind of funerall duties, If thou he of the first sort be informed, that in the sermon thou shalt find some few things ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not to the substance, but to the amplification of some vse, which I could not for the straightnes of time deliuer. In the commendations of this most commendable Noble thou shalt find some few things ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, which slipped out of my memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry at the time when I deliuered it, but not many; and the like number added which came to my knowledge
<pb facs="15"/> since. At also one thing displaced, namely his meditations vpon his sermons in the morning, which he did after dinner. I assure thee I haue set downe nothing, as I deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red nothing, but the true and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall grounds of euery particular, I knew my selfe; diuers particulars I receiued of others who are iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, honest, &amp; religious, agreeing al with the grounds of my own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, &amp; so as I had groūd to beleeue them, I knew nothing why I might not then, and now communicate them to thee, whereby I may profit thee by the blessing of God more, then my praise can honor him. But if thou art one of the second sort, knowing my vse to he very sparing in praising of the dead, and so may wonder I should be so plentifull in the commendations of this honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble gentleman, know, I neuer had such a subiect to speake of, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou respect nature or grace, his earthly or heauenly condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
   <pb facs="15"/>
   <p>For this cause I haue bin the more large, and specially because he was a publike person, more eies were vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and well they might be, for hee was not so eminent in place as he was in grace, for his gifts and graces &amp; power of religion were so excellent and rare, as I neuer yet knew in any, whom I had occasion to speake of I wish I might hereafter meet with some like him, but I haue little hope, though I do not despaire. If I find any deseruing as he did, I will not lessen their worthinesse nor darken their light, specially if they be publike persons. Yet mē must giue me leaue in all things, to goe vpon my owne grounds, and not tie me to their conceits. Affection of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten blindeth those who are speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally linked together, when it can not deceiue other;, who are a far of: often when friends highly thinke of their friends estate, the physition dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth better of their condition, and finds both spirits and bloud tainted, when they thinke they are
<pb facs="16"/> in good health. I would willingly set forth true golden vessels to the view of the world, but I haue no affection to gild potsheards. If I know mens liues I can the better iudge of their deaths, if I knew they haue liued well, I shall be better perswaded of their deaths: if euill, I shall be made to doubt much, of that, though it be seemingly good, yet <hi>I</hi> had rather thinke charitably then speake confidently. In this kind if I speake sparingly I pray men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> blame those who giue me no more ground, and not to reproue me, that dare not be so bold as some others, I will adde no more, neither will I longer detaine thee, gentle rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, from Gods word of life and death, nor from the life and death of this worthy noble. I pray God giue thee as much good by them, as I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to thee, to thy heart and life, and so farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord Iesus, RICHARD STOCKE.</signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="16"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>