<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST HIGH AND ALMIGHTY
God the Father, Creator of the World, and to the King of Kings,
Lord of Lords, and onely Ruler of Princes, Iesus Christ, the Glorious Redeemer
of the World, And to the most holy &amp; Blessed Spirit, the Comfort of all true Beleeuers,
and Sanctisier of the World, Three Persons, and one Eternall Omnipotent God.</title>
           <author>Taylor, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117734_Bo1_6_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13415</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23725</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117734</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST HIGH AND ALMIGHTY
God the Father, Creator of the World, and to the King of Kings,
Lord of Lords, and onely Ruler of Princes, Iesus Christ, the Glorious Redeemer
of the World, And to the most holy &amp; Blessed Spirit, the Comfort of all true Beleeuers,
and Sanctisier of the World, Three Persons, and one Eternall Omnipotent God.</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>All the vvorkes of Iohn Taylor the water-poet : Beeing sixty and three in number. Collected into one volume by the author: vvith sundry new additions, corrected, reuised, and newly imprinted, 1630</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Boler (Bowler), James 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Elizabeth.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 148, 2, 93, 92-200, 225-343, 1, 14, 13-146 pages, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb n="39" facs="26"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST HIGH AND ALMIGHTY
God the Father, Creator of the World, and to the King of Kings,
Lord of Lords, and onely Ruler of Princes, Iesus Christ, the Glorious Redeemer
of the World, And to the most holy &amp; Blessed Spirit, the Comfort of all true Beleeuers,
and Sanctisier of the World, Three Persons, and one Eternall Omnipotent God.</head>
   <p>MOst mighty, gracious, mercifull, and glorious God, that triest the
heart, and searchest the reines, from whom no secret is hid; in
the assurance of thy neuer-failing clemency, and hope of thy gracious
acceptance, I humbly offer to thy most dread Maiestie, these my poore
labours, which out of thine owne Word, and by and through thy bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
assistance, I haue (for the glory of thy great Name compiled) I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
my selfe the meanest of men, and the most vnworthy of thy
vnworthy seruants, to present my polluted &amp; imperfect duty to thee, that art the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
of perfection, purity and holinesse; but thou that knowest mine intentions meeke
and humble, free from the expectation of worldly applause, and onely ayming to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend
and reforme the too much, too frequent impieties of Cursing and Swearing, so hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
to thee, and so abusiue to thy Law, vpon the knees of my heart I prostrate my selfe
before the feete of thy Mercy seate, beseeching thee for thy Names sake (too much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned)
for thy Glories sake, too much abused, for thy Sonnes sake, who with thy selfe
art neglected, contemned and reuiled, that thou wilt be pleased to arise, O Lord, and
scatter thine enemies; that though this worke of mine bee but weake, and I the worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
far weaker, yet through my frailty be thou pleased to shew thy power; let my lines
be like <hi>Shamgars</hi> Goad, <hi>Iudges, 3 31.</hi> Like <hi>Iaels</hi> Nayle, <hi>Iudges 4.21.</hi> Or che Iawe-bone
which <hi>Samson</hi> fought withall, <hi>Iudges 15.</hi> Or <hi>Dauids</hi> Sling, <hi>1. Sam. 17.</hi> That (through
thy might) these accursed <hi>Philistines,</hi> with vncircumcised hearts, may be either amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
or confounded; That all the reuiling <hi>Rabshakehs</hi> may be made to know, that thou art
icalous of thy glory: so blesse, I beseech thee, these my labours, that children reading
them, may be seasoned with a feare and reuerence of thy Maiestic: that those who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
doe hate Cursing and Swearing, may hereby be the more confirmed in that godly
hatred: That the wretched carelesse blasphemers and accursed takers of thy Name in
vaine, may be ashamed &amp; reformed, that thereby thou maist be glorified, thy Church cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted
and edified, and our sinfull liues amended, and finally our soules euerlastingly sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,
through thy meere and infinite mercy, and our blessed Sauiours boundlesse merits:
To whom (with thee and the holy Ghost) be all praise, power and glory, now and for euer.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy Eternall Maiesties lowest and least
of thy vngracious seruants,
IOHN TAYLOR.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>