<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONEST AND friendly Reader.</title>
           <author>Howes, Edmund</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117863_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13042</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23332</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117863</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONEST AND friendly Reader.</title>
                 <author>Howes, Edmund</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The abridgement of the English Chronicle, first collected by M. Iohn Stow, and after him augmented with very many memorable antiquities, and continued with matters forreine and domesticall, vnto the beginning of the yeare, 1618. by E.H. Gentleman. There is a briefe table at the end of the booke</title>
                 <author>Stow, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>—English Stock</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>—English Stock</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 464, 467-486, 489-568, 44 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>TO THE HONEST AND friendly Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or thy sake with the rest of my louing Countrimen, and for the modest delight of other Nations, of what qualitie soe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, through the earnest perswasion of many my good friends, fauourers of knowledge, I was the rather induced to performe this businesse, and to arme my selfe with my best patience a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the daily iniuries and discurtesies which in these affaires I haue indured both in Court and Countrey, without the least part of pride or presumption on my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe. A time may come, to their disgrace, wherein I may retort their vndeserued malice. But as concerning the ignorant, proud and enuious, it will be hard for me to escape their braine-sicke imputation. For my owne part I acknowledge others excellency, and my owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sufficiency. What I haue done, was in a kinde of volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary necessitie; as is euident: for that euery man (so far as I could perceiue) though they thought it a very good worke, yet they held it no wisedome to run headlong into iudgement, and for the pleasure of others to waste their time, spend their money, displease superiors, and endure the cruell censure of the multitude, onely vpon hope of Master <hi>Stowes</hi> reward. All which, notwithstanding, for the generall good of all men, &amp; without intent of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb facs="6"/>
to any, seeing so many memorable accidents like to be buried in obliuion, I haue vndertaken sixteene yeares supplement, and enlarged it with very many memorable antiquities.</p>
   <p>And according to my promise I haue published my larger worke three yeares past. The manifold abuses which haue beene offered me by the shape of man, and the small respect by those of good spirit, and solide sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, haue so checkt my forwardnesse, that I stand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed, hauing already beene condemned, and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dged before I was tried, or heard to speake. What I haue written, is free from leazing: Be thou therefore of what Religion or condition soeuer, expect nothing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> contained, to be written for any purpose of flattery, time seruice, or offence: truth I sought, and truth is here set downe. Peace and good thoughts possesse thee. Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thy very louing friend,</hi> Edmond Howes.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>