<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>G., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117964_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01891</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12031</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117964</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>G., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The saints interest in God : opened in severall sermons, preached anniversarily upon the fifth of November. By John Goodwin pastor of S. Stephens Coleman-street</title>
                 <author>Goodwin, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Overton, Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Dawlman (Dolman), Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>64, 341, 3 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="23"/>
   <pb facs="23"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Good Reader:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether hee hath done wel or ill, whoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he was (be it my selfe, or some other) who was the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall of making more Presse-worke of these Sermons, I conceive it is not worth the lightest ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise
<pb facs="24"/>of thy thoughts, to consider, judge, or deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. If he hath done ill, doubtlesse it cannot bee much: things that are weake, though otherwise unusefull, yet will they serve for foile, to set off that which is strong with more grace and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; as the Thistle in Lebanon commends the stature and beauty of the Cedar in Lebanon. And the truth is, that many Bookes of worth and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue indeed, had need of some further recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,
<pb facs="24"/>in one kinde or other, unto men, then their owne worth: they suffer ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scurity, and neglect at the hands of men, this notwithstanding. Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinencies would be of great consequence, if they could bring things of consequence into request.</p>
   <p>If he hath done well, thou thy selfe wilt easily be perswaded to say, that this cannot be much: howsoever, in this point thou and I shall not much differ. Now then in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters where the difference
<pb facs="25"/>is very small, and almost imperceptible, a man may soone be out more in deliberation, then it is possible for him ever to recover, or get in againe by any resolution. As in suing at Law for a trifle, the victory or conquest, with all the advantages, will not defray the one halfe of the cost and charge of the Warre. I would gladly therefore save thee thy time and thoughts touching the premisses.</p>
   <p>Yet two things there
<pb facs="25"/>are, which have their plea in their mouthes (such as they are) for loosing their prisoners, and setting them at liberty in the world: The one is the occasion of their Preaching; the other, their argument or Subject.</p>
   <p>For the first, it was the Anniversary remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of that great bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle fought between Hell and Heaven, about the peace and safety of our Nation, on Novemb. <hi>5. 1605.</hi> wherein Hell was overthrowne, and Heaven
<pb facs="26"/>and We rejoyced together. I have not (to my present remembrance) met with any thing published of late of any speciall influence or tendency, to maintain the life and spirit of the solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity &amp; joy of that day and deliverance. And pity it is that such a Plant of Paradise should wither, or languish for want of watering. Such a deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, may, through the Mercy and Goodnesse of God, prove a breeder, and become a joyfull Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of many Children,
<pb facs="26"/>like unto her selfe, if the hearts of our Nation did converse with her more frequently, and more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionately.</p>
   <p>The Argument or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject discoursed in these Sermons, is, the true Church her Interest in God, with all her mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. A Subject (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse) that hath passed through many hands, and gained much of many: But the depth and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinesse of it is such, that it still calleth upon the greatest abilities of men,
<pb facs="27"/>to be further sought and inquired into. I assume nothing unto my selfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the discoveries of other men: if thou meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est with any thing, that may excuse or qualifie the Printing of the whole, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member him that said concerning a sinfull City, <hi>Gen. 18.32.</hi> I will not destroy it for ten righteous mens sake. If thou either desirest, or fearest the sight of any thing more of mine, thou maist make thine owne bargaine here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, by handling this piece
<pb facs="27"/>accordingly. For as for me, I am not conscious to my selfe, either of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnesse, or backward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of being made pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique: the tongues and judgements of men (if they could agree) may easily over-rule me either way. It argues some di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stemper of spirit, to be importune upon the world, with a mans private conceptions: neither is it the best posture, to put the world upon importunity with us, to purchase them, if they
<pb facs="28"/>have a minde to them.</p>
   <p>Pardon me thus far; and that which remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, I shall pray for thee, that thou maist with the Church, have Interest in God, and that this Interest may be established and confirmed unto thee by the reading this piece, untill, through fulnesse, thou breakest out with <hi>David,</hi> saying: <hi>The Lord is my Light, and my Salvation; Whom shall I feare?</hi> Psa. <hi>27.1.</hi> And by this time, when thou knowest not whom,
<pb facs="28"/>or what to feare, I hope thou wilt be at good lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, and in case to pray for him, who resteth</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord alwaies, I. G.</signed>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Colemonstreet</hi> Lond. <date>
            <hi>Aug. 7. 1640.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>