<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117744_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12535</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22859</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117744</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The common-vvelth of England : and maner of gouernment thereof. Compiled by the honorable Sir Thomas Smith, Knight, Doctor of both lawes, and one of the principall secretaries vnto two most worthie princes, King Edward, and Queen Elizabeth: with new additions of the cheef courts in England, the offices thereof, and their seuerall functions, by the sayd author: neuer before published. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Smith, Thomas, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 <publisher>Seton, Gregory.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 148 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O conceale the graces in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spired by God, or the gifts ingraffed by nature, or the vertues atchieued vnto our selues by industrie, in al ages, &amp; of all vvise men vvas accounted vndueti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, vnkindnes and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie vnto that Commonvvealth, in the vvhich, and vnto the vvhich vvare both bread and borne: but to suppresse the vvorthie vvorkes of any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, may iustlie be iudged not onelie iniurie to the person, but euen enuie at the vvhole vvorlde. Wherefore, chauncing vpon this short discourse, compiled by the honourable Knight Sir <hi>Thomas Smith,</hi> and considering that the same coulde not but be a great light vnto the ignorant, &amp; no lesse delight vnto the learned in the lavves and policie of sundrie Regiments: I thought it part of my duetie, as vvell for reuiuing of the fame of so nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a man, as for the publicke imparting of so pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie a Treatise, to present the same vnto thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different and discreete iudgement. Wherein al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the errors and rashnes of Scribes, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the contrarietie, and corruption of copies, happening both by the length of time since the first making, as also by the often transcripting,
<pb facs="3"/>
might iustlie haue beene mine excuse, or rather discourage: yet vveighing the authoritie of the Author together vvith the grauitie of the matter, I made no doubt but that the reuerence due vnto the one, and the recompence deserued by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vvould easilie counteruaile all faults commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a Clarke and vvriter. And vvhereas some termes or other matters may seeme to dissent frō the vsuall phrase of the common lavves of this Realme: notvvithstanding, to him that vvill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider that the profession of the maker vvas princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pallie in the ciuil lavves, and therefore not to bee expected as one excellent in both, and also that the finishing of this vvorke vvas in Fraunce farre from his Librarie, and in an ambassage euen in the midst of vvaightie affaires, it cānot nor ought not vvithout great ingratitude be displeasant or in any sort disliking. Wherefore (gentle Reader) accept in good part my zeale and this honorable mans trauaile, assuring thy selfe that the same framed by an expert vvorkemaster, and forged of pure and excellent mettall, vvill not faile in prouing to be a right commodious instrument.</p>
   <closer>Vale.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>