<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>DEDICATED
To theReader, you must note, that this Gentleman did send me from the Fairne Iland, a barrell of Gulls and Cormotant egges, by 
ing of which, I haue attained to the vnderstanding of many words which our Gulls and Cormotants doe speaks here abou, Sensible, Reasonable, Affable, Amiable, Acceptable,
minded, Honourable, in VVit, Iudgement, and Vnderstanding Able, Robert
Rugge Gentleman, Reare Adelantado of the Holy Iland, the Fairne, and
the Staples, on the Coast of Northumbria.</title>
           <author>Taylor, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117734_Bo1_28_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13415</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23725</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117734</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>DEDICATED
To theReader, you must note, that this Gentleman did send me from the Fairne Iland, a barrell of Gulls and Cormotant egges, by 
ing of which, I haue attained to the vnderstanding of many words which our Gulls and Cormotants doe speaks here abou, Sensible, Reasonable, Affable, Amiable, Acceptable,
minded, Honourable, in VVit, Iudgement, and Vnderstanding Able, Robert
Rugge Gentleman, Reare Adelantado of the Holy Iland, the Fairne, and
the Staples, on the Coast of Northumbria.</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>All the vvorkes of Iohn Taylor the water-poet : Beeing sixty and three in number. Collected into one volume by the author: vvith sundry new additions, corrected, reuised, and newly imprinted, 1630</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Boler (Bowler), James 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Elizabeth.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 148, 2, 93, 92-200, 225-343, 1, 14, 13-146 pages, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <head>DEDICATED
To the<note n="a" place="bottom">Reader, you must note, that this Gentleman did send me from the Fairne Iland, a barrell of Gulls and Cormotant egges, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>ing of which, I haue attained to the vnderstanding of many words which our Gulls and Cormotants doe speaks here abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>,</note> Sensible, Reasonable, Affable, Amiable, Acceptable,
minded, Honourable, in VVit, Iudgement, and Vnderstanding Able, Robert
Rugge Gentleman, Reare Adelantado of the Holy Iland, the Fairne, and
the Staples, on the Coast of Northumbria.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>No hanging Tap'strie, Quilt, or Couerlet,</l>
      <l>This dedication of my wit could get:</l>
      <l>No Mattresse, Blanket, Sheet, or Featherbed,</l>
      <l>Could haue these labours of my working head:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb n="126" facs="146"/>
      <l>But (cold by nature) from my Nurses dugge,</l>
      <l>My inclination still hath lou'd a <hi>Rugge:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Which makes my thankefull Muse thus bold to be,</l>
      <l>To consecrate this worthlesse worth to thee:</l>
      <l>Thou that within those happy Iles doest bide,</l>
      <l>Which Neptunes waues doe from our Land diuide,</l>
      <l>Where in the <hi>Holy Iland</hi> stands a Fort</l>
      <l>That can defend, and iniuries retort:</l>
      <l>That doth command a goodly Hauen nigh,</l>
      <l>Wherein a hundred ships may safely lye:</l>
      <l>Thou in the<note n="b" place="bottom">The <hi>Fairne Iland</hi> standing 7. miles from the <hi>Holy Iland</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sea, the <hi>Holy Iland</hi> stands seuen miles from <hi>Barwiske.</hi> In the <hi>Fairne</hi> all sorts of Sea-fowle breed in such abundance, as you cannot step but vpon Egges or Fowle: They misse not to lay on Saint <hi>Markes</hi> day, and a fortnight after Lammas there is none to be seene. The <hi>Staple Ilands</hi> belong to the <hi>Fairne,</hi> and stand two miles from it into the Sea, where the Fowle vpon the rockes (like pinacles) are so thicke both vpon the sides, and vpon the tops, and with such curiosity build their nests, as the wit of man cannot lay that egge in his place againe that is once taken vp, to abide in the same place. Vpon their flight the Sea is couered for halfe a mile, and the heauens aboue head obscured for the present.</note>
         <hi>Fairne</hi> and <hi>Staples</hi> bearst such sway,</l>
      <l>That all the dwellers there doe thee obey:</l>
      <l>Where <hi>Fowle</hi> are all thy faire inhabitants,</l>
      <l>Where thou (Commander of the <hi>Cormorants</hi>)</l>
      <l>Grand Gouernour of <hi>Guls,</hi> of <hi>Geese</hi> and <hi>Ganders,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>O'r whom thou art none of the leaft Commanders:</l>
      <l>Whereas sometimes thou canst not stirre thy legs,</l>
      <l>But thou must tread on tributary egs:</l>
      <l>For they like honest, true, plaine-dealing folkes,</l>
      <l>Pay thee the custome of their whites and yolkes,</l>
      <l>Which to thy friends oft-times transported be,</l>
      <l>As late thou sentst abarrell-full to me:</l>
      <l>And in requit all to so good a friend,</l>
      <l>This <hi>Prison,</hi> and this <hi>Hanging</hi> here I send.</l>
      <l>Because within the<note n="c" place="bottom">There is but one house there, all the dwellers else be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
               <desc>•••</desc>
            </gap> Sea-fowle, who will neither know offences not punish<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
               <desc>•••</desc>
            </gap>.</note>
         <hi>Fairne</hi> and <hi>Staples</hi> teo,</l>
      <l>The dwellers doe as they doe please to doe.</l>
      <l>Their pride and lust, their stealing and their treas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>,</l>
      <l>Is all impouted to their want of reason:</l>
      <l>I therefore haue made bold to send thee this,</l>
      <l>To shew them what a <hi>Iayle</hi> and <hi>Hanging</hi> is.</l>
      <l>Thou hast from <hi>Hermes</hi> suck'd the Quintessence</l>
      <l>Of quicke Inuention, and of Eloquence:</l>
      <l>And thou so well doest loue good wittie Bookes,</l>
      <l>That makes thee like <hi>Apollo</hi> in thy lookes:</l>
      <l>For nature hath thy visage so much grac'd,</l>
      <l>That there's the ensigne of true friendship plac'd.</l>
      <l>A chaulkie face, that's like a pewter spoone,</l>
      <l>Or buttermilke, or greene cheese, or the meone,</l>
      <l>Are either such as kill themselues with care,</l>
      <l>Or hide-bound miserable wretches are.</l>
      <l>Giue me the man, whose colour and prospect,</l>
      <l>Like <hi>Titan</hi> when it doth on gold reflect;</l>
      <l>And if his purse be equall to his will,</l>
      <l>Hee'l then be frolicke, free, and iouiall still:</l>
      <l>And such a one (my worthy friend) art thou,</l>
      <l>To whom I dedicate this Pamphlet now;</l>
      <l>And I implore the Heau'ns to proue so kinde,</l>
      <l>To keepe thy state according to thy minàe.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours with my best wishes,
IOHN TAYLOR.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>