<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ An Aduertisement to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117875_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13156</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23450</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117875</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ An Aduertisement to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvvere to a certaine libel supplicatorie, or rather diffamatory : and also to certaine calumnious articles, and interrogatories, both printed and scattered in secret corners, to the slaunder of the ecclesiasticall state, and put forth vnder the name and title of a petition directed to her Maiestie: vvherein not onely the friuolous discourse of the petitioner is refuted, but also the accusation against the disciplinarians his clyents iustified, and the slaunderous cauils at the present gouernement disciphred by Mathew Sutcliffe</title>
                 <author>Sutcliffe, Matthew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barker, Christopher, Deputies of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 208, 6 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="115"/>
   <head>❧ An Aduertisement to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas in the former discourse somewhat hath bene said in answere of the Petitioners lewd ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniations concerning the triall of <hi>Iohn Vdal,</hi> and the iudgement not long since pronounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him, which he pretendeth to be disorderlie and iniurious, it may be that such as list to cauill at such things as they mislike, will take exceptions against the same, as if I meant to abase the high authoritie of Iudges, or make the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the highest courtes of Iustice an argument for the rude populasse to dispute of, or to subiect the ordinarie trials of law to the controlment, or at least canuases of priuate persons. Least any should either in this behalfe except against me, or enter into any such con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of me, I thought good expresly here to aduertise thee, that both my words and meaning are contrary.</p>
   <p>Concerning matters of common Iustice betwixt partie and partie, I know that no iudgement is reuersed but by writ of errour, and that in matters concerning the Crowne, the verdicts of Iurors and senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Iudges for the Queene are finall, and that the lawe doeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, that Iudges and Iurors will proceede with that indifferencie and equitie, that it will not haue their doings controlled nor exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by priuate persons. Neither is it any part of my meaning to call any law in question, or controll the doings of so honourable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons as in that fact sate Iudges. Nay this is the thing which I doe so much reprehend in the Petitioner and his faction, that most saucilie and arrogantly they take vpon them to examine the doings of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the actes of Parliament, the sentences of Iudges, the verdicts of Iuries, and all recordes of Iustice. Neither is there any companion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them so base, but he taketh to himselfe libertie to censure and controll Princes, Parliaments, Iudges, Lawes, yea whatsoeuer, and whomsoeuer. Among others, the author of the Petition hath beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued himselfe as presumptuouslie and proudly, as the best. Ignorance
<pb facs="116"/>belike maketh him bolde:<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> the rather for that it is ioyned with impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie. What through presumption, and what through impudencie he hath taken vpon him contrary to the Iurors verdict and Iudges sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, to prooue <hi>that Vdall offended not against that statute of 23. Eliz. cap. 2.</hi> whereupon he was condemned.</p>
   <p>This notorious impudencie and presumption, I thought good to lay open before mens eyes: and therefore hauing vndertaken to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere others of the mans bold assertions and forged accusations of the ecclesiasticall state; I thought it not amisse withall to touch his bolde demeanour against Iudges, and presumptuous censure of their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. Not that I meant to make priuate men Iudges of their superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, but that you may see the boldnesse of them that spare none that are not of their humors, and reuell both at the Clergie and Iudges.</p>
   <p>If the proceedings of magistrates were not iustifiable, yet is this course which these men haue taken very lewd and offensiue. How much more offensiue then will it seeme, when it appeareth that the Iudges haue proceeded according to lawe, and done not onely Iustice, but shewed great mercie and fauour to the partie? And how wiselie doeth this man seeme to haue pleaded for his client, when I thinke himselfe will not denie, but that hee liueth rather by mercy, then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merite? that he was most fauourably dealt withall, all that were by will witnesse, and himselfe I thinke will not denie: if he should, very many arguments would conuince him.</p>
   <p>For first, whereas diuers seditious Sermons might haue bene ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected against him, he was onely endited for his seditious practises in making and publishing the booke of Demonstration of Discipline, as they lewdly call it.</p>
   <p>Secondly, whereas <hi>Chatfield</hi> could haue spoken diuers things very materiall against him, yet was he not forced to come to testifie.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, being by diuers witnesses, and great euidence, sufficient to induce any Iury to passe against him, conuinced, yet had he this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, to be asked, for satisfying the Iury, and clearing himselfe, if he would take it either vpon his conscience, yea or credite, that he was not the author of that booke, and might percase haue escaped, if he
<pb facs="116"/>durst haue denied so plaine a matter. Seeing he would neither af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme vpon his conscience, nor credite, his innocencie, what reason should the Iury haue had, to take that vpon their conscience, which the partie himselfe would not take either vpon his conscience, or cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite?</p>
   <p>Lastly, although the sentence of law be passed vpon him, yet is the execution of lawe differred. Wherein if he doe not acknowledge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe fauourably dealt withall, all men will acknowledge, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serueth litle fauour.</p>
   <p>The obiections and exceptions brought by the Libeller, are most false, and friuolous. He saith, <hi>that there is no offence in writing that booke, committed against the statute of 23.</hi> Eliz. cap. <hi>2.</hi> Wherein he crosseth the sentence of the Iudges, and most wise men of this lande: and speaketh most euident vntrueth. For if railing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst her Maiesties Ecclesiasticall lawes, and gouernment, and see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the subuersion of it, be no offence, these fellowes challenge to themselues great impunitie and licence.</p>
   <p>He auoweth, <hi>that it was not prooued that one man made the booke, and the Epistle before the booke,</hi> which is not mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall: for if he writte the wordes conteined in the enditement, then was the enditement truely found. Besides, the same is vntrueth: for it is absurd to surmise, where a man publisheth a booke, that another setteth to the Epistle. and he that made the Epistle, doeth in termes auowe the booke. Neither skilleth it, that some haue thought that <hi>Penry</hi> had his hand in it, for that doeth not hinder, but that <hi>Vdal</hi> might also be a doer in it. But what neede we other argument to prooue this withall, then that <hi>Vdal</hi> would not disauow either Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, or booke? or what neede any dispute about the difference of the Epistle, and booke, seeing the enditement compriseth both vnder the name of booke, and both doe followe the title?</p>
   <p>That which he saith, <hi>that he was conuicted for the Epistle, and the euidence brought for the booke,</hi> is vntrue: for the eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence was brought for both. And very improbable it were, that any should be condemned for matter without the enditement, or that
<pb facs="117"/>there should in the enditement be made a difference betwixt the booke and the Epistle.</p>
   <p>These things considered, let all men iudge whether it be likely, that <hi>Iohn Vdal</hi> should be condemned guiltlesse? and whether the bare affirmation of a man lying desperately, should be taken against the deposition of witnesses, recordes of the Court, verdict of the Iury, and sentence of so graue and religious a Bench, especially the man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so guilty, and the case so plaine? His very friendes condemned him, and his owne conscience accused him.<note place="margin">Chatfields deposition.</note>
      <hi>Chatfield</hi> deposeth, <hi>that he sawe papers in</hi> Vdals <hi>Studie, conteining libellous matter, which himselfe wished</hi> Vdal <hi>to make away:</hi> and confesseth, that Vdal <hi>saide to him in choller, that the Bishops had best to take heede howe they stopped his mouth, for if they did, he would fall on writing, and giue them such a blowe, as they neuer had in their liues.</hi> Which blowe could not be vnderstoode, but of that whereof he was conuicted. In his Sermons he fell often vpon the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of his booke, which considered, with other circumstances, may shewe him guiltie: yea, and so guiltie, that being demanded by the Bench, he could not deny it: no, though he might haue saued his life by the deniall, and renunciation of the booke.</p>
   <p>Seeing then all this notwithstanding, the mans innocencie is in a booke (publikely diuulgued) defended against such notorious euidence, and vpright proceedings; who doeth not see, that I haue reason to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test the notorious presumption of such censors? If any deserue blame, not they that speake in defence of iustice, but those that traduce it are to be blamed. That therefore which was well meant, without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie to any, receiue with fauour: and if in this matter thou wilt shewe signes of displeasure, let not the innocent, but such as presumptuously reprehend, and by faction seeke to ouerthrowe lawe, and iustice, feele it.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>