<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1563</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117552_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00685</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10819</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117552</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ane answer to ane epistle written by Renat Benedict : the Frenche doctor, profesor of Gods worde (as the translator of this epistle calleth him) to Iohn Knox, and the rest of his brethren ministers of the word of God: made by Dauid Feargussone minister of the same word at this present in Dumfermling</title>
                 <author>Fergusson, David</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lekpreuik, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1563</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="2" facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <head type="sub">Dauid Feargussone vnto the Reader wisheth grace mercy and peace from God the Father, and from our Lord Iesus Christ with y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> spirit of righteous iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dgement.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue not interprised (belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued brethrē in Christ Iesus) to answer this Epistle as one more able so to do, then the rest of my fellowes in office: but rather driuen thereunto by the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessant requeist of some zealous and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie persones, who broght it to my hādes for that purpose, after that it had bene caried as a matter of great importance from one place to an other: &amp; so at length translated by an certane Freir out of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine into Inglish in fauor of suche perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>es <note place="margin">What mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> ued me to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> wryt.</note> as he thereby wold gratifie) it wes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>reatlie bosted of: partlie therefore to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ffie the reasonable requeist of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>aid persones, and also to stop the mouth
<pb facs="3"/>
of the aduersarie frome further braging but chiefly for the discharge of my consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the office whereunto God hath called me. I haue occupyed my pen in answering as after followeth. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thogh this pithles Epistle haue lytle or no strength to deceaue any that haue but meanly teasted of the treuth, yet because it may be a peice of help to hold them stil in error that are as yet within it (in my iudgement it wold not be past ouer in si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence) nether do I know whither any man hath vnto this hour answered it or not. For asmuch as I se it a thing which all learned men will not onely laugh at, and so contempe it, as not worthy of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer but also iudge it suche a mater as they will spend no tyme vpon, seinge that they may be better occupyed nor to āswer a foole accordig to his folie: but list <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>c. 26</note> he est came him self wise in his owne cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite. I haue thoght good to write sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in this mater: vnto the which wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting I haue added my name, nor for vain <note place="margin">Why I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sit my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e.</note>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>lorie God knowes, but to this end one li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>, that when the Reader shal find the reules of Rethorick transgressed, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Eloquence omitted (no man be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="3" facs="3"/>
but I allone (moreouer if it shal hap pen that I be sumwhates longer then ye wold wishe, werie not yet I beseche you to reid it to the end, for certanely as I suppose no man is able fully to answer this ordorles confused Chaos without many wordes. To the end therefor that ye may the better vnderstande the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (because this mans letter kepeth no certane ordor) so far as the confusione of it will suffer. I haue deuided it, and that in four Sectionis: first writing his wordes faithfully as they are translated, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after my answer. Fair well deare brethren in Christe Iesus our onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and iudge with equitie.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>