<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           <author>Browne, Gregory</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117656_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12609</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22931</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117656</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 <author>Browne, Gregory</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Ottoman of Lazaro Soranzo : VVherein is deliuered aswell a full and perfect report of the might and power of Mahamet the third, great Emperour of the Turkes now raigning: together with the interestes and dealinges which he hath with sondrie other princes, what hee is plotting against the state of Christendome, and on the other side what we may practise and put in execution against him to his great damage and annoyaunce. As also a true description of diuers peoples, countries, citties and voyages, which are most necessarie to bee knowen, especially at this time of the present warre in Hungarie. Translated out of Italian into English, by Abraham Hartvvell</title>
                 <author>Soranzo, Lazzaro</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 <publisher>Windet, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 107, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ven as for Princes that would learne
wel to gouerne and maintaine them
selues, aswell in time of peace, as of
warre, there is no one thing more
necessarie, then the knowledge, first
of their owne affaires, and next of
the state of other principalities, (as
those do write, who haue the greatest vnderstanding in ciuil
causes, &amp; as Experience it selfe doth manifestly declare:) so
is it most fit and cōuenient for them, to vse their vttermost
care &amp; diligence, that they may haue perfect skill &amp; discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
to iudge betweene truth and falshood. For if the second
part of their knowledge, I meane touching other mens states
&amp; Principalities: (for of the first it is not my purpose to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course)
bee not founded and established vpon truth, it will
neuer be possible that their counsailes shall sort to any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite
or aduauntage, because it is well knowne, that a false
information, either of a speech, or of an Astion, or of a
place, may oftentymes breed no lesse damage, and daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
then a Counseller that is either of small capacitie, or
else a lyer, or a Captaine that hath neither wisdome nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience.
And therefore verie greatly are those Princes to
be commended, who not onely endeuour to enforme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
of the wittes and loyaltie of their owne seruants, but
also for the more certaintie how matters do passe in truth,
maintaine either at home in Court, or abroad in forreine




<pb facs="7"/>
places, Men of learning, and of practise: the one for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
of Historie, and properly appertaining to good ciuill go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment,
and the other for the knowledge of the estates,
inclinations, designements, interests, treasures, armour,
weapons, confederacies, preparations, and all the forces of
other Princes: whereunto may be added also as a matter of
great impertance to know those Countries, which haue not
onely beene knowne many a yeare ago, but also those that
haue beene lately dicouered, or may hereafter bee made
knowne to the world. In respect whereof, assuredly aboue
all other <hi>Don Iohn</hi> king of Portugall, and <hi>Isabell</hi> of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon,
are most worthie of eternall memorie, for the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerie
of the East Indies, and of the new world, which was
performed by their fauour and assistance. And the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
of that which hath beene said, is this, touching the first,
because such matters hauing beene reported or written, for
the most part either to please, or for some aduātage, or falsly
penned by persons that neuer were present at the Action, or
for feare haue concealed the truth, their reports and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings
haue need of great caution &amp; censure, before they be
beleeued: and touching the second, because one eye-witnes, as
the Poet sayth, is more certaine &amp; worthy of beleefe, then a
thousand eare-witnesses, as they do most manifestly approue,
who by the view of their own eies, which they haue made in
diuerse Prouinces, do find &amp; acknowledge, that in bookes of
Cosmographie, Geography &amp; Chorographie, there be many
faults and errors to be noted in the gouernement of sundry
principalities, in the maners and customs of diuerse peoples,
and in the true situation of seuerall places and Countreyes:
besides many other tales and fables, which are here and
there dispersed, as well in writers of old, as in writers of late
times, and onely because the Authours of them haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten




<pb facs="7"/>
and recorded either all these matters, or at least verie
many of them, without euer seeing any part of them, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring
themselues wholy to the ancient descriptions, which
in deed do not fully answere to the knowledge and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
of these dayes, and without iustifying the same by such
persons as haue not onely seene them, which euery common
Curseters and prating cousener, can also do: but also such as
haue had the skill to obserue euery action, and an intent
truly to report it againe. <hi>Homer</hi> called <hi>Vlysses</hi> a wise
man, (which is the goodliest title that can bee giuen to a
Prince, or to a Captaine) not because he had heard, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
hee noted and obserued the manners and customes
of sundrie peoples, and sawe many Cities. And peraduenture
it was the reason which moued <hi>Plato</hi> to make a law, that
none of his Citizens should trauaile abroad before hee was
xl. yeares olde, to the end that being growen wise by age, he
might with more iudgemēt obserue the affairs of the world,
and then report them to his Countrey for the common be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite
thereof. True it is that those Princes, which doe not
willingly admit any trafficke with straungers, contrary to
the law and course of all Nations, as for example the Mos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couite,
and Presbyter Iohn, but especially and aboue al other
the Princes of China, who being strengthned by fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
and keeping continuall watch and ward for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose,
will not suffer their subiects to passe or trauell into for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine
Countries, because they hold <hi>Platoes</hi> opinion to bee
true, which he setteth downe in his common wealth, that
strange fashions and customes may corrupt home-borne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures:
such princes (I say) haue no neede in deed, to be any
diligent inquisitors or searchers of other mens actions. But
for other states, that with all humane intertainment and
entercourse do admit all forreiners, and cōuerse kindly with




<pb facs="8"/>
them, and embrace their enterests and confederacies, and
therfore are more strongly &amp; entirely enforced of necessitie
to guard themselues from their neighbors that are of great
power &amp; might, to the end they may the better maintaine
their owne seigni<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uries and dominions: for such states (I
say) it is great reason &amp; verie conuenient, that they should
throughly informe themselues, &amp; endeuour to their vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most,
not only ingeneralitie, but also in euery particularitie
to vnderstand all matters whatsoeuer which may be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
not vnto priuate Interestes and commodities, such as,
matters of trafficke, and marchandizes be, but to the state
of the whole common wealth, which are properly belonging
to Princes themselues. For as we do read written Hystories
to the end we may learne how to gouerne and manage mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
aswell present as to come, by vnderstanding and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
how things haue fallen out, that haue beene hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
recorded in particularitie: so ought we also to knowe
how the affaires of the world do presently stand, to the ende
we may prouide remedies in time, and meete with all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences
according to the generall knowledge which
we haue learned by our reading: for such is the course and
order of our knowledge, that by singularities we proceede to
the notice of vniuersalities. And therefore the Venetian
Magnificoes, who are not meanely exercised and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced
in matters of state, do not onely send vnto other prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
such Embassadors as are of quicke wit and conceit, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the custome of other principalities, but also haue
established for a lawe, that at their returne they shall in the
Senate make a true and particular report of the Prince and
state, with whom they haue beene Ledgers during the time
of their Embassage: and so by that meanes they shall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct
the yonger sort, which are trained vp in the studie of




<pb facs="8"/>
politike affaires, to be the better enabled for the seruice of
their Countrey. And to the same purpose, that their Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon-wealth
may be also better gouerned, as well by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
of such matters as haue alreadie passed, as also by the
fresh information of things presently in action, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue
and keepe the said writings with great faithfulnesse
and secrecie in a Register especially appoynted therevnto.
And this was the cause, that I perceyuing how the actions of
the Turkes, were publikely either too much extenuated and
diminished, or else beyond all truth magnified, and enlarged
rather vpon want of true instruction and information, then
vpon any sting of passionate affections, which oftentimes
make report of many matters to diuerse priuate persons ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
indiscreetly, and inconsiderately, began to bethinke my
selfe, that it could not choose but proue verie profitable to
the state of Christendome, if I would take vpon me the care
to examine the present estate of the Turkish Empire, and
endeuour to discouer the disignements which that Prince
hath plotted against the Christians, in the best manner I
could. And forasmuch as it is not alwayes good, to giue too
much credite to auncient Records, though they be neuer so
true, because Principalities and states are easily altered and
chaunged, either vpon the nature or disposition of the new
succeeding Prince, or vpon condition and circumstance of
time, or vpon some other accident: (yea and so much the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
for that the Venetian records which were woont to be
most faithfull and sincere, are not now imparted or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated
to any man by a speciall prohibition which they
haue made amongst themselues, the auncient reportes also
beeing now to no purpose, and the briefe that is ordinarily
deliuered abroad, being rather imagined and full of errors
then containing matter of truth) I haue resolued with my




<pb facs="9"/>
selfe, to be more diligently enformed, as farre as possibly I
could, of all those particulars which I thought meet and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie
to bee knowne in these times, because I am verily
perswaded, that the present warre now in hand, is a matter
of the greatest consequence that is at this time currant in
the world. All which I haue done vpon speciall and priuate
conference that I haue had with persons of great experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
and iudgement, who are lately come out of those parts,
not trusting mine owne selfe in such matters, which I haue
heretofore seene, and oftentimes verie deeply considered of.
And so at last I haue reduced the whole into a briefe or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious
Method, for the benefit and seruice of Christian
princes, &amp; specially of those, who in regard of their interests
with the Turke, haue greatest neede of such information.
For seeing I was not able, by reason of mine infirmitie, to
follow the warres, as <hi>I</hi> ought to haue done, after the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
of <hi>Benedict Soranzo</hi> my father, who died at the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest
of <hi>Gorzolari</hi> in fighting against the Turkes, yet had
I a desire at the least to doe some seruice to the common-wealth,
which alloweth it to be a matter lawfull for euerie
man to labour and write, as <hi>Polyaenus</hi> of Macedonie
writte to the Emperours <hi>Antoninus</hi> and <hi>Verus,</hi> rather
then by choosing to liue idle and free to my selfe, I shoulde
seeme altogither vnprofitable and vnfruitfull to all others.
So did <hi>Diogenes,</hi> when the rest of the valiant and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious
Citizens were verie busie in defending the walles
of their Countrey, he went vp and downe in the Market
place, rolling his Tunne to and fro, because he alone would
not be idle (as he said) whiles other were valiantly labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
with their weapons.</p>
   <p>And therefore in this discourse or report, I will entreate
of the Ottoman Empire and specially vnder <hi>Mahamet</hi> the




<pb facs="9"/>
third, vntill the yeare 1597. The time I do of purpose set
downe, because I know verie well, that the euent and suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse
of warre may alter many things, according to the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabilitie
of the Prince, or necessitie of sundrie occasions,
which euen to this houre haue altered and changed sundry
matters. And this will I doe principally and chiefly regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
that which apperteyneth to the knowledge of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
warre, which the Turke now wageth agaynst the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour,
and the Transiluanian, or any other matter, which
by occasion of the same warre may fall out to be conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.
For if I would haue vndertaken a longer course, I
should haue too much enlarged this volume, peraduenture
to the griefe and tedious conceits of other men. Besides
that a great part of the remnant of this hystorie, I haue at
large extended in other my writings, and part thereof I
may perhappes performe in other occasions. Howbeit I will
not forbeare to tell you of many matters, especially of such
as may be at all times profitable and beneficiall to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendome:
to the ende, that aswell those which liue at this
day, as also those which shall succeede vs in posteritie may
in some sort reape some benefite and pleasure of this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,
wherein that I may proceed methodically, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly,
I will distinguish and diuide this present relation in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
three parts.</p>
   <p>In the first it shall be entreated of the Head, of the
Members, and of the forces of the Ottoman Empyre.</p>
   <p>In the second, of the Cogitations and Designements of
the Turkish Prince: of the causes of this present warre, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
with the beginning and proceedings thereof: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
for the better vnderstanding of euery thing, the original
of the said warre shall be fetched and repeated, euen from
<hi>Amurath,</hi> father to this liuing <hi>Mahamet.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="10"/>
In the third and last, it shall be discoursed, that suppose
the Grand Turke will be reconciled, whether it be good for
the Emperour, and the Transiluanian, to entertaine peace
wiih him. Wherein also many matters shall be discouered,
which (if the warre shall continue) may be plotted agaynst
him by the said Princes, and which at all times may bee
practised by other Christian Princes, to meete with such
perils and dangers as are now imminent, or any other
which may hereafter light vpon Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendome
by the Ottoman
forces.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>