<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117628_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12533</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22857</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117628</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>De republica Anglorum : The maner of gouernement or policie of the realme of England, compiled by the honorable man Thomas Smyth, Doctor of the ciuil lawes, knight, and principall secretarie vnto the two most worthie princes, King Edwarde the sixt, and Queene Elizabeth. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Smith, Thomas, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 <publisher>Day, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Middleton, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Seton, Gregory</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 119, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O conceale the graces inspired by God, or the giftes ingraffed by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or the vertues at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiued vnto our selues by industrie, in all ages and of all wise men was accounted vnduetiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, vnkindnesse &amp; impietie vnto that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, in the which, and vnto the which we are both bred and borne: but to suppresse the worthie works of any author, may iustly be iudged not only iniurie to the person, but euen enuie at the whole world. VVherefore chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing vpon this short discourse compiled by the honorable knight sir Thomas Smyth, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering that the same could not but be a great light vnto the ignorant, &amp; no lesse delight vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the learned in the lawes and policie of sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie regiments: I thought it part of my dutie, aswel for reuiuing of the fame of so notable a man, as for the publike imparting of so pythie a treatise, to present the same vnto thy indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and discreete iudgement. VVherein al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the errors &amp; rashness of Scribes, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the contrarietie &amp; corruption of cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies,
<pb facs="3"/>
happening both by the length of time si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens the first making, as also by the often tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scripting might iustly haue been mine excuse or rather discourage: yet weying the authoritie of the author togither with the grauitie of the matter, I made no doubt but that the reuerence due vnto the one, &amp; the recompence deserued by the other would easily counteruail all faults committed by a clarke &amp; writer. And whereas some termes or other matters may seme to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent from the vsual phrase of the cōmon lawes of this realme: not withstanding to him that will consider that the profession of the maker was principally in the ciuil lawes, and therefore not to be expected as one excellent in both, &amp; also that the finishing of this worke was in Fraunce farre from his librarie, and in an ambassad euen in the midst of waightie affaires, it cannot nor ought not without great ingratitude be disple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant or in any sort disliking. VVherefore (gentle Reader) accept in good part my zeale and this honorable mans trauaile: assuring thy self that the same framed by an expert workemaister, and forged of pure and excellent mettall, will not faile in proouing to be a right commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous instrument.</p>
   <closer>Vale.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>