<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Praeface of Iohn Serranus vpon the Booke of Solomon, called Ecclesiastes, or the Preacher, conteining the Argument and Contents of the Books.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117199_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11933</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22247</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117199</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Praeface of Iohn Serranus vpon the Booke of Solomon, called Ecclesiastes, or the Preacher, conteining the Argument and Contents of the Books.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A godlie and learned commentarie vpon the excellent book of Solomon, commonly called Ecclesiastes, or the Preacher : in the vvhich commentarie are briefely and plainly layde downe the methode, sense, and vse of that most profitable sermon, on the which, yet there hath neuer bin set forth any exposition in the English tong before this time, in such large and profitable manner. VVritten in Latin by Iohn Serranus, and newly turned into English by Iohn Stockwood, school-master of Tunbridge</title>
                 <author>Serres, Jean de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 <publisher>Harrison, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 445, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>
      <hi>A Praeface of Iohn Serranus vpon the Booke of Solomon, called Ecclesiastes, or the Preacher, conteining</hi> the Argument and Contents of the Books.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the beginning certain pointes seeme to be set down in the way of a Praeface concerning the authoritie ende, method, and vse of this Booke: that these matters being vnderstood, a more sure and fit way may be made vnto the reading of this most excellent Sermon and also vnto the most notable profit which thereby may and ought to come vnto vs.</p>
   <p>Because that some doe doubt of the person of <hi>Solomon,</hi> it co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>eth to passe that hereby they take occasion of impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>ng not only the authoritie of this Sermon, but also of all other his writinges: as if the same priuiledge of credite and authoritie were not to be giuen vnto them, which is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the canonicall Scriptures.</p>
   <p>And concerning <hi>Solomon,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Sundrie opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of Solomō</note> the opinions of the learned are diuerse, and that for most weighty considerations, for in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of the notable testimonies of the goodnesse of God towardes him, some thinke very well of his saluation, and holde that there is no doubt to bee made of the same, albeit he fell into a most foule fault, the whiche coulde not make voyde in him the excellent giftes of God: amongest the whiche, that gift of forgiuenesse of sinnes not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of, and the foundation of the same, the eternall ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of God, obteyneth the first place: and therefore that it is not meete that by reason of such a faulte wee shoulde
<pb facs="6"/> doubt of his saluation, no lesse then of manye other holye men, whose notable faultes are playnely sette downe in the bookes of the scripture, to the ende that in this miserye of man his infirmitie and weakenesse we might perceiue the stedfastnesse of GOD his mercye, making those whome he will,<note place="margin">The reasons of them that doubt of the saluation of Solomon.</note> worthye of eternall life. Some others doe in suche sorte weigh the circumstances of his most greeuous sinne, that they make a very great doubt of his saluation. For the Scripture doth flatly set downe, that the heart of Solomon went aside from the God of Israell, and that by foule abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of the goodnesse of God towards him, as vnto whome God had appeared twise. Moreouer that this fell oute vnto him at the last ende almost of his life, after so manye and so great tokens of God his mercye and liberalitie towardes him, in that age, wherein if euer, he ought in deede to haue had bene wise. That it was also a shamefull kinde of fault a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst true religion, the which in the faythfull (howsoeuer they are sometimes diuerslye carried awaye of their owne lustes) doth take such deepe roote, that it cannot chuse at al times, but bring forth most plentiful fruit of reuerence and constancy. To conclude, that there appeareth no testimonye of his repentance, and that the renting asunder of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which within short time followed, doeth teache that God did in no wise forgiue vnto him this fault.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The minde of the Author touching the saluation of Solomon.</note>Doubtlesse the fault of <hi>Solomon</hi> was most greeuous, and cannot by any meanes be excused. For that hee whiche had receiued suche singuler giftes of GOD aboute the laste tyme of his lyfe, did of wicked rashnesse fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye vnto Superstition, and to the offence of the church and destruction of manye, did sette vp publike Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and tokens of that his fallinge awaye, it is a thing so shamefull, as is that whiche is moste shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
   <p>Yet are not these thinges to this ende set downe vnto vs, that we shoulde take vpon vs so muche authoritie ouer the secret iudgementes of God, that wee shoulde conclude so singular a person whome the Lorde woulde haue to be a Figure of his Christe, to bee appoynted vnto euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting destruction, wherefore as it is a pointe of rashnesse certaynely to pronounce of so weightye a matter: so on
<pb facs="6"/> the contrarye parte, it is a token of safenesse and modestye, in matters of suche importaunce, and nothing at all apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning vnto our knowledge, by staying oure iudgement to be wise out of the worde of God, and there out only to gather those thinges whiche hee will haue of vs to bee knowne.</p>
   <p>The fall then of so excellente a personage,<note place="margin">To what ende the fal of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon is set forth vnto vs</note> is therefore set forth vnto vs, that we should knowe with howe great care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse we ought to walke betweene the sleightes of the Deuill and sinne, in whose snares the best men are somtimes entrapped: and moreouer that we holilye vse the giftes of God, least being puffed vp with them, we bee depriued of his grace, of the which being voyde, and trusting vnto our strength, we must needes runne headlong into assured de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction. Further the expresse and plaine setting downe of the faulte of Solomon, appertayneth vnto the Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye following of the scattering of the kingdome of Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, the cause whereof to haue rested in the posterity of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> is playnely proued by this notable sinne of Solomon. But for all this, whatsoeuer may bee determined eyther of the saluation or damnation of Solomon,<note place="margin">The fal of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon is no discredit to his writings, And why?</note> this notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing must be holden for certaintye, that the reproche of his falling awaye or punishment, maketh nothing at all agaynste his Writinges, and that therefore the authority of them is not hereby lessened nor diminished: For as muche as Solomon is not the Author, but onlye the Writer and interpreter of the truth in them conteyned and taughte, for the authoritie of doctrine must not hang vpon the person of the minister, but altogether vpon the dignitye of the Author. And there is nothing, eyther in this or in the rest of the writinges of Solomon, the which doeth not very well agree with the truth of the Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, the which is all one and simple truth: as with one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured consent, the learned and right minded antiquity hath acknowledged: and the Hebrew copie it selfe numbred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the holye writinges doeth sufficiently declare.</p>
   <p>Therefore I will not make anye longer staye in the proofe of that matter, the whiche I set downe as sure, and agreede vppon: namelye, that the writinges of Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and also this Sermon, are Canonicall Scripture,
<pb facs="7"/> and plainely agree with the truth, and that God would haue them remaine abroade for the edifying of his Ghurch. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye we are to begge of him that we may learn the pure and true meaning of this Sermon, and applye it vnto oure profite.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The cheefe and or scope of this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course.</note>Hauing layde downe the authoritie of this Booke, the nexte is, that we see what is his scope, that is, his cheefe end, and what is the matter whereof it entreateth. They whiche haue in suche sorte marked out this end, that they saye, that <hi>Solomon</hi> in setting forth the vanitie of this lyfe (that is to say of the councels and doinges of men) minded to make vs contented, and to be of quiet mindes in the common affairs and chaunces of this life, that we should vse with thanks gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the creatures of God, which through his blessing are frankely giuen vnto vs, being contented with thinges pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, without carefull pensiuenesse for thinges to come: doe in deede say something, but yet doe not plainely ynough set downe the matter: like as they doe not also who do thinke the principal point of this worke thus to be diuided: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that this whole sermon is an auouching of doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning God his prouidence, and a confuting of such things as may be obiected against it, in the whiche are comfortes to strengthen our mindes against the confusion of thinges, and threatninges against those vnbrideled outrages of men of lewd disposition, which in this life run rashlye on on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head without all feare as it were of punishment. For these places are very excellently handled in this discourse, yet are they not to be iudged the cheefe and principall ende of the same, but they are fitly applied for the proofe thereof. Now the rules of a true demonstration doe require, that the thing it selfe be seuered from the circumstances of the same. And as the thing or matter is one, so ought it to be noted oute with one certaine name, and not to be darkelye shadowed with a long discourse of many words, least that it bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded with the circumstaunces of the same, the whiche were altogether disagreeing from good order of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching.</p>
   <p>Therefore I take the principall ende of this discourse to be, OF THE CHEEFE, or, SOVEREIGNE GOOD, the whiche by his contrary is notably declared.
<pb facs="7"/> For when as Felicitie or happinesse is the principall and cheefe ende of oure whole life, and that all men with the whole labour and endeuour of their willes and studies are caried therevnto, and because in that common consent and desire of one and the same thing, there are so many and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers opinions of men of all sortes, and yet in the mean sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son the greatest part of men are led far and wide away from <hi>Felicitie or happinesse,</hi> it is altogether needefull that there should be extant a plaine doctrine of Felicitie, wherevppon we might certainely rest: least in stead of true happinesse, we laye holde vpon the shew and shadow of happinesse. The which doubtlesse will come to passe, if we follow the gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and leading of the wit of man, which with pēsiue, rash, and wandring error, seeketh felicitie in things of this world The which pensiuenesse and errour of men, <hi>Solomon</hi> doeth here so artificially describe and paint out, being a fit iudge of this controuersie, that the heate and earnestnesse of those reasoninges, and debating the matter cannot more liuelye be layd before vs. For first he teacheth that happinesse is no where to be found in things of the world, <hi>viz.</hi> hee sheweth, <hi>What happines is not,</hi> against the argumēts of man his reason, dreaming falsly of a vaine shew of happinesse. Then hauing confuted the errours of this corrupte reason, hee teacheth <hi>What felicitie or happinesse is,</hi> and as he had parted and seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it from all the counsailes and dealinges of the life of man: so hee doeth altogether place it in the feare of God, that is to say, in the true knowledge of the true God, and in his diligent and earnest seruice: and finally he doeth diuerslye and singulerlye declare the vse of this knowledge. That this is the true ende, and handling of this whole dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, the thinges being diligently weighed, I hope that all learned and sober minded men will confesse with mee, and that the same may fitly be diuided into three pointes. For first the contrary member of this principall question is set downe by the waye of confutation, namely, that <hi>true felicity is neuer to be found in any worldly matter, yea and that the title of happinesse is falsly giuen vnto them,</hi> for as muche as in them there is no sufficiencie or fulnesse, so that the minde maye be content with his owne estate, but most great want of all thinges. Secondlye, the especiall matter of this discourse is
<pb facs="8"/> shewed, and that expresly, <hi>What true felicity or happines is,</hi> the which is wholy placed in godlines. And he teacheth that the same is not a vain &amp; idle contemplatiō, but indeed a work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful &amp; effectual, the which goeth far &amp; wide, through the life of ours. Thirdly the vse of this most notable doctrine, is at large set forth, &amp; in discoursing thereof, throughout all the parts of man his life, a great part of this treatise is occupied. For he diligently teacheth &amp; noteth a double force, &amp; as it were reason of this vse. First that we should strengthen our minds with conuenient remedies against the want &amp; vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of fleeting and brittle things, that is, of such things as are to be found in this mortall and miserable life, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that we should turne our selues from the vncertayne and cumbersome state of the same, vnto thinges heauenly and euerlasting, and vnto that hope of restoring: and in the meane season assure our selues that the prouidence of God will watche ouer our affayres, that trusting vnto his ayde, hauing our mindes pacifyed, wee should beare the toyles and laboures of this lyfe, and being contented with the present state of thinges, we should vse and enioye the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God, and abandoning the desyres of vayn thinges, wherevnto worldly men in vaine doe giue themselues, wee shoulde seeke sound sufficiency and fulnesse of mind with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the loue of this world, and among all the garboyles of the life of man, looke for vnto our selues an happy end. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly that we should earnestly thinke vpon the leading of our life godly and honestly: the which is the way vnto hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse, and the second effect of this vse.</p>
   <p>All these thinges are plentifully and notably discoursed by Solomon, with a certaine and constant rowe of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: the Obiections which seeme to be agaynst this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine are diligentlye rehearsed, because these prophane and worldly cogitations and thoughts do stir vp great &amp; dayly turmoiles in the mindes of men. Against these also are set down conuenient and fit remedies, to ease our myndes of the abashmente of these confusions and garboyles whiche doe compasse and beset this life of ours: there are adioined many promises to comfort the heartes of the faythfull, and threatnings against the authors and workers of those sturs, and that for the sake of the godlye, least that they should be
<pb facs="8"/> too much dismayde at the outwarde felicitie of desperate and lewde persons, therefore as the state of this discourse is most simple and one, namely <hi>concerning felicitie or happinesse,</hi> so there are vsed in the same, especiall pointes of doctryne touching God his prouidence,<note place="margin">Sundrie nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble matters handled in this discourse.</note> touching the true and righte vse of his benefites, touching the vanitie of man his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and lustes abusing the good Creatures of GOD, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the true and sound sufficiencie or contentednesse of mind, and such other like: and that with such picked frame of wordes, with such pithie strength of sentences, with such a seuerall rowe of argumentes in so greate varyetye of matter, that the sharpe wit of all the Philosophers (and that in this common place of Felicitie or happinesse, then whiche in all Philosophie there is handled nothing more weightie and notable) compared with this treatise seemeth to be vtterly colde and of small accountes.<note place="margin">The discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of al the philosophers nothing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to this Sermon.</note> Which thing shal appeare by the reading of the discourse it self: it shal more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer be delightsome in the meane season, seuerallye to pointe oute by setting downe the particular partes of the discourse, the thinges whiche generally and breefely I haue shewed.</p>
   <div type="method">
      <head>This therefore is the particular distribution or handling of this whole discourse.</head>
      <p>First of all is layd downe the contrary part of the principal question,<note place="margin">The dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and order of this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course.</note> the which is at large handled from the very begin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning, euen vnto the end of the 4 chap. <hi>that felicitie or happines is not at all in those thinges and affayres which are vsuall in this lyfe.</hi> Therefore is the generall proposition set downe in the beginning by way of confutation, That all thinges which are vnder the sunne are vayne, and that Felicitie is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prised in them. Afterwardes there are reasons broughte to prooue the same, taken from the sufficiente reckoning vp of partes, by induction or alleaging of those thinges in the which mā his reason doth place happinesse, the which doe most clearely appeare in the fellowship of men, and vse of life. What is more beautifull or excellente then know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge? yet he teacheth that felicitie is not in it, and that in the first chapter.</p>
      <pb facs="9"/>
      <p>Secondly he teacheth that it is not in <hi>Pleasure,</hi> nor in the <hi>Wisedome of man,</hi> by the ayde whereof notwithstanding, it is thought that the life of man in euery respect may conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently be lead the which discourse he continueth vnto the 16 verse of the third chapter.<note place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>leasure and the Wisdome of man. Vertue.</note> And what shall we say of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue? Are not they amongst men most happy, which directe their life according vnto her rule? And he considereth of vertue according vnto the maner of men, and not in regarde of her selfe, that is to say, according vnto that issue whiche it commeth vnto among men most vsually. <hi>Solomon</hi> maketh aunswere, that such are the affaires of men, that among so sundrie and many tormentes of fortune, as they saye, vertue is not sufficiently able to defende her selfe: nay that in that kinde of life there is sometime great miserye, because that innocencie is many times iniured and oppressed vnder the pretence and title euen of law or iustice, and the very throne of iustice is the minister of great vngodlinesse and iniustice: also in the common course of life, the best men often go to the pot, and the worst of all sit (as they say) on Cockhorse. And in a thing so honourable and royall, this is the head of cheefest misery, for that ouer and aboue the raunging of suche outrages in the life of man, and the rewarding of Godlinesse with so pitifull a wages, yet notwithstandinge the good doe die as well as the bad, as if death without any difference did swallow them vp, and in such sorte, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing seemeth to be left after this life. For so doth man his reason iudge, whereof there cannot chuse but be perceyued an infinite misery of this mortall life, as if the estate of the deade, or of them which neuer liued, were farre better then the estate of them that liue. Which thing he doth from the sixteenth verse of the third chapter, vnto the fourth verse of the fourth chapter.</p>
      <p>Those sortes of life being after this maner examined, hee commeth vnto certain particular trades of life,<note place="margin">Single life.</note> and noteth those in which seemeth to be eyther lesse trouble, or more commoditie. <hi>The single life is commended,</hi> as being quit and free from those great encombrances, wherewith the marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed life is often loaden.<note place="margin">The life of Noble men.</note> The life of noble and great men by a certaine singular priuiledge seemeth to excell other kindes of life, yet he teacheth that happinesse is neyther in the one
<pb facs="9"/> nor the other: and therfore by the conclusion of the indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction he confirmeth that generall sentence: <hi>that al is vanity:</hi> the which (as we haue sayd) he was to proue by way of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation first of all, before that he shewed the contrary: that is to say, both what true happinesse is, and by what meanes we attaine therevnto.</p>
      <p>Before he come to that second point, hee setteth downe certayne thinges in the maner of a Praeface. For meaning to place true happinesse in the feare of the Lord, that is, in the true knowledge of GOD, he teacheth that it is not a certaine outward obseruing and keeping of ceremonies, or a bosting of Religion, consisting in many wordes: and this hee doth from the fourth chapter, verse seuenteenth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to sixte verse of the fifte Chapter, and afterwarde doeth so discourse the matter, that breefely shewing and setting downe the summe of the whole disputation in these words, Feare God, he sheweth the vse thereof fully and throughlye euen vnto the last end of the booke, which is the third parte of the whole disputation.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>Of Godl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>nesse,</hi> in which he placed the cheefe point of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse, he teacheth a double vse. The firste, namelye,<note place="margin">Godlinesse.</note> that it ministreth fit and conuenient remedies against that carefulnesse of mind, the whiche is wonte to arise of the wante of worldly thinges: which want hee had before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared at the full. Secondlye that it teacheth a way to frame our life well and honestly.</p>
      <p>He vseth therefore an especiall garnishing and as it were poolishing of those thinges, the whiche hee had taken before for the makinge vnto happinesse according vnto the common iudgemente of man his reason, and as hee had taughte that happinesse was farre from them, so he streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theneth our mindes against them. Therefore in the 5. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and seuenth verse, he entreateth first of the remedies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst that most greeuous tentation. Of the which hee had spoken cap. 3. ver. 16. How namely it commeth to passe that innocency is punished vnder the shewe and title of iustice, and they oftentimes become the ministers of iniustice, the which by God are appointed the keepers and maintayners of Iustice, ver. 7.8.9. From the 10. ver. he beginneth to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of the remedies against the want &amp; vanity of riches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb facs="10"/> setting out that same disease it selfe many wayes vnto the 8. ver. of the 6. chapter.</p>
      <p>In the eyghth verse of the sixth Chapter, hee teacheth a remedye agaynst the vanitye of man his knowledge, of the which he had entreated in the very beginning of the dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Then hee mindeth to shew remedies agaynste the quiddities and hardnesse of man his wisdome, of the which also hee had spoken chapter 2 and 3. from the thirde verse of the 7. chapter. vnto the 8. verse, hee teacheth remedies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynste triumphing pleasure. From that eyghth verse of the seuenth chapter vnto the eyghteenth verse of the same chapter, he teacheth remedies against impatiencie, the which ariseth of sorrow concerning thinges in trouble and out of order: and then especially, when as vertue is euill entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted euen vnder the coloure and shewe of iustice, of the whiche matter hee had intreated chapter third, and fourth, and fifth.</p>
      <p>From thence he maketh himselfe an entrance vnto the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde part of the vse which he teacheth to proceede of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse, namely <hi>of the framing of our life aright:</hi> in the whiche second part notwithstanding he very fitly repeateth manye thinges which appertaine vnto the first part. First of all hee setteth downe general rules concerning the framing of our life well and honestly whose sure and certayne safegarde he sayth to consist in godlinesse it selfe: from the ninteenth verse of the seuenth chapter vnto the twentie and one verse of the same.</p>
      <p>Then he giueth a lesson for the auoyding of curiositie, vnto the 22 verse of the same seuenth chapter, from the 23. ver. vnto the ende of the chapter, <hi>Of auoyding of lust and Wantonnesse.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>In the 8. chap. ver. 1. <hi>Of Modestie</hi> vnto the second verse.</p>
      <p>From that vnto the fift, of <hi>Prudence,</hi> whereby wee maye know safely how to behaue our selues with Kinges &amp; great personages.</p>
      <p>From the 5. ver. vnto the 15. ver. of the 9. chap. <hi>Of stoutnes of mind</hi> to behaue our selues constantly and couragiously in so great hurliburly of things of this world, that we bee not ouerwhelmed with those waues, where is discoursed a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble place <hi>Of the end of the wicked.</hi>
      </p>
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <p>There is handled an excellent comparison of Wisedome with Folle, from the 16. ver. of the 9. chap. vnto the 3 ver of the 10. chap. from the 4 ver. of the same chapt. vnto the 7. is taught a lesson of modesty, <hi>Of the keping of modesty euē toward waiward &amp; bad magistrates.</hi> The 8. ver. of the same chap. <hi>of auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of deceit,</hi> and <hi>Of babling,</hi> ver. 9.11. Then of <hi>Industrie and diligence,</hi> ver. 15. of a King, ver. 16 &amp; 17. that is to say, how a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileable it is for the commō wealth to haue a good king. The 18 ver. of the same cha. of Slouthfulnes, that is to say, of the hauing no care for a mā his houshold, against the which he matcheth thrift and profitable diligence ver. 18. Herevpō taking occasion in the 10 chap. he setteth down a most holy precept concerning Charity, to helpe the poore, albeit there appeare no hope of recouering of that which we giue vnto thē. In the 12. chap. applying that doctrine vnto yong men, the which do most neede the same, he teacheth a most hole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some &amp; necessary lesson, <hi>Soberly to vse this life, &amp; with the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest thinking vpon death,</hi> as it were with a bit to holde in and rule the delites and wanton pleasures thereof, and not to let passe the occasion to doe well: least we be ouertaken with death at vnwares. Therefore he warneth yong men in their flourishing and strong age, earnestly to think vpon old age, yea and also death it selfe.</p>
      <p>So he maketh an end of the whole disputation, and as the rules of a true demonstration doe require, he setteth downe the summe of the disputation in plaine words, <hi>The end of the whole law is heard, Feare God, &amp;c.</hi> Of which words doubtlesse the contents and matter of the whole disputation is to bee iudged, as if he should say: <hi>That which was to be proued.</hi> And he doth in such sort note the chiefe and principall ende, that he doth withall shew the cheefe and essentiall partes of the disputatiō He declareth by way of praeface that he bringeth not these thinges neither from the opinion of the common people, nor from the schooles of man his wisedome, but fetcheth out of the very storehouse of the truth▪ which soū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the Church of God, grounded on sure sentences of God his decrees, as namely that happines consisteth in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, and in the true vse therof, that is in the keeping of the commandements of God: That this is all man, or the whole of man, that is the principall and cheefe end of man his life▪
<pb facs="11"/> the master end, as they vse to speake. Finally that God by his prouidence doth wisely order things that are entangled, and will in his time repaire them.</p>
      <p>The issue therfore of the whole disputation is perfect and ful. That happinesse is not to be founde in thinges of this world: That the same doth consist in godlinesse, to wit, by the which we are ioyned vnto God, that we maye obtayne life euerlasting, that is, true and perfect happinesse: that the vse and profit of Godlinesse is very great and very excellent, the which doth plentifully flow through all the parts of our life.</p>
      <p>This seemeth to be the discription and frame of this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, in the which with a wonderful knitting together of arguments, and a loftie and indeed philosophicall kinde of writing is handled a most weighty place of true moral phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophy, <hi>Concerning the cheefe and soueraign good, and of the way to attaine it, and of the vse of the same</hi> But after a far other sort, then the morall Philosophers are wont to do, which in their darkenesse and ignorance haue hard and scarcelye reteined some certaine small sparkes of the original truth, the which are here very plainly declared.</p>
      <p>And in the very maner of reasoning there is apparant, a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table example of that order of disputing, whiche is to bee found among the more sounder philosophers, the which do proue their matters with most inuincible and strongest rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, the which in their art they call Demonstrations: The matter first is barely set down, then is it afterwardes more finely polished and garnished: the mater is canuased to and fro: there are vsed many inductions: the principles and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine conclusions which spring of them, are plainely and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently shewed: the laying open of them is diligentlye handled, the vse often repeated: a recital and abrigement of the whole disputation and discourse, shewing the matter and principal circumstances of the same. And it shal be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable in the Table following, to set downe the summe and cheefe points, of the discourse which is moste obscure and hard.</p>
      <list>
         <pb facs="11"/>
         <head>A Table of the Doctrine contained in this discourse.</head>
         <item>
            <hi>The principall and cheefe end of this ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon is, concerning the cheefe and soueraigne good, in defining and setting out of the which because that men doe manye wayes goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wry, laying hold onlye vpon a shadow of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse in stead of true happinesse, therefore</hi> Solomon
<list>
               <item>
                  <hi>In the first place shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>What happinesse is not, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally teacheth, that the same is not in worldly thinges, the whiche hee proueth by the reckoning vp of the cheefest parts of the life of man, to wit,</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>That it is not in the knowledge of man,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Nor in Pleasure,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Nor in man his Wisdome,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Nor in vertue also herselfe, if i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> be considered by the issue and fal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling out of things,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Nor in any kind of lyfe, eyther of priuate or of great and famous personages.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Cap.</hi> 1.12. <hi>ver. to the end of the chapter.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ca.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>to the</hi> 3. <hi>cap. ver.</hi> 15.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 16. <hi>vnto the</hi> 6. <hi>ver. cap.</hi> 4.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. <hi>verse</hi> 4. <hi>vnto the ende of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>In the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde place hee tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>What happinesse is: namely, to feare God, that is to say, to worship God with a true and vnfay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned mind, the which is the scope and drifte of the cheefe question. Cap.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 6. <hi>and</hi> 12. <hi>ver.</hi> 13.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>In the</hi> 3. <hi>place hee handleth.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The vse of the doctrine of happines, the whiche he setteth downe to bee double, to wit,</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>In ministring remedies againste the vanity of the life of man.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>In a rule of well and honest fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of our life.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Cap.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 9. <hi>vnto the</hi> 6. <hi>cap. v.</hi> 8.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. <hi>ver.</hi> 9. <hi>vnto the end: where he gathereth the summe and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgement of the whole discours.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </item>
      </list>
      <pb facs="12"/>
      <pb facs="12"/>
      <p>These thinges being thus set downe, it remaineth, that we should vnderstand what is the vse of this most notable dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course.<note place="margin">The vse of this discourse The policie of Sathan.</note> For Sathan hath sundrie wayes abused the truth of this Doctrine, impudently to establish al kind of lies, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hath come to passe, that this booke being obscured and darkened with these vnfit and wrong interpretations, could not choose but lye in moldinesse and dust, that is to saye,<note place="margin">
            <p>Against such as abuse the words of this sermon.</p>
            <p>Absurdities rising of the misse vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing of some places of this booke.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1</hi> Philosophye condemned.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> The mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the soul.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> Doubting of our saluation.</p>
         </note> be little esteemed and regarded, Some being vnluckilye giuen vnto man his Philosophie, and by the selfe same thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wraying their minde far indeed from true Philosophie, out of this that <hi>Solomon</hi> doth earnestlye finde faulte with vayne Philosophie▪ woulde conclude that Philosophie is vayne, whereas Solomon sayth, <hi>That all thinges are harde and full of laboure:</hi> as if all other actions of life were to be layde aside, that they may wholy giue thēselues vnto the study of those hard matters. Lewd &amp; wicked persons make bolde to thrust vpon vs the Epicurish, &amp; godlesse frantike opinion of the mortality of the soule, out of the words of <hi>Solomon,</hi> for that he saith, that there is all one ende of a foole, and of a wise man, of a man, and of a beast. Out of these wordes, <hi>A man knoweth not loue or hatred.</hi> Mad and vnskilfull Sophisters, doe shake the foundation of oure Fayth: that is, the assured perswasion &amp; vndoubted assent and beleefe of the goodnes of god toward vs, without the which the knowledge of our saluation is altogether vaine: vaine are the sentences of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises, vpon the which as vpon vndoubted and sure princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and grounds of best knowledge fayth staying, gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth euerlasting conclusions of the perpetual goodnesse and mercye of God towards vs: &amp; finally vain is the Autor him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe of those good thinges (which God forbid that wee should so much as once thinke) who hath so holily promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed these thinges vnto vs, and whose promises, when as we laye holde on by fayth, we doe as it were by oure seale confirme him to be true.</p>
      <p>Whereas <hi>Solomon</hi> often sayth, that al thinges are vanitie,<note place="margin">
            <hi>4</hi> The vtter o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow of the whole course and trade of life.</note> and willeth vs to forsake the worlde, some frantike spirites haue affyrmed that hereby is established the forsakinge and giuing ouer of those duties in whiche the trade and course of the societie and fellowship of man doeth consist, that is, the vtter ouerthrowe and destruction of life: as if
<pb facs="13"/> mariages, gouernementes. necessarye laboures in the Churche, in the common wealth, and in our families at home, and suche other thinges, whiche appertaine vnto the maintaynaunce of this life, were condemned, that through the vnprofitable idlenesse &amp; giuing ouer all things in them forsooth which wholy intende to consecrate and hallowe themselues vnto God our mindes should be troubled, and shunnish all company of men, then the whiche nothing can bee imagined and deuised more pernicious and hurtefull. Of the whiche deuises notwithstanding there haue bene manye vnhappye mayntainers among the auntiente Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours of the Church:<note place="margin">Auntient Do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctors patrons of fooleries.</note> and haue layde the foundations of iniquitie and superstition, whilest contrary vnto the flatte prohibition of the Apostle, they vrge too earnestly bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily excercise. What needeth many wordes? Oute of this playne truth the frantike and prophane boldnes of mē hath brought in infinit idols and shadowes of truth not through any fault of this most excellent doctrine.<note place="margin">The booke of the Preacher a very hard booke.</note> For albeit there is no man but that hee maye see this Booke to bee darke and harde to vnderstand (as Peter sayth of Paule) yet in vayne doe frantike heades take occasion of erroures vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their owne destruction of thinges amisse vnderstoode, like as they doe of other scriptures▪ when as this doctrine is not only true and altogether aunswerable and agreeing with the canonicall scripture, but is also very profitable for the well framing of the life of man.</p>
      <p>The which Rockes that we maye auoyde, certaine rules are of vs to be set downe before vnto the which we may as it were diligently leuel in the searching out of the meaning of the wordes and the vse and profite is particularlye to bee shewed, the which wee ought to reape by reading this ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</p>
      <p>Let the firste rule bee, that Solomon doth oftentimes speake,<note place="margin">Certain rule<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> necessary fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> the true vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding of this sermō.</note> not according vnto his owne minde, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto the iudgement of reason being corrupted, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit he seeme to lay downe thinges barely and playnelye: namely of purpose so precisely framing his speeche, that the image of this blynde reason maye bee more clearely and liuely represented. So there are often chaunginges of speeche,<note place="margin">The first rule <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</note> the whiche, if Solomon his purpose bee not
<pb facs="13"/> throughlye examined, maye seeme to haue a cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie force and meaning.</p>
      <p>The Seconde, that wee must not giue iudgement of the whole sentence by some parte of the sentence,<note place="margin">
            <hi>2</hi> The second rule.</note> but must weigh the whole it selfe by his circumstances, comparinge togither the things that go before with the things that followe. For as it is a point of inciuilitie (as the Lawers do teach) to catch some one parcel of the lawe, not view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whole lawe, so is it no point of a Diuine, snatching at some certaine wordes, to iudge of the whole sentence. For many things are spoken in some respect, and that most truely, the whiche in them selues and simplye shoulde not bee true: as it shall appeare by the places them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues.</p>
      <p>The thirde,<note place="margin">
            <hi>3</hi> The thirde rule.</note> that <hi>Solomon</hi> doeth not condemne the things themselues, and creatures of God, as knowledge, the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant vse of things, prudence, riches, honours, and other such like, but the abuse of these things, that is to saye, the studies, counsailes, desires, endeuours of mankinde abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the good creatures of GOD. For it is blasphemie to condemne the creatures of God, the which cannot bee but verie good, whereas all the fault of the vanitie of them is to bee layde vppon man, as being cause thereof. For whatsoeuer God hath created (sayeth the Apostle) is good, and nothing to bee refused, if it bee taken with thanks gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing: the which vse also of the creatures <hi>Solomon</hi> doeth eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently and clearely teache.</p>
      <p>The fourth, that the ground of all these precepts, the which seeme to be meere ciuil, &amp; to appertaine vnto this life,<note place="margin">
            <hi>4</hi> The fourth rule.</note> must be wisely noted, that they may be distinguished from poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike or Philosophicall precepts, with the which otherwise they might after a sort both in wordes and meaning seeme to agree. Namely that the knowledge of the redeemer is the life, &amp; as it were the soule of al this doctrin, &amp; therfore that forgiuenes of sins &amp; repentance, the promise of euerlasting life in the persō of the sonne of god, &amp; to be short his voice sounding in the true church vnto the true &amp; sound vnderstā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of this doctrine, ought first of al to be laid down, &amp; to be the euerlasting and in deede chief principles of the same. Herby shal this holie Philosophie be distinguished frō hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb facs="14"/> and prophane: and the sounde and liuely portraiture of vertues, which are here set downe vnto vs, shall be seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from politike vertues, that is to saye, from the shadowe and shewe of vertue: that wee shoulde not reckon <hi>Solomon</hi> in the same number with <hi>Hesiodus,</hi>
         <note place="margin">The precepts of Solomon do greatly differ from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of the Heathen Phi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>losophers.</note>
         <hi>Pythagoras, Phocylides, Plato,</hi> and the rest of the teachers of the Heathen: like as <hi>Solomon</hi> him selfe doeth also plainly witnesse that his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is the selfe same, the which to wit hee hath learned from one Pastor, that is <hi>Moses</hi> the minister of the lawe, or rather from Christ the euerlasting teacher of his Church, &amp; that he onely applyed it as it were prickes vnto the men of his time, and taught it in the Church, in whose bosome hee must rest himselfe, whosoeuer will truely profite in the same and thereby reape assured and certaine commoditie. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though wee must also knowe this, that alwayes the chiefe light of the worde of God is to be sought out of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of our Lorde Iesus Christ deliuered by his Apostles, least any man should thinke that we doe so commend one, and the same light of the fathers before Christ, that by the comming of Christ him selfe we did not perceiue the sonne to haue shined more brightly then at noone day.</p>
      <p>Through the guidance and helpe of these rules, and the true laying open of the wordes, the meaning of this ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon will not be ambiguous or doubtfull, nor the vse and profit vncertaine, the which no doubt will be manifold by the sure and certaine vnderstanding of this moste excellent doctrine.</p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>1</hi> The first pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit.</note>This truely is verie great and most profitable, to knowe the way not onely how to lead this life well and happily, but also the way how to come vnto that euerlasting happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, which remaineth for vs in Heauen. For when as this cause hath moued all men, of all ages (in whom there haue any sparkes of trueth remained) that setting asyde all other things they haue giuen themselues wholy to search out the best state of life:<note place="margin">A way to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto happinesse.</note> no doubt they spent their so great care &amp; trauaile in that studie for the hope to liue happily: and yet it is manifest that they haue beene so busied in this matter, that they may seem not so much to haue attained the thing which they sought, as to haue made vowes of a thing most excellent. Therefore the authoritie of this doctrine ought
<pb facs="14"/> to be most honourable vnto vs, whereby wee may attaine not onely vnto the knowledge, but vnto the sure &amp; sounde knowledge of so worthie a matter, not hauing <hi>Plato, Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stotle, Cicero,</hi> or some other blinde man to our guide, but Christ himselfe the true archeleader vnto life, as who is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs from his father the waye, the trueth, and the life. In laying open this happinesse. What it is, and what way wee may attaine vnto it, this sermon is chiefely occupyed.</p>
      <p>Also in so great imbecillitie and weakenes of mankind,<note place="margin">
            <hi>2</hi> The second profit. To beare our selues vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly &amp; stout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly among the discommodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of this life.</note> among so manie mazes of so great confusions, out of which there is no way to be found out, it can harde and scarsly be chosen, but that our mindes shall be greatly amazed: when as wee beholde the falles of mankind, the ouerthrowes of kingdomes, the deathes as well of good as bad, the good in their life time to be often troubled with great miseries, the wicked not onely to bee safe and free from troubles, but also to flourish, and to bee indued with wealth &amp; king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. Against these so daungerous awhapementes as it is needfull that our mindes should be strengthened with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient remedies, so this sermon doeth yeld vnto vs those remedies clearly and plentifully.</p>
      <p>And among all the vanities of the life of man this is the most vaine, that there can scarsly any man be founde,<note place="margin">
            <hi>3</hi> The third profit. A remedie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentednesse with our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state.</note> which liueth content with his estate: the which is ingraffed in all men by the blot of sinne, that they are carried about to &amp; fro with vaine desires: yea, and more ouer doe defraude &amp; bereaue themselues of the vse of thinges present, and vexe themselues in vaine with care and carking for thinges to come, and cannot soundly enioye the benefits of God. But if perfect contentednesse of minde be a true note of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: doubtlesse this pensiue and toylesome care and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king is a token of chiefest vnhappinesse. This sermon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foordeth fit remedies against this miserable and restlesse vanitie also, and that so conueniently and plentifully, that there can be nothing so pensiue and toylsome in this life, which may not be asswaged with these remedies.<note place="margin">
            <hi>4</hi> The fourth profit, that in the common societie we do our duties.</note>
      </p>
      <p>It should be an ouerthart satietie and contentednesse of minde, carelesly to despise the duties of life, such as the law commaundeth. Therefore <hi>Solomon</hi> teacheth, that we ought to be in such sort prepared, that wee be so farre foorth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb facs="15"/> with the present state of things, that we withdrawe not from God that obedience the which wee owe vnto him. The which he teacheth to be the true vse of that same god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse, which he affirmeth to be the sure waye vnto happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse Therefore that God is to be obeyed, the duties of our calling diligently to be done, &amp; all the encumbrances, the which are linked with the same, to bee borne and suffered with a quiet minde.</p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>5</hi> The fift pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, that we follow our vocation and calling.</note>He setteth downe a way and meane how to beare these encumbrances with a constant minde: that is to say, that we heedefully followe the rules of God his commaundements, refraine from man his curiositie, the which through confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in it selfe stirreth vp vnto things beyond the compas of our vocation: that we should not walke proudly &amp; rash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the ministerie of our vocation, trusting vnto our own strength: but that we aske help of God, &amp; be obedient vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, what euent or issue soeuer doe in the ende fall out, and out of his promise perswade our selues. that so farre as he shal see it expedient, our course shal profit the church, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto the proportion &amp; measure of our giftes.</p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>6</hi> The sixt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, that wee strengthen our mindes by the worde of God with sound patiēce</note>But least that we might suppose that in this booke is set before vs a certaine kind of Phylosophical mortification or patient enduring of labours, <hi>Solomon</hi> doth diligently teach, that the liuely doctrine of the church concerning the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes of sins &amp; life euerlasting with the persuasion wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is ioyned the gift of regeneratiō or newbirth, is the foū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of these comforts, the which good mindes doe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand to be true &amp; healthfull. For, for this cause he will haue vs to enter into the house of god, and to come to heare the voyce of that only pastor, of whom he doth plainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse that he hath receiued all that he hath. To wit, that the sonne of God apeareth not only the iudge of our fightings, but also to fight with vs, that by his power wee may ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, yea, and also that his power getting the victori might triumph in our infirmitie or weaknes.<note place="margin">A difference betweene hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thenish and Christian pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</note> This Christian pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence therfore, of the which the preacher entreateth so plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this booke, doth far &amp; wide differ from heathenish or Philosophical patience the which consisteth only in this, to thinke that there is nothing befalling to a man, but that it may befall vnto it, to count all things vnder it self that may
<pb facs="15"/> happen vnto a man, &amp; despicing them to contemne all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane chaunces, and to be wholy fitted &amp; framed by reason, by whose rule it suffereth it self to be gouerned, &amp; suffereth those paines for duties sakes, the which reason hath ordeined to be suffered. But in as much as that same reason it selfe is blind, we must also holde that the guidance of the same is preposterous &amp; ouerthwart: and that therfore there is no true patience: no right framing of duties, before the which the acknowledging of the true God doeth not shine, the which is the rule of true obedience: to wit, that wee beare with a quiet mind the labors &amp; miseries the which god wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs to beare, &amp; that we obey his commandemēts, albeit that it be with the assured hasard of our liues, moreouer that we beg &amp; wait for help from him &amp; that through the hope of this help from God, we constantly perseuer &amp; continue in the rase of our calling begun, &amp; that with assured contē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tednes &amp; quiet of mind, we asswage the sorrowe, the which by reason of the incumbrāces of this life cannot choose but greatly dismay our minds, &amp; that we hope for happy successe such &amp; so great as the lord shal please to giue.</p>
      <p>These &amp; other most excellent profits may be gathered by the reading of this sermon: as for the places in which these profits are contained, I did not think good for this cause se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerally to set down, because that euery foote they come in the way of the reader. But hereout let vs learne so to frame our selues, that abandoning the vanitie of worldly desires, we wholly giue our selues vnto the seruice of God, &amp; that we go in that path of happines, the pledges wherof we haue in this life through assured &amp; sound quietnes of mind, &amp; the pleasant vse of the gifts of God, vntill that at the appointed time, we attaine vnto the possession of perfect happines the which God hath laid vp for vs in heauen. This setting down of the manifold profit of this book, will prepare the minde of the reader vnto the more full reading of this sermon. Let it be enough for vs to haue noted the chief points.</p>
      <p>Now in the laying open of the wordes themselues there lyeth no smal hardnes.<note place="margin">Great hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in the words of this booke.</note> For in the very phrase of speaking (the which in deede is poetical, &amp; therfore more loftie with the garnishments of figures) <hi>Solomon</hi> seemeth beyōd the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon course of speaking, to haue vsed a certain more exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>te brauenesse of a more fine &amp; excellent pensill. Such
<pb facs="16"/> a kind of loftinesse and maiestie of speache, as wee also see especially in <hi>Esaias:</hi> albeit neither <hi>Moses,</hi> nor <hi>Iob,</hi> nor <hi>Dauid</hi> are without their grace and exquisitenesse in writing. So the holye Ghost, whose iudgement concerning thinges is best, hath also vsed the best and most elegant words: so that they are to be taken for starke fooles who accusing the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie of the scripture of childishnesse and not knowinge how to speake, doe therefore refuse it, because they are not able to conceiue the finenesse and trimnesse of the same. For when as they are blinde in the thinges themselues, why should they not be blinde also in the wordes? And let vs set against their vnskilfulnesse the forceable and pithie elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of the holie Ghost most farre in speaking excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all the giftes without question of all heathen writers. An this verily is true, if not onely the wordes, but rather the power and force of the scripture bee weighed, so that those things which in some Prophets may seeme base, and as it were creeping on the ground, do yet notwithstanding with their weight, and their heauenly maiestie throwe downe and as it were trample vnder their feete all the flourishing and furniture of man his wisedome.</p>
      <closer>
         <salute>Vale.</salute>
      </closer>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>