<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Illustryous and ryght hygh excellency of Princes, and to the ryght noble magnificence of Lordes and nobilitie of Fraunce, Iames Colyn vnworthy ordenary Secretary to the Kynge oure Souueraigne Lorde, and of hys chamber, Sendeth ryght humble gretynge wyth encrease in hon∣nour in perpetuall felycyte.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1550</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117701_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13758</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24056</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117701</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Illustryous and ryght hygh excellency of Princes, and to the ryght noble magnificence of Lordes and nobilitie of Fraunce, Iames Colyn vnworthy ordenary Secretary to the Kynge oure Souueraigne Lorde, and of hys chamber, Sendeth ryght humble gretynge wyth encrease in hon∣nour in perpetuall felycyte.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The hystory writtone by Thucidides the Athenyan of the warre, whiche was betwene the Peloponesians and the Athenyans, translated oute of Frenche into the Englysh language by Thomas Nicolls citezeine and goldesmyth of London</title>
                 <author>Thucydides</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Tylle (Tylly), William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1550</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>cvi, cvi-clxxix, clxxix-cc xxiii, 1 leave, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb n="iiii" facs="4"/>
   <head>To the right Illustryous and ryght hygh excellency of Princes, and to the ryght noble magnificence of Lordes and nobilitie of Fraunce, Iames Colyn vnworthy ordenary Secretary to the Kynge oure Souueraigne Lorde, and of hys chamber, Sendeth ryght humble gretynge wyth encrease in hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in perpetuall felycyte.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>HERODOTVS</hi> the father of hystoryans wytnessethe, that there is a regyon, adioynynge to the Thraces, inhabyted by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne people named Trauses: whiche in tymes past were accusto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that whan a chylde was borne amongest them, incontinent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as it was oute of the mothers wombe, the parentes and neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours dyd assemble together, and there receyued hys fourthe comming with cryes, wepynges, and lamentacions, remembrynge howe manye myseryes and calamytes he shulde of necessyte suffre in thys worlde. And to the contrary, when a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ye of them departed from thys lyfe vnto death: they accompanyed him to hys graue, in greate festynge and reioysynge: in synging and ioyfully reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>synge the multytude of euyls and tourmentes, frō which he was exempted by death. whiche thynge puttynge in consideration, the Ancyent Grekes vsurped in suche sorte, that Ausonus the Porte made or deuysed a prouerbe, whiche sayd, that it were right good for a man not to be borne, or yf he were borne, to dye ymmedyatly: so narowely loked they vnto the incommodities of mans life. And to saye the trouthe, yf that we would dylygently regarde it, we shulde fynde wyth Plyny: that nature hath dearely and at to hygh a pryce, solde vnto vs, the haboundaunce of thynges, which she bryngeth fourth to oure vse, and that we haue no ioye nor swetenes, that maye not be, sadnes and bytternes, which is indyuidently ioyned vnto them. For besyde the incomparable dangier, that we must passe for to come into thys lyghte, albeit that we be borne to haue lorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyp and commaundement ouer the other beastes, yet none of them commeth vnto the worlde so vnprouided &amp; yll appoynted, as we do, nor so frayle, weake and passyble as we be. And as the same Authour Plyny in the Prologue of the seuenth boke of hys naturall hystorye more largely and subtelly recyteth, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath geuen to all beastes euen from theyr byrthe, lybertye, vesture, haby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacyon and grateful nourriture. But mā alone is he, that assone as he is borne, falleth bare to the grounde, begynneth hys lyfe by beyng bounden or swadled, is constrayned to borowe hys garment of an other, to trauayle hys membres and hys spyryt to buylde hys lodgynge, to get hys foode by sweate of hys bodye and contynuall laboure of hys handes: after the difficultes of hys rysynge vp, and the length of tyme, that he must haue to learne to go and to speake. But yet thys is worse, that where all other beastes, do geue themself by natural instinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon, to that, which properly appertayneth to thoffyce of theyr nature, thone to flye, thother to swymme: It is man alonly that knoweth nothing withoute te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>achynge, nether to go, nor speake, neyther to eate, nor fynally to do any thynge, that is in the worlde, without teachyng, excepte it be to wepe. So that thys py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfull ignoraunce hath geuen place and auctoryte vnto the Prouerbe Italian, whiche sayeth, that a man muste be borne wyse, or els to be borne two tymes. For yf he be borne wyse, he maye escape infynyte inconuenyences, where as
<pb facs="5"/>
through faulte of experyence, he tombleth dayly duryng the cours of this short lyfe, into greate preiudice of hys wytt. Yf he be borne two tymes, in the seconde lyfe, he maye ayde hym selfe with that, that he shal haue learned in the fyrst and shall not wander in the darknes of erroure, as he is constrayned to do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge into thys worlde without guyde or lyght of knowledge. Then as it is more necessarye for man to learne, then for any other beastes: and that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuynge of knoweledge, consysteth in the spyryt: It semeth very strange to thinke from whence it maye procede, that (seynge that Nature hath fourmed vs of membres and spyryt, and that the membres mortall and weake, make vs lyke vnto beastes, so much in this more auau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>taged than we, that the more parte of them be more stronge and myghty, &amp; lesse subiected to dyseases: and y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> the spyryt durable and euerlastyng, by the whiche we are parttakers wyth An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gels maketh vs excellēt &amp; worthy aboue al other creatures) yet alwayes we seke and take payne to please the body by all meanes possyble (euery man gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly towarde hym selfe) and that there be not many that passe vpon the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, or better to say: there be fewe found y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ones woll regarde it. There is no man of so lowe estate, that he careth not to couerre hys parsone wyth some sorte of clothynge. And the nomber of them is infynyte, that for to geue it more grace &amp; deckynge, be not contended or take it to be suffycyent to be wrappe it in golde, pourple &amp; delicate silkes, except they trauayle straunge countres of the worlde, for to get stoanes, most rare and precyous, and employ them to the curiosite of theyr nyce trymmynge, where maye not a man see that the more parte of men lyuinge, not onely haue not theyr thought vpō true vertue and dutie double rewarded, but also that they kepe it not ones vnder shadowe or coueringe of the lyne or small threde of good conditions? Nowe what shall we saye, that for to sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>isfy oure corporall actes, of the earthe, which within fewe yeares must re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tourne into duste (to the sustenance whereof the thynges present, and that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth offre vs in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uerye place, myght suffyce) There are no feldes, no seas, nor forestes, which be not by vs with greate diligence trauersed and serched to thentent, that we maye haue delicious meates and please our sensuall appety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. That whiche more is, albeit, that for hys commoditie and ease, to defende the sonne, snowe, rayne and iniury of the ayer, one lodgynge or Cabayne well closed myght be ynough, yet we loue better to cause strange marbles to be brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght from the furthest regyons of the earthe habytable, for to make, buylde &amp; edifye large and greate pallaces. Where as for the most part, we regarde not wherwith the heauenly part, which is in vs, is repasted and fedde, nor yf his lod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynge be conuenyently prepared: and sonner we set afore it the leues of vyce, thā the moste sauoury and swete fruictes of vertue, holding it more comonly reclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and locked in the obscure and base vsage of sensualytie, then in preferring it, to haunt the clere and hygh operacions of honnestie. Furthermore yf at any ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me we fele any parte of oure body dysordered by sy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>knes, we seke by all meanes &amp; wayes possyble, for to recouer the health decayed: but we are litle carefull to prouyde recouerey, or to mynystre mete medecyns to oure mynde, beynge euil at ease. Shuld this come paraduenture for this cause? that for so much as the body is sene more then the spryt, we thynke therfore that it hath more nede of suche prouisyons? this argument is not suffycyent, for not onely the bodye hath not more apparance, than the spyryt, but also y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> body is by hī greatly e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in it, and that it be a true spyryt, it hath as many faces, as it sheweth ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racyons: and the body neuer sheweth hym selfe, but one fourme, in the which in many yeares he is scarsely seene of many men, where the operatiōs of the
<pb n="v" facs="5"/>
spryt, may be in shorte tyme knowen throughe all the world. And this self bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy continueth but very fewe dayes, where the spryt, whiche is euerlastynge, aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth euerlastingely, and may reteigne by him self through many worldes, that, wherin we accustome ourself, duryng the tyme, that he is with the body. To the which thynges and other infynitt, whiche may be alleaged for this purpose, yf men woulde haue suche consideration, as they ought to haue, it woulde cause better lyfe and more increase at this tyme than it dothe, and we hauyng care suf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fycient for our body (but more garnyshing our thoughtes and myndes, and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them better, and geuing them more honorable habitacion) shulde be more worthy to haue them, than we be, and shulde take more greate care to conserue them in helthe. And yf peraduenture they chaunced at any tyme to be diseased: we shulde enforce our selfes with moste diligence, to remedy theyr diseases, more then we do. Which be: Arrogance, superfluite, ambition, Couetice, immesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable desyre of lyuinge, and that whiche maketh vs lyke vnto beastes, <hi>IGNO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RANCE,</hi> so contagyous, and pestylent in the mynde of man, that it semeth, that all other spyrytuall infyrmytes, whiche trouble him, do all procede from thys alone, for where she is, God is not duely honnored, vyce ys not exchued, nor any publique nor priuate action or offyce, is rightfully &amp; in order admynistred. So that the sentence vsurped by ancyent men, saying: that euery ignorant personne is euyl, hath bene of good right receyued. And to this approueth that, which Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence had no doubte to cause to be spoken by an olde man of experience, that the earthe beareth nothynge worsse, than a ignorant man. For as he is in all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges rude and vntaught, so in this, he is intollerable: that he thinketh nothing well done, but that, whiche he doth hym self. And truly ignorance is muche vnmete and vnsyttynge in al parsones. but in them of nobilitie muche more re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proueable and parnycyous. Who lyke as they surmounte the other in dignite of bloude, Riches, apparayll and auctoryte, so this is theyr greate reproche, yf they do not passe other in excellēcye of knowlaige, that apperteygneth to theyr vocation, extendynge more to the charges and publique administracions, than to a heape of vnprofytable pastymes and exercyses of recreation, wherin they lose a greate parte of theyr tyme, whiche might muche better be employed to learne the rolle of the parsonage, whiche shulde become them to playe in the courte of the common welthe when theyr tourne or course shulde come. The coste shalbe to deere, yf they be forced to become wyse by theyr expences, as to learne in makynge warre. For warre is a thyng to be vtterly exchued, and wys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is right miserable, that is gotten by vse onely. And it is certaine, that they, whiche lacke prudence and knowlaige, can do no noble actes in tyme of warre nor of peace. Which regarded by Salomon Kyng of Iewry, after that he, which can geue all thynges: had geuen hym chose to deman̄de what he would: he requi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red nothynge, but wysedome. which chaunceth aither by a souueraine priuelege of nature, or ells is obteygned by a great knowlaige of learnyng, ioyned with a naturall wytt, whiche is the rudder of the shyppe. And of such vertue and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacyte, that by meanes of it, as sayth Cicero, there be founde many great and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous personages wythoute learnyng. And the natural man without learning ys more hable to receyue prayseworthynes and vertue, then the learned wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out naturel wytt. And at all tymes, for the good that maye be, to trust in it, and to employe it, without experyence, to take part vpon the multitude of dyuers chaūces, which happenne hourely in thys worlde, is as perilleur, as to say<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e a voyage withoute any calamyte. For althoughe the shyppe be good and strong, and well garnished and tacled voyth sayle and ballast, yet he, whiche is wythin,
<pb facs="6"/>
knoweth not at a chaunce what wynde bloweth, nor the Reace, that he oughte to kepe, withoute the compas, by meanes whereof it hath alwayes be sayde, that e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>peryence is maystres of thynges, teachyng vs to rule and gouerne, in thinges present and to comme, by Iudgement and remembrance of thinges passed. But whan they, that vnderstande matters, speake of Experience, they arrest not them selues vpon that naturall wyt onely. Whervpon is comme the Prouerbe, which sayeth: In wasting one leeneth. Nother is it in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> experiēce, which is gotten in the onely lyfe of one man. For that is to short, frayle &amp; soden, for to make dewe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uysyon for all the proufes, that we haue to do with, in this worldly pilgremage. And withoute learnyng it is lesse suffycyent for to geue vs good and clere kuow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laige of antiquite. The ignorance wherof, as wryteth Paulus Emilleus, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strayneth the self same men, which arne becomme aged in studye of other artes liberall, alwayes to resemble chyldren, ignorant of parseuerance and commone lyfe, to lyue as straungers in theyr natyue countreye, and lytle worthy to be cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led to the gouernaunce of the common wealthe, and to the company of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayls. But rather they woll sygnyfye the prays, which in the Frenche tongue is geuē to an excellent man, saying: He knoweth muche, and hath sene much, thus speakynge of that same experyence, which is ioynned w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> lernynge. For as May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Philip de commines sayth wysely in hys hystory, men do see more in one only boke within thre monethes, than twenty men, lyuinge in course one after an other, can see wyth the eye. Wyth thys, the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ule and warly learnynge, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitucions of lawes and Royalmes, the facyons, whereby they are acquired and maygteyned, the meanes whereby they fall into decaye, and agayne whereby they arne reestablyshed and restored: all these thynges be onely conteygned in the descryption of good hystoryes and none where els. The contempte wherof, togethers with lacke of knoweledge of them, hath bene very often cause, of right greate Ruynes and totall destruccyons of many estates, and yet shalbe so longe, as audacite wyth the contempte of good learnynge, shall haue more libertie, then the contemplacyon of Antiquite, the very inuētres of good thynges. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the right vertuouse, ryght myghtye and ryght Christian, Frances the furst of that name, by the grace of God the Frenche Kynge, my souerayn Lord and mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stre, hauynge clere vnderstandynge, and knowynge the proffitt, that the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laige of hystoryes hath brought hym, both in warres, &amp; also in counsayle, for to gouerne and conducte hym in the dyuersytes of hys fortunes: hath wylled not onely to wytnes, but also to put in wrytynge, and to communicate by acte (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally cōtrary to an other act of Alexāder the great) the frute &amp; delectacion, that men ought to marke &amp; perceyue therby. But after y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we shal haue recyted them both, you shall iudge which of thē is more worthy of prayse. Alexander then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng passed into Asia, had newes, how Aristotell hys mayster had publyshed and made commō the bokes of speculatiue sciences, for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which cause he wrote vnto hym letters of thys tenure. It is not well done of the, to publyshe the bokes of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> science speculatyue: for in what thyng, shall we frō hencefourth be more excellēt then other, yf the doctryne which we haue learned, begynne to be cōmon to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye man. As for my self, I loue better to be excellent in science, than in puissance &amp; strengthe, farewell. The scienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he calleth speculatiue, be the metaphisicals, which, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lutarche wytnesseth, arne of no vtilitie, neyther to belearned, nor to be taught, &amp; yet Alexander was angry, that they were made commō. But Kyng Fraunces hauyng, in hys library, Thucydides the Athenian, translated into our lāguage by so noble a parsonage, as was the Lord Claudius of Seissel (who so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lēpnised it for his chief worke) for that, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the sayd boke was not elleswhere to be found, of his proper motion is cōtent to cōmunicate it to princes, lordes &amp; gentle
<pb n="vi" facs="6"/>
men of hys Royaulme, though that he were anhistografier, so highly esteamed amonge hys countrey men, that they causedde an ymage to be made lyke hym, hauing a tonge of golde, for the elegancye and truthe, whiche he vsed in hys hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storye, and that Demosthenes Prynce of all oratours, that euer were, toke such delyte therin, that he wrott yt eyght tymes w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hys owne hande. And for trouth none of them that euer meddled therwith, drew euer nere vnto him, to descriue the deliberacions, counsells and exploytes, kepynge that, which belongeth to persones, places and tymes. In suche sorte, that for to be comprysed &amp; contayg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the examples of all mens offyces and dutyes, aswell in thys boke, as in those of Diodorus the Sicilian, of the Capitaynes and successours of Alexander, and of Appian of Alexandria, of warres, ciuile and forayne, all thre of one self trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, all thre reposying in the knigly librairy, all thre, not elleswhere to be foūd amonge the vulgare people, the kynge perceyuing, that the science of straunge tongues was not yet spred abroade, generally amonge the noblenes of his Roi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ulme, hath wylled thys company to be set as vpon a pyllerre, frō whence they maye be sene of all partes, to thintent, that of that, whiche shalbe founden to be therein Imitable and good to followe, A man maye take and vse to the teachin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to the profyt of the common welthe and edification of him selfe. And that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same, wherof men may perceyue the ende and begynnynge to be contrary vnto honestye, maye be prudently considered, for to saue hym selfe from fallynge into the lyke. From hence is it (my ryght redoubted and ryght honorable Lordes) y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> in steede of Tristrams, Girons and Lancelotes and other, which do fylle boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes wyth dreames, and wherin many haue euyll bestowed theyr good houres, ye haue, by the benefyt of the Kynge, no lesse frutefull than, pleasante passe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme, for to knowe what people were Pericles, Nycias, Antigonus, Lysima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus, Eumenes, Hanibal, Scipion, and many other sage and valyant Capitay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hose notable actes be descryued in the volumes aboue rehersed, geuynge your occasyon, to assay by your power to transforme youre selfe into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vertues, that youe shall perceyue to reluce and shyne in suche excellent parsones. And to make your proffyt, by the fautes, whiche youe shal perceyue to be therein noted, In takyng fynally for youre defence and guyde thys doctryne, historiall, whiche is (as Cicero truly sayth) the wytnes of tyme, the lyght of trouth, the lyfe of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, the Maistres of the lyfe, and the messangier of Antiquite in all &amp; euery the passages of the one and of thother fortune. Which shall geue youe the clere lyght of true experyence, for to conducte you vertuously in prosperitie, &amp; hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably, to passe aduersite to the right great compforte &amp; quyetnes of your spy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryt. But now it is time that we harken, what the translator shall saye, and that makynge an ende of oure Prologue, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynne to rede hys, and afterwardes, manfully to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue and followe the principalle worke, in assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to fynde there, Recompence of our payne.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>