<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE BVYERS yearely of Almanackes and Prognostications.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117185_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05326</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1547</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117185</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE BVYERS yearely of Almanackes and Prognostications.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A helpe to discovrse. Or, A miscelany of merriment : Consisting of wittie, philosophical and astronomicall questions and answers. As also, of epigrams, epitaphs, riddles, and iests. Together with the covntrymans counsellour, next his yearely oracle or prognostication to consult with. Contayning diuers necessary rules and obseruations of much vse and consequence being knowne. By W.B. and E.P</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Becket, Leonard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 237, 240-249, 248-276, that is 279, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="120"/>
   <pb n="215" facs="120"/>
   <head>TO THE BVYERS yearely of Almanackes and Prognostications.</head>
   <p>Prefatio siue Admonitio pia &amp; vtilie.</p>
   <l>THou whose short span of life, as plaine appeares,</l>
   <l>Hangs but vpon the wast of some few years</l>
   <l>Which that Arithmetician best of men</l>
   <l>Cast but in his account threescore and ten.</l>
   <l>How soone they will determine digge thy graue,</l>
   <l>Thou maist obserue that seest what wings they haue,</l>
   <l>How with no sound they wheele their times about,</l>
   <l>Eating with silence Liues and Leases out:</l>
   <l>As here's a date but yesterday renude,</l>
   <l>Nor more it seemes, yet doth a yeare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude;</l>
   <l>
      <pb n="216" facs="121"/>In which that Dayry of little cost</l>
   <l>Is now runne out, and that small value lost</l>
   <l>Wherewith t'was purchasd if thou not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend</l>
   <l>Thy thoughts to make it thus farre forth thy friend,</l>
   <l>That euery yeare thy Almanacke thou buyest,</l>
   <l>Thou art one yeare nearer to the yeare thou dyest.</l>
   <l>And from that meditation so prepare</l>
   <l>Thy lise, that death neere seize thee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares.</l>
   <l>One yeaee thus to another yeelding roome,</l>
   <l>Haue fild vp many a sepulcher and tombe,</l>
   <l>Fretted out brasse with age, marble with rust,</l>
   <l>Conuerted generations into dust.</l>
   <l>Frō which collect though nere so yong thou bee,</l>
   <l>This may doomsday finall yeare of thee;</l>
   <l>And frō that motiue such a method borrow</l>
   <l>As thou shouldst liue an age, or die to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>