<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE OF THE AVTHOR TO THE CONSVLS, AND THE WHOLE Order of the Senators of the famous Common wealth of Halberstat.</title>
           <author>Quedlinburg, Gerhardi.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117393_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01635</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11767</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117393</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE OF THE AVTHOR TO THE CONSVLS, AND THE WHOLE Order of the Senators of the famous Common wealth of Halberstat.</title>
                 <author>Quedlinburg, Gerhardi.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The soules watch: or, A day-booke for the deuout soule : Consisting of 52 heauenly meditations, and diuers godly prayers, fitted to all the dayes of the weeke. Being holy exercises for a sanctified conuersation, and spirituall riches for the inward man. By Iohn Gerhard Dr of Diuinity, and superintendent of Heldburge. Englished by R.B. With the Lords Prayer expounded by him</title>
                 <author>Gerhard, Johann</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Harrison, John 4</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harrison, John 4.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Williams, Francis</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 432, 443-512 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE OF THE AVTHOR TO THE CONSVLS, AND THE WHOLE <hi>Order of the Senators of the</hi> famous Common wealth of <hi>Halberstat.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey which compare Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and Physicke together, are many, and they seeme to vnfold the matter very well. For, as the end of Physicke is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, to maintaine health in mans body, and to recouer the same when it is lost: so Diuinity, in respect of the diseases of the soule, after the same manner doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge a double end: for it shewes not onely how wee may be freed from sinnes, but also how wee may bee preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in grace. Both Physickes, as well that of the body, as that of the soule are of God, as said <hi>Gregory,</hi> therefore also they
<pb facs="6"/> agree in the Author. Physike hath her certain principles: that is to say, Reason, and experience, which for that are called certain legs thereof, with which she ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepteth that which is agreeable, and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth that which is disagreeing: so Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity hath her sure and vnmoued princi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, the Word of God, comprehended in the Propheticall and Apostolicall Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, with which that which agrees, she doth accept of, that which disagrees, she doth refuse. Others goe further, &amp; shew, that all true Physike is of regeneration, seeing that nothing can regenerate which is not it selfe regenerated, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to the cleansing of the vitall spirits from the impure tinctures of diseases, which is as it were a certaine regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there are required regenerated bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, that is, spirits which are bodies spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall for penetration and tincture: and neuerthelesse they are all spirits corpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reall: so also the true end of Diuinity is, that spirituall regeneration of the inward man, which the Truth doth testifie to bee made of Water and the Spirit. They adde also the comparison of the Philosophers stone, with the blessed stone in the Church: but because this is neither knowne of all, nor granted of all, I will
<pb facs="6"/> not dwell on these things, it is sufficient for my purpose, that out of the comparisō of Diuinity with Physike, I can gather by very good reason, that Diuinity is a prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike doctrine: and therefore that they do not iudge aright, which contend that it is onely speculatiue, which in number are some of these Schoole men; for although not onely those things that are to bee done, but also which are to bee beleeued and hoped for, are proposed vnto vs in this heauenly Philosophy, yet that doth not hinder, but it may as yet bee called practike, for Physike also is occuped in the Theory of certaine things, neither yet is therefore a speculatiue discipline, because it followes this same Theory by reason of practice, and in order to prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice: so is it in Diuinity; yea, I may adde, that in those very things that are to bee beleeued, or in the Articles of the Faith, there is required not bare knowledge onely, but also consent, which that it is an action of the part of the will, they doe confirme by fit arguments to whom this care doth appertaine.</p>
   <p>Now, if Diuinity bee a practike doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, then the end thereof shall not bee bare knowledge and subtile Theory, but rather practice. If ye know these things,
<pb facs="7"/> blessed are ye, if ye do them, saith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour to his Disciples. The matters of our Religion doe not consist in words, but in deeds, saith <hi>Iustin.</hi> Not to talke onely, but also to be, makes Christians, saith <hi>Ignatius.</hi> The summe of Christian Religion is to imitate him whom thou worshippest, saith <hi>Augustine.</hi> What is Christianity? The likenesse of God according to that which befals the nature of man, saith <hi>Basil.</hi> Now if the end and perfection of Christian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion bee not a bare knowledge, but a practise, how few true Christians shalt thou finde at this day? there is euery where much science, little conscience. It is very well done that the Orthodoxe doctrine is defended by Bookes, Disputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Sermons, and all manner of meanes, but we must also doe our endeuour, that our life may answer to the Christian pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession. If I haue the knowledge of all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries, and haue not loue, I am nothing, saith the Apostle. What then shall they answere hereafter, which haue not the knowledge of all, but of few? not a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, but a very slender knowledge of my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries, and yet they are proud of it; they contemne others, they enuy others, scarcely making any account of Christian Charity. I will hither ascribe a place out
<pb facs="7"/> of a certaine notable Booke. He that will fully and sauourly vnderstand the words of Christ, it behooues him that hee study to conforme his whole life vnto Christ. What doth it profit thee to dispute on high of the Trinity, if thou want humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, from whence thou maist displease the Trinity? If thou knewest the whole Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the sayings of all the Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, whar would all this profit thee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the loue of God, and grace? Vanity of vanities, and all is vanity, besides the loue of God and his seruice only. Knowledge without the feare of God, what doth it import? If I knew all things which are in the world, and were not in charity, what would it helpe me before God? By how much the more and better thy knowledge is, by so much the more grieuous and heauy from thence shall bee thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, vnlesse thou liue the more holily. Be not therefore lifted vp for any Art or Science, but rather feare for the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that is giuen vnto thee. Hither also pertaineth a place of <hi>Erasmus.</hi> Whereto pertaines it to dispute how many wayes sinne may be taken, whether it be onely a priuation, or else a blemish inherent in the soule: let the Diuine rather labour this, that all men may abhor and hate sin.
<pb facs="8"/> Wee contend without end, what distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guisheth the Father from the Sonne, and both of them from the holy Ghost, <hi>res an relatio,</hi> and how it can be that they should bee called three, of whom there can bee none which is other, seeing they are one essence: how much doth it more pertaine to the purpose, to labour this by all meanes, that we worship and adore god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily and holilty that Trinity, whose Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty it is not lawfull to search into, and that wee expresse the vnspeakeable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord thereof by our concord, as farre as we may, so that hereafter it may come to passe, that wee may be taken into the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowship thereof? We dispute, how it can be, that the fire with which the soules of the wicked shall bee tormented, seeing it is materiall, can worke vpon an incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reall thing: how much more did it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne to labour with all our strength to this end, lest that fire finde any thing in vs, which it may burne, &amp;c?</p>
   <p>But I say, againe, that the thing it selfe is not taxed, but the abuse of the thing: it is well done, that our endeuour and stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is spent on the accurate knowledge of the Articles of the Faith: it is well done, that the Orthodoxe doctrine is defended against Heresies, if so be that the summe
<pb facs="8"/> and perfection of Christian Religion bee not thought to consist therein, if so bee also there bee a respect had of Christian I fe and charity. There is an ill life where there is not a good beliefe in God: and againe, it is an vnprofitable beliefe, where there is not a good life: there is no true faith within, where workes doe not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare without: they that walke not in the light, are not the sonnes of light: they are not Christians which doe not lead a life worthy of a Christian.</p>
   <p>That therefore in this most cold old age of the world, I might put to some heate to Piety, that is almost extinct, that I might put to a goad or somewhat that would pricke forward, to those that are slow in the way of the Lord, and that I might admonish my selfe and others of our duty, I haue written this little Booke of holy meditations at successiues houres, insisting in the foot-steps of <hi>Augustine, Bernard, Anselme, Tauler,</hi> and others in this kinde, whose sayings I doe diuers times vse in this Enchyridon, yet no where (which might most easily haue bin done) doe I put to the names of the Authors, seldome note the places of Scriptures; for I did feare, lest thereby the meditation of those that read, might be troubled. I doe
<pb facs="9"/> not think that it skils much to be known, whether any thing bee exprest in the words of the Fathers, or in mine, so that that which is spoken be diligently atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto. If it please any one to attribute all things that are spoken fitly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniently in this little Booke to the holy Fathers, and to assigne those things vnto me which are vttered nothing so fitly, I doe not stand against it; that onely I seeke, that some fruit may redound from thence to the sonnes of the Church: and truely I shall thinke I haue my wish, if out of the reading of this Booke, some one godly &amp; holy cogitation do arise but in one soule, at one moment. If any man meet with words that are not so pure, so fitly vsed, I say moreouer with words that are not so fitly agreeing with the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of Faith (which yet I hope he shall not) let him not straightway cast away the whole Booke, nor straightway marke me for an Hereticke, but let him weigh the kinde of writing. I handle holy things, which doe not much desire Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toricall ornaments: I write Homilies, not exact disputations; I would haue a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter care of things, then of words. Thou shalt not finde here thornie and knotty quest ons, but earnest exhortations to
<pb facs="9"/> holy life: thou shalt not finde here scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous conceits, but the spirituall riches of the inward man: thou shalt not finde here, that which may exercise thee in the subtility of disputing, but that which may instruct thee in the way of humility. I doe sometimes follow Allegories, not that I thinke that all things must bee transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med into Allegories, but because this kinde of writing, being directed to teach and admonish, not to striuing and dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, did not seeme to refuse them, but why do I speake more about this matter, and why doe I bring so many things to defend my selfe? seeing I haue already satisfied the indifferent Readers; but I shall bee neuer able to satisfie the vniust Censurers.</p>
   <p>Now to you <hi>(most famous, wise and prudent men)</hi> doe I dedicate and offer these holy meditations, that there may be some pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like testimony extant of mine obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance towards your Honours, your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy in preseruing of the purity of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is knowne of all, and praised of all, your singular prudence in the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Common-wealth, your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuolence towards all that are lettered, these and such like things haue easily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded me, that I should not doubt to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb facs="10"/> these first fruits of my studies, such as they be, this vsury of my winters rest, such as it is, to your Honors, with due signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of reuerence, and specially seeing by my grandfathers, on the fathers and on the mothers side, of godly memory, some of your Honors famous Order doe come neere vnto mee in consanguinity and affinity. Take therefore <hi>(most excellent Men)</hi> with a cheerefull countenance and indifferent minde, this paper gift from my tenuity, receiue me into your protection, and goe forward to fauour my studies as heretofore, so hereafter. I beseech the good great God, with humble sighes, that he will continue your good things vnto you, that is, that hee vouchsafe most fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourably to preserue the holy pledge of his Word, peace and tranquillity, an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py increase of the Common wealth, and all those good things which he hath most largely bestowed on your City, and that he vouchsafe also to passe them ouer to your posterity.</p>
   <p>At <hi>leanes</hi> in the moneth of Aprill. 1606.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honours most dutifull</hi> M. IOHN GERHARDI. <hi>Quedlinburg.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>