<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE OPION OF Corranus Amnensis touching Silesio: with his iudgement of his workes; and of those, his high ap∣provement of that Master∣piece, entituled The Arcadian Princesse.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117416_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12245</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22553</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117416</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE OPION OF Corranus Amnensis touching Silesio: with his iudgement of his workes; and of those, his high ap∣provement of that Master∣piece, entituled The Arcadian Princesse.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Arcadian princesse; or, The triumph of iustice : prescribing excellent rules of physicke, for a sicke iustice. Digested into fowre bookes, and faithfully rendred to the originall Italian copy, by Ri. Brathvvait Esq</title>
                 <author>Silesio, Mariano</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Bostock, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 192, 191-254, 250, 8 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>THE OP<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ION OF <hi>Corranus Amnensis</hi> touching <hi>Silesio:</hi> with his iudgement of his workes; and of those, his high ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of that Master<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece, entituled <hi>The Arcadian Princesse.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ith what pregnancy of wit, and solidity of judgement the ever-living <hi>Silesio,</hi> whom to silen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> were to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract from the fame of <hi>Florence,</hi> was indowed, may sufficiently appea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e by his exq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>isite Labours. In which <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> so sweetly contend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>d, as they erected such trophies in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> lines, which exceeded the bounds of <hi>Fate,</hi> or <hi>Time,</hi> to be by oblivion blemished; or by neglect seazed. Hee was descended of a noble Family, which hee renowned by his owne actions, by making his own penne the surviving Annall of her
<pb facs="8"/>
memory. Hee was twice elected by the generall voyce and vote of the State, for Embassador to the <hi>Genue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>s:</hi> where he demeaned himselfe with such cautious reservance and judicious pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as hee became no lesse admired abroad where he stood interessed, than honoured at home when he returned. But wearied with affaires of State, and desiring much retirement, he pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately withdrew himselfe into the Country; where willing to publish some Workes, by leaving to the world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he left the world, such legacies of his love, in his life, as might live in his death; he composed div<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rs Subjects of infinite benefit and approvement to the State. Howbeit, in his yonger yeares hee stood much affected to Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sy; wherein hee so excelled, as his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ems were held equall with those enli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened composures of <hi>Tasso's.</hi> His In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention was much employed in his youth, (which time he bestowed in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servance of the Court) in Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Maskes and other Theatrall present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; wherein none ever contended
<pb facs="8"/>
with him, who in the end did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuously veile unto him. But grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to riper yeares, hee retired from these, and accommodated his stile to the maturity of his time. In which se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious studies such accomplishment se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded his retirement, as his private recluse could not be free from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course: so highly did such as perused him, lov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> him, as they desired nothing more than to live with him. Amongst others of his <hi>Labours,</hi> during his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, hee wrote a Booke entitled the <hi>Arcadian Princesse,</hi> which hee caused to be transcribed and sent to <hi>Florence;</hi> a Worke in my opinion, of incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble worth, for <hi>Language</hi> and <hi>Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> That <hi>Parthenius,</hi> of whom hee makes such honourable mention, was such a <hi>favourite</hi> of the <hi>Muses,</hi> as so many Poems of his as are extant, have equall'd, if not surpast those Moenian Measures of <hi>Petronius.</hi> Having thus flourished for many yeares, with much fame in <hi>Florence,</hi> and enjoyed the sweetnesse of many retired houres in his Countrey repose, He bad the world
<pb facs="9"/>
farewell with a smile. <hi>Anno Dom.<note place="margin">This Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>or dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers from the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>rmer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
               <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</note> 1368.</hi> And was interred with all so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity in the <hi>Lemnian arch.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>