<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO NO MATTER VVHO,
NO GREAT MATTER VVHERE,
YET TO BE READ, THERE IS MATTER WHY,
ALTHOVGH NOT MVCH MATTER WHEN.</title>
           <author>Taylor, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117734_Bo1_5_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13415</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23725</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117734</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO NO MATTER VVHO,
NO GREAT MATTER VVHERE,
YET TO BE READ, THERE IS MATTER WHY,
ALTHOVGH NOT MVCH MATTER WHEN.</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>All the vvorkes of Iohn Taylor the water-poet : Beeing sixty and three in number. Collected into one volume by the author: vvith sundry new additions, corrected, reuised, and newly imprinted, 1630</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Boler (Bowler), James 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Elizabeth.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 148, 2, 93, 92-200, 225-343, 1, 14, 13-146 pages, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="25" facs="19"/>
   <head>TO NO MATTER VVHO,
NO GREAT MATTER VVHERE,
YET TO BE READ, THERE IS MATTER WHY,
ALTHOVGH NOT MVCH MATTER WHEN.</head>
   <p>IT is no matter in whose hands or censure this my <hi>Superibae Flagellum,</hi> or
Whipping, or Stripping of Pride fall into: If it come into the view of
true Nobility or Gentry, I know it will be charitably accepted. If into
the hands of degenerate yongsters, that esteeme Pride more then all the
Liberall Sciences, who account the foure Cardinall vertues, inferiour to
their owne carnall vices, such a one will put me off with a scornefull tush,
a pish, or a mew, and commit my Booke to the protection of Ajax. If a
wise man reade it, I know it will be discreetly censur'd; if a Foole, his
Bolt is soone shot, and I am arm'd against it; if a Learned man peruse it, he will beare with
my bad Schollership; if an vnlearned, I care not for his opinion; if a man of knowledge view
it, he will pardon my ignorance; if an ignorant Asse see it, he will bray out his owne; if an
honest rich man spy it, he will be the poorer in spirit, though not in purse; but if a proud
Diues handle it, he will esteeme it worse then his Dogges; if a proud Courtier reade it, hee
will teare it to tatters; whilst a Generous Affable Gentleman, will louingly entertaine it. If
beauty chance to behold it, it will bid it welcome, if Pride stand not in the way; if a strong
man that is not proud of it, grow acquainted with the contents of my meaning, I thinke it
will content him; if Parents, or children, or all, or any body, that are not poysoned with
pride, doe but see or heare it distinctly, read and vnderstand it with iudgement, I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded
it will passe and repasse, with friendly vsage, but if any of the contrary faction come
within the Aire of it, they will vse it in some sort, as bad as the hangman will vse them. And
So much for, To no matter <hi>who.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>It is no great matter <hi>where</hi> this be read, for as a good man (being banished) is neuer out of
his Country, because all Countries are his, so my Booke in Church, Court, Citty,
Countrey or Cottage, is one and the same; it may perhaps alter the place where it comes
from worse to better, but the place can neuer alter the honest intents of it, from better to
worse. Therefore no great matter <hi>where.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>To be read there is matter, <hi>why</hi> because it strikes at the roote of a most deadly sinne, which
almost as bad as an vniuersall deluge, hath ouerflowed the most part of the world; and though
the Preachers on Earth, (Gods Trumpets, and Ambassadours from Heauen) doe diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
and daily strike at this abomination, with the eternall Sword of the euerlasting Word,
yet what they cut downe in the day, like Mushromes, it growes vp againe thicke and three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>old
in the night; for whilst the husband-man sleepes, the enuious man sowes tares.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="26" facs="20"/>Wherefore, I hauing a talent of knowledge lent me, by which I know that I must render
an account one day, how I haue imployed it, and hauing written neere forty seuerall Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets
in former times, I purpose henceforward (God willing) to redeeme the time I haue
so mis-spent, imploying my Pen in such exercises (which though they be not free from a rel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish
of mirth. yet they shall be cleare from profanation, scurrillity, or obsceannesse. I doe
know, Pride is at such a height, that my Mole-hill Muse can neuer by mineing at her foote,
shake her head; for where Diuinity preuailes not, Poetry in meddling doth but shew the Suns
brightnes with a Candle. Yet forasmuch as I know that Pride cast Angels out of Heauen, made
diuels in hell, threw man out of Paradise, was a maine causer of the drowning of the first
World, is a deuourer of this world, and shall euer be accursed in the world to come, by
this knowledge, I haue with a mix'd inuectiue mildnesse, shewed in this Booke the vanities of
all sorts of Pride, not that I hope for amendment, but to shew my honest intendment.</p>
   <p>I haue seene sixe or seuen fashion hunting Gallants together sit scorning, and deriding a
better man then themselues, onely because either his Hat was of the old Blocke, or that his
Ruffe was not so richly lac'd, his Cloake hath beene too plaine, his Beard of the old transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
his Bootes and Spurres of the precedent second edition, and for such slight occasions
a man hath beene slighted, ieerd and wonderd at, as if he had beene but a Zany to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion,
or a man made for the purpose for them to whet their scorne vpon, and therefore to
reade this, there is a matter <hi>why.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>It is not much matter <hi>when,</hi> for be it read on Friday the Turks Holyday, on Saturday the
Iewes Sabbath, on Sunday the Lords Day, or on any day or all dayes, nights or houres,
there is Diuinitie with Ala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ritie, Poetrie with mirth, and euery thing so interwouen, one
with another, that if it please not the generality, yet I hope in particularitie it will tolerably
censur'd by all that hate Pride, and loue humility. And therefore, not much matter <hi>when:</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>IOHN TAYLOR.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>