<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Friends Inuitation: no Flatterers Encomion.</title>
           <author>Croyes, Anthony</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117830_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12957</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23250</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117830</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Friends Inuitation: no Flatterers Encomion.</title>
                 <author>Croyes, Anthony</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Essayes and characters, ironicall, and instrvctive : The second impression. With a new satyre in defence of common law and lawyers: mixt with reproofe against their common enemy. With many new characters, &amp; diuers other things added; &amp; euery thing amended. By Iohn Stephens the yonger, of Lincolnes Inne, Gent</title>
                 <author>Stephens, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Knight, Philip</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>19, 125, 125-380, 397-434 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>
      <hi>A Friends Inuitation:</hi> no Flatterers Encomion.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>VVHen many are inuited to a Feast,</l>
      <l>Though the inuiter doth not know his guest,</l>
      <l>And therefore cannot well prouide in hast,</l>
      <l>One dish so curious, as may please each tast:</l>
      <l>Yet if this Host hath such a carefull minde,</l>
      <l>As that he will, for each mans stomacke, finde</l>
      <l>A seu'rall meat; and so prouide with care,</l>
      <l>Good hous-roome, harty welcome, &amp; good fare.</l>
      <l>Shall we condemne his liberall act and loue,</l>
      <l>If thank-lesse Inuitants the same disproue?</l>
      <l>Some (peraduenture) doth one dish there see,</l>
      <l>Which with his nature doth not well agree:</l>
      <l>Some other may perchance dislike the feast,</l>
      <l>Because it is not all what he likes best.</l>
      <l>And so with diuers censures they doe take,</l>
      <l>Due praise from him who did the banquet make:</l>
      <l>Which may discourage him that doth intend,</l>
      <l>Such carefull cost another time to spend.</l>
      <l>Yet (worthy Author) let not this dismay</l>
      <l>Thee, to goe forward in that vertuous way</l>
      <l>Thou hast propounded; nor let that be lost</l>
      <l>Which is so rare. Thou art a noble Host,</l>
      <l>And cause thou knowest not the mindes of those,</l>
      <l>That shall receiue thy feast, thou dost dispose</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="6"/>Of things so fitly, that all here may finde,</l>
      <l>Diuers prouisions for each Readers minde.</l>
      <l>What if perchance some surfet at thy feast,</l>
      <l>Because they cannot easily digest</l>
      <l>Some vicious quallity, which raignes so rife</l>
      <l>In vicious minds (made known by their lewd life)</l>
      <l>So rife; as you the danger haue exprest,</l>
      <l>That knowing it, they might the vice detest?</l>
      <l>Pitty their weaknes then, seeing thou dost tell,</l>
      <l>Nothing to poyson humor, but expell.</l>
      <l>What if some others will thy feast abuse,</l>
      <l>Because it is of seu'rall kindes? resuse</l>
      <l>The Founders dignitie, because tis knowne</l>
      <l>Mens tastes and palates onely be their owne?</l>
      <l>Thou mad'st it not for onely one mans sake,</l>
      <l>But all the worlds, if all of it partake.</l>
      <l>Take resolution therefore to thy minde;</l>
      <l>Adde winges vnto thy fainting courage; binde</l>
      <l>All thy due strength together; to prouide</l>
      <l>So rare a Banquet; which may long abide</l>
      <l>To all mens profit, and the founders praise.</l>
      <l>He therefore doth inuite the guests that sayes</l>
      <l>This is a Noble Feast; and wisheth this,</l>
      <l>That he, which of this feast doth iudge amisse</l>
      <l>May (if he wants what is in this combin'd)</l>
      <l>Seeke to atchieue the same, but neuer finde.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>ANTHO. CRO<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>YES. <hi>of Grayes Inne Gent.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>