<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right worship∣full Sir Dauid Murray, speciall Gentleman of the Prince his Bed-chamber, multipli∣cation of mercy, grace, and peace.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117170_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19508</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5937</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117170</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right worship∣full Sir Dauid Murray, speciall Gentleman of the Prince his Bed-chamber, multipli∣cation of mercy, grace, and peace.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The triumph of a Christian : contayning three excellent and heauenly treatises. 1 Iacobs wrestling with God. 2 The conduit of comfort. 3 A preparatiue for the Lords Supper. Full of sweet consolations for all that desire the comfortable sweetnesse of Iesus Christ, and necessary for those who are troubled in conscience. Written by that worthy man Master William Couper, minister of Gods word</title>
                 <author>Cowper, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Budge, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 491, that is 194, 3, 88, 10, 118, 10 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="126"/>
   <pb facs="126"/>
   <head>To the right worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sir <hi>Dauid Murray,</hi> speciall Gentleman of the Prince his Bed-chamber, multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of mercy, grace, and peace.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worshipfull, albeit no distance of place can dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynt them in affection, whō God hath conioyned by the band of one spirit: yet is it no small stop of that Christian conference, wherby eyther of them might happely edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, and be edified of others. I haue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore taken mee to the next remedy, since I cannot reach towards you with my tongue, I haue endeuoured by writing to bestow vpon you some <hi>Spirituall Gift,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> according to my line or measure, for recompence of that Comfort, which I
<pb facs="127"/>
haue reaped of that Grace of God which is in you.</p>
   <p>I know these colder parts of the Ile, wherein we soiourue, doe not vsually ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der such ripe fruites as those on which the Sunne beates more hotely; yet are they also profitable in their kinde for nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishment, specially of such▪ who from their youth haue beene accustomed to feede vpon them. Neyther hath the Lord our God debarred vs from Communion of that which is the greatest glory of the Ile: the Sun of righteousnesse hath shined vpon vs also. The Lord hath made our<note place="margin">Es. 42. 16.</note> darknesse to bee light, and lead vs who were blinde a way wee knew not. The Lord hath set his Standard amongst vs.<note place="margin">Esa. 49. 22.</note> Hee hath not onely sayde to the South, keepe not backe, but hee hath also com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the North to giue and to bring<note place="margin">Esay. 43. 6.</note> vnto him his Sonnes from farre, and his Daughters from the ends of the Earth. As the going forth of the Sunne, is from<note place="margin">Psal. 19. 6.</note> the one end of Heauen to the other, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing in the East, and running on like a mighty man, his race towards the West;
<pb facs="127"/>
so hath the Law gone forth of Sion, and the Word of the Lord from Ierusalem: the light of the Gospell through many na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions<note place="margin">Esa. 2. 3.</note> hath come from them of the East, toward vs in the West, where now it stands more meruailously, then the Sunne stood in Gibeon in the dayes of <hi>Ioshua,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iosh 10. 12</note> till the fulnesse of the Gentiles in these<note place="margin">Ro. 11. 25.</note> parts, the remnants of <hi>Iaphets</hi> house bee brought into the Tents of <hi>Sem.</hi> How long it will so continue the Lord know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
   <p>Now the shadows of the euening are stretched ouer them of the East: the Sun is gone downe ouer their Prophets. Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse<note place="margin">Mich. 3. 6.</note> is vnto them in stead of Diuinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. If our vnthankefulnesse prouoke the Lord to withdraw it from vs, woe in like manner shall bee to this Land, when God<note place="margin">Hos. 9. 12.</note> departs from it. There was neuer people before vs had any more but their day of Grace, some longer, some shorter, but as they had a Morning, so hath an Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning also ouertaken them. <hi>While there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ioh. 12. 35</note>
      <hi>wee haue the light, let vs walke in the Light: Blessed shall wee bee, if</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luk 19. 42</note>
      <pb facs="128"/>
      <hi>wee know those things, which belong to our peace:</hi> for in our dayes, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise which the Lord made two thousand and sixe hundred yeares agoe, is aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly performed: <hi>that hee would giue<note place="margin">Psal. 2.</note> the ends of the earth to his Sonne for a possession:</hi> Happy are they among vs, who shall be found of that number, sought out by the Candle of the Gospell, as peeces<note place="margin">Luke. 15. 8</note> of lost Money, and like wandring Sheepe taken out of the mouth of the Lyon, and giuen in a Gift to Christ, that hee may saue them: these are <hi>the Redeemed of the Lord,</hi> let them praise the Lord; and among them come yee in also, and giue glory to God: take in your heart and mouth with <hi>Dauid</hi> that Song of thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing: <hi>The Lots are fallen vnto mee</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 16. 6</note>
      <hi>in pleasant places:</hi> and <hi>I haue a faire Heritage.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>It is written of <hi>Theodosius,</hi> that hee thanked God more, for that hee was a Christian, then for that he was an Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour; because the Glory hee had by the one would vanish, but the benefits hee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed by the other hee knew, were to
<pb facs="128"/>
continue for euer: and though it may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e most iustly great matter of your ioy, that by the fatherly care of our Gracious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, yee haue beene placed a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mestique Attendant on his Maiesties most Princely Sonne, euen from his very Cradle (wherein hetherto you haue beene praised for Fidelitie, and I hope shall be so to the end) yet let this bee your great<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>st Glorie, that the Lord hath made you par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of that blessing which commeth by the Gospell, and giuen you the earnest of that Inheritance prepared for them, who are sanctified by Faith in Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus. For increase whereof in you, as I dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly send vp my weake Prayers vnto the Lord, so shall I be aboundantly contented<note place="margin">Act. 20. 32</note> to know that these small fruits of my h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>s<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, which haue growne this last Sum mer in the pleasant valley of <hi>Perth,</hi> not far from your natiue soyle, may be any way profitable to confirme and establish that which GOD hath wrought in you. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> them therefore (right Worshipfull) come towards you, as those fruits which <hi>Iacob</hi> sent to <hi>Ioseph</hi> from Canaan Southward,<note place="margin">Gen 43. 11</note>
      <pb facs="129"/>
to more plentifull Aegipt; though not as supplements of your neede, yet as Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of that loue which I beare toward you in the Lord, to whose mercy I commend you for euer in Iesus Christ.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your W. in the Lord Iesus,
M. <hi>William Cowper,</hi> Minister of Christ his Euangell at Perth.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>