<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Rea∣der, and especially to the re∣ligious Housholder, whose desire and care is, to enforme himselfe and his family, in that truth which is according to godlinesse.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117277_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06030</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1642</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117277</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Rea∣der, and especially to the re∣ligious Housholder, whose desire and care is, to enforme himselfe and his family, in that truth which is according to godlinesse.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A helpe to true happinesse. Or A briefe and learned exposition of the maine and fundamentall points of Christian religion. By Mr. Paul Bayne</title>
                 <author>Baynes, Paul</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bladen, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 396 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Christian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and especially to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Housholder, whose <hi>desire and care is, to enforme</hi> himselfe and his family, in that truth which is according to godlinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> (a chosen vessell to Christ) carried such an vpright minde and zealous affection to the glory of God,<note place="margin">Acts 9.15.</note> and edifying of the body of Christ, which is the Church, that although hee doe earnestly exhort all men to put on the girdle of sinceritie (a most fit &amp; comely ornament for Ministers of the Gospell) yet he professed,<note place="margin">Eph. 6.14.</note> that he did reioyce and would reioyce in the sound
<pb facs="5"/> preaching of Christ crucified,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.18.</note> though the Preachers thereof were not (all of them) so sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely affected as they should haue beene.<note place="margin">Mat. 25.21.</note> Euen so our <hi>Paul,</hi> the Author of this little Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary (now entred into his Masters ioy) notwithstanding for his sound knowledge in the mystery of godlinesse, hee was well able, and for his loue to the Church of God, very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to haue written a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Catechisme of his owne; or might haue chosen some other, already extant in print, better digested then this: yet obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing by the often impressions, and by other experience, the large spread &amp; good acceptance that these few Questions &amp; Answers found among a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Christians, hee chose ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to giue light, and to put life
<pb facs="5"/> to these, then in so great varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of printed Catechismes to forth another of his owne fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</p>
   <p>Wherin (Christian Reader) I doe obserue a gracious proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God our heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, towards such as desire with <hi>Cornelius</hi> to feare God with all their Houshold, and to bring vp their young children and seruants in the nurture and admonition of the Lord.</p>
   <p>For by this meanes thou hast (to vse the phrase of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle) a patterne of wholsome words,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Tim. 1.13.</note> to direct and help thee to lay open and whet vpon thy family, these breefe and fami-points heere propounded, which though they bee plaine in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, yet by reason of the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie of them, they are made much more lightsome, easie
<pb facs="6"/> and vsefull, by this most plaine and pithy Commentary.</p>
   <p>Wherefore I would aduise and entreat thee (whosoeuer thou bee) that hast already ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a taste of these short Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions &amp; Answers, which haue beene so long extant, and so of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten printed and reprinted, that thou wouldest now vse this help, to take a more full draught of them: and thou shalt finde (by the blessing of God) that the profit wil exceed the pains.</p>
   <p>Onely one thing I would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertize thee of, touching the description and nature of saith, that the first Author of these short Questions and Answers, hauing had some further cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and conference about it, doth thinke that true iustifying faith (being the primary grace and glory of a Christian) may
<pb facs="6"/> bee thus described; that it is, A beleefe of the Gospell,<note place="margin">What true faith is.</note> whereby a man doth truely rest and cast himselfe vpon Christ alone, for remission of sinnes and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall saluation, both of soule and bodie. Which description, (though there be diuers other, both godly and learned) I take (vnder correction) to be most pertinent, and fit for the proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and examining of our selues, according to that exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of <hi>Paul,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.5</note> whether we bee in the faith or no (wherin stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the maine comfort or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfort of euery Christian man or woman in the world) therin notwithstanding humbly sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting my selfe and my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, to the censure of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Diuines, and to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church of God; and especially to that part of Gods
<pb facs="7"/> Church, which his right hand hath planted in this Land.</p>
   <p>Thus most humbly &amp; hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily beseeching the Father of lights,<note place="margin">Iam. 1.17.</note> from whom proceedeth euery good giuing and euery perfect gift, to giue thee a bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing by the good labours of this blessed man, I commend thee to the grace of our Lord Iesus Christ, to whom bee all glory and praise in the Church for euermore, Amen. From my house in the <hi>Black-Friers,</hi> this <hi>22.</hi> of May, <hi>1618.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>