<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A summary Conclusion of the vvhole.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117917_Ba2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68764</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23041</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117917</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A summary Conclusion of the vvhole.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The theatre of the empire of Great Britaine : presenting an exact geography of the kingdomes of England, Scotland, Ireland, and the iles adioyning: with the shires, hundreds, cities and shire-townes, within ye kingdome of England, divided and described by Iohn Speed</title>
                 <author>Speed, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Hall, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hall, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Humble, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Humble, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sudbury, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sudbury, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 146, that is 280, 10 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), maps (metal cuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb facs="536"/>
   <head>A summary Conclusion of the vvhole.</head>
   <figure>
      <p>ALL FOR THE BEST▪</p>
   </figure>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y the assistance of the <hi>All-Sufficient</hi> (the onely defence and Preseruer of man) my insufficient abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, haue attained the end of this worke, and my weake vnable Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son brought to a Period this large Edifice of GREAT BRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAINS THEATRE. How acceptable to others, I know not; but with what paines and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile to my selfe, my decaied strength too manifestly hath felt, and with what care of truth, the <hi>Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> alleaged through the whole Processe, are my witnesses; whose lines haue beene the measures, and Antiquities the matter, that hath raised the <hi>Fabrick</hi> vnto this height. The attempt was great, and farre vnfit (I must confesse) for me to vndergoe; which, euen at the first entrance was so censured by the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious, and in the continuance hath so proued: that now it being finished, as the Silkeworme endeth her life in her long wrought clew, so I in this <hi>Theatre</hi> haue built my owne Graue; whose Architecture howsoeuer defectiue it may be said to be, yet the proiect is good: and the cost great, though my selfe haue freely bestowed this paines to the Presse, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pressing a penny from any mans purse. For me to shew the vtilitie of History, were to light a dimme candle before the bright Sunne; or to prescribe a methode for their vses, were, with <hi>Phormio</hi> to reade a Lecture of Cheualrie vnto great <hi>Hannibal,</hi> warres experienced Conductor: But, as our owne concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vs neerest (wherein my pen hath taken the freest accesse) so let me abridge the whole in a small Circle, and incompasse that briefly, which hath beene rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in a farre wider circumference.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <note place="margin">The first Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants.</note> (2) Our Land, peopled from <hi>Iaphet</hi> the first sonne of <hi>Noah,</hi> fell vnto those sonnes of <hi>Gomer,</hi> who inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited these parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> whose issue were most fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mously knowne by the name of <hi>Britaines.</hi> At first, naked, rude, and ignorant of the true God; yet no sooner were frequented with the ciuill <hi>Romanes,</hi> but that they couered their Cut-painted bodies with Garments; and shortly imitated them euen in their <note place="margin">Their ciuilitie.</note>most ciuilized actions; yea, scarcely was Christ taken downe from his <hi>Crosse</hi> but they became <hi>Christians</hi>
      <note place="margin">Christianity.</note>(the greatest glory of any Nation) and among them the <hi>Gospell</hi> had her first progresse by established au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. Their Gouernment was vnder Kings, and <note place="margin">Gouernme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>▪</note>those of as honourable a respect, as were any other in these West-parts of the World, both in training their Subiects vnto due obedience, and ministring of Lawes for the maintainance of estate. Their warres <note place="margin">Warres.</note>domesticke and forraine were so managed with Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie and valour, as in the one they valiantly defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded themselues against their assaults, and in the other steeded the <hi>Romanes</hi> in most of their Conquests: which cost them lastly their owne subuersions, when their warriers and virgins were consumed and trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported into other parts, whilst their natiue Land lay exposed to the will of Inuaders.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <note place="margin">Their first Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rs.</note> (3) The glory-thirsting <hi>Romans</hi> (from a crew of lawlesse Shepheards now lately become Lords of the World) were the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st that set foot, with displaied Ensigne, for the Conquest of <hi>Britaine,</hi> and the same
<pb facs="537"/>
first assaied by <hi>Iulius Caesar</hi> from the Coasts of <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia.</hi> Which his attempt was so honourable in esteeme of their Emperors, that <hi>Claudius</hi> (the fifth in succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion) <note place="margin">Their Triumphs.</note>holding the Triumph but base, that attends vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on authority without action of Price, made choise of <hi>Britaine</hi> to adorne his triumphant Chariot, that this Iland (sited, as was thought, in another World, and but part thereof shewed by <hi>Caesar</hi> to the <hi>Romans)</hi> might adde remembrance of name to his forgetfull Person: and to that end, hauing made hither himselfe, stamped his Conquest vpon his Coines thus, DE BRITANN: and vpon his aged knees <note place="margin">Their esteeme.</note>crept vp the steps of the <hi>Capitoll,</hi> to giue thankes of victory vnto his gods on the day of his <hi>Triumph;</hi> which, though for a small part of this Ilands subie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, was yet accomplished with more then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie magnificence, and the shewes greater then vsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally had beene seene, for the Conquests of farre lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and better knowne Kingdomes. And with as great a care was it kept, whilst the <hi>Romans</hi> kept their owne greatnes. But when their high-mounted <note place="margin">Their ruine.</note>Pillar ouerswayed her owne Base, and the farre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spread boughes were growne too weighty for the stemme, many hands at once grasped at the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Crowne, and all of them together tare the Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches from the Body of that faire Tree. By whom also the faire and flourishing Cedars of <hi>Britain</hi> were shaken, and left naked both of fruite, and leafe. So that now the glory of the one declined, and the beauty of the other vtterly defaced, and neither of them able any longer to support their owne stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, gaue place vnto <hi>destiny</hi> that would now haue both downe; whereby the <hi>Iewell</hi> so much desired, <note place="margin">Abandoned by the <hi>Romans.</hi>
      </note>and which had beene kept with such care, was now laid at stake to them that could winne it, and <hi>Britain</hi> abandoned by the <hi>Romans,</hi> without further claime, after they had beene Lords thereof the space of fiue hundred yeeres.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <note place="margin">Inuaded by <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
      </note> (4) The next Actors vpon <hi>Britaines</hi> faire Stage, were the <hi>Saxons,</hi> a people of <hi>Germany,</hi> fierce, bold and irreligious, as, for the most part, the rest of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in those daies were. These infesting with Pira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies the Coasts of <hi>Britaine</hi> and <hi>Gallia,</hi> grew both feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and famous in profession of military seruices. In <hi>France</hi> they seized vpon the Country of <note n="*" place="margin">Baic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>x.</note>
      <hi>Baio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casses;</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> by intrusion they vnseated the <hi>Sueuians;</hi> in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Friesland,</hi> they incroached vpon the <hi>Batauians,</hi> and <hi>Cimbrica Chersonessus</hi> (now a continent of <hi>Denmarke)</hi> they made the place of their aboad. From whence they often assailed the Coasts of this Iland, euen whilst the <hi>Romans</hi> held it for theirs, and were often put backe by <hi>Stilicho</hi> and others, whose praises the <hi>Poet Claudian</hi> chaunted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud. But the <hi>Romans</hi> departed, and <hi>Britaine</hi> left bare of men, their land wasted by famine, tumultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vprores, and by bandings of Great-ones who <note place="margin">
         <hi>By</hi> Picts &amp; Scots.</note>should be greatest; the <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Picts</hi> (ancient Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to their Peace) tooke the aduantage, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually made bloody incursions into their Land. And albeit a stone-wall was raised athwart the whole Continent, to impeach their inroades, yet that auai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <note place="margin">The occasion of <hi>Saxons</hi> comming.</note>little, their assaults were so great. Whereupon the <hi>Saxons</hi> were sent for, and in their first seruice freed the <hi>Britaines</hi> from those raging <hi>Picts;</hi> The Lands defence then they vndertooke, and the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants consented to maintaine the charge; which whilst it was in giuing was thankefully receiued, but once receiued was vngratefully forgot. And they (like the Rauens of <hi>Arabia,</hi> who so long as they are full, yeeld a pleasant noise, but being empty make a horrible crie) emptied faster then the <hi>Britains</hi> could <note place="margin">Their vsurping on the Land.</note>fill, and euer complained they had not inough, till lastly by surprize they got all into their owne clawes. <note place="margin">Their diuiding the Land into an Hep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>archie.</note>Then deuided they among themselues the best of the Land, and droue their Receiuers into the worst and waste mountaines of <hi>Wales,</hi> euery of their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines sharing a part to himselfe, and of one Emperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Crowne made seauen <hi>Diadems</hi> to adorne their owne heads; which long were not worne, without intestine warres, each of them striuing to inlarge his owne, vpon his next, till God and destiny againe <note place="margin">The Hepta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e againe reuolued to a Monarchie.</note>brought all vnto <hi>One,</hi> euen to great <hi>Egbert,</hi> who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bade the Ilands old Name, and commanded these now vnited Prouinces to be called <hi>Anglia.</hi> Yet no <note place="margin">
         <hi>Britaine</hi> first na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>England.</hi>
      </note>sooner was this accomplished, with assured hopes conceiued, that the <hi>Saxons</hi> glory should thence for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ascend and spread forth with peace, but that a sauage nation, as fierce as the <hi>Scythians,</hi> cast their cies of desire vpon that beautifull Crowne, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently attempted, but neuer intermitted any bloody cruelties that could forward the same, till they had set it on their owne <hi>Helmets;</hi> and these <hi>Saxons</hi> worne <note place="margin">The <hi>Saxons</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion.</note>out with resistance, gaue place to the <hi>Danes,</hi> when time had worne out fiue hundred sixtie three yeeres of their Gouernment.</p>
   <p n="5">
      <note place="margin">The <hi>Danes</hi> intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</note> (5) These <hi>Danes</hi> thus succeeding (though with no better right to enioy) were a stout sturdy Nation whose many Piracies both <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Bretaigne</hi> had many times felt, before they attained the end of this their Goale. For these, multiplying like <hi>Bees</hi> in the Hiue, the land of their owne natiuitie was too little for each to haue a part: vpon which occasion a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome <note place="margin">The occasion thereof.</note>was practised to banish some that the rest might haue roome. These Exiles therefore (chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly consisting of their youth) fell vpon other Landes with no lesse danger, then the falling of a sword out of the sheath, and greeuously wounded wheresoeuer they fell; but no where more deadly then in <hi>England.</hi> Which for two hundred and eighteene yeeres con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, <note place="margin">Their continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance here.</note>they vncessantly assaulted; sometimes har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing the Countrey before them, and carrying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way great Booties to their Ships: sometimes impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerishing the People, by exacting great summes of <note place="margin">Their deuastati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons here.</note>money for composition of Peace: sometimes expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Inhabitants, and seating themselues in their places: and sometimes sharing the Country with their Kings, and taking vnto themselues none of the worst; but not as other Conquerors to build, sow, and plant, but to lay wast, cast downe, and destroy, sparing neither Erections for ciuill vse, nor places of Oratory dedicated to diuine. Yet the Garland once gotten by their King <hi>Canut,</hi> was worne with great glory, and by three of those <hi>Danish</hi> Kings, <hi>Englands</hi>
      <note place="margin">Their three Kings.</note>
      <hi>Crowne</hi> was enioied. The first of them Potent, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, wise and iust. The second, illegitimate, an vsur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per very agill, but idle: And the third a Tyrant, a Taxe-raiser, lasciuious and a glutton, in which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse <note place="margin">Their end.</note>at <hi>Lambeth</hi> he suddainely ended his life, when the Land became cleared of the <hi>Danes</hi> sore oppressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, after they had a long time attempted, and their Kings for fiue and twenty yeeres space worne the royall diademe of this Realme.</p>
   <p n="6">
      <note place="margin">The <hi>Normans.</hi>
      </note> (6) These foure Nations fulfilling their times by Heauens assignement, in gaining, keeping, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine loosing, the rich Garland of GREAT BRITAINES gouernment: a fift, inferiour to none, made thereunto a double claime, and by a <note place="margin">Their title to <hi>England.</hi>
      </note>third (more sure then both) which was, their <hi>conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring sword,</hi> got it. These last (which I pray may be last) were the <hi>Normans,</hi> a people fierce and valorous, whose many Sea-aduentures were so great, in the daies of <hi>Charles the Great,</hi> as that he wept to forsee the harmes they would doe to his in <hi>France,</hi> which proued so many that <hi>Charles the Bald</hi> (his Grand-Child) <note place="margin">Their attempts and seatings in <hi>France.</hi>
      </note>was forced to part with the Earledome of <hi>Charters</hi> vnto <hi>Hasting</hi> a Norman; <hi>Charles the Grosse</hi> with the County <hi>Newstria,</hi> vnto <hi>Godfrey</hi> their Chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: and <hi>Charles the Simple</hi> with all the Countreys which lay betwixt the Riuer <hi>Seine</hi> and <hi>Loyre,</hi> vnto <hi>Rollo</hi> their Leader, whereof he became Duke, and that Dutchie from him named <hi>Normandy.</hi> Whence <hi>William the Bastard</hi> the seuenth in discent, in a bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die <note place="margin">
         <hi>William</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors victory.</note>field at <hi>Battell</hi> in <hi>Sussex,</hi> wan the English Crowne from King <hi>Harold</hi> that held it; when, by changing of Lawes, disheriting of Nobles, and bestowing the Lands Reuenewes vpon his, he laid the foundation <note place="margin">The succession of the Crowne vnduely swa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ed.</note>of a glorious Monarchie. At first, somewhat bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, (as Conquests commonly proue) and the
<pb facs="537"/>
Crowne banded for, among brethren and kindred (as what will not the desire of a Diademe doe?) the two yonger brethren successiuely wearing it, to the preiudice of their <note n="*" place="margin">Robert Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thcose.</note>Elder, and <hi>Stephen</hi> hauing no right, but such as Intruders pretend. But <hi>Henrie</hi>
      <note place="margin">The Plantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets succession.</note>
      <hi>Plantagenet</hi> placed on the Throne, and three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thirty one yeeres taken vp in the Raignes of foureteene Kings of his line, their Acts afforde <note place="margin">Their large inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance.</note>matter of more Princely consequence, their Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions spread wider, themselues being the lawfull In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritors to the third part of <hi>France,</hi> and to the <hi>Whole</hi> by the <hi>Title</hi> of their <hi>third Edward,</hi> and by the <hi>Conquest</hi> of their <hi>fifth Henry.</hi> And surely had not the ciuill dissentions of <hi>Lancaster</hi> and <hi>Yorke</hi> spent their wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons in the woundes of themselues, those Kings and their Successours vndoubtedly had beene double <note place="margin">Their ciuill dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentions.</note>crowned euen to this day. But these <hi>Roses</hi> pluckt off by dissentious hands, and their Branches torne downe in home-bred broyles, their roiall rootes lay <note place="margin">The <hi>Tueders</hi> succession.</note>as it were dead in the Earth, till <hi>Teuder of Lancaster</hi> with <hi>Plantagenet</hi> of <hi>Yorke,</hi> gaue them vigor and sappe, by binding both together in wedlockes goulden band. Whereby also the long dead stemme of the auncient British Kings beganne againe to bud forth, <note place="margin">Fiue Princes of that sirname.</note>and fiue renowned Princes of that Sirname succee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in-<hi>Englands Throne.</hi> The <hi>first</hi> of them, the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chest, and wisest King, of this Westerne-World; The <hi>Second,</hi> the sorest wounder of the Papall authority; The <hi>third,</hi> the forwardest in all pious actions. The <hi>fourth</hi> the feruentest for the Religion of <hi>Rome;</hi> And the <hi>fifth</hi> a <hi>Mayden-Queene,</hi> the most famously re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned among the Worlds Monarkes, vnder whose raignes one hundred and sixteene yeeres were fully <note place="margin">Comin. lib. 4 cap. 10.</note>complete and run. And were it not that the English are taxed to be ouer-much addicted vnto vaine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesies, and that <hi>Merlins</hi> was prohibited by decree <note place="margin">The Crowne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the old <hi>Britaine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> and <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> to her olde Name.</note>of Counsell, I might alledge his, and that of <hi>Aquila</hi> at <hi>Shaftesbury,</hi> both of them foreshewing that the <hi>British Empire</hi> after the <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>Normans,</hi> should returne againe to her auncient <hi>Stocke</hi> and <hi>Name.</hi> Notwithstanding Truth bids vs acknowledge, how farre God hath accomplished both these in the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <note place="margin">The Vnion of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hole Iland in the persō of our Soueraigne.</note>Person of our now-<hi>Soueraigne,</hi> the one by his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent from the loines of that Roiall <hi>Tuder</hi> King <hi>Henry the Seuenth;</hi> and the other, by his <hi>Edict,</hi> in restoring to the <hi>Iland</hi> her auncient Name, <hi>Britannia:</hi> himselfe being the <hi>first Monarch</hi> of the two Kingdomes V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and the greatest of Command, since <hi>Canutus the Dane.</hi> The Cordes of whose <hi>Royall Tents,</hi> we pray, may be further extended, that those naked <hi>Virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> may be couered vnder the Curtaines of his most Christian Gouernment; and that the <hi>Scepter</hi> of his <hi>Peace</hi> may bud, as <hi>Aarons Rod</hi> in his hand, and in the hand of his Sonne, and Sonne Sonnes, so long as the <hi>Sunne</hi> and <hi>Moone</hi> endureth.</p>
   <p n="7">(7) These then (worthy Reader) are the Heads, whence haue issued such plentifull Springs, that now met together in one Body the Streame is grown very bigge, which thing I euer feared, but could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer preuent; offending rather with the <hi>Niggard</hi> who thinketh euery mite too-much, then sinning with the <hi>Prodigall</hi> in superfluous excesse; so plenteous is our Story, and so largely requires it to bee writ. Through all which my weake body with many yeeres labour hath alone trauelled, aswell in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiewing of the Geographicall parts of the Land, as in the compiling of the succeeding History, though far vnable to perfect either, according to their owne worths. But lest the waight of the whole should rest vpon so slender a proppe as my selfe: I haue laid my buildings vpō far stronger arches, as by the many al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged authorities may appeare. For first, the Chards <note place="margin">L. Har. Christ. Saxton. Iohn Norden. Wil. White.</note>for the most part traced by others, and most of them diuulged vnto view, were the foundations of my begunne paines; in supplying their wants with my many additions, and dimensions of the Shire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>townes, and Cities true platformes. The further descriptions of sundry prouinces, I haue gleaned from the famous workes of the most worthy and learned <hi>Cambden,</hi> whose often sowed seedes in that Soile hath lastly brought forth a most plenteous haruest. For the body of the Historie, many were the manuscripts, notes, and Records, wherewith my honored and learned friends supplied me; but none more (or so many) as did the worthy repairer of ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting times ruines, the learned <hi>Sir Robert Cotten</hi> Knight Baronet, another <hi>Philadelphus</hi> in preseruing old Monuments, and ancient Records: whose Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binets were vnlocked, and Library continually set open to my free accesse: &amp; from whence the chiefest garnishments of this worke haue beene enlarged and brought: such as are the antique altars, &amp; Trophies in Stone, by him preserued from perishing obliuion; The Coines of gold, siluer, alcumy, and copper, of the <hi>Britaines, Romans, Saxons, Danes,</hi> and <hi>English,</hi> with the Broade Seales of those Kings since the same were in vse: all of them so followed from the originall moddles, and moneyes, by the most exquisit and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious hand of our age, as any eye may witnes they are <note place="margin">Christ. Swister.</note>the true prints from those stamps. The like most ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable helpes, both of Bookes and Collections, (especially in matters remoter from our times) I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually receiued from that worthy <hi>Diuine, Master Iohn Barkham,</hi> a gentleman composed of <hi>Learning, Vertue, &amp; Curtesie,</hi> as being no lesse ingenuously wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, then learnedly able, to aduance and forward all vertuous endeuours. Besides these, some other supply I haue had: for my disease growne dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and life held in suspence; it behoued him who had towards the publishing bestowed so great cost, to forward the finshing; and to that end hee procured mee to his further charges an <note n="*" place="margin">M. Ed. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ol.</note>assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant in the liues of our middle <hi>English</hi> Kings: whose Stories and raignes (by the Iudicious) may by their stiles bee knowne to bee writ with another penne. Lastly for the matters of <hi>Herauldrie,</hi> the willing and ready paines of Master <hi>William Smith, Rough Dragon,</hi> (an Officer at armes) was euer at hand: and by these hands this building is mounted to such an height as thou seest: which thus now finished, this scanted Epitome, may well serue thy foote-steppes, as staires to ascend these fiue nationall Stories alreadie finished, and leade thee into the sixth now most happilie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne. Where from those mounted heights, thou maist behold, how <hi>Time</hi> hath squared the Stones of these buildings: how <hi>Fortune</hi> hath va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in contriuing the Worke: and how the <hi>Fates</hi> haue erected, polished, and puld downe, the supporting Pillars of GREAT BRITAINES THEATRE. From whose <hi>Tarras</hi> with <hi>Dauid</hi> cast not thy lusting eie vpon vnlawfull delights: Nor with <hi>Babels</hi> King boast, that this was built by thy <note place="margin">Deu. 26.</note>owne might: But with <hi>Moses</hi> confesse that from a small stocke (as a graft of the Lords planting) thou art now growne into a great Nation, mighty, and ful of people. And with <hi>Salomon</hi> make supplication <note place="margin">2. Chro. 6.</note>vnto thy great <hi>Iehouah,</hi> that the <hi>Arke of his strength</hi> may euer rest in this House, &amp; his eies be euer open thereon day and night. With the <hi>Prophet</hi> pray that <note place="margin">Isaiah 54. 11.</note>this building may be as beauteous as his, the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations laid with <hi>Saphires,</hi> her Windowes with the <hi>Emerauds,</hi> and her Gates with the <hi>Carbuncles.</hi> That the desarts of this <hi>chosen Zion</hi> may be as <hi>Eden,</hi> and her <note place="margin">Isaiah 51. 3.</note>wildernes like the <hi>Garden of God.</hi> Her Gouernment <hi>Peace,</hi> her People the <hi>Saints of Saluation,</hi> &amp; her Kings <note place="margin">Hag. 2.</note>the <hi>Signets on Gods right hand,</hi> successiuely to sit on this Royall Throne, till <hi>Christ the King of Kings</hi> shall come in the Clowdes, and from the Raine-Bow the Throne of his Maiesty pronounce vs blessed, and make vs heires with himselfe of that Kingdome which neuer shall haue end. <hi>Vnto which</hi> CHRIST, <hi>with his</hi> FATHER, <hi>and</hi> HOLY SPIRIT, <hi>three in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons but</hi> ONE GOD <hi>eternall, vndiuideable in Deity, be ascribed all Praise, Honour, Glorie, Wisdome, Power and Might for euermore.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
   <trailer>FINJS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>