<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117870_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13158</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23452</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117870</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe examination, of a certaine peremptorie menacing and disleal petition presented, as is pretended, to the Kings most excellent Maiestie, by certaine laye papistes, calling themselues, the lay Catholikes of England, and now lately printed, and diuulged by a busie compagnion, called Iohn Lecey</title>
                 <author>Sutcliffe, Matthew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Burby, Cuthbert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 133, 136-146, 145-141, that is 147, 5 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> DOE not beleeue, gentle reader, that many lay papists will sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe this petition, albeit pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to bee framed and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited by all of them to the King. It were a matter too sawcy, for wise, and ciuill men to challenge the king of breach of pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mise, as they do pag. <hi>8:</hi> and too presumptuous to rayle on religion publiquelie professed, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors thereof, to the Kings face, as they do in diuers places. Neither do I think, that all are so foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish, as to make themselues pledges and hostages for their Masse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priests, suffering such slippery cōpaniōs to dominere in their houses, to confer with their wiues &amp; daughters, to wast their estate, while they haue no Counterbond from them, either for the others good behauiour, or theire owne securitie. This I am well assured, that what soeuer is pretended, this petition neuer came Originally from the heades of lay papistes. For neyther may such men withoute licence, reade <hi>Caluines</hi> Institutions, nor <hi>Luthers</hi> bookes, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther discourses written by men of our side: nor may they take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to discourse of Religion, as the Authors of this petition doe.</p>
   <p>I wold therfore pray the simpler sort of plain meaning Papists, not to take what soeuer is sharpely spoken against the Masse Priestes masked vnder the name of lay papists, and the sole deuisers of this
<pb facs="4"/>petition, and their abherents, the Authors of many treasons and mischiefes, as spoken or meant against themselues, and all sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced simple soules. And against such as so violently run a course a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst truth, and seek to blow vp the King and State: I doubte not, but all indifferent men will esteeme my speech moderate, and this kinde of dealing most fitting and conuenient. What? shall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumcized Philistims raile at the people of God, and seeke our destruction; and shall not true Christians be permitted liberty to represse theire insolency, to countermine their vndermining trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and freely to defend the truth?</p>
   <p>When themselues do publish their petitions, they may not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse to haue them publiquelie examined; and no reason haue they to complaine of wrong, seeing themselues thus handled, when not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding their wicked intentions, they put forth their Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyes, requests, and discourses into other mens handes, as if they were most loyall and honest men.</p>
   <p>Hitherto they haue abused the worlde with a false pretence of antiquitie, and falselie chalenged to themselues the name and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>Catholiques.</hi> They doe also before such, as are ignorant of matters of state, stand vpon termes of loyalty, and loue of theire Prince and country. But now that we are so farre vrged, we shall God willing, make it appeare, that their Popish deuises are nothing but a pack of nouelties latelie brought into the Romish church, &amp; that their Religion is full of heresies, impieties and blasphemies: and lastly that diuers of their practises are full of Salt peter, and most dangerous to the state: and that their importunate desires are repugnāt both to reasons of religion &amp; state, and also to modest and ciuill cariage.</p>
   <p>My sole request to thee shall be, that thou woldest be please to com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pare our answer with the lay papists petition, and to iudge accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to proofes, We seeke for trueth, we defend the Kings preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue and state. Let no man therfore shut his eies against that light, by which we may see truth, nor bee carelesse in matters so nerelye touching the safety of the King and state, neither let any papist bee offended with vs, while we seeke his saluation. <hi>Non ideo vobis displiceamus,</hi> saith Saint Augustine <hi>to certein Donatists, epist.
<pb facs="5"/>204. ad Donatum, quia reuocamus errātes, &amp; quaerimus perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos.</hi> and so wee say also to the simple, and abused papists, <hi>Let vs not displease you, because we seek to call you from your errors, and to gaine that which is lost,</hi> We doe not hate you, as our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimen, but we detest your errors, being humorously affected to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine superstition. In speaking also for common peace and safety we seek your peace. The petitioners say, they are resolued and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend reason of their resolution. But nothing is more fantastical or foolish, then to resolue vpon false suppositions, and to build with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out firme foundation. neither is any thing more sottish then to seek that, which being granted, would turne to theire dishonoure and hurt, if not destruction.</p>
   <p>To confirme the weake, and to recall those which goe astray wee haue done our best endeuour: wee haue also defended the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of religion, his maiestie, and the state, as became vs. The rest wee referre to gods grace; beseeching him, so to enlighten all chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian mens heartes with the knowledg of his eternall truth, that not onelie the professors of religion may stand firm against the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing perswasions of seducing and seditions Iebusites and Masse-Priests: but also such, as encline too much to error and superstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and nowe seeme malcontented, maye be gathered into the true Church, and shew themselues true subiects, embracing truth and perseuering therein to their liues end.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>