<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPVL, and his much respected friend, Sir THOMAS GARDINER Knight, all happinesse in Christ Iesus.</title>
           <author>Scot, Patrick</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117205_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12091</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22395</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117205</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPVL, and his much respected friend, Sir THOMAS GARDINER Knight, all happinesse in Christ Iesus.</title>
                 <author>Scot, Patrick</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first sermon of R. Sheldon priest, after his conuersion from the Romish Church : preached before an honourable assembly at S. Martins in the Field, vpon Passion Sunday, &amp;c. Published by authoritie</title>
                 <author>Sheldon, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 67, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPVL, and his much respected friend, Sir THOMAS GARDINER <hi>Knight, all happinesse</hi> in Christ Iesus.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, I present this my Sermon vnto you, and place your worthy name in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frōt thereof; thereby to shew my respectiue loue vnto you, &amp; to let you vnderstand; that if there be any fault committed in the publishing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; that you ought to beare a great portion of the blame, who haue bin (amongst very many others) earnest. with mee to afford it publike attire. If the Pon ifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians be distasted therewith, they may in some part thanke them selues; some of them haue beene too cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mourous out of the relation either of ignorant, male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolent, or semi-popish hearers, in rumoring the same, to haue beene but a rouing discourse, sometimes ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned; somewhiles vnlcarned; but alwaies very bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter against the Papists; so bitter, that in it, I branded all those of that sect and heresic (excepting none what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer) with the vile marke of disloyalty &amp; traiterous spirits. In consideration whereof, I was easier induced to let it see light, and in so publike a habit to vndergoe all censures: and (to giue thereader some satisfaction) this also the rather, because through confuse noises, and clatterings, of voices, and of dores (my selfe, stay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not lesse then a whole houre in an open pew, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the deliuery of my Sermon;) the recollection of my memory was then somewhat confused: so that, for that cause, and through want of time also, I did not,
<pb facs="3"/> nor could not pronounce all thereof, so fully, and in that sort as I intended it. The scope thereof (kind Sir) being briefly and contractly (not intended for so publike, and so honourable an assembly) to delineat the inestimable perfections and dignities of Christ; to perswade all my Auditours to a sincere and most zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous affiance for saluation in his onely blood: to most assured loyalties to their Prince, and Countrey, and to a detestation against all Pop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sh, Ignatian, bloody, and sanguineous attempts, against the state of this Church and Countrey: I doe not know any one of your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ranke and calling, to whom a discourse of this kind would prooue more acceptable, more welcome. Make acceptance of it (Sir) therefore, with that loue and respect, with which it is sent; and doe mee this fauour, that if you heare any semi-papists, or anie that are leaning that way, or any other, doubtfullie to coniecture or surmise, whether my c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nuersion bee from the heart or not; or for hope of preferment, to speake as you haue heard, as you thinke, and perfectlie know of mee: for you know, and knew from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, from whom my encouragements haue beene; from God; from Iesus Christ: whose name therefore, be euer magnified and blessed; to whose blessings, and gratious fauours, I commend both you and yours, for euer.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From my chamber, <date>this 28. of Aprill, 1612.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your worships most assured in Christ Iesus, R. SHELDON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>