<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE IVDGEMENT OF Conradus Minutius, touch∣ing Silesio: and the surviving memory of his Labours.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117416_Fr1_9</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12245</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22553</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117416</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE IVDGEMENT OF Conradus Minutius, touch∣ing Silesio: and the surviving memory of his Labours.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Arcadian princesse; or, The triumph of iustice : prescribing excellent rules of physicke, for a sicke iustice. Digested into fowre bookes, and faithfully rendred to the originall Italian copy, by Ri. Brathvvait Esq</title>
                 <author>Silesio, Mariano</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Bostock, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 192, 191-254, 250, 8 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>THE IVDGEMENT OF <hi>Conradus Minutius,</hi> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Silesio:</hi> and the surviving memory of his <hi>Labours.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vfficiently wee cannot admire, much lesse imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate these exquisite com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posures of that Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine <hi>Silesio.</hi> By so much more famous for his Learning, because borne in a time, almost ignorant of learning. He was of pregnant wit, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent conceit, solid judgement and reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive memory. Hee scorned nothing more, than to impe his wings with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers feathers; for his usuall saying was this: <hi>He does himself dishonour, who makes himselfe witty by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Labour.</hi> In the time of his reside at Court, there were no Transcripts held so precious as his Poems. In his
<pb facs="11"/>
r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>per yeares, bidding adue to those <hi>trifles of youth,</hi> (for so was hee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to style them) he addressed his em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments to more serious studies: for observing, how the <hi>State</hi> tooke especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all notice of him, he held it indiscreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to bestow his oyle on ought lesse, than what might redound to the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the <hi>State.</hi> Albeit, in his latter yeares, being much addicted to priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, He retired and withdrew himselfe from the grandeure of publique af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires: resolving to dedicate the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of his dayes to a <hi>contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive life,</hi> which hee called his <hi>soules love:</hi> where hee breathed forth many divine fancies full of spirit and morall profit. Hee dyed, <hi>Anno Dom. 1368.</hi> and was honourably buried in the <hi>Lemnian arch,</hi> with a pyram<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>dall Monument erected over him.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>