<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
           <author>B., E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117685_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12679</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22999</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117685</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>B., E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true discourse of the armie which the King of Spaine caused to bee assembled in the hauen of Lisbon, in the kingdome of Portugall, in the yeare 1588. against England : The which began to go out of the said hauen, on the 29. and 30. of May. Translated out of French into English, by Daniel Archdeacon. Whereunto is added the verses that were printed in the first page of the Dutch copy printed at Colen, with answeres to them, and to Don Bernardin de Mendozza</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>70, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="5" facs="2"/>
   <head>The Epistle to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath beene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes (Christian Reader) a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all practise of the wicked and vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not onely neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting the almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to trust in their owne might: but relying on themselues and theyr own power to glory and boast there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of vnto the world. So we reade in the first age of the world, <hi>Lamec</hi> tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting to the inuentions of his sons <hi>Iabal, Iubal,</hi> and <hi>Tubalkaijn,</hi> boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth himselfe vnto his wiues that hee would not take the least iniurie, no not of the meanest person, but he woulde slay a strong man in his wound and a yong man in his hurt.
<pb n="6" facs="3"/>
      <hi>Nimrod</hi> in the second age waxing mightie on the earth, and without all reuerence of the Lord, or (as the scripture speaketh) in the presence of the Lorde, hunting men like wilde beastes, neuer lefte vntill by his cursed seede hee had erected hym a tower whose top might reache vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heauen, thereby to get him a name, and to shewe vnto the world what hee was able to doe. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the like vaineglory, wee reade of <hi>Nabuchadnezar, Nichanor,</hi> and diuers other.</p>
   <p>But as this hath bene a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall custome of the wicked, so they haue not herein respected or had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard vnto any thing more, then first the encouragement of their owne, I meane the vngodly, then the discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of the faithfull and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: for heereby they would seeme to perswade them, that for as much as they are fewe and weake, as the
<pb n="7" facs="3"/>
godly alwaies are in respect of the wicked, and therefore not able to match or counteruaile thē in power, they are not to stand with them, but as others haue done to yeeld to thē: to this end tendeth the proud boast, and vaunt of blasphemous <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>schake</hi> Embassadour to that wicked <hi>Senacharib.</hi> Make warre saith he to <hi>Eliakim</hi> with my maister the king of <hi>Assiria,</hi> and I will deliuer thee two thousand horses, if thou be able to set riders on them. And afterwarde haue any of the gods of the nations by any meanes deliuered their land from the king of <hi>Assiria</hi>: where are the Gods of <hi>Chanath</hi> and <hi>Arphad?</hi> where are they of <hi>Sepharuaijm</hi> and <hi>Hhiuua?</hi> nay haue they deliuered <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria,</hi> that the Lord should deliuer <hi>Ieruschalaijm</hi> out of my hand. Thus to the discouragement of the people of the Lord <hi>Rabschake</hi> vaunteth and boasteth himselfe.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="8" facs="4"/>Inferiour to none of these are at this day our Italian <hi>Lamec</hi> and Spanish <hi>Nimrod,</hi> the pope I meane and the Spanishe king: the one whereof trusting to the inuentions and practises of his priestly proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, to small and great threatneth death without cause, being so much worse then cursed <hi>Lamec,</hi> the other hauing with <hi>Nimrod,</hi> like beastes hunted men with dogges in <hi>India,</hi> woulde fayne vse the like practise heere in England, and hath by hys ships, made like <hi>Babel</hi> towers, vaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himselfe to make vs afrayd: and because the sight of these, he knewe, could not come vnto all, hath heere as thou mayst beholde, like <hi>Sancha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib</hi> by <hi>Rabschake</hi> by this booke, as by his embassadour, published vnto thee his whole power.</p>
   <p>Neither yet commeth this embas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage either to <hi>Chirkija,</hi> or <hi>Eliakim,</hi> to our gratious prince or her honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="9" facs="4"/>
counsayle, that they in his owne tongue might answere him againe, but he hath published it to all beside our selues, in Italian, Spanishe, Dutch, and French, and yet to them thereby to discourage vs: for these he telleth, he hath thus many huge shippes, so many thousandes of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med men, such multitude of muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as no man could deliuer vs out of his hand, or as if hee cried out with <hi>Rabschake</hi>: Let not England deceiue you, for it cannot deliuer you out of my hand, nor let not <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> perswade you to trust in the Lord, saying, doubtlesse the Lorde will deliuer vs, and not giue ouer our countrey into the handes of the king of Spaine. But make apoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with me, and come foorth vnto me, and so yee shall eate euery man of the fruit of his owne Vine, and of his owne Figge-tree, and drinke euery man the water of his owne
<pb n="10" facs="5"/>
Cesterne. Haue not I practised (by receiuing and cherishing diuers of their owne nations) to make them fit instrumentes by treason to serue my purpose, and what shoulde ayle me that I haue not already conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their countrey. Thus beloued, the Spanish <hi>Nimrod</hi> practiseth not onely to feare vs, but to allure all men from taking part with vs.</p>
   <p>But such trust beloued haue wee in the Lord, and so little account in respect of the Lord we make of the power of man, that we suffer them to say euen as much in English too, nay wee teach them to speake it in our owne tongue, not that our purpose is as theirs was to daunt or discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the fearefull multitude, but to propound vnto the world their folly in boasting thus vaynely, and then to encourage our selues to go forward in that hope and confidence we haue had in the Lord.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="11" facs="5"/>For touching their folly, how ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous hath it bene, that when as in respect of the time it hath bin a prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise of long continuance, and of so mighty and many Monarchies, as the Pope, the king and the prince: and last, of such prouision, that for ships they haue built them like Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stels: for men, made choyse of expert and mightie: for munition, they haue much and marueilous: they shoulde come so long prouided against a land as it were vnawares, so manie and mightie Monarchies against so smal and litle an Iland: such huge ships a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst so small pinases, as it were, and of these to take (as the Lord bee praised they haue) so strange repulse, is in respect of the trust and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence they put in them, and of the triumphes and boastes before the victorie they made in diuers places of them, no doubt in the feare of the Lord to be not onely derided and
<pb n="12" facs="6"/>
laughed at, but acknowledged a most strange and wonderfull worke of the Lorde, as who knewe their dwelling, and their going out, and coming in, and their furie against him. And therefore because they had raged against him, and their tumulte was come into his eares, did put a booke into their nostrisles and a bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle into their lippes, and brought thē backe the same way they came, not suffering them to enter into the land nor to come against it with a shielde, nor to cast a banke about it, but hath deliuered it for his owne sake, and for his seruants sake.</p>
   <p>And concerning the confidence and encouragement, wee are on the view of this catalogue, to conceaue, how can it be but most speciall and singular, seeing the deliuerance hath bin most singular? For when we shal see from what strange crueltie, and forraine power we haue bene deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="13" facs="6"/>
shall we not alwaies after say, Praysed be the Lord which hath not giuen vs as a pray vnto their teeth but our soule is escaped euen as a bird out of the snare of the fowler the snare is broken and we are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, our helpe therefore is in the name of the Lord which hath made both heauen and earth. For hence we learne that a horse (and so a ship with men and all meanes els) is but a vayne thing to saue a man, neither that anie man is deliuered by much strength, but that whereas they put their trust some in horses, some in Chariots, we must remember the name of the lord, &amp; with <hi>Iehoschaphat</hi> crie: <hi>We had no strength to resist so great a multitude coming against vs, neither knew we what to do, but our eies were fixed on thee O Lord.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thus therefore thou seest what was our drift and purpose in publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing this in our natiue toung which
<pb n="14" facs="7"/>
hath bin heretofore in diuers lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, not as the aduersarie would to discourage thee, but to make shew vnto thee how vayne it is to trust in outward meanes, and then to learne thee to trust in the Lord, who is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to saue thee, and as hee hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie begun, will do still, if thou go forward to trust in him. For the lord hath caused the forces of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, this their great Armado, to be daunted, and greatly endangered by his great wisedome, putting into the minds of our Captaines and sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours, to prouide sixe or seauen of the worst of the ships they had at sea, with such necessaries as should serue best to set them on fire withall, which they sent amongst the Spaniards, thereby to remoue and scatter them, yea euen when they thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues most sure, and likelyest to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue more succor, &amp; as they lay fast at Ankor neere Calis. Wherefore
<pb n="15" facs="7"/>
they arose and sought euery man to helpe himselfe, hewing and slipping their cables, &amp; leauing their ankors behinde them. Yea and some he hath caused to run aground vpō one shore, and some vpon an other, and some suncke, and other some taken with diuerse of their men, some of them of great name, with their ensignes, ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, stremers, and gitterns, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of diuerse were hanged about the battelments and crosse of Paules, on the <hi>8.</hi> of September <hi>1588.</hi> &amp; on the <hi>9.</hi> at London bridge, thereby to comfort his English <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and all her faithfull subiects. For the which his many and sundry benefits, wee beseech him graunt all that faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeue in him, grace to continue thankfull in glorifying him and his holy name for euer, to the good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of all other.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>E. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>