<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>MOST REMARKABLE testimonies cōcerning B. Aloysius and this History, giuen by foure Reuerend, and Religious Fathers, who had read the same, and com∣pared it with the publike Instru∣ments at Brescia.</title>
           <author>Silvester, F.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117299_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18332</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4912</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117299</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>MOST REMARKABLE testimonies cōcerning B. Aloysius and this History, giuen by foure Reuerend, and Religious Fathers, who had read the same, and com∣pared it with the publike Instru∣ments at Brescia.</title>
                 <author>Silvester, F.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The life of B. Aloysius Gonzaga of the Society of Iesus : eldest sonne of Ferdinand Prince of the S.R. Empire, and Marques of Castilion. Written in Latin by the R. Fa. Virgilius Ceparius of the same society. And translated into English by R.S</title>
                 <author>Cepari, Virgilio</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 518, 10 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="testimonies">
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <head>
      <hi>MOST REMARKABLE testimonies cōcerning</hi> B. Aloysius <hi>and this History, giuen by foure Reuerend, and Religious Fathers, who had read the same, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared it with the publike Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at</hi> Brescia.</head>
   <div type="testimony">
      <head>The Testimony of the VICAR OF THE INQVI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, of the Order of S. Dominicke.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
         <hi>Fr.</hi> Siluester Vgolotus, <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Diuinity of the order of the Friars Preachers, &amp; Vicar Generall of the holy Office of the Inqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
               <desc>•••</desc>
            </gap>ion, in the Citty and Diocesse of</hi> Brescia, <hi>do testify, and vnder my oath af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that I haue read the life of that B. Prince Lord</hi> Aloysius Gonzaga, <hi>Marques of</hi> Castilion, <hi>and of the Religious Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb facs="13"/>
of</hi> IESVS, <hi>written by the most Reuerend Father</hi> Virgilius Ceparius <hi>a Deuine, and Preacher of the same Society, which I haue cōpared with the publike instruments, out of which it was drawne, and I find that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer is recounted of the vertue and sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>s B. young man, is all taken from te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonies confirmed by oath, and from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments made by the Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>riarchall, Archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>iscopall, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>piscopall authority of many Citties. Moreouer, I do verily belieue, that not only that which is related in this history, but euen much more is very true. For when I knew this B. Prince being as yet but of tender age, and that I conuersed with him, I found by good experience, that from his very child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood he was accounted a Saint, &amp; commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by all, as one of an Angelicall life, and conuersation; of which thing I my selfe could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> many examples. And now in this history there is not only any thing repugnant either to sayth or good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>ners, but it is euen written prudently, and with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>eligious spirit, and aboundeth with examples of sanctity. Verily, I am most confident that it will bring very much spirituall profit, not only to reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
<pb facs="13"/>
men, out euen to those that are secular, as namely to Princes and Lords, vnto all which this B. Father, hath b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ne both a Guide and Example. In testimony wherof I haue written, and subs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ribed these letters. Giuen at</hi> Brescia, <hi>in our Couent of</hi> S. Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicke.</p>
      <closer>
         <signed>I THE ABOVE NAMED Fr. Siluester, whatsoeuer I haue aboue testified, affirme it vpon my oath.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="testimony">
      <head>THE READER OF THE BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictine Monkes of Cassino.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
         <hi>D. Paul Cattaneus</hi> Monke of the order of <hi>S. Benedict,</hi> of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>assino,</hi> or of <hi>S. Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> at <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>dua,</hi> Reader of Philosophy, &amp; Cases of Conscience in the Monastery of the <hi>SS. Faustinus,</hi> and <hi>Iouita</hi> at <hi>Bres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> being sworne do testify that I hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> read the life of that Blessed Prince A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LOYSIVS GONZAGA Marques of <hi>Castilion,</hi> and afterward Religious of the
<pb facs="14"/>
Society of IESVS, written by that most Reuerend F. VIRGILIVS CE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PARIVS a Deuine &amp; Preacher of the same order; and that I haue compared it with all those authenticall instruments and Registers, from whence it was drawne; and that I haue found what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer thinges are said therin, to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by sworne witnesses, and those worthy of credit; And that it is so far from conte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ning any thing contrary to good manners, that it is replenished with holy examples, and most worthy to be published for the generall profit of the faythfull. For out of that very motion of mind, and fruit which I my selfe tooke therin, I do easily perswade my selfe, that it will take no lesse effect with whomesoeuer shall read it. And also I my selfe, who knewe him many yeares in the world before he gaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to religion, am able to testify, that he was by the common consent of all esteemed a holy yong man; that he was commended; and that many of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable actes, were ordinarily in the
<pb facs="14"/>
mouthes of men, as of one remarkable for Sanctity. And when he departed to enter into Religion, all the people that were subiect to his dominion strucken with the losse of so great a Prince, gaue themselues ouer to lamentations. In te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony of which thinges I haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and subscribed these letters with my owne hand Giuen in the Monastery of <hi>S. Faustinus.</hi>
      </p>
      <closer>
         <signed>
            <hi>I THE FORSAID</hi> D. Paul, <hi>confirme all these thinges vnder my oath.</hi>
         </signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="testimony">
      <head>THE PROVINCIAL OF the Capuchins.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>
            <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE life of the B. Prince</hi> L▪ A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loysius Gonzaga, <hi>Marques of</hi> Castilion <hi>adorned with all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and merits, religious of the holy Society of</hi> IESVS, <hi>which heerafter is set downe by that very Reuerend</hi> F. Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius
<pb facs="15"/>
Ceparius <hi>Doctour of Diuinity, and preacher of the same Society, and with great diligence collected out of the testimonies &amp; authorities of sworne witnesses (as my selfe haue found in particular, comparing these with the same, and vnder my oath affirme it,) is altogeather worthy to be published, for the glory of God, who sheweth himselfe so admirable in his Saints, for the example of Christian Princes, for the edifiyng of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and fayth full people. This Prince wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of all glory, was borne (as I may say) ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily; and whilst he liued, was adorned from God with such, and so great giftes and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, that truly I am of an opinion that three singular thinges may be recoūted of him.</hi> The first, <hi>that, as once was said of Saint</hi> Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture, <hi>by his Maister</hi> Alexander Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lensis, Adam seemed not to haue sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in him: <hi>so remote from all suspition of sinne, did he retaine his state of innocency.</hi> The other, <hi>that in his manners he rather seemed to be like an A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>ell, then a man: so much did the spirit in him ouercome the flesh, the mind the sense.</hi> The third, <hi>that after a singular kind of manner, that same
<pb facs="15"/>
saying of the Wiseman agreeth vnto him:</hi> Consummatus in breui, expleuit tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora multa: <hi>Being consummate in short space, he fulfilled much time. For in a short space of time, that he liued in this mortall life, he attained vnto that, which in many yeares for the most part, many Saints scarcely arriued vnto, and mounted vnto that degree of perfectiō, which many others haue in vaine attempted to obtaine. For if that common pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe be true, that,</hi> Communis vox popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, vox Dei: <hi>the common voyce of the people is the voyce of God: for so much as this B. Prince is thought in the opinion of all, and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated by the voyce of all, as a Saint, by the Princes, by the Prelates of the Church, by his Confessours, Maisters, Tutours, Parents, the people of his Dominion; it must of necessity follow that he was a great Saint, and that he may very worthily, as in heauen, so also vpon earth, be canonized for a Saint. Whome I wish an intercessour and aduocate for me, to the Diuine Maiesty. Giuen at</hi> Brescia, <hi>in our House of the</hi> SS. Peter <hi>and</hi> Marcellinus.</p>
      <pb facs="16"/>
      <closer>
         <signed>I <hi>Fr. Iohn Francis of</hi> Brescia, <hi>Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial of the Friars Capuchins in the Prouince of</hi> Brescia, <hi>Preacher, &amp; Reader of Diuinity, haue written and suscribed with my owne hand all these things, and with my oath do ratify the same.</hi>
         </signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="testimony">
      <head>FATHER RECTOVR the Society of IESVS.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>
            <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> IOHN Baptista Peruschus</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> Rectour of the Colledge of the Society of IESVS at <hi>Brescia,</hi> after the Reuerend <hi>Fa. Virgilius Ceparius</hi> of our Society, came to this our Colledge of <hi>Brescia,</hi> to the intent that he might commit to writing the life of our blessed Brother <hi>Aloysius Gonzaga,</hi> of the same Society, haue compared the
<pb facs="16"/>
same life written by him, with those re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistred Tables and Monuments, out of which with great labour and industry it was taken; and being sworne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, that whatsoeuer is said therin, is found in Authorities and Testimonies confirmed by oath. I do also testify, that the selfe same Father, to the intent that he might procure those Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and frame an authenticall histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, trauailed to all these townes of <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bardy.</hi> And so much the more willingly do I subscribe to these things, for that I was familiatly acquainted with <hi>B. Aloysius,</hi> both before he forsooke the world, and also when he was ioyned vnto vs in religion at <hi>Millan,</hi> and <hi>Rome;</hi> and many signes of his sanctity, which the same Father recounteth in this booke, I my selfe knew. And I am well assured, that in the opinion of all them that knew, him and liued with him, he was reputed a Saint. And after his death the fame of his sanctity daily increased, &amp; in many townes of <hi>Lombardy,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I haue liued now many yeares, it so
<pb facs="17"/>
far forth spread it selfe, that it cannot be imagined how it should do more. In testimony wherof I haue giuen this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my owne hand writing.</p>
      <closer>
         <signed>Ioannes Baptista Peruschus, who do confirme vnder my oath al the things aboue related.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div type="testimony">
      <head>CLAVDIVS AQVAVIVA Generall of the Society of IESVS.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>
            <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E haue granted leaue, that this Booke of the life of</hi> B. Aloysius Gonzaga <hi>of our Society, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posid by</hi> F. Virgilius Ceparius <hi>Deuine of the same Society, and by our selues, and many other our Deuines read and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, be committed to print, if it may so seeme good to the most Reuerend Father, the Maister of the Sacred Pallace. For we hope
<pb facs="17"/>
that it will bring no small spirituall fruite, to men both religious and secular, who shall read it. And for this respect we do more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly graunt it, for so much as it appeareth vnto vs vpon certaine notice, and our owne proper knowledge, that this holy and Blessed young man, was most accomplished in all kind of vertue, &amp; of much edification in his exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. For he did not only so alwayes liue in the world that he gaue documents of vertue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all, but also after he was by vs adioyned to the Society, he was euermore a perfect</hi> Idea <hi>of Sanctity, and so commonly reputed of all who were acquainted with him, those few yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res that he liued amongst vs. At which time we discouered, that Almighty God was very much delighted with that pure soule, &amp; that he enriched her with many excellent naturall gifts, out of which there shined forth most ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly workes, and Angeticall manners. So he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and so continually perseuered, till depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out of this life he passed to Heauen; whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, relying vpon firme grounds, we do veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belieue, that this holy soule, for the enioying of eternall glory, and imploring the grace of God for vs, did immediately fly. Of all which
<pb facs="18"/>
thinges we most willingly giue testimony, to the intent that we may testify the truth, to the glory of our Lord, from whom all sanctity floweth, &amp; vnto whom be euerlasting prayse and honour.</hi>
      </p>
      <closer>
         <dateline>At Rome <date>
               <hi>this 14. of Iuly</hi> 1605.</date>
         </dateline>
         <signed>Claudius Aquauiua.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>