<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>S., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117453_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12824</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23132</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117453</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>S., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Pacata Hibernia : Ireland appeased and reduced· Or, an historie of the late vvarres of Ireland, especially within the province of Mounster, vnder the government of Sir George Carew, Knight, then Lord President of that province, and afterwards Lord Carevv of Clopton, and Earle of Totnes, &amp;c. VVherein the siedge of Kinsale, the defeat of the Earle of Tyrone, and his armie; the expulsion and sending home of Don Iuan de Aguila, the Spanish generall, with his forces; and many other remarkeable passages of that time are related. Illustrated with seventeene severall mappes, for the better understanding of the storie</title>
                 <author>Stafford, Thomas, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 391, 1 page, 19 plates (16 folded), maps, portraits, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>VT of a necessitie imposed by powerfull Custome
somewhat must bee sayd to you <hi>Reader,</hi> both to
prevent mistakings touching the publishing of
this VVorke, and to prepare you with some un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudicate
affection to the reading thereof. The
large space of time (thirtie yeeres and upwards)
betweene the matters Acted, Written, and now
published, may beget some wonder, in what obscure corner this
Worke hath lyen all this while, without notice given or taken; or
if knowne, why so long kept from publike view. For answere
heereto, understand indifferent Reader, that it was composed while
the Actions were fresh in the memories of men, by the Direction
and appoyntment of the Right Honourable Earle of <hi>Totnes</hi> (late
deceased) then Lord President of Mounster, so often mentioned in
this Historie. The Collection made, was by him first reserved for
his owne private Information; Secondly, preserved for the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
of a Generall Historie of that Kingdome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> when it
should please God to raise up some industrious Writer to undertake
a compleat Description of those Affayres; And lastly, out of his
retyred Modestie, the rather by him held backe from the Stage of
Publication, lest himselfe being a principall Actor in many of the
particulars, might be perhaps thought, under the Narration of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
proceedings, to giue vent and utterance to his private merit and
Services, howsoever justly memorable. He leaving the world, left it
among his Papers, where it was found by the now Publisher there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
to whom they were bequeathed, and by whom it hath beene
offered to the view and censure of divers learned and judicious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons:
By them it hath been esteemed worthy the view of the
world, that those of present and future times, who desire not to be
strangers to what hath passed, and been acted at home, may receiue
true Information heereby. In confidence whereof, I presume that
whether you bee English or Irish that shall reade this Historie, you
shall finde much matter of contentment to advance the Honour of
both Nations: If English, behold the most dangerous and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>growne
Rebellion that ever was since the Kings of this Land were
Lords of that Isle, suppressed by the puissant valour of thy victorious
<pb facs="6"/>
Countreymen, and a powerfull Invasion of a braue and warlike
Nation repulsed, and sent home to their Natiue Land: Or if you
bee of that other Nation, you may obserue the loyall fidelitie of the
greater part to their lawfull Prince, though animated to disloyaltie
by the strongest perswasions of their supreme Spirituall Pastor, with
promises of heavenly reward. Heere also you may behold a fatall
period given to the Rebellious Insurrections, under whose burthen
that Countrey hath groaned some hundreds of yeeres, and a firme
and assured Peace established to the comfort of them and their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steritie.
And whether English or Irish, forget not (next after the
right hand of the most High bringing mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>htie things to passe) to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
the Prudence, Courage, and Felicitie of that late Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne,
who in her deepe and declining age, did seale up the rest of
all her worthy Actes with this accomplishment, as if shee had
thought that her taske would bee unfinished, and Tombe unfur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished,
if there could not be deservedly engraven thereon, <hi>PACA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TA HIBERNIA;</hi>
The lot whereof was cast, and fell happily
on our side, by the prosperous successe of those Preparations and
Encounters which befell this short time of about three yeeres, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
by way of Annalls and Iournalls in this present Narration;
whereto thou must adde the like acknowledgement of the Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
care, and provision taken by our late Soveraigne of blessed
memory King <hi>Iames,</hi> in the establishment not onely of Peace, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
of good Lawes and Iustice there flourishing, and continued by
the Providence and Piety of our present Soveraigne King CHARLES,
the true Inheritor of his renowned Fathers Vertues as well as King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes.
For the storie it selfe, it was collected, not out of flying ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours,
and popular tales, but (as the Title promiseth) out of the care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
and diligent Observations of the principall Actors in the servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
there related; And for the truth of their Reports, I hope it shall
receiue the Approbation of many Honourable and Worthy Persons
yet living, who may justly challenge a large portion of the honour
atchieved in those Warres. But I will detaine you no longer, (Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
Reader) but leaue you to the use of what is heere presented,
commending it and my selfe to your favourable censure.</p>
   <signed>T. S.</signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>