<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO
THE HIGH AND MIGHTY
MONARCH, AND MY DREAD
Soueraigne, CHARLES, by the Grace and Prouidence of
God, King of Great Britaine, France and Ireland, Defender, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Taylor, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117734_Bo1_6_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13415</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23725</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117734</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO
THE HIGH AND MIGHTY
MONARCH, AND MY DREAD
Soueraigne, CHARLES, by the Grace and Prouidence of
God, King of Great Britaine, France and Ireland, Defender, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>All the vvorkes of Iohn Taylor the water-poet : Beeing sixty and three in number. Collected into one volume by the author: vvith sundry new additions, corrected, reuised, and newly imprinted, 1630</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Boler (Bowler), James 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Elizabeth.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 148, 2, 93, 92-200, 225-343, 1, 14, 13-146 pages, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb n="40" facs="27"/>
   <head>TO
THE HIGH AND MIGHTY
MONARCH, AND MY DREAD
Soueraigne, CHARLES, by the Grace and Prouidence of
God, King of Great Britaine, France and Ireland, Defender, &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>My Gracious Soueraigne,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>I Your Maiesties poore vndeserued seruant, hauing formerly (oftent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>es)
presented to your Highnesse many small Pamphlets (the best fruits of my
leane and sterill inuention) and alwaies your Princely affability and beunty
did expresse and manifest your Royall and generous disposition: and
whereas your Gracious Father (of euer blessed and famous memory) did
not onely like and encourage, but also more then reward the barren glea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings
of my Poeticall inuentions: so now I am bold to present vnto your
Maiestie this my best and superlatiue part of my last studies, I know (Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
Sir) that mans Pilgrimage here must haue a period; and as the Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
falls East or West, so it rises, and He that knowes the heart, doth know
that I doe (not hypocritically) take to heart, that many numberlesse Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
Curses and Oathes, which are carelesly, presumptuously and damnably breathed euery day, houre and
minute, against the Almighty and infinite Maiestie of God: Sure I am, that God takes my part in resisting
and writing against these crying crimes, and I am perswaded that your Maiestie hath an innated Christian
hured of them, I likewise know that all good men doe abhorre and detest them; and as on the one side I will
(or would) not be a Stoicke or Precisian, nor on the other side an Atheist, so in the mid-way I haue written this
small Treatise, to expresse my selfe a Christian, and what a Christian in these points should be; and though
the worke be small and rudely compil'd, though I (the Author) am altogether meritlesse of any good, yet is the
matter great, and so great, that it merits the protection of all such as doe acknowledge there is a God. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
I humbly beseech your Maiestie to accept and Patronize this poore labour of mine, that your powerfull
approuement of it, may make it passe thorow all your Kingdomes and Territories <hi>Cum Priuilegio,</hi> that
children by reading it in their youths, may haue an ingrafted hatred of these sinnes; that elder people may
thereby here formed from them; that all in generall may loath and abhorre them; that God may be honoured,
and our soules eternally saued.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties humble
Subiect and seruant,
IOHN TAYLOR.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>