<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NORABLE, SIR THOMAS ERS∣KENE, LORD VICOVNT FENTON, Baron of Dirrilton, Captaine of his Maiesties Guards, Gentleman of his Highnesse Bed∣chamber, and one of his Maiesties most Honorable Priuie Councell, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Allyne, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S117998_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16963</idno>
           <idno type="STC">385</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S117998</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NORABLE, SIR THOMAS ERS∣KENE, LORD VICOVNT FENTON, Baron of Dirrilton, Captaine of his Maiesties Guards, Gentleman of his Highnesse Bed∣chamber, and one of his Maiesties most Honorable Priuie Councell, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Allyne, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Teares of ioy shed at the happy departure from Great Britaine, of the two paragons of the Christian world. Fredericke and Elizabeth, Prince, and Princesse Palatines of Rhine : Duke and Dutches of Bauaria, &amp;c. By R.A</title>
                 <author>Allyne, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Archer, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedicatory_poem">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE,</hi> SIR THOMAS ERS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>KENE, LORD VICOVNT FENTON, Baron of Dirrilton, Captaine of his Maiesties <hi>Guards, Gentleman of his Highnesse</hi> Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber, and one of his Maiesties most Honorable Priuie Councell, &amp;c.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>MY heart abhorres vngratefulnesse, as hell,</l>
      <l>Yet how to cleere my selfe, I cannot tell.</l>
      <l>I do not plow the fertile plaines of <hi>Inde,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Whose fruitfull gifts may match the giuers mind;</l>
      <l>I reape no haruest, from rich <hi>Arabian</hi> fields;</l>
      <l>Nor drinke the golden streames, that <hi>Ganges</hi> yeelds.</l>
      <l>My greatest gift hath nothing to commend it,</l>
      <l>Except the giuers gratefull mind that send it,</l>
      <l>The least in meanes, but not the last in loue,</l>
      <l>If equall power could poore goodwill approue.</l>
      <l>Which, if your honor, do but rightly weigh,</l>
      <l>A gratefull mind is more, then gold can buy;</l>
      <l>In signe whereof my simple <hi>Muse</hi> affoords,</l>
      <l>A worthy subiect, drawne in worthlesse words;</l>
      <l>A base-borne sister to the sacred <hi>Nine,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Which neuer yet did taste <hi>Castalian wine,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Nor sund her selfe vpon <hi>Parnassus</hi> side;</l>
      <l>But liu'd obscurely on the banke of <hi>Clide,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>A flood, beyond <hi>Permessis</hi> streames in pleasures,</l>
      <l>But vnacquainted with the <hi>Muses</hi> measures.</l>
      <l>The field from whence these fruitles gifts do flow,</l>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <l>But new broke vp, in time may riper grow.</l>
      <l>Which if it do, if by excesse of toile,</l>
      <l>This barren field may turne a fertile soile;</l>
      <l>Vnto your Honor (though their vse be small)</l>
      <l>Ile consecrate the field, the fruit, and all.</l>
      <l>Which once, I wish, may yeeld some greater worth,</l>
      <l>Or still be barren, and bring nothing forth.</l>
      <l>Meane time, take this, not as the totall sum,</l>
      <l>But as the interest of the rest to come.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours, Most obsequious seruant, Robert Allyne.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>