<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE NOBLE AND MVCH DESERVING, Sr. WILLIAM PORTMAN, BARONET.</title>
           <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118116_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13272</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23573</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118116</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE NOBLE AND MVCH DESERVING, Sr. WILLIAM PORTMAN, BARONET.</title>
                 <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sermons vpon solemne occasions : preached in severall auditories. By Humphrey Sydenham, rector of Pokington in Somerset</title>
                 <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Robinson, Humphrey</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 240, 251-316, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="50"/>
   <pb facs="50"/>
   <head>TO THE NOBLE AND MVCH DESERVING, S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. WILLIAM PORTMAN, <hi>BARONET.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Tartle not, (my Noble Sir) This is no <hi>Challenge</hi> I present you with, but a <hi>Flag of truce;</hi> for though it have an <hi>Alarum</hi> in the <hi>Front,</hi> and the <hi>subject</hi> speakes <hi>warre</hi> altogether, and <hi>discord,</hi> yet it prepares to <hi>peace,</hi> such a peace as presupposeth <hi>victory,</hi> and victory, <hi>life;</hi> and life, <hi>Eternity.</hi> To tell you here the <hi>nature</hi> of this <hi>warre,</hi> it's <hi>feares, stratagems, dangers, sufferings,</hi> were but to <hi>preach</hi> by <hi>Letter,</hi> and degrade a <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> to an <hi>Epistle.</hi> The following discourse shall give you a hint of all, where shall find, that he that is a true Christian souldier <hi>must be at peace with others, though he have no concord with himselfe.</hi> This is the modell of the whole
<pb facs="51"/> fabrick, and this I offer to your Noble hands, which when it shall kisse, be confident you cannot hold faster, than (please you try) the heart of him that offers it. Sicknesse and Age (both my compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, now) are but <hi>ill Courtiers,</hi> and as little acquainted with the <hi>nature</hi> of Ceremony, as the <hi>practise;</hi> A <hi>Complement</hi> then, you cannot stile this, but an <hi>expression</hi> of my <hi>zeale</hi> to the merits of your <hi>dead Brother;</hi> to whom, as I was of old a faithfull <hi>Servant,</hi> so still a true <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norer</hi> of his <hi>Name,</hi> though not (O my unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse!) an <hi>Attendant;</hi> which I cannot so much ascribe to <hi>negligence,</hi> or <hi>error,</hi> as to <hi>Fate.</hi> But suppose <hi>either,</hi> or <hi>all,</hi> or <hi>others,</hi> I murmure not, but <hi>blesse</hi> rather; and blesse thus:</p>
   <p>God preserve <hi>you</hi> and <hi>yours,</hi> and send you length of dayes, and accumulation of honours, and fruitfulnesse of Loynes; that as your <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes</hi> looke greene and flourishing, so may your <hi>Name</hi> also; to the glory of your God, the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of your Countrey, the hope of your friends, the Ioy of your Allies, and the Prayers of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your wel-wishing Honorer, HVM. SYDENHAM.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>