<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader, Grace mercy and peace from God be multiplied.</title>
           <author>Ainsworth, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118775_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12475</idno>
           <idno type="STC">228</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118775</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader, Grace mercy and peace from God be multiplied.</title>
                 <author>Ainsworth, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The communion of saincts : A treatise of the fellowship that the faithful have with God, and his angels, and one with an other; in this present life. Gathered out of the holy Scriptures, by H.A</title>
                 <author>Ainsworth, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 493, 9 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader, Grace mercy and peace from God be multiplied.</head>
   <p>THe communion of Christians with the Lord and among themselves, is a doctrine (good reader) both need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and comfortable to be knowen: for it is the stay and strength of the soule in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tentations, and the meanes to conse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>v the Church stedfast in faith and love. And if in this point mens minds be setled aright, vpon the ground of Gods word; they wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be as the <note n="‡" place="margin">Exod. 36. 20. 23. 24▪ <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
      </note> boards of the Tabernacle stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpright, with their tenons sastened in sockets of silver. For what is sweeter to a troubled conscience, then the assurance of salvation; and what is better to stablish our weak &amp; fainting faith, then when both flesh and hart do fayl, to know &amp; feel, that <note n="†" place="margin">Psal. 73. 26</note> God is the rock of our hart, and our portion for ever? Againe, how good is it, &amp; how plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant, for brethren to dwel togither in vnity!<note place="margin">Psal. 133.</note> like the pretious ointment on Aarons head, &amp; the dew on the mountains of Sion. God hath appointed his holy son Iesus, to be the head and governour of his people; the <note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 5. 9.</note> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of eternal salvation to al the that obey him. He hath set vp also the kingdome of Christ on earth, which is his Church▪ the <note n="‡" place="margin">1 Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> pillar and ground of truth. He is the <note n="‖" place="margin">Ioh. 8. 18.</note> light of the world, whom al must folow, that
<pb facs="3"/>
would have the light of life; &amp;<note n="†" place="margin">Rev. 21. 9. 10. 11.</note> Ierusalem his spowse, is made bright by his glory, &amp; the people which ar saved<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 21. 24▪</note> shal walk in the<note place="margin">Isa. 60. 1. 2. 3.</note> light of it. He is the<note n="‡" place="margin">Isa. 9. 6.</note> Father, this the<note place="margin">Gal. 4. 26.</note> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of vs al. Of the Son it is said,<note n="*" place="margin">Psal. 2. 12.</note>
      <hi>happy ar al that shrowd in him,</hi> for he is our<note n="†" place="margin">Isa. 32. 2.</note> hiding place from the wind, our refuge from the tempest of Gods wrath: of Sion also it is said, y<seg rend="sup">•</seg>
      <note place="margin">Isa. 14. 32.</note> the poor of his people shal shrowd in it; for there hath the Lord<note n="†" place="margin">Isa. 4. 5. 6.</note> created a clowd by day, and flaming fyre by night, (as when<note n="‡" place="margin">Exod. 13. 21</note> he brought his Israel out of Aegypt) &amp; vpon al the glorie, is a defence; there is a shadow in the day for the heat, a refuge &amp; shelter for the storm and for the rayn. It is requisit therfore, that al men come<note place="margin">Mat. 11. 28</note> to Christ, if they would have life, and by him<note n="†" place="margin">Ioh. 14. 6.</note> vnto the Father, &amp; abide in<note n="*" place="margin">1 Ioh. 1. 3.</note> communion with them both; that they may be<note n="†" place="margin">Phil. 3. 9.</note> found in him, and haue the justice which is of God through faith; that they may<note n="‡" place="margin">vers. 10.</note> know him, and the vertue of his resurrection, and the fellowship of his afflictions, &amp; be made cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable vnto his death: this is as the first and great commandement of the law, &amp; the second is like vnto it, that they seek<note place="margin">Deut. 12. 5</note> the place which he hath chosen to put his name there, &amp;<note n="*" place="margin">Psal. 26. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> love the place wher his honour dwelleth, wher he<note n="†" place="margin">Song. 1. 6.</note> feedeth &amp; causeth (his flock) to ly-down at noon; that thither they bring<note n="‡" place="margin">Isa. 60. 5.</note> their riches, their glory &amp; honour,<note place="margin">Rev. 21. 26.</note> that of every such one the Lord may count when he writeth the
<pb facs="3"/>
people,<note n="a" place="margin">Psal. 87. 6.</note>
      <hi>He was born there;</hi> that so being<note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 29. &amp; 4. 26. 28 31.</note> Christs, and children of the free woman, &amp; heyres by promise; they may<note n="c" place="margin">Act. 26. 18</note> receiv for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givnes of syns, and inheritance among thē which ar sanctified by faith in him: for he hath sayd, that<note n="d" place="margin">Isa. 65. 9.</note> his elect shal inherit his mountayn, &amp; his servants shal dwel there. But, two things ther are, which wil hinder our feet frō running this way, if we beware not of them: the one is, too much liberty which many men take in the faith of the gospel and obedience of the same, whiles they turn Gods grace into wantonnes, and abuse his mercy to the fulfilling of their own lusts and licenciousnes; wheras they should make an end of their salvation<note n="e" place="margin">Phil. 2. 12.</note> in fear and trembling, knowing that even the<note n="f" place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 18.</note> righteous ar scarcely saved. Whiles also they take boldnes to communicate in spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual actions with any, supposing that the syns of some, or of the publick congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on cannot hurt them, especially if in hart they disallow the evil, and condemn the same. Such men seem not to discern the nature of communion, how far it reacheth; or the contagiō of syn, how far it infecteth. They seem neyther to hav learned the Law<note n="g" place="margin">Hag. 2. 12. 13. 14.</note> which taught that a man by bearing or touching holy things, was not himself made holy therby, but a polluted person touching any of them, made them vnclear: nor the doctrine of the gospel, which confirmeth,
<pb facs="4"/>
that<note n="h" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Cor. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> they which eat of the sacrifices ar par takers of the altar; &amp; al they<note n="i" place="margin">vers. 17.</note> one bread &amp; one body, w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> partake of one bread; wher if ther be but a<note n="k" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Cor. 5. 6. &amp;c.</note> litle leaven, it maketh sowr the whol lump. And then look how farr they partake with other mens syns; so farr ar they in dāger, to<note n="l" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>. 18. 4.</note> receiv of their plagues.</p>
   <p>The other impediment, is over much straytnes which some men hav in their own bowels: whiles their feeble consciences ar too much affected, both with their own &amp; others infirmities. Such had need to have their knowledg and faith increased, their harts inlarged, least by expecting a greater perfection in themselves and others, then is to be found vpon earth, they faint &amp; fall. Let such look on the image of Christ, as he is portrahed<note n="m" place="margin">Psal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>3. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. &amp;c.</note> in the scriptures, whiles the chastisemē<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of our peace was layd vpō him; so shal they find balme for their wounded consciences; and healing for their sowles by his stripes; and their shivered bones wil reioyce. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>or of his cup must we al drinck our parts, &amp; be baptised with his baptisme, into his death, before we can tast the sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his life; &amp; be vnder the rigor of that schole-maister<note n="n" place="margin">Gal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 24.</note> the Law like servants, ere we can perceiv the adoption of sons, &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of his faith and Gospel. And if he which knew no syn, and had but our syns imputed vnto him, felt such feares and so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes in his pretious sowl, and was so smit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n
<pb facs="4"/>
of God and humbled, so despised and reiected of the world: what shal we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, in whose<note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h ther dwelleth no good thing. Let them also look vpon the estate of Christs church in all ages from the<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>▪</note> beginning, how it hath been vexed with troubles &amp; terrors, within &amp; without, &amp;<note place="margin">2. 5.</note> they shal find Sions case to be continually as<note n="o" place="margin">Rev. 12. 2</note> a woman in travel, whose payns &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities<note place="margin">Gal 4. 19. 26. 27.</note> are sometimes so great, that the children come to the birth,<note n="p" place="margin">2 King. 19. 3.</note> and ther is no strength to bring forth. And when they hav viewed the many tribulations through w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> the Lord hath led his people, how he hath suffred them to be buffeted of Satan, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted by enemies without, and molested w<seg rend="sup">th</seg> hypocrites within, for their trial &amp; hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation; they wil confesse that we must walk here by<note n="q" place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 7.</note> faith and not by sight, for our<note n="r" place="margin">Colos. 3. 3.</note> life is hid with Christ in God; his spowse<note n="s" place="margin">Song. 1. 5.</note> is black, for the Sun hath looked vpon her, her own mothers sons hav been angry against her, and al the glory of the kings daughter<note n="t" place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 45. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>▪</note> is inward.</p>
   <p>And furthest astray are such vayn men as imagine to themselves a state of perfection, as if they had already<note n="u" place="margin">Phil. 3. 11. 12.</note> attayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the resurrection of the dead: &amp; do dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime al Churches and societies where synnes are to be seen. Moses face is<note n="x" place="margin">Exod. 34. 30. 33, 35.</note> hid frō thē as with a veil, they discern not the vse<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3, 13. 14. 15.</note> of his law, nor end of his ministerie, for a
<pb facs="5"/>
veil covereth their harts; neyther see they<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> the possession that syn hath in them, yea<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>. 7. 17 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.</note> in al Saincts, so long as they dwel in these howses of clay, for which cause they sigh desiring to be clothed with their howse<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>. 5. 2.</note> which is from heaven, to be loosed and to be with Christ. And when the voyl shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>. 1. 23.</note> taken from those mens harts, who so farr mistake themselves to be that they are not: they wil crie with the Leper, <note n="f" place="margin">Lewit. 13. 45.</note>
      <hi>I am vnclean, I am vnclean;</hi> &amp; wil <note n="g" place="margin">Ezech. 16. 61. 63.</note> remēber their wares and be ashamed, &amp; never open their mouth any more because of their shame, but will <note n="h" place="margin">Ezech. 20. 43.</note> judge themselves worthy to be cut of, for al their evils that that they have cōmitted. Such also as eyther of ignorance, or worse humour, doe vnorderly depart, and rend themselves vpon every occasion from the church and body of Christ; wil walk better, when they have learned to <note n="i" place="margin">Gal. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> bear one an others burden, and tread in the steps of Christ, his prophets and Apostles; who v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed al good means with patience, to reclaim the offenders, before they forsook them. Yet because the faith must not be held <note n="k" place="margin">Iam. 2. 1.</note> in respect of persons, neyther may we <note n="l" place="margin">Exod. 23. 2</note> folow a multitude to do evil; and it often falleth out, that the <note n="m" place="margin">Isa. 1. 21.</note> faithful city becometh a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, and they which wer <note n="n" place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>c. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> yesterday Gods people, are risen vp on the other syde as against an enemie: therfore the Saincts should be wise in hart, and not hold com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb facs="5"/>
with any but in the Light, in the faith, in the true worship of God; for he is gealous even over his own people, and wil not <note n="o" place="margin">Exod. 23. 21.</note> spare their misdeeds, but wil take his kingdome from them, and remove <note n="p" place="margin">Rev. 2. 5.</note> the cā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlestick out of the place, if they repent not; &amp; as he saith by his prophet, <note n="q" place="margin">Amos. 3. 2</note>
      <hi>You onely hav I knowen of al the families of the earth, therfore wil I visit you for al your inquities.</hi> Thus may Christiās walk as they ar counselled by the wisdom of God, not being <note n="r" place="margin">Eccles. 7. 18</note> just overmuch, neyther <note n="s" place="margin">vers, 19.</note> wicked overmuch, laying hold, and not withdrawing their hand from this, <note n="t" place="margin">vers. 20.</note> that he which feareth God, shal come forth of them al.</p>
   <p>For this cause hav I endevored, (though the vnfittest among many,) to help forward in the way of truth, such as love the same with me; and hav penned this treatise folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing, for their sakes, that hav not meanes and leysure to serch the scriptures as they should and would, or by reason of their weaknes cannot gather and compare the scriptures togither for their cōfort &amp; assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in these points, as they desire. I have laboured both for playnnes &amp; brevity, as I could in so large &amp; ample argument; &amp; by references rather sent the reader to look himself into Gods book, then to insist vpon collections or expositions of mine own. Wherin if any places be alleged amisse or impertinent, or things gathered otherwise
<pb facs="6"/>
then the text wil afford; (as through my ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norāce, or vnheedines, no doubt many may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e:) I humbly ask pardon for the same, both of God and his people; and do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> reader not to rely vpon my judgment in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, but as himself by the wisdome of Gods spirit, shal see agreable vnto truth. For if any shal buyld vpon my words, with out sure ground from the Law of the Lord; he shal first offend God, who hath given his scriptures by divine inspiration to teach and perswade al truth, to improve and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 16 17.</note> al error, to instruct in righteousnes, &amp; make men perfect vnto every good work; he shal injury me also, who have written these things to be tryed and examined by Christs law, not to be accepted for a law; and he shal injury his own sowl, by relying vpon the word of frayl man whose breath is in his nosthrils, which cannot stablish the hart, nor assure the conscience in any thing. Let therfore the grasse wither &amp; the flower fade, for it is the <note n="x" place="margin">Isa. 40. 8.</note> word of our God that shal stand for ever.</p>
   <p>Finally this one thing I would advertise thee of, (good reader,) that somtimes I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the scriptures otherwise then our cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon translations hav them; when the force of the Original words, doth afford an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or more ample sence. Herin I fear not to be blamed of any that love the truth in incorruption; and for the places so chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,
<pb facs="6"/>
I leave them to their trial, that are men of judgement. The Lord who is au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of every good gift vnto al men, who passeth by the syns of his servants, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereth al their trespasses; passe by in mercy, whatsoever in this work is done amisse: &amp; turn these my labours, to the glory of his name, &amp; the benefit of his people. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Henry Ainsworth.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>