<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To Master Barrow, and Ma∣ster Greenwood.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118836_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01735</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11868</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118836</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To Master Barrow, and Ma∣ster Greenwood.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A short reply vnto the last printed books of Henry Barrow and Iohn Greenwood, the chiefe ringleaders of our Donatists in England : vvherein is layd open their grosse ignorance, and foule errors: vpon which their whole building is founded. By George Gyfford, minister of Gods holy worde, in Maldon</title>
                 <author>Gifford, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Cooke (Coke), Toby</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 98 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prefatory_letter">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To Master <hi>Barrow,</hi> and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>Greenwood.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>E complaine much of hard dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling offered you, and say ye are blasphemed with odious tearmes. And if ye doo erre, your desire is to be reduced by a Christian man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. It is certaine when men are cleane aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ye in simplicitie, &amp; the matter toucheth but themselues, they are to be dealt withall without seeking their dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace: But when they be publike and notorious seducers, defacing Christs Ministers, and many poore sheepe of Christ are in hazard to be spoyled. They that take it to be vncharitable dealing, to disclose, and to paynt out such seducers in their colours, and to disgrace them vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly, to the end that the simple may not be spoyled by thē as a praie, doo want some iudgement. For as it is Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian charitie in the Shepheards to deale meekely with the sheepe, so is it high treachery and vnfaythfull dealing to Christ and his Church, when the VVoolfe dooth come in sheepes clothing, not to pluck it off, and to let the sheepe see that he is a VVoolfe. VVhy else did our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our call the Pharisies, hypocrites, Serpents and generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Vipers? VVhy sayd S. <hi>Paule</hi> of the false Apostles, beware of dogges? Ye haue drawen many into an outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
<pb facs="4"/>
presumption against God and his people, flat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the rules of his holy word, as shall appeare in the discourse. Ye hauerent out of the hearts of many, all reuerence and loue towards the preachers of the Gospell, and led them into such a presumptuous opinion of their owne vnderstanding, that if they become not heretikes, yet experience doth teach, that many of them growe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to irreligious prophanenes. Master <hi>Barrow</hi> and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>Greenwood,</hi> I doo not know your persons, and I protest vnto ye, there is no priuate thing hath moued me to seeke your disgrace, but indeede the care of Christs sheepe. And let it appeare by the things which follow whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I haue done ye any wrong.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>