<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his louing Masters and friends, the Students of Lyncolns Jnne, R. R. wisheth profite and pleasure in their studies.</title>
           <author>Rawlyns, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1587</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118508_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13761</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24060</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118508</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his louing Masters and friends, the Students of Lyncolns Jnne, R. R. wisheth profite and pleasure in their studies.</title>
                 <author>Rawlyns, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cassius of Parma his Orpheus : with Nathan Chitræus his commentarie, abridged into short notes: most profitable for the framing of the manners of schollers. Translated and abridged by Roger Rawlyns of Lyncolnes Inne, student in the common lawes</title>
                 <author>Telesio, Antonio</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1587</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prefatory_letter">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To his louing Masters and friends, the <hi>Students of Lyncolns Jnne, R. R. wisheth</hi> profite and pleasure in their studies.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost beloued Gentlemen, I haue herein desperatelie aduentured vpon your fauours, hoping that you will take affection for satisfaction, where iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is wanting for currant payment. If I haue offended through follie or imperfection, you may giue me thankes for that, because therein is exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised your wisedome and patience, (as Saint <hi>Paule</hi> speaketh of himselfe) <hi>wisemen can easilie beare with fooles.</hi> If you shall iudge me of presumption, (as the Prouerbe is, <hi>Sus Mineruam</hi>) why then (alas) pardon that too, I most hartelie pray you: for, I must confesse, (without flatterie) that I doo so much the more feare your censures, by how much the more I long after your goodwills. The best for me, is, that the price of my bookes is but your pardon and loue, which ye may giue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cost: and which if ye shall denie me, yet will I not cease to loue you, and to cloy you with my countrey fruites.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your most louing friend and seruant:</hi> Ro. Rawlyns.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>