<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118078_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14770</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25067</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118078</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tvvo histories of Ireland : The one written by Edmund Campion, the other by Meredith Hanmer Dr of Divinity</title>
                 <author>Campion, Edmund, saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Ireland--Dublin</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Matthew.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stationers’ Society, Dublin</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 138, 2, 219, 221-223, 2, 8, 127, 9 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="195"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow far these collections may conduce to the knowledge of the <hi>antiquities</hi> and <hi>state</hi> of this Land, let the fit reader judge: yet something I may not passe by touching M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>Edmund Spenser</hi> &amp; the worke it selfe, lest I should seeme to offer injury to his worth, by others so much celebrated. Hee was borne in <hi>London</hi> of an ancient and noble fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and brought up in the Vniversitie of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> where (as the fruites of his after labours doe manifest) he mispent not his time. After this he became Secretary to <hi>Arthur</hi> Lord <hi>Grey</hi> of <hi>Wilton,</hi> Lord Deputy of <hi>Ireland,</hi> a valiant and worthy Governour, and shortly after for his services to the Crowne, he had bestowed u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him by Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> 3000. acres of land in the Countie of <hi>Corke.</hi> There hee finished the later part of that excellent poem of his <hi>Faery Queene,</hi> which was soone after un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunately lost by the disorder and abuse of his servant, whom he had sent before him into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> being then <hi>a rebellibus</hi> (as <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Annal. r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>r. Anglic. &amp; Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bern. pag.</hi> 729, <hi>edit.</hi> 1625.</note>
      <hi>Camdens</hi> words are) <hi>è laribus ejectus &amp; bonis spoliatus.</hi> He decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb facs="196"/>
at <hi>Westminster</hi> in the yeare 1599. (others have it wrongly 1598.) soone after his returne into <hi>England,</hi> and was buried according to his owne desire, in the collegiat Church there, neere unto <hi>Chaucer,</hi> whom he worthily imitated, (at the costes of <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of <hi>Essex,</hi>) wherupon this Epitaph was framed,
<q>
         <l>Hîc prope <hi>Chaucerum</hi> situs est <hi>Spenserius,</hi> illi</l>
         <l>proximus ingenio, proximus ut tumulo.</l>
         <l>Hîc prope <hi>Chaucerum Spensere</hi> poeta poetam</l>
         <l>conderis, &amp; versu quàm tumulo propior.</l>
         <l>Anglica te vivo vixit plausit{que} poesis,</l>
         <l>nunc moritura timet te moriente mori.</l>
      </q>
As for his worke now <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Ex Bibliothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>câ Re</hi>
         <seg rend="sup">mi</seg>
         <hi>in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sto patris D.</hi> Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobi Vsserij <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiep. Armacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni.</hi>
      </note> published, although it sufficiently testifieth his learning and deepe judgement, yet we may wish that in some pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages it had bin tempered with more moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The troubles and miseries of the time when he wrote it, doe partly excuse him, And surely wee may conceive, that if hee had lived to see these times, and the good effects which the last 30. yeares peace have produced in this land, both for obedience to the lawes, as also in traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique, husbandry, civility, &amp; learning, he would have omitted those passages which may seeme to lay either any particular aspersion upon some families, or generall upon the Nation. For now we may truly say, <hi>jam cuncti gens una sumus,</hi> and that upon just cause those ancient statutes,
<pb facs="196"/>
wherein the natives of <hi>Irish</hi> descent were held to be, and named <hi>Irish</hi> enemies, and wherein those of <hi>English</hi> bloud were forbidden to marry and commerce with them, were repealed by <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>Vid. lib. Status. Hiborn. edit. Dubl. an.</hi> 1621. <hi>pag.</hi> 427.</note> act of Parlament, in the raigne of our late Soveraigne King IAMES of ever blessed memory.</p>
   <p>His proofes (although most of them conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturall) concerning the originall of the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, customes of the Nation, and the first peopling of the severall parts of the Iland, are full of good reading, and doe shew a sound judgment. They may be further confirmed by comparing them with <hi>Richard Creagh's</hi> Booke <hi>de linguâ Hibernicâ,</hi> which is yet extant in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal manuscript, &amp; althogh mixed with mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of story, leaning too much to some fabulous traditiōs, yet in other respects is worthy of light.</p>
   <p>Touching the generall scope intended by the author for the reformation of abuses and ill customes, This we may say, that although very many have taken paines in the same subject, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the raigne of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and some before, as the <note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>Floruit subini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium reg. Edw.</hi> 4</note> author of the booke intituled <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus populi,</hi> and after him <note n="e" place="margin">
         <hi>Floruit sub Hen.</hi> 8.</note>
      <hi>Patrick Finglas,</hi> cheife Baron of the Exchequer here, and afterwardes cheife Iustice of the common pleas, yet none came so neere to the best grounds for reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a few passages excepted, as <hi>Spenser</hi> hath done in this. Some marginall notes I have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, although not intending any, untill the fourth part of the Booke was printed.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>