<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Cope, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118371_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19308</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5722</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118371</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Cope, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A religious inquisition: or, A short scrutinie after religion : Wherein the large cope of true religion is narrowly inquired. By Iohn Cope, of Grayes-Inne, Esquire</title>
                 <author>Cope, John, of Gray's Inn</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 <publisher>Boler (Bowler), James 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 120 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, (for so you must be to me, if you haue patience, or will spend time in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding so slight a piece of writing as this is) instead of an Epistle, I will tell you a tale, which is this. There was a yong man, who after the death of his Parents, was minded to venture his fortunes vpon the Seas, and was furnished as hee thought, with a prety tite vessell, which was likewise fraught with commodities that were passable. This yong man lanched out into the Ocean, where, for a long time
<pb facs="5"/> together, he had so faire gales of winde as his heart could desire: thus with full sayles he made his way thorow the deepes, but being ignorant of the passages of the Sea, and would not be ruled by the Pilotes, and Mariners, of which kind he had some that were skilfull, hee suddenly ranne himselfe into a crosse Sea; where (after hee had beene sorely tossed, and troubled, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed with the surging waues) his Barke began to leake, which wrought in him a sore dismay: but the dashing of these angry bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes one against another, was a meanes to worke this weather-bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Vessell into a calmer Sea. This Young man resolues to returne home, and (though with much losse) to desist from his adventure, or to repaire his decayes; but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the narrow Seas, where
<pb facs="5"/> he found a boysterous passage, he discouered his owne Country, and knowing of a safe Hauen that had beene open, whence he put forth at his going to Sea, where many a tottered shippe had found har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, he intended to put in there: but so it was, through the neglect of keeping the Hauen in repaire, it was so choaked with quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sandes, that no ship could venture to make passage into it, without danger of shipwracke; as it fell out with this yong man, who put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to shore, split the prore of his barke vpon a sand. This yong man had two Iewels giuen him by his Parents, in both which they had in their lines a ioynt interest. At his going to Sea, he lest one of them with his friends to keepe for him; the other he wore, tied with a string about his necke next his heart; and though he had sustai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="6"/> great losse, at last a Fisher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man light vpon him, who finding a Iewell about his neck, that seemed of some worth, though much ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mished with the beating of the salt water vpon it, being moued with compassion, tooke him into his boate, &amp; setting him on shore, holpe him to land so much of his goods as could be preserued, and with much difficulty he saued his broken Vessell. If the Reader desire to know any farther meaning of this Fable, thus it is applyed: The yong man was my selfe, my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents knowne to be deceased, the Sea, was the world, the vessell, my estate, as well of minde and body, as that of my outward meanes; the fraught, some measure of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, apprehension, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory: some knowledge both in humanity and diuinity: farther, my health, strength of body, and
<pb facs="6"/> vse of sences, which were good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments and part of this aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The Ocean may resemble the large scope I gaue my selfe, wherein I was carried amaine by the whisteling gales of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of pleasures, which did so fill the sayles of my empty affections, as that I feared not to passe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row any deepes of hazard. My ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norāce in the world was like, with the Yong mans vpon the Sea. The Pilots, and Mariners, whose direction I refused to follow, were some of my friends, that better knew the course of the world then my selfe. The crosse Sea I fell into, was the incounter betweene pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie, and aduersity: as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter betweene plenty and want, betweene pleasure and trouble, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene sicknesse and health: and so betweene any present good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed, and any contrary euill that
<pb facs="7"/> approacheth: and now my Barke began to leake amaine, when I could not with all the power of my vnderstanding, body, or estate, so fast pumpe out the waters of aduersity, as they brake in vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, which made mee almost heartlesse: yet after much tossing and struggling in vaine against the insulting fury of the billowes, I was cast vpon a calmer Sea of patience. Thē I resolued to returne home to a better vnderstanding of my selfe, and see if I could find any meanes to repaire my decay: yet when I came neere home, I found but an vnquiet passage tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the narrow Straights I had put my selfe into: how-euer, disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering where I was, I aduētured to put in whence I had hoysed sayle, expecting harbour; but found the Young mans successe. The two Iewels bestowed vpon me by my
<pb facs="7"/> Parents, were Religion, and a good name: the former I kept as neere my heart as I could, which yet had lost much of its lustre, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing continually dashed vpon with the brinish water of many corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which I passed thorow. The Fisher-man that tooke mee vp, who had good knowledge of my Iewell, was such a one, as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Christ vndertooke to make his Apostles, fishers of men.</p>
   <p>Now, gentle Reader, be pleased out of my Fable with the moral, to take my intention in putting forth these few and imperfect Leaues, which is to let all that know mee vnderstand, what my Religion is; which they may well suspect ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be none, or not the right, after so dangerous passages in the world. And in the next place, my earnest suite to my friends is, that (as farre as charity will moue
<pb facs="8"/> them,) they would endeauour (without apparant cause, to sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend their good word or opinion of me) to preserue my good name; which I therefore desire to leaue in their custody. And lastly, my purpose in divulging these worthlesse Lines, is, to tie my selfe by them, to the obseruation of my owne directions: (the frailties of corrupt nature being tolerated withall:) which successe if I find, I shall haue my full desire; and so rest a well-wisher to you and all good Christians:</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>IOHN COPE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>