<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>D., J.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118002_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13209</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23507</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118002</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>D., J.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lectures vpon the eleventh chapter to the Romans. Preached by that learned and godly divine of famous memorie, Dr. Sutton, in St. Marie Overies in Southwarke. Published for the good of all Gods Church generally, and especially of those that were then his hearers</title>
                 <author>Sutton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 478, 16 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is no small part of mans miserie, that being created by God in a state of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse and immortalitie, hee hath made himselfe mortall by his sinne and fall. And it is an evidence of Gods infinite and never suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently admired mercie, that hee hath not onely by the death of his best beloved Sonne, restored all his elect to a state of incorruption, and eternall life, and bles<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sednesse in the world to come, but also in this world hath provided certaine meanes and medicines, for the curing, in some sort, even of death and mortalitie it selfe, which in their owne nature are apt to bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie us all in perpetuall oblivion. Namely, that whereas by Gods just &amp; unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able sentence we must all dye, yet by ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration we propagate our kinde, and so,
<pb facs="7"/>though mortall in our selves, wee are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalized in our posteritie. Besides which benefit, common to all mankinde, God vouchsafeth a more peculiar blessing unto those whom he calleth to be spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Fathers in the Church, begetting chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren unto God by the seed of the Word, and preserving them in this life of grace by their fruitfull and powerfull preaching of the Gospell. Especially if hee also ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth them to leave unto their children the riches of their holy writings for their instruction, and increasing of their spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall growth, in all grace and goodnesse, as it were holy legacies bequeathed by their last will and testament. For those spirituall births of the braine are herein much to bee preferred before the fruit of the wombe, in that they continue an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable memorie of their Father after his death, whereas the other often dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerating from the vertues of their Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stours, doe staine their names with their vices and dishonourable actions. But much more doth God honour those who
<pb facs="7"/>thus honour him, in giving them power to speake unto his people, even when their bodies rot in the grave, and making them instruments of his glorie, and of much good vnto his children, even for a long time after death. So that as wicked men doe not onely whilest they live, by their sinnes treasure up wrath against the day of wrath, and prepare a fire in which they shall everlastingly be burned, but also by propagating their sinnes unto posteritie, and leaving behinde them the example of their vices, whereby others daily are suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessively corrupted, doe adde fuell to that hellish fire, and increase their never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding torments: So Gods servants, even after they are dead, have still a stocke go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when as they leave behinde them their Christian vertues for examples, and their holy writings, teaching and perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding others to follow them, whereby a daily addition is made to their glorie and happinesse. Such legacies after his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath this reverend and faithfull ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of Christ left for the use and benefit
<pb facs="8"/>of the Church, and such children to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate his name and memorie unto all posteritie, I meane the summe and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of many his learned Sermons, which he preached in his place &amp; charge, at <hi>S. Marie Overies</hi> in Southwarke, to the great benefit, comfort, and contenment of those that heard him. The which though he had not polished and perfected for the Presse, (as he might have done if it had pleased God to have prolonged his life) yet I thought it not fit that they should alwaies be hidden from the world, because they had not on them their best apparrell. They were, I assure thee, his owne legitimate children, conceived and bred in his owne braine, which were thus farre fitted for their birth, and prepared for the Presse, though himselfe wanted life and strength to bring them forth. Esteeme them not the lesse because they are Orphans, but entertaine them rather with the more love; and if thou findest in them any defects and wants, pitie them the more, because they have lost their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="8"/>who would (had he lived) have sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed them: and esteeme them both in their own worth, and also for their fathers sake. And if I finde that thou givest this kinde entertainment, to these his fruitfull labours, as it were, his first borne; there are divers other children of the same fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which shall ere long bee brought to light; I meane his Lectures on the twelfth Chapter to the Romans, and on a great part of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>19. Psalme, with some others. In the meane while I commend them to God, and the word of his grace, which is able to build thee up, and to give thee an inheritance among all them that are san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord Iesus. J. D.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>