<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN
READER.</title>
           <author>Jemmat, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118150_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13529</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23821</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118150</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN
READER.</title>
                 <author>Jemmat, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Christ revealed: or The Old Testament explained : A treatise of the types and shadowes of our Saviour contained throughout the whole Scripture: all opened and made usefull for the benefit of Gods Church. By Thomas Tailor D.D. late preacher at Aldermanbury. Perfected by himselfe before his death</title>
                 <author>Taylor, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Dawlman (Dolman), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Fawne, Luke.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 339, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN
READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have heard of a demurre made, as though some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
were put forth under this Authors name,
which it none of his. I assure thee in the word of
a Minister, that for the workes that have my E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle
prefixed (and I heare of no other publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
with his name) there is not one note nor notion which is
not the Authors owne, according to his papers. And the like I
affirme concerning this Treatise of Types, which now I pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish.
The use of it is manifold: To open divers places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:
To shew the meaning of legall shadows and ceremonies:
To declare the faith of <hi>the Elders,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Heb. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 2.</note>
      <hi>who received a good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port:</hi>
To manifest our faith,<note place="margin">Eph. 4. 5.</note> one with theirs, <hi>one faith, one
Lord, one Baptisme,</hi> one salvation: To magnifie and commend
Christ to every soule, that it may be saved, and he honoured.
To discerne and bewaile the blindnesse of Gods ancient peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
the Iewes, and pray for their returne to the truth not catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
at shadowes: Of whom, in present I may say with detesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of their madnesse, as he said against the Philosophers, <hi>Nos
qui non habitu,</hi>
      <note place="margin">M. Min. Fel. Octav.</note> &amp;c. <hi>Wee Christians, whose excellencie stands
not in outward things, but spirituall, glorie that we have found
what they (with all their diligence) have sought, and could
not finde. Why are we unthank<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>full? Why doe we stand in our
owne light, if the truth of the Deitie hath in this our age at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
to maturitie? Let us enjoy and make use of our owne
good, and follow the truth in truth: avaunt superstition, be
packing all impietie, let true religion be preserved and flourish.</hi>
Yet withall,<note place="margin">Rom. 11. 26.</note> seeing there is a promise that <hi>all Israel shall be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi>
let us pray for the performance, and that with all earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
as that converted Iew gave exhortation to his sonne, <hi>So
long poure forth thy prayers for the remnant of Israel,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ludov. Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>retus: 1553.</note>
      <hi>till God
looke from his high habitation, and see, and have mercy on
his people for the Lords sake, his Anointed, that in our daies
Iudah may be saved, and the children of Israel may dwell safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
in their owne land, and spend their daies in good, the Lord
making his good Spirit to rest upon them.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>William Jemmat.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>