<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the godly reader grace / and pea∣ce from God the father / and from our Lorde Iesus Christ.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1574</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118505_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13881</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24184</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118505</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the godly reader grace / and pea∣ce from God the father / and from our Lorde Iesus Christ.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A full and plaine declaration of ecclesiasticall discipline owt off the word off God : and off the declininge off the churche off England from the same</title>
                 <author>Travers, Walter</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schirat, Michael</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Heidelberg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1574</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 193, 3 pages, 1 folded leaf of plates, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the godly reader grace / and pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce from God the father / and from our Lorde Iesus Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F off longe tyme, and euen almoste from the beginninge off the vvorl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, vve had not fully knovven, and tried the frovvardenesse off mannes nature no doubt all men vvould ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke it as a thinge incredible, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one could be foūd, vvhich vvould refuse, or not moste desyrously em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace, so svvete and holesome discipline off Christ, as both is propounded to vs in his vvorde, and set forth in order in this present book. VVhich as beinge simply considered it is merueilous so truly seemeth a great deale more straunge, if vvee vvay hovv easely men are brought to admit that ciuile discipline (vvhereby the commodities off this present life are kept) allthoughe hard and confirmed vvith more seuere punishmentes. But iff vve turn our eyes to the ouer hard and cruel slaughter off the Popishe Discipline, and marke a litle vvith vvhat quietnes and patience it vvas born: surely it must needes, not make vs vvonder, but be astonished. For vvhat foolishnes is it, so mutch to care for this frail and bri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle life, as not onely to admit, but oftē times vvillingly to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sire all seuerity off discipline euen thoughe it be as great, as that off Lycurgus vvas: and to be so backvvard cither in get<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinge or keeping off that life vvhich allvvaies shall indure: as not to yeld to the most moderate, and best tempered di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scipline off all that euer vvere? And iff this blindnesse off men vvere pardoned (vvhich notvvithstanding at the lēght
<pb facs="3"/> shall most certenly be punished) that it bothe loueth more and folovveth vvith greater diligence, the commodities off this inconstant life then of that vvhich shall abide for euer: vvhat madnesse shall it be thought, that vve haue so quietly and easely borne, that cruel boutchery off the Popishe disci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pline vvhereby bothe body and soule, haue miserably been tormented: and so hardly or not at all to suffer, this most sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerein medicine for our vices. For the lavves off Discipline vvhich vve there felt, vvritten off the Romā dragon as it vve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re vvith bloud: vve may here try by our Sauiour Christ &amp; the Apostles, vvrittē (as one would say) vvith milk. And this eith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er ignorance of the vvorld iff it knovve not these thinges, or pride iff it refuse a knovvne benefit, or other peeuishnesse &amp; peruersity vvhat soeuer, maketh almost al good mē to feare, lest the iust God beinge angry that his fatherly and gētle rod is cōtemned, and taking vp his rod off yrō and iustice: those churches that remaine (vvhich are very fevve) be altogither broken, brused into litle peices, euen vvholy as it vvere into smale cromes. VVhich thinge as it maketh me pensiue for all churches generally, vvhere the Apostles discipline hath no abiding, so for thee O England, to vvhō being bound both by commune duty off a cytisen, and by publike mynistery vvhich somtimes I exequuted, I confesse that I ovve all kind off great and speciall duty) yt maketh me mutch to doubt, and to be very careful.</p>
   <p>I speake nothinge off that vnreuenged, and vnpurified shedinge off giltlesse bloud vvhiche vvas committed in the reigne off Queene Mary, especially against those vvhich both vvere then the autours off that murther, and vvhose mindes thurst, and handes itche ro commit the like vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes againe: onely I admonishe, that off the riuers the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reoff, vvhiche, run̄e and ouerflovve in all places, euē the least
<pb facs="3"/> drop might be the destruction off a great, and most mighty kingdome. Therefore to let these and other thinges passe, vvhiche are not novve to be spoken off: those bandes off vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, vvhihe haue proceded partly from the absence off th' A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>postles Discipline, partly from the presence off the counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fait thereoff, vvhich remaineth vvith vs synce Popery, haue vveakened our churche vvith seidge off fourtene yeres togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and shortly vvill destroy the same, except against tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se battering peices and cānons off vices, vve speedely set the trēche, &amp; truly brasen vvale off the Apostels Discipline. And I vvould to God thovv hadest kept some meane there in (iff there can be any meane in Sinninge) and by thrustinge avvay the Discipline beinge offered, hadest not more greiuously prouoked, the vvrathe off God against the. For the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer thinges althoughe they vvere heynous, yet because they came off ignorance might the rather obteine some pardon: novve vvhen she hathc made her selfe knovven vnto vs beinge iniuriousliy handled, and suffringe violence, it is greatly to be feared off vs, lest povvringe out her complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes into the bosome off her heauēly father (from vvhō she cometh) she kindle that vvrathe against vs vvhere vvith all England onles it speedely repent, may shortly be set on fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. The thinkinge off these thinges doth often dismay me, and vvhen I greedely seeke after, bothe hope off the health off England, and reasons vvhereon to gather hope, they dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue as it vvere all hope out off my breast. And that so muche the more because these many yeres, not onely the exceadin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge great patience and longe suffringe off God, striuinge vvith our hardnesse, and greedinesse off sinne that neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth) hathe put to flight our priuy ennemyes, scattered their companyes, brought to nothinge their snares layed for vs bothe at home and abroad: but also that God hathe eft soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="4"/> heaped nevve benefites vppon vs or at least vvas ready to haue heaped iff vve had been so ready to receiue as he to gyue, and had not suffered the opportunities vvhiche vvere offered vs, or rather put into our mouthes to haue slidē frō vs. In these so many, so great, so oulde and as it vvere harde houldlinge diseases, althoughe I bee almost ouercome bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the vvithe dispeire off recoueringe the former health, and feare off losinge that vvhiche vve haue: yet ceasse I not no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vve and then to lift vp my minde so throvven dovvne, and to aduance it to the hope off a better estate off thinges.</p>
   <p>Off vvhiche the foundations beinge laied, in the mercy off God vvhich hathe no ende, I cherishe and confirme the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me by certeine signes, vvhiche I haue obserued to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose. For callinge to minde the former tymes, vvhen I see that mercy off God to haue shined forthe, and vve not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not thinckinge off it but almost vvith generall consent off all men criynge out to the contrary) to haue gyuen vs li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght in the holesome doctrine off the Gospell: novve in the leaninge, or rather affection off the greatest part off Gospel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers bothe highe and lovve tovvardes discipline, if I persvva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de my selfe that one day it shall haue place amongest vs, I ought to seeme not to haue done it rashely. As for that, that our most Excellēt Prince, and some off the cheiff coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seillers off the Realme, vnto vvhome our common vvealth is cōmitted, haue hytherto been smale fauorers off Discipli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, althoughe it seeme to reache as it vvere euen at the thro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>at off our church: yet becavvse all men vnderstande that it is hathe happened, as vvell by secret vvhisperinges as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen accusations partly off Bishopes, partly off those vvhich stande for Bishoprickes (vvhiche perceiue that they cā not stande, if the churche stāde and florishe) vvee dispeire not of the good vvill, and redinesse, off the prince, and her counseil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers
<pb facs="4"/> tovvardes this cause. For vve hope vvhen the vanity &amp; falsenesse of slaunders, as off treason) Rebellion, destroyin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge off common <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ealthes, confusion, Anabaptisme, Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme (whiche all they lay vpon discipline, and those that are desyrous thereoff) shalbe seen we hope I say it vvill come to passe, that those whom we haue hytherto felt, som̄ewhat est raunged from this cause, wee shall try hereafter freindly and fauourable thereunto. For we so trust to the goodnesse off the cause that vvee can hardely thinke it able to be brought to passe, that it shoulde be condemned not beinge hard, off so witty a Prince, and so wise counseillers. Nowe whereas Her Maiesty, accordinge to the excellent learninge and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongest vvomen without all comparison, vvhiche she ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the, is delighted vvith thinges that are vvritten in latin: wee haue conceiued great hope, that this cause which hytherto she hath tasted here and there, out off the false rumores off those which deale iniustly with vs, as it were out of the chan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nels, shall more fully be dravven out of our ovvne bookes, as it were out off the founteines. VVhich that she would doe vve throwinge dovvne our selues at Her Maiesties feet do in most humble manner and vvith all supplication bese<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che Her, in the name off Christ (whose matter this is) the noblest, and far moste excellent off all Kinges. And in this place, I marke an other signe, to confirme my minde in the mercy off God: that our mercyfull Father, hathe prouided a notable vvorckman, vvhose breast he hathe filled vvith all kinde off treasures, bothe off artes and tonges.</p>
   <p>Novve seinge that he hathe framed a Bezaleel for vs, to make the vessels and instrumentes off the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, he seemeth not as yet to haue cleane left, off to thinke, off repayringe the ruines off our Church. For
<pb facs="5"/> he hathe so behaued him selffe in a cause (bothe for the diuerse iudgementes off many, and the fevvnesse off those that haue vvrit thereoff) most harde: as it seemeth, scant that any thing coulde haue bene taught either more exactly, or more plainly, in one vvhich had bene, bothe allovved by all mennes opinions, and commonly vvritten vppon by many. For Discipline shevvethe her selfe, and cometh forthe open<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in the sight off all men, not onely vvith good vvordes and excellent sentences, as it vvere arayed vvith costly garmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, but also the same as it vvere vvith methode, come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly plaitted and seemely girded. And vvhereas the very matter off Discipline, is off it selfe amiable and louely, bein<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge decked vvithe Rhetoricke, Logicke, diuersity off toun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, purenesse off speache, knovvledge in the ciuile Lavve, as it vvere vvithe broidures, vvhat loue ought it to kindle in the mindes off men? Novve iff this fruit to read and looke vpon hathe pleasure in it, hovve mutche more pleasant and svvet shall it be to tast? But iff any vvill say, that I gyue ouer hasty iudgement in this matter, I am content to lose so mutch off mine estimation (iff I haue any) as shall seem to be vvanting either off iudgement, or learninge to this litle booke. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scipline therefore hauinge tvvise suffred repulse at our han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des commeth vnto vs the thirde tyme, the same vvhich she vvas before, but vvith greater traine, and ornamētes (as are meet for a most noble dauhter of the noblest kinge. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore onles vvee vvill try the sharpenesse off the vvrath and displeasure off God, let vs goe forth to meet her comminge, let vs open vnto her all the gates and hauēs off the realme, let vs run into her most louinge armes, let vs gyue her the kisse off loue and reuerence, finally let vs bothe receiue her vvillingly, and keepe her constantly, vvith all kinde off ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and duty. For that vvhiche happeneth sometime to
<pb facs="5"/> Princes that hide them selues vnder baser apparell, that they are not greatly angry thoughe they be not knovven off their subiectes, but vvhen they shevve them selues in prince<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly aray and furniture, are offended greiuously iff they be not acknovvledged: the same doubtlesse shall vve try in this prince. For iff hytherto she either more basely appareilled, or hauinge a vayle before her face, and not suffringe men to knovve her fully, hathe kept in her angre vvithin her breast: yet surely she vvill nevver suffer so great brightnesse to be contemned, or refused, as may perce the eyes euen off men that are blinde. And iff they vvhich disdaine a costly gift be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge offred in an earthen vessel, are vvorthely punished for their rashenesse: certenly they shall neuer escape a most greiuous punishement off their madnesse, vvhiche despise it beinge gyuen in a gorgeous and costly dis he. Hereunto may be added that the author off the booke, not buklinge him selffe vvith any aduersary, and hauinge his minde bent onely on the cause, inueieth not against any mannes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. VVherin hauing vnderstanded off some in part offended vvith me modestly ansvveringe an importunate man, and lightely stinginge him againe, vvhich thrust others thoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vve vvith most sharpe reproches: surely as I am sory that they are displeased vvithe me, so I reioyce for their cause, that in this treatise all comparison off personnes beinge se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated, they shall haue nothinge, vvhich may offend sutch mindes as are somevvhat to deinty. VVherefore I haue done my indeuour, that I might bringe to light, this (bothe for these and other causes) so excellent a Ievvell, committed to my custody, beinge persuaded, that I could not, vvitheout the haynous sinne off sacriledge, haue buried in silence as it vvere in graue, so notable a thresure. Vvhiche truly I haue do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne so faithfully, that allthoughe I savve him differinge from
<pb facs="6"/> me in the interpretatiō off a place or tvvo notvvithstandin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge I haue left them vnchaunged, and reserued them vvhole to the iudgement off the church.</p>
   <p>It remaineth o England, that thovv for vvhose sake all this paine is taken, bringe vnto the readinge hereoff a min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de void of all affection, neither hindred vvith any error of cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stome, nor dismayed vvith the vayne noyes and pomp off Bis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hopes, nor rūninge headlonge vvithe any preiudice, or desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re off mainteninge any side: that thovv look onely vpon the matter, try the vveight off euery argument, not by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull scoles off men, or off the greatest, but by the auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie off the vvorde off God, as it vvere by the gouldsmithes vveightes, that thovv acknovvledge the truthe once kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvē, keepe it in thy minde, bringe it into practise (euery one so far as his vocation vvill suffer) as it vvere into present pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session. Novve I most humbly beseche god the father off our Lorde Iesus Christ, that out off the threasures off his vvisdome and strenght, both openinge thyne eies to see, and strenghtheninge thy handes to put in execution, he vvould vouchsafe to perfect, and alvvayes to continevve, the good thinge vvhiche is begonne in thee.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>