<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHOVR to the godly Readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118310_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03079</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13203</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118310</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHOVR to the godly Readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The right rule of Christian chastitie : profitable to bee read of all godly and vertuous youthes of both sexe, bee they gentlemen or gentlewomen, or of inferiour state, whatsoeuer. Collected and written by one studious to gratifie his freendes, and profit his kindred: first (priuately) for the instruction, forewarning and forearming of certayne younge gentlewomen his neare and deare cosins: and after published by the same, in hope to profit the Church &amp; common wealth, according to his talent. The methode wherof is to bee seene immediatly after the preface to th reader</title>
                 <author>Hergest, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>How (Howe, Haw), William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 91, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>THE AVTHOVR to the godly Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Hen I had collected &amp; drawen</hi> (dearely beloued and courteous Reader) this Treatice or discourse of Christian Chastitie, out of <hi>Chitraeus, Strigelius, Musculus, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin, Hemingius, Bernardus Cantabrigiensis, Erasmus Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdamus,</hi> and other learned and Godly writers of this age, for the further instruction, premonition, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arming of my neare and deare Cosins, against such sore and dangerous assaultes and temptations, as commonly euen in the very entraunce of the tempestuous &amp; stormie Sea of raging youth are to bee encountred withall. And had found and perceaued through Gods grace both mine owne minde and theirs, not a litle to be confirmed in the purposed race of chaste and vnstayned life (most fit for single persons) by the collecting, writing, and often rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge of the same: I thought it contrary to the rule of Christian Charitie to hide or with holde that from my christian brethren, that I was perswaded might do them good, without any (I hope) my great losse or hinderance. And though I am not ignorant how daūgerous a matter it is for the vnpractised, in this lerned age furnished with such sage and graue heads, with so many fine wittes, and with youth of such rare towardnesse, and wonderfull for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnesse, and so beautified, and adorned with all kinde of Science so exactly knowen, to commit any thinge vnto the open view of the eyes of the worlde: Yet seeinge this is written for the vnlearned onely (whom I trust it will profite) and not for the learned who neede no instruction, I feared not to preferre common vtilitie, before prinate daunger. And be it that all lawdable attemptes are sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to Enuies stinge, yet am I not so white liuered, or faint harted to desist from dooinge good to my power, and
<pb facs="9"/>according to the vttermost of my gifte and Talente, for feare of the barking of Dogges. For none other accompt doo I make of the vndeserued defamations, and causeles detractions of <hi>Zoylus</hi> and his cankred crewe: As for the good (I doubt not) but they will take good endeuours in good parte, though abilitie be not altogether answerable to good will. Finally, whereas it is truely affirmed and euen in the best learned verified: Humanum esse errare, <hi>That, it is a thing incident to man to erre,</hi> and therfore it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee, but the vnlearned (amonge whom I supply a roome) must now and then misse the quishin: I craue thy gentle patience and fauourable correction therin. Which if I shall obtaine wilbe an encouragement vnto mee for thy further vse and employing of my small Talent here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to thy further benefit as health, money the senowes and strength of thinges to bee donne, leasure, and the state of a Seruaunt will permit. Farewell in the Lorde that liueth for euer and euer.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>