<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Honorable Sir Thomas Sackuile, Knight, Baron of Buckhurst, Lorde high Treasurer of Englande, Lieuetenaunt of her Highnes within the County of Suffex, most worthy Chaun∣celor of the Uniuersitie of Oxenford, Knight of the noble order of the Garter, and one of her Maiesties most honourable priuie Counsell.</title>
           <author>Walker, Ferdinando</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118471_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13830</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24135</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118471</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Honorable Sir Thomas Sackuile, Knight, Baron of Buckhurst, Lorde high Treasurer of Englande, Lieuetenaunt of her Highnes within the County of Suffex, most worthy Chaun∣celor of the Uniuersitie of Oxenford, Knight of the noble order of the Garter, and one of her Maiesties most honourable priuie Counsell.</title>
                 <author>Walker, Ferdinando</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Spanish Mandeuile of miracles. Or The garden of curious flowers : VVherin are handled sundry points of humanity, philosophy, diuinitie, and geography, beautified with many strange and pleasant histories. First written in Spanish, by Anthonio De Torquemeda, and out of that tongue translated into English. It was dedicated by the author, to the right honourable and reuerent prelate, Don Diego Sarmento de soto Maior, Bishop of Astorga. &amp;c. It is deuided into sixe treatises, composed in manner of a dialogue, as in the next page shall appeare</title>
                 <author>Torquemada, Antonio de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Mattes, Edmund.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 158, 2 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Honorable Sir <hi>Thomas Sackuile,</hi> Knight, Baron of Buckhurst, Lorde high Treasurer of Englande, Lieuetenaunt of her Highnes within the County of Suffex, most worthy <hi>Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celor of the Uniuersitie of Oxenford, Knight of the noble order of the Garter, and one of her Maiesties most honourable priuie Counsell.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ifting mine eyes vp from out the low &amp; humble valley of my ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure fortunes, vp to that bright shining eminent hill of Honour, on which the fauour of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty, the noblenes of your birth, &amp; your many excellent vertues haue seated you, I cannot (Right honorable and my most singuler good Lord) but lay a sharpe and rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous censure vpon my own presumption, that being (though bounde to this flourishing Kingdome for my education) yet a stranger borne, and to your Lordship meerely vnknowne, haue thus boldly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentured to presse into your presence, and to craue your honourable patronage to a worke, whereof (howe soeuer it deserue) I cannot to my selfe chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge any prayse. It was the first labour of a worthie Gentleman of your Lordships Countrey of Sussex, one that doth much loue and honour you, who did it for his exercise in the Spanish tongue, and keeping it by him many yeeres, as iudging it vtterly vnwoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of his owne name, did lately bestowe the same vpon me, with expresse charge howsoeuer I should
<pb facs="3"/>
dispose thereof, to conceale all mention of him: wherin I should haue doone both him and my selfe too much wrong in obeying him: him, in depriuing him of his deserued prayse for so worthy a worke, &amp; my selfe, in arrogating vnto me the glory of this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, to the well handling of which, in such ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite manner as he hath done it, I know my owne forces altogether weake and insufficient: VVith all humblenes therefore, I beseech your Lordshippe to vouchsafe your noble name for a protection of this my bold endeuour, and with your accustomed gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlenes to pardon this rash attempt, proceeding whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie from an infinite and vehement desire I haue, to doe you all possible honour and seruice, that the poorenes of my capacity or fortune can stretch vnto.</p>
   <p>I beseech the Almightie to blesse your Lordship, and my honorable good Lady, with all your noble familie, with all happinesse, honor and length of life, that you may long remaine a strong and happy piller of this glorious Common-wealth, vnder the blessed gouernment of her most sacred Maiesty, whom God long preserue. London, this 23. of Aprill. 1600.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships most humble and deuoted: Ferdinando Valker.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>