<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE GODLY AND Gentle READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118412_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13763</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24062</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118412</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE GODLY AND Gentle READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Newes from the north. Otherwise called The conference betvveen Simon Certain, and Pierce Plowman, faithfully collected and gathered by T.F. student</title>
                 <author>T. F., student</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE GODLY AND Gentle READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou hast heer Godly and gentle <hi>Reader</hi> the Conferēce betwéen <hi>Sim Certain</hi> and <hi>Piere Plovvman</hi> two great Clarks as thou maist vnderstand by their Discourse, which I have gathered &amp; reported as faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and as truely as my simple memory could retaine the same, and that with some trauail which I accounted my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. First vnto them and others by them héerin mentioned.</p>
   <p>And secondly vnto all &amp; euery good man and woman whose mindes and harts God may sturre vp vnto Godlynes and Vertue by their good ensample. Namely all such as are Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Maisters of housholdes, but chéefly and principally of common Innes and Tauerns whose good or euil example spreadeth far and wide and I feare in these our dayes rather in corruption of life and maners then in edifiyng or increase of Vertue and Godlynes according to the saying of Iesus of <hi>Sirack</hi> that it is as hard for a Merchant to be no Lyar and for a Tauerner or Inholder to be no drunkerd which thing although hée hath said to be very hard yet (for the Inholder) that his rule admitteth exception, thou maist héer finde with out traueling to <hi>Rippon</hi> in Yorkshire to learne and so for a grote or sixpence thou maist know y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which cost mée abooue fiue marcks to learne besides my trauail and time spent, which yet if it please thée to accept: I shall account right wel bestowed, which God graunt &amp; that in all thy Iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys thy hed ake not before thou alight in such an Hostry. Farwel.</p>
   <epigraph>
      <q>Aut bibe aut abi.</q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>