<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE Edward Lord Howard, Ba∣ron of Escrick, my ve∣ry Honourable good LORD.</title>
           <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118102_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13271</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23572</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118102</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE Edward Lord Howard, Ba∣ron of Escrick, my ve∣ry Honourable good LORD.</title>
                 <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sermons by Humph. Sydenham late fellow of Wadham Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 26, 29-38, 2, 8, 38, 4, 44 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE <hi>Edward</hi> Lord <hi>Howard,</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of <hi>Escrick,</hi> my ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Honourable good LORD.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen you were pleased, the other yeare, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me your <hi>Chaplaine,</hi> I had intended, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd my praemetiall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations to your <hi>Lordship,</hi> from the <hi>Pulpit;</hi> But I was, then, preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a sudden, and seuere <hi>sicknesse,</hi> which hath, hitherto, disabled me to tender you any thing that way. Now, because I would
<pb facs="3"/>not be obnoxious to a double mis-conceit, I present you this <hi>peece</hi> from the <hi>Presse,</hi> that your <hi>Lordship</hi> may <hi>reade,</hi> and so <hi>remember</hi> the <hi>record,</hi> both of my <hi>deuotions,</hi> and <hi>endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours.</hi> I heartily <hi>wish</hi> I were so compleatly <hi>recouer'd</hi> for <hi>attendance,</hi> that I might as well <hi>speake,</hi> as <hi>write</hi> my <hi>labours;</hi> and then (perhaps) I should better satisfie your <hi>Lordship,</hi> then in this <hi>common kind;</hi> which hath made <hi>many</hi> of my <hi>Profession</hi> (and may <hi>mee</hi>) <hi>ridiculous.</hi> But I feare my infirmities, and therefore, as I must begge the honourable <hi>charitie</hi> of your <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> so of your <hi>Protection</hi> also. For as I was, at first, a <hi>suiter</hi> for your <hi>seruice,</hi> (In which I haue cause to glorie) both for the <hi>greatnesse</hi> and <hi>goodnesse</hi> of your <hi>selfe,</hi> and <hi>name</hi>) so I am, still, for the <hi>graces</hi> of it: and doe hope, that when you haue made a ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler <hi>enquiry,</hi> who I am, and where I haue spent my <hi>time,</hi> and <hi>talent;</hi> your <hi>Lordship</hi> will not disdaine to <hi>owne,</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> mee with your succeding <hi>fauours.</hi> In a word (my <hi>noble Lord</hi>) I shall not forget <hi>what</hi> you haue made <hi>mee,</hi> nor the <hi>dutie</hi> enioyn'd me by <hi>it:</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>I will pray for <hi>you,</hi> for your <hi>Lady,</hi> for your <hi>little Ones,</hi> and for the <hi>growth,</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance</hi> of the house begun in <hi>you;</hi> and what else is requir'd in a <hi>religious obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance,</hi> you shall surely find in the <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>loyaltie</hi> of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Lordship's humble seruant,</hi> Hum. Sydenham.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>