<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONORABLE AND THE MOST WOR∣THY MECAENAS, SIR John Winter Knight, Secretary of State, and Master of Requests to the Queenes most excellent Majestie.</title>
           <author>Tatham, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118165_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13393</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23704</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118165</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONORABLE AND THE MOST WOR∣THY MECAENAS, SIR John Winter Knight, Secretary of State, and Master of Requests to the Queenes most excellent Majestie.</title>
                 <author>Tatham, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fancies theater· By Iohn Tatham Gent</title>
                 <author>Tatham, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Best, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>162 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HONORABLE AND THE MOST WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THY MECAENAS, SIR John Winter Knight, Secretary of State, and Master of Requests to the Queenes most excellent Majestie.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>HONOR'D SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He confidence I have of your Native goodnesse (of which the World is sufficient Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later) has prompt mee to this audacious presumption, which with
<pb facs="3"/>
some would have beene held a crime in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sufferable. But I know your Honor is so farre from a Censurer, that you had rather cherish endeavours then destroy 'em: Besides, there's a certaine Sect of selfe-affecters, that will (unlesse some judicious Patron be fixt to the fronts-peece, as the beames of the Sunne, to correct their sawsie peering, with blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse) not only disgorge their Envie, but wrest the sense to be succinct; I (know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Name to be such, as amongst the discerning Spirits deserves the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Attributes of worth; and of such sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular power, 'twill extirp the Malevolent thoughts that raigne in the vulgar and most infectious Traducers) tender this, as my first Sacrifice, at the Altar
<pb facs="3"/>
of your mercy. And if it may obtaine the reflection of your acceptance, 'twill so much encourage your poore Admirer, that I shall be Ambitious in the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of your favours: These are the Mayden-blosomes of my Muse, which (without your protection) may (in their infancie) be destroyed by the breath of <hi>Zoïlus</hi>; but shelter'd by your Honor, they shall live, and dare the Criticks ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, retorting to their owne shame. Sir, the fostering this Orphan will make you famous for Charity, and impose an obligation beyond expression, upon</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors truly devoted, JO. TATHAM.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>