<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Noble and Right worthy Prince Thomas Duke of Norfolke, Earle Marshall of Englande, one of the Lordes of the Queenes Maiesties priuie Counsell, and Knight of the ho∣norable order of the Garter.</title>
           <author>Hake, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1571</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118357_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68815</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23971</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118357</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Noble and Right worthy Prince Thomas Duke of Norfolke, Earle Marshall of Englande, one of the Lordes of the Queenes Maiesties priuie Counsell, and Knight of the ho∣norable order of the Garter.</title>
                 <author>Hake, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The imitation or following of Christ, and the contemning of worldly vanities : wherevnto, as springing out of the same roote, we haue adioyned another pretie treatise, entituled, The perpetuall reioyce of the godly, euen in this lyfe. Seene and allowed according to the order appointed</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1571</date>
                 <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 3-132, 26 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ To the Noble and Right <hi>worthy Prince Thomas Duke</hi> of Norfolke, Earle Marshall of Englande, one of the Lordes of the <hi>Queenes Maiesties priuie Counsell,</hi> and Knight of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable order of the Garter.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F Augustus Caesar,</hi> renou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Prince, being presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a poore and simple Poet with a fewe briefe and compendious Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grams, dyd not onelye, by aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering with the lyke, seeme to accept and allowe that his tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile,
<pb facs="4"/>
but also wyth great and ample rewarde, giue encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therewithall: I trust that your Lordshippe (being of your selfe both wise and well affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) will much more in this so precious a present, receyue my trauayle and fruitefull exployt. The worke of it selfe, deserues a good Patrone, and the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynesse thereof putteth me in mynde of your grace. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in the same, no difficult questions at all are pursued (I meane in matters of religion)
<pb facs="4"/>
yet ghostly instructiōs and right Godly lessons at large are dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: knowledge of letters and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terall sense, therein so much is nothing supported, as amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life &amp; maners aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. How much it is needfull in these present dayes, your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe (I thinke) doth well vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand: &amp; to you it is knowne, how far doth dissent our life frō our knowledge. And by howe much the more it shalbe by your Lordshippe thought worthy the sale, by so much vndoubtedlye,
<pb facs="5"/>
your honor the better, shall shew your selfe fautor and friend vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vertue. Not distance of place coulde haue altered my mynde, but that to your grace I woulde haue presented this signe of good will and loyall entent. And yet (notwithstanding such in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde affection) I am to craue pardon of skillesse attempt, and hoping no lesse then fauor ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I leaue your good grace, vnto the Almightie, who alwaies in honour preserue your estate.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your humble Oratour. Edwarde Hake.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>