<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1564</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118528_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13955</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24265</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118528</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A godly and necessarye admonition of the decrees and canons of the Counsel of Trent, celebrated vnder Pius the fourth, Byshop of Rome, in the yeares of our Lord. M.D.LXII. and. M.D.LXIII : Wrytten for those godlye disposed persons sakes, whych looke for amendement of doctrine and ceremonies to bee made by generall counsels. Lately translated out of Latine</title>
                 <author>Flacius Illyricus, Matthias</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1564</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 125, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur Lorde and Sauioure Iesus Christ, when he hadde confirmed the mindes of his Disciples, agaynste the daungers of persecution, whych they shoulde be in daunger of, for the confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the truth of his doctrine, with a spirite thurstyng our saluation, brake foorth into these woordes: What pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth it a man (sayd he) though he win al the world, if he lose hys own soule: <note place="margin">Math. 16.</note> Or what recompence shal a man geue for his soule: And his meaning was to admonish not onely his Disciples, but also al vs together with them, how much the saluation of soules is to be made of, which being deliuered from the bodye, and once abiected from God, can by no price or recompence he redemed agayne.</p>
   <p>But then are they most of al endaungered, when they straye from the true knowledge of God, and his syncere woorshipping. For God is lyfe and truth, and therefore the death of the soule is, to decline frō the rule of the wyl of God, reuealed in Christ. But bicause the Lorde speaketh not vnto vs from heauen, but hath vpō earth instituted the ministery of teaching, whereby men are instructed of the wil of God, we see that for that cause (I say) men are diuerslye affected. For they which teach in the churche of God doo not euerye where professe one and the selfe same doctrine.</p>
   <p>And when Christ sayde of true teachers: He that heareth you, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <note place="margin">Luke. 10. Math. 18.</note> me. And agayne: If he shal not heare the church let hym bee vnto thee as an Ethnicke and a Publicane, they excedinglye doubt, vnto what congregation, in so great a diuersitye of opinions they ought to soyne them selues.</p>
   <p>For on the one syde, they are holden by ordinary succession (as they ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> it) and custome and consent of very long tyme, in whose congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion yet neuerthelesse they see very many errours, and no small abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, which they them selues vnderstand, and iudge that they ought of necessity to be amended. On the other side against humane traditions they heare the expresse woorde of God brought foorth and vrged, but for asmuch as they fynde among those mē also occasion to be offended, and chiefely bicause they thinke that the chaunging of doctrine and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies pertaineth not vnto euery man, but vnto the ordinarye po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, they can scarse tel which way to turne them selues.</p>
   <p>They flye therefore vnto the authority of a Counsel, as to an one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sanctuary, whereby they iudge that dissension sprong in the Church may most commodiously be taken awaye. Of which thyng when deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration was had long tyme and often by the orders of the Empyre,
<pb facs="3"/>
neither yet by any conditions whereby on eyther syde it was requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, it could be obtained, the saluation of many men, hath by the stay of so long tyme bene miserably endaungered.</p>
   <p>And although such are iustly to be reproued, whych neglecting the very sounding from heauen of the sonne of God: Heare him, haue a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde vnto the authority of men: for the consideration of our saluation is not so obscurelye taught, but that euen the moste simplest in fayth may comprehende it, yet I thinke not that this kinde of men is to bee abiected. But rather in that part wherin we see that they ar sicke, we must after the exāple of the Apostels, to our power study to heale thē. <note place="margin">Actes. 2.</note>
   </p>
   <p>For that happeneth in this our time, which we reade happened at Ierusalem on the day of Pentecost, after the ascention of Christe into heauen: For when the people saw and heard the Apostels with sundry tounges celebrate the wonderful things of God, whom yet the Prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes, Scrib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>s, and Phariseis had a litle before condemned and perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, they were vtterly at their wyts ende and in doubte whose doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine they should embrace. For Christ seemed no lesse to commend the doctrine of the Phariseis, than the doctrine of the Apostels. when he said: Upon the chaire of Moses syt the Scribes and Phariseis, that <note place="margin">Math. 2.</note> which they say, doo ye. What maruaile is it if the rude and vnlearned people were doubtfull? For the Phariseis vnto whom they were so long tyme addicted in learning the woorshippyng of God, taught one thing, and the Apostels an other thing. The selfe same thing vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedlye wee see happeneth in this our age. For with our Elders great hath bene the authority of the Church of Rome, wherewith the eyes of many men are yet styl blinded. But no lesse. yea rather farre greater is the authority of the woord of God, whereby are reproued errours and abuses, which haue throughe the negligence and auarice of men crept into the Church. A man that wyl ryd him selfe our of these diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, ought not vtterly to be vnskilful in holy matters, and so to be addicted vnto the Church, that in the meane tyme he same not against the manifest wil of God, expressed in the woord of the Gospel.</p>
   <p>But there are two rockes, betwene which godlye men must wyth great care and diligence sayle. For some by reason of lightnes of mind, without iudgement and true faith embrace euery maner of religion. But other some to stubbornlye resist, and wyll not once so muche as vauchsafe to know the doctrine set foorth, bicause their minde is bent vnto an opinion, which they defend for the truth. Or bring ouercome with the pleasures of this worlde, they haue no care of the truth, nor saluation of their soules.</p>
   <p>But there is none amongest them that are trulye godlye, so rude to thinke that so great inconstancye of minde in the doctrine of religion, or stubbornes in errors should be numbred among vertues, but by the holy scriptures they are taught that either of them is to be auoyded. For against inconstancy the Apostle speaketh: Let vs not be as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ytile <note place="margin">Ephesi. 4. Iohn. 4.</note> ones wauering, neither let vs be caried about with euerye wynde of
<pb facs="3"/>
doctrine. But against stubbornes in errour Iohn hath left in writing: Proue the spirites, whether they be of God. Wherwith the selfe same Apostle agreeth: Quench not (saith he) the spirite, despise not prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. <note place="margin">1. Thes. 4,</note> But proue ye al thing, that which is good, hold.</p>
   <p>But bicause it is a singular gift of God, to proue spirites, and as the Apostle saith prophecye, that is, the naturall interpretation of the holy scripture belongeth not to euery man. Manye suppose that thys care pertaineth onely to Bishops and Priestes, that a Synode being assembled, learned and modest men on eyther partye, and suche as are addicted to nothing but vnto the truthe and healthe of the Churche, should temperately conferre together of articles in controuersye. For they thinke them selues farre inferiours, than that they shoulde take vpon them to iudge of so great matters, where disputacion is had of the saluation of soules.</p>
   <p>Although these men which thus iudge touching matters of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be in some part woorthye of pardon, or rather compassion, yet me thinketh they are gentlye and modestlye to be admonished of certayne thynges.</p>
   <p>For first in that they iudge that it is profitable and necessarye, that godly and learned prophetes (for so the Apostle calleth the interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of holy scripture, and Bishops) shoulde assemble together in a Synode and conferre their sentences together concerning the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles proposed, in this part they seme not to erre. For we rede that not onely the successours of the Apostels did so, but also the Apostles them selues, as the Actes of the Apostels and Counsels doo testify.</p>
   <p>So straight waye after the ascension of Christe into heauen, when at Antioche there arose a question as touching the obseruation of the <note place="margin">Actes. 15<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> law of Moises, as a thing necessary to the rightcousnes of mā, which is auayleable before God: Paule and Barnabas by the consent of the Church of Antioche went vp to Ierusalem to the Apostels and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, that it might be manifestiye knowen vnto the Churches, that they in al pointes agreed with the rest of the Apostels, against the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned lye of the false Apostels. For the false Apostles had euerye where abroade in the Churches accused Paule and Barnabas of this thing, namely, that they vnder the name of the Gospell deliuered an other, and farre diuers doctrine vnto the Gentiles.</p>
   <p>Lykewise also in the primitiue Church▪ there wer by the authority of godly Emperours assembled the Counsels of Nice, Constantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Ephesus, and Chalcedonia, against Arrius, Macedonius, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storius, and Eutiches, to retayne styll a godlye consent in doctrine of the deuinity of Christ, Of his two natures deuine and humane in one person, Of the person and deuinity of the holy Ghost.</p>
   <p>So also after that, for the taking away of dissentions betwene the <note place="margin">In the coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel of Basill S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ss. 1.</note> Clergy, and offences out of the Church, there wer Synodes had not onely in euery prouince, but also there was a decree made, that from that tyme for euer there shoulde with in ten yeares hee celebrated an
<pb facs="4"/>
vniuersall Counsell. For that thyng is accustomed to happen in the Church, which happeneth in houses, which vnles they be with bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soms often made cleane, they wil be couered with filthynes and dust: So also vnles the Teachers of the Church doo with a perpetual care and diligence geue vigilant heede, and continuallye institute godlye conferringes together of sentences, easy is the fal of doctrine and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, &amp; except they be in tyme corrected, they are accustomed to draw a wonderful great ruine vnto the Church.</p>
   <p>But in this thing they seeme not to indge wel, in that they think that the peace and tranquility of the Churche may by this meanes be recouered and preserued firme. For although the disputacions and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of godly Counsels haue brought great vnity vnto the Churche of God, in which the peruerse and vngodly opinions of heretiks haue bene by testimonies of the holye scripture vehement<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ye reproued, yet the Ecclestastical history testifieth that no lesse contentions, yea also sometimes greater contentions haue happened in the Church of God after the Counsels had bene celebrated. Upon which occasion Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Nazianzenus being moued with the euent of the Counsels wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that from that tyme forward he determined, to eschewe all Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodes of Bishops, bicause he found that no Synode had a good ende: or which rather brought not increases of euyls, than an ende of them. Although that this good man in this point seemed somewhat to erre, for that he there for that cause iudged that Synodes are vtterly to be auoyded, bicause he sawe that the peace of the Churche coulde not by Counsels be made firme.</p>
   <p>For although it were to be wished, that al men should rest in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the truth, which is in godly Synodes instituted by testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the vndoubted holy scripture, yet this is not the sole &amp; one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ende of Counsels. For there alwaies haue bene, are and shalbe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious wits, which endeuour them selues to perturbe the peace and concorde of the Churche. But the principal end of Counsels is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication and confirmation of sounde doctrine, and the confutation of errours and peruers opinions. Whych althoughe it satisfieth not all men, yet it satisfieth al the godlye, whose simplicitye is correspondent vnto a godly explication of the truth.</p>
   <p>Therefore, whether the peace of the Churche bee restored, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee not restored, yet a godlye conferring of sentences in godlye Synodes is both profitable and necessary. And vnlesse suche a confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring were had, it were to be feared, least the multitude and variety of opinions should at the length bring no lesse cuyll and discommoditye vnto the Church of God, than brought the superstition of tyme past.</p>
   <p>And bicause some daunger commeth of disputations that are to ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement, godly princes may by their authority easely remedye this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyl, who of necessity must be present at them: as we reade was done in the Counsell of Chalsidonia, that by their authoritye contentions and wanton wyttes were restrayned wythin the bondes of Christian
<pb facs="4"/>
modesty. For euen as it is trulye sayde: that by to muche alteration the truth is lost, so also semeth it no lesse to be truly said: that by quiet disputing, &amp; godly conferring of sentences, the truth is brought forth, whereunto the sonne of God hath promised that he wyl be present to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the father and the holy Ghost, yea if there be but twoo or three gathered together in his name. And it is better presently to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate of matters with a modest conferring together being appointed, than by mutual writing to inflame the hartes of either party.</p>
   <p>Farther, in this thyng also they iudge not ryghtlye, for that they thinke, that in suche Counsels are matters entreated of, which vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and wholy passe the capacity of the laity.</p>
   <p>For although al the Laity neither can, neither are bound exactly to know the reasons and argumentes of al and singular controuersies, yet no godly Counsell hath decreed of anye thing, which of necessitye pertaineth vnto the saluation of al and singular men, which also such as are but euen meanely instructed in the chiefe pointes of their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian faith vnderstand not wel, and as much as to them is sufficient is playne ynough.</p>
   <p>The ten commaundementes are knowen, the articles of fayth are knowen the forme of the Lordes praier is knowen, the maner of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme and institution of the Lordes supper are knowen, the ministerye also of remitting and retaining synnes in the name of Christe is kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen. In which principal pointes are contayned, almoste all maner of controuersies that the world hath in religion.</p>
   <p>Wherefore the Laity ought so to stand and leane vnto the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Counsels that in the tyme they knowe that it is no lesse subiect vnto the woord of the Lorde, than are men which bee moste simple in Christian faith. And by this meanes there should be no new thing or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained in Counsels, or which is repugnant vnto Christian faith, but forasmuch as it is a very easye thing to fall from Christian fayth into sundry and pernitious errours, it is nedeful that these errours should in godly Synodes by men of vnderstanding bee knowen and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, least the faith of the simple should decay, which ar not able to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstande and to attayne vnto scholastical and synodical disputations, if men would there vse them.</p>
   <p>Wherefore the ruder sort of the Laity depend not vpon the decrees of Counsels, to beleue this thing or that thing, but vpon the symple and playne doctrine, which is most briefely contained in the principall pointes of the Cathechis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e. Unto which also the Counsels giue help, least they should be troubled with the subtill reasoning of ambitious men, which being neglected, they content them selues with the moste plaine &amp; most simple doctrine of the Cathechis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e, according to which they may for their simplicity iudge of al doctrines as muche as is suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for them.</p>
   <p>But this woorthily much greueth godly men, that when there is mencion wade <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>f Papisticall Synodes, the true iudge cannot execute
<pb facs="5"/>
his office. For in the last former communication celebrated at Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes in the yeare. 1557, they whiche were appointed collocutors on the Bishop of Romes side, by apert and manyfest woordes affirmed that the holy scripture is not the voice of the Iudge, by whom one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sentence should be geuen in knowing and iudging of controuersies of religion, but that it is matter of strife. Which their sentence if they should still stand vnto, then shoulde godlye Teachers come wyth no fruite to institute a conferring with them, for they haue no other rule to know the truth besydes the holy scripture. For this is a perpetual rule. Whatsoeuer is found to be repugnaunt vnto the scripture of the prophetes and of the Apostels, of what authority so euer it be, it must be reiected. But they which can not abide this sole and onely Iudge, it is manifest that these haue a mystrust in their cause: Unto which the holye fathers haue made all their writinges subiect: which in all partes agreeth with it selfe, when as the fathers often tymes, are not onely repugnaunt one to an other, but also vnto themselues, whyche thing besydes other thinges Augustines bookes of retractations doo testifye.</p>
   <p>But the doctrine of the Prophetes &amp; of the Apostels is an vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted testimony of the wyl of God, and a most certaine rule of the truth, and the very expresse voyce of the Iudge. If we (sayth the Apostle) or an Angel from heauen preache anye other Gospell vnto you, than that which wee haue preached vnto you, let him bee accursed. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: <note place="margin">Gala. 1.</note> If any man come vnto you and bring not this doctrine, receaue him not into your house, neither say ye so muche as God speede vnto <note place="margin">2. Iohn. 1. Math. 7. Luke. 3.</note> him. And the father from heauen speaketh: This is my welbeloued Sonne in whom I am well pleased, him heare ye. Wherefore there can be no other Iudge in controuersies of religion, than the woorde of God deliuered in the scripture of the Prophetes and of the Apostles, vnto which al Canons, al constitutions, al the writinges of al the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ought to be subiect and bounde vnto this voyce of the Iudge, whereby they shoulde be eyther approued or reiected. In this matter let nothing bee attributed vnto the arbitrement of a priuate man: let there be a godly and modest conferring together of sentences institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, of the matter of strife, which are the sundry opinions of men, and not the holy scripture, which in al partes agreeth with it selfe, beynge spoken by the spirite of truth. If it onelye myght beare rule in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels, controuersies would easely be quieted.</p>
   <p>Wherefore forasmuch as euen from the beginning of the spreadyng abroade of the Gospel through out the whole world Synodes of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and godly men haue bene iudged of al the godly not onely health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but also necessary: Of which Synodes this ought to be the onelye purposed scope and ende, namely that the doctrine of the Church may be purged to the prayse of almighty God, and offences taken awaye, and discipline woorthy for the Gospel restored and preserued in al or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. The bishop of Rome Pius the fourth hath agayne called a coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel
<pb facs="5"/>
of Cardinals, bishops, &amp; Monkes at Trent: wherin he with great glory &amp; magnificence, promiseth both the purging of doctrine from al errours and heresies, and also a sooner amendement of maners, and woorthy for the Gospel as well in the Clergye as in the people. And to the end the vnlearned should not deubt of the diligence of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Counsell, they are not afeard not onelye to accuse them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues of dissolute lyfe, but also to make them selues gyltye before the whole world as the fountaine and authors of al euyls: as the actes of this Counsel shal declare in their place.</p>
   <p>And who would not be glad to helpe such a one which promiseth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgation of the doctrine of the Church and maners with such care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes and endeuour, chiefelye in suche a dissipation of Churches? Who would not to his power helpe so godlye and holye an enterprise? But if wee examine the Canons and decrees, whiche not long since came foorth from this Counsell, euery Christian man shal easely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, that these good holy Fathers entende nothing lesse: yea rather all their labour and endeuour is onelye to thys purpose, to oppresse sound doctrine, and that being oppressed, stubbornly to defende idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, superstition &amp; abuses which are brought into the Church of God.</p>
   <p>When I vnderstoode these thinges, of such things which are eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye where caryed about in many mens handes, and there wythal saw very many to hang in doubt and suspense by expectation of this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel and authority thereof, and earnestly to hope for a symple, godly and plaine determination of controuersies of religion, of whyche number yet in the meane time (whilest they haue bene decreeing of al the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersies) manye haue not without great daunger of their soules de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted out of this lyfe: I thought I should doo a woorthy act, if brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and perspicuously I should declare by the woord of the Lord, what is to be iudged of their disputations, decrees and Canons, and what is to be hoped for of the euent of this Counsel. And I trust I shal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, and that moste manifestiye, that all Christians are by Pius the fourth, bishop of Rome, called to this Counsel, not as lost sheepe to be sought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> healed of the Pastor, but vnder a most pleasaunt &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>eke forme of a Cat, the saluation of the faithful is layde in wayte for, and the sheepe of Christ are lyke to be torne in peeces, euen as it were of Wolues clothedin sheepes clothing, as many as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> them selues to be brought to this amity and familiarity.</p>
   <p>And I desyre the godly &amp; Christian Reader, that remouyng away peruerse affections, which otherwise euen in things humane ar most wicked counsellers, he bring to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of this cause an vpright minde, which subdueth it selfe not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> persuasions, but soly and onely vnto the woorde of God. For by that meanes I trust it shall come to passe, that he shal easely be able to vnderstand, what is to be iudged of papistical Counsels. Now therfore by Gods helpe and furtheraunce, we wyll come to the matter it selfe.</p>
   <p>The thynges that came to my hand being sent from Trent, are not
<pb facs="6"/>
all of one kynde. For certayne thynges were proposed to deliberate vpon for the reformation of the Church, certayne thinges are decrees of the Counsel and Canons appointed to be obserued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the Church. But how fewe so euer they be in number, yet they so open vnto vs the hart of the Fathers assembled at Trent, that we may easely perceaue what affection they beare vnto the true and sincere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>yth and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whych we professe.</p>
   <p>But least anye man hauing lytle say the to our sayinges, myghte doubte of the truth of the thing, I thought it good to annexe to this writing all and syngular thynges, as they came to our handes from Trent being printed by the Printers longyng to the Papacye. that the godly Reader may see, that we speake nothing but with such fidelitye as is conuenient, neyther doo we of purpose or wyll cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ll in any thyng, but onely ayde and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sende the truth of the heauenly doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, and desyre to farther all them that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>