<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my friend both by water and land IOHN TAYLOR.</title>
           <author>B., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118270_Fr1_10</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13493</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23791</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118270</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my friend both by water and land IOHN TAYLOR.</title>
                 <author>B., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The scvller : rowing from Tiber to Thames with his boate laden with a hotch-potch, or gallimawfry of sonnets, satyres, and epigrams. With an addition of pastorall equiuocques or the complaint of a shepheard. By Iohn Taylor</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Butter, Nathaniel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Gosson, Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <head>To my friend both by water and land IOHN TAYLOR.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>OFt hast thou traueld for me at thy Oare,</l>
      <l>But neuer in this kind did'st toyle before.</l>
      <l>To turne a Poet in this peeuish tyme,</l>
      <l>Is held as rare as I should write in rime,</l>
      <l>For one of thy profession, yet thy Art,</l>
      <l>Surpasseth mine: this serues to paint that part,</l>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <l>I meane thy Poetry which in thee lurkes,</l>
      <l>And not thy sweating skill in water workes.</l>
      <l>I cannot but commend thy Booke, and say</l>
      <l>Thou merritst more then common Scullers pay:</l>
      <l>Then whistle off thy Muse, and giue her scope.</l>
      <l>That she may soundly cease vpon the Pope:</l>
      <l>For well I see that he and many more,</l>
      <l>Are dar'de by her (which scarce was done before)</l>
      <l>Proceed (good <hi>Iohn</hi>) and when th'ast done this worke,</l>
      <l>Feare not to venter trussing of the Turke.</l>
      <l>I like thy vaine, I loue thee for those gifts</l>
      <l>Of Nature in thee, far aboue the shifts</l>
      <l>That others seeke plodding for what they pen,</l>
      <l>Wit workes in thee, Learning in other men,</l>
      <l>Thou natiue language we haue done thee wrong,</l>
      <l>To say th'art not compleat, wanting the tongue</l>
      <l>Cald Latine, for heere's one shall end the strife,</l>
      <l>That neuer learned Latine word in's life.</l>
      <l>Then to conclude, I truly must confesse,</l>
      <l>Many haue more bene taught, hut learned lesse.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy assured friend R. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>