<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           <author>Traske, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118597_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13875</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24178</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118597</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 <author>Traske, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of libertie from Iudaisme, or An acknowledgement of true Christian libertie, indited and published by Iohn Traske: of late stumbling, now happily running againe in the race of Christianitie</title>
                 <author>Traske, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Butter, Nathaniel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 42, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Courteous READER,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I may not question thy Christianitie, then, I hope, not suspect thy charitie, in the view of this short Treatise. And though it bee somewhat confused, yet better is a tattered habite, where the body is sound, and the heart sincere, then gorgeous and well set attire on a false heart, and rotten carkasse. And what euer this booke may seeme to portend, yet I aime at nothing but mine owne discharge of dutie, in the free acknowledgement of all my failings. I meddle not with the instruction of any, but the helpe of such as haue beene hurt by mee; and that all may know that I haue done with Iudaisme. Helpe mee, therefore, as I should helpe thee, against secret slanders, and willing mistakings of some maleuolent ones: And tell them that with me, that Pentameter is so true:
<q>
         <l>
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>,</l>
      </q>
      <q>
         <l>Euerie forced businesse is grieuous,</l>
      </q>
That I should neuer haue done ought by costraint: Yea, I know certainly, that <hi>Nemo inuitus bene agit, etiam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>si bonum est, quod facit,</hi> No man vnwillingly doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="5"/>
thing well, though that which he doth he verie good. It is almost a whole yeare since God graciously relieued mee in so great a straite. And though some pennes haue runne (as I since perceiue) and tongues beene exercised, in wounding mee causelesly in other things; yet God is sufficient to take iust reuenge, if my obedience were once fulfilled: Which vengeance, God auert, if it be his will, by giuing them hearts to raze out some vntruths out of their more then satyricall Inuectiues, and forbeare reproches for time to come. And desiring thy patience to reade the whole ouer, passing by the quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations in reading, though not in trying the truth of them all: I rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy brother,<lb/>
that prayeth for thee,<lb/>
IOH: TRA.</signed>
      <date>May 5. 1620.</date>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>