<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the looser sort of Women.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118753_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14083</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24393</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118753</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the looser sort of Women.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Asylum veneris, or A sanctuary for ladies : Iustly protecting them, their virtues, and sufficiencies from the foule aspersions and forged imputations of traducing spirits</title>
                 <author>D. T. (Daniel Tuvill)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lisle (L’isle, Lyle), Laurence</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 64, 75-162 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the looser sort of Women.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>STand of you foule adulterate brats of Hell,</l>
      <l>Whose lunges exhale a worse then sulph'rous smell,</l>
      <l>Do not attempt with your prophaner hands</l>
      <l>To touch the Shrine, in which chast Ʋirtue stands.</l>
      <l>Hence <hi>Messallina,</hi> hence, backe to the stew,</l>
      <l>And in that cage thy blouded Pinions mew.</l>
      <l>Hence you that weigh not, so your thoghts be still'd,</l>
      <l>Though <hi>Naboth</hi>'s bloud be innocently spill'd;</l>
      <l>And being bankrupt of each natiue grace,</l>
      <l>Thinke to catch <hi>Iehu</hi> with a bird-limed Face.</l>
      <l>Hence frisking Faëries, that like <hi>Herods</hi> Noice,</l>
      <l>Esteeme of dancing, as your cheifest peice,</l>
      <l>And with <hi>Sempronia</hi> care not, so your Lute</l>
      <l>Delight the Hearers, though your Soules be mute.</l>
      <l>Hence you, that seek by Philtres, drugs, &amp; charms,</l>
      <l>To bring the curl'd-head Youth into your armes;</l>
      <l>And doe not feare by poyson to remoue</l>
      <l>A worthy Husband, for a worthlesse Loue.</l>
      <l>Hence you, that practise <hi>Aretines</hi> vile shapes,</l>
      <l>Yet can so fairely soder vp your scapes.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="5"/>
That in your Nuptialls first assaults, the Bed</l>
      <l>Shall boast the conquest of a Maiden-head.</l>
      <l>Hence you that striue to haue your outsides brave,</l>
      <l>Yet are within far fouler then your Slaue;</l>
      <l>And will not let, being stirr'd by ranker veines,</l>
      <l>The Groome away, to try your Stallions reines.</l>
      <l>For Women only is this Place ordain'd,</l>
      <l>But you are Monsters, and their Sex haue stain'd.</l>
      <l>Hence therefore, hence, you base, vnhallowed crew,</l>
      <l>Hope for no shelter heere, All such as you,</l>
      <l>That hitherwards for helpe, and succour flie,</l>
      <l>Pluckt from the Altar, must abiure, or die.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>