<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE
Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118243_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15415</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25689</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118243</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE
Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Hexapla in Danielem: that is, A six-fold commentarie vpon the most diuine prophesie of Daniel : wherein according to the method propounded in Hexapla vpon Genesis and Exodus, sixe things are obserued in euery chapter. 1. The argument and method. 2. The diuers readings. 3. The questions discussed. 4. Doctrines noted. 5. Controversies handled. 6. Morall observations applyed. Wherein many obscure visions, and diuine prophesies are opened, and difficult questions handled with great breuitie, perspicuitie, and varietie, which are summed to the number of 536. beside the controversies 134. in the table, in the end of the booke: and the best interpreters both old and new are therein abridged. Diuided into two bookes: the first containing the historicall part of this prophesie, in the 6. first chapters: the propheticall, in the 6. last. By Andrevv Willet Professour of Diuinitie. The first booke</title>
                 <author>Willet, Andrew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 <publisher>Greene, Leonard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legge (Legg), Cantrell.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legge (Legg), Cantrell.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Thomas 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 196, 4, 197-269, 280-520, 18 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE
Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>VGVSTINE thus wrote to a friend of his, excusing the prolixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
of his Preface,<note place="margin">August. praefat ad Valeri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m.</note>
      <hi>Scio me non esse oneri tibi, si prolixum aliquod mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,
quia legendo diutiùs sis nobiscum,</hi> I know I am not burthensome
vnto you, if I send you any prolix writing, because you are so
much the longer with me: But I will forbeare by any long or te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious
Preface to keepe the Reader in suspence; though if I should, I presume
of his courtesie, that he would vouchsafe it the reading. The length of the
Worke, doth make me more short in the Preface: a smal entrance in, may serue
to a large house: and the greatest cities haue not the greatest gates. I shall not
neede in many words to shew the excellent vse of this prophecie of <hi>Daniel,</hi>
nor what I haue performed in it: the generall Questions set before the
Booke, shall satisfie the Reader in the one, and the worke it selfe shall speake
for the other. I haue gathered together the best things, and most worthie of
obseruation, out of writers both old and new, both Protestants and others:
that the Reader may in few houres finde that, which I was many weekes in
setting together: for here I say and professe with <hi>Hierome,</hi>
      <note place="margin">ad Vigilant.</note>
      <hi>Operis est &amp; studij
mei, multos legere, vt ex plurimis diversos flores carperem, non tam probaturus om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,
quam bona electurus: assumo multos in manus, vt à multis multa cognoscam:</hi> It is
mine endeauour and studie, to read many, and out of sundrie to take diuerse
floures, not to that ende to approoue all, but to sort out the best: I take many
into mine hands, that from many I may know much; and impart to others,
that which I know.</p>
   <p>In the reading of this Booke, let the Reader take these directions: I haue
followed the same course, which I propounded vnto my selfe in other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries,
as the title of the booke sheweth: But I thought it best to set
downe the whole text, for more plainenesse and perspicuitie, and not the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
Readings onely: wherein <hi>C.</hi> standeth for <hi>Chalde: H.</hi> for the <hi>Hebrew: L.</hi> for
the <hi>Latine: S.</hi> for the <hi>Septuagint: P.</hi> for <hi>Pagnine: A.</hi> for <hi>Arias Montanus: V.</hi> for
<hi>Vatablus: B.</hi> for the great English Bible: <hi>G.</hi> the <hi>Geneva</hi> translation: <hi>I.</hi> for <hi>Iunius:
det.</hi> is put for <hi>detract: add.</hi> for adding: The Authors names which are cited in
this Booke, are summed in the Epistle set before the second part thereof.</p>
   <p>If by these my trauels I may profit the Church of God, I haue my desire:
it is mine onely terrene reward and encouragement, if my poore labours
may finde acceptance: other rewards they sooner carie that labour not, then
they which labour:<note place="margin">Hos ego v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culos feci, tulit alter honores. Virgil.</note> as the Poet sometime complained, <hi>that he made the verses,
and other had the honour:</hi> As for my selfe, I finde by experience that saying of
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>Augustine</hi> most true, <hi>In eo quod amatur, aut non labor autur, aut labor ipse amatur:</hi> in
that which one delighteth in, either there is no labour at all, or the labour it
selfe is loued: and it giueth me encouragement, that I am not in the number
of them,<note place="margin">Metth. 6. 2.</note> of whome our blessed Sauiour saith, <hi>Receperunt mercedem suam,</hi> they
haue receiued their reward. God graunt vs all faithfully to labour in
our vocations in this life, that we may receiue our euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting
reward in heauen with Christ our blessed
Lord and onely Sauiour, to whome
be praise for euer.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>