<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Est, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118580_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00405</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10536.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118580</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Est, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sathans sowing season. By William Est minister and preacher of Gods word in Bydeford</title>
                 <author>Est, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bonian (Bunnian), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 7-101, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_Christian_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb n="7" facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not long ago (cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Reader) that I handled the same sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect in substance, as in this succeeding Treatise in my Booke intituled <hi>The Scourge of Security,</hi> or the expul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and returne of the vncleane spirit: which after it passed the perusing of some of my learned and sincere friends, they wished that I had beene more copious, and sharpe, then therin I was, in scourging the carnall security that is so farre spread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade, in all sorts, in this pampering and selfe louing age. Which sparingnesse in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing, I haue in this following discourse in part amended, according to my simple and single talent, not hiding it in the earth, or keeping it to my selfe, but opening
<pb facs="4"/>
it to thy view, and desiring the exchange of thy feruent and faithfull prayers for this my well wishing to thy saluation, and that it may, at the generall account, be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to him that first gaue it, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of true zeale and knowledge, both in thee and me. And I humbly pray, that I, who reproue this sinne of security in thee, (which is the open gap to let in all thy spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual enemies into thy body &amp; soule) may my selfe flye it, and thereby bee the more carefull how wee displease so gracious a God, and grieue so louing a Father as we haue in heauen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord
WILLIAM ESTH.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>