<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epilogue vnto him, for whom the first draught of this Apologie, was priuately addressed.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118523_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19394</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5822</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118523</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epilogue vnto him, for whom the first draught of this Apologie, was priuately addressed.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An apologie for svndrie proceedings by iurisdiction ecclesiasticall, of late times by some chalenged, and also diuersly by them impugned : By which apologie (in their seuerall due places) all the reasons and allegations set downe as well in a treatise, as in certaine notes (that goe from hand to hand) both against proceeding ex officio, and against oaths ministred to parties in causes criminall; are also examined and answered: vpon that occasion lately reuiewed, and much enlarged aboue the first priuate proiect, and now published, being diuided into three partes: th first part whereof chieflie sheweth what matters be incident to ecclesiasticall conisance; and so allowed by statutes and common law: the second treateth (for the most part) of the two wayes of proceeding in causes criminal ... the third concerneth oaths in generall ... Whereunto ... I haue presumed to adioine that right excellent and sound determination (concerning oaths) which was made by M. Lancelot Androvves</title>
                 <author>Cosin, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barker, Christopher, Deputies of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 130, 10, 140, 2, 4, 255, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="epilogue">
   <head>The <hi>Epilogue</hi> vnto him, for whom the first draught of this <hi>Apologie,</hi> was priuately addressed.</head>
   <p>THus haue I as plainely as I could, and as briefly as the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter would suffer (in my rude maner) shewed vnto you, my simple opinion, in the points aforesayd, lately called into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie: and (by the way) in others also, wherein you haue so earnestly (almost) importuned me to trauell. If it doe (but as it is like) not satisfie you; impute it to the shortnes of time, lacke of good leisure, and chiefly to your owne bad choise of me. If any thing be mistaken by ignorance, or ouerslipt (as I doubt not but very much is, and may be) keepe you promise with me: and let this simple <hi>Treatise</hi> haue no more, nor other readers of it, then I wish. and so shall I haue lesse cause to doubt, but that the censures of it, will be nothing so sharpe, as (I feare) they may be iust, for want of skill in me, to deale in matters of this qualitie.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>