<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Impartiall Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118669_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14953</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18507.221</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118669</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Impartiall Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Septemb. 2. Numb. 37. The continvation of our forraine avisoes, from the 20. of the last moneth to this present : Containing, the confirmation of the newes published the 20.th of August, concerning the severall encounters betwixt the King of Sweden and General Tilly, with the three dayes welcome given him, upon his project of nayling the K. of Sweden ordnance. An apologie of the King of Swedens (formerly published in the Dutch) not vnfit to give satisfaction to the world, concerning his not releeving of the citie Magdenburgh, wherein you shall finde a briefe relation of the Kings proceeding ever since hee began the warre in Germanie. The landing of the L. Generall, the Marquis Hamilton at Stralsunt, with all his men sound and well</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 14 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Impartiall Reader.</head>
   <p>IN our last Avisoes the 20. of <hi>August</hi> (which was devided into 2. parts) wee printed severall passages of the late good successe and Victories of the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> against Monsieur <hi>Tilly,</hi> as wee received them from forreine parts, which was published by us with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out addition or subtraction, &amp; might have given some credit to the same, and deserued a more favorable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction from the most malevolently affected, yet from some it could receive no better approbation, than that all was lyes, and that the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> was kild, or taken Prisoner, and his Army utterly defeated, as at this houre some shame not impudently to maintaine both heere, and beyond sea at <hi>Antwerp, Bruxels,</hi> and else-where. Wherefore wee doe now publish (as wee have received them from better hands a confirmation of the Truth thereof with some circumstances not in our former, and against which, let the most barking curre open his mouth and say as formerly. God grant him the multiplication of the like victories and good successe untill all his Enemies be vanquished, and a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Peace setled in all the parts of <hi>Germany,</hi>
   </p>
   <trailer> Amen.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>