<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE WHOLE
rabble of English-borne, Romish
male-contents, and disturbers of
this State.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118537_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13961</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24270</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118537</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE WHOLE
rabble of English-borne, Romish
male-contents, and disturbers of
this State.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fierie tryall of Gods saints (these suffered for the witnes of Iesus, and for the word of God, (vnder Queene Mary,) who did not worship the Beast ... As a counter-poyze to I.W. priest his English martyrologe. And the detestable ends of popish traytors: (these are of Sathans synagogue, calling themselues Iewes (or Catholiques) but lie and are not ... Set downe in a comparatiue collection of both their sufferings. Herewith also the concurrance and agreement of the raignes of the kings of England and Scotland, since the first yeare of Q. Mary, till this present, the like before not extant))</title>
                 <author>Burton, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Johnson (Jonson), Arthur</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 40, 24, 10, 2 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_Papists">
   <pb n="22" facs="14"/>
   <head>TO THE WHOLE
rabble of English-borne, Romish
male-contents, and disturbers of
this State.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OT HOPING
hereby to reclaime you
(that are already by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans
witchcrafts sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced)
from your many
dangerous and perniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
errors, which cleaue
more fast vnto you then
the skinne vnto the flesh, or the flesh vnto the
bones, for that were <hi>Extra spem sperare,</hi> a hope
without any ground: Nor yet in bitternesse of
spirit (onely) purposing to rayle vpon you as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
of you most jmpudently haue done against
your owne Mother, for that were want of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity:
nor any waies intending to giue satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
vnto your vnsatisfiable obstinacy and wilfull-willing
blindnesse, by reasoning scholastically,
or propounding and framing logicall (or as you
vse sophisticall) arguments to conuince your fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,
for that would be in me presumption; For
what am I that after so many rare wits, and vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futable
iudgemēts in matters Diuine, as haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
laboured your conversion, I should hope
<pb n="23" facs="14"/>
of better successe therein then they before haue
had?</p>
   <p>I rather conclude with <hi>Abraham,</hi> who told
the rich man that desired a messenger to be sent
from the dead to the liuing to warne them that
they might auoyd the like daunger of comming
there, <hi>That if they will not belieue the Prophets, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
would they belieue though one came frō the dead:</hi>
so if you will not be perswaded by the scriptures,
and the strong and vn-answerable arguments of
such excellent Diuines as haue already laboured
your convesion, neither will you be perswaded
though Christ himselfe should descend from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
in person to confute you.</p>
   <p>But my scope and drift herein is, <hi>(pro viribus)</hi>
First to preuent the fall of those who yet stand but
are ready to fall. Secondly, to free my late Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> that sometimes peere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse
Prince, and my now dread Soueraigne the
Kings Majestie, and their State-ministers from
many false and Serpentine jmputations, layd vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
them by men of your rancke, of bad spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
whose throats are open Sepulchres, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
to burie true Honour, Faith keeping, Grace,
Mercie, Pittie, Piety, Protection, Truth and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
in eternall obliuion; breathing out from
thence (as from the fournace of Hell) insteed
thereof nothing but Dishonour, Breach of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise,
Disgrace, Crueltie, Bloud, Want of deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
Oppression, Heresie, and Irreligion.</p>
   <p>These are the motiues that enforced my pen▪
<pb n="24" facs="15"/>
these the reasons of my non-silence, who other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
could haue been contented quietly and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely
to haue reposed my selfe in the joyfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation
of Gods manifold blessings and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
of an extraordinary nature towards this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
by continuance of the Gospell amongst vs,
Which, that it is the Truth, and that he himselfe
with his owne right hand hath planted it, and
defended it by the power of his owne arme, the
many strange Miracles (for such say you must
needs approoue the Truth) which himselfe from
time to time since before the beginning of Q. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeths</hi>
raigne vntill this present hath wrought,
doe euidently confirme and prooue.</p>
   <p>For is it possible that our late famous Queene
of euer-blessed memorie,<note place="margin">The Miracles that god hath wrought for confirmation of his gospell.</note> and our now Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
the Kings Maiestie, should haue escaped
the many pitts that haue beene digged for them,
and not haue fallen therein? Is it possible that
Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> full of yeares but fuller of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne,
should haue liued vnto a gray-headed
age, and quietly dying in her bed, to be maugre
all her enemies, brought in peace vnto her graue?
Is it possible that this present State wherein wee
liue should now haue a Being, seeing that Hell,
the Pope, <hi>[Vt obiter notē.</hi> The word Recusant,
(now so common) vntill the Eleauenth yeare of
Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Ragine, was altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne,
(as may appeare by all Statutes and
Acts of Parliament before that time made, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
there is not a word thereof at all) vntill which
<pb n="25" facs="15"/>
time all Papists, some very few excepted, (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding,
that the Religion then professed
in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> was the very same
that it was in the former yeares of her Raigne)
came ordinarily to our Churches, nor was dispa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
of religiō any cause of Recusancy, vntil such
times that the roaring Bull of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> 5. (for
then the land began to swarme with Recusants)
was published, and Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> by him A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathematized:
Then the case was suddenly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered,
those who before frequented our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
now withdraw themselues from our Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;
Those who before yeilded obedience to
his <hi>Maiestie,</hi> now would not acknowledge her
for their lawfull Queene; herevpon followed
jmmediatly the rebellion in the North, and other
dangerous conspiracies by your faction. And
to proue that Religion was not the cause of their
Recusancy (besides that which hath beene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouesayd)
<hi>Scotland</hi> will testifie, wherein albeit
there haue beene and are many knowen Papists
both men and women, yet in all the time of King
<hi>Iames</hi> his Raigne there, nor yet since he raigned
here, haue any of thē absented thēselues or refused
to come to our Churches in <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp; yet I make
no question but you will say that the Romish re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
is one and the same there that it is here:
you must needs then graunt, that not religion
but the Popes pleasure (vnto whose girdle you
are tyed) is the cause of Recusancy, and it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooueth
his Maiestie to haue speciall regard vnto
<pb n="26" facs="16"/>
you that are Recusants, and by all good meanes
that he can to assure his owne estate, in another
regard then only that you will not, <hi>interesse sacris,</hi>
with vs, for Recusancy and Treason are so lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
one in the other, and compacted, that hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
can hee bee a Recusant that is not a Traitour
likewise. See more hereof if you please in
the 130 and 131. pages of <hi>Tortura Torti.]</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minarie
Priests and Iesuites, Traitors and sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
persons haue conspired against it, had not
the Lord himselfe miraculously defended it, and
maintained his Truth?</p>
   <p>I need not instance particular deliuerances, for
who is he amongst vs that remembers not many?
But yet I cannot without ingratitude to God,<note place="margin">Two mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</note> our
most gracious preseruer, ouer-slip in silence those
two myracles of myracles,<note place="margin">The 1.</note> to wit, <hi>Our deliuerance
from Spaines (so falsely by them tearmed, but blessed
be God therefore) inuincible Armado, An.</hi> 1588. and
from the mynes of fire and Gunpowder prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
by ympes of Hell,<note place="margin">The 2.</note> for Englands Funerall An.
1605. which latter but that mine own eyes haue
seene their preparations, I should (with <hi>Thomas)</hi>
scarcely haue belieued:<note place="margin">The Iesuits reported in Spaine that there was no such matter as the gun-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Treason. Related by the L. <hi>Cooke</hi> at the Earle of <hi>Northumberl.</hi> conviction, in the Star-chā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. Iune 27. 1606.</note> And no maruell though
in <hi>Spain</hi> the report therof can with many hardly
be credited, for some at our own home that haue
not with their owne eyes seene it, or with their
eares heard the Delinquents, <hi>Viva voce,</hi> confesse
it, can hardly, yet conceaue halfe the malice ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
it seemes to those that haue any sparkes of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie,
so passing cruell and incredible. These
<pb n="27" facs="16"/>
if the Gospell must needs be confirmed by myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,
are true myracles.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>These are no counterfait jugling trickes, or
Popish impostures to delude the simple,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Childish and strawish My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles.</note>
      <hi>such as
were the</hi> Sicknesse-healing Child, or the Picture of
the Traitour <hi>Garnets</hi> face in a wheat strawe, found
perhaps amongst a Popish Taylors wiues shreds, or
brought in in the belly of a Griffin or Gryfō, intēding
thereby the ruine of <hi>Troynovant,</hi> as were the armed
men of <hi>Yore</hi> in the bellie of <hi>Synons</hi> woodden horse,
for <hi>Troye</hi> the old its Destruction: <hi>such as these
we leaue to you to insert into your</hi> Legenda Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea,
<hi>or Legend of lyes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>As for persecution for conscience,<note place="margin">In your sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to the kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, Anno. 1603. &amp; An. 1604 in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places thereof: as also in diuerss other treaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable bookes since by you set forth and dispersed.</note> against
which in diuers of your pamphlets you so loud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
cry, the comparison of times for continuance
wherein, of persons for numbers in those times,
how many, whose bloud on both sides haue been
shed, and the causes (partly) wherefore, in the
following Table will appeare. But the grounds
of religion, contained in the holy Scriptures of
the old and new Testament, penned by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
and Apostles, on which we build our faith,
and the refutation of errors and false doctrine
maintained by Romish Recusants, Priests, and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suites
which in former times and in these times
also haue &amp; do cause so great disturbances &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutions
of the Church of Christ, I leaue to bee
defended by those graue and strong pillars of our
Church, and learned Fathers of our Clergie,
whose foundnesse in doctrine all the Papists in
<pb n="28" facs="17"/>
the world are vnable to evince.</p>
   <p>Concerning that dishonour wherewith very
frequētly but falsely (as is well<note n="*" place="margin">Tortura Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti. Page 83.</note> approued by the
then Bishop of <hi>Chichester)</hi> you taxe your Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
Lord the Kings Maiestie for breach of
promise with Recusants, concerning a toleration
of Popish religion, that <hi>(quantum in me est)</hi> I may
confute such vnjust exclamations against his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties
Person and his Honour, I will briesly touch
that poynt, by declaring not onely vnto you, but
vnto all the world that shall take notice hereof,
what mine owne eares heard in an open Court
(of mercy I may say rather then of justice in this
case) debated and censured.<note place="margin">The Starre-chamber.</note>
   </p>
   <p>The case stood betweene the Kings Majestie
&amp; a great Peere of this Land, amongst whose ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
grosse slippes and juglorious acts, this poynt
was as the rest (all which his Majestie was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,
nay (as sayd the Lord <hi>Cooke</hi> then the Kings
Attourney) commanded that they should not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise
bee handled then as matters of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt)
ripped vp and scanned. His name I could
particularly instāce, but because it pleased my So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne
to deale with him not in rigor of law &amp;
justice but meerly in Grace, I hold it not my part
(othewise then what for clearing of the truth I
needsly must) him by name to disgrace.</p>
   <p>Wherfore that I may helpe to wash away those
aspertions of dishonour, vnjustly throwen vpon
his sacred Majesty by men of bad spirits, and that
like spots and staines neuer to be done away▪ they
<pb n="29" facs="17"/>
may seat themselues within the muddy Circle of
the duskie Moone, their true Centre, and not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipse
the bright honour of our splendant Sun &amp;
glorious North-star, I will here relate frō whence
by much probabilitie, this error at first sprange.</p>
   <p>This noble fore-remembred Personage,<note place="margin">Omne animi vitium tanto conspectius i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> se crimē habet, quanto maior qui peccat ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur.</note> whose
greatnesse addes a greatnes to his fault, (if I may
linke Nobilitie with such jgnoble actions) ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiously
(as it should seeme) affecting a singular
greatnesse, not at all regarding Religion (as some
haue thought) further then as it might serue him
as a ladder to promotion, was in shew outwardly
a seeming Protestant, but vnder-hand and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertly,
willing to be held a Papist, jnsomuch that
by his close carriage hee was very honourablie
thought of by his Majestie, &amp; chosen by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie
to be very neere vnto him, and yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse
highly accompted of and respected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
the Romanists for a sure friend of theirs,
vpon whom they might hold a Dependance; Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified
hereby, that with his owne hands he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered
and presented their Popish Supplication
vnto his Majestie at <hi>Theobalds,</hi> for a toleration in
Anno. 1603.</p>
   <p>And that I may not seeme maliciously of my
selfe without a ground to taxe him herein of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition,
<note place="margin">The now <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Cooke.</hi>
      </note> obserue with me, that at his tryall (by one
for his learning judicious, for his knowledge ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced
in matters of State) it was by euident
arguments prooued that his proceedings argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
a manifest Discontentmēt, and withall that all
<pb n="30" facs="18"/>
discontentments proceeded from either want,
disgrace, or ambition; but not from want, for his
possessions and yearely revenues were exceding
great; not frō disgrace, for his Majestie had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
waies graced &amp; highly honoured him; (which
graces as he then did, so I now could particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
jnstance, but that thereby I must needsly disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
his person) and therefore of necessitie from
Ambition.</p>
   <p>Likewise as then by one was obserued his am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition
in his jntentions and thoughts, so by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of higher rancke and dignitie was noted his
dissimulation in his actions,<note place="margin">The Lord Archbishop of <hi>Cant.</hi>
      </note> for said he, there are
in all his proceedings, <hi>Vestigia manifesta,</hi> &amp; <hi>vestigia
occulta,</hi> giving withall an jnstāce herein, <hi>That this
great personage had admitted</hi> T. P. <hi>that Archtraitor
to be a Pentioner,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The word thē vsed was, To hold an Axe ouer the Kings head.</note> but yet without hauing any oath
administred him, either for his allegeance, or yet
for his particular discharge of that place where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto
he was admitted, and yet vnderhand giuing
out that he was sworne, wherevpon he jnferred
thus, <hi>That wheresoeuer things were palliated which
were, or fayned to be which are not, there alwaies is
some deceit.</hi> At which time he was by a third ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
personage taxed expreslie for his <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie,</hi>
as being <hi>Iacke on both sides,</hi> whereby hee
had made himselfe odious to both Protestants (so
tearmed) and Papists:<note place="margin">The L. <hi>Zouch.</hi>
      </note> nor yet (though these are
jnough) are these all. But to returne to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose
and matter in hand.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Before he ascended vnto that height of honor
<pb n="31" facs="18"/>
(which then by the Kings speciall favour he was
advanced vnto) I meane in Queene</hi> Elizabeths
<hi>time, when his predecessours carriage had givē
just occasion of the successours further disgrace,
then</hi> [at this very time was the same person imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
vnto his maiestie with letters from <hi>Garnet</hi> the
Iesuites Prouinciall, who had about that time recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
the Popes Breues to this purpose, <hi>Quandocun{que}
contigerit miseram illam faeminam</hi> (meaning Q.
<hi>Elizabeth) ex hac vita exire,</hi> &amp;c. that whensoeuer
that wretched woman should die, the papists should not
admit of any other to inherite, how neere so euer in
bloud, vnlesse he were a (Romish) Catholique, and not
so onely, vnlesse he would also sweare to vphold to his
power the popish Religion. But the Kings happie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation
with his good Subiects, caused those to bee
converted into ashes, and then come other Breues en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyning
their obedience to his Maiestie, but <hi>Coacta
virtus non est virtus,</hi> Gramercy horse when you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
choose, then obay. This is that <hi>Obedientia, ex
necessitate, nempe ferreâ jlla &amp; coactâ,</hi> which <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi>
noteth <hi>Recognitionum, pag.</hi> 16. And
how long this? vntill they be able to cast him out whō
they were forced to receaue. And your <hi>Watson</hi>
soone attempted that which hee knew his vnholy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
the Pope hartily wished. Hee was a lowe man in
person, but he aspyred high when he thought to bee
Lord Chancellor of <hi>England:</hi> but missing that, hee
was aduanced to the Gallowes for preferment, but I
thinke being purblind, he missed the waye that hee
meant] <hi>I say did this double-hearted Lord jm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy
<pb n="32" facs="19"/>
T. P. the Traytor vnto the Kings Majestie
then King only of Scotland, with certain letters
of advise, but much in the behalfe of the English
Romish Catholicks, aduising him that he should
at such time as it should please the Lord to call
him to the possession of this his kingdome (which
as now he doth, so long Lord grant he may qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly
enjoye) giue faire promises and hopes of tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration
vnto the Papists, thereby (as he therein
pretended) to prepare a more easie entrance for
his Majestie when time should serue.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The Kings Majestie (not as then suspecting
the depth of this his Councellors drifts, but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding
him simply) returned him an answere,
with thankes for his advise, but withall jnferring
a clause directly (as since it appeareth) contrarie
to his Councellors expectation. His Majesties
words in answere to the letter, were in effect as
followeth.</p>
   <p>
      <q>Whensoeuer it shall please GOD in his due
time to call mee to the possession of my right in
<hi>England,</hi> I purpose not to make any jnnovation in
the State, or to alter the Lawes and Ordinances
thereof, &amp;c.</q> Wherevppon a wise man would
(as the L L. did) haue thus jnferred: No alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
in the State, no changing of Lawes and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances
therein established; why then no tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiō
of Poperie, no allowance of Recusancy; &amp;
not because it pleased the kings Majestie out of
the meeknesse of his Spirit (voyd of guile and
double dealing) to returne him thankes for his
<pb n="33" facs="19"/>
aduise (although hee did not so much as make
shew that he liked thereof) therefore to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
that a toleration should be granted.</p>
   <p>But he in his ambition besotted with his own
follie, not expounding his Majesties words as he
meant, but as he himselfe conceited them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
he so (as it should euidently appeare) wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed
that it might bee, did so farre exceed the
limits of his commission, and was so farre vainely
transported,<note place="margin">Ʋide Tortûrā Torti Pag. 83. Prom<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ssa nes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioquae commē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti sunt quae ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men nulla sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt &amp; quod factū nunquā est, id fuisse ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men factium in vulgus sparge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant.</note> as that at <hi>T. P.</hi> his returne from the
Kings Majestie, it was amongst the Papists divul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
(though falsely) that the King had also by the
sayd <hi>T. P.</hi> giuen directions to the afore-remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred
great Personage, by word of mouth to
wind himselfe into their favours, (for that was
the word) and to giue hopes of toleration in his
Majesties name vnto Recusants, and herehence
chiefly arose that scandall of the kings Honour,
that he had broken promise with Recusants. For
the better confirmation whereof, and that his
Majesty neuer intended any such matter of tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<note place="margin">
         <hi>vide</hi> the Earle of <hi>Northamp.</hi> printed speech at <hi>Garnets</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignment in pag. 1. of A aa</note> Conferre herewith <hi>Watson</hi> the Priest his
confession vnto the Honourable Lord the Lord
of <hi>Northampton</hi> at <hi>Winchester;</hi> who being by the
Earle (by his Majestie therevnto appoynted) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined
vpon the poynt of promise of toleration,
freely confessed that albeit he were by some fals<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
accused to be the Author of that report, yet it
was most true that hee could neuer at any time
draw any comfort from his Maiestie in the point
of conscience.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="34" facs="20"/>
All which notwithstanding (besides the just
cause that the Powder-treason, and other dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
conspiracies against his Maiesties life and
kingdomes, hatefull to God and all good men,
gaue, of an hard hand ouer the Papists) yet let a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
of you (that I may vse the words of an Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
Counsellor) even the most jmpudent &amp; bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen
faced amongst you,<note place="margin">The Earle of <hi>Salisburie</hi> in his answere to certaine scandalous papers.</note> shew any the least prints
(if you can) of bloudy steppes in his Majesties
Course: Nay rather I may much more truely
say, hee is a man composed all of mercy, and
not of any earthly element, subiect to passions
and disturbance, but in a farre more diuine man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
then ordinary men, resembling his Maker, for
good Kings and mercifull are the most liuely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentatiue
jmages of the Deitie, which causeth
as the wicked without warrant, vpō Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,
so Traitors and miscreant without reason
vppon his Majesties Clemency jmpudently to
presume, to their more just condemnation.</p>
   <p>And here let me tell you (yet voyd of any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire
of bloud or bloudy courses, as God can beare
record vnto my soule, but onely admiring the
mercies of our King) That I greatly doubt
whether any Prince in the world (King <hi>Iames</hi>
excepted) if the like treason as was the Powder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treason,
had been plotted against him by persons
of another religion or sect whatsoeuer, would
haue suffered either man, woman, or child of so
dangerous and damnable a profession, to haue
breathed within his Dominions, especially if the
<pb n="35" facs="20"/>
grounds of their religion (as doth that of yours
by euident proofes elswere convinced) do allow
of any such doctrine and enterprises.<note place="margin">D. <hi>Reynolds</hi> in his preface before his cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with <hi>Hart.</hi> D. <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> M. <hi>Stocke,</hi> with many more.</note>
   </p>
   <p>This Powder-plot-treason was in it selfe, in
the eyes of some of the actors therein, so horride
and detestable, as that one of your owne Iesuites
from an apprehension of the jmmane cruelty
thereof, (not mooued with any commiserati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of their miseries, who were by their designes
destinated to the rage thereof, but proceeding
from a trembling feare least it should be discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red)
could say to his fellow in profession and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<note place="margin">Greenewell, <hi>&amp;</hi> Garnet.</note>
      <hi>That if it were discouered it would be the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
ruine and dissolution of their Society.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Remember also <hi>Robert Winters</hi> dreame and
the horror thereof,<note place="margin">Reported at his arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt in <hi>VVest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minst.</hi> Hall Ianu 27. 1605 mentioned in the Earle of <hi>Northamptōs</hi> speech in the first pag of L.</note> how it terrified his very soule
with the gastly appearance of some of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorts.
And forget not the fearefull vengeance of
God in suffering their faces to be so vgly disfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
with Gunpowder in <hi>Littletons</hi> house, who
had prepared a Destructiō for this whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
with the same matter and Substance; and
then conclude that God is iust, and therefore in
his justice did punish their wickednesse with the
inventions of their owne braines.</p>
   <p>Was it not time to lop those ambitious aspy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
thoughts of <hi>Watson</hi> the Priest and his confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates,
<note place="margin">Confessed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his owne hand in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly read in the Star-chā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber at the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, of the Earle of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberl.</hi> Iun. 27. 1606.</note> as also to clippe the winges of the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-Treason
contriuers and their fauorites, the
first affecting in his owne person the high Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celorship
of <hi>England;</hi> and the latter building
<pb n="36" facs="21"/>
their hopes aboue the Moone,<note place="margin">Confessed in diuers exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations vnder their hands openly read the time and place afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayd.</note> amongst them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
concluding to set vp a Protector of their
own choosing out of the number of those Popish
Lords, that by them were intended should bee
preserued from that generall destruction of their
sulphurious fire, all of them directlie ayming at
the vtter ruine and destruction of this noble and
renowned Iland, and to make desolate the most
glorious Kingdome that is couered by the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens.</p>
   <p>But as the most fruitfull trees beare their tops
lowest,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> and the most barren and vnfruitfull shoote
vp highest, euen so is it amongst men. Those
that are most emptie of vertue and laudable qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities,
aspire in their ambition to places of highest
honour vncalled, whereas the more worthy and
vertuous would in their humility refuse them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
jmposed, were it not onely for this, that they
may thereby be the better jnabled to do good.</p>
   <p>Admit that the Kings Majestie had in a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
pollicy promised a toleration, before he were
fully seated in his kingdome, or come into this
Kingdome, nay that hee had so also meant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
as some of you haue falsely and jmpudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
giuen out; yet had he not, for your extreame
ill carriage and disloyall demeanour, just cause to
haue reuoked it? For before that liberty could
be established for you, there must needes haue
beene a repeale made of those Lawes and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes
formerly made against Recusancy, which as
they were by act of Parliament confirmed, so
<pb n="37" facs="21"/>
must they haue been by the like authority disanul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.
<note place="margin">These for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward spirits (as they wold be thought) for the Kings Succession would yet haue bereft vs of his head before the Crowne had adorned it.</note> But your <hi>Watson</hi> and <hi>Clarke</hi> thought to make
a shorter cut then so, by preventing the King in
the performance of that which <hi>Watson</hi> himselfe
knew full well the King neuer purpose nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised,
albeit it should seeme by <hi>Watsons</hi> owne
confession, that he had much laboured and jm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuned
his Majestie therein. Since which
time also, if his Majestie had promised the like (as
some of your faction haue falsely giuen out) was
not that matchlesse Powder-treason plotted,<note place="margin">Tortura Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti. Page 84.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triued,
<note place="margin">See the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to the kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie in Ann. 1604 neere beginning thereof.</note> furthered, and assisted by beasts (for men
I cannot call them, but rather deuils) of your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
both Priests, Iesuites, and (as you stile your
selues) lay Catholiques, a sufficient warrantise
without prejudice to his honour, to recall such
a grant as might giue protection to Caterpillers,
Degenerate persons, Miscreants, Vipers, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters,
and not men, and whatsoeuer name more
odious, that also; yea vnworthy to bee called
by the name of any of Gods creatures, for they
persist in their created natures, but the other do
not but are degenerated from men to Devils.</p>
   <p>That their damnable practise doth rightly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralize
the tale of the Husbandman, wherein hee
is fabled to haue found a Snake stiffe and almost
dead with cold, and to haue brought him home
in his bosome and warmed him by the fire, which
after recouering began to hisse at the good man
of the house for his paines, and would with his
venomous tongue haue stung him to death, who
<pb n="38" facs="22"/>
had before saued his life; which plainely bids
King <hi>Iames</hi> beware that he nourish not vipers in
his own Kingdome, I pray God not in his Court.</p>
   <p>You seeme in some places of your writings to
taxe Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and in her all true profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ors
of religion for a backward and frozen zeale
towards the Kings Majesties rightfull succession
in these his kingdomes,<note place="margin">See your sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to his Maiestie, Anno. 1604. chap. 5.</note> &amp; to blazō your own for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnesse
in his Majesties behalfe: but know,
you false-hearted and degenerate men, that king
<hi>Iames</hi> knowes how to judge of spirits,<note place="margin">Also in the first part of Engl. three Conversions, neere the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning thereof.</note> and to hold
you but hollow-hearted vnto him now, because
whiles you were yet Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> subiects,
you were then so vnto her, and to esteeme of
our late Queene Honourably, and of vs as faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
Subiects then vnto her, so now no lesse vnto
him. And albeit that for some reasons of State
vnto her selfe best knowen, and which no doubt
but his Majestie now very well vnderstandeth, it
pleased her to conceale the kings right from the
multitude, yet I verily perswade my selfe that his
Majesty did neuer so much as conceiue a thought
that Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did euer purpose or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
to debarre him in his right of lawfull succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.
And in this poynt your fellow Catholiques
thought to cast a Bone between his Majesty and
his good subiects, but you are made to swallow
it your selues, and some whose throats were to
little it choaked. Nor may I here let passe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touched
that Propheticall speech of that worthy
Matriarke (Honourable amongst women) Q. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth,</hi>
      <pb n="39" facs="22"/>
who when in the first yere of her raigne
shee was motioned to dispose her selfe to Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age;
that her subiects might enioy an happy issue
of her own body, like as <hi>Abraham</hi> when his
Sonne <hi>Isaac</hi> sayd <hi>Behold the fire and the wood, but
where is the Lambe for the burnt offring?</hi> Gen. 22. 7.
replyed, <hi>Deus providebit mi fili;</hi> So shee <hi>(Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi>
daughter by fayth) likewise, <hi>Fideles mei sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diti,</hi>
my louing and faithfull Subiects, although
you may justly fear what may be the euent of my
disposednes to a Virgin life, yet be not depressed
with care that way, nor dejected with sorrow,
but trust in God, for <hi>Deus providebit,</hi> hee euen
God, euen that God who made <hi>Sarahs</hi> barren
wombe fruitfull, and he who, although I should
marrie, can cause my wombe to be barren, He,
who <hi>had another meat to eat that his Disciples knew
not of,</hi> Ioh. 4. 32. Euen he I say will provide you
a king of his owne choosing, whome you do not
so much as dreame of, <hi>My Fathers Will must bee
done,</hi> Ioh. 4. 34. <hi>I the Lord will bee their God, and
my seruant</hi> David <hi>shall be the Prince amongst them.
I the Lord haue spoken it,</hi> Ezech. 34. 24. Which
that your eyes haue, after 44. yeares after that,
seene accomplished, do ye and your vn-holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
the Pope fret out your heart-strings, (for so
God blesse, curse ye and spare not) but let all good
and faithfull subiects say alwaies, <hi>The Lords name
be praised.</hi> Her own words (worthy to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
in letters of gold) are recorded by <hi>Io. Stow</hi> in
his Annalls of <hi>Eng.</hi> in the beginning of her raign.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="40" facs="23"/>
And to draw to an end with you, because you
harpe so much vppon two strings, to wit, breach
of promise and bloudshedding;<note place="margin">Mentioned in M. <hi>Fox</hi> his booke of Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyrs in the ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry beginning of Q. <hi>Maries</hi> Raigne.</note> remember the
vowes that Queene <hi>Marie</hi> made to the <hi>Suffolke</hi>
men (by whose ayd shee was setled in her King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome)
and her violation thereof, although not
forced therto by any Conspiracy of the Gospel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers
then, or any attempt (by persons different to
her in religion) against her person after her right
once proclaimed; and withall forget not how
much bloud her breach of promise cost, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
waighed both in an equall ballance of an
jmpartiall and not prejudicate judgement, If
then you justly can, vrge both and spare not, but
in the meane space view in the Table following
with the eyes of pittie the Catalogue of them,
whose bloud was by her and her bloudy Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters
so cruelly, only for religion, shed and exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted.
And so wishing that you would be, but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
hoping that you will be, good Subiects vnto
his Majestie; as I found you so I leaue you, voyd
of Religion, emptie of honesty.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>By him that affoords you as good means to know me,
as your Martyrologist hath done me to know him. <figure>
            <figDesc>monogram incorporating the letters 
FRANCIS BTO (?and U)</figDesc>
         </figure>
      </signed>
   </closer>
   <postscript>
      <lg>
         <l>This knot doth showe</l>
         <l>(If thou would'st know)</l>
         <l>The Authors name;</l>
         <l>Then it vntye</l>
         <l>(And him descrye)</l>
         <l>Or your Priest blame.</l>
         <l>For had he set his name to his</l>
         <l>Then had I mine also to this.</l>
      </lg>
   </postscript>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>