<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Same in English</title>
           <author>Cr., Sa.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118094_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13221</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23520</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118094</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Same in English</title>
                 <author>Cr., Sa.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Svvedish discipline, religious, civile, and military : The first part, in the formes of prayer daily used by those of the Swedish nation, in the armie. Together with two severall prayers, uttered upon severall occasions by that pious King; which God immediately heard and granted him. The second part, in the excellent orders observed in the armie; whereof we here present you the articles, by which the souldiery is governed. The third part, in the Kings commission for levying of a regiment: his order for drawing vp of a private company; of a squadron; and of a brigade: with his manner of enquartering a private regiment; and of an army royall: vnto which is added the best manner of building and fortifying of a towne of warre. All, in fiue severall figures expressed and explained. Last of all, is the famous Battell of Leipsich, in two fayre figures also set forth: and now this second time more fully and particularly described</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dawson, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                            <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 35, 1, 39-90, 43, 1 page, 4 folded leaves of plates, diagrams, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The Same in English</head>
   <l>OH! whom may I thee style, most glorious King</l>
   <l>Or to thy worth what names can worship bring▪</l>
   <l>A <hi>Romulus</hi> in conduct may'st thou be,</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Camillus</hi> in vnconquered honestie.</l>
   <l>In courage thou art great <hi>Achilles</hi> peere,</l>
   <l>In counsell <hi>Nestors,</hi> farre from <hi>Nestors</hi> yeere:</l>
   <l>In th'on-set <hi>Alexander,</hi> one would deeme thee,</l>
   <l>In constant valour, <hi>Caesar</hi> I esteeme thee.</l>
   <l>In martiall skill a <hi>Scipio</hi> thou art,</l>
   <l>An <hi>Hannibal</hi> in stratageme and art.</l>
   <l>All Wonders thou exceed'st of elder age,</l>
   <l>Which <hi>Greece,</hi> or <hi>Rome,</hi> hath left vpon times stage.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Mars</hi> with <hi>Astraea</hi> thou alone dost crowne,</l>
   <l>Fury with Faith, Sword with Law, Armes with Gown.</l>
   <l>If thus the <hi>ravening Tyrants</hi> thou represse,</l>
   <l>And galled neckes from slavish yoke release:</l>
   <l>If (justice strange!) thou part the rescued prey,</l>
   <l>To each his owne, purloyning nought away:</l>
   <l>Of foes if willing Subjects thou create,</l>
   <l>By conquest bettered in their Faith and State;</l>
   <l>Let <hi>Thracia</hi> be thy pay, for <hi>Almaine</hi> free'd,</l>
   <l>For Faith restored <hi>Rome,</hi> shall be thy meed:</l>
   <l>Let Heaven poynt at thy birth, serue in thy warres,</l>
   <l>And blaze thy holy Armes with new-borne starres:</l>
   <l>Be thou the oppressed's Shield, the poores reliefe,</l>
   <l>The Saints good Angel, and Christ's Herauld chiefe,</l>
   <l>Tremble yee guiltie Tyrants to come on,</l>
   <l>Vpon the Sword of Christ and <hi>Gideon.</hi>
   </l>
   <closer>
      <signed>By <hi>Sa: Cr.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>