<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE TRVLY NOBLE, BOTH BY BLOVD and VERTVE, Sir IOHN POULETT, KNIGHT: Sonne and Heire to the Right Ho∣nourable, IOHN, Lord POVLETT, Baron of Henton St. George.</title>
           <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118116_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13272</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23573</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118116</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE TRVLY NOBLE, BOTH BY BLOVD and VERTVE, Sir IOHN POULETT, KNIGHT: Sonne and Heire to the Right Ho∣nourable, IOHN, Lord POVLETT, Baron of Henton St. George.</title>
                 <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sermons vpon solemne occasions : preached in severall auditories. By Humphrey Sydenham, rector of Pokington in Somerset</title>
                 <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Robinson, Humphrey</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 240, 251-316, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="26"/>
   <pb n="39" facs="26"/>
   <head>TO THE TRVLY NOBLE, BOTH BY BLOVD <hi>and</hi> VERTVE, <hi>Sir</hi> IOHN POULETT, <hi>KNIGHT:</hi> Sonne and Heire to the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, <hi>IOHN,</hi> Lord POVLETT, <hi>Baron of Henton S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. George.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F there be a Succession of <hi>Vertues</hi> with the <hi>Fortunes</hi> of <hi>Great men,</hi> doubtlesse there should be of the <hi>Services</hi> of those that <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> them. This makes me speak boldly through the sides of your <hi>Noble Father,</hi> whose continued <hi>respects</hi> towards me, and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements,</hi> I cannot better acknowledge than by my thankefull expressions to <hi>such a Son;</hi> who (in the hopes and expectations of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey)
<pb facs="27"/> shall no lesse inherit <hi>Him,</hi> than his <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes;</hi> Ana then, <hi>Honour, Riches, Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> you cannot but prescribe for; &amp; what else may either intitle you to <hi>Greatnesse</hi> here, or to <hi>Glory</hi> hereafter. Such a <hi>Patronage</hi> as <hi>This,</hi> I could not but listen after, where is as well <hi>Vertue</hi> to countenance me, as <hi>Power;</hi> and so perhaps, <hi>Censure</hi> and <hi>Prejudice</hi> may be a little <hi>hush't,</hi> or at least, not so loud, but that the labours of poore men may travell the world; if not without their <hi>snarlings,</hi> (for who can so muzzle a blacke mouth'd Curre?) yet without their publique <hi>Barkings</hi> and traducements. Beleeve it, Sir, what I present you here is <hi>mine owne,</hi> though but a <hi>mite;</hi> and a mite thus <hi>offered</hi> cannot prove lesse acceptable to a noble <hi>Treasury</hi> than an <hi>Oblation</hi> of a richer value, since your <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will offerings</hi> were ever of best esteeme, both with <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Good men;</hi> which doth hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully incourage me of your faire entertainment of <hi>This,</hi> from the hands of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your most devoted HVM. SYDENHAM.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>