<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Readers: chiefely, his late Auditors at S. Brides in London.</title>
           <author>Jerome, Stephen</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118682_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04391</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14512.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118682</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Readers: chiefely, his late Auditors at S. Brides in London.</title>
                 <author>Jerome, Stephen</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Seauen helpes to Heauen : Shewing 1. How to auoid the curse. 2. How to beare the crosse. 3. How to build the conscience. 4. How with Moses to see Canaan. 5. Simeons dying song, directing to liue holily and dye happily. 6. Comforts for Christians against distresses in life, and feare of death. 7. Feruent prayers, to beare sicknesse patiently, and dye preparedly. The second edition: much enlarged by Steuen Ierome, late preacher at S. Brides. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Jerome, Stephen</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 16, 517, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>To the Readers: chiefely, his late Auditors at S. <hi>Brides</hi> in <hi>London.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Friends, whom I loue vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly, in truth, and for the Truth, as I haue published this myrrhour of dying <hi>Moses,</hi> and Song of holy <hi>Simeon,</hi> for the good of Gods Church in generall (to whom I haue deuoted my selfe, my life, my labours) so in my reserued thoughts, more peculiarly, I tender and present it vnto you, my late Auditors, aboue the rest. First, as your due by right, being some few Gleanings after the Haruest, and some few Grapes of the Ʋintage of my Ministery amongst you, or more plainely and properly the flowers of some Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Sermons, occasionedly preached, now printed for you. Secondly, that you might receiue by this single and simple labor a double benefit, by a redou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled reflexion vpon your vnderstandings, memories and affections; as through the organ of the eare, by hearing, so of the eye, by reading: both which, Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophie cals <hi>Sensus doctrinae,</hi> the senses of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. For which respect I haue turned my tongue into a penne, and the gesture of a liuing man into a dead letter, writing the same things with <hi>Peter,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> spoke twise the same words. Which penning, though in respect of preaching, it be but as a pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted fire, to the powerfull Element; as the dead por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traiture,
<pb facs="8"/>
to the liuing person; like the dead corps, to fighting <hi>Hector,</hi> yet the same things red to those that before heard them, haue the place of the Moone, at least to enlighten the brain, though Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, the power of the Sunne to heate the heart. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides that, you may act the noble Beraeans part the better, in trying the spirits; more retentiuely, and deliberately examining the Truth, then infirme and weake memories could conueniently from a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luble tongue. Thirdly, they are as desiredly so deseruedly yours, euen as my selfe was, with my labours, by mutuall consent: and therefore I send you onely backe those Exercises which you haue payed for: and withall (in my occasioned corporeall absence) the presence of my spirit, the pledge of my heart, the argument of my well-wishes, and constant desires towards you, an Epistle of that zealous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection which I iustly beare you, a testimonie of my gratefull remembrance of all those true effects of your Christian loue towards me: the answering of which loue is not the least of my earthly desires. As a true seale whereof, I send you this poore Paper-present, desiring your acceptance, as of the gift, so chiefely of the heart of the giuer. Good it may doe you, if God concurre with his grace and his spirit; weake meanes may worke Mortification, euen the Cockes crowing may awaken <hi>Peter:</hi> hurt it can doe none, vnlesse accidentally the fault be in your selues; euen as to some the Word it selfe and the Sacraments, with all holy things, are the sauour of death; euen as meates and medicines to a weake
<pb facs="9"/>
stomacke and distempered body, turne to diseases and Anguors, by reason of vicious humours.</p>
   <p>To giue you a fore-taste and relish of what you shall further finde in these vnited Treatises, the chiefe marke that I ayme at, is (after the patterne of two myrrours of men; the one, the Pronouncer of the Law, the other a Trumpe of the Gospell,) to teach you how to dye as well as willingly. A Lesson which the wisest amongst the Heathens, euen their Sages, Philosophers, and Gymnosophists; nay, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny learned Scribes, Disputants, and great Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies amongst Christians, eyther neuer knew pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecptorily, or forgot to pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ctise, as their Tragicall ends (some whereof I haue exemplified) doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate. A point taught onely in the Theorie, in the Schoole of Christ to his Disciples, his docible <hi>Simeons;</hi> wrought in the practicke part by his spirit▪ in the hearts of the Saints of Sion.</p>
   <p>Further, I haue let you see your owne faces in two examplary Glasses, what you ought to be, euen Gods Seruants, righteous with m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n, religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous with your God, that so your worke may receiue the reward, euen true beatitude, the soueraigne good. Labouring moreouer so to wash the foule spots and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>sions of your sinne-soyled soules, that you may appeare beautifull and gracious, as <hi>Hester</hi> to <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>s,</hi> when Death Gods Purseuant fetcheth you to stand before the King of Kings: being not defectiue, (at least in desire and endeauour) to lay before you the true exemplary forme and perfect model<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> how to liue holily, so to die happily.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="9"/>What I haue done further thousands will iudge, I neyther prayse nor disprayse mine owne doings, a Heathenish Master tels mee, <note n="a" place="margin">Aristotle apud Val. Max. lib. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
      </note> the one were vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the other folly: onely I may testifie thus much truely, that I haue not beene penurious in paynes. For, since I vndertooke this taske, in as many weekes as <hi>Virgils</hi> Poems yeeres, I haue polished it, as I could, (as the Beare her Whelps by licking) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vsing some Authors for this purpose, drinking deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at their Wels, where I thought the waters sweet, decking this for Gods Israell, with Aegiptian Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, euen some Heathenish Illustrations, as is lawfull and laudible in this kinde.</p>
   <p>For the manner of penning, you haue my good will, if not skill in cooking what is catered; if I adde sometimes sowre Sauce, let it relish the better with you, what is vntoothsome to a fleshly palate, will proue wholesome to a sound soule. For my words, I haue not beene very curious though cautelous, God and Nature haue administred them to my Pen, as to my Tongue, without martyring my selfe about them: if I haue erred, it is rather on the right hand then the left, in the excesse then defect, (as some haue taxed the one in <hi>Osorius;</hi> others, the other in <hi>Lipsius</hi>) rather chusing to flow and ouerflow (as <hi>Tully</hi> once did, before Athens brought him within his banckes) that I may be intelligible in expressing the notions of my soule, then with an affected concise Lipsian and Laconian breuitie to be obscure, as is said of <hi>Aristotle, Theophrastus</hi> and others, who for their stiles are said to write to torment their
<pb facs="10"/>
Readers; I haue laboured to giue a good garment, to a good body; to clothe a good subiect in words fitted, not affected.</p>
   <p>For the matter; you haue here not what Sathan shewed Christ, the World with her glory and her pompe: but a Map of mans Miserie, a Modell of his Mortalitie, of the Worlds Vanitie, Lifes Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie, so brittle, so briefe, so short, so certainely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine in his flitting, in its fading, that the Word intitles our life in this world, <hi>a Pilgrimage, Gen. 47.9. a Flower, Esa. 40.7. a Smoke, Psal. 102.3. a Weauers shittle, Iob 7.6. a House of clay, a Shepheards Tent, Iob 4.19. Esay 38.12. a Shadow Iob. 8.9. a Dreame, Iob 20.8. Vanitie,</hi> nay, <hi>Nothing, Psal. 39.5.</hi> All which points, with sundry moe, I haue according to my Talent, laid open at the full, with sundry incouragements, euery where inserted against such feares as the thoughts of these things naturally possesse men withall.</p>
   <p>It was my purpose also to haue added some com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, as against the feare of death naturall, so of death spirituall and eternall, in the corroberation of the weake Christian against Sathan, the wounds of Conscience, and terrours of his owne Soule: but the length of these Lines, already extended beyond their propounded limits, ioyned with weaknesse of body, cause me to omit or pretermit this, till some other occasion; where I shall, if it be requisit, reueale what I know in this practicall part of Diuinitie, in the meane space I referre you to draw cooling wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from those Springs of Israel, to whom the Lord
<pb facs="10"/>
hath giuen the tongue of the Learned, to speake a word to him that is weary, in due season; in perusing the Workes of the worthy <hi>Perkins,</hi> D. <hi>Sparkes, Espmes,</hi> good old <hi>Linakers Comforts for affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Consciences, Hughes Troubled mans Medicine, The Pensiues Practise,</hi> the <hi>Conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latory Letters</hi> of that zealous <hi>Greenham, D. Hil, Wilcox &amp;c. Ferrarius</hi> vpon <hi>51.</hi> Psalme; <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Knox</hi> vpon the <hi>6.</hi> Psalme, <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Downams Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Warfare, Luthers Consolations, The sicke mans Salue;</hi> chiefely, that best sixe-penny Manuel that I know in English <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Fremans Comforters, Wolcomb</hi> his <hi>Sinners salue;</hi> with all those that haue strengthened the soule directly against desperation. Besides, if you desire further satisfaction in any point, eyther positiue or contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall, concerning death naturally; in which these my poore paines doe not content you, the zealous &amp; learned Lucubrations of men of good parts and paines, offer themselues, as <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Perkins</hi> and <hi>Lup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Sutton,</hi> with <hi>D. Hill,</hi> by their printed Workes, as their titles are, will teach you how to die well; <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Draxe</hi> lends the sicke man a Guide, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Salue; <hi>S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Thomas Eliot</hi> lends a preserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue against Death,<note place="margin">Also see M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Vau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> and Mr. <hi>Tukes</hi> Bookes of the same subiect.</note>
      <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Bradford</hi> writes against the feare of Death, <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Caue</hi> out of French shewes how to remoue that feare; <hi>Wolcombe</hi> lends Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour against Deaths assaults, <hi>Erasmus</hi> shewes Deaths chances, <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Foxe</hi> exhorts the sicke: Deaths generall Proclamation is extant in Print, with his Trophies and Conquests. <hi>Couerdaile</hi> out
<pb facs="11"/>
of Dutch hath translated a Booke of Death. <hi>Ars moriendi,</hi> the Art of dying hath bin long extant<note n="*" place="margin">Printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1506</note>. Also, the learned know what not onely the Fathers, but Papists haue writ of this Argument, as <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus, Inclinus, &amp;c.</hi> as also some Germane Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants▪ as <hi>Bibembachius,</hi> and <hi>Brandmillerus</hi> in their Funerall Sermons, with others, both in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine and English; all which I haue seene, most of which, before, and vpon this occasion, read: and in many of them (omitting the principals) found small satisfaction, so that none by comparing mee with them shall finde me seruilely tyed to any of them, or taking any thing so verbally or by sentences from them, as it is not mine owne by method, digestion, and application. Neyther, I hope, will it be more blame-worthy in me, to write after these, then it was in <hi>Curtius</hi> to write the life of <hi>Alexander;</hi> in <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tista Egnatius</hi> to write the liues of Emperours; in <hi>Platina</hi> to write the liues of the Popes; after that seauenteen approued Authors had writ of the same subiect before the first; thirteene, before the second; and fifteene before the third, as a warrantable Writer reckons them <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Text<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>r</hi> in Epistola ante suam Officinam.</note>.</p>
   <p>And now hauing acquainted you what I haue done, how, and why, I send all vnto you▪ as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> sent his Seruant away with a blessing, euen such a one as I desire and intend. With which thought now the custome of all Epistlers cry it is time to conclude, least it be too tedious; yet beare I pray you with mine error of loue, which still extends my lines (being vncertain when or whether euer to
<pb facs="11"/>
see all your faces againe in earth, by reason of that mortalitie we speake of, or to speake to you by audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble voyce) to commend vnto you (as a departing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would, some things to his children, as dying <hi>Dauid</hi> did to suruiuing <hi>Salomon</hi>) onely these two things: first, that you would spend well the time of your short life▪ secondly, that you would prepare your selues for death. The first makes way to the second, (as the Needle for the Thread) the second for a third: euen a dignitie amongst liuing Angels, as Grace sits for Glory. First therefore, because the daies of your pilgrimage are as few as euill<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 47.9.</note>, as short as sinfull, that euen for that cause, as the Apostle counsels<note n="b" place="margin">Eph. 5.16</note>, you would redeeme the time: account of it (as not onely Christians, but euen the Heathens, <hi>Theophrastus, Seneca</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">De vitae breuitate, sic Epistola 1. ad <hi>Lucil.</hi>
      </note>, with others, haue pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed it) as the greatest treasure yea, aboue your patrimonies and inheritances, from which you will not suffer your selues to be disinherited. Beware the losse of it (as <hi>Lodouicke Blosius,</hi> and that mysti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call <hi>Thaulerus</hi> counsell amongst the rest of their documents) as of the most pestiferous poyson that is, knowing that one of the offences whereof those Remembrancers and Checquer Officers, your guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie consciences shall accuse you at the day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment shall be abuse of time. Nay, saith <hi>Bernard</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">Sermone ad Schol.</note>, as a haire of our heads shall not perish <note n="e" place="margin">Luke 21.18.</note>, so not a moment or minute of time, whereof wee are Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, without an account rendered. Doe not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore spend and misspend your short dayes that are allotted you for Gods seruice, and the working out
<pb facs="12"/>
your owne saluation, eyther in idlenesse, doing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <note n="f" place="margin">Nihil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendo, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, male a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendo. <hi>Seneca.</hi>
      </note>, or doing other things, or euill things: not in the pursuite of profit, the prosecution of pleasures; not in the seruice of the sinners Trinitie, the flesh, the world, the diuell; <hi>not in chambering &amp; wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonnes, not in surfetting &amp; drunkennes</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 12.13.</note>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not in heathenish lusts, cardings, dicings, and the like; not in frequenting soule-soyling Enterludes, Paganish Playes; not in the practise of gaming and prohibited playing<note n="h" place="margin">Prou. 21.17.</note>; nay, saith <hi>Chrisostome,</hi> not in prittle prattle, not it idle talking <note n="i" place="margin">Mat. 12.36.</note>, scurrulous ieasting, Satyricall gibing, vaine discoursing, witty quipping, foolish tales-telling, vnchristian backbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, carnall gossipping, sensuall company-keeping, profane taunting, counterfeiting gestures, Apish actings, light and lasciuious dauncings, making mowes, and such antique toyes, to make men merry: but in holy actions, proceeding from such mortified affections as shall declare you to be crucified to the world, and the world to you, that first happily you may dye to the world, that so hopefully you may dye out of the world. I vrge not these to take from you the vse of all recreations: I know (what <hi>Iob</hi> felt<note n="k" place="margin">Iob 6.12</note>) that your flesh is not brasse nor steele, but brittle and flexible: I know, that the spirit is willing, the flesh as weake<note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 26.41.</note>: I know, that as Birds and Beasts require rest, so man, without which no flesh is du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <note n="m" place="margin">Quod caret alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na requies durabile non est.</note>: I know, that rest is not sufficient without recreation, which caused all Nations to vse those <hi>Feriae,</hi> which wee turne into Feasts; which recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, not onely the best of Heathens, as <hi>Amasis,
<pb facs="12"/>
Socrates, Scaeuola, &amp;c.</hi> Nay, the strict Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, but euen the strictest Christians haue appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uedly vsed: I know, the Apostle approues of that <hi>Eutrapelia,</hi> or vrbanitie, which Philosophy makes a <note n="n" place="margin">
         <hi>Arist.</hi> in Eth.</note>vertue; nay, Christ himselfe who oft wept <note n="o" place="margin">Iohn 11.35 Luk. 19.41</note>, yet euen often lead his disciples with him into the fields, as though he should say, you are men, rest &amp; refresh you: neyther was I euer perswaded in iudgement or practise, but that the birds flying, dogs smelling, &amp;c. is not onely for mans profitable vse, but honest de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light: those limits being obserued, which iudicous Diuines <note n="p" place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> in <hi>Cases of Conscience. Dearing</hi> in Hebraeos, in initio. <hi>Aquinas.</hi> 22<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. q 168.</note> haue from the word prescribed. Yet for all this you must not abuse what you may lawfully vse; you must not turne Christian liberty into licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious carnalitie; you must not make of Recreations, occupations; you must not passe away the time in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stime, as is the foolish speech and wicked practise of fleshly minded men. To which men I say, with <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardine, De Sena,</hi> that if they once come to lodge in Hell, the place for impenitent profanenesse <note n="q" place="margin">Psal. 9.17</note>, if the trafficke of time should be carried thither to be sold, they would giue if they had a thousand worlds, for one halfe houre to repent in. Preuent you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time, lest afterwards you fruitlesly repent your neglected opportunities, like <hi>Diues</hi> in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable<note n="r" place="margin">Luke 16.24.</note>. Whilst you haue time doe good <note n="s" place="margin">Gal. 6.10</note> to others, to your owne soules; labour in the Ʋineyard, in that calling wherein you are planted and placed<note n="t" place="margin">Mat. 20.1.2.</note>; thinke that day lost (with the heathenish <hi>Cato</hi>
      <note n="v" place="margin">Plutarke.</note>, &amp; <hi>Titus Vespasian)</hi> in which you doe not some good; imploy your Talents gainefully, at least painefully<note n="x" place="margin">Lu. 19.13</note>; worke
<pb facs="13"/>
out your saluation in this day of saluation; do works acceptable in this acceptable time <note n="y" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.2</note>; worke whilst it is day, before the night come <note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 9.4.</note>; trafficke in the Mart-time, buy in the Fayre; hoist saile in the Tide-time; prepare corne in the plentious time; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with the Emmet <note n="b" place="margin">Pro. 6.6</note>, against a rainy day, hord vp in lifes summer what may bestead you in deaths winter; if with <hi>Bernard, Basil,</hi> and that holy <hi>Arse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">Dion. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus. in opu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sculo.</note>, you be not so strict to redeeme time, from sleepe and repast, and the ordinary workes of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet at least, like Christians, from words and workes which are vaine and vicious, knowing that onely that time is yours, which is spent righteously, and religiously, all the rest you are coosened of by Sathan, that is spent in the seruice of sinne, euen as <hi>Sauls</hi> reygne is onely reckoned two yeeres, because in those he onely reygned well <note n="d" place="margin">1 Sam. 13.</note>, as <hi>Simile,</hi> and that noble <note n="e" place="margin">Dion. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus.</note> Conuert accounted in his death, that he had liued onely seauen yeeres; and <hi>Barlaam</hi> in <hi>Damascene</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">Sustur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a de Barl c. <hi>18.</hi>
      </note>, that he had liued onely forty yeeres, though they both dyed old; because all their life before in sinne, was a death and no life, and so they prize it, so the Saints haue thought it <note n="g" place="margin">Hier. in Aggeum. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
      </note>.</p>
   <p>Now a word or two to prepare you for death, as <hi>Moses</hi> did the Israelites for their Passeouer: in which, for the first part of your preparation, I commend vnto you the frequent and serious medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Death, after the practise of Patriarkes, Prophets, Apostles, Christians and Pagans, whom you shall finde further exemplified in this Treatise, this thought will further your Repentance, strike
<pb facs="13"/>
at the roote of sinne, makes you with the Pylot that sits at the stearne, beare off from the shelues and rockes of many dangerous occasions; will cause you to vse your talents well, like that Seruant that fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his Masters comming <note n="h" place="margin">Luke 12.38.</note>. The Niniuites fast, and repent<note n="i" place="margin">Iohn 3.8.</note>; the Publicanes feare and quake<note n="k" place="margin">Luke 3 9.10.</note>, when <hi>Ionas</hi> cryes to the one, and <hi>Iohn</hi> to the other of their imminent end; <hi>Ahab</hi> is humbled <note n="l" place="margin">1 Kin 21 v. 19. v. 27.28.</note>, <hi>Felix</hi> trembles <note n="m" place="margin">Acts 24.26.</note>, the Captaine ouer fiftie fals downe and supplicates <note n="n" place="margin">2 Kin. 1.13.</note>, when from <hi>Elias</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> they heare and see the sentence of death and iudgement; this or nothing will draw your hearts out of the earth, if with Moales and Antes they be there wrooting: this will pull downe the lofty and Giant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lookes of Pride, quench the fire of Lust, curbe the ranckour of Malice, bridle the fiercenesse of Wrath, (euen as dust cast amongst angry Bees, makes them quiet,) mortifies many moe sinnes, kindles and keepes deuotion, as ashes keepes in fire. Therefore I counsell you to number your dayes <note n="o" place="margin">Psal. 90.12</note>, to remember your ends <note n="p" place="margin">Eccl. 1.40.</note>, to make your Sepulchers in your Gardens <note n="q" place="margin">Iohn 19.41</note>, to thinke of death in life, to strew Ashes with <hi>Daniel</hi>
      <note n="r" place="margin">In Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryph. Dan. c. 14.</note>, to discerne the steps of death, least it steale away your time, and the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of life inueigle your hearts, as <hi>Absolon</hi> did the hearts of his Fathers Subiects, least the euill day take you▪ as the snare the Bird, and the net the fish; least that be obiected to you which God once to Israel, that you remembred not your ends<note n="s" place="margin">Lam. 1.9.</note>.</p>
   <p>Other Rules I might prescribe, but that I may not make the gate too great for the Cittie, for
<pb facs="14"/>
some Cynicke to scoffe at: I referre you to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion of the Tractaite it selfe <note n="t" place="margin">See the last Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired Pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
      </note>. I will not giue Coleworts twise sod <note n="v" place="margin">Cramba bis cocta.</note>.</p>
   <p>Now, the last thing that I desire of you is, that you will reade without partialitie and preiudice. If there be any circumstantiall errours in Printing, as transposition, addition, or defects of some Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Syllables, or Words; not right placing of the Comma's, Colons, or full Points, or seeming de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, in not alwayes quoting the Chapter and Verse, to which I haue reference testimonially, or exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plarily, (which perhaps would haue stuft the Booke too full) or in any such circumstances, which my farre absence from the Presse might occasion: I pray you let your loues make the best constru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: if any thing be amisse that is mine owne; if ought here be good, that is the Lords, and his Grace in mee: to which good Grace commending you, and these my poore labours for you, I rest, as now, so euer,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the best bond STEVEN IEROME.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>