<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Wor∣shipful, Sir Richard Lea, Knight, all increase of true honour with God and men.</title>
           <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118419_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02513</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12642</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118419</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Wor∣shipful, Sir Richard Lea, Knight, all increase of true honour with God and men.</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The arte of diuine meditation : profitable for all Christians to knowe and practise; exemplified with a large meditation of eternall life. By Ioseph Hall</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <distributor>Cooke, Matthew</distributor>
                            <distributor>Macham, Samuel 1</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 193, 3 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipful, Sir</hi> Richard Lea, <hi>Knight, all increase of true honour with God and men.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, euer since I began to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow my selfe vpō the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mō good, studying wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my labours might bee most seruiceable; I still found they could bee no way so well improued, as
<pb facs="3"/>
in that part which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth deuotion, and the practise of true pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: For on the one side I perceiued the number of Polemicall bookes, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to breede, than ende strifes; and those which are doctrinall, by reason of their multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, rather to oppresse than satisfie the Reader; wherein if we write the same things, we are iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged tedious; if different, singular. On the other part respecting the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I sawe the braines of men neuer more stuffed,
<pb facs="3"/>
their tōgues neuer more stirring, their hearts ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer more emptie, nor their handes more idle. Wherefore after those suddē Meditatiōs which passed me without rule, I was easily induced by their successe (as a small thing moues the willing) to send foorth this Rule of Meditation; and after my Heauen vpon earth, to discourse (although by way of example) of heauen aboue. In this Arte of mine, I confesse to haue receiued more light from one obscure
<pb facs="4"/>
namelesse Monke which wrote some <hi>112.</hi> yeeres agoe, then from the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections of all other wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: I would his humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty had not made him nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardly of his name, that wee might haue knowen whome to haue thanked. It had been easie to haue framed it with more cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riositie: But God and my soule knowe, that I made profit the scope of my labour, and not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plause: and therefore (to choose) I wished ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be rude than vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable: If now the
<pb facs="4"/>
simplicitie of any Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, shall bereaue him of the benefite of my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, I knowe hee may make his vse of my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. Why I haue hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it with your name, I need not giue account to the world; which alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy knowes your worth and deserts, and shall see by this, that I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge them: Goe you on happily (according to the heauenly aduise of your <hi>Iunius)</hi> in your worthy and glorious profession; still bearing your selfe as one that knowes vertue
<pb facs="5"/>
the truest nobility, and Religion the best vertue: The God whom you serue shal honor you with men, and crowne you in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. To his grace I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly commend you: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questing you onely to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the worke, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue your fauour to the Author.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships humbly deuoted, IOS. HALL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>