<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Dedication]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118104_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14916</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25223</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118104</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Dedication]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ancient funerall monuments within the vnited monarchie of Great Britaine, Ireland, and the islands adiacent : with the dissolued monasteries therein contained: their founders, and what eminent persons haue beene in the same interred. As also the death and buriall of certain of the bloud royall; the nobilitie and gentrie of these kingdomes entombed in forraine nations. A worke reuiuing the dead memory of the royall progenie, the nobilitie, gentrie, and communaltie, of these his Maiesties dominions. Intermixed and illustrated with variety of historicall obseruations, annotations, and briefe notes, extracted out of approued authors infallible records, lieger books, charters, rolls, old manuscripts, and the collections of iudicious antiquaries. Whereunto is prefixed a discourse of funerall monuments. Of the foundation and fall of religious houses. Of religious orders. Of the ecclesiasticall estate of England. And of other occurrences touched vpon by the way, in the whole passage of these intended labours. Composed by the studie and trauels of Iohn Weeuer</title>
                 <author>Weever, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sadler, Laurence</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 871, 17 pages, 2 leaves of plates, illustrations, portraits, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Art and architecture</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>TO THE SACRED AND IMPERIALL MAIESTIE OF OVR DREAD SOVERAIGNE, THE MOST MAGNIFICENT, ILLVSTRIOVS, AND PVISSANT MONARCH, CHARLES: BY THE DIVINE PROVIDENCE, OF GREAT BRITAINE, FRANCE, IRELAND, AND MANY ILANDS, KING.</p>
   <p>THE MOST POWERFVLL PROTECTOR OF THE FAITH: THE MOST ROYALL PATRON, PRESERVER, AND FOSTERER OF THE VNDOVBTED RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIGION OF <hi>IESVS CHRIST.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>THE PATTERNE OF TRVE PIETIE, AND IVSTICE, AND THE PRESIDENT OF ALL PRINCELY VERTVES.</p>
   <p>HIS HIGHNESSE MOST LOWLY, AND MOST LOYALL SVBIECT IOHN WEEVER, IN ALL HVMILITY, CONSECRATETH THESE HIS LABOVRS: THOVGH FARRE VNWORTHY THE VIEW OF SO RESPLENDANT A GREATNESSE.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>