<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, THE LORD ROBERT DVDLEY, EARLE OF LEICESTER, BARON OF DENBIGH, KNIGHT OF THE MOST NO∣BLE ORDER OF THE GAR∣TER, OF HER MAIESTIIS most Honorable priuy Coun∣saile, &amp; Chauncelour of the Vniuersitie of Oxford: LAVRENCE HVMPHREY WISHETH GRACE, PEACE, AND MERCY FROM GOD THE FATHER &amp; OVR LORD IESVS CHRIST.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118809_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03851</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13966</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118809</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, THE LORD ROBERT DVDLEY, EARLE OF LEICESTER, BARON OF DENBIGH, KNIGHT OF THE MOST NO∣BLE ORDER OF THE GAR∣TER, OF HER MAIESTIIS most Honorable priuy Coun∣saile, &amp; Chauncelour of the Vniuersitie of Oxford: LAVRENCE HVMPHREY WISHETH GRACE, PEACE, AND MERCY FROM GOD THE FATHER &amp; OVR LORD IESVS CHRIST.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A view of the Romish hydra and monster, traison, against the Lords annointed: condemned by Dauid, I. Sam. 26. and nowe confuted in seuen sermons : to perswade obedience to princes, concord among our selues, and a generall reformation and repentaunce in all states: by L.H</title>
                 <author>Humphrey, Laurence</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <publisher>Barnes, Joseph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Cooke (Coke), Toby</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 192 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, THE LORD ROBERT DVDLEY, EARLE OF LEICESTER, <hi>BARON OF DENBIGH,</hi> KNIGHT OF THE MOST <hi>NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE ORDER OF THE GAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER,</hi> OF HER MAIESTIIS <hi>most Honorable priuy</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saile, &amp; Chauncelour of <hi>the Vniuersitie of</hi> Oxford: LAVRENCE HVMPHREY WISHETH <hi>GRACE, PEACE, AND</hi> MERCY FROM GOD THE <hi>FATHER &amp; OVR LORD</hi> IESVS CHRIST.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE are, Right honorable, as farre as I can iudge,<note place="margin">Two peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous poin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> of popery.</note> in the Romish Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on two principall parts, and peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie pointes, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Opinions, and outragious Actiōs: both drawen and borrowed from our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Aduersary: who one way soweth, in
<pb facs="3"/>darkens and in the night, among the wheat of gods word, the cockle &amp; darnel of perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious doctrine: the other way he murdreth them from the beginning,<note place="margin">Iohn 8. 1. Pet. 5.</note> and roareth like a Lyon, and in his continuall and cruell cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuite seeketh whom he may deuour: euerie way hunteth after blood, and our destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on spiritual and corporal. As Christ is hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and meek: as the cognisaunce of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians is loue: so the badge of Antichrist is bloody, ful of cruelty, voide of charity.</p>
   <p>To passe ouer the corruptions of doctrin, This second Monster of <hi>Rome,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hydra of Rome hath many heads</note> this <hi>Hydra</hi> is of many heades: These Actions of <hi>Popes</hi> are diuerse, both here seen and felt, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood abroad, and euery where practised. As <hi>Ashur</hi> was Gods rod, and <hi>Ʋespasian</hi> his seruāt against the <hi>Iews:</hi> so this reputed Vicar of Christ, hath been the whippe of Princes, the scourge of all Christendome. By his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion in Masse, he hath learned to offer an vnbloody sacrifice: In his Actions, he is <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat</hi> mingling sacrifices with mans blood.<note place="margin">Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 13.</note> By his opinion hee is guilty of that which is written:<note place="margin">Psal. 144.</note>
      <hi>His mouth speaketh lies:</hi> In his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of that which followeth, <hi>His right hande is the right hand of iniquity.</hi> But ô that al Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were of King <hi>Dauids</hi> mind, not to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, nor to communicate with such bloody
<pb facs="3"/>sacrifices,<note place="margin">Psal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> nor to haue these false cruel gods names in their lips.</p>
   <p>Although your Lordshippe knoweth his dooings in this realme better then I can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer: yet I purpose, by your good leaue and licence, to set down the proceedings of this <hi>Hydra,</hi> and his actions by degrees and steps for some Instruction, and a Caueat to my countrymen.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The first Act and head.</note>The first head of this Romish Monster is a Temporal sword, open defiaunce against kings and kingdomes, misliked by him: He wil be not onely a Bishop of Bishops, but a king, nay a Conquerour of kings: Hee hath in his hande the wheele of fortune to make kings goe vp, and goe downe, according to his pleasure, in driuing &amp; guiding the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot, and maketh them thus to say:
<q>Regno, regnabo, regnaui, sum sine regno.</q>
One saith: <hi>I doe raigne,</hi> another: <hi>I wil raigne,</hi> another: <hi>I haue raigned,</hi> another: <hi>I am put from my raigne.</hi> He maketh <hi>Apollo</hi> to giue ouer the chariot of the Sunne, and to resigne it to any rechles &amp; rash <hi>Phaeton,</hi> though he set on fier heauen and earth. Hee wil win the horse, or loose both horse and saddle. He can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that <hi>Dauid</hi> or any other godly Prince bee vnhorsed, and vnseated: and that wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton and rebellious <hi>Absalom</hi> bee placed and
<pb facs="4"/>setled. This bloodie action of warring is performed sometime in their owne person: as <hi>Iulius</hi> the second that fought against the French with <hi>Paules</hi> sword, and others both Popes and Cardinals may bee witnesses: sometime by inciting, and setting on other Princes against a Realme or Seignory. As <hi>Pippin</hi> &amp; <hi>Charles</hi> were imploied against the <hi>Lombardians</hi> by the commaundement of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Cau.</hi> 23. <hi>q.</hi> 8</note> And <hi>Gregory</hi> the great willeth the <hi>Tus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans</hi> to doe the like.<note place="margin">Thom. wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing. in Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ar: <hi>1.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Boniface</hi> by letters solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited the King of <hi>England</hi> against the <hi>French</hi> King, and promiseth aide. And another time Kings of <hi>Fraunce</hi> are set vp against <hi>England.</hi> Al these experimentes fal out in our time by a Catholick cōsent in the councel of <hi>Trent:</hi> that all Catholicke Princes should prepare against <hi>England,</hi> and others of the reformed religion. This cannot be good: for euen the <hi>Pope</hi> himselfe saith that it is not good.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Cau.</hi> 23 <hi>q.</hi> 8 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Tim. 2.</note>
      <hi>Pope Nicolas</hi> saith to <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Emperour: No man that is a souldior to God entangleth himselfe</hi>
      <q>
         <hi>with secular businesse.</hi> And if the souldiours of the woorlde apply themselues to warfare, what hath the Bishoppes and souldiours of Christ to doe, but to goe to their praiers?</q>
      <hi>Quid ad Episcopos &amp; milites Christi, nisi vt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent orationibus?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If this head of <hi>Hydra</hi> by Gods mightie &amp;
<pb facs="4"/>mercifull hand bee cut off, so that forreiners wil not, nor cānot satisfie the turn, &amp; his lust,<note place="margin">The <hi>2.</hi> head a trumpet of ciuil warre</note> beholde another head riseth, A Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Rebellion to al Catholickes against their dread Soueraigne, for he will set all at six and seuen, and mooue euery stone, he wil goe thorough thicke and thinne. Examples wee haue in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> with ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of ciuill dissension displaied to the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Almighty of God, to the distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of our publicke and godlie peace, &amp; to the vtter ouerthrowe of noble families.</p>
   <p>Yet, there is another heade springing as a supply to the rest, The spiritual sword, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication</hi> of Princes,<note place="margin">The <hi>3.</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cōmmunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> interdictment of Realmes, condemning all that bee not at his beck to the bottomlesse pit of hel. As <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niface</hi> the eighth excommunicated <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> because he would not honor &amp; worship him nor acknowledge him to be his Land Lord in the Kingdom of <hi>France.</hi> In this action, he curseth and banneth, hee ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solueth and blesseth, and yet this absolution is not woorth a straw, nor his curse more to be feared of a wise King, then the noise of a tumbrel or a rattle, as that Noble Prince of <hi>Orenge</hi> did wel account, and boldly protest.<note place="margin">Jn Apolog.</note>
   </p>
   <p>Besides these,<note place="margin">
         <hi>4.</hi> Deposing of Princes.</note> another cruell Buls heade groweth out, forthwith by a Bull to depose,
<pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>ex officio &amp; pro imperio, a Christian Prince.</hi> So it pleased <hi>Pope Zachary</hi> to throwe out King <hi>Childerick</hi> and <hi>Pope Gregory</hi> the fourth, King <hi>Ludowick:<note place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>ug. Steuc. contra Vall.</note> Pope Pius</hi> the Queenes Maiesty, releasing the people from al bands of loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and subiection, with a full licence of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion: but this was but a word, no blow.</p>
   <p>God sometime giueth that spirite to Prince and people, that these proceedings take no place: then an other heade starteth vp,<note place="margin">
         <hi>5.</hi> Priuie practises.</note>
      <hi>Priuie murdering,</hi> authorised as lawefull by this Antichristian Prelate. Secretlie and subtillie this Popishe <hi>Hydra</hi> woorketh with poison, with pistol, with gunne, with sword, with tooles of Death, all framed in the shoppe of the lame Smithe <hi>Vulcan,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Vasa mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ia.</note> nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the fornace of the Diuel, as the <hi>Mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sacres</hi> and murders of manie Honorable, &amp; worthie men in manie places do testifie: In fraunce the murder of Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> after he was taken prisoner, contrarie to the law of armes: of the Admiral <hi>Chatellion</hi> shot thorowe in the streats and murdered in his chamber: of <hi>Dandalot:</hi> of <hi>Ramus</hi> after he had giuen a certain summe of crowns to saue his life: of <hi>Marlorate</hi> walking in his gardē: of an other preacher killed in the pulpit: In <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande</hi> the murder of the King: of the Lorde Iames: of the Lord <hi>Russell:</hi> In the lowe
<pb facs="5"/>cuntries the murder of the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orenge,</hi> who first was perscribed, and proclaimed a Traitor and an hereticke, with this large promise, that whosoeuer could bring him quicke or dead, or kill him,<note place="margin">In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> should haue fiue and twentie thousand crowns in money or land. And if he were meanly borne he, shoulde be made a gentleman, and if he had committed any faulte, neuer so heynous, he should be pardoned. These be horse-lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches that drawe bloude,<note place="margin">Prou. 30.</note> and haue neuer enough.</p>
   <p>Al these actions haue been here attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: in these steppes hath this Monster wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked among vs: which all sauour of violence, oppression, murdering of the Lordes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, and of his Saints. The reason of this Action is set downe by <hi>August. Steuchus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Contr. La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Vall.</note> descending from the roote of an erronious opinion: <hi>Contra Haereticos opus est fustibus, non Anathematis, quae contemnunt.</hi> The Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks contemne the Popes curses, they must be beaten downe with clubbes.</p>
   <p>To accomplish these fierce,<note place="margin">
         <hi>6.</hi> Heade <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>f craft and peri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap>, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal of the rest.</note> and forcible actions, there is ioined another craftie head of this monster, and now lately and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally by <hi>Iesuits,</hi> hauing Commission from <hi>Rome</hi> to teach periury, and disobedience to Princes, to promise faire, to performe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb facs="6"/>to dispraise the state, to magnify the Pope, to tell the subiects in their eare a tale of a tub, of a Catholicke Church, and a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick faith, of pardons by their <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> masses, Confessions, and of many other goodly bables, of saluation by their traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of damnation by our religion, which is nothing, but lying, cogging, and deceiuing the simple. This quality and counterfaite Religion hath bin told before in an exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to <hi>Princes: It is most euident, that there is no part of the Christian woorlde,</hi>
      <note place="margin">In fas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ic. rer. expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ēdar. cōtra decimas.</note>
      <hi>which hath not bene craftily tempted by these kind of Monsters: &amp; that many Kings and Princes haue been frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulently circumuented by them.</hi> And againe: <hi>They know how to deceiue notably, to circumuent, to forswear, to forge testaments, to prophane diuine and humane thinges, to make strife, to trouble the quiet, to confoūd heauen with earth.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>There is yet to make vp 7 deadly sins, the seuenth head, a Magical head,<note place="margin">The <hi>7.</hi> the heade of witchcraft.</note> woorking by witchcraft &amp; sorcery: for as he wil cōsecrat, so hee can inchaunt, as blesse, so poison the creatures of God for the dispatch of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,<note place="margin">Alphonsus a learned Prince.</note> but God is aboue Belzebub. <hi>Alphonsus,</hi> whē his enemy <hi>Cosmas</hi> a <hi>Florentine</hi> sent him for a present the books of <hi>Titus Liuius,</hi> and his Phisition counsailed him not to handle them, as sent from an enemy, for fear of poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
<pb facs="6"/>or infection: Doe you not know (saith he) that the souls and liues of kings are not subiect to the will of priuate men,<note place="margin">Aeneas syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de dictis Alpho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> but safe and secure vnder the prouidence and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of god? <hi>Cor &amp; corpus Regis in manu Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Prou. 21.</note> The heart and the body of a king is in the hand of the Lord.</p>
   <p>These and such like heady actions are in this realme continually practised: which may witnesse to the world what monstrous religion the <hi>Pope</hi> bringeth and brocheth to vs. No maruel if the first part be naught, and his faith corrupt, sith the second, his fruites and actions be so abhominable.<note place="margin">The Pope is like Martiall Marius.</note>
      <hi>Marius the great Captaine of Rome was woont to saie: That he could not hear the voice of Lawes, among the peales of gunnes, the noise of drumslats, and sound of trumpets.</hi> The <hi>Pope,</hi> that is so busie, so occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied in bloody and <hi>Martiall</hi> matters and cōspiracies, hath no leisure to study or hear or preach the Law of God, or to aduaunce the Gospel of Peace in Christ Iesus.</p>
   <p>I haue, Right Honorable, entred into the consideration &amp; confutation of both these parts of popery in other books: but now se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing daily the present &amp; perilous practises of the later, both here &amp; elswher: setting aside for the time the first concerning the <hi>Pope</hi> &amp; his Iesuitical doctrin, I haue lately trauailed
<pb facs="7"/>somewhat in the second, opening to my countrimen their frontick and bloody dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and calling them by al meanes of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suasion, as I could, to conformity and due o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the Prince, and to the loue of their owne country, for the common safety and preseruation of vs all, in body and soul. Alas, who would haue thought that there should haue beene any need to haue either spoken or written of this matter to English Subiects, liuing so long vnder a gratious, &amp; peaceable gouernement: farre passing the times past, and the like not to be hoped for after it? Who would haue thought that any Englishe and Christian man woulde haue once muttered or murmured against such a Prince? for countries sake to bee loued, for religion to be obeied, for sundry graces and gifts to bee woondred at, for all these good blessings of God by hir to vs, to be honored? Are there yet foolish frogs, begging of the <hi>Romish Capitoline Iupiter</hi> either a blocke to crush them, or a Storcke to deuoure them? Though by Gods appointment the Oliue is content to be ouer vs with her fatnes, &amp; the fig with her sweetenesse, and the vine with her fruitfulnesse: yet wee are not content to haue them, but only <hi>Rhamnus,</hi> or a bramble good for nothing but to burn and consume
<pb facs="7"/>vs.<note place="margin">English Iewes.</note> Are there yet remaining the Offpring of <hi>Iewes,</hi> desiring a <hi>Saul</hi> for a <hi>Samuel?</hi> Professing &amp; protesting, <hi>Nolumus hunc regnare,</hi> We wil not haue him raign ouer vs? &amp; that cannot abide the title of <hi>Christs crosse, Iesus of Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, King of Iewes?</hi> Or can there be found yet an <hi>Esau,</hi> that will say in his heart,<note place="margin">Gen. 27.</note>
      <hi>The daies of mourning for my father will come shortlie: then wil I slaie my brother Iacob?</hi> I will make awaie with the mother of the Lande, and the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brethren too? And must wee after the inuention, yea the fruition of wheate, and sweet corne, returne with the old world, <hi>ad glandes,</hi> to Akornes: as in the late time of Queene <hi>Marie?</hi> The Religion published by her Maiesty offendeth them: And can this Romish Religion being so stained with bloode, as I haue declared, please them? Is there no remedy, but to turn the blessing of the Prophet <hi>Esay,</hi> by a contrary Text into a curse?<note place="margin">Esa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>.</note> For our gould, to receiue brasse: For our siluer, iron: and for this gouernement of peace, the tyranny of Exactours and Task<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>masters?</p>
   <p>For remedy, and some redresse against these bloud-suckers of <hi>Rome,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing.</note> and our rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious mutiners at home, I haue eft soones called to the memorie of our countrimen, their duety towards God and their Prince,
<pb facs="8"/>and Country, and then doubtlesse God wil be a Buckler, and shielde to them and to vs all.</p>
   <p>In this copulatiue,<note place="margin">An exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to a true vnity.</note> in this double dutiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes towards God &amp; the Prince, we must be ioined with a full consent altogether, as one man, or as the twinnes of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> who were sicke together, and hadde their fits together, and recouered together, as <hi>Austine</hi> reciteth out of <hi>Cicero:</hi> So we, head and foote,<note place="margin">De ciuit. Dei lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
      </note> and al the body must consent in the true worship and seruice of God: we al, high and low, with hart &amp; hand must agree in this duety towarde the Prince against all forreine or domesticall aduersaries. These two dueties are recommēded to vs by <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brose. This becommeth Christians to wish for the tranquillity of peace,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ambrose Epist. <hi>33.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>and for the constancy in the faith and in the truth.</hi> And in the same place: <hi>Rogamus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note>
      <hi>Auguste, non pugnamus,</hi> We beseech O Emperour, we fight not.</p>
   <p>If wee deale thus duetifully towardes God, and obediently towardes our Prince, then will God mercifully and mightily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend both Prince and vs. No diuelish witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, no Ruffians dag or dagger, no inuasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of forreiners, no craft or art of any ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, no nor this seuen-headed beast shall annoy Prince, Peare, or People. He can, he
<pb facs="8"/>will send twelue legions of Angels.<note place="margin">Matth. <hi>26.</hi> Pohd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>h. <hi>8.</hi> Hist. Ang.</note> Then shalbe truly verified that which long a go was prophecied: <hi>The Kingdome of Englande, shalbe the Kingdome of God:</hi> and that God is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, &amp; must be the Protector &amp; King of it. If our Prince and Nobles, and Subiects wil sincerely serue him: we shall haue the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of our lord,<note place="margin">
         <hi>1.5.</hi> in ora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. cont. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>Seruum Christi non custo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia Corporalis, sed Domini prouidentia sepire consueuit,</hi> saith <hi>Ambrose.</hi> No guard of men or bodies, but the prouidence of the Lord is the hedge and defence of the seruants of <hi>Christ.</hi> It may be for our sinnes, that the great ships of <hi>Tharshis</hi> may come:<note place="margin">Ies. 2.</note> but vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon our repētance,<note place="margin">De <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neide so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Remora, Pl. l. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi>
      </note> God wil send <hi>Remoram</hi> euen a litle fishe that shall stay the shippes though vnder saile. It may bee, that some Load stone may drawe some Iron vpon vs, but the Lord will prepare a Diamond that shal with stand the Load-stone,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>13.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
      </note> that it shall not haue power to drawe any at all. It may be that <hi>Catiline</hi> wil make a coniuration, but god wil send one <hi>Cicero</hi> or other to espy it &amp; ouerthrow it. Al the Traitors against <hi>Iulius Caesar</hi> within three years perished,<note place="margin">Sue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>on in Julio Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sare.</note> som one way, some an other way, some by Iudgmēt, some with shippe wracke, some in battell, others with the same poinadoe, wherewith <hi>Caesar</hi> was stricken, none of them had a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall
<pb facs="9"/>death. <hi>Calippus,</hi> because he would stab in and sticke <hi>Dion</hi> his friend, was stabbed, and killed with the same dagger himselfe by his owne frinds. This shalbe the reward of al those that conspire against the Lordes annointed.</p>
   <p>I haue troubled your honour with many words, vttering my wishes to my countri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and declaring to you the argument intreated of in these Sermons. I haue dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaied the new Monster lately receiued, &amp; daily rising and raging against vs. And as in this generall diuision of <hi>Christendom,</hi> euery nation and faction prouide their Armour: And as your L. and the whole body of the right honorable Counsel make euery way a politick preparation, and euery man see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his piece, &amp; his furniture: So I, hauing no weapon, but only my tongue and pen, haue thought good in my calling, after my weak &amp; simple sort, to fight with the helpe of them both, against this huge Monster, and against all enimies. When I beganne first to expound this Text of Scripture in Ianuarie last, at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and proceeded in it there and in some places of <hi>Hamptonshire,</hi> &amp; ended it at <hi>London,</hi> at the Crosse in May: I little thought of printing it: and so the matter out of my heade, and almost out
<pb facs="9"/>of my papers, I fear my short, and vnperfect notes haue brought foorth an vnperfect, &amp; vntimely fruit. Howesoeuer it is, I must commit it now to the world, and appeale to your Lordships patronage for it. I had rather offend by this temerity and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, than to incurre the suspicion of silence and neutrality, knowing the danger and penalty of <hi>Solons</hi> lawe, if in this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon trouble;<note place="margin">Plutarc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap> Solone.</note> and turmoile I should shewe my selfe to be idle and of no part.</p>
   <p>I am bold to offer to your Lordship as a poore scholasticall New-yeares-gift, &amp; as a gratulation of your prosperous returne, and as a smal signification of my bounden duty to you, my very good Lord, and a speciall Patrone of our Vniuersity, and a friend of this cause which <hi>Dauid</hi> began, and I haue rudely prosecuted and ended. The Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus protect our noble <hi>Dauid,</hi> your honor, the honorable Counsaile, &amp; the whole Realm, &amp; graunt vnto vs all many good new-years, to his glory, and to the commodity &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of his Church, <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Oxon.</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>Decemb.</hi> 28.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>