<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>IN PRAISE OF THE Author Maister Thomas Coriat.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118544_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19381</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5809</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118544</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>IN PRAISE OF THE Author Maister Thomas Coriat.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Mr Thomas Coriat to his friends in England sendeth greeting : from Agra the capitall city of the dominion of the great Mogoll in the Easterne India, the last of October, 1616. Thy trauels and thy glory to ennamell, with fame we mount thee on the lofty cammell</title>
                 <author>Coryate, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>52 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>IN PRAISE OF THE Author Maister <hi>Thomas Coriat.</hi>
   </head>
   <lg>
      <l>THou that the world with pleasures full hast pleasur'd,</l>
      <l>And out of measure many kingdomes measur'd.</l>
      <l>Whil'st men (like swine) doe in their vices wallow,</l>
      <l>And not one dares for's eares thy steps to follow:</l>
      <l>Not one within the Compasse of the Cope,</l>
      <l>Like thee that dar'st suruay the Horoscope:</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="5"/>
For who is he that dares call it a lye,</l>
      <l>That thou hast trotted into Italie;</l>
      <l>By th'edge of <hi>France,</hi> and skirts of <hi>Spaine</hi> th'hast rambled,</l>
      <l>Through <hi>Belgia</hi> and through <hi>Germany</hi> th'ast ambled.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>And,</hi> Denmarke, Sweden, Norway, Austria,</l>
      <l>Pruce, Poland, Hungarie, Muscouia,</l>
      <l>With <hi>Thracia,</hi> and the land of merry <hi>Greekes,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>All these and more applaud thee, that who seekes</l>
      <l>Vpon the top of Mount <hi>Olimpus</hi> front,</l>
      <l>Perhaps may see thy name insculp'd vpon't,</l>
      <l>And he that durst detract thy worthin <hi>Europe,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>I wish he may be hang'd vp in a new rope.</l>
      <l>It were a world of businesse to repeat</l>
      <l>Thy walkes through both the <hi>Asiaes,</hi> lesse and great,</l>
      <l>Whereas (no doubt) but thou hast tane suruay</l>
      <l>Of <hi>China</hi> and the kingdome of <hi>Catay.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="5"/>
Th' East Indies, Persia, Parthia, Media,</l>
      <l>Armenia, and the great Ass-iria,</l>
      <l>Caldea, Iurie, (if we not mistake vs)</l>
      <l>Thou hast or'e look'd the Sea call'd Mortuus Lacus.</l>
      <l>And I durst venter somewhat for a wager</l>
      <l>Thou hast seene Ionia, Lidia, Misia Maior,</l>
      <l>Old Iliums Ruins, and the wracks of <hi>Priam,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>But of Inuention I (alas) so dry am,</l>
      <l>I beate my braines, and with outragious thumping,</l>
      <l>My lines fall from my pen with extreame pumping.</l>
      <l>Auaunt dull <hi>Morpheus,</hi> with thy Leaden spirit,</l>
      <l>Can matter want of him that wants no merit?</l>
      <l>As he through <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Arabia's</hi> coasting,</l>
      <l>My lines from <hi>Asia</hi> into <hi>Africke</hi> poasting,</l>
      <l>I'le follow him alongst the Riuer <hi>Nilus,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>In <hi>Egypt,</hi> where false Crocodiles beguile vs.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="6"/>
Through <hi>Mauritania</hi> to the Towne of <hi>Dido,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>That slew her selfe by power of god <hi>Cupido.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>The Kingdomes vnsuruai'd hee'le not leaue one</l>
      <l>
         <hi>From</hi> Zona<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> oride, <hi>to the</hi> Frozen Zone.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>With</hi> Prester Iohn <hi>in</hi> Aethiopia</l>
      <l>And th'ayrie Empire of <hi>Eutopia.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>