<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE GREAT ORNAMENT OF HER SEX, AND NAME, MISTRIS ANNE PORTMAN, &amp;c. THE accumulation of Honours, here, and of Glory, in future.</title>
           <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118064_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13269</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23570</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118064</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE GREAT ORNAMENT OF HER SEX, AND NAME, MISTRIS ANNE PORTMAN, &amp;c. THE accumulation of Honours, here, and of Glory, in future.</title>
                 <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The rich mans vvarning-peece : A sermon, vpon occasion, formerly preached, and now published, by the author, Humfrey Sydenham, late fellow of Wadham Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 38 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE GREAT ORNAMENT OF HER SEX, AND NAME, MISTRIS ANNE PORTMAN, &amp;c. THE accumulation of <hi>Honours, here,</hi> and of <hi>Glory,</hi> in future.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>My worthiest,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat you formerlie vouchsafed to peruse in a rude <hi>transcript;</hi> J here present you in a character, like your selfe, and vertues, <hi>faire, and legible;</hi> J thinke it my <hi>prime honour,</hi> that it must now weare your <hi>liuery,</hi> and what shall immortall it, your <hi>name;</hi> Had it nothing else to make it liue in the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb facs="3"/>and esteeme of others, <hi>this</hi> were enough to giue it both <hi>countenance,</hi> and <hi>eternity;</hi> Greatnesse can onely patronize our endeauours, Goodnesse glorifies them. Vnder that stampe and seale of yours J haue aduentured it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, that you might know my respects are the <hi>same</hi> in publike, which they were, lately, vnder a priuate, though noble roofe; J neuer yet whispered an obseruance, but J dar'd proclaime it to the world, and then, too, when there might be some pretence and colour to suspect my loyalty; where I am engag'd once in my seruices, and professe them, J am not beaten off by the causelesse distastes of those J honour; you J euer did, and the <hi>name</hi> you beautifie; on which, though I am no longer an <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendant,</hi> J am still a <hi>votary,</hi> and such
<pb facs="3"/>a one, whose <hi>knee</hi> speakes as loude for it, as his <hi>tongue;</hi> his deuotions, as his thanks; and both these from a heart swept so cleane of deceit, or falsehood, that could it lodge so much <hi>sophistrie</hi> as to teach the <hi>lips</hi> to quauer, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble, J had not been thus (perhaps) vnder the furrowes of a displeased brow, but might haue prooued as faire in the smile and cringe of many, as J am now <hi>downe the winde,</hi> both in their <hi>countenance,</hi> and <hi>opinion.</hi> But, <hi>sinceritie</hi> is the <hi>same,</hi> still, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in <hi>exile,</hi> or <hi>aduancement,</hi> in dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, or honour; wheresoeuer I trauell J carry <hi>my selfe</hi> with me; I am not torne into <hi>distractions,</hi> and <hi>feares,</hi> not parcelled (as others) into <hi>doubtes,</hi> and <hi>hopes;</hi> but, where J am, J am in the <hi>whole man;</hi> and, where J am, <hi>so,</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>I am <hi>All</hi> yours; <hi>All</hi> in my <hi>morall, ciuill,</hi> and <hi>diuine</hi> obseruances, one that will <hi>thanke</hi> you, <hi>honour</hi> you, and <hi>pray</hi> for you, vnfainedly, willingly, constantly, whilest I am thought wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the <hi>name,</hi> or <hi>attribute</hi> of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your most humbly-deuoted</hi> Humfry Sydenham.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>