<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118284_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01881</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12021</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118284</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The creatures praysing God: or, The religion of dumbe creatures : An example and argument for the stirring vp of our deuotion and for the confusion of atheisme. Benedicite omnia opera Domini Domino; laudate &amp; superexaltate eum in secula. G.G</title>
                 <author>Goodman, Godfrey</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 34, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Reader, The Authour himselfe not vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safing his name, title, or preface to this his worke, and very vnwilling that it should be publisht, I thought fit to let thee vnderstand, that the booke it selfe containes no paradox, notwithstanding the title: for the naturall seruice of God in dumbe Creatures, when they obey God, in their owne kinde, and follow their owne naturall course, this is it, which he calls <hi>The Religion of dumbe Creatures</hi>: and as it is frequent, and vsuall, to make compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons in particular instances, so here in generall their seruice is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to our Religion.</p>
   <p>To commend the worke, seeing I am so farre ingaged, as that against the Authors will, it was my importunity to publish it, were in effect to commend mine owne iudgement, I will here onely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you with the reasons that moued me;</p>
   <p>First, to take away grose Atheisme, which denies any God, he vseth no Sophistry, no perswasion, not the testimonies either of God, or of men, but herein craues aide of the dumbe Creatures, and in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect desires them to beare witnesse, who instantly acknowledge a God, and discouer many excellent, and admirable attributes in God, and this he calls their confession, or the naturall implicite faith of the Creatures, <hi>pag.</hi> 9.</p>
   <p>Secondly, that this knowledge of God, which we learne from na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is an imperfect knowledge, though otherwise, it was the sole knowledge of the ancient heathen Philosophers, he brands it with this imputation, that it is no more in effect then the religion of dumbe beasts; but as reason is aboue sence, so faith aboue reason: rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son points out mysteries, faith discouers them; by vertue of which faith, we ioyne with the Angels in their seruice, as the dumbe beasts doe ioyne with vs in nature: and here he takes away all naturall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections against the mysteries of religion, beating downe mans cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riosity, <hi>pag.</hi> 16.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, how the Creatures praise God in their voices and sounds, which in effect are their prayers; in their naturall law, which is their decalogue; in all their qualities and affections, both naturall, and as they are sometimes meanes and conduit-pipes of grace, whereby nature is sanctified, <hi>pag.</hi> 23.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, how all naturall Sciences may be reduced to Theology,
<pb facs="3"/>
suppose the Metaphysicks, naturall Philosophy, morall Philosophy, which are indeed the branches of naturall Theology and are incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated into the body of our diuinity. And hence you may as well exclude the morall law, the decalogue, and the whole state of nature, as to exclude humane learning; which showing the perfections and excellencies of nature, doth therein show the praise and commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Maker. <hi>pag.</hi> 31.</p>
   <p>Fifthly, this naturall religion not only comprehends in it selfe all naturall sciences, but it is further a supposed ground and foundation in all religions. Thus Iudaisme, <gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="2 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, as well as Christianity, acknowledge God in nature; though the Iudiciall, and Ceremoniall law began with <hi>Moyses,</hi> the Gospell with Christ, yet the naturall law, together with the state of nature, began with <hi>Adam,</hi> not by any reuelation, but by ingrafted and inbred principles, and therefore is common to all nations, to all religions. Hence he ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers these two notes, first, that different and opposite religions may notwithstanding ioyne together in such things as are good, and alike approueable in both: for so we ioyne with dumbe Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in their naturall seruice, and that the bounds of the Church are not to be hedged in, according to mens priuate phansies and imaginations; or according to the Prouinces, and iurisdiction of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats, but according to the vnity and concent of faith. Secondly, that be the religions neuer so opposite and contrary, yet all agree in the naturall law, and therefore are bound to performe to each other, all naturall rights, suppose the discharging of trust, where it is reposed, to vse morall honesty in our actions, obedience to our superiours, allegiance to the Prince, and the like; thus may different religions liue quietly and peaceably vnder one iust gouernment. If this were obserued, surely it would cause much peace in the Christian world, so much distracted and disquieted at this day, with infinit and innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable sects and religions, <hi>pag.</hi> 34.</p>
   <p>To conclude: What can be more glorious to God, then that his praise should be set forth by all his Creatures? what greater chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, then to comprehend them, not within the walls of our Christian Church (though once they were contained in the Arke) yet within the compasse and circuit of religion? what greater deuotion, then by their example to stirre vp thy selfe? though the Angels be out of sight, and thou canst not heare their hymnes, yet the beasts may awaken thy dulnesse; what greater humility, then to stoope to the basest wormes, and together with them, to associate thy selfe in Gods seruice?</p>
   <p>These reasons (I confesse) did moue me to publish it: and as I had no other intent, but Gods glory, so I beseech him to giue a blessing to thy reading hereof, that it may tend to the increase of thy deuotion.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>