<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118636_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18885</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5318</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118636</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Scipio's dreame. Or The statesman's extasie : Wherein is contayned an epitomie of all the sciences, naturall, morall, and supernaturall. Tending to proue the immortalitie of the soule, as the proper merit of iustice</title>
                 <author>Cicero, Marcus Tullius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Chapman, Laurence</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 30 pages, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Classical authors</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>OVRTEOVS READER;</hi> Hee that doth not ayme at the highest pitch of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, can neuer attayne to the lowest degree there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; which gaue mee incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, though yet but in the Infancy of the <hi>Muses</hi> to vndertake this taske, which howsoeuer my paines proue accepted of, yet I am confident, for the worth of the first Writer, it will find fauorers. And though it come not apparelled with the Maiesty of a Courtly robe, yet I hope it hath an honest Countrey comeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And my desire to communicate it to such as knew it not in the Naturall and Nationall habit thereof, will gaine a fauourable constru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that it commeth in our English attire, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the matter thereof is for all men, for all times, full of compleat and eminent know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge:
<pb facs="4"/> and the rather because this, amongst many of that Noble and wise mans workes hath not come to light in our language, for ought I euer knew, yet is it of merit in the first place, and especially when many men now a dayes do sleepe out their dayes not dreaming of the reward in the Life immortall, which the wise Heathen did propound to themselues as incitements to graue republiquists to take care, <hi>Nequid detrimenti, respublica capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at.</hi> And it may moue some more lofty tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring spirit to lend his tongue in a straine more lofty. And because great matters cannot bee expected from blooming yeares, my duty shall be discharged, if my diligence be not scorned; For <hi>Non debent, qui magna prestare ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queunt, parua negligere.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>