<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>

What I WAS, is passed by,
What I AM, away doth flie;
What I SHAL BEE, none do see;
Yet, in that, my Beauties bee.
The AVTHORS Meditation upon sight of his PICTVRE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118583_Fr2_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15631</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25900a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118583</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>

What I WAS, is passed by,
What I AM, away doth flie;
What I SHAL BEE, none do see;
Yet, in that, my Beauties bee.
The AVTHORS Meditation upon sight of his PICTVRE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A collection of emblemes, ancient and moderne : quickened vvith metricall illustrations, both morall and divine: and disposed into lotteries, that instruction, and good counsell, may bee furthered by an honest and pleasant recreation. By George VVither. The first booke</title>
                 <author>Wither, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Grismand (Grismond), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Grismand (Grismond), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 62, 6, 63-124, 6, 135-196, 6, 209-270, 10 pages, illustrations (engravings, woodcut), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>
      <figure>
</figure>
      <l>What I <hi>WAS,</hi> is passed by,</l>
      <l>What I <hi>AM,</hi> away doth flie;</l>
      <l>What I <hi>SHAL BEE,</hi> none do see;</l>
      <l>Yet, in <hi>that,</hi> my <hi>Beauties</hi> bee.</l>
The AVTHORS Meditation upon sight of his PICTVRE.</head>
   <l>VVHen I behold my <hi>Picture,</hi> and perceive,</l>
   <l>How vaine it is, our <hi>Portraitures</hi> to leave</l>
   <l>In <hi>Lines,</hi> and <hi>Shadowes,</hi> (which make shewes, to day,</l>
   <l>Of that which will, to morrow, fade away)</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="7"/>And, thinke, what meane <hi>Resemblances</hi> at best,</l>
   <l>Are by <hi>Mechanike Instruments</hi> exprest;</l>
   <l>I thought it better, much, to leave behind me,</l>
   <l>Some <hi>Draught,</hi> in which, my living friends might find me</l>
   <l>The same I <hi>am;</hi> in <hi>that,</hi> which will remaine,</l>
   <l>Till all is ruin'd, and repair'd againe:</l>
   <l>And, which, in absence, will more truely show me,</l>
   <l>Than, <hi>outward Formes,</hi> to those, who think they know me.</l>
   <l>For, though my gratious <hi>MAKER</hi> made me such,</l>
   <l>That, where I love, belov'd I am, as much</l>
   <l>As J desire; yet, <hi>Forme,</hi> nor <hi>Features</hi> are,</l>
   <l>Those <hi>Ornaments,</hi> in which J would appeare</l>
   <l>To <hi>future Times;</hi> Though they were found in me,</l>
   <l>Farre better, than I can beleeve they be.</l>
   <l>Much lesse, affect I <hi>that,</hi> which each man knowes,</l>
   <l>To be no more, but Counterfeits of those,</l>
   <l>Wherein, the <hi>Painters,</hi> or the <hi>Gravers</hi> toole,</l>
   <l>Befriends alike, the <hi>Wiseman,</hi> and the <hi>Foole:</hi>
   </l>
   <l>And, (when they please) can give him, by their <hi>Art,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>The <hi>fairest-Face,</hi> that had the <hi>falsest-Heart.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>A <hi>PICTVRE,</hi> though with most exactnesse made,</l>
   <l>Is nothing, but the <hi>Shadow</hi> of a <hi>SHADE.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>For, ev'n our <hi>living Bodies,</hi> (though they seeme</l>
   <l>To others more, or more in our esteeme)</l>
   <l>Are but the <hi>shadowes</hi> of that <hi>Reall-being,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Which doth extend beyond the <hi>Fleshly-seeing;</hi>
   </l>
   <l>And, cannot be discerned, till we rise</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Immortall-Objects,</hi> for <hi>Immortall-eyes.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Our <hi>Everlasting-Substance</hi> lies unseene,</l>
   <l>Behinde the Fouldings, of a <hi>Carnall-Screene,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Which is, but, <hi>Vapours</hi> thickned into <hi>Blood,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>(By due concoction of our daily food)</l>
   <l>And, still supplied, out of other <hi>Creatures,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>To keepe us <hi>living,</hi> by their wasted natures:</l>
   <l>Renewing, and decaying, ev'ry Day,</l>
   <l>Vntill that <hi>Vaile</hi> must be remov'd away.</l>
   <l>For, this lov'd <hi>Flesh,</hi> wherewith, yet cloth'd we go,</l>
   <l>Is not the same, wee had sev'n yeares ago;</l>
   <l>But, rather, something which is taken-in,</l>
   <l>To serve insteed of what hath wasted bin,</l>
   <l>In <hi>Wounds,</hi> in <hi>Sicknesses,</hi> in <hi>Colds,</hi> and <hi>Heates,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>In all <hi>Excrescions,</hi> and in <hi>Fumes,</hi> and <hi>Sweates.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="8"/>Nor shall, this present <hi>Flesh,</hi> long stay with us:</l>
   <l>And, wee may well be pleas'd, it should be <hi>Thus.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>For, as I view, those Townes, and Fields, that be</l>
   <l>In Landskip drawne; Even so, me thinks, I see</l>
   <l>A Glimpes, farre off, (through <hi>FAITH'S Prospective glasse</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Of that, which after <hi>Death,</hi> will come to passe;</l>
   <l>And, likewise, gained have, such meanes of seeing,</l>
   <l>Some things, which were, before my <hi>Life</hi> had being,</l>
   <l>That, in my <hi>Soule,</hi> I should be discontent,</l>
   <l>If, this my <hi>Body</hi> were, more permanent;</l>
   <l>Since, <hi>Wee,</hi> and all <hi>God's</hi> other <hi>Creatures,</hi> here,</l>
   <l>Are but the <hi>Pictures,</hi> of what shall appeare.</l>
   <l>Yet, whilst they <hi>are,</hi> I thankfully would make</l>
   <l>That use of them, for their <hi>CREATOR'S</hi> sake,</l>
   <l>To which hee made them; and, preserve the <hi>Table,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Still, <hi>Faire</hi> and <hi>Full,</hi> asmuch as I were able,</l>
   <l>By finishing, (in my alotted place)</l>
   <l>Those <hi>Workes,</hi> for which, hee fits me by his Grace.</l>
   <l>And, if a <hi>Wrenne,</hi> a <hi>Wrenn's</hi> just height shall soare,</l>
   <l>No <hi>Aegle,</hi> for an <hi>Aegle,</hi> can doe more.</l>
   <l>If therefore, of my <hi>Labours,</hi> or of <hi>MEE,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Ought shall remaine, when I remov'd, must be,</l>
   <l>Let it be that, wherein it may be view'd,</l>
   <l>My <hi>MAKERS Image,</hi> was in me renew'd:</l>
   <l>And, so declare, a dutifull intent,</l>
   <l>To doe the <hi>Worke</hi> I came for, e're I went;</l>
   <l>That, I to others, may some <hi>Patterne</hi> be,</l>
   <l>Of <hi>Doing-well,</hi> as other men to mee,</l>
   <l>Have beene, whilst I had life: And, let my daies</l>
   <l>Be summed up, to my <hi>Redeemer's</hi> praise.</l>
   <l>So this be gained, I regard it not,</l>
   <l>Though, all that I am else, be quite forgot.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>