<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Publisher to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118670_Bo1_1_20</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14949</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18507.205</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118670</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Publisher to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>July. 16. Numb. 9. The continuation of the most remarkable occurrences of newes, since the 4 of Iune, vntill this present. 1630 : Containing, amongst diuers others, these particulars. The preparation and landing of the King of Sweden in Germany, with a mighty army, against the emperour: together with a list of his whole army, horse and foot. A late skirmish and ouerthrow giuen by the States forces, to Count Iohn of Nassaw, himselfe being taken prisoner, being sore hurt: together with diuers men of note neare Wesel. Newes of the arriuall of the two Spanish plate fleets at the Havanna, with the Gargazin of their lading and riches. The great ielousie of the emperour, of the Turkes comming into Hungary, with the great cruelty of the said Turkes, vsed against certaine merchants of Hungary. The arriuall of diuers Dutch ships; richly laden, both from East-Indies, and from Farnambuco together with many other particulars, both from Italy Sauoy, France, and the Low-Countries</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 14 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="publishers_note">
   <head>The Publisher to the Reader.</head>
   <p>SInce the former particulars, we are tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> informed that his Maiesty of <hi>Sweden</hi> was met in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e <hi>Swound,</hi> with two Fleets of sixe or seuenscore saile, and that he is since landed at <hi>Stalesunt</hi> with a Royal Army, and it is hoped will bee the restorer of the liberties of the poore distressed Princes of <hi>Germany.</hi> Of what consequence it will be to the <hi>French</hi> King and his designes in <hi>Jtaly</hi> wise and inteligent men vnderstand▪ This yeare 1630, is like to produce more action in Christendome then was this hundred yeares; and more Newes is like to come to our hands▪ If wee. may receiue better encouragement then we haue done, for we haue lost by our publication, both our labour and a great deale of money this tenne moneths, which was the cause we published scarce one a moneth; It being most mens desire to heare of action, which seldome fals out in the Winter. We presume we shall now fit their humour, with action enough euery weeke if their purses be as ready to pay as wee shall bee ready to publish, the greatest talkers of Newes (as the <hi>Pauls</hi> walkers) are the poorest buyers. Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>
            <hi>Iuly the</hi> 16. 1630.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>