<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE FRIENDLY, VNFRIENDLY, PRE∣judicate, or Indifferent Rea∣der, or Hearer, and so con∣sequently to all, and every body.</title>
           <author>Taylor, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118199_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13438</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23746</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118199</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE FRIENDLY, VNFRIENDLY, PRE∣judicate, or Indifferent Rea∣der, or Hearer, and so con∣sequently to all, and every body.</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Differing worships, or, The oddes, betweene some knights service and God's : Or Tom Nash his ghost, (the old Martin queller) newly rous'd, and is come to chide and take order with nonconformists, schismatiques, separatists, and scandalous libellers. VVherein their abusive opinions are manifested, their jeeres mildly retorted, and their unmannerly manners admonished. By Iohn Taylor</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lee (Ley), William 3</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 25, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE FRIENDLY, VNFRIENDLY, PRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicate, or Indifferent Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or Hearer, and so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently to all, and every body.</head>
   <l>
      <hi>I</hi> (with applause) have writt, neere seavenscore Books,</l>
   <l>Yet never fear'd base words, or scurvy looks:</l>
   <l>Though some detracting spirits snarle and hisse,</l>
   <l>I (with mine owne hand) doe acknowledge this:</l>
   <l>Let Rake-hells raile, and Rebels kick and spurne;</l>
   <l>The <hi>Bush</hi> shall be unburnt, when they shall burne:</l>
   <l>Such as would sink the <hi>Arke</hi> (<hi>which doth denote</hi>
   </l>
   <l>That then Gods Church was in that sacred <hi>Boate</hi>)</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="3"/>More barbarous than the barbarous souldiers were</l>
   <l>That did refuse <hi>Christs seam-lesse Coate</hi> to teare;</l>
   <l>To such as these, and none but such as these,</l>
   <l>My lines may have a rellish to displease;</l>
   <l>And I doe say (as better men have said)</l>
   <l>God is my record, I am not affraid</l>
   <l>Of <hi>Force</hi> or <hi>Fraude</hi>; for he that feareth such,</l>
   <l>Will never dare t' abide the <hi>Test</hi> or <hi>Tutch</hi>:</l>
   <l>Nor is it flatt'ry that doth cause me write,</l>
   <l>(My <hi>Climactericall</hi> doth say, Good Night)</l>
   <l>And 'tis a Court-like adulating sinne,</l>
   <l>Which I ne're us'd, nor will I now beginne;</l>
   <l>He that's offended, let him tell wherefore,</l>
   <l>And shew some reason why he hath therefore;</l>
   <l>And where my error is, but shew me it,</l>
   <l>In all Humility I will submit.</l>
   <l>Some sattin <hi>Momus,</hi> or some silken <hi>Zoylus,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Or <hi>Midas</hi> puft in plush, or musky <hi>Troylus</hi>;</l>
   <l>This was not writt to doe them any pleasure,</l>
   <l>Nor can their Wisedomes take of it true measure;</l>
   <l>If such as understand not, are offended,</l>
   <l>I bid them all come kisse my Muse, and mend it.</l>
   <l>But sure, as long as God is on my side,</l>
   <l>What need I care if raskals doe deride;</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="3"/>My deere, deere Mother, <hi>Englands Church,</hi> 'tis she,</l>
   <l>(In humble duty) drawes these lines from me;</l>
   <l>For though I am no Clergie-man, I know,</l>
   <l>That I obedience unto <hi>HER</hi> doe owe;</l>
   <l>In <hi>HER,</hi> I was baptised, and in <hi>HER</hi>
   </l>
   <l>I have been shew'd Truth, and to shun to erre;</l>
   <l>In <hi>HER</hi> th' eternall food (most excellent)</l>
   <l>I have receiv'd, in th' Word and Sacrament,</l>
   <l>And for <hi>HER</hi> sake (to <hi>vindicate</hi> her cause)</l>
   <l>Expecting neither proffit nor applause,</l>
   <l>These following lines unto the world I send,</l>
   <l>Which (I am sure) shall last, till time shall end.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>J. T.</hi> Poeta Aquaticus.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>