<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118970_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02277</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12407</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118970</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Miscelanea. Meditations. Memoratiues : By Elizabeth Grymeston</title>
                 <author>Grymeston, Elizabeth</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <publisher>Bradwood, Melchisidec.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, Felix</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>62 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="34"/>
   <pb facs="34"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>THO' the Design of this Publication is of so commendable a Nature in its self, as to need nothing to be said in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of it; yet it may not be amiss, to make some Reflections in Prose, when the Ballad has escap'd the Censure of Verse, and take notice of the Clemency of those Gentlemen its Presumptious Author taxes with Cruelty.</p>
   <p>We have seen, these two or three days last past, Papers publickly cry'd about, that dar'd the Face of Authority, and the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers abus'd that compose that Venerable As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly that sat for the Redress of our Griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, and has been employ'd in asserting our Right and Liberties; yet has their Patience been such, as to shew us regard to those A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buses which bore none to Truth, and pass by Calumnies they were sensible the Good Laws they had oblig'd us with, could not deserve.</p>
   <p>Whosoever the two Authors are, the scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous pieces of Scandal that comes from 'em, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Impudence enough in 'em to be call'd
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="35"/>
liament thought 'em beneath their notice, I could not but think my self oblig'd to send some Remarks of mine to keep 'em Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, since all the People of <hi>England</hi> are scandaliz'd in the Persons of those that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>present us.</p>
   <p>And tho' I may not probably make such a Figure in Metre, as this Champion of Quality, or the Prose defender of Rebellion; I am certain I have spoken more Truth, and am ready to own my self to be of the same order of Men, which their way of writing points them out to be of. For if they are of that House they write in defence of, I dare affirm them to be the most unmannerly P—rs living; but his Stanza's are of such a Complexion, and his mercinary Paragraphs have such an unsavoury Tincture that I could not but think 'em two of our suburbian Hirelings; And as such, I have endeavour'd to treat 'em.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>