<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the loving Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118078_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14770</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25067</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118078</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the loving Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tvvo histories of Ireland : The one written by Edmund Campion, the other by Meredith Hanmer Dr of Divinity</title>
                 <author>Campion, Edmund, saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Ireland--Dublin</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Matthew.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stationers’ Society, Dublin</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 138, 2, 219, 221-223, 2, 8, 127, 9 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the loving Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T my times of leisure from ordinary stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, I have since my first arrivall hither, enquired out antiquityes of the land, wherein being holpen by diverse friendly Gentlemen, I have given th'adventure to frame a Story, which I bring from the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry first originall untill th'end of this last yeare <hi>1570.</hi> I follow these Authors, <hi>Giraldus Cambrensis,</hi> who devideth his worke into two parts, from the first (which is stuffed with much impertinent matter) I borrow so much as serveth the turne directly, the second which containeth two bookes, and discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth the conquest of <hi>Henry Fitz Empresse,</hi> I abridge into one Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: where <hi>Cambrensis</hi> endeth, there beginneth a nameles Author, who in certaine short notes containeth a Chronologie untill the year<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of Christ <hi>1370.</hi> From thence to <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, because nothing is extant orderly written, and the same is time beyond any mans memory, I scamble forward with such records as could be sought up, and am enforced to be the briefer. From <hi>Henry</hi> th'eight hitherto, I tooke instructions by mouth, whatsoever I bring besides these helpes, either mine owne observation hath found it, or some friend hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed me, or common opinion hath received it, or I reade it in a pamphlet, or if the Author be worthy the naming I quote him in the margent. Scottish Histories I used these twaine, famous in their times, <hi>Iohn Major,</hi> and <hi>Hector Boethius.</hi> For English, wherein the state of Ireland is oft implyed, because I am not in place to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the auncient, I have credited these late writers, <hi>Fabian, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidore, Cooper, Hall, Grafton,</hi> and <hi>Stowe:</hi> diligent and thankes-worthy collectors. Touching the rest of all sorts, from whose bookes I picke matter to my purpose, they are mentioned as they fall in
<pb facs="6"/>
ure, which here I list not to reckon, being loath to fill the page with a ranke of empty names. Irish Chronicles, although they be reported to be full fraught of lewde examples, idle tales, and genealogies: <hi>Et quicquid Graecia mendax audet in historiâ,</hi> yet concerning the state of that wilde people specified before the conquest. I am perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that with choice and judgment, I might have sucked thence some better store of matter, and gladly would have sought them, had I found an interpreter, or understood their tongue. th' one so rare, that scarcely five in five hundred can skill thereof, th'other so hard, that it asketh continuance in the Land, of more yeares then I had moneths to spare about this busines, my speciall meaning was to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther so much as I thought the civill subjects could bee content to reade, and withall to give a light to the learned Antiquaries of this Countrey birth, who may hereafter at good leisure supply the want of this foundation, and pollish the stone rough hewed to their hand. Notwithstanding as naked and simple as it is, it could never have growne to any proportion in such post-haste, except I had entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to such familiar societie, and daylie table-talke with the worshipfull Esquire <hi>Iames Stanihurst,</hi> Recorder of Dublin. VVho beside all curtesie of Hospitality, and a thousand loving turnes not heere to be recited, both by word and written monuments, and by the benefit of his owne Library, nourished most effectually mine endeavour. It remaineth that <hi>I</hi> request my Countrymen to bend their good liking to my goodwill, and the English of Ireland to favour the memory of their noble auncestors, both twaine to deliver me from all undue and wrong suspitions, howsoever the priviledge of an history hath tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red mine inke with sweet or sowre ingredients. Verily as touching the affaires and persons heere deciphered, how little cause <hi>I</hi> have with any blind and corrupt affection, either wayes to be miscarryed, themselves know best that heere be noted yet living, and other by enquiring may conjecture. Farewell. From Droghedah the <hi>9.</hi> of Iune. <hi>1571.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>