<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY Prince, JAMES, Duke of LENNOX, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Wither, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118583_Fr4_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15631</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25900a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118583</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY Prince, JAMES, Duke of LENNOX, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Wither, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A collection of emblemes, ancient and moderne : quickened vvith metricall illustrations, both morall and divine: and disposed into lotteries, that instruction, and good counsell, may bee furthered by an honest and pleasant recreation. By George VVither. The first booke</title>
                 <author>Wither, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Grismand (Grismond), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Grismand (Grismond), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 62, 6, 63-124, 6, 135-196, 6, 209-270, 10 pages, illustrations (engravings, woodcut), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedicatory_poem">
   <pb facs="78"/>
   <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY Prince, <hi>JAMES,</hi> Duke of <hi>LENNOX,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
   <l>VVHen <hi>Richmond,</hi> your, beloved, <hi>Vnkle,</hi> liv'd,</l>
   <l>(For whose departure, all this <hi>Empire</hi> griev'd,</l>
   <l>And, yet laments) his GRACE did not refuse</l>
   <l>To deigne respects, to my obscured MVSE;</l>
   <l>Nor scorne, from <hi>Highest-worth,</hi> to stoope so low,</l>
   <l>As, mee, in my despisednesse, to know:</l>
   <l>And, had not <hi>Bashfulnesse</hi> restrain'd my <hi>Wit,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>From pressing-on, (when he incourag'd it,)</l>
   <l>My <hi>PEGASVS,</hi> had learn'd, e're now, to rise,</l>
   <l>Which, yet, with lame, and sickly <hi>Feathers</hi> flies.</l>
   <l>But, <hi>HEE</hi> hath left us; and, I thought not on</l>
   <l>The losse I had of HIM, till he was gone;</l>
   <l>Nor could I dreame, till he did hence ascend,</l>
   <l>What t'was to want an <hi>Honourable-friend:</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Nor, what they feele, whom <hi>Fate</hi> constraines, to tarry</l>
   <l>On stormy Plaines, without a SANCTVARIE.</l>
   <l>Assoone, as from among us, he made wing,</l>
   <l>My <hi>Hopes</hi> did waine, and, I began to sing</l>
   <l>A <hi>Mournfull-song,</hi> not easie to forget;</l>
   <l>Because, I beare the <hi>burthen</hi> of it, yet.</l>
   <l>Nor was I silent (though my <hi>Epicede</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Appear'd not, for the publike eye to reade)</l>
   <l>But, griev'd in private, as one wanting <hi>Art,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>To give, the <hi>Life of praise,</hi> to his desart:</l>
   <l>Which, if I could have equall'd with his <hi>Name,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>His <hi>Death</hi> had gain'd my <hi>Verse,</hi> a <hi>living-Fame.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>And, why expresse I this? except it give</l>
   <l>Your GRACE, a fit occasion to perceive,</l>
   <l>That, my decayed <hi>Hopes</hi> I would renew,</l>
   <l>And, faine derive them downe, from HIM to YOV?</l>
   <l>That, as you branched from his Princely <hi>Stemme;</hi>
   </l>
   <l>(Are, honour'd with his <hi>Ducall-Diadem</hi>)</l>
   <l>And, imitate his Vertue; So, you might</l>
   <l>Be <hi>Lord,</hi> in mee, of that, which was his right:</l>
   <l>And, for his Noble sake, vouchsafe to own</l>
   <l>A <hi>Servant,</hi> which, to you, is yet unknowne.</l>
   <l>As <hi>Prologue,</hi> to the service I intend,</l>
   <l>This PRESENT comes; and, without <hi>Hope,</hi> or <hi>End,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Of gaining further <hi>Grace,</hi> or more <hi>Esteeme,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Than may, with humblest modestie, beseeme</l>
   <l>His <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Honest-meaning,</hi> to expect,</l>
   <l>Whose, <hi>Merits</hi> have, no visible effect,</l>
   <l>Conducing to your profit; and, from whom</l>
   <l>The best of his intents, are yet to come.</l>
   <l>I cannot thinke, these <hi>Lots,</hi> or <hi>Emblems,</hi> are</l>
   <l>So worthy in themselves, as they'l appeare</l>
   <l>In your acceptance; Or, that they can give,</l>
   <l>Such Grace to YOV, as they'l from you receive.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="79"/>Yet, if YOV please, they may be, otherwhile,</l>
   <l>A profitable Meanes, to help beguile</l>
   <l>A Melancholy thought; And, have the pow'r</l>
   <l>To shorten (without losse) a tedious howre.</l>
   <l>Sometime (no doubt) content you are in walke</l>
   <l>In <hi>Artlesse Groves;</hi> Or, to admit the talke</l>
   <l>Of Rustick <hi>Swaines</hi> (though ev'ry day you might</l>
   <l>Your self in well-trim'd <hi>garden-bowr's,</hi> delight,</l>
   <l>Or, heare the learnedst <hi>Muses,</hi> when you please;)</l>
   <l>Ev'n so, for change you may, perhaps, in these</l>
   <l>A <hi>Recreation</hi> finde; and, in some measure,</l>
   <l>A <hi>Profit,</hi> intermixed with your <hi>Pleasure.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>I will not make my <hi>Promises</hi> too large,</l>
   <l>Lest, my <hi>Performances,</hi> they overcharge</l>
   <l>With <hi>Expectation:</hi> but, I leave them, SIR,</l>
   <l>To <hi>Bee,</hi> and to <hi>be thought,</hi> the same they are.</l>
   <l>And, if your EXCELLENCE, (when you behold</l>
   <l>The Ground whereon I first became so bold,</l>
   <l>To make this Entrance) shall vouchsafe to daigne</l>
   <l>Those <hi>Favours,</hi> which, I dare not thinke to gaine</l>
   <l>By <hi>Meer-deserving;</hi> you may then, perchance,</l>
   <l>My <hi>Willingnesse,</hi> to <hi>Ablenesse</hi> advance:</l>
   <l>And reap in <hi>Mee</hi> (when ripened they are grown)</l>
   <l>Some timely <hi>fruits,</hi> of that, which <hi>you</hi> have sown.</l>
   <l>Till then, let it suffice, that I professe</l>
   <l>A cheerefull, and a thankfull Readinesse</l>
   <l>To honour <hi>YOV;</hi> and, openly to show</l>
   <l>The Dutie, which, it may appeare, I owe</l>
   <l>To HIM that's gone. And, let your GRACE descend</l>
   <l>To take this <hi>Pledge,</hi> of what I more intend.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Who am in all humilitie Your GRACES to be commanded, GEO: WITHER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>