<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Est, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118323_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00406</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10536</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118323</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Est, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The right rule of a religious life: or, The glasse of godlinesse : Wherein euery man may behold his imperfections, how farre hee is out of the way of true godlinesse, and learne to reduce his wandring steppes into the pathes of true pietie. In certaine lectures vpon the first chapter of the Epistle of S. Iames. The first part. By William Est preacher of Gods word</title>
                 <author>Est, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Lee (Lea, Leigh), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 318 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>¶ To the Christian <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is an vsuall A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology (Christian Reader) made for the diuulging of bookes: <hi>That it was at the motion and vrgent im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of friends;</hi> complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning also that the Print is peste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the Presse oppressed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready with an exceeding multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Writers: which one rightly compareth vnto Guests bidden vnto a sumptuous feast, which, for fashion sake, will seeme to dislike with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse and variety of dishes, as
<pb facs="5"/>superfluous, and yet their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite inuites them to feed on euery kind of meate. This ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse is no lesse triuiall then fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous; and the best Apology (in my iudgement) that we can make is, the iniquity of these times, wherein the arrogant Athiest, the loose Libertine, the shallow conceited Schysma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, the pestilent Papist, the carnall Professour, &amp;c. seeme to breathe forth their infectious blasts, and proclaime defiance to Gods glory, and true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian piety: This indeed should rouse vp, and awake, the Tribe of <hi>Leuy,</hi> to gird their spirituall sword vpon their thigh, to <hi>fight, the good fight of the Lord,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.18</note>
      <hi>in sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and out of season,</hi> against the monsters of this age, by Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, Writing, by all meanes,
<pb facs="5"/>to labour, <hi>Ornare Spartam quam nacti sunt,</hi> and striue to cut off the head of this cursed <hi>Hydra,</hi> and reduce <hi>Syon</hi> to her perfect beauty, that shee may shine as a pure and vncorrupt Virgine to bee presented vnto her Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome Iesus Christ.
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.2</note> This ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding growth of sathans seed, which seemeth to bee euen ripe for Gods reuenging sickle, should stirre vp Gods Watch-men (considering the great charge they sustaine, and the strict account shall bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at their hands) to bee euer vigilant, to stand in the gappe, with the sword of the Word ready drawne, least their Maister <hi>comming in a day they thinke not,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luk. 12.46 2. Tim. 2.3</note>
      <hi>and in an houre they are not aware of,</hi> finding them secure and carelesse, <hi>shall giue
<pb facs="6"/>them their portion with the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeuers:</hi> This should moue vs, I say, to bee Souldiers, not Sluggards, to stand euer in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestra, non in Orchestra, To fight the Lords Battell, as the good Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of Iesus Christ,</hi> and not to fit as idle spectators, taking de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to behold the inundation of iniquity. And this indeed is a iust and irrefragable Apology (neuer gainesaid of any that is truely religious) in defence of my selfe and others, which in tender zeale of Gods glory do enter the lists, and challenge the combate, to encounter with the monstrous sins of this age, by Prayer and Preaching, Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and all spirituall Artillery. The Lord giue a powerfull working to his blessed Word: If there bee any which being
<pb facs="6"/>puffed vp with a proud conceit of their owne gifts (as these ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulcerate times are full of enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Critickes, which cannot looke with a right eye vpon the doings of others, but with their Canine tooth must needes bee biting) shall not vouchsafe these my poore labours the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, let them know I haue not laboured for such, but to profit the vnlearned, the simple, and ignorant: <note place="margin">Heb. 5.12. 1. Cor. 3.2. Mat 25.25 Luk. 19.20.</note> Such <hi>as haue need of milke and not of strong meate: not hiding my talent in the earth, nor laying it vp in a napkin with the vnprofitable seruant.</hi> These first fruits of my labours vpon this excellent part of Scripture, I haue intituled, <hi>The Glasse of Godlinesse,</hi> because the Apostle, in this Epistle chiefly, insisteth vpon good workes and a godly
<pb facs="7"/>life, as the inseparable fruits of a liuely &amp; iustifying faith, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in euery one may see his ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mishes, how farre exorbitant his steppes are from the pathes of piety, and indeuour by Gods grace to reforme the same. And whatsoeuer thou shalt finde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiue, or omitted, in this first Part, shall, by Gods assistance, be supplied when I come forth with the rest. In the meane time, (Gentle Reader) I request thee diligently to peruse, religiously to vse, kindly to accept, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourably to interpret, this little Mite, which I offer to the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sury of the Church, in sincerity of heart, for the furtherance of a godly life. And so I conclude with this of the wise sonne of <hi>Sirach:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Chap. 33.15.16.</note>
      <hi>I am awaked vp last of all, as one that gathereth but after
<pb facs="7"/>others in the Vintage,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Tanquam is qui spicas legit post messores.</note>
      <hi>in the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of the Lord I am encreased, and haue filled my wine-presse; yet, like a Grape-gatherer, I haue not laboured for my selfe onely, but for all them that seeke know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord, WILLIAM EST.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>