<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the right honourable and mine especiall good lorde, Iohn̄ Erle of Warrewike, Uisconte Lisle, knight of the most noble ordre of the Gar∣ter, lorde great chambrelaine, and highe admyrall of Englande.</title>
           <author>Thomas, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1549</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118381_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13726</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24018</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118381</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the right honourable and mine especiall good lorde, Iohn̄ Erle of Warrewike, Uisconte Lisle, knight of the most noble ordre of the Gar∣ter, lorde great chambrelaine, and highe admyrall of Englande.</title>
                 <author>Thomas, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of Italie : a boke excedyng profitable to be redde: because it intreateth of the astate of many and diuers common weales, how thei haue ben, [and] now be gouerned</title>
                 <author>Thomas, William, Clerk of the Council to Edward VI</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Berthelet (Barthelet), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1549</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 72, 4, 73-155, 157-216 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶To the right honourable and mine especiall good lorde, Iohn̄ Erle of Warrewike, Uisconte Lisle, knight of the most noble ordre of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, lorde great chambrelaine, and highe admyrall of Englande.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough many wise and lerned men haue so sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancially set foorth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite cōmodities that grow of the readyng of histories, that my wittes can not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teigne to a small part of the due commendacion therof: Yet seeyng my trauaile at this present hath been to publishe vnto our owne nacion in our mother tounge the dooynges of straungers, and specially of the Italian nacion, whiche semeth to flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risshe in ciuilitee moste of all other at this daie: me thought I coulde no lesse dooe for the incourageyng of theim that shall take this boke in hande, than partely reherse what profite thei maie gather by trauailyng therin. First thei shall see, vpon what little beginnyng many great astates haue risen, and how thei that haue had the power to rule, by vsyng their auctoritees well and prudently, haue merited immortall fame of honour and preise: and by vsyng tyrannie and ill gouernaunce, haue contrariwise borne eternall sklaunder and shame. It encourageth the vertuouse men, by the exaumples that thei reade, to encreace in vertue and nobilitee: and
<pb facs="3"/>
sheweth the viciouse, what the fruite of their abuses are, and how naughtie dooynges haue moste commonly naughtie endyng. It moueth the noble prince to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teigne peace and iustice: and sheweth the tyra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne, what plagues folow of warre and crueltee: and that though his tyrannie passe vnplagued in this worlde (whiche hapneth seldome) yet shall his name be hated and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in all ages and amongest all nacions, as <hi>Nero, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liogabalus</hi> and suche other princes be. It sheweth also, howe mutable fortune is, and howe that, whiche hath been gotten with extreeme peines, vnmeasurable expences, and vnreasonable effusion of bloudde, hath ben loste in a moment: and that commonly he that hath conquered most in warre, at the beste is yet a loser: and finally, that of diuision, either amongest the nobilitee or the commons, there ensueth vtter destruction of real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and subuercion of common wealthes: Wherun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to there is none so great a minister as the alteracion of auncient lawes and customes.</p>
   <p>¶All these thynges, with infinite moe, histories dooe so set foorth to the eies of princes (if thei reade theim well) that their hertes shalbe more enclined with peace and iustice to enriche their subiectes, and therby procure theim selfes glorie, than by murtheryng of innocentes, rauishyng of honest wiues and maidens, burnyng, spoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng and destruction of countreis (whiche are the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes of warre) to make theim selfes conquerours of that thei can not longe enioie. For surely, more preise shall that prince deserue, that leaueth his realme quiete and welthie vnto his successour, than he that for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest of other countreis enpouerissheth and disturbeth his owne.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>¶And because this little woorke declareth bothe these extremitees, as well what a numbre of beautifull citees haue been edified, and what great countreis haue been enriched by peace and concorde, as also how many good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thynges and wonderfull regions haue been destroied by striefe and warre: Therfore woulde I wishe all noble men to reade it, to the ende thei maie hereof take occasion so honourablie to spende their life time, that after their death, thei maie shine in fame for euer.</p>
   <p>¶And knowyng your lordshippe for your excellent fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of chiualrie, bothe by sea and lande, to be suche a one as is hable to iudge, whether mine opinion be good or not, like as your wonderfull knowlage in ciuile or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders hath made you woorthie to be no lesse esteemed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in counsaile, than as you haue been tried a moste valiaunt capitaine in the warres: I therfore coulde finde none, to whom I might so woorthily dedicate my little trauaile as to you: Most humblie bese<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng your lordeship to accepte it at my poore handes, as the giefte of him that wisheth you all health and honour. At Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the .xx. daie of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. 1549.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your good lordeshippes most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at commaundement, William Thomas.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>