<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST ILLVSTRIOVS Princesse, FRANCIS, Dutchesse Do∣wager of RICHMOND, and LENNOX, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Wither, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118583_Fr4_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15631</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25900a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118583</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST ILLVSTRIOVS Princesse, FRANCIS, Dutchesse Do∣wager of RICHMOND, and LENNOX, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Wither, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A collection of emblemes, ancient and moderne : quickened vvith metricall illustrations, both morall and divine: and disposed into lotteries, that instruction, and good counsell, may bee furthered by an honest and pleasant recreation. By George VVither. The first booke</title>
                 <author>Wither, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Grismand (Grismond), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Grismand (Grismond), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 62, 6, 63-124, 6, 135-196, 6, 209-270, 10 pages, illustrations (engravings, woodcut), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedicatory_poem">
   <pb facs="77"/>
   <pb facs="77"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST ILLVSTRIOVS Princesse, <hi>FRANCIS,</hi> Dutchesse Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wager of <hi>RICHMOND,</hi> and <hi>LENNOX,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
   <l>FAME sayes (great PRINCESSE) that the <hi>Pow'rs-above,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Will soone forgive; which, I desire to prove:</l>
   <l>For, I am guiltie of a <hi>Venial-sinne</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Against your GRACE; and, have remain'd therein</l>
   <l>Without an <hi>Absolution,</hi> so long time,</l>
   <l>That, now, my <hi>Conscience</hi> checks me for the <hi>Crime</hi>;</l>
   <l>And, to reprove me for it, will not cease</l>
   <l>Till I have, someway, sought to make my <hi>Peace.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>To palliate my <hi>Fault,</hi> I could produce</l>
   <l>Enough, perhaps, to stand for an <hi>Excuse.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>But, when I mind what <hi>Favours,</hi> and what <hi>Fame</hi>
   </l>
   <l>I might have purchased unto my <hi>Name,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>(By taking Courage, to have done my best)</l>
   <l>I dare not make <hi>Excuses</hi>; but, request</l>
   <l>Your pardon, rather, and, that some <hi>Oblation</hi>
   </l>
   <l>May gaine my <hi>Person,</hi> future acceptation.</l>
   <l>To that intent, this humble <hi>Offring,</hi> here,</l>
   <l>Within your gracious presence, doth appeare.</l>
   <l>And, that it may the more content your eye;</l>
   <l>Well-graven <hi>Figures,</hi> help to beautifie</l>
   <l>My lowly <hi>Gift:</hi> And, vailed are in these,</l>
   <l>A <hi>Treasury</hi> of Golden <hi>Sentences</hi>;</l>
   <l>By my well-meaning <hi>Muse,</hi> interpreted,</l>
   <l>That, with your NAME, their Morals may be spread,</l>
   <l>And scattred, <hi>Largesse-like,</hi> (at your commanding)</l>
   <l>To helpe inrich the <hi>Poore in Vnderstanding.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>If YOV accept the <hi>Tender,</hi> I shall know,</l>
   <l>Your GRACE is pleased with your <hi>Servant,</hi> so,</l>
   <l>As, that there may be hope, my future Actions,</l>
   <l>Will give the more contenting Satisfactions:</l>
   <l>And, your <hi>Encouragements,</hi> my <hi>Pow'rs</hi> may raise,</l>
   <l>To make the BEAVTIES of your <hi>Later dayes,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>More glorious, far, than your fresh YOVTH's perfection,</l>
   <l>Though, knowne to be, the <hi>Load-stone</hi> of <hi>Affection.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>For, like the loving TVRTLE, you have stood</l>
   <l>So constant, in your vowed <hi>Widdow-hood</hi>;</l>
   <l>So strictly, kept a solitarie state;</l>
   <l>So faithfull beene, to your deceased MATE;</l>
   <l>So firmly true, and truly kinde, to <hi>them,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Which are the <hi>Branches</hi> of his <hi>Princely-stemme</hi>;</l>
   <l>And, personated in so high a <hi>Straine,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>The parts of HONOVR; that, my rusticke <hi>vaine,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Must raised be, before it can ascend</l>
   <l>To say, how much, your <hi>Fame,</hi> doth you commend.</l>
   <l>Yet, if these <hi>Lines,</hi> (or, <hi>that</hi> they Vsher in)</l>
   <l>For me, some <hi>Passage</hi> may, anew, begin</l>
   <l>To your <hi>Esteeme</hi>; I, may so happily,</l>
   <l>Illustrate forth, the <hi>Golden-History</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="78"/>Of those <hi>Affections,</hi> which within your Brest,</l>
   <l>Have to the world remained unexprest.</l>
   <l>That, future times, to your applause may reade,</l>
   <l>The matchlesse <hi>Paterne</hi> of a <hi>Widdowed-bed,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Which you have drawne, for those to <hi>imitate</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Who can; and, for the rest to wonder at.</l>
   <l>For, what (thereto) yet wanteth, in my <hi>Muse,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Your GRACE, as my <hi>Minerva,</hi> may infuse.</l>
   <l>Nor, will it be in vaine, to shew the worth</l>
   <l>Of those <hi>Perfections,</hi> truly blazed forth,</l>
   <l>Which you may personate: Nor, shall it be</l>
   <l>To your <hi>Content</hi> unusefull, when you see</l>
   <l>The <hi>Best part of your selfe,</hi> (as in a <hi>Glasse</hi>)</l>
   <l>Disclosed, and set up, before your GRACE,</l>
   <l>To represent those <hi>Beauties,</hi> wherein lurkes,</l>
   <l>More sweetnesse, than in <hi>Picture-drawers</hi> Workes;</l>
   <l>And shew, how temp'rall <hi>Glor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>es,</hi> and <hi>Affections,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Have hourely ripened you, for those <hi>Perfections</hi>
   </l>
   <l>That, make <hi>Immortall</hi>; and, which are that <hi>End,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Whereto, all Earthly <hi>Graces,</hi> ought to tend.</l>
   <l>Then, if your EXCELLENCE, desire to heare,</l>
   <l>Those MVSES, honour you, whose prayses; are</l>
   <l>Attending <hi>Vertue</hi>; and, shall please to live</l>
   <l>That <hi>Life of Glory,</hi> which my <hi>Verse</hi> can give;</l>
   <l>Your GRACES favour, (when you please) hath pow'rs</l>
   <l>To make both MEE, and all my <hi>Muses</hi> yours.</l>
   <l>And, wee are hopefull, that, so well wee know</l>
   <l>Your <hi>Merits,</hi> and those <hi>Duties,</hi> which wee owe,</l>
   <l>That, wee shall raise, your HONOVR'S <hi>Trophies</hi> high,</l>
   <l>Though, <hi>Wee our selves,</hi> upon the pavement lie.</l>
   <l>Thus, I have made mine <hi>Offring</hi>; and I stand</l>
   <l>Attending, now, to kisse your GRACES hand.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your GRACES in all humilitie,</hi> GEO: WITHER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>