<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118389_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17054</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3928</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118389</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A commentary upon the Canticle of Canticles, written first in Italian by Antonio Brucioli, and now translated into English by Th. Iames fellow of New colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Brucioli, Antonio</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>46, 3-161, 5 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Booke.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His booke of the Canticles is a holy and admirable booke, very spirituall, full of myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and most hidden senses; whereby it is most euident, that they haue bene not a litle deceiued, which go about to diminish the credit and authoritie thereof: for because herein are contained, sundry enterchangeable discourses, and dialogues of mutuall loue betweene the bride and the bridegrome, therefore forsooth haue they thought it good to call this booke in questiō; as if it were not an vsuall matter with the holy Ghost in the holy Scripture, to set down the sincere and vnfained loue of God and the Church, vnder the figure of chast and holy wedlocke: as also to discouer the force of wickednesse and Idolatrie, by the simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the adulterous woman, as it is to be seene in the second and third of Ieremie,
<pb facs="10"/>
and in the sixteenth Chapter of Ezechiel. Besides all this, there are certaine places in this booke, whereby no otherwise then as it were by certaine beames and lights, this point is made so cleare and manifest, that we may very well say without any maner of doubt or wauering at all, that this Treatise is not carnally and literally, but spiritually and mystically to be vnderstood. In such sort, that I hold this for an vnfallible and certaine truth, that there are comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and contained in this small booke, the exceeding great affection and loue of our Lord Iesus Christ, and the holy Church of the faithfull beleeuers, the necessarie vse of the word of God, the profite and pleasant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse thereof, the efficacie of faith, and heat of charity. Furthermore we learne to know what are the operations of the spirit, and what are the works of the flesh: &amp; briefly, that which doth any maner of way cōcerne or respect the Church; and all this, vnder the figuratiue talk and communication be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Bridegroome and the Spouse. Now Christ is the Bridegroome, as it is in the <hi>3.</hi> of Iohn verse <hi>29.</hi> He that hath the
<pb facs="10"/>
bride, is the bridegrome, and the Church is his spouse. Hosea Chapter <hi>2.</hi> Thou shalt call me <hi>Ishi</hi> or my husband, &amp; I wil marry thee vnto me for euer. And this spouse is atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on with her young maidens, that is to say, with the particular soules of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, which do follow after the odoriferous and sauery ointments of our Sauiour Iesus Christ. And the bridegrome likewise hath his friends that do follow &amp; accōpany him, to wit, the true Bishops, &amp; sincere Prechers of the word of God, which he cals vnto him to eate &amp; drinke, &amp; make merry with him. These men heare the voyce of the Church, that is to say, the words of Christ. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse, this is not so to be vnderstood, but that all the faithfull may rightly terme thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues frēds of the bridegrome. The title or inscriptiō is the Song of Songs, as if therin were contained songs which did farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed all other songs, in plenty of holy myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and they are called the songs of Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, or Salomons songs, because hee writ them being inspired by the holy Ghost of the true Salomon Iesus Christ. VVe reade of many Canticles or songs in the scripture, as
<pb facs="11"/>
the song of Moyses, Deborah, Iosua, Anna, Dauid, Abacuck, and others, but this booke compriseth not one onely song which Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon song, but there are many songs herein contained, all written in one book, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning one matter, and one argument; wherin are expressed most truly the chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, faith, loue, ioy, delights, and diuerse kinds of benefits (not without vehemēt &amp; earnest affections) wherewith our most lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing &amp; merciful redemer doth follow his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect with inexplicable graces, by the grace &amp; fauor of the almighty God. So that they being stirred vp by the holy Ghost, do with certaine vnspeakeable affections of loue, regard, behold, and approch neere vnto the diuine grace and bountie of God: desiring most earnestly and deuoutly to be commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, approoued, and daily more and more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steemed and fauoured of him: in such sort that if there be found any error or fault in their liues and conuersations (as spots and blots or wennes in their forheads do some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times happen) yet that they may not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused or reiected for this or the like things, or have any cause to distrust his mercifull
<pb facs="11"/>
kindnesse or louing fauor, but that the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling out of louers, may be the renewing of loue. For louers being iealous one of another are mutually and suddenly prouoked vnto wrath, &amp; as suddēly reconciled and pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and afterwards they become greater friends then they were before. This then is the principall intent and purpose of this booke. This is the song of God the spouse, vnto euery faithfull soule, and generally vnto al the Church. Neither are we to look for any precise order in this dialogue or cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, which is not vsuall amongst perfect louers, where all things how soeuer and where soeuer done, are taken in very good part, where, euen errors, ignorances, and mistakes are accepted of, and laught at, and where quarrels, contentions, strife, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and blowes also many times, are heard of, approued, and in most friendly sort ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. And in this booke, there be foure sundry sorts of persons to be obserued of vs. The bridegrome, and the friends of the bridegrome; the spouse and her young dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels or waiting maides, and as the bride saith one thing, and the bridegrome ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
<pb facs="12"/>
so the young virgins that waite on the spouse, and the friends of the bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome, are brought in speaking contrarie and diuerse things, yet all of them betoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning godly &amp; kind affections. Now by the bridegrome we may (as we have before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared vnto you) vnderstand Christ, by the spouse the Church, by the friends of the bridegrome the Preachers of the Gospell, &amp; such as shew vs the way vnto Christ, and direct vs vnto his eternall marriage, and heauenly banquet. The young virgins are the faithfull soules, which do alwayes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the Spouse, and we must note, that the Spouse doth alwayes long to bee in the house, bed, or other secret and inward place, with her welbeloued, according vnto the custome of women, and the bridegrome, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of men, calleth the Spouse foorth into the vineyeard, or abroad into the fields, or vnto some such places: because so it is, and it is most true, that the Church of it selfe would willingly (if so be that it were possible) bring vp her children in quiet rest and tranquility, but he on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther side, thinketh it good to exercise her
<pb facs="12"/>
with many tribulations, and persecutions, to the ende that she may the better come vnto the consideration of eternall things, and also that if matters do happen well and happily, yet, that amiddest her prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity she may not bee too far delighted with the pleasures and entising baits of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent world: but alwayes hope, and grone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an heauenly countrey.</p>
   <trailer>Thus endeth the preface, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie followeth.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>