<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO
THE MOST HIGH
AND MIGHTY
MONARCH, CHARLES,
by the Grace of God, King of Great
Britaine, France, and Ireland, Defender
of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Holland, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118709_Fr1_10</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15807</idno>
           <idno type="STC">26068</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118709</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO
THE MOST HIGH
AND MIGHTY
MONARCH, CHARLES,
by the Grace of God, King of Great
Britaine, France, and Ireland, Defender
of the Faith, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Holland, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cyrupædia : The institution and life of Cyrus, the first of that name, King of Persians. Eight bookes. Treating of noble education, of princely exercises, military discipline, vvarlike stratagems, preparations and expeditions: as appeareth by the contents before the beginning of the first booke. Written in Greeke by the sage Xenophon. Translated out of Greeke into English, and conferred with the Latine and French translations, by Philemon Holland of the city of Coventry Doctor in Physick. Dedicated to his most excellent Maiesty</title>
                 <author>Xenophon</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 <publisher>Allott, Mary.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Allott, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Crooke, Andrew 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Holland, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 131, 130-213, 7, 14 pages, 1 leaf of plates, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>TO
THE MOST HIGH
AND MIGHTY
MONARCH, CHARLES,
by the Grace of God, King of Great
Britaine, France, and Ireland, Defender
of the Faith, &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most dread <hi>Soveraigne.</hi>
      </salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen that Maiden-Monarch, the Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
of the World in her time, Queene
<hi>Elizabeth</hi> (of famous memory) swai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
the Imperiall Scepter of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
in her latter dayes, my deere Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
Doctor <hi>Philemon Holland,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented
unto her Maiesty, his <hi>English</hi>
Translation of the <hi>Romanes most re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed</hi>
* <hi>Historiographer.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> And it
pleased her Highnes full of Clemency,
to reach out the Golden Scepter of her gracious acceptance thereof▪</p>
   <l>Sol occubuit, nox nulla sequuta est:</l>
   <p>For no sooner was that glorious Sunne set, to our sight on Earth, in
our Horizon, and translated to shine in heaven, but your Royall Father
King <hi>Iames</hi> (of blessed memory,) appearing even then by his radiant
beames out of the North, in maturitie of time, came to weare the same
Imperiall Diademe lawfully descended upon his Head. At whose very
first entrance, my said Father dedicated his translation also of * <hi>Traja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi>
his <hi>Masters Morals</hi> unto his Majestie,<note place="margin">Plutarch Anno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> who was no lesse pleased
to hold forth his Gracious hand and accept the same.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="10"/>Also,<note place="margin">Anno. 1610.</note> when my unworthy selfe offred mine owne Collections, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled
<hi>(Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ologia Anglica)</hi> unto his Highnesse, he most graciously
received it.</p>
   <p>And now, most deare <hi>Soveraigne,</hi> unto this present version of <hi>Xe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nophons
Cyrupediam</hi> out of Greek, which is, as I may say, the Authour
his Master-Peece, and my fathers worke likewise, your Majestie hath
the sole right; in regard that he enterprized it long since, and that by
speciall order and direction from your Royall Father, delivered unto
him by one of his neere servants in Court; (even when your selfe were
in your tender yeeres) for the contemplation and use of your most Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous
and Magnanimous Brother, <hi>Prince Henry,</hi> now in Heaven.
Of whose vertuous life and Princely exercises, more may bee seene in
the said <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ologia.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>His death caused a demurre as it were in publishing thereof: untill
of late my father, importuned by some friends, having revised and fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed
his said Traduction, destined it to me his sonne, that in regard
both of the Author and Argument, it might lie no longer in obscurity,
but at length (and as I hope in good time) see the light of the Sunne.</p>
   <p>The Author then of these books, <hi>Xenophon,</hi> a deepe Philosopher, a
politike Counseller of State, and an expert Warriour beside, how-ever
hee penned them <hi>Non ad Historiae fidem,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Epist. ad Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Fratrem.</note> as <hi>Cicero</hi> writeth,
<hi>sed ad Effigiem justi Imperij:</hi> yet in such request they
were, that <hi>Scipio Africanus</hi> the famous Romane Commaunder,
was never wont to lay them out of his hands; for, as the same Oratour
recordeth, <hi>Nullum in hijs praetermissum est officium diligentis &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derati
Imperij.</hi> No mervaile then, that <hi>L. Lucullus</hi> A noble Generall
under the <hi>Romanes,</hi> being at first a raw and unexpert Commaunder,
by serious studying upon these books on ship-boord, became so wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
a warriour, and compleat Generall, as that he vanquished the most
puissant, politick, and victorious <hi>Mithridates,</hi> King of <hi>Pontus,</hi> who
had before, subdued in manner all <hi>Asia.</hi> And all these books wrote
he so sweetly and eloquently in Greek, that he was named the <hi>Muse,</hi>
or (as <hi>Suidas</hi> writeth,) The <hi>Bee</hi> of <hi>Athens.</hi> Insomuch as the very Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
were reported to have spoken in <hi>Xenophons</hi> voice; as out of whose
mouth, by the testimony of that<note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> Romane Oratour, alluding to <hi>Nestor</hi>
in <hi>Homer, melle dulcior fluebat oratio</hi> Which albeit my father in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish
could not Parallele: yet treating as he doth of the life and atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of so worthy a Prince; of whom may I seeme to crave Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage,
in the first place but of your sacred Selfe, my liege Lord? For these
<pb facs="10"/>
books how ever Englished, may haply hereafter, if your Majesty shall
thinke so good, be held worthy the view and imitation of your right
Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>al Son, our most hopeful Prince <hi>Charles.</hi> whom I cānot name but
with this zealous and devout prayer, <hi>That he may grow up in stature
and in favour with God and Man.</hi> Vouchsafe therefore, I most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
crave, of your innate Clemency, which makes you renowmed
throughout the Christian world, not to withhold your Golden Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
but in like manner as your late Predecessours and Progenitours
have done, to welcome into your Court, Greeke <hi>Xenophon</hi> his <hi>Cyrus,</hi>
a <hi>Persian</hi> Prince by birth, but now clad in <hi>English</hi> Accoustrements,
speaking our Language, and hither arrived to kisse your Roiall hand:
especially seeing he is that <hi>Cyrus</hi> the elder, of whom the holy<note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
maketh honourable mention. And why should I doubt hereof,
considering he being a warlike Monarch and skilfull in Armes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to the auncient discipline, tendereth discourse of military Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,
Stratagems and Expeditions, now in these dayes (not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
Gods providence,) of Action: when as your Majesty and your
subjects are so deeply engaged with your Royall Allies and Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates,
in Martiall Actions, who fight <hi>the Lords Battailes;</hi> and that,
blessed be God, with late good and vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>torious successe; so as we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
but hope still, for better, now that your Royall Aide is not wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
and the <hi>Britains</hi> Banners are there advanced. For although your
Majestie, in great wisedome hath of late laid downe Armes, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained
Peace with some Christian Princes; so as wee for the time
may say, <hi>Dulce bellum inexpertis:</hi> Yet, as the wisest of Kings said,
<note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>There is a time for Warre, as well as for Peace.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Demaundeth your Majesty now, what he is, that dareth to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach
so neere your Presence, as to speake of Warre in time of Peace<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
Give your poore vassall leave to answer in the submissive voice of a
loyall subject: He is no Schollar professed, nor Martiall man, yet a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
of learning; and being one of the <hi>Trained Band,</hi> to guard <hi>CA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MERAM
REGIS,</hi> alwaies prest without your Imprest money, to
fight, if occasion be presented, in defence of your Majesties person, of
the Realme, of that Faith and Religion, whereof you, under God, are
entituled The sole <hi>Defender:</hi> yea, even to lay downe his dearest life:
For according to my fathers <hi>Imprese, Pro Christo &amp; Patria, dulce
periculum:</hi> Which I desire of God, may be my last <hi>Cygnean song.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>However, The Lord of Hosts fight for you: The God of <hi>Iacob</hi>
protect you: The King of Kings preserve your most excellent Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie
<pb facs="11"/>
in health and safety of soule and body, from all your enemies, spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
and temporall, Foraine and Domestique. The same IEHOVAH
preserve you from all Warres, Disasters and Diseases; and in the end,
he give you one Coelestiall <hi>Crowne,</hi> for your <hi>three Terrestriall.</hi> And
let not him prosper or thrive that will not eft-soones say and pray▪
<hi>LET THE KING LIVE:</hi> yea and I adde,</p>
   <l>Methushelahs life the King of Heaven <hi>Him</hi> lend,</l>
   <l>Vpon <hi>Whose</hi> life, Millions of Lives depend.</l>
   <p>To conclude these illiterate Lines: The English Translatour of this
<hi>Booke</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>my deare Father) <hi>now an old man, full of yeeres,</hi> and living still
in your Mediterranean City <hi>Coventry,</hi> (named in former times <hi>CA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MERA
PRINCIPIS</hi>) farre remote from Court, could not
himselfe present this last labour of his unto your Highnesse hands, but
hath left it unto me so to doe. Deigne therefore my Liege Lord, and
deare Soveraigne, with my Fathers loyalty and mine prostrated, your
benigne Aspect hereunto and gracious Protection thereof, though
from the unworthy hand of him (who thrice humbly beggeth par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
for his boldnesse)</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties meanest,
yet most loyall Subiect,
HENRY HOLLAND.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>