<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118933_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14227</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24542</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118933</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvver to a challenge made by a Iesuite in Ireland : Wherein the iudgement of antiquity in the points questioned is truely delivered, and the noveltie of the now romish doctrine plainly discovered. By Iames Vssher Bishop of Meath</title>
                 <author>Ussher, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Ireland--Dublin</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>—Irish Stock.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stationers’ Society, Dublin</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 527, 9 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is now about six yeeres (as I gather by the reckoning laid downe in the <hi>25<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
      </hi> page of this booke) since this following Challenge was brought unto me from a Iesuite; and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that generall Answer, which now serveth to make up the first chapter only of this present worke. The particular points, which were by him but barely named, I meddled not withall at that time: conceiving it to be his part (as in the <hi>34<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
      </hi> page is touched) who sustained the person of the <hi>Assailant,</hi> to bring forth his armes and give the first onset, and mine, as the <hi>Defendant,</hi> to repell his encounter afterwards. Only I then collected certaine materials out of the Scriptures and writings of the Fathers, which I meant to make use of for a second conflict, whensoever this
<pb facs="8"/>
Challenger should be pleased to descend to the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dling of the particular articles by him proposed; the truth of euery of which he had taken upon him to prove, by the <hi>expresse testimonies of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the primitiue Church,</hi> as also by <hi>good and certaine grounds out of the sacred Scriptures, if the Fathers authoritie would not suffice.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thus this matter lay dead for diuers yeeres to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: and so would still have done, but that some of high place in both Kingdomes, having beene pleased to thinke farre better of that little which I had done than the thing deserved, advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed me to goe forward, and to deliver the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Antiquitie touching those particular points in controversie, wherein the Challenger was so confident that the whole current of the Doctors, Pastors and Fathers of the Primitiue Church did mainly run on his side. Hereupon I gathered my scattered notes together, and as the multitude of my imployments would give mee leave, now entred into the handling of one point and then of another: treating of each, either more briefly or more largely, as the opportunitie of my present leisure would give me leave. And so at last, after many interruptions, I have made up in such manner as thou seest, a kinde of a <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinall
<pb facs="8"/>
History</hi> of those seuerall points, which the Iesuite culled out, as speciall instances of the consonancie of the doctrine now maintained in the Church of Rome, with the perpetuall and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant iudgement of all Antiquitie.</p>
   <p>The doctrine that here I take upon me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, (what different opinions soever I relate of others) is that which by publike authoritie is professed in the Church of England, and compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in the booke of <hi>Articles</hi> agreed upon in the Synod held at <hi>LONDON</hi> in the yeere <hi>1562.</hi> concerning which I dare be bold to challenge our Challenger and all his complices, that they shall never be able to prove, that there is either any one article of Religion disallowed therein, which <hi>the Saints and Fathers of the Primitive Church did generally hold to be true,</hi> (I use the words of my challenging Iesuit) or any one point of doctrine <hi>allowed,</hi> which by those Saints and Fathers was generally held to be <hi>untrue.</hi> As for the testimonies of the Authors which I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage, I have beene carefull to set downe in the margent their owne words in their owne language (such places of the <hi>Greeke</hi> Doctors only excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whereof the originall text could not be had) as well for the better satisfaction of the Readers (who either cannot come by that variety of
<pb facs="9"/>
bookes, whereof use is here made, or will not take the paines to enter into a curious search of every particular allegation) as for the preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of those trifling quarrels that are commonly made against translations. for if it fall out, that word be not everie where precisely rendred by word (as who would tie himselfe to such a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danticall observation?) none but an idle cavil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler can obiect, that this was done with any pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to corrupt the meaning of the Author; whose words he seeth laid downe before his eies, to the end he may the better judge of the translation and rectifie it where there is cause.</p>
   <p>Againe, because it is a thing very materiall in the historicall handling of controversies, both to understand the Times wherein the severall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors lived, and likewise what bookes be truly or falsly ascribed to each of them: for some direction of the Reader in the first, I have annexed at the end of this booke, a <hi>Chronologicall Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue</hi> of the Authors cited therein (wherein such as have no number of yeeres affixed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, are thereby signified to be <hi>Incerti tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi>; their age being not found by me, upon this sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den search, to be noted by any:) and for the second, I have seldome neglected in the worke it selfe, whensoever a doubtfull or supposititious writing
<pb facs="9"/>
was alleaged, to give some intimation whereby it might be discerned that it was not esteemed to be the booke of that Author, unto whom it was inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled. The exact discussion as well of the Authors Times, as of the Censures of their workes, I refer to my <hi>Theological Bibliotheque:</hi> if God here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after shall lend me life and leasure, to make up that worke, for the use of those that meane to give themselves to that Noble study of the doctrine and rites of the ancient Church.</p>
   <p>In the meane time I commit this booke to thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable censure, and thy selfe to Gods gracious direction: earnestly advising thee, that whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver other studies thou intermittest, the carefull and conscionable reading of Gods booke may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be neglected by thee. for whatsoever becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of our disputes touching other antiquities or novelties: thou maiest stand assured, that thou shalt there finde so much by Gods blessing, as shall be <hi>able to make thee wise unto salvation,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>2 Tim. 3.15.</hi>
      </note> and <hi>to build thee up,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Acts 20.32.</hi>
      </note> and <hi>to give thee an inheritance among all them that are sanctified.</hi> Which next under Gods glory, is the utmost thing (I know) that thou aimest at: and for the attaining whereunto I heartily wish,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Coloss. 3.16</hi>
      </note> that the <hi>word of Christ may dwell in thee richly, in all wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>