<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118569_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21157</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7511</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118569</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The analysis of chyrurgery : being the theorique and practique part thereof. Briefly composed for the benefit of all those who desire the knowledge of this worthy profession. By the paines and industry of Ed: Edwards Doctor in Physicke</title>
                 <author>Edwards, Edward, doctor in physick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 110, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="1" facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, I doe not write to fill thy fancies with fables or fruitlesse lines to fill papers, but I present unto thee a fruitfull garden full of comfortable flowers. I consider we that live in this iron age, (where so much impiety o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwhelmeth the world, being so full fraught with an inundant deluge, or overwhelming floud of malice and disdaine) that men goe to hard edge one with another, must not care for the reproachfull taunts of envious snarlers, which wicked impes in these our dayes, swarme so abundantly, that few professions are free of such wretches, whose like informer ages was never seene; with such diabolicall devices, as impudent boasting, disdainfull mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, complainers, false accusers, dissembling hypocrites, being part of the errours of that brood of sycophants of this age; which declare their base low prized conceits, ever shewing themselves squint eyed in all good things; who out of malitious, poysoned, and cankered disdaine, seeke ever to abuse such as meane well: for who is more wicked than those which oppose themselves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst vertue, finding fault with others, yet doe no good them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves? like the dog in the manger, which will neither eate hay himselfe, nor suffer the horse to eate: but I wish all such as seeke the advancement of Gods glory, and their Countries good, neuer to be dismayed of such spitefull wretches. If the heathen held
<pb n="2" facs="5"/> it odious to conceale any thing that might either preserve health, or cure diseases; then how vile may we account those, that make shew to be religious Christians, to omit it, nay, not onely so, but doe use all their endeavours to hinder such as desire to performe it. A lover of the truth ought to hide nothing secret, that hee hath found out for health, saith <hi>Hippo,</hi> and <hi>Galen, vide Gal. de Compos.</hi> but to reveale it to Gods glory, and the good of the publike weale: wherefore forasmuch as every man is bound by the lawes of God and nature, to live under the title of some ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest and godly calling, and therein to endeavour himselfe to the uttermost of his power, so farre forth as God shall enable him, wherein he must above all, remember that he study and labour to advance in all his attempts and actions, first the glory of God, and then the good of his Country and Common-weale, which du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is not performed by such as do omit, either to reveale, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise leave behinde them in writing, such secrets as God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed upon them, for the advancement of his glory, and to leave it to posterity, but the envions sect I thinke are drenched in the forgetfull hellish lake of frozen oblivion, out of whose peevish braines no good can be expected, and small comfort had, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a scoffe or a frumpe. I speake it with griefe of conscience, to thinke that there should bee such a frozen hearted crew of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse caitiffes, infected with that incurable poyson, unworthy the name of Christians, having their conscience (if any) seared up with a hot yron, that nothing can open it, not considering that he which hath the meanes, and doth not cherish, shall with the hider of his talent perish: these neither love God in his mercy, nor fear him in his justice, therefore not excusable in the day of venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, odious to God and christian charity, who with restlesse rage doe manifest their godlesse mindes, holding nothing tollerable, but what they like and allow. In what they loathe, every mite is made a monster, every trifle a trespasse, and every Gnat a Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mell; so untunable is it to their ugly eares. I thinke these persons lovingly linke in league with the devill, having obstinate wils, and barren fruitlesse hearts, sencelesse, except in things that feed their filthy fancies, onely they swell with intollerable pride and envy; they live Foxe-like, these participate not with that worthy renowned Knight, Sir <hi>Philip Sidney,</hi> who said, love
<pb n="3" facs="5"/> them that doe some good, because there be many that doe none at all: let such take heed that they perïsh not with such as hide their talent, therefore according to my bounden duty herein (with that poore myte which God hath indued me withall) I doe here leaue some fruits of my labours to posterity. Wee reade that the poore Widdowes myte, was more accepted because she gave all, then the great gifts that were given by the mighty ones out of their superfluities. <hi>Alexander</hi> accepted a cup of cold water at the hands of a begger, so doe I bestow these rude lines, as a token of my love, not ambitiously for vaine glory, or as one that goeth about to instruct the learned, but the ignorant, nor to impaire the credit of any good meaning professor of this worthy faculty, for (God knoweth) I love and reverence them, and although this worke be to me very tedious and toylesome in this mine old age, yet will I not deny the importunate request of my faithfull loving friends in satisfying their desire herein. Furthermore for my part, I hold it neither fit nor lawfull for every ignorant person that practiseth Chirurgery, being unskilfull in that deep thrise worthy learned faculty of Physicke, to undertake, or once offer to give inward medicines to any Patient, without the counsell of the learned Physitian: let them consider how pretious the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is on which they worke, <hi>(viz.</hi> the body of man) being the image of God: yet many of these homicides (chiefly in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try) having neither feare of God, learning, art, nor honesty, doe daily like brazen faced monsters, boldly adventure on all the parts of physicke, wherein they have no skill, to the great disbonour of God, the utter ruine and spoyle of their unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Patients, and infamy to both these worthy faculties, being as unfit thereto, as the Asse to play on the Harpe: which carelesse crue of abusers deserve sharpe punishment, as deceitfull male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors and murtherers. A most lamentable thing that it should be suffered: and here for the avoyding of tedious circumstances, I doe abreviate my speeches, discoursing no further, till a more fit opportunity be offered.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Vale in Christo.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>