<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT REVE∣rend Father in God, ARTHVR, Lord Bishop of BATH and WELLES, Vice chancel∣lour of the Vniversitie of Oxford, and Warden of New Colledge, IOHN TERRY wisheth all in∣crease of that Glory and Ver∣tue, wherevnto you are called by our most glo∣rious &amp; holy Lord. 2. Pet. 1. 2.</title>
           <author>Terry, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118354_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13629</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23912</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118354</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT REVE∣rend Father in God, ARTHVR, Lord Bishop of BATH and WELLES, Vice chancel∣lour of the Vniversitie of Oxford, and Warden of New Colledge, IOHN TERRY wisheth all in∣crease of that Glory and Ver∣tue, wherevnto you are called by our most glo∣rious &amp; holy Lord. 2. Pet. 1. 2.</title>
                 <author>Terry, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The reasonablenesse of wise and holy truth: and the absurditie of foolish and wicked errour</title>
                 <author>Terry, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 <publisher>Lichfield, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wrench, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 38, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in God, ARTHVR, Lord Bishop of BATH and WELLES, Vice chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of the Vniversitie of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and Warden of <hi>New Colledge,</hi> IOHN TERRY wisheth all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of that Glory and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, wherevnto you are <hi>called by our most glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious &amp; holy Lord.</hi> 2. Pet. 1. 2.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y duety bindeth me (right Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and my very Good Lord) to offer vp to God for you the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of thankesgiuing and prayer. Some of the Heathen of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred sacrifice to the sunne rising for benefits to come: and other to the Sunne setting for such as were already receaued. VVherefore it being a great shame for a Christian to be out gone in any good dutie by an Heathen, I cannot but offer vp to our most bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Sauiour Christ the true Sonne of righteousnesse, the sacrifice of thanksgiuing: first, for causing such a bright starre as your Lordship is to appeare aboue our Horizon in the west: and secondly for causing you to set with leauing much good to that Colledge, whereof my selfe was once a member. And how can I also but
<pb facs="3"/> offer vp prayer to God; first, that the fresh memorie of your renowned learning and religious life may instill such a sweet influence of celestiall grace into the hearts of all the members of that societie, that they may bee effectually stirred vp to walke in your waies, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vote themselues by your example to the publike good: as secondly I am to beseech him that walketh in the midst of the seauen golden Candlesticks, and holdeth the starres in his right hand, that he would hold &amp; vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold you long to his owne glory, and to the edification and comfort of his people, among whom hee hath now placed you to hold out the word of life. And thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending you to God the Father of light, and to the word of his grace the most worthie instrument thereof, with all humble thanks vnto your Lordship for your louing acceptance of this small paper present, I rest</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships in all Christian loue and dutie, JOHN TERRY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>