<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND MOST NOBLE LORD, ROBERT EARLE OF WARWICK, Lord RICH, Baron of LEEZE, &amp;c. My very good LORD, and most noble PATRON: Increase of Grace; Honor and Happinesse.</title>
           <author>Sym, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118072_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13280</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23584</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118072</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND MOST NOBLE LORD, ROBERT EARLE OF WARWICK, Lord RICH, Baron of LEEZE, &amp;c. My very good LORD, and most noble PATRON: Increase of Grace; Honor and Happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Sym, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lifes preservative against self-killing. Or, An useful treatise concerning life and self-murder : shewing the kindes, and meanes of them both: the excellency and preservation of the former: the evill, and prevention of the latter. Containing the resolution of manifold cases and questions concerning that subject; with plentifull variety of necessary and usefull observations, and practicall directions, needfull for all Christians. By John Sym minister of Leigh in Essex</title>
                 <author>Sym, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Dawlman (Dolman), Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawne, Luke.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>36, 326, 18 pages, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND MOST NOBLE <hi>LORD,</hi> ROBERT EARLE OF <hi>WARWICK,</hi> Lord RICH, Baron of LEEZE, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> My very good LORD, and most noble PATRON: Increase of <hi>Grace; Honor</hi> and <hi>Happinesse.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat Eminencie</hi> that is in a most <hi>excellent Maecenas,</hi> to supply the <hi>defects</hi> and <hi>mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi> of an obscure <hi>Author;</hi> and that <hi>Relation</hi> and <hi>obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> that a poore <hi>Clerk</hi> may have to a most
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>noble, worthie,</hi> and <hi>respective Patron,</hi> hath made me presume to make choise of your <hi>noble Lordship</hi> for a <hi>Guardian</hi> of this my poore <hi>tractate:</hi> which is of a compounded <hi>Denomination,</hi> consisting of contrary <hi>ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients,</hi> of <hi>life,</hi> and <hi>death;</hi> of <hi>saving</hi> and <hi>kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling;</hi> by such reflecting acts of the <hi>doers</hi> upon themselves, as make the <hi>Agents</hi> and <hi>patients</hi> thereof to be the same <hi>individualls.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The <hi>discourse</hi> is of a mixt and various nature; and the theame of <hi>self-killing</hi> is the <hi>subject</hi> both of <hi>Divinity,</hi> and of <hi>humanity;</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> and of <hi>Law:</hi> the full handling whereof may be serviceable to the <hi>Kings Majestie,</hi> for preservation of the <hi>lives</hi> of his <hi>people,</hi> against the blowes and mortall wounds of a <hi>self-killing</hi> hand: and may be usefull for the publick good of the <hi>Church</hi> and of the <hi>Common wealth;</hi> both for the safety of the <hi>soules</hi> and <hi>bodies</hi> of their mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; and also, in point of <hi>Honour;</hi> that the <hi>government</hi> of so gracious a <hi>King,</hi> and the glory of so famous a <hi>Nation</hi> may not be ignominiously stayned, by <hi>self-murdring practises.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>In which <hi>respects,</hi> it was most requisite that I should <hi>dedicate</hi> the <hi>treatise</hi> of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to such a <hi>noble Guardian,</hi> as hath a most speciall care to uphold and advance both <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Iustice;</hi> the <hi>honour</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>kingdome;</hi> and the <hi>welfare</hi> both of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> in all the <hi>members</hi> of the same, as your <hi>Honourable Lordship</hi> alwaies hath, in the places of your imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and residence: which, in cognizance of us in the <hi>Ministery,</hi> is specially apparent, by your <hi>noble</hi> and <hi>pious</hi> care of providing <hi>able, painefull,</hi> and <hi>godly Ministers</hi> to the Churches under your speciall <hi>Patronage,</hi> bestowing your Church-livings, both free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and to the <hi>fittest</hi> and <hi>best</hi> deserving that you can finde for those places; and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing and furthering the <hi>Clergie,</hi> what you can, in all godly and legall courses; whereby multitudes of <hi>soules</hi> being saved, and the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> (under our <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne</hi> the <hi>King</hi>) advanced and supported in the <hi>Honour</hi> of her <hi>Ministery,</hi> all have cause to praise <hi>God,</hi> and to pray to <hi>God</hi> for your <hi>Lordship,</hi> and for your <hi>noble Family,</hi> the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
<pb facs="4"/>instruments of so much divine and publick good; whereof many blessed <hi>soules</hi> in <hi>heaven</hi> (saved by that meanes) are witnesses before God, to your eternall praise, honour and comfort, with your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <hi>progenitors,</hi> of that practise.</p>
   <p>And I confesse, it is the dutie specially of us of the <hi>Ministery</hi> to write your most <hi>Illustrious name,</hi> and highest <hi>Commendations</hi> with the poynt of a <hi>Dyamond,</hi> in letters of <hi>Gold,</hi> upon the most durable <hi>pillars</hi> of <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity;</hi> and ever to celebrate your due <hi>praise,</hi> both, for honour of your <hi>noble</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servings, and also for vertuous and pious <hi>example</hi> and incouragement to all <hi>posterity,</hi> and <hi>noble Peeres,</hi> in that poynt specially of upholding and advancing true <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>piety,</hi> both in and by that carefull and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scionable course of bestowing your <hi>Church-livings,</hi> and regarding of your <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters;</hi> and also, by your constant <hi>profession</hi> of the <hi>truth;</hi> and, according to the same, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessedly worshipping the true <hi>God;</hi> thereby publickly obliging your selfe to such <hi>holines</hi> of heart and conversation in <hi>walking with
<pb facs="4"/>God,</hi> according to the rules of true <hi>Religion;</hi> as may give your <hi>Lordship</hi> sound and grounded <hi>hope</hi> of eternall life, and may verifie in you the realitie of that most Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian and <hi>heroick motto,</hi>
      <q>Garde ta foy.</q>
   </p>
   <p>In a word, <hi>Divine Providence,</hi> and <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens favour</hi> hath made your <hi>Lordship Rich;</hi> not onely by <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>name,</hi> but also in <hi>honor</hi> and manifold <hi>blessings</hi> upon you, and in much good done by your meanes, whereby you stand bound to be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly thankfull to <hi>God;</hi> and to be ever mindfull that your <hi>Eminency</hi> objects your <hi>Lordship</hi> to the worlds prying <hi>observation,</hi> and to mens rigid <hi>censure,</hi> which requires your more carefull circumspection in your whole conversation, that you may be as farre distant from all <hi>ignoble vices,</hi> and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full courses, (which staines and abases <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>greatnesse</hi>) and as <hi>Illustrious</hi> in all <hi>vertues,</hi> and commendable <hi>actions,</hi> as your <hi>noble condition</hi> is elevated above the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ranck of men; which conciliates and
<pb facs="5"/>procures <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>comfort</hi> of a higher <hi>nature;</hi> and of more lasting <hi>continuance,</hi> than that which can be had from, or by <hi>Titles,</hi> and <hi>humane dignities,</hi> or from sycophan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing humoring and flattering, that so you may attaine to eternall glory and happines after this short life ended.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Most noble Lord,</hi> I commed this <hi>treatise</hi> to you, not onely that you may put credit and respect upon it, for publick favour and entertainment, and to give encouragement to the <hi>Author:</hi> but also, with all <hi>observancie,</hi> to subject it to your <hi>judicious censure;</hi> and my selfe to the <hi>service</hi> of your <hi>Honour</hi> and noble <hi>Family,</hi> for the furtherance of the <hi>good</hi> and <hi>salvation</hi> of you and yours, by the dayly <hi>prayers,</hi> and faithfull labours of him that ever remaines</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From your Lo<seg rend="sup">ps.</seg> Leigh in Essex.</dateline>
      <signed>Your Lordships devoted, faithfull and obsequious servant in Christ, <hi>Iohn Sym.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>