<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ DIVERS &amp; SVNDRYE GOOD
Instructions &amp; Rules for all such as are the
true Practisers of Phisick and Chirurgerie, which are
very meete and conuenient to be obserued and knowne
vnto them, And also concerning Bloud-letting, Pur∣ging,
and of the vse and commoditie that often times
commeth thereof.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118082_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13300</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23606</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118082</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ DIVERS &amp; SVNDRYE GOOD
Instructions &amp; Rules for all such as are the
true Practisers of Phisick and Chirurgerie, which are
very meete and conuenient to be obserued and knowne
vnto them, And also concerning Bloud-letting, Pur∣ging,
and of the vse and commoditie that often times
commeth thereof.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A rich store-house or treasury for the diseased : Wherein, are many approued medicines for diuers and sundry diseases, which haue been long hidden, and not come to light before this time. Now set foorth for the great benefit and comfort of the poorer sort of people that are not of abilitie to go to the physitions. By A.T</title>
                 <author>A. T., practitioner in physicke</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 <publisher>Blower (Blore), Ralph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 66 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>❧ DIVERS &amp; SVNDRYE GOOD
Instructions &amp; Rules for all such as are the
true Practisers of Phisick and Chirurgerie, which are
very meete and conuenient to be obserued and knowne
vnto them, And also concerning Bloud-letting, Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging,
and of the vse and commoditie that often times
commeth thereof.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR AS MVCH</hi> as Health is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable
and pleasant to all men, since
that all men do continually wish, and
pray eyther for the restitution or cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance
of the same, and how that
it is the propertie of nature, onely to
fighte and striue against diseases,
and also that the Phisition is but the
minister and seruant of nature, either
to apply such thinges to her, as may be vsed to distroy the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease
withall, or els by taking away the greatest parte of the
same matter which causeth and mainteyneth the sickenes,
and therefore it is very meete &amp; necessarie for euery Phisition,
before such time as he doe minister any thinge at all to the sick
person, diligentlie to learne, and to search out perfectly the
principall cause of the disease, in the which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>be be ignorant,
it is more by good fortune, then by any cunning or skill, that he
doe euer cure any disease at all. For how is it possible to helpe
nature, with that which she hath neede of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> except it be first
knowne, what she needeth, which none can knowe, except the
cause of the disease be first manifestly knowne vnto him, soe y<seg rend="sup">•</seg>
he may minister thinges directly, contrary to the cause of the
same disease. And therefore I doe most greatelye lamente
<pb facs="4"/>
the ignorance of the common sort of People, who for the moste
parte are perswaded, that one medicine is sufficient for one
disease, &amp; not regarding that one disease may come of sundrye
causes, and therefore it doth necessarilie require diuers medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines,
as for example, weaknes of the stomacke (that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
digest well, or that it hath no good Appetite) is one disease,
which neuerthelesse may come a dozen sundrie waies at the
least. Therefore the cure of it cannot be alwaies with one me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine,
As if weakenes of the stomacke, doe come of a weake
distempure of it selfe onely, then it must of necessitie be made
hotte by some meanes, but if heate be the cause of weakenes,
then it must needes be cooled, Likewise you must moisten dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
and drye moisture, But if the weakenes doe come of some
superfluous humour that both abound, which hath flowed into
the stomacke, or hath been there ingendred, then must that ill
humour, of necessitie be purged out, eyther by a vomite, or els
a purgation with a meeke medicine for it, And if it be fleame,
then with a medicine that expelleth sleame, But if choller be
abounding there: then must it be such a medicine as doth purg
choller, And likewise for melancholy, a meete Purgation
must be vsed to expell the humour, But if the imbecillitie of the
stomacke, be caused by a distillation and Rewme, that falleth
out of the head into it, then is the cure to be remedied in y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> head,
and not in the stomacke, Likewise if distempure of the liuer
or spleene, doe weaken the stomacke, then the cure consisteth
in the healing of those members, and not in ministring of any
thinge for the stomacke.</p>
   <p>Therefore let no man thinke it sufficient for the Phisition,
if he knowe that a man hath such a disease, as the Ague, the
Collick, the Flix, or such other like &amp;c. that then hee maye
straighte way (if he be skillfull) minister a medicine meet for
it▪ Noe not foe, but he must first search by all meanes possible,
the very cause it selfe of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> disease, which many ignorant Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
doe perswade themselues, that a skilfull Phisition may doe
<pb facs="4"/>
in all diseases, by the onely sight &amp; inspection of the <hi>Vrine,</hi> But
alas they are altogether deceiued, and for to come to y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg
of the cause of some inward disease, the <hi>Vrine</hi> profiteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
at all, for in moste inwarde diseases of the bodye, there
ought as greate a regard to be had and taken to the <hi>Pulses,</hi>
and to the dispositions &amp; state of the <hi>Braine,</hi> of him that is sick,
as there should be had of the <hi>Vrine.</hi> Also the <hi>Egestions, Sweat,
Spettle,</hi> and other <hi>Excrements,</hi> are not to be neglegted, in soe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much,
that at some time they do declare y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> cause of the disease,
and the state thereof, when the <hi>Vrine</hi> doeth not shewe any
thinge at all.</p>
   <p>Likewise for example, in a <hi>Plurisie,</hi> or an inflamation of the
<hi>Lunges,</hi> or in a <hi>Squinancie,</hi> or such like, there is more to be
knowne by <hi>Spettle,</hi> then there is by <hi>Vrine.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Also in a <hi>Laske,</hi> or a bloudye <hi>Flixe,</hi> or in a <hi>Collicke,</hi> or <hi>Ili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ake,</hi>
there is more certaintie of Iudgment, to be geuen by <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestion</hi>
or <hi>Ordure,</hi> then there is by <hi>Vrine:</hi> Which thinges,
those that are not altogether addicted to their owne fantasies,
may easely by good reason, be perswaded to credite, for <hi>Vrine</hi>
is nothing else, but the watrie and washie parte of the bloude,
for it is seperated from bloud in the <hi>Liuer,</hi> and sucked from
thence into the <hi>Raines,</hi> from whence it distilleth downe into y<seg rend="sup">•</seg>
      <hi>Bladder,</hi> and soe passeth foorth. Seeing therefore that <hi>Vrine</hi>
is the excrement that is seperated from y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> bloud: there is good
cause why it should shew the state of the <hi>Liuer,</hi> &amp; of the <hi>Bloud,</hi>
in all partes of the body, and it can also declare the state of all
such members as it passeth by, as of the <hi>Raines,</hi> the <hi>Bladder,</hi>
and such like.</p>
   <p>But certainely in other diseases that be out of the <hi>Vaines,</hi> &amp;
be distant from the places, by which the <hi>Vrine</hi> passeth, there is
no certaine iudgment to be geuen by the <hi>Vrine</hi> vnlesse the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemencie
of the disease hath infected the <hi>bloud</hi> or the <hi>Liuer</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
some sort, Neuertheles such is y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> ignorāce of many people,
that they thinke him woorthye of noe estimation in Phisicke,
<pb facs="5"/>
which cannot at the first sighte of the <hi>Vrine</hi> (although it hath
been carried xx. Miles) tel whether it be the water of a man
or a woman, and how the disease greeueth the patient better
then himselfe, &amp; also whether he shall liue or dye, what disease
soeuer it be, which thinges vndoubtedly in diuers diseases are
impossible to be knowne by the onely sight and inspection of
the <hi>Vrine.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Therefore it is very necessarie for him that will minister
Phisicke, duly and rightfully to obserue these 4. rules follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
(That is to say) first to see the sick Person, &amp; to conferre
with him or her, which soeuer it be, for there is none that can
soe well declare any griefe (whatsoeuer it be) as he can that is
troubled therewith. Secondly to view and feele the Pulses,
and to obserue well the state of them. Thirdlye to view very
diligently all the excrements, not onely the vrine, but also the
<hi>Spettle, Sweat</hi> and <hi>Ordure.</hi> Fourethlie and last of all, to haue
a respect to the place where the griefe is, and to consider well
the accidents that doe arise thereof, not omitting to know the
former diet and trade of life, which the sicke person hath vsed,
These thinges then being diligentlie &amp; seuerally marked, the
Phisition may more certainly learne the chiefest cause of the
disease, the strength thereof, and to what ende it will come
vnto, then by seeing the <hi>Vrine</hi> onely, and also by what meanes
he may minister a meete medicine for it, whereby the sick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
may soone finde ease, and purchase vnto himselfe excea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
greate fame.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thus</hi> haue I partely declared, what thinges oughte to be
knowne of euery Phisition, that thereby he might withdraw, &amp;
take awaye the fonde and foolish opinion, that a greate
number of people do deeme to be true, that is, that the sight of
the <hi>Vrine</hi> is sufficient ynough, for a cunning Phisitiō, perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
to know the disease of the sicke, and the true cause thereof,
&amp; to minister apt medicines for it. And now I cease to speake
any more hereof, but I will as briefly as I may entreate som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
of the vse and benefit that doth arise &amp; come of <hi>Purging,</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
and <hi>Bloud-letting,</hi> &amp; I would wish all those that do practise
the same, to be carefull thereof.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Note</hi> also that if the bodye of a manne, doe abound with
humours, which are ready to oppresse nature, then whether
there be any sicknes in the body present, by meanes of them, or
if there be but daunger of sicknes, those humours must be eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuat
out of the bodie, eyther by <hi>Bloud-letting, Purging, vomit,
Sweating Bathes,</hi> or else by some other kind of euacuation.
But I will speake here onely of euacuation by <hi>Bloud-letting</hi>
and <hi>Purging,</hi> and first of all of <hi>Bloudletting.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>There be diuers thinges to be considered of, before <hi>Bloud-letting,</hi>
as the age of the patient, the complexion, the time of
the yeare, the region, the custome, the strength, and the vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie
of the disease.</p>
   <p>The age must be considered, because Children vnder 14.
yeares of age, and old folke may not be let <hi>bloud,</hi> vnlesse great
necessitie require it.</p>
   <p>The complexion is to be noted, because a hote complexion
hath large vaines, and aboundeth with much <hi>bloud,</hi> and they
may therefore forbeare a good quantitie of <hi>bloud;</hi> But colde
complexions haue narrow vaines and litle <hi>bloud,</hi> and therfore
theire euacuation must be small.</p>
   <p>The time of the yeare must be very well marked, that the
weather be not too hote nor too colde, and therefore the spring
time is the most aptest time for <hi>bloud-letting,</hi> because that
then it is temperate.</p>
   <p>The Region and Cuntrey, is to be spoken of, because it is
to be noted, that if the Region be very hote, or else very colde,
it is not good to let <hi>bloud,</hi> but a temperate Region is moste
meetest of all for it.</p>
   <p>Custome is not to be neglected, for thereby we may knowe
that they that haue bene accustomed to <hi>bleede,</hi> may better
suffer <hi>bloud-letting,</hi> then those that were neuer letten <hi>bloud</hi>
at any time before.</p>
   <p>The strength of the Person must be regarded, for if there be
<pb facs="6"/>
greate weakenes, then is it very daungerouse to let <hi>bloude</hi> at
all, except great necessitie compelleth.</p>
   <p>Also the vehemencie of the disease is worthie to be marked:
for if it be a vehemente disease, then you must let <hi>bloud</hi> foorth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with,
if the former circumstances will permit it.</p>
   <p>These thinges being considered, if they will permit <hi>bloud-letting,</hi>
and if it be in a needefull cause, then it shalbe very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie
to knowe in what signe the Moone is in, for you muste
take heed that she be not in the signe that gouerneth that mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
wherein you intend to open the vaine, &amp; also to forsee that
shee be in such a signe, as is good to let <hi>bloude</hi> in.</p>
   <p>The vses and commodities of <hi>bloud-letting,</hi> are these that
are here expressed.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>First,</hi> This is a generall rule, that <hi>bloud-letting</hi> is a very
good remedie for all diseases that be engendred of aboundance
flowing or eruption of <hi>bloud,</hi> as be chieflie the Feuers called
<hi>Sinochy.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Also the <hi>Phrenesie, Squinancie, Plurisie, Peripnewmony,
Opthalmie,</hi> and against all inflamatious, and impostumatiōs
engendred of <hi>bloude</hi> in the <hi>Lyuer,</hi> the <hi>Spleene,</hi> the <hi>Raines,</hi> the
<hi>Wombe,</hi> the <hi>Share,</hi> the <hi>Arme-holes,</hi> the <hi>Armes,</hi> the <hi>Legges:</hi>
and to conclude, in all inwarde or outwarde partes, wheresoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
the inflamation bee: <hi>bloud-letting</hi> is good for it, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
it be now present; or that there be any danger, that it wil
shortely engender.</p>
   <p>Also <hi>Bloud-letting</hi> is good in <hi>Feuers,</hi> whether they be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall
or intermittent, insomuch that the obstructions &amp; stop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinges
of the <hi>Vaines,</hi> be caused of immoderate repletion of the
humoures.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Note</hi> also that <hi>Bloud-letting</hi> doth emptie aud euacuat from
the bodie, all humours alike, as well the good as the bad.</p>
   <p>And therefore it is chieflie to be vsed, when there is to great
an ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>dance of <hi>bloude</hi> in the bodie &amp; other humours, which
doe straine the <hi>vaines,</hi> and that there is greate daunger &amp; ieo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardie
in breaking of some <hi>vaines,</hi> or the brusing out of some
<pb facs="6"/>
fluxe of <hi>bloude,</hi> or of choking, and to extinguish naturall heate.
And therefore in such cases, you must let <hi>bloud</hi> with all spead,
although the sicknes be not already present.</p>
   <p>For by letting of <hi>bloud</hi> in due season, the superfluous full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
of the <hi>vaines,</hi> is brought into a meane state againe, and the
paines that came of the fulnes and stretching of the vessels, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eased:
And the heauines that was felte in the bodie, is cleane
taken away, and the bodie is lightened, and made more quick
and nimble, to doe all such actions as nature hath ordeyned it
to doe. Also it causeth nature, to haue a larger scope, &amp; a free
passage by opening &amp; emptying of the straight waies &amp; passa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
of the <hi>vaines</hi> and <hi>Arteries.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Last of all, if it be done in time, it preuenteth diuers and
sundrie diseases, into which the bodie was both apt and readie
to haue fallen into.</p>
   <p>Many more commodities might here be rehearsed as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<hi>bloud-letting,</hi> which is done when necessitie requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth,
and as it ought to be done, but to conclude (omitting all
other) Note this for a generall rule, that <hi>bloud-letting</hi> is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
good against all kinde of diseases, which be caused and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred
of <hi>bloude,</hi> and not onely when the diseases are present,
but also it is good letting of <hi>bloude,</hi> to preuent any such disea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,
if they be forseene or feared, alwaies regarding that there
be none of these impediments aforesaid, which doe prohibite &amp;
forbid <hi>bloud-letting,</hi> except it be in great necessitie and extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie,
for then as the common prouerbe is, <hi>Necessitas non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet
legem,</hi> that is: Necessitie hath noe lawe.</p>
   <p>Heere would I leaue of to speake of <hi>bloud-letting,</hi> but that
there commeth into my minde, the common opinion of the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant
people, which doe certeinly beleeue, that if any person
be let <hi>Bloud</hi> one yeare, y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> he must likewise be let <hi>bloude</hi> euery
yeare, or els he is in (I cannot tell) how great danger, which
fond opinion of theires (whence soeuer it sprong at the first) is
noe more like to be true, then I shoulde say, when a man hath
a greate wounde by chaunce, in any part of his body, whereby
<pb facs="7"/>
he loseth much <hi>bloud,</hi> and that after it is healed, he must of
necessitie haue the like wounde againe the next yeare, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide
as much <hi>bloud,</hi> or els he is in daunger of greate sicknes
or of death, Which opinion, if I my selfe did affirme it to be
true (although it be most false) yet I might vse the like reasō
and aucthoritie to defende it, that the common people doe vse
for theires: for they can say nothing if they be asked why they
thinke soe, bnt that they haue heard many say soe, Therefore
I would wish that noe man should credite any longer this fond
and foolish opinion, being most false, vnlesse he can shewe good
reason for it, which I ame very well assured of, noe man can
doe. Mary this I thinke, that like as <hi>bloud-letting</hi> is not good
against all diseases, soe also it is not good in all persons, but
onely in those that will be content to vse afterward a moderate
and conuenient diet.</p>
   <p>Those therefore that doe abound with <hi>bloud,</hi> and will be let
<hi>bloud</hi> to preserue themselues, from the daunger of any disease,
which is like shortely to ensue and molest them, They must for
a long time after, be content to vse a moderat and conuenient
diet, For those that be vntemperat &amp; gluttonous in meates, or
are great drinkers, &amp; wine-bibbers, they doe not onely receiue
no commoditie at all by <hi>bloud-letting:</hi> but also often times,
they catch more hurt by it, then they should haue had without
it, for in 3. or 4. daies space after, they fill &amp; stuffe themselues
with more raw iuices and humours (by meanes of vnmeasu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surable
diet) then they had before, and often times they do dye
through connulcion.</p>
   <p>And therefore note that there is such force and vertue in a
moderate diet, to eschue and decline diseases, that without the
due obseruation of it, <hi>bloud-letting</hi> is to noe purpose at all.
And therefore if the common saying of the people be true in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
body, that they must of necessitie be let <hi>bloud</hi> often, it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
true, but it is in such as keepe an immoderat diet, present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
after <hi>Bloud-letting,</hi> and therefore I do aduertise all men,
to beware of excesse in eating &amp; drinking after <hi>bloud-letting.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>Note</hi> also y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> after <hi>bloud-letting,</hi> none ought to walke very
fast, or to runne, or to vse any vehement exexcise, but let him
be quiet and rest himselfe, vntill such time as his spirites shall
be wel refreshed and quieted againe.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Note</hi> also, that no person being let <hi>blood,</hi> ought to sleepe
immediatly after <hi>bloud-letting,</hi> but let him keepe himselfe
both quiet and wakinge, and auoiding all contention and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise
of body and minde, and about two houres after lettinge
of <hi>bloud,</hi> there may a litle foode be taken, but let it be suc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
will make good iuice and nourish apace, and within 4. or 5.
houres after <hi>bloud-letting</hi> or some what afore, the patient may
be permitted to sleepe, soe that it be prouided for, &amp; taken heed
of, that he doe not turne himselfe vpon that Arme, where the
<hi>vaine</hi> was opened, and let him also take good heede that he do
not loosen the band, and soe let the <hi>bloud</hi> flowe out againe, and
let him afterwardes vse a sparing diet, dayly increasing it by
little and litle, vntill such time as he be come to his accustomed
or ordinarie diet againe.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>And</hi> note that the morning is the most meetest time of all for
<hi>bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letting,</hi>
when euery digestion is perfectly finished, &amp; the
superfluities and excrements of ech of them fully auoided out,
which thinges of necessitie must be foreseene, that they bee so,
Or at the least in a time of great extremitie, the next apt time
to let <hi>blood</hi> in, is when the stomacke is somewhat emptie, and
that is about sixe or eight houres after meate. <hi>Thus</hi> much I
haue entreated of as concerning <hi>blood-letting,</hi> and now I
am purposlie minded to speake somewhat of the vse and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities
that come of <hi>Purging.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>First</hi> it is to be vnderstood, that euery kinde of <hi>Purgation,</hi>
hath that secret vertue and propertie in it selfe, that when it is
receiued into a mans body, and prouoked to exercise the vertue
that it hath by naturall heate labouring to digest it, then doth
it draw vnto it all such humours, as it hath vertue and power
to <hi>Purge.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And therefore a <hi>Purgation</hi> is an euacuation of vicious and
<pb facs="8"/>
corrupt humours, which doe oftentimes trouble and molest y<seg rend="sup">•</seg>
body, but not of all corrupt and bad humours alike.</p>
   <p>For euery <hi>Purging</hi> medicine, doth drawe vnto it selfe, one
peculier and proper humour (that is) eyther <hi>Hegme</hi> or <hi>chol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi>
or else melancholie or watery humours.</p>
   <p>And therefore those persons that be perfectlie in health,
ought not to take a <hi>Purgation,</hi> since they doe not abound with
corrupt humours, wherefore in those, when the medicine fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>
no such superfluous humours as it hath vertue to drawe,
it consumeth and wasteth the <hi>bloud</hi> and the flesh. And for that
cause, whole folkes are not purged by <hi>purgations,</hi> but rather
consumed and wasted, for it is manyfest hereby, that <hi>Purgatiōs</hi>
be very daungerous to them that are in perfect health, which
thinge is testified also of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> in the 37. <hi>Aphorisme,</hi> of
his second booke, where he saieth after this sort, <hi>Qui corpore
bene se habent hos purgare periculosū est,</hi> (that is) it is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
purging of those that be in perfect health.</p>
   <p>Also because euery purging medicine hath vertue to drawe
one peculier homour, there is good heede and care to be taken,
that such a medicine be ministred as hath vertue to drawe out
the humour abounding, and none other, or else in stead of much
good, that of it selfe it would doe, if it were conueniently mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred:
it may contraryewise doe exceading great hurte, and
woorke many inconueniences to the body. And accordinge to
to the saying of <hi>Hipocrates</hi> in the last <hi>Aphorisme</hi> of his firste
book<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, in this maner. <hi>Si qualia oportet purgari purgentur, cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert,
et facile ferunt, si contra, difficulter,</hi> that is, yf such things
be purged as ought to be, it profiteth, and may easily be suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
but if it be contrarywise, it hurteth and may scarcely bee
borne. Therefore there ought diligent care and heed to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
in the receiuing of a <hi>purgation,</hi> that it be ministred by a
skilfull Phisition, that hath certainly found out what humour
it is that aboundeth. But alas the greatest number of the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
sort of people, do, hould an opinion that if they may haue
a medicine for a little money, which will poruoke them often
<pb facs="8"/>
to the stoole, what humour soeuer it be, and purgeth out, they
are safe ynough: howe be it, I would wish them hereafter al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
to haue in minde this saying of the most excellent Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition
<hi>Hipocrates</hi> in the xxxii. <hi>Aphorisme</hi> of the first booke,
<hi>Deiectiones non multitudine sunt estimandae, sed si talia deijci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur,
qualia conueniunt,</hi> that is: Egestions are not to bee
esteamed for their great quantitie, but if such bad humours be
purged out as they ought to be (that is) such vicious &amp; corrupt
humours as doe abound and bee superfluous in mans bodye,
then is the bodie quieted for a long time after, if it be dieted as
aforesaid.</p>
   <p>There be diuers thinges chiefly to be considered of by eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye
Phisition before such time as he doe minister any <hi>Purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
to the sicke person: as the qualitie and quantitie of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour,
the strength of him or her that is sicke, the age, the time
of the yeare, and lastly the disease.</p>
   <p>The qualitie of the homour is greatly to be considered, that
thereby he may perfectly knowe what kinde of humour is to be
euacuate, &amp; purged out, for it must be onely that which trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth
the bodie, with superfluous aboundance thereof.</p>
   <p>As if great aboundance of <hi>fleame</hi> doe molest and trouble the
bodie, then hee must of necessitie minister a medicine whiche
purgeth fleame, and so likewise for all other humours what so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
abounding in any part of the bodie.</p>
   <p>Also he that doth vndertake the ministring of any medicine,
ought to haue great respect to the strength of the sicke or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eased
person: for if he be very weake and feeble, there ought
no <hi>purgation</hi> at all to be ministred vnto him, because all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
of <hi>purgations</hi> doe both weaken nature &amp; diminish strength,
and the stronger the sicke person is, the more he is weakened
thereby. Let all men therefore beware of vehement &amp; strong
<hi>purgations,</hi> least they put their liues in hazard &amp; danger. By
the age of the Patient. the Phisition is put in minde that chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
and old men ought not to receiue any <hi>Purgations,</hi> except
maruailous great necessitie doe require it. The time of the
<pb facs="9"/>
yeare is not to be neglected, for there be some times of the yeare
wherein <hi>Purgations</hi> ought not to be ministred, as in Sommer,
and especially during the time of the <hi>Dogge daies,</hi> as they are
most commonly called, and also during all the time, that the
Sunne is in <hi>Leo,</hi> for then is nature burnt vp, and made soe
weake withall, that she is not able to suffer the force and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
of a <hi>Purgation,</hi> but the Spring time is the most meetest
and principalest time in all the yeare, for the taking of <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi>
because it is then temperate.</p>
   <p>Last of all, the Phisition ought diligently, to behould &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template
the disease, that he knowing certainly what kind of
disease it is, may the more better finde out of what humour, it
is caused, <hi>As for example.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Yf</hi> the Phisition do perceiue y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> disease to be a tertian <hi>Feuer,</hi>
straightway he knoweth that it is caused of great aboundance
of choller, and therefore he must of necessitie minister a meete
medicine to purge choller, withall, and so likewise in all other
diseases.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Note</hi> likewise, that if there be none of the impediments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue
named, a <hi>Purgation</hi> is good to be ministred to all such as
haue aboundance of euill iuice or corrupt humours in the
body, for it draweth out all the bad humours that doe molest y<seg rend="sup">•</seg>
body, and thereby doth restore it to his owne state againe.</p>
   <p>But if a <hi>Purgatiō</hi> be rashly ministred eyther to one that nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
it not, or at an inconuenient time, or that it be such a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine,
as draweth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> out the humour which then aboundeth,
or if the medicine be vehement and very strong, it will surely
put the Patient in great daunger of his life.</p>
   <p>These thinges therefore ought to be well taken heede of by
all menne, lest they catch great hurt when they hope for some
great profite.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>But</hi> if a <hi>Purgation</hi> be discreetly ministred to him that hath
need of it in due time, and by an apt and meet medicine, which
is of that force and abillitie, to drawe out the abounding hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours
in sufficient quantitie, then doth the medicine purchase
<pb facs="9"/>
most singuler great commodties to the body, for it euacuateth
and emptieth out all the chiefest causes of the diseases and sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses,
eyther present or els to come, being ingendred of any
superfluous or corrupt humour, as are most commonly <hi>Feuers,
tercians, quartaines, quotidians,</hi> or <hi>Fluxes,</hi> and are caused of rawe
humours or sharpe choller, <hi>Dropsies, Goutes, Palsies, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>targies,</hi>
and diuers other &amp;c.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Note</hi> also that before a <hi>Purgation</hi> be ministred, there ought
a medicine to be taken, which should prepare the body, &amp; make
it apt to purge, and therefore it is called a preparatiue, it is
geuen for two causes, eyther to deuide, extenuat, &amp; make them
grosse and clammy humours, that they may be ready to flowe
out, when the medicine draweth them, or else it is geuen to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
and vnstoppe the conduits &amp; vessels of the body, by which
the <hi>Purgation</hi> must drawe the superfluous humour to it.</p>
   <p>And this is that which <hi>Hipocrates</hi> doth counsaile in the first
<hi>Aphorisme</hi> of his second booke, where he saith, <hi>Corpora cum
quis{que} purgare voluerit, opportet fluuia facere,</hi> that is, when
any man will purge the body, he must make it flowing, by ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
and vnopening of the vessels.</p>
   <p>The most meetest time of al to receiue a <hi>Purgation</hi> is in the
morning, for then are all the digestions perfectly finished, and
the stomacke is without meate, There is also great heede to be
taken in what signe the moone is in, before such time as any
<hi>Purgation</hi> be ministred, for some signes are very good for it, &amp;
other some are euill, Therefore I would wish all such as doe
take vpon them the ministring of any <hi>Purgation,</hi> to haue great
regard before they do minister it, of the sicke person, the time,
and the place greeued, and also to marke wel all such thinges
as are before rehearsed, least that they doe more hurt thereby
in one day to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sicke person, then they are able to doe him good
in a whole yeare, and yet they may doe it of meere simplicite,
not knowing themselues what they haue done, neyther are
they able to cure the same wound which they themselues haue
made.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="10"/>
A <hi>Purgation</hi> must be taken hote, for soe it offendeth the
stomacke least, and it will worke the sooner.</p>
   <p>Also those that are apt to vomite, and are not able to endure
the smell of the <hi>Purgation,</hi> let them stoppe their nosethrills, or
else let them smell to some odorifferous thinge, when they are
about to take it, and assoone as it is taken, it is good for the
Patient, to smell to a toste of browne bread dipped in <hi>vineger,</hi>
and to applie warme clothes to the stomacke, and to wash the
mouth presently after that it is taken, with some odoriferous
<hi>wine,</hi> or els to chew some sweete and pleasant thing to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
the bitter taste or smell of the medicine, &amp; by this meanes
vomiting shal be eschewed.</p>
   <p>Likewise for the space of one houre after that the <hi>Purgation</hi>
is taken, let the Patient sit still and keepe himselfe quiet, and
without any sleepe at all, that the strength of the medicine may
passe into all partes of his body, but if the <hi>Purgation</hi> do worke
slowly, let him walke vp and downe for a good space after, if he
can, and when it worketh, in any case there must be great care
taken, that the Patient do not sleepe, for soe the operation of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg>
medicine would be stopped.</p>
   <p>Also in the time of <hi>Purging</hi> immoderate heate and cold are
to be eschewed, and therefore a very great fier, and the cold &amp;
open ayre are both hurtefull, for the body must be kept in a tē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate
heate.</p>
   <p>After that the <hi>Purgation</hi> hath done workinge, the Patient
must be nourished with a meane quantitie of some broth, that
will breede good iuice, and be easelie digested, and afterwards
by little &amp; litle, returne to his accustomed diet againe.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thus</hi> haue I as brieflye as I could, declared the commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
which doe come of <hi>bloud-letting</hi> and <hi>Purging,</hi> being wel
and duely ministred and vsed, and also of the discommodities
that will eusue both of <hi>bloud-letting</hi> and <hi>Purging</hi> if they be at
any time misused, wishinge all men as they doe tender theire
health and liues, to beware of those ignorant persons, who doe
most commonly vse to open but one kinde of vaine, for all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="10"/>
of diseases, and doe occupie but one kinde of <hi>Purgation</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
all humours, not considering at all, the strength and
the age of the Patient, neyther the time, nor the chiefe cause
of the comminge of the disease whatsoeuer it bee, nor of any
other of the circumstances afore named, but let them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
seeke for the counsaile and aide of one that is
knowne to be skilfull in Phisicke and Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie,
and is circumspect in his doinges.
Who can consider what neede they
haue, &amp; what is most meete
to be ministred vnto
them for y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> same
disease.
∴</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>