<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Goldwell, Charles</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118445_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73841</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6951</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118445</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Goldwell, Charles</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Two sermons on the third of the Lamentations of Ieremie : preached at Hanwell in the first yeare of his Maiesties raigne, 1602. The one by I.D. the other by R.C</title>
                 <author>Dod, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Man, Jonas (Jonah)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Thomas 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sharpe, Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>70, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing occasion to reuise notes of certaine Sermons taken by penne from their mouthes, whose la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours both in word and writing haue been and are no lesse profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table than acceptable vnto Gods Church, I thought it not amisse to take some small paines to copie out some of them, that if perhaps they should be thought worthie of publike view, they might be offered to the light: if not, they might be reserued for more pruiate vse. Amongst the rest, I iudged these two Sermons not the vnfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test for such a purpose, and so did others, whose in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement also I had for the publishing of them. They were preached in the beginning of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties raigne, at that time when generall humiliation by fasting, was by authoritie enioyned vpon occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Pestilence, then dangerously dispersed: which albeit through Gods mercifull proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence it be now well allayed, yet the infection of sinne, the very true cause thereof, still remaineth and gathereth new strength. For the staying where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, if any remedie may be gotten hence, I hope for more easie pardon, from the authors, of my boldenes in publishing: and from the reader for
<pb facs="3"/>my many faylings in penning these their labors. I did my best in taking from them, and offering vnto thee, that, and in a manner nothing but that which they then deliuered. The substance of the matter I doubt not, is all sound, and will much content a wise and well affected heart. The manner and forme of words and sentences is more imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect than in the deliuerie it was, or now might haue beene, if the authors had either penned it before the preaching thereof, or vndertaken the thorow polishing of it since. But howsoeuer, sith that could not bee obtained which might haue beene wished, my desire was greater to satisfie thirstie soules with this that is done, then was my feare to offend curious heads and itching eares by the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of doing it.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>IOHN WINSTON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>