<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE REA∣DER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118882_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03687</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13814</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118882</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE REA∣DER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Hornbyes hornbook : Iudge not too rashly, till through all you looke; if nothing then doth please you, burne the booke. By William Hornbye, gent</title>
                 <author>Hornby, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bailey (Baily, Baley, Bayly), Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>38 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>TO THE REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>MY <hi>Braine</hi> now (gentle Reader)'s brought to bed</l>
      <l>Of that a while she painefull laboured:</l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ypen a carefull Mid-wiues part hath plaid</l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o see her of her Orphant safely layd,</l>
      <l>Wrap'd vp in raggs of meane intelligence,</l>
      <l>Without the Robes of learned eloquence:</l>
      <l>And though she be shees not abortiue borne,</l>
      <l>Though Retorique her shaps did ne're adorne:</l>
      <l>Nor is she of a base and bastard straine,</l>
      <l>Her Parentage is honest, simple, plaine,</l>
      <l>All of her Father, true <hi>Inuentions</hi> getting,</l>
      <l>As tis most honest, requisite and fitting.</l>
      <l>She is no filtch-line of anothers wit,</l>
      <l>Such Theft she hateth and abhorreth it,</l>
      <l>And she dare looke euen with a modest grace,</l>
      <l>Her better <hi>Muse</hi> with boldnesse in the face.</l>
      <l>A Cottyers child may be as truly got,</l>
      <l>As is a Courtyers euery way, why not?</l>
      <l>As faire and louely too in shape and face,</l>
      <l>And euen as well adorn'd with inward grace,</l>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <l>And proue as faithfull, iust, and plaine a man,</l>
      <l>For he nere temporise, nor flutter can;</l>
      <l>He doth not know the art of Adulation,</l>
      <l>He neuer is acquainted with such fashion,</l>
      <l>The difference of these two in this appears,</l>
      <l>Th'one Robes of silke, th'otherraggs doth weare:</l>
      <l>Euen so although (this homely brat of mine)</l>
      <l>Doth want rich robes of Art to make it shine</l>
      <l>Through out all places, where it haplie goes,</l>
      <l>Yet meere simplicitie, and truth it showes.</l>
      <l>The two collauded, and applauded springs,</l>
      <l>Where all the <hi>Muses</hi> most delitious sings,</l>
      <l>Within their armes did neuer me infold,</l>
      <l>Nor did my eyes their glory yet behold;</l>
      <l>Such blisse to me (alas) did ne're belong,</l>
      <l>I had the greater iniurie and wrong.</l>
      <l>Then (gentle Reader) if that title faire,</l>
      <l>With thy good nature I may right compare:</l>
      <l>Pardon my Muse, which for no ill intent,</l>
      <l>Into the world I homely here haue sent.</l>
      <l>Here is no enuy that at all doth lurke</l>
      <l>In this my harmelesse Muses little worke:</l>
      <l>And if that any discontent doth grow,</l>
      <l>Tis not my fault, but theirs which take it so.</l>
      <l>Those people then whose consciences are cleare</l>
      <l>From all such things as I haue written here,</l>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <l>Accept my minds true meaning and good will,</l>
      <l>More then my Retorique, my Art and skill;</l>
      <l>If some cannot commend it nor defend it,</l>
      <l>Then in their wisdomes let them kindly mend it:</l>
      <l>If neither; cease then a malignant tongue,</l>
      <l>And doe a harmlesse honest Muse no wrong.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours, as you like him, <hi>Cornu-apes.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>