<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most Illustrious, H. &amp; B. of Roan, Princes of Leon. FRED. Prince of Sedan. H. of Tri∣mouille, Prince of Talmont. N. Duke of Seuilly. AMORI. Marquis of La Moussay Mon. Le Vidame de Chartres. N. Marq. of La Force. ST. Marq. of Duras. CL. Earle of Montgomery. LE. E. of La Suze. GASP. E. of Chastillion.</title>
           <author>Du Moulin, Pierre</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118563_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20957</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7336</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118563</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most Illustrious, H. &amp; B. of Roan, Princes of Leon. FRED. Prince of Sedan. H. of Tri∣mouille, Prince of Talmont. N. Duke of Seuilly. AMORI. Marquis of La Moussay Mon. Le Vidame de Chartres. N. Marq. of La Force. ST. Marq. of Duras. CL. Earle of Montgomery. LE. E. of La Suze. GASP. E. of Chastillion.</title>
                 <author>Du Moulin, Pierre</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A preparation to suffer for the Gospell of Iesus Christ. Or, A most Christian exercise full of comfort and consolation for these present times. Written in French by the learned, and zealous, Peter Du Moulin, Professor of Diuinitie, in the Vniuersitie of Sedan</title>
                 <author>Du Moulin, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 80 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the most Illustrious, H. &amp; B. of <hi>Roan,</hi> Princes of <hi>Leon.</hi> FRED. Prince of <hi>Sedan.</hi> H. of <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouille,</hi> Prince of <hi>Talmont.</hi> N. Duke of <hi>Seuilly.</hi> AMORI. Marquis of <hi>La Moussay Mon. Le Vidame de Chartres.</hi> N. Marq. of <hi>La Force.</hi> ST. Marq. of <hi>Duras.</hi> CL. Earle of <hi>Montgomery.</hi> LE. E. of <hi>La Suze.</hi> GASP. E. of <hi>Chastillion.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most Illustrious Lords,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N these tottering and vncertaine times, when the loue and respect of the world, and the terrour of persecutions, and tribulations, makes many look back, that haue laid fast hold on the Plough of true Religion. I thought it most expedient to salute you with this Treatise of a secure and safe Preparation against the assaults of malicious hearts, and attempting hands, that by the heroicall ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of Christian patience, and constancy, you may be able to resist whatsoeuer impious force or violence, which would faine make a breach in your Noble, Religious, and Zealous hearts.
<pb facs="5"/> This I haue done, not out of any doubt or feare of your firme and setled resolutions; but onely to giue you to vnderstand how farre your Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lustrious persons are interressed in the daily and continual praiers of the whole Church, for your happy and victorious successe; and that whensoeuer you vouchsafe but to read this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Discourse, your Lordships may be put in mind of the zealous and affectionate prayers of Gods people, who hauing made my vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy selfe their generall mouth, and voyce, I doe not a little reioyce of the fit opportunity I haue herein, to manifest vnto your Lordships mine owne particular humble loue and affection, which being grounded vpon the many noble and apparant vertues of your Lordships, and innumerable fauours and benefits imparted to me without desert, desires yet in so small and slender a testimony as this, to make known the large extent of my wishes and desires, that God may accumulate vpon your Lordships in so holy and iust a cause, all auspicious and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed successe, as he, whom all your Lordships ioyntly, and each of you in particular, will euer rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships most bounden and deuoted, P. DV MOVLIN.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>