<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE NO LESSE VERTVOVS THEN HONO¦rable, Sir HENRY NORREIS Knight, Lorde Norreis, Barron OF RICOT, ENCREASE OF HONOR, WITH ALL grace, and all felicity. ({inverted ⁂})</title>
           <author>Hackey, Roger</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118991_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02457</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12589</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118991</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE NO LESSE VERTVOVS THEN HONO¦rable, Sir HENRY NORREIS Knight, Lorde Norreis, Barron OF RICOT, ENCREASE OF HONOR, WITH ALL grace, and all felicity. ({inverted ⁂})</title>
                 <author>Hackey, Roger</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon needfvll for theese [sic] times : wherein is shewed, the insolencies of Naash King of Ammon, against the men of Iabesh Gilead, and the succors of Saule, and his people sent for their reliefe. Preached at Paules Crosse the 14 of Feb. 1590. by R.H. fellow of the Ne Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Hacket, Roger</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barnes, Joseph</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>56 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE NO LESSE VERTVOVS THEN HONO<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable, Sir HENRY NORREIS <hi>Knight, Lorde Norreis, Barron</hi> OF RICOT, ENCREASE OF HONOR, WITH ALL grace, and all felicity. ({inverted ⁂})</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE is none soe weake sighted (right Honorable) but nowe by long experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ēce they may see, the deep and vnchangeable hatred of the popish faction, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved against our dread soveraigne, as the party most principal, and others the embra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cers &amp; professors of gods truth. The which hath so depraved &amp; poysoned many their hartes, that it hath not only removed from them, all loyalty to their prince, &amp; loue to their countrie; but also hath carried thē so far, against the streame of al goodnes, and sence of nature; that they haue by sundrie meanes, and sundry persons, attempted to doe violence, vpon her sacred maiesty; and farther haue sought, so far as in them laye, to moue rebellions in the lande, and with
<pb facs="3"/>
their owne ruines, and ruinns of their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, to worke the overthrowe of this their countrie, &amp; vnsufferable slavery vnto a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rē enimy. Whose wicked malice, although god of his goodnes hath hitherto detected and blowne abroad, to their own shame &amp; and great confusion: yet there cause, hath been of late more specially commended, &amp; vndertaken by the greate pation of the holy league, who vnder a shew and couler of religion, and of yeelding succours vnto there cause, doth affect the soverainty and Empire not only of thē, &amp; of this our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, but of al other kingdomes here in the west. Wherefore it standeth all good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vpon, which loue their liberty, &amp; would not that a stranger should reape that they haue sowen to giue eare vnto the calles of their superiors, by whose providence (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der god they haue bin hitherto kept, and stil may be continued in wealth &amp; liberty. For if the counsel of their rulers shal not fit their restles &amp; vncōtēted humors, but they wil needes hearken, either to the sinister persuasion of some evil disposed; or to the vnprovident miserablenesse, of their al co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veting natures; they shall not only thrust from them that good, which their gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours woulde procure: but by sparing of a little, put them selues in daunger of lee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
<pb facs="3"/>
more. For if (which god forbid) the enemie shoulde be suffered, to make our neighbour countries, the shops and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his warres; and without impeache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prepare, his navyes and armies as before; and with fier and sworde, to enter and make some smal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2+ letters">
         <desc>••…</desc>
      </gap>y in this our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie: although hee bee manfully beaten backe, and forced to retire, nay flye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all order: yet the havockes made by them, together with the spoiles of lose per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sons, and of others, not so well affected amongst our selues; woulde multiply the charges we haue hitherto beene at: beside the dishonour of our countrie, hurre of the people, and infinite dammage of many our brethren, vpon whomsoever it shal light. All which as it sufficeth here for to remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber so for the better instruction of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in this pointe, I commende this small treatise vnto their reading. And whereas (Right Honorable) youre godly desires, haue alwaies been for the welfare of your country, and aduauncement of gods truth, and you haue of your loynes, many worthy children, set a part and marked of god to such an ende: I thought good both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the matter, and my manifold due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to commend this treatise to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors fauor and protection. Of which as
<pb facs="4"/>
I nothing doubt, so I shal not cease to com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mend you and yours, to the gracious gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, blessing, and protection of God. From new College the 27 of March.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors in all duty <hi>ROGER HACKEY.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>