<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONO∣RABLE, MY MVCH Honour'd Friend Sir WILLIAM HOVVARD, Sonne to the Illustrious THOMAS EARLE Of Suffolke.</title>
           <author>S., A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118665_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20965</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7344</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118665</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONO∣RABLE, MY MVCH Honour'd Friend Sir WILLIAM HOVVARD, Sonne to the Illustrious THOMAS EARLE Of Suffolke.</title>
                 <author>S., A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A wittie encounter betweene Monsieur du Moulin, and Monsieur De Balzac : Esteemed two the most elegant pens of their nation. Wherein they deliver things weighty, and important both in religion and state. Faithfully translated out of the french (sic) coppy by A.S. Gent</title>
                 <author>Du Moulin, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Fisher, Benjamin</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 117, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE, MY MVCH Honour'd Friend Sir WILLIAM HOVVARD, Sonne to the Illustrious THOMAS EARLE Of Suffolke.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Sir,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> dare adventure to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to you, and the Age, these ensuing Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, written by two esteemed great in the Learned Republique. Truth cōmands me to answer for them, that there is no proportion
<pb facs="3"/>
betweene their bulke, and value, being defective in nothing but length. For the Authors them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues <hi>Monsieur du Moulin,</hi> and <hi>Monsieur de Balzac,</hi> their Pens are justly ranked amongst the most excellent of their Nation. The Logicke, and many worthy Divine workes of the former have gained him a great name euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst his adversaries: the latter (though of the like abillity) hath made himselfe Master of a more glorious Fame; but in my judgement, Imp'd out with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a false Feather; neither his great Cardinall, nor <hi>Monsieur du Moulin</hi> shall with their most cunning Rhetoricke lull me into such a grosse errour as to beleeve him Master of that▪ Eloquence which Antiquity desir'd, yet
<pb facs="3"/>
despair'd of. O! that any man who hath had the least cast of <hi>Cicero's,</hi> and <hi>Livy's</hi> flowing, or <hi>Seneca's</hi> distilling Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence should give so sinister a judgement! Great praise is due to the man, and it is by all deservedly paid him, but what is in him most elegant you can terme, at the best but the Scraps of <hi>Cicero's</hi> abundant E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence, whose <hi>Zany</hi> if wee call him wee doe him a grace, if wee introduce him a Corri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall, wee doe <hi>Cicero</hi> an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front.</p>
   <p>I confesse the times are infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely bound to him, and his like, for keeping ciuill Language from degenerating into Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risme, and most men from hack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, hewing, and enterfaring in
<pb facs="4"/>
their discourse, but I will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver allow them as Emendators of the Ancients, it is enough if as happy Imitators I admit them.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>O Marcus! Marcus! did thy Ghost now walke amongst us, thy bloodlesse face would essay to blush after death, to heare thy all-convincing, char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Tongue, (which hath made Guilt tremble, and shooke Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rany it selfe) compar'd with the faint, Hectick Eloquence of</hi> Balzac, <hi>which now even in its Birth is neare utter extincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereas thy Rhetoricall Flowers shall budde, and flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish till fire consumes the World, and all Terrestriall Oratory gives way to the Celestiall. Nor would thy shame be lesse,</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
Anaeus Seneca, <hi>to have (after all the glories thy Penn hath purchas'd) such a competitor as</hi> Balzac, <hi>who holds the same place with thee, and</hi> Cicero, <hi>that in the Triumvirat with</hi> Anthony <hi>and</hi> Octavius <hi>did</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidus, <hi>who in the Government of the World stood onely for a Cypher.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But to justifie my assertion I will take so much paines as to compare their stiles. That of <hi>Cicero</hi> is not compos'd for the Scene, onely to delight, but for the Sand also, and the Fight. it is like a Tree which produceth not onely the Foliage, as an Ornament, but the Fruite too, as foode.</p>
   <p>Here you may detect <hi>Venus,</hi> and <hi>Minerva,</hi> kissing in every
<pb facs="5"/>
line. With the reading of him the most prostrate, groveling witt must needes bee raised, the most benummed take fire. This is none of those lukewarme Spirits, which can infuse no heate into others because they have none themselves; for as we cannot light a Taper at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not already lighted: so we can not take flame from a wit not already fired.</p>
   <p>The mind of this Writer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flames his Stile, his Stile his Reader. Now for that of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi>; his words are choise, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and so Significant, that at the first view a man would thinke they implyed more, then indeede they doe. It is pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to his Genius alone to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend plenty, and solidity of
<pb facs="5"/>
sence in parcimony of Speech, Perspicuity in Brevity. Then his matter is alwaies grave, and weighty, drawne out from the very Center of History, and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophy.</p>
   <p>To come to the Stile of <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zac.</hi> You may at first sight discover in it not a becomming care, and a neate dresse, but a vaine affectation, and the <hi>Fucus</hi> it selfe. And as his Language is affected, so his conceptions are for the most part idle, and shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, no way able to satisfie the expectation of a full, and knowing man. They consist for the most part of Hyperbolicall Complements, and malitious Invectives: witnesse with mee the supreame Spirit, that I taxe him not as a detracting Enemy,
<pb facs="6"/>
but an impartiall Examiner. Iustice her selfe will warrant me to pull that Palme out of his vsurping hand, which Ignorance had there placed. I confesse I can not endure to see him borne by the vulgar breath to so high a pitch, as to out-soare all Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, who hath not written so many Pages as hee hath mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne equals, nay Superiours in that persuasive Art. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of this their so immoderate praise, is no other then that their infant knowledge derides the Simplicity of their Ancestours, whose Science it should have in admiration. My owne indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Printers petition, (who complaines much of the Bookes brevity,) have caused me to spin out this Epistle to an
<pb facs="6"/>
unvsuall length. My comfort is (if this way I deserue censure) I am faulty with <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca,</hi> and many brave Authors, who haue delivered their minds in Letters far more prolixe. I am now onely a Petitioner to the Reader for a license to adde so many words onely as will let you know, (Noblest Sir,) that I truely honour You, and and that I create you (who understand well the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall) Iudge of the Translation, which hath already beene Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd with many great Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probations. I am confident that you will make use of your mercy rather then your Iustice towards him, who into your hands hath voluntarily put the life of his Reputation in good
<pb facs="7"/>
Letters, to him farre, far dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer then his Naturall, during which he vowes to remaine</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Sir,</salute>
      <signed>Your most humble Servant, A. S.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>