<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The prologue to the reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1556</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118795_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68194</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13558</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118795</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The prologue to the reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The displaying of the Protestantes, [and] sondry their practises, with a description of diuers their abuses of late frequented : Newly imprinted agayne, and augmented, with a table in the ende, of all suche matter as is specially contained within this volume. Made by Myle Huggarde seruant to the Quenes maiestie</title>
                 <author>Huggarde, Miles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Caly, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1556</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>130, 8 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>¶ The prologue to the reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is commōly seen that they which with pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceptes and rules doo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte others, and seme therein to excell, because thei suppose thei can not be corrected, do eyther much good, ouer whome they haue the gouernement, or els to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same thei cōferre great damage, they themselues not escapinge without infamy. In lyke maner, our late elders and ministers (for so they termed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues) if with the holsome erudition of Goddes vndouted truthe, and with the admouiciōs and perswasions of the gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, they had applied the same to the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of lyfe, and amendement of the conuersation of them, ouer whome they toke vpon thē the charge, no doubte they had doone muche good too the common welthe, and to the reformacion of mans corrupt nature. But vsing themselues cleane contrary, that is to saie, neyther vsinge gods truth as it ought to be, but
<pb n="6" facs="6"/>
rather abusyng the same, neither in their attemptes established an vniforme reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, nor yet perswaded correction of lyfe. They haue brought this publike state of Englande into great detriment and mysery, as lamentable experience to our great smarte declareth. And because (moste frendly reader,) thou maiest per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue partely, with what vile doctrine a great parte of this realme hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lured, and with what pestilent perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions men haue bene ledde, and partely with what detestable vices, and horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble abuses the scholemaisters thēselues haue bene infected: This presente vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume, entituled <hi>The displaying of the protestantes,</hi> is compiled, not for any malice or enuie mēt to any of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> parties, but for good will to the Reader, &amp; for a naturall pietie to this our countrey, the naturall nourice and mother of vs all. Whiche protestantes may a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tely be cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared<note place="margin">Plato. lib. 2. De Re Pub.</note> to <hi>Plato</hi> his <hi>Gyges,</hi> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> tale of whom <hi>Tidly</hi> reci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eth in his third boke of his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices. At the falling downe from aboue of certen stormes of wether, the earthe opened in diuers places, by reason of the
<pb facs="7"/>
drought before. <hi>Gyges</hi> being a Kynges: Shepeherde, entred in to the earthe at a great hoole, and founde a brasen horse (as the fables declare) in whose sydes wer dores, which being opened, he espied the corse of a dead man of a wonderfull hugenes, and a golde ringe vpon his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, which as sone as he pulled of, he put it vpon his own. The nature of the ring was this: that when he had turned the head towardes the palme of his hande, he was inuisible, and sene of nobody, &amp; yet sawe euery thynge: and turnyng the rynge from him agayne, he was sene of euery body. And so vsing this aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the rynge, he laye with the quene wife to <hi>Candaules</hi> kyng of <hi>Lydia.</hi> So the<note place="margin">Herodotus in Cli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> protestātes, whē it pleased god to plague this our countrey for the synne of the people, with the vnquiet stormes of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie, got them out of the company of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shepehardes, &amp; dispersed themselfes into the earth, and at length entred into brasen horses, the houses of the cheif go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours then, abusyng the same with false interpretacion of Gods worde, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng thē beleue by their craftie suggesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="7" facs="7"/>
that all thinges which had cōtinued in the churche of God to that tyme, was of no veritie, but deuised by man, calling the same toyes and ceremonies of Rome: who hauing a zeale to Gods truth, and credityng the merye conceiptes of these yonglinges, trusting their talk had been the vndoubted veritie, pelded to their practises. Then these shepeherdes percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cheif magistrates prone to sondrie alteracions &amp; nouelties, beganne by litle and litle also to corrupt the consciences of the vulgare people, infecting the same with the poyson of heretical doctrin, that at length they became altogethers dead corpses of wōderfull hugenes. Then fra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med they rynges to seme inuisible to the worlde: then played they <hi>Gyges</hi> part, then ruled they the rooste, then began they to swarme in routes, then clustered they like humble bees to deuoure the honye combes from the hiues of the poore bees, then like cōmon souldiors after the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell began they to fall to spoyle, then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced thei Churches, then made they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke of the ornamentes of the same.</p>
   <p>And in this sorte with heresie and spoile
<pb facs="8"/>
feding the common peoples simplicitee with a counterfait zeale, they murdred mens consciences, &amp; distroied the realme and the common welth thereof. After whiche their practises yet gaue they not ouer like fainte hearted souldiors, but with stiffe standing stomakes continued to thende. And as <hi>Gyges</hi> by vertue of his ringe cōmitted adulterie with <hi>Candaules</hi> wyfe who was then kinge of <hi>Lydia,</hi> and within shorte time after by her vngraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous counsaile dispatched him of his life, euen soo these adulterate protestantes thought it not sufficient to effeminat the mindes of the simple with their false doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trine, and to contaminate the same with the venime of their viperous tongues, but alsoo therewith haue so slaine the consciences of many, that like desperate men they make haste to their owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction. Whoo beinge puffed vp with presumption, seeke to clime vppe to the chariote of the sonne.</p>
   <p>But as <hi>Phaeton</hi> was serued for goyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to aspire to his fathers secretes, &amp; with a flashe of lightening was set al on fyer: So are these presumptuous and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraūt
<pb n="8" facs="8"/>
people plagued with the lyke, as a due rewarde of presumption. This it is to followe the hyssinges of the vipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouse broode, who neuer departe their haunt, til they haue infected whole coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treis. For this cause (welbeloued rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) this present treatise is publyshed, to set before mennes eyes the edible prac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tises of these protestantes, who in their owne conceiptes presume, they haue the vndoubted truth. Whome if you marke <hi>intus et in cute,</hi> you shall well vnderstande the contrary. But peraduenture some man will muse of this woorde <hi>Protestante,</hi> because it is no vsuall terme. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is a worde greatly pleasyng thē<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selues, a woorde inuented after they &amp; hartes desyre, a worde deuysed of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, a woorde wherein they greatly triumphe, &amp; such a worde which serueth moste aptlye for the purpose: therefore it is here most frequented. And it is the participle of the verbe <hi>Protestor,</hi> which is to declare, what should be eschewed. A very apt worde, and mete for suche, who in very dede were al togethers <hi>Protestan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> That is to saye disswaders of hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some
<pb facs="9"/>
lawes whiche touched the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macion of mannes nature, and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of suche good orders as were constituted for the bridlinge thereof. Therfore to conclude this proeine, I moste hartely beseche the to reache hether thy diligent and indifferēt eares, and iudge well of myne entente, and do not imploye thy iudgement, lyke vnto hym who alredy is maried to his owne fancie: Letting the to wyt, that of mans malicious iudgement I force not, for I knowe the passions of maliciouse sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makes. In this doyng I do not doubte▪ but thou for thy parte, shalt haue a iust cause to praye vnto God for vnitie (the sure bande of all common welthes) and to graunte vnto all men grace, to withstande heresies assaultes. And I finally for my parte, shall haue the like to thynke my paynes well im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>played. And thus I commytte the to God. (∴)</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>Mense Iuni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>, 1556.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>