<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶The Translatour to the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1572</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118019_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14710</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25013</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118019</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶The Translatour to the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An hundred, threescore and fiftene homelyes or sermons, vppon the Actes of the Apostles, written by Saint Luke: made by Radulpe Gualthere Tigurine, and translated out of Latine into our tongue, for the commoditie of the Englishe reader. Seene and allowed, according to the Queenes Maiesties iniunctions</title>
                 <author>Gwalther, Rudolf</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1572</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>56, 904, 915-919, 3 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>¶The Translatour to the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Monge the manyfolde and subtile policies that the newe broched Diuines (I meane such as haue crept out of the schoole of <hi>Thomas Aquinas, Iohn Duns, Occham, Dorbell,</hi> and such other Doctors) haue deuised for the maintenance and vpholding of their kingdome, there was neuer any one of more efficacie and force for that purpose, than to haue the people kept from reading the holye Scriptures of God in their owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per tongue and language. And yet bicause they shoulde haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matter ynough, to occupye their heades and eyes vppon, they inuented a booke called the golden Legende, the authour whereof vndoubtedly had both a leaden mouth and an yron face, as <hi>Lodouicus Viues</hi> a learned Spaniarde did very well perceyue and testifie. To this they ioyned their Festi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall, and such like bookes, (or to vse their owne terme more truely than they doe) bible babble, stuffed with most monstrous and impudent forgeries, some of them so dishonest, that it woulde and did abhorre manye christians eares to heare them. And to this ende also they sette vp in euerye Church and Chappell such blockishe and stony schoolemaisters, as coulde and did teach nothing else but lightnesse and vanitie, lyes and errours. And to be briefe, whatsoeuer mannes ydle braine coulde deuise, whatsoeuer anye Monke or Friers grosse <hi>Minerua</hi> could forge or inuent, though it were no better than <hi>Amadis de Gaule,</hi> the foure sonnes of <hi>Amon,</hi> the tales of Robin Hoode, and such other like fables, yet were they thought very trimme and gaye geare to occupie the peoples eares withall. Yea, had they bene more fabulous than these (if more might haue bene) they shoulde haue bene borne and suffred, rather than the holy Scriptures in such a tongue as the people might haue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstoode. For this cause, whosoeuer in consideration that the people were thus led about in the blinde mases of mannes inuentions, woulde haue translated any péece of Scripture or other fruitefull treatise into the Englishe tongue, for their vtilitie and edification, he and all his wrytings were iudged to be burned as Hereticall. For (say they) the laye people had bookes good ynough for them set open in euerye Church, meaning their carued and painted Puppetrie, and woulde suffer them to reade vppon none other. Then also were hatched and maintained such straunge paradoxes and opinions as these: <hi>Ignorance is the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of deuotion: The Scriptures make heretikes: The Church cannot erre: The laye folke must not medle with Scriptures: We will beleue as our forefathers haue done,</hi> meaning those that liued not past thrée or fower ages before, and such as had bene fedde with like acornes and swill, as they had bene vsed to, and had neuer tasted one morsell of the swéete breade of Gods eternall and liuely worde. And although these things be well ynough knowne vnto the learned, so that they néede no such slender remembrances as these of mine are, yet for the vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neds sake, for whose cause I chiefely tooke paines to put this booke in Englishe, I will shewe (by Gods helpe) both by Scriptures, apparaunt reasons, and auncient Doctors, that these newe Doctors in this doing wrought altogither agaynst Gods forbode. And yet woulde I haue no man to looke that I shoulde fully shewe and declare all the testimonies that might be brought for proofe of any part of my triple diuision. For so might I write not an aduertisement for the vnskilfull, but a worke and treatise, which in quantitie might match or excéede the translation it selfe. As touching Scriptures, the newe Doctors and we also agrée herein, that whatsoeuer is in eyther of the Testaments, the olde or the new, concerning good maners and holy conuersation, it all serueth indifferentlye, for all times and ages. Therfore of consequence it must also serue for vs. But in the olde Testament the fathers taught their children and families the lawes and rules of both the Tables, that is to say, their duties aswell vnto God, as vnto man. <hi>Ergo,</hi> we also must doe the like. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> receyued the commaundementes to teache them to the people, which he faithfullye and trulye did, appoynting them to trayne and bring vp their youth and posteritie in the same, not onely making them to learne them by rote, like Dawes, Pyes, and Popingayes, but opening and declaring vnto them the sense and meaning aswell of their Feastes and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
<pb facs="5"/>
dayes which God did institute, as of their sacramentes of Circumcision and Passeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. These be his wordes: <hi>Harken ô Israel, the Lorde our God is Lorde onely. Thou shalt loue the Lorde thy God with all thine hart, and with all thy soule, and with all thy might. And these wordes which I commaunde thee this daye shall be in thine heart. And thou shalt shewe them vnto thy children, and shalt talke of them when thou art at home in thyne house, and as thou walkest by the way, and when thou lyest downe, and when thou risest vp, and thou shalt binde them for a signe vpon thine hande,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.</note>
      <hi>and they shall be as frontlets betweene thine eyes, and thou shalt wryte them vpon thy postes, and vpon thy gates.</hi> And in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same chapter it foloweth further: <hi>And when thy sonne asketh thee in time to come, saying: what meaneth these testimonies, ordinaunces, and lawes, which the Lorde God hath commaunded you? Then shalt thou saye vnto thy sonne: wee were Pharaos bondmen in Egipt, and the Lorde brought vs out of Egypt with a mightye hande. And the Lorde shewed signes and woonders great and euill vpon Egipt, vpon Pharao, and vpon all his housholde, before our eyes. And brought vs out from thence to bring vs in, and to giue vs the lande which hee sware vnto our fathers. &amp;c.</hi> The holy prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> also spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the same commaundement of God declared by the mouth of <hi>Moses,</hi> sayth: <hi>Heare my lawe, ô my people, enclyne your eares vnto the wordes of my mouth. I will open my mouth in a Parable, I will declare hard sentences of olde. Which we haue hearde and knowne, and such as our fathers haue tolde vs. That wee shoulde not hide them from the children of the generations to come, but to shewe the honour of the Lorde, his mightie and wonderfull workes that he hath done. He made a couenaunt with Iacob,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 78.</note>
      <hi>and gaue Israel a lawe, which he commaunded our forefathers to teach their children, that their posteritie might knowe it, and the children that were yet vnborne. To the intent that when they came vp, they might shewe their children the same.</hi> Here mayst thou sée, O good Reader, that the true Christians and faythfull among the Israelytes, as they were commaunded, euen so they taught and instructed their families and children in the wayes and works of the Lord. So that of them it coulde not be verified as yet, that they <hi>had shut vp the kingdome of heauen from menne,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 23.</note>
      <hi>neyther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ntring in themselues, neyther suffring other that woulde,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 15.</note> neyther th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t <hi>they were blinde leaders o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> the blinde.</hi> For those broodes of Phariseyes, Saduceyes, and Essenes,<note place="margin">They began in the dayes of <hi>Ioannes Hircanus</hi> high Bishop of the Iewes about an hundred and thirtie yeares before Christ was borne.</note> were not hatched till many hundred yeares after, which when Christ came, had turned godlynesse into gaine, and religion into rechelesnesse, as the like swarmes of religious (commonly called, but in déede most superstitious) did amongst vs, and yet doe where they are still suffered. And bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they feare that the Lord in his zeale wil whip such wicked merchants as they are, out of his Church in all places, as it appeareth very well he doth dailye, his name be glorifyed therefore, this maketh them to storme, fret and fume, and to take counsayle against the Lorde, and against his annointed. This maketh them stirre coales, and to play Rex, this causeth them to imprison, to hang, to drawe, to drowne, to burne, to cut mens tongues out, to gagge them that they shall not speake, to banishe and proscribe, séeing they can no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger prescribe, but verily all in vaine, for as much as there is no wisedome, counsayle,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Prou.</hi> 21.</note> or deuise that can preuayle against the Lorde. But let vs returne to the holy prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> whose sayings and testimonies (bicause they haue alwayes bene of such worthy estimation in the Church of God) let vs bring yet furthermore to confyrme the truth of our assertion. In the .lxxxj. psalme he bringeth in God thus speaking to the people of <hi>Israel: Heare ô my people, and I assure thee ô Israel, if thou wilt hearken vnto mee, there shall no straunge God. &amp;c.</hi> If God speake here to all the people in generall, high and lowe, riche and poore one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then of congruence belongeth it to all people in generall to hearken and carie awaye what is sayde. But howe shall they heare, if they haue not his worde, marke his saying: <hi>If thou wilt harken.</hi> And it must be vnto him we must harken. For whosoeuer speaketh not as he doth, must not be hearde, though it were an Aungell from heauen, as <hi>Paule</hi> sayth:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Galat.</hi> 1.</note> yea, if Christ woulde come and preach any other Gospell, than he hath already preached, we ought not, as some of the olde writers saye, to heare him. Howe much lesse then ought we to harken what these newe Gospellers say, who speake <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Actes.</hi> 20.</note> contorted wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted and peruerse things, altogither repugnant to Gods worde and saying. The prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes also in all their sermons and writings, crie vnto the people, <hi>audite verbum domini,</hi> heare the worde of the Lorde. Loe here is no state, or degrée, no age, or sexe excluded, but all must heare. For <hi>populus</hi> and <hi>turba,</hi> as is often read, in the olde and newe Testament comprehende <hi>promiscuam multitudinem,</hi> the whole multitude one with another.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 15.</note> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no sort is excepted from hearing. But me thinketh I heare what one of these new Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines
<pb facs="6"/>
replyeth: Sir (sayth he) when did we forbid any kinde of persons from hearing our Sermons? No in déede, but when men came to heare you, they coulde not heare <hi>the worde of the Lorde,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 15.</note> but <hi>doctrines that were the preceptes of men,</hi> wherewith Christ sayth, <hi>you worship him in vaine.</hi> It had bene somewhat tollerable, to haue forbidden men the reading of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, so that you had taught them nothing but the scriptures, as you ought to haue done. But to preach your owne fantasies and inuentions, and to forbidde men to search the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which Christ so earnestly commaundeth them to doe, was too too presumpteous for a seruant to doe against his Lordes commaundement. Howbeit, you saye Christ and the Pope haue but one Consistorye, and therefore bicause he commaundeth it, you thinke you may safely doe it. But S. <hi>Paule</hi> aunswereth all these pretie obiections at once, saying: <hi>Bee yee not the seruants of men.</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. <hi>Math.</hi> 16.</note> Howbeit, hereto you will say the Pope is not <hi>purus homo,</hi> a pure man. And that I am sure all that knowe what he is, will easilye graunt you. Surely, S. <hi>Paule</hi> was so little offended that the Thessalonians searched the Scriptures,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Actes.</hi> 17. 1. <hi>Thes.</hi> 12.</note> to sée whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his preaching agréed therewith, yea or no, that he rather much liked and commended them for their doing. But you in no poynt resemble <hi>Paules</hi> condicions, but in persecuting Christ his Church. The same <hi>Dauid</hi> likewise in his .xix. Psalme, hath matter ynough, though there were none other any where else both to prooue howe necessarye the worde of God is for all men to knowe, and also to aunswere the obiections of all our newe Diuines. <hi>The lawe of the Lorde</hi> (sayth he) <hi>is an vndefiled or perfite lawe conuerting the soule. The testimonie of the Lorde is sure, and giueth wisedome vnto the simple.</hi> He calleth the lawe perfyte, to aunswere those controllers which saye the Scriptures are not sufficient, and therefore haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged a sort of vnwritten verities, (so they call them) which they haue matched in authoritie with the Scriptures, and haue commaunded men payne of death to receyue and beléeue them before the Scriptures. He sayth, <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>erteth or turneth the soule,</hi> that is to say, it maketh him that readeth them a newe man, a repentant person, a faythfull beléeuer, and a godly liuer, So farre it is from peruerting or corrupting any godly student thereof. He calleth it <hi>a sure and faithfull testimonie of the Lorde,</hi> whereas mannes policies, councels and deuises are alwayes vncertaine, chaungeable and vnsure. <hi>It giueth wisedome vnto the simple.</hi> Why then shoulde they be kept from it. Uerily this hath bene Gods practise in all ages, as appeareth by all hystories, that he hath reuealed his worde and will to no kinde of people sooner, than vnto those that are simple, as may be séene by those thankes that our Sauiour Christ gaue to God his father in the behalfe of his Disciples being but simple Clarkes, saying; <hi>I thanke thee O God,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 11. <hi>Luc.</hi> 10.</note>
      <hi>fath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>r of heauen and earth, for that thou hast hidden these things</hi> (verilye the vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his kingdome) <hi>from the wise,</hi> that is to saye, the great Doctors, in their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyte, and in the worldes iudgement, <hi>and hast reuealed them vnto the simple,</hi> that is, to the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned and despysed wightes of this worlde. For so doth <hi>Chrysostome</hi> expounde the wordes: <hi>Rusticall people and Ideotes</hi> (sayth he)▪ <hi>were illuminated, persons of small account in the worlde, or in the knowledge of God, but not of obstinacie but ignoraunce.</hi> If our new Diuines would admit these sayings of Christ, and <hi>Chrysostome,</hi> they shoulde soone perceyue how vnchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianly they speake, and also howe vnlyke the olde Doctors, whyle they raue and fare so fowle wyth poore Artificers and Craftesmen, whome it hath pleased God in these dayes, so to enriche with his spirite, that when they haue bene called before these our newe <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines,</hi> they haue shewed more true Diuinitie, than all the whole Sinagoge of them were able. I report me to <hi>Eusebius</hi> Ecclesiasticall hystory, and to our owne, entituled the Actes and Monumentes of the Church. But <hi>Dauid</hi> goeth on saying: <hi>The statutes of the Lorde are right, and reioyce the heart: the commaundement of the Lorde is pure, and giueth light to the eyes. The feare of the Lorde is cleane and endureth for euer: the iudgementes of the Lorde are true and righteous altogither. More to be desired are they than golde, yea, than much fine golde: sweeter also than hony and the bony combe. Moreouer, by them is thy seruant taught.</hi> What? I warraunt you, this olde Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine <hi>Dauid</hi> neuer ment that they taught eyther heresie or error. In diuers other places of his Psalter, maye be séene the earnest exhortations that he maketh to all the people, to heare the worde of God, as in the .xlix. Psalme, <hi>O heare ye this all ye people, ponder it with your eares, all ye that dwell in the worlde. High and lowe, rich and poore, one with another.</hi> What shoulde they heare? euen that that immediately followeth, <hi>howe his mouth shall speake of wisedome, and his heart muse of vnderstanding.</hi> Here are none excluded from hearing what <hi>Dauid</hi> shall say,
<pb facs="6"/>
but such as dwell in <hi>Vtopia.</hi> The Diuines therefore that will barre any dwellers in this worlde from hearing or reading of <hi>Dauid,</hi> must there go preache this doctrine. Agayne, <hi>Wherewithall shall a yong man clense his waye? euen by ruling himselfe after thy worde.</hi> Againe,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.</note>
      <hi>Thy worde is a lanterne to my feete, and a light vnto my pathes.</hi> Againe: <hi>When thy worde goeth forth, it giueth light and vnderstanding euen vnto the simple.</hi> Againe: <hi>Kings of the earth, and all people, Princes and all Iudges of the worlde, yong men and maydens, olde men and children, prayse the name of the Lord.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 148.</note> Here by an enumeration of al states and degrées, sexes and ages, may we sée that none are secluded from praysing the Lorde, which then is done moste acceptablye, when we sing prayse vnto him, as the same <hi>Dauid</hi> sayth, <hi>with vnderstanding,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 47.</note> which vnderstanding we can not haue without his worde. Infynite more places there be in the Psalter to this effect, as the diligent Reader thereof shall finde, whereof this is one verye notable, and therefore not to be omitted: <hi>Out of the mouthes of very babes &amp; sucklings, hast thou ordeyned strength,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 8. <hi>Math.</hi> 21.</note>
      <hi>that thou mightest still the enimy and the auenger.</hi> It is the more notable, for that Christ alleageth it in the .xxj. of <hi>Mathewe,</hi> agaynst the Scribes and Phariseyes, in defence of the people, which so thankefully welcommed and receyued him into Ierusalem, in the same sense that it is here brought for. But let vs nowe come to the testimonies of the newe Testament. Our Sauiour Christ hauing to doe with those Iewes which of all other in the worlde at that time, most gloried in the knowledge of God and his religion, bicause they had Bishoppes, whose succession, they coulde shewe by order euen from <hi>Aaron,</hi> and therefore had antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ynough, hauing Scribes, Phariseyes, Sadduceyes, Essenes, Nobles, Communes, and all the worlde on their side: yet did he plainly tell them that they erred, and were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, for that they vnderstoode not the Scriptures. For to the Sadduceyes which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed no part of the olde Testament, but the bookes of <hi>Moses,</hi> denying the resurrection, for that they imagined (if there were any) men shoulde knowe their wiues, as they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore done in the worlde, as appeareth by their captious and foolishe demaunde, Christ aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered: <hi>yee erre, not vnderstanding the Scriptures and power of God.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 22. <hi>Marc.</hi> 12. <hi>Luc.</hi> 20.</note> Where we maye plainely learne that ignoraunce in the Scripture is the cause of error, contrary to these newe Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes assertion, that saye: <hi>Ignorance is the mother of deuotion.</hi> Whereas true deuotion cannot be without the true vnderstanding of Gods will, and his will by no meanes ordinary can be vnderstanded, but by his worde. Therefore to auoyde errour, it is moste méete that people haue the Scriptures to search and vnderstande the will of God by. Another time, hauing to doe with the Phariseyes also (as these two sectes of men were the greatest assay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantes that Christ euer had, whereby we learne it is no newe practise that they most per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute Christes Church, that challenge most authoritie and learning in the same) he bade them for that they séemed to haue such exact knowledge in the worde of God, and yet knew not that he was that <hi>Messias</hi> and Sauiour, that God had promised them, to search better in the Scriptures, and they shoulde finde that the Scriptures in all places,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5.</note> did testifye and beare witnesse that he was the same. Whereby Christ plainly giueth vs to vnderstande that without the Scriptures we cannot truly knowe him. These two places declare suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently howe necessarye the Scriptures are for all that will knowe Christ. We will adde two other testimonies to shewe howe profitable they are. S. <hi>Paule</hi> in his Epistle to the Romaines, sayth: <hi>Whatsoeuer thinges haue bene written afore time,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.</note>
      <hi>they haue bene written for our learning, that through pacience and comfort of the Scriptures, we might haue hope.</hi> They are not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for Monkes and Friers onely to pore vpon, but for our learning, that is, for as many as professe Christ, which thing being spoken by <hi>Paule</hi> of the olde Testament (for as yet the newe was not written) howe much more learning may we nowe receyue, hauing the writings of the Euangelistes and Apostles ioyned all togither? Likewise in his seconde Epistle to <hi>Timothie</hi> the thirde Chapter, he sayth: <hi>All Scripture inspired of God is profitable to teach, to reprooue, to correct and amende in righteousnesse, that the man of God may be perfite, instructed vnto all good workes.</hi> This <hi>epitheton</hi> or adiectiue, inspired of God, quite wypeth awaye all vnwritten verities, all mannes gloses, and traditions, all fayned visions and myracles, such as are to be founde in <hi>Gregorie</hi> the Popes dialogues, and throughout the workes of our newe Diuines. Since therefore the Scripture teacheth, reprooueth, correcteth and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth, maketh men perfite and furnished with all good workes, what thing then can there be deuised in all the worlde of more profite and vtilitie? Had I not bounde my selfe
<pb facs="7"/>
by a particion, to prooue by apparant reason also the truth of this assertion, I shoulde néede no further to trouble eyther my selfe with more writing, or you with more reading. But such promises as these we are bounde to performe. First therefore this is one reason verye euident &amp; playne, that séeing <hi>our Sauiour Christ</hi> (as <hi>Paule</hi> sayth) <hi>woulde haue all men to be saued, and to come to the knowledge of the truth:</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</note> and for that ende did and suffered whatsoeuer he did and suffred, while he liued here on earth: the meane whereby men shoulde attaine vnto that truth and saluation, which are Gods holy Scriptures, ought by no meanes to be kept from them. The practise of our Sauiour, admitting all men to his sermons and familiar communication, Publicanes, souldiors, artificers, Phariseys, harlots, strayed shéepe, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous persons, yea, kéeping company most with such, abundantly prooue the same. And bicause the scriptures as teaching y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> way to come vnto god best of all other things, are mée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test for such straglers, &amp; all men by testimonie of the same scripture, of their owne nature &amp; disposition are such straglers, therfore ought all straglers, that is to say, all men to haue the law &amp; the scriptures, wherby they may both sée howe they haue strayed out of the way, and how to returne into the same againe. The <hi>Maior</hi> is prooued by Christ, <hi>Math.</hi> 22. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5. &amp; by the olde Doctors, as we shall sée when we come to the last part of our particion. The <hi>Minor</hi> God himselfe maketh <hi>Genes.</hi> 8. where he sayth: <hi>The imagination of mans heart is euill euen from his youth.</hi> The writings of the Prophetes and Apostles, doe inculcate and repeate nothing more. The places are infinite, therefore I quote them not. The commaundement of Christ a little before his ascention bidding his Apostles to go into all the world, and teach the gospell to all Nations, doth further prooue it, as their practise also declared, teaching the same somewhile to Tentmakers, somewhile to Tanners, somewhile to women that were Dyers, otherwhiles to Souldiers, yea, at all times, to all states and degrées of persons. And whereas Christ was borne, dyed and was buryed, rose againe, and ascended into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for all men, and shall come agayne to receyue all states and degrées of men, for with God <hi>there is no respect of persons,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Actes.</hi> 10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>but in euery Nation, he that feareth him, and woorketh righteousnesse, is accepted of him.</hi> What are we that we shoulde withstande god, and kéepe this knowledge from any kinde of menne? What meaneth it moreouer that Christ will haue his light to shine throughout his house,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 5. <hi>Mar.</hi> 4. <hi>Luc.</hi> 8.</note> that he will haue his worde preached on the house toppes, that the light of his gospell must not be put vnder a bushell? why doth he many times conclude his sermons thus generally: <hi>He that hath eares to heare, let him beare?</hi> Why doth god cry vnto the Prophets,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 19. <hi>Math.</hi> 11.13. <hi>Marc.</hi> 4. <hi>Esay.</hi> 58.</note> bidding them to speake out, and exalt their voyces like to a Trumpet, and to tell his people their wickednesse? Christ suffred all men, Tinkers, Taylers, Carpenters, Coblers, Masons, and Bricklayers, to heare his voyce, and will these Comptrollers barre them from reading his bookes? But I wote what a newe deuine will saye. In the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church when the scriptures were extant for all men to reade, what a swarme of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes bredde they which disturbed the whole church? What heresie hath there bene at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time so absurde, but it hath had hir colour of maintenance out of the Scripture? Sir, by the way, I will take it for graunted, that you say the Scriptures were extaunt in the primitiue Church, for all men to reade, as in déede they were. And so was it gods will they shoulde be, and for that cause did the holy ghost mooue the Euangelistes and the Apostles, to wryte the gospels and the Epistles in the Gréeke tongue, which then was vniuersallye vnderstoode of most Nations, yet notwithstanding, these heresies bredde (as you say) the primitiue church neuer called the scriptures in, ne yet forbade any kinde of people the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of them. You haue done both without all example of the primitiue church, whereby may and doe appeare your newe proceedings. But nowe to aunswere question with que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion: what heresie I praye you euer was there, but the same hath bene confuted by the scriptures? Bicause some men haue misvsed the scriptures, shall all menne be depriued of them? shall the Bées be kept frō gathering hony of the swéete flowers, bicause spiders make poyson of them? shall all they that can vse wine and breade to chéere and strengthen mans heart, giuing god thanks for them, taste or assay none of them, bicause a great many abuse them to surfetting &amp; drunkennesse? Lay the fault where it is, in the men, not in the things that they misvse. What fault is in the money that lyeth and rusteth in the cofer of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous? what in the knife or sworde that killeth a bodye? <hi>Ptholomeus Philadelphus</hi> thought himselfe very well occupied (as in déede he was) when he caused y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bookes of <hi>Moses</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>
and the prophets to be translated into the Gréeke tongue by thréescore and tenne learned men, called the seauentie Translators or Interpreters, two hundreth thréescore and sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentene yeares before Christ was borne. An hundreth and fower and twenty yeares after Christes ascention, <hi>Aquila</hi> a Iewe, in the dayes of <hi>Adrian</hi> the Emperor, translated them againe. After him <hi>Theodotion</hi> in <hi>Commodus</hi> dayes. Then <hi>Symachus</hi> vnder <hi>Seuerus.</hi> Then was there an other translation founde at <hi>Hierusalem</hi> without anye name, called the common translation. After this againe <hi>Origene</hi> tooke great paynes to correct the sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentie Translators, adding of his owne where he thought they were not full, and taking from them where he sawe redundance and superfluitie. All these no doubt labouring to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucidate and make playner, as much as in them lay, the former translations. Yea, S. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> after all this, was not afrayde to translate the whole Bible againe, into the Latine tongue, which is perished. He translated diuers other treatises also out of Gréeke into La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, as <hi>Didimus</hi> worke touching the deitie of the holy ghost. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> bishop of <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus</hi> Epistle to <hi>Iohn</hi> the Patriarch of <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> and diuers other such. And bicause none shall saye, what maketh this for the translating of the Bible into other more vulgar ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, as into the Englishe. &amp;c. For they can well admit the Hebrewe, Gréeke, and Latine tongues, and any other that the people vnderstande not, therefore S. <hi>Hierome</hi> translated the Bible into the Sclauonian tongue, that is to say, into his owne natiue countrie tongue. We haue therefore antiquitie ynough on our side for proofe of our diuers translations. Neyther did he euer feare or make account of such inconueniences, as these new Diuines pretende, spring of such translations, or any thing regarded the sharpe censure and checks of diuers Comptrollers, that founde fault with his doings, but helde on and continued to the ende translating, wryting, and endyting, sending his bookes onewhile to virgins, one other whyle to married women, sometime to widowes, but euer to one kinde of person or other, being still exercised and occupied in such doinges. And I marueyle why these men should be so offended, that euery Nation shoulde haue the scriptures in their owne tongue, séeing in some places of their writings they make the holy ghost the author of this opinion and iudgement. Doth not <hi>Aeneas Syluius</hi> which was afterwarde Pope, and called <hi>Pius secundus,</hi> tell vs, that when about the yeare of our Lord .900. there fell a great contention at Rome, whether the Hungarians shoulde haue their seruice in their owne tongue, yea, or no: that there was a voyce hearde from heauen, saying: <hi>Let euery thing that hath breath,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 150.</note>
      <hi>prayse the Lord, and euery tongue giue thankes vnto his holy name?</hi> Whervpon (sayth this <hi>Aeneas</hi>) the Councell brake vp, and the contention surceased. So that by this storye, whosoeuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth Gods people Gods seruice in their owne proper tongue, resist Gods ordinance and commaundement. These men count it a great absurditie, that a woman, a childe, or an artificer, shoulde talke of the Gospell, or of the Scripture. And yet many times we may heare women, children, and artificers, vnderstande more of Gods holy mysteries, than a number of some ruddy Rabbines, that notwithstanding looke very high and lofty. <hi>Moses</hi> was not of this minde and opinion. For when <hi>Iehosuah</hi> his seruant would haue had him to forbid <hi>Heldad</hi> and <hi>Medad</hi> from prophecying, he aunswered,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Numer.</hi> 11.</note>
      <hi>woulde God that all the Lordes people coulde prophecie, and that he woulde giue his spirite vnto them all.</hi> Christ commaundeth little children to be suffred to come vnto him, and not to be forbidden.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Marc.</hi> 10.</note> But who maye not more iustly thinke it a greater absurditie, to heare women, children, and artificers patter their <hi>Pater noster</hi> in a tongue that they so little vnderstande, that Cardinall <hi>Ascanius</hi> Parot at Rome was as wise as they. Yea, the Crowe that saluted <hi>Augustus,</hi> coulde saye his <hi>Aue Caesar,</hi> better than they coulde their <hi>Aue Maria.</hi> And surely if the newe Diuines <hi>godly intention</hi> may not in this case helpe at a pinch, they may also saye and say truly, as an other Crowe did at another time, <hi>we haue lost all our labour.</hi> So little doth God allowe such godly intention. For he biddeth we shoulde not <hi>be like Horse and Mule,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 32.</note>
      <hi>in whome there is none vnderstanding.</hi> Then séeing we haue the Scriptures, aswell of the olde Testament as the newe, so full and whole on our side, séeing Christ commaundeth vs <hi>to search the Scriptures,</hi> séeing S. <hi>Paule</hi> sayth, <hi>they are written for our learning and instruction,</hi> séeing we haue thexam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Primitiue Church, permitting all men to haue and reade the Scriptures in all tongues, séeing we haue so many translations of the Scriptures, I meane of olde tyme, I speake not of those in the Englishe tongue, in <hi>Ethelstanes</hi> dayes, and in the Saxons
<pb facs="8"/>
tongue, ne yet of that gift of tongues giuen to the Apostles, to the intent that all Nations might heare the great workes of God in their owne language, séeing there is nothing in the Scriptures, eyther threatened or promised, but it appertayneth to all men in all ages, nothing done by Christ of olde, but the same in one respect or other is dailye done. For Christ is newly borne among vs euen at this day. There are <hi>Herodes</hi> that goe about to murther him in his Cradle euen at this day.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 2. <hi>Luc.</hi> 2. <hi>Math.</hi> 14.15. <hi>Luc.</hi> 5.</note> He notwithstanding groweth in fauour with God and men euen at this day? He healeth all maner of maladies, Leprouse, Demoniacks, Dumbe, Blinde, Deafe, Dropsies, Palsies, bloudy Fluxes at this day, so that we say, <hi>sonne of Dauid haue mercy vpon vs,</hi> and <hi>Lord, if thou wilt, thou canst make vs whole.</hi> Yea, he rayseth men from death to life againe by the power of his worde euen at this daye?<note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 9.20. <hi>Math.</hi> 8. <hi>Luc.</hi> 5. <hi>Math.</hi> 21. <hi>Mar.</hi> 12. <hi>Luc.</hi> 20. <hi>Math.</hi> 26. <hi>Marc.</hi> 14. <hi>Luc.</hi> 22. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 18. <hi>Math.</hi> 27. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6.</note> He teacheth, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, promiseth, comforteth euen at this day. There are Iewes which will not suffer their vayled <hi>Moses</hi> to yéelde to his brightnesse in these dayes? He hath Scribes, Phariseys, and Sadduceyes, that lye in wayte to catch and entangle him in his talke euen nowe a dayes also. He hath more than one <hi>Annas</hi> and <hi>Caiphas</hi> to buye, and more than one <hi>Iscarioth</hi> to sell him at this daye. <hi>Herode, Pylate,</hi> and their Crewes want not to mocke, whip, and crucifie him, yea, to kéepe him downe also in his graue, that he rise not againe, euen at this day. And yet all this notwithstanding, he hath still also at this day his little flocke that doth and will depende vpon him, saying: <hi>Lorde, to whome shall we go? Thou hast the wordes of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life.</hi> Therefore whatsoeuer the newe Diuines say to the contrary, let vs still reade the Scriptures, and sticke to that olde Diuinitie. But bicause many men are ledde not so much eyther with reason or testimonies of Scriptures, as with authoritie of Doctors, to fulfill my promise, and somedeale to satisfye (if happily it may be) their preposterous zeale and peruerse iudgement, I will shewe also that the best and soundest of the olde Doctors, haue alwayes bene of this opinion, that all people at all times ought to haue the scriptures in their owne tongue. And if any man as delighting in a worke of supererrogation, that is to say, for a man to doe more than he hath bounde himselfe to, or néedeth, shall require so much. I will also by the olde Doctors aunswere the obiections of such as thinke the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ought not to bee read of all men, bicause of the difficultie of them, and that varietie of translations cause and bréede errors. And first we will begin with the Doctors of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Church, not for worthynesse eyther of life or learning, that hath bene at anye time in them, more than in the Gréekes. For verily the Gréekes are able to shew as many worthy writers of their Church, as the Latines can by any meanes, if I say not more: but bicause perhaps some Romanist or Latine man may hit vpon this writing, which (if he be partial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected toward the Latine Doctors) may first sée what the opinion of the Latine Church was in this poynt, by one of the most approouedst Doctors in the same Church. S. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> vpon these wordes of <hi>Paule</hi> to the Colossians,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Colos.</hi> 3.</note>
      <hi>Let the worde of Christ dwell plentifullye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you,</hi> sayth thus: <hi>By this place it is declared, that euen the laye people ought to haue the woorde of Christ among them, not onely sufficiently, but also abundantly, and to teach and admonishe one another.</hi> Here besides that S. <hi>Hierome</hi> permitteth the lay people to haue the Scriptures, and that plenteously, he also suffereth them to teach and instruct one another, saying moreouer that it is their dutie so to doe. <hi>Chrysostome</hi> vpon the same place and wordes, sayeth euen the same thing, though in more large and ample maner: <hi>Harken</hi> (sayth he) <hi>all yee secular people, that haue charge of wife and children, howe the Apostle commaundeth you chiefly to reade the scriptures, and that not lightly and slenderly, but with great diligence.</hi> And a litle after that again: <hi>Lysten</hi> (sayth he) <hi>I pray you, all you laye people, Buye you the Bible, which is the medicine of the soule: Or if you will haue nothing else, get you the newe Testament, the Gospels and Actes of the Apostles for your continuall and diligent teachers.</hi> And by and by after he addeth: <hi>This</hi> (sayth he) <hi>is the cause of all euill, that the scriptures are not vnderstanded.</hi>
      <note n="ix." place="margin">
         <hi>Homely vpon the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lossians.</hi>
      </note> Note well I pray you howe <hi>Chrysostome</hi> holdeth this as an vndoubted and infallible truth, that ignoraunce in the Scriptures is the cause of all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. Our Countrie man <hi>Beda</hi> called worshipfull (as I suppose) bicause of his great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and reuerende life and demeanor, is of the very same iudgement, as appeareth by that he hath written vpon the first Epistle of S. <hi>Peter</hi> the seconde Chapter. I might also here shewe howe the sayde <hi>Beda</hi> for more than nyne hundreth yeares past, translated the Gospell of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> into the Englishe tongue, and howe <hi>Constantine</hi> so greatly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for his godlynesse, caused infinite copies of the Byble to be written and sent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode
<pb facs="8"/>
into all the partes of his Empyre, long before that. But returne we to <hi>Chryso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome,</hi> who many times chideth (as it were) with his hearers, for that they giue no better héede to his sermons, sometimes againe, he prayeth and desireth them, that they woulde come oftner to them, and reade and pervse the scriptures at home at their houses, more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently than they had vsed. Otherwhiles he aunswereth the obiections they vsed to make for their excuse. But let vs heare his owne words. <hi>Tell me</hi> (saith he) <hi>I pray you, you that stand here present, which of you can say one Psalme without the booke, if it were required of you, or any other peece of the scripture?</hi> And he by &amp; by maketh their obiection &amp; answere. <hi>But</hi> (sayth he) <hi>this is your defence for all such faultes: I am (say you) no Monke, I haue wife and children, and charge of housholde, verily this is it, wherewith as it were with the plague, you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>arre and corrupt all thinges, bicause you thinke the reading of scriptures belongeth to Monkes onely, where in deede it is much more necessary for you, than for them, for they that go abrode in the world, and daily receyue wounde vpon wound, haue more neede of Gods medicine than other men, Wherefore it is a more grieuous and heynous fault, to thinke the lawe of God to be superfluous, than to be ignorant in it, for these be wordes proceeding of a diuelishe cogitation. Hearest thou not Paule say, the scriptures are written for our correction?</hi> Thus much hath <hi>Chrisostome</hi> in his second Homelie vpon S. <hi>Mathew,</hi> &amp; these words also to the like effect in the same place folowing. <hi>This sect</hi> (sayth he) <hi>is the working of the deuils inspiration, that will not suffer vs to loke vpon the treasure, least we should attaine to the riches therof. Therfore he perswadeth men that there is no profit ryseth by reading the holy Scriptures, bicause he woulde see no practise followe of the hearing.</hi> Againe, in his .xvij. Homelie vpon the Epistle to the Hebrues, he bringeth other like obiections, whervnto he also answereth: <hi>Thou wilt saye</hi> (sayth he) <hi>I haue not reade it, this is no excuse, but a fault.</hi> And in his .xxviii. Homely vpon the <hi>Genesis,</hi> he earnestly erhorteth and counsayleth all men to the hearing &amp; reading of the scriptures. These be his words: <hi>I pray you</hi> (sayth he) <hi>come hither oftener, and harken more diligently to the reading of the holy Scripture, and not onely when you come hither, but at home also take the holy Bible in your handes, and receyue with great studie the commoditie therein conteyned.</hi> And a little after that againe. <hi>I pray you therfore</hi> (sayth he) <hi>let vs not lose so great a commoditie through our negligence, but let vs apply the reading of the holy scripture, euen at home also.</hi> Nowe if these newe Diuines, which haue gone so long disguised vnder the visar of antiquitie, will yet farther replye and saye, that the Scriptures are to difficult for all men to vnderstand, and that they are not sufficient to discusse all controuersies that may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rise in the church, but that we must wayte for the <hi>Oire</hi> and <hi>determiner</hi> of counselles, or that diuersitie of translations bréede obscuritie and errours among the people: we will hereto also make them an aunswere, and that out of the doctors, that it may herein also appeare, that they doe but pretende doctors, seing they will not yéelde to the doctors, when they heare them speake, and make so expressely against them. First touching hardnesse and difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, wherewith they charge the scripture. Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> in his second booke of christian doctrine and sixe chapter, sayth thus: <hi>The holye ghost hath so honorably and wholesomely tempered and qualified the holye Scriptures, that it hath put hunger awaye by playner places, and lothsomnesse by darker.</hi> And againe in his thirde Epistle to <hi>Volusianus,</hi> he sayth: <hi>The maner of speech, wherof the holy scripture consisteth all men may easely come vnto, although verie fewe can pearce through it, vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the playner things therein conteyned, like a familiar friend without all coulour, to the heart aswell of the vnlearned, as learned. And those things which it hydeth in mysteries, it doth not set out with haul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie elocution, fraying the slowe and vnlearned minde to come neere it, lyke as the poore man commeth vnto the riche, but allureth all men with lowlinesse of speeche, feeding them not onely with manifest truth, but exercising them with secret, hauing the verie same things in playner places, that it hath in harder. Cyrill</hi> in his seauenth booke against <hi>Iulian</hi> sayth: <hi>to the intent that the scriptures might be knowne to all men both small and great, they are so commodiously set foorth in familiar speache, that they passe nones ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie.</hi> Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> vpon the .xix. chapter of <hi>Esay</hi> sayth. <hi>It is the maner of the scriptures, after harder things, to set playner.</hi> Saint <hi>Austen</hi> in his .83. booke, and .69. question, affirmeth that <hi>circumstaunce of the Scriptures, openeth the sence and meaning. Tertullian</hi> in his booke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Praxeas</hi> prooueth, that <hi>the rather and selder places, must be expounded by the mo, and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tener.</hi> And <hi>Chrysostome</hi> among many places, hath one verie notable in his first Homely vpon <hi>Mathew,</hi> where he sayth: <hi>The Scriptures are easie to be vnder standed, of the bondman, of the Plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, of the wydowe, of the childe, and of him that seemeth to be verie slender witted.</hi> Howbeit, though they will after a sort let passe other scriptures as vncomptrolled, yet <hi>Paules</hi> wrytings and
<pb facs="9"/>
Epistles of all other séeme very harde vnto them, and that they woulde séeme to prooue by <hi>Peters</hi> wordes in the thirde Chapter of his seconde Epistle, whereas God knoweth all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther scriptures, euen the easiest are alike harde to such as <hi>Peter</hi> speaketh of. For they be <hi>vnlearned and vnconstant and fickle persons,</hi> which peruert and turne them to their owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction. But will you heare what <hi>Chrysostome</hi> aunswereth to this obiection, speaking of <hi>Paules</hi> Epistle to the Romaines, in his Preface vpon the same, that you maye sée there is none so pieuishe an obiection of these newe Diuines, but the same is aunswered by some olde Doctor or other, if they be well searched. <hi>Ignorance</hi> (sayth <hi>Chrysostome</hi>) <hi>is not the cause hereof</hi> (he meaneth that they vnderstoode not the Epistle to the Romaines) <hi>but that they will not continually haue in their handes the writings of this holy man. For that which we our selues knowe (if peraduenture we know ought at all) we know it not by the pregnancie and goodnesse of our owne wit, but for that we be so entirely affectioned to that man, that we neuer cease reading of him. For they that loue men, knowe more of their doings than other men, as being more carefull for their lou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rs than other are.</hi> And therevpon concluding he sayth: <hi>Wherfore if you also can finde in your harts, earnestly and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to bestowe your labour in reading him, there shall bee nothing else required of you. For Christes say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is true, Seeke and you shall finde, knocke and it shall be opened vnto you.</hi> And surely <hi>Chrysostome</hi> spake not this to Priestes and religious men onely, but to all his Church of <hi>Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> and vniuersally to as many as shoulde reade his workes. And he sayeth further in his .vij. homely to the Hebrewes, in reproofe of those that vsed not to looke vpon y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> scriptures: <hi>No man will take heede</hi> (sayth he) <hi>vnto the Scriptures. For if we woulde marke them, we shoulde not only keepe our selues from errour, but deliuer other also that are deceyued out of the same, and pull them out of daunger.</hi> Moreouer, vpon the seconde of <hi>Genesis</hi> the .xiij. Chapter he sayth: <hi>Let vs come to the scope and marke of the holy Scripture, which expoundeth it selfe.</hi> And againe: <hi>The holy Scripture expoundeth it selfe, and suffereth not the hearer to erre. Tertullian</hi> also one of the first wryters next the Apostles,<note place="margin">In his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie toward the ende.</note> in his Apologie for the Christians, sayth: <hi>He that will harken to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, shall finde God, and he that will studie to vnderstand them, shall be enforced to beleue them.</hi> These places of Doctors as well of the Latine Church, as of the Gréeke, are sufficient ynough to teach and perswade any reasonable bodye, the iudgement that the whole Church vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall had, both as touching the Scriptures to be had and read of all men, and also to prooue the facilitie and easinesse of them to be vnderstanded, and so consequently mine assertion, and howe Catholikely our Church doth, and like vnto the Primitiue Church, in permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all persons indifferently to haue the Scriptures to looke and reade in to their instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and vnderstanding. And if any of these newe Diuines will not herewith be satisfyed, but will yet vrge custome, authoritie of Predecessors, and such lyke weake instances, for their new <hi>Mumpsimus,</hi> rather than they will yéelde to this olde <hi>Sumpsimus:</hi> then let vs aunswere them roundly thus with the words of S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> vpon the .ix. chap. of <hi>Ieremie,</hi> saying: <hi>Neyther must the error of our parents nor forefathers be followed, but the authoritie of the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the commaundement of God teaching vs.</hi> And though they crie out neuer so much, they haue the Scriptures, whereby to prooue their opinions, which God wote many a time they apply to their purpose as handsomely as the deuill did when he reasoned with Christ in the wildernesse, and as the olde and new Heretikes did and doe, which (as they say, so we like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise affirme) doe accloy the Church in déede very much: then let vs aunswere them with <hi>Tertullian</hi> saying thus, in his booke of the fleshe or true manhoode that Christ tooke: <hi>Let all Heretikes</hi> (sayth he) <hi>vse his scriptures, whose worlde they also vse. This shall serue for a testimonye of their condemnation, that they decke and furnishe their blasphemies with his examples.</hi> And if they will haue Councels to decyde and controll all controuersies, whereof consist they, I pray you, not of men? What are menne, such creatures as cannot erre? Then shoulde they be no men. The best Doctors in the Church, haue erred in some part or other of their writings, or at least haue thought they might erre. I report me else to their owne sayinges in their bookes, to be founde in euery place, where they neuer arrogate to themselues anye such prowde priuiledge and immunitie from erring, as the late loftie Prelates of Rome hath done, but with all lowlynesse submit their writinges to the Scriptures, and to those that shall see or perceyue more in them than they haue done, yea, requiring men fréely to finde fault and correct, where they haue not attayned to the truth. This woulde they neuer haue done, if they had knowne or thought they coulde not haue erred. And what one of the
<pb facs="9"/>
Popes can we name in the Church for this sixe hundred yere or more, comparable eyther in life or learning with any one of these olde Doctors, which thus modestlye haue written of themselues? And shall we thinke better men than these Doctors haue met in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, since their dayes? I say no more, but I woulde there had mette so good. They will yet saye, Heresies haue bene alwayes confuted in Councelles, and I saye Heresies haue bene alwayes confirmed in Councels. Did not the Councell at <hi>Ariminum</hi> in Italie holde and conclude with the Arrianes? Did not the seconde Councell at <hi>Ephesus,</hi> holde with <hi>Entiches</hi>? Did not the Councell at <hi>Chalcedon</hi> so fowly erre, that they woulde haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to <hi>Leo</hi> then Bishop of Rome, the title of supremacie, and vniuersall Bishop, which he refused, wherein surely he erred not? But what they since haue done, that by slaughter and murther, and other such vniust meanes haue vsurped it, both heauen and earth knoweth? The Councell also gathered by <hi>Cyprian</hi> at <hi>Carthage,</hi> did grieuouslye erre, enacting that they that were baptised by Heretikes, shoulde be baptised againe, before they woulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them into their Church. And the Councell at <hi>Constance,</hi> did moste abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably consent in error to robbe Gods people of the one halfe of Christes sacrament. What did the late Councell at <hi>Trent,</hi> being fouretéene yeares at the least in trauell, bring forth at length? Forsooth <hi>Horatius</hi> mountaines in Italie were great with childe, and after their harde trauell brought forth a Mouse. What one error or abuse in their Church, of so many, as all the worlde nowe séeth, and they (although they be impudent ynough) cannot denie, haue they refourmed? Surely neuer might that worthy Bishoppe of <hi>Nazianzum</hi> his saying be more truly spoken than of these Councels, <hi>If I must needes write the truth</hi> (sayth he) <hi>I neuer sawe any good ende or conclusion of these Bishops Councels,</hi> in his Epistle to <hi>Procopius</hi> the .xlij. Epist. And yet they shame not still to say, the holye ghost is President of their Councels, and that he is shut in the closet of the Popes breast. But I trowe it is not that holy ghost that Christ sayth, <hi>breatheth where it will,</hi> for that it woulde not be so partially tyed to the Popes bosome, or that appeared vpon Christ in likenesse of a Doue. It is I beléeue, that ghastly ghost the Owle, that sate so long in the Consistorie on a time ouer the Popes heade, a méete holy ghost I assure you for such a consistorie and closet. Lette vs therefore leaue them, and this president of their Councels, and marke what séemeth good to Gods holy spirite, and to the Euangelistes and Apostles, and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>llowe the same, considering as S. <hi>Augustine</hi> sayth in his seconde Epistle to S. <hi>Ierome,</hi> that <hi>no Scriptures are to be allowed, but the vndoubted Canonicall.</hi> And in his first booke and seconde chapter against the Epistle of <hi>Parmenian,</hi> he iudgeth it <hi>a rashe and presumptuous part to beleeue anye, that prooueth not that hee sayth by scriptures.</hi> And in his thirde booke and .vj. chapter against the letters of <hi>Petilian,</hi> he <hi>hold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>th any thing accursed, that is beside the lawe and the Gospell.</hi> In his first booke of christian doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, xxxvij. chap. he sayth: <hi>Our faith staggereth, if it be not vpholden by scriptures.</hi> In his .166. Epistle, he sayth both <hi>Christ and his Church is knowne by the scriptures.</hi> In his seconde booke of Christian doctrine and .vj. chap. he sayth <hi>the holy ghost hath caused the darker thinges in the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to be opened by playner.</hi> And <hi>Chrysostome</hi> in his seconde exposition vppon <hi>Mathewe,</hi> the .xxiiij. and .xxix. Homelies sayth, <hi>The true Church can no waye else bee knowne, but onely by the Scriptures, bicause whatsoeuer things else in the Church, Heretikes haue aswell as Catholikes.</hi> But now to that they saye, diuersitie of translations in Scripture bréedeth error, although the same be sufficiently ynough confuted before, by the example of the seauentie Translators or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters, by those fiue or sixe more that after Christes time corrected them, by <hi>Origen,</hi> by <hi>Hierome,</hi> by the Euangelistes and Apostles, writing in the Gréeke tongue: yet we will alleage one or two places out of olde Doctors for confirmation of the same. For touching all obiections that the aduersaries can make, they are so fully aunswered by the olde Doctors, as partly you maye haue perceyued, that it were but vaine further to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell therein. S. <hi>Augustine</hi> which is one of the fower Cardinall and principall Doctors, that our aduersaries allowe, who impugne this opinion, sayth thus against them. <hi>They that haue translated the Scriptures</hi> (sayth he) <hi>out of the Hebrewe tongue into the Greeke, maye be numbred, but the Latine interpreters by no meanes. For in the beginning of the fayth, assoone as one had gotten a Greeke booke into his handes, and seemed to haue some knowledge in both the tongues, he tooke vppon him to interprete the same. Which thing did more further than hinder vnderstanding, so that the readers be not negligent. For the pervsing of diuers bookes hath often times opened the darker sentences.</hi> The place is
<pb facs="10"/>
in his seconde booke of Christian doctrine, and .xij. chapter. And <hi>Nicholaus de Lyra</hi> one of our aduersaries owne Doctors, sayth in his Preface vpon the <hi>Genesis:</hi> that <hi>Diuersitie of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positors stirreth vp attention:</hi> But to bring more testimonies in a matter so cléere as daye, is but impertinent, séeing that both Gods lawe and mans alloweth the truth, though testified but with two or thrée witnesses. Thus hast thou gentle Reader my promise made in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, confirmed by authoritie of Scriptures, euident reasons, and testimonies of auncient Doctors, though not in such abundant wise as might be, yet in as large a sort as the lawe and rule of a Preface will permit. Let vs therefore addresse and prepare our sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues diligently, not onely to reade the Scriptures, but also to vnderstande them, and not to vnderstande them onely, and there to stay, (as I am afrayde too manye in these dayes make that their onely ende of reading) but also to frame our selues to expresse our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing in our liues and conuersation, least hauing the Gospell still in our mouthes, and shewing nothing thereof in our maners, and yet protesting a more sounde and exact know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge than others, we encrease at length but our owne punishment and damnation, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>euery one that sayth Lorde, Lorde, shall not enter into the kingdome of heauen, but he that doth the will of the father which is in heauen.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. <hi>Luc.</hi> 12.</note>
      <hi>And howe the seruant that knoweth his maisters will and doth it not, shall be beaten with many stripes.</hi> Let vs remember that the temple of <hi>Salomon,</hi> and the writings of the lawes and Prophetes among the Iewes, little profited them, bicause they abused them, and woulde not leade a life aunswereable to such blessings of God. God spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not that stocke of the Iewes of so many hundreth yeares groweth,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.</note> verily no more will he vs, that are but Impes graft and set in the same stocke, if we doe not better than we doe, and they did. But againe, if we liue a repentant life as we ought to doe, and a thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto God for his innumerable benefites, and specially for the light of his worde nowe shining in our Church of Englande, so ordering our works that they may shine <hi>before men, and glorifie our father which is in heauen:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 5.</note> then rage the worlde neuer so much by Gods permis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion against his little flocke, for their proofe and triall, yet shall it neuer be able to take one of them out of his hand,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iohn.</hi> 10.</note> but that he will ayde and assist vs with the presence of his spirite, and rule (as <hi>Dauid</hi> sayth) <hi>in the middle among his enimies,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 110. <hi>Psal.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>and bruse them with his yron rod, and breake all them in peeces like a potters vessell,</hi> that any maner of way without repentance molest and afflict his dearely beloued spouse and Church. Let vs not therefore feare any threates or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprises of this worlde, knowing that we shall ouercome in him that hath alreadye ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Deuill and the worlde,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4.</note>
      <hi>Greater</hi> (sayth S. <hi>Iohn) (is the spirite) that is in you, than hee that is in the world.</hi> For there was neuer yet tyrant that rose against Gods Church, but some shamefull &amp; horrible ende folowed him most cōmonly in this world. The ecclesiasticall story is full of examples, &amp; of late God hath shewed some notable in this case, both here in our coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, and abrode, who list to marke and consider them. True it is that christians haue bene made away and murthered, vpon verye light and tryfling occasions, and are also at this daye, where tyrants doe reigne. For in <hi>Tertullians</hi> dayes, which liued about two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth and nine yeares after Christ: <hi>If the riuer Tybris at Rome had flowed vp to the walles, if Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus the riuer in Aegypt had not watered their fieldes, if there had bene no raine, if there had bene anye earthquake,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Apolog.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>dearth or plague, by and by the people would crye to haue the Christians throwne to the Lions.</hi> And all this was to ridde the countrie of them, and to deface their beliefe and doctrine. But what followed hereof? Uerily nothing lesse than they wéened. For <hi>Tertullian</hi> tolde them plainely: <hi>Torment, racke, condemne, and make vs awaye, and your vniust dealing with vs, is but a tryall of our innocencie. Therefore God suffreth vs to suffer this at your handes. The more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite your crueltie is towarde vs, the more it allureth to take our partes.</hi> And whereas they call vs Sectaries, as then they did the Christians, lette vs reioyce in that we see our quarrell and theirs, our slaunders and theirs so like, and tell them as <hi>Tertullian</hi> telleth <hi>Scapula</hi> the Romanes President: that <hi>this sect shall not fayle or decay, but the more it seemeth to be cut downe, the more let them be assured, it is builded vp.</hi> And considering what they be that are our condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Let vs also saye: <hi>Such and such consecrators of our condemnation we reioyce in.</hi> For as <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> sayde, <hi>whosoeuer knoweth him</hi> (meaning <hi>Nero</hi>) <hi>must needes vnderstande that of force it must be some singuler good thing that he woulde condemne:</hi> so may we as truely say, of <hi>Boner, Storye,</hi> and such like, that haue condemned our faythfull brethren and sisterne, that whosoeuer knewe what they were, how they liued and howe they dyed, must néedes know also that it
<pb facs="10"/>
coulde be none other than good that they woulde condemne. And therefore lette vs saye to them with <hi>Tertullian</hi> for a short aunswere: <hi>when you condemne vs, God pardoneth vs.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs not feare them that can kill the body, but then can doe no more, ne yet that, but when God permitteth: but rather let vs feare him, that can cast both body and soule into the fire of hell, which is Iesus Christ our Sauiour,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>Math.</hi> 24. <hi>Marc.</hi> 13.</note> knowing that he will crowne all those that striue lawfully, and continue vnto the ende: to him therefore with the father and the holy ghost, thrée per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons and one eternall maiestie of godheade, all honor, power, and glory, be now and euer, worlde without ende. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>