<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ An homolie to be reade in the time of pestilence, contayninge the true causes of the same: And likewise a moste present reme∣dye for as many as be alreadye, or hereafter shalbe infected wyth that dysease: Gathered out of the holy scripture, by John Hoper Busshoppe of Worce∣ster and Gloucester. ANNO DOMINI. 1553.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1553</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118879_Bo1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03634</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13759</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118879</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ An homolie to be reade in the time of pestilence, contayninge the true causes of the same: And likewise a moste present reme∣dye for as many as be alreadye, or hereafter shalbe infected wyth that dysease: Gathered out of the holy scripture, by John Hoper Busshoppe of Worce∣ster and Gloucester. ANNO DOMINI. 1553.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An homelye to be read in the tyme of pestylence, and a moste presente remedye for the same</title>
                 <author>Hooper, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Oswen, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Worcester</pubPlace>
                    <date>1553</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>34 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prefatory_letter">
   <head>
      <pb facs="5"/>¶ An homolie to be reade in the time of pestilence, contayninge the true causes of the same: And likewise a moste present reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye for as many as be alreadye, or hereafter shalbe infected wyth that dysease: Gathered out of the holy scripture, by John Hoper Busshoppe of Worce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster and Gloucester. <date>ANNO DOMINI. 1553.</date>
   </head>
   <epigraph>
      <bibl>Marci. i.</bibl>
      <q>Repente and beleue the gospell.</q>
   </epigraph>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the desire of all sicke men to knowe what medicine and remedye hath beene knowen moste to preuayle, best too re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue, and soonest to cure &amp; make whole the person dyseased. And the greater and more daungerouse the syckenes is, the more circumspect and wise the sicke man muste be in knowledge and choise of the medicine: Lest happely he seeke a remedy inferior and to weake, for the greatnes &amp; strength of his disease. The nature &amp; cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicion therfore of pestilence being so daū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gerous (as it is in dede) y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> who so euer be infected or attemted therw<seg rend="sup">t</seg> al, hath nede to be well instructed, and thorughly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded of a sufficient remedye, stronger
<pb facs="5"/>
then the sickenes it selfe. Or els the dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sease shall more hurte the sicke pacyente, then the medicine can do him good: Thē must nedes followe the deathe, and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of the diseased person. It beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth therefore all men that be mortall, to knowe the most generall, and most daū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous dyseases that mortalitie shalbe troubled withall: And then, as he seeth his greate and necessary aduersaries and syckenes, to knowe also the greatest and most necessary remedy and helpe against his diseases. And because sinne hath soo preuayled in vs, that trueth perswaded vnto vs by thexamples of others, sooner instructeth, and longer tarieth then any thinge taught vs by doctrine or testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye: I shall (before I enter into the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of the pestylence) shewe the strength, and nature of sickenes from thexamples of souche godly persons, as in the worde of god are mencioned of,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 6.42.</note> for oure instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Kinge <hi>Dauid</hi> (emonges other dysea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses) fell intoo the pestilence: The great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and daunger whereof passed all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane &amp; worldly healpes, as it appeareth by hys lamentable crye and complaynte
<pb facs="6"/>
vnto the Lorde. My soule (saieth he) is sore troubled: But how long Lord wilt thou differre thy help: And the same crie and complainte he made vnto the Lorde when the plage of pestilence had infected his whole Realme,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Sam.</hi> 24</note> from Dan too Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabe: And sawe the remedye therof to be onlie in god. Praying him to commaund his Aingel to stryke the people no more.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Esay.</hi> 37.38</note>
      <hi>Ezechias</hi> the kinge sawe, that besides god al meatsonnes and remedies were to weak, and inferior for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> strength and power of the pestilence &amp; sickenes▪ wherfore he tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him selfe to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wall, and praied god to do that for him that no phisicke nor me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine washable to do.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Corin.</hi> 15</note> And sainct Paule in hys wonderfull oratyon that he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth concernyng the resurrectyon of the dead, waigheth moste deapely the nature &amp; condicion of mannes myserable estate in thys lief: Bourdeinnyng hym wyth suche strong aduersaries, sicknes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seases both of body and soule, that euery man may see, how impossible it is for mā to fynde deliueraunce from the tirannie, and strengthe of syckenes, excepte onely the mercy of god in Christe Jesu. Nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beryng
<pb facs="6"/>
there, sixe and aduersaries so stronge, as the least of them (except Christ helpe) is hable to destroy both bodie and soule. The first, is corruptiō. The second, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie. The third, sinne. The fourth, the lawe: condempning sin. The fifth, death The sixte, hell: necessary and indiuisible plagues and sickenes of man in this lief. Against the which he findeth no remedy neyther by Galien, nor Hipocrates, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet by thearth of <hi>para.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Plin. lib</hi> 2▪ <hi>cap.</hi> 96.</note> y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> men say cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth al woundes: But with greate faith &amp; confydence marketh and weigheth the strength of deseases (though they be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer so stronge) too be yet inferior too the medsone and remedy, that god hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for vs onlie in Christe. Therefore compareth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> inferior strength of althose sicknes, vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sufficient remedy of god, through Christ: saying after this maner Thankes be vnto god which hath geuē vs victorye thorough oure Lorde Jesus Christ. Wherby it is euident and plaine, that god is thonely remedy for al plages &amp; deseases. How be it, nowe I shal more speciallye open y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> causes of the plage, and the nature of the same: y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> our sicknes &amp; the
<pb facs="7"/>
causes therof may be more knowen, and the better auoyded.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.</note>The principall cause of pestilence is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened by S. Paule by thies wordes. By sinne (saith he) came death into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> world: and for the cause of sinne, god sendeth the plage of pestilence and all other diseases that punisheth towardes death.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psalm,</hi> 42.</note> Asking <hi>Dauid</hi> sayth, Thou doest punishe the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derin of men for sinne. Moises also plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly sheweth, that the principall and chyef cause of pestilence is not in the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ayer, nor in the superfluous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors within man:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.</note> But that sinne and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> transgression of goodes lawe is the very cause and chief occasion of pestilence &amp; of al other diseases. And y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> experience therof was tried in the pestylence that raigned in king Dauides time for his sinnes, and the sinnes of the people.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam,</hi> 24</note> So that al y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture of god manifestly declareth that the contempt and breache of goddes lawes, is the chief and principall cause of pesty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and of all other plages that he sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for our punishment. And from this cause procedeth those causes (y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> phisicions speake of) the corruption of the aier, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<pb facs="7"/>
is neuer corrupted nor can corrupte man or beast, excepte mā (for whose sake and comfort both ayer and all other bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes were made) be firste corrupted by sin and transgression of goddes lawes. Nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther could man take any surfeit by mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, nor anye yuell humors coulde be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendered of any meates, were not y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> man that vseth them corrupte &amp; first infected with sinne. But when the Lord doth see that the people forgeate or contempne his blessed commaundementes, and that souche as be appointed to rebuke and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish suche transgressours of goddes la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, suffer without punyshment, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of god, and his holy commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes to be oppressed, and set at naught, as we se daylie they be in deed: From these causes our sinne and abhominacion the Lord taketh occasion to turne hys good creatures made for oure lief, to be a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of oure deathe: which neuer woulde be, were not our hainouse dishonouring and contempte of God. For the Lordes creatures be perfectly good,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gene.</hi> 1.</note> and made al to comforte and reioyce, holsome, cleane and pure withoute all infectyon. But se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge
<pb facs="8"/>
that the contempte of god, and the filthines of sinne, is nether by the Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie opened, declared, ne detected, neyther by the heades of the countrey, and offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers appointed vnder god and the kyng, punished. Except therfore there shoulde nothing els liue in this world then sinne abhominacion and contempt of god: god is forced, for the taking away &amp; destructi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of filthy lief, and filthy liuers, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point an extra ordinary magistrate to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme and punish the mother of all mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyef, synne, and contempte of gooddes holye woorde. And soo altereth, not by chaunce, nor by the influence of sterres, the holesomnes of the ayer intoo pesty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lente and contagyouse infectyon: And the meate and drynke wyth theyr nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimente and foade intoo poyson and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nome, that by their meane, sinne and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners myghte bee slayne and taken oute of thys worlde, and no longer too blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme God. Thus dothe the woorde of god declare theffectuouse and pryncypal cause of pestylence too be the contempte of Goddes woorde, that shoulde kepe men in ordre bothe too God and man.
<pb facs="8"/>
The breakynge whereof hath alwayes brought these plagues into Realmes,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Li.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> as prophane writers also manifestly declare <hi>Orosius</hi> sayeth, that the greate dearthe and famyne that came emonges the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, in the tune of <hi>Caesar Augustus,</hi> was because <hi>Caius</hi> his neuewe contempned to honor the liuing god, as he was taught at Hierusa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lē, whē he passed into Siria. Wherfore it is expedient, and before al thinges neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary (for as monthe as the plage is come into soundry places about vs) for euery one to trye hym selfe, what iust causes of thys pestylence eche man hath wythin him selfe. Euery Christian man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man muste searche whether theyr religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and christianitie be souche, as god by hys worde dothe maintayne to be good: for there is no greater occasyon of pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, then superstycyon and false rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyon. The Busshoppe, Person, Uy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care and Curate, must examine them sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, what knowledge of goddes word is in them, and what dilygence they haue taken too brynge the people to a ryghte knowledge, and perfecte honor of God: for there is noo greater daungere of
<pb facs="9"/>
pestilence, then where as the Cleargie is either ignoraunte of goddes worde, or negligent in teachyng thereof. The Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices &amp; gentlemen must loke howe they kepe them selues and the kynges Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties people in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> true knowledge and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of goddes lawes and the Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: for nothing prouoketh the pestilence more daungerously, then where as suche as sitte and be appointed to do iustice, do their owne affections with contempte &amp; iniuries bothe to god and man, and the plage of god will reuenge it. All we ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore that be subiectes and liue vnder one god and one kinge, must (nowe that god hath sente vs this pestilence) see that we haue true, louing, faithful, trustie and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedyent hartes wyth one hole minde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together to obey, reuerence, loue, healpe, succour, defende and vpholde with all our wittes, gooddes, ryches and strengthe this oure onely Kinge, the Magistrates and councellours that be appointed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hys highnes.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.</note> For as Saincte Paule saieth, he that disobeieth and resisteth the hygher powers appointed by god, re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sist god, prouoke the pestilence and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce
<pb facs="9"/>
of god against vs.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Io.</hi> 3.</note> And we must take hede also that we hate not one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: yf we do, the plage wyll not ceasse, and the places that yet be not infected, god shall infecte, what so euer defence man maketh againste it. And although Galien of all remedyes saieth, to flie the ayer that is infected, is best: Yet I know that Moses by the worde of god, sayeth. Flee whether thou wylte, in case y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> take wyth the, the contempt of god, &amp; breache of his commaundement, god shall fynde the oute. Yea, and although manye me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines be deuised, and assureth the infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be made whole: yet not wythstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.</note> I know goddes worde sayeth the contrary, that he will sende vnto vnsen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, careles, and wilfull sinners, souche a plage and incurable a pestilence, that he shall not be deliuered, but dye and perish by it. Therfore, forasmouche as synne is thoccasion chiefly of pestilence, let euery man eschewe and auoyd it both spedelye and penitentlie, and then shall ye be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued from the plage sufficientlye, as ye shal perceaue in the remedy of this daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous plage, that begynneth to raigne
<pb facs="10"/>
emonges vs.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 96.</note> For doubtles, although we could flye to Locris or Crotone where as Plinie sayeth, the pestilence was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.</note> yet god saith incase we feare not him we shall surely be infected.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>The remedy against the pestylence.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oke as the scripture of god one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly sheweth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> very cause of pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: so doth it the very true and onely remedye agaynst it. I doo not dislike y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> remedies that naturall phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke hath prescribed: yet I do not hable them as sufficient remedies, for their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection sake. I woulde also they were vsed, and the remedies prescribed in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des boke not omitted. For I see all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medyes that euer was deuysed by man, is not hable to remoue assuredlie the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stylence from hym that is infected there wythall, althoughe they be neuer soo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellente and good. And I fynde the same concernynge the preseruacyon from the pestylence deuysed by man, alsoo insuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyente for mannes preseruacyon, yet not to be contempned: for the reason of theyr chiefest preseruacyon is very good and
<pb facs="10"/>
allowable, and yet not sufficient: Which is, of all things chiefly to be vsed against the pestilence, fleing and departure from the place wheare as the ayer is corrupte. Wherefore for souche as maye, nothing is better then too flee, and excepte he do, he offereth him selfe too a presente daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of deathe: But yet the woorde of God sayeth plainelye, that flee whether we wyll, yf we forsake not synne, and serue the lyuynge god, the plage shall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertake vs. And thys can not be a suffy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyent remedy, for there be certen persons that can not flee although they woulde: As the poorer sorte of people that haue no frendes nor place too flee vntoo, more then the poore house they dwell in. Like wyse there be souche offyces of truste, as men for noo cause maye flee from it: As the Busshoppe, Person, Uicare and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, who hath the charge of those that god pleaseth too infecte wyth the pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Io.</hi> 10.</note> and yf they forsake theyr people in thys plague tyme, they be hirelinges &amp; no Pastoures, and they flee frō goddes people into gods high indignaciō. Such alsoo as haue places and offices of truste
<pb facs="11"/>
for the commune wealth, as the Capitai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of souldiers in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> time of warre, Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Justices in the tyme of peace: Incase they should flee their countryes or leaue theyr warres for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> plage of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stylence, they shall neuer be good souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, nor good Justices for the commune wealth. And they shalbe accompatable to almighty god for all the hurte and detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that hath happned vnto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in their absence. Wherfore, seing there is no certen remedy deuised by man, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for suche as can not flee, nor for thē that may flee, we must seeke another me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine and healpe at goddes hande: who can and wil preserue those that be whole, and make them whole that be sicke, yf it be expedyent for man, and moste for hys owne honor. The best preseruatyue ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore too kepe men from the pestylence,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Enod.</hi> 5.</note> is this that Moses speaketh of: Let vs do sacrifice vnto the Lorde,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Numer.</hi> 14</note> least we be stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with pestilence or swearde. And Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sua and Caleb toulde the people that a faythfull trust in the Lord was the best remedy for them: which if they contemp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned, they shoulde fynde, that God there
<pb facs="11"/>
threatened speakynge too Moses: Howe long wil this people be vnfaythfull: I wyll strike them with pestilence, and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sume thē. Also Dauid knewe that thone<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly remedye to kepe Jerusalem from the plage, was,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam. ult.</hi>
         </note> that god shoulde tourne hys wrath from the Citie, for his sinnes, and the sinnes of the people.</p>
      <p>But now to bryng the remedy the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the vnderstandynge of the people, I will shewe it by thys place of Saincte Mark. Repent ye and beleue the gospell:<note place="margin">
            <hi>Cap.</hi> 1.</note> In y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whych wordes is contained thone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie medicine against the pestilence, and al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>so al other diseases, if the text be wel and aduisedly considered, wherein Christe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth a very naturall ordre to heale all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seases. For as the remedy naturallye of all deseases is taken from contrary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicions and qualities that worketh and maintaineth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sickenes: So doth Christ in these wordes declare that the preserua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion and healpe of sinne and wickednesse (the cause of pestylence) proceadeth from vertues and condicions contrary to the quallities and nature of souche thynges as preserue and kepe this wycked sinne &amp;
<pb facs="12"/>
sicknes in man. As when a man is faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into sickenes by reason of to mouche coulde and moysture: the remedye muste bee gathered naturallye from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, heate and drouthe. For thys is a commune and true principle contraries be holpen by their contraries: If nature waxe too coulde, it muste bee holpen wyth heate.<note place="margin">
            <hi>Galiende sempera.</hi>
         </note> If it be to hotte it muste be cooled. If it be to moyste, it muste be dried. If it be to drye, it must be moys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. If it be to coulde and moyst, it must be heat and dryed. If it be coulde and drie, it must be heat and moisted. If it be to hotte and moyste, it muste be cooled and dryed. If it bee hotte and drye, it muste be cooled and moysted: These be veary naturall remedyes if they bee well vsed wyth true proporcion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenyente vse after phisicke. And as these bee good and naturall for the bodye wherein the pestilence dwelleth: Euen so is Christes medicyne in the fyrste of Saint Mark a more present and certain remedye for the soule that keapeth the body in lief, to remoue or to remedye the synne of man, whyche is the cause of all
<pb facs="12"/>
plages and pestylence. Incase (too re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue synne the cause of syckenes) thys medicyne of Christe bee vsed, as thother is vsed too remoue theffecte of synne whyche is syckenes. As the bodye that is fallen into syckenes by to muche colde or moysture, eyther by nature that ory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynallye was corrupted by Adam, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by oure owne accustomed and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge of synne, it muste be made whole by the heate of repentaunce and trewe faythe in the merytes of Christe Jesus, who dyed for the synnes of the worlde. For thys is a trewe and moste certen principle of all relygyon, one contrarye muste remedye thother, seyng Adam by his fault beganne oure death by sinne: it muste be cured by Christe that is wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute sinne. And where as our own wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes be synne and fylthynes, where with all god is dyspleased: we must desire the workes of Christ to worke the good wil and fauour of our heauēly father again. And where as by our own wittes, wyse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, religion and lerning we haue cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ydolatry &amp; supersticion: we must now by goddes wisdome, goddes word &amp;
<pb facs="13"/>
his most true religion, amende our faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and turne to true and godly honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of him. Farther, where as our own inuencyons hath broughte vs from the knowledge of god: the remedye is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des worde must bring vs to him againe.<note place="margin">
            <hi>Psal.</hi> 19.118 2. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 3.</note> For against all vntruthes brought in by man: the worde of god is thonelye reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. The experience therof we may haue plainly in the scripture, where as for the saluacyon of the worlde, god appoynted Christe hys onely sonne to be borne,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Math.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Luc.</hi> 2. <hi>Ion.</hi> 1.</note> and also to be opened vntoo the worlde, that by him it might be healed of all sickenes and sinne, as it appereth by S. Mathew and other of the Euangelistes. Yet was the world so blind, and so corrupted with synne, that Christe was borne and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto them, and they of the world no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the better,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Cap.</hi> 3.</note> as it appereth in S. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew: Where as S. Jhō y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Baptist in few wordes (whych be these: Repente ye, for the kyngdome of god is at hande) she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the remedy of all sinnes and sycke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and the meanes how to receyue and take the same remedy. The remedy was onlye Christe,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Ioan.</hi> 1.3.</note> as he sayeth in S. Jhon,
<pb facs="13"/>
and also in S. Mathewe:<note place="margin">
            <hi>Math.</hi> 3.</note> And the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to come by the remedy was to repent, as ye shall know farther hereafter when ye knowe what repentaūce is.<note place="margin">
            <hi>Cap.</hi> 4.</note> The same may you also see in S. Jhon in the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loge betwene Christe and Nicodemus: A man after the iudgement of the world that knew lief &amp; death, sickenes &amp; health, the cause of thone, and also of thother, as well as any learned man emonges al the congregatiō and churche of the Jewes: yet in deed as ignoraunt of his own sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and also so farre from y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge how to come to health as an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt man might be. And the cause was that he vnderstode not the nature of sin, as it is estemed by the worde of god, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> remedy thereof y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> god hath prescri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed and appoincted. Wherefore Christe tolde him by playne wordes, excepte he were holpen and cured of his desease and sicknes by contrarye remedyes, he could neuer vnderstand nor come by his helth, and no meruaile: for he knew the sicknes of synne noo otherwise then hys forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and the worldly men knew sinne. That is too saye, knew suche sinnes as
<pb facs="14"/>
were knowen to reason, and done by the body and outward action of men: And the same knowledge had he, and no more of the remedye againste the syckenes of synne. And as his fathers and the world thoughte (so dyd hee) that the merites of their sacrifices and the well doing of thē selues, was a sufficient remedye to heale them both in body &amp; in soule. Where vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Christ most mercifully pitieth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> poore man, &amp; wyth contrarye knowledge both of sicknes, and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> remedy therof, sheweth that the desease man is infected wyth, goeth farther then reason and the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter action of the bodye, and occupyeth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> soule of man with concupiscence, rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, frowardnes &amp; contumacie againste god: Wherefore he calleth all y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> man hath of him self but fleshe.<note place="margin">
            <hi>Ioan.</hi> 3</note> And sheweth that the remedye againste this sickenes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not of the worthynes of any sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice or merytes of his, or any sinfull man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes workes: But that the remedy there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of dependeth onely vpon the merytes of his bloude and passion, and sheweth the same by the comparyson of the Brasen Serpente appoyncted by Moises. And
<pb facs="14"/>
argueth thys waye, as the people that were stronge wyth the Serpentes in the wildernes were not made whole by their owne workes, or for the dignitye or ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyce of anye sacryfyce that they offred, but by the syghte of the Serpente that represented Christe too come: Euen soo Nicodemus nor anye other that is stong wyth the Serpentes of synne, be made whole by theyr owne woorkes or anye sacrifyce they can offre, but onely by the merites of Christe. And euyn as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple could not come too the knowledge of this remedy by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> serpent, thorough their fathers, or theyr owne wysedome: noo more can Nicodemus or any man liuing come too the knowledge of the remedye, for syckenes and synne, in oure sauyoure Christe,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Ioan.</hi> 3.</note> except he learne it by the woorde of God thoroughe the instructyon of the hoyle ghoste.<note place="margin">
            <hi>Marci.</hi> 1.</note> The same remeadye alsoo vseth Christe in hys woordes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rehearsed, repente ye and beleue the gospell: In the whyche woordes oure sauiour Christ sheweth all thinges to be considered in syn &amp; in the remedy thereof. For in the firste parte of hys wordes he
<pb facs="15"/>
declareth how that men should knowe y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> causes of sicknes, and in the second parte the remedy &amp; help for the same. The cause of sicknes (as it appeareth by this worde repente) is that men haue by their owne folly turned them selues from the truth of God, to the erroure and fonde opinion of man: from true faythe too vncertaine fables: from verteous &amp; godlye workes, to vncleanlynes and corruption of lyfe. Christe therfore seyng the worlde howe it is in daunger by reason it hath forsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the wisedome &amp; rule of goodes word, calleth it home agayne too a better way, byddynge it repente: As though he had sayed, tourne too a better mynde, and leaue the wayes accustomed, and learne to be wyse, and walke in the wayes and wysedome appoyncted by God. Here ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth alsoo, that the causes of all the daungers that Christe wylled hys au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyence too repente for, was their synne and iniquytye. The cause of synne, was infydelytye and accustomed doing of euill: The cause of infidelitie and accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomed doing of yuel, was ignoraūcie or misunderstandynge of goodes woorde.
<pb facs="15"/>
The cause of ignoraunce or mysunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standinge of goddes word was Sathan goddes and mannes enemie, and mans willing consent to the diuelish sophistry and false construinge of goddes woorde. And from these causes springeth all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seases and sicknes,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Ioan.</hi> 3.</note> death and euerlasting dampnatiō: from the which Christ was sent (of gods inestimable loue towardes vs) to redeme &amp; saue vs. Notw<seg rend="sup">t</seg>standing these effectes of pestilence, sicknes, death and euerlasting dampnation can not be remoued, except firste the causes of them be eschued, wherfore learne ye and teach other to knowe the causes aboue menci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, and also how they maye be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: For as long as they worke their pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pre nature in manne, so longe wyll they bringe foorthe their naturall effectes, sickenes troubles, deathe and dampna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon. The originall cause of all yuell was Sathan,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</note> and the vngodlye consent of oure forefather Adam in Paradise, in crediting more the deuils sophistrie and glose, then the plaine and manifest word of god. And the remedye of thys cause is god, that of loue agaynste Sathans ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
<pb facs="16"/>
promised in the seade of a woman, healpe agayne for man:<note place="margin">
            <hi>Ioan.</hi> 1.3.5.</note> And that euerye man y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> beleueth the deuil in euill, must re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and beleue god &amp; his word in good.</p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>Ioan.</hi> 1.3.</note>Ignorancie and mistakyng of goddes word, is the second cause of euil: The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie wherof is knowledge and right vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derstanding of goddes word.</p>
      <p>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>Ioan.</hi> 16.</note>Infidelitie &amp; accustomed doing of euill, be the third cause of euil: True faith and accustomed doyng of good, remedyeth them.</p>
      <p>Sinne and iniquitie be the causes of sick<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, death and dampnaciō: vertue &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines healeth &amp; remoueth, that they shal not bringe man to euerlasting death, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though sin and sicknes be not cleane ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken frō man, yet doth god in Christ take away the dampnation of sin, &amp; suffereth death to destroye by sickenes none other thing then the body of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sinner, so that he vse this remedy (repent and beleue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell) and shal at length call y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> body dead by death, out of thearth: And place it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyue with the soule in heauen.</p>
      <p>But now to vse this helpe and remedie agaynst the pestilence: which Christ cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth,
<pb facs="16"/>
repente and beleue the gospell.</p>
      <p>The sicke man muste remembre what the first word repente meaneth, and how he maye come by it. Repentaunce that God requireth, is the retourne of the synner from synne, intoo a newe lyfe in Christe. Whiche retourne is an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacyon and renouacyon of the mynde of manne by Goddes spiryte in Christe, wyth denyall of the former lyfe, too begynne a newe and better lyfe. And thys repentaunce spryngeth from the knowledge of sinne by the lawe of God. From the knowledge of sinne, commeth the hatred of synne: from the hatred of synne, proceadeth the leauynge and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from synne. From y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> departure from synne, commeth by faythe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Christes bloud, remissiō of sinne. From remission of synne, commeth our acceptatyon into goddes fauoure: from oure acceptatyon intoo Goddes fauour, commeth the gyftes of the holye ghost to doo, and worke by verteouse lyfe, the wyll of God. From the doyng in Christ the wyll of god, commeth goddes defence and fauour y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> taketh from vs all
<pb facs="17"/>
plages and pestylence. From the delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of plages and pestylence cōmeth euerlastyng lief,<note place="margin">
            <hi>Ioan.</hi> 3.3.6.</note> as Christe sayeth: And as thys medicine called, repent ye, and be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue the gospell, declareth. There be also manye that be sycke and in greate daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and perill by reason of synne, and yet fele not the sore and grief therof. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they passe not whether they seke for any remedye or not: And for lacke of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng heede they fall daily to more wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes then other. Wherefore it is euery ministers office of the churche diligently (and especially in the tyme of pestylence and plages) to call vpon the people for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendmente of lyfe. And too shewe them truely, diligently and plainly this medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine of repentaunce. Whiche consisteth of these partes. First, in knowledge of sinne, then in hatred of synne. Thirdly, in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sakyng of synne. Fourthly, in beleuyng y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> forgeuenes of sinnes for Christes sake: And fifthly to liue in verteous and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lief, to honor god, and to shewe hys o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to goddes lawe, that by sinne is transgressed. And these partes of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce (whyche be the very true and one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="17"/>
medicines against sickenes and sinne) be knowen onely by goddes lawes. For by the lawe of god, sinne is knowen, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tested and forsaken, if it be hearde or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by men that pray vnto god, thei may vnderstand it. Fayth also that beleueth, remission of sinne is shewed, opened and offered by the gospell: wherin be contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned goddes merciful promises towardes sinners. And those promises sinners re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by faith, that beleueth what so euer god hath promised in Christ, he will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme it. Fayth doth credite and receiue forgeuenes of sinnes by the operacion of goddes holye spiryte in the poore sinner. The sinner studyeth and lyueth a verte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous life, being led by the holye goste, and worketh to serue god wyth souche wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, as goddes holy commaundement cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundeth euerye true christian man too worke and doo. And for the better assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce and farther stablishyng of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce and acceptation into the fauoure of god by beleuyng the gospell, the poore sinner vseth and receiueth the holy sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Christes precious body &amp; bloud, in remembraunce that Christe died to be
<pb facs="18"/>
his medicine agaynst sinne, and theffecte thereof. Wherefore, now that it pleaseth god for oure offences to shewe by plages and sicknes how he is offended: Let vs all that be ministers of the church, and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> watche men of the people, cal vpon them diligently to repente and beleue the gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and to liue a godly and verteous life that for Christes sake he will turne mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully hys plages from vs: and geue vs his most gracious fauour to preserue his vniuersall churche, oure most godlye Soueraigne Lorde and Kynge, King Edward the sixte, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties most honorable Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and the whole Realme. So be it.</p>
      <p>18. <hi>May▪</hi> 1553.</p>
      <p>Imprinted at Worce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by Jhon Oswen, Prynter ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Kinges Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie for the principalitie of Wales and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the same.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <pb facs="18"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>