<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Aduertisement of the Authour to the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118417_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13774</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24072</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118417</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Aduertisement of the Authour to the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The true copy of tvvo letters, with their seuerall answeres, contayning the late apostasie of the Earle of Lauall, after his returne from Italy : VVherein the principall poynts in controuersie with the papists, are learnedly and fully confuted. By D. Tilenus. Faythfully translated by D.D.S</title>
                 <author>Tilenus, Daniel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 <publisher>Butter, Nathaniel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The Aduertisement of the Authour <hi>to the Christian Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Vriosity and pleasure are two dangerous diseases, and euery one apart, is strong ynough to ouercome his patient: how much more, while being both together, they conioyne to assayle him, as it were, agreeing both by the body and the soule; the one ingendring himselfe within the spirit, the other within the flesh, each of them consuming and destroying the parts that breed it; euen as the Worme de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyeth the Apple, the Viper, her mother: They symbolize in many things, and as two sister-like twinnes, they attyre thēselues with one selfe same habit; the definition of the one, not much disagreeing frō the nature of the other: So that to this end an ancient Father sayd, That Adultery was nothing else, but a curiosity of an other mans pleasure; the one alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating the spirit of the patient from the knowledge of salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and causing him to take appetite to those things, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the ignorance is wisdome, and the practice damnable, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him the disciple of the father of lyes, subiect to the Prince of darknesse, the first inuenter of those mysteries of hell: the other changeth his body, which ought to be the member of Iesus Christ, the temple of the holy Ghost, into the member of an harlot, and habitation of vncleane spirits: both of them be bad, very fit to corrupt youth, to seduce it to the stewes of Antichrist, where there is somewhat to please both those intising humours: for what doth more resemble the curiosity of Magicke, then the charmes of hallowed <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> of the Transsubstantiation? to the characters of Soccrers, then the marks of the beast, deciphered in the book of Reuelation? A great part of this deuillish Art bewrayeth itselfe by auricular confession, imitating the forme of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatories, registred in the decrees of <hi>Buchart,</hi> Bishop of <note place="margin">Lib. 9. cap. 5<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Wormes. As touching the pleasure of the flesh, where may a man find the exercise more free, the excesse more enormous, then within the great Babylon, where the bodily lust hath no lesse sway, then the spiritual: Where haue bin inuented these
<pb facs="6"/>
sacred Canons, which do not only with the Council of Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, <note place="margin">Dist. 3. C. 4. Is qui non habet Caus. 12. q. 1. c. dilectis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sionis.</note> permit concubines, but also commaund and ordaine the community of wiues with <hi>Plato,</hi> and of goods with the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists?</hi> Behold these two rocks, which, as wel as ambition &amp; couetousnes, ouerwhelme the faith of many by lamentable shipwrack. This is the course, wherin lately the <hi>Earle of Laual</hi> ouerthrew himselfe, to the great griefe of those, who hoped hee would one day succeede to the piety and vertue of his predecessors: but these qualities are gifts personall, not he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary, as the name &amp; temporall goods. After that he had languished a long time in these diseases, possessing both his spirit &amp; his flesh, there was also marked in him diuers symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes and signes of an euil successe; and among other things, was perceiued a fact direct cōtrary to that which S. <hi>Luke</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribes: for hauing past to change the ayre in Italy, a country which is not thoght very good for those persons that be most <note place="margin">Act. 19. 19.</note> wholsome and whole, he did not refuse all kind of pleasures for his body; &amp; besides, made prouision of mortall receits for his soule, buying at a high rate, writings, like to those, which the disciples of the Apostles cast into the fire, notwithstāding they were of great value, so soone as they did imbrace the christiā faith at <hi>Ephesus:</hi> by which purchase, he declared very well, to be more disposed to take place in the Temple of the great <hi>Diana</hi> of the Papists, thē to haue preserued that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it pleased God to haue honored him in his true Church, who condēneth those detestable curiosities: and in the end, the Apostem beginning to grow &amp; gorge forth the venome contained in these his two letters, in which he propoūdeth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers questions, not so much as to receiue light of his doubts, wherin such diseases had tane away both his desire &amp; vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stāding: but because after a iust refusall of a verbal conferēce made vnto his vniust demaūds, being addressed to those who vnderstood that resolutiō which he had already taken, he had need thē of some other mask to end the <hi>Catastrophe</hi> of his <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy,</hi> instead of extreme vnction, &amp; funerall preparations of his religiō dead in his soule long time before, dissembling in the mean time this spiritual death toward these, who did their indeuour for his preseruatiō, as appeares in matters of estate, who cōceale, for certaine dayes, the death of their great Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:
<pb facs="6"/>
but seeing he could not so wel coūterfet the voyce of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> but that the hands of <hi>Esau</hi> did discouer him: neither was he able himself to support any longer the pestilēt smel which his neutrality did breathe forth amōg the liuing &amp; the dead, betwixt the preaching of the Gospel, &amp; the Idolatrous masse, but that he was forced to discouer his maske.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>And hauing trāsported himselfe to the Couent of the Capucians in Paris, he burted solemnly his religion, accōpanied with many exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cismes, abiurations, confessions, pentiencies, and such ceremonies:</hi> which did serue him no lesse to his obsequ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es, thē did the des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate painting &amp; attiRes to <hi>Iesabel,</hi> which she did take in the instāt houre she was to be cast Forth of the window to break her neck. They had great desire to adorne the lamentable pompe of the poore young Earle, by some pray, which they thought to haue caught on our professors: and to this effect, after the refusall of the verball conference which he deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the Iesuits had perswaded him to aduise in that same in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant vpon the said doubts, with diuers persons in diuers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, hoping that in diuersity of stile, they might incoūter cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain differēces of beleeuing in those that should answer: but not finding one iust subiect on our part, to fal in any such in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience, but rather to alienate him frō the wickednes of the corrupters of his youth: We supposed nothing should di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert vs frō putting to light, the obiections made on the one part, &amp; the answers giuen on the other side; to the end, that cōFerring the one with the other, euery one who hath eyes to see, may vnderstād, that those which wil not know that which is, should imagine to thēselues, to see that which they see not; which be the two kinds of blindnes, wherwith God by his iust iudgement doth punish those that forsake the spirit for the flesh, the truth for vanity; the light for darknes, the Sauiour of the world, for the son of perdition: neuerthelesse, we hope, God willing, that those, who haue not much edified Christs Church by their life, shall farre lesse ruine the same by their death, seeing that their voluntary separation from our cōmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, doth no other thing then ease vs frō the necessary trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of cutting thē off frō our society; no more then the wind, which driueth away the chaffe in the ayre, easing thē which in the meane time are about to clense the floore.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>