<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER, GRACE AND PEACE.</title>
           <author>T., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118816_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14155</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24472</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118816</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER, GRACE AND PEACE.</title>
                 <author>T., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tvvo learned sermons : The one, of the mischieuous subtiltie, and barbarous crueltie, the other of the false doctrines, and refined hæresis of the romish synagogue. Preached, the one at Paules Crosse the 5. of Nouember, 1608. The other at the Spittle the 17. of Aprill. 1609 In the first, are examined diuers passages of that lewde English libell, written by a prophane fugitiue, against the Apologie for the Oath of Allegeance. In the seconde, are answered many of the arguments published by Rob. Chambers priest, concerning popish miracles; and dedicated (forsooth) to th Kings most excellent Maiestie. By Robert Tynley, Doctor of Diuinitie, and Archdeacon of Ely</title>
                 <author>Tynley, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Adams, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hall, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER, <hi>GRACE AND PEACE.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am to pray thee (Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader) not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe it to the itching humour of these times, (wherein the saying of the Poet is truly verifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Scribimus indocti, docti{que} &amp;c.</hi> neuer more writing and printing, from the pens of the vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as well as the learned;) nor to any vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory that J seeke in publishing these Sermons, which I made account should haue had their last period with the compasse of the times wherein they were deliuered. Jt is the authoritie of su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h as
<pb facs="3"/> with mee is sacred, and whose word is my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, that they come further abroad, to thy view, then I intended when I made my first rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning.</p>
   <p>Wherein if thou shalt finde ought that may serue for thy instruction, and better strengthning in these last and perilous times, wherein there are so many back-sliders, and fallers away from the truth; I shall thinke my labour, whatsoeuer, abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly rewarded, and God shall haue the praise and glory of it.</p>
   <p>My purpose was, in the first of them, to set be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thine eies the wilie snares, and cruelty of the <hi>Romish Synagogue,</hi> by whose firie zeale and blinde deuotion, the powder-treason was neere vpon the kindling: from which most barbarous and bloody treacherie being deliuered, beyond all that man could imagine and conceiue, by his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly prouidence and powerfull hand, which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all in all, (when we were like sheepe appointed to the slaughter, and as silly birds, ready to be intrapped by the snares of the Fowlers) if wee should bee silent in Gods praises, or forgetfull of that our wonderfull deliuerance, well may <hi>our right hands forget their cunning, and our
<pb facs="3"/> tongues for euer cleaue to the roofes of our mouthes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Jn the latter, I haue to my abilitie done my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to giue thee warning of the <hi>false Prophet;</hi> who was neuer more busie then he is now, <hi>compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing sea and land to make a Proselyte,</hi> one of his profession; <hi>and when he is so, making him two-fold more the childe of Hell then him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felfe is.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thou maist thereout obserue the shop and forge where popish doctrine is hammered, euen vpon the anuill of old haeresies, long sithence condemned by the Catholike Church; howsoeuer the Iesuites (the Pope his holy anker) garnish and polish it with their rhetoricall flowers, and by all the paines and skill that is in them, to make it salable to the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, which cannot iudge of their colours.</p>
   <p>Read iudiciously, and with a minde that loueth truth; not praeoccupated with a praeiudicate opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and I hope thou shalt finde something that may fauour with thy relish.</p>
   <p>As for the <hi>Momes,</hi> that are ready to carpe at all mens paines, when themselues will not put to one finger to helpe support the common burden; J passe not for them; the rather because I hope to find
<pb facs="4"/> them more indifferent Iudges, which know what belongeth to these labours. To whose learned and charitable censure I submit my selfe, and commend thee to the blessed prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Almighty. Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From my Charge of</hi> Wictham <hi>in</hi> Essex, <date>
            <hi>23. Maij. Anno 1609.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>The least of all thy Brethren, R. T.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>