<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A BRIEFE INTRODVCTION TO THE FOLLOWING MEDITATIONS.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118010_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13238</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23531</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118010</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A BRIEFE INTRODVCTION TO THE FOLLOWING MEDITATIONS.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The paradise of delights. Or The B. Virgins garden of Loreto : With briefe discourses vpon her diuine letanies, by way of meditation. For the comfort of all such, as be deuout vnto her; and desyre her holy patronage &amp; protection. By I.S. of the Society of Iesus</title>
                 <author>Sweetnam, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 217, 7 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>A BRIEFE INTRODVCTION TO THE FOLLOWING MEDITATIONS.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE naturall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of mans wil is such, that of necessity it requireth the help of the Vnderstanding, to the due performance of
<pb facs="11"/>her noble acts, according to that vulgar <hi>Axiome</hi> of Philosophers, <hi>Nihil volitū, quin praecognitum,</hi> Nothing can be desired, vnlesse it be first knowne, whereupon it comes to passe, that the Wil cannot work but according to the light that it hath frō the foresaid vnderstanding: and the greater that the knowledge is of the good apprehēded, the more doth the affection of the Will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, and kindleth an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest desire of the thing vve loue.</p>
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <p> Wherfore my intended purpose in these present Meditations, being to stirre vp the harts of al that right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly peruse them, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend respect, and deuout affection vnto the euer bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and most happy Virgin Mother of God; I must first lay before your eyes, the greatnes of her excellent Vertues, &amp; singular graces (as farre as my weakenes shalbe able) that the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing being once fully possessed vvith an impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnable conceipt of her vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable
<pb facs="12"/>Perfections, the wil may be the more strōg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moued, to loue and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rēce so beautiful a creature.</p>
   <p>To this effect I haue made choice of her deuout Letanies of <hi>Loreto,</hi> wherin most admirable tytles, and most manifest arguments of her greatnes are propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed vnto vs; by vvhich not only our Vnderstanding, may be aboundantly enri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with diuine conceits, but also our Will may be greatly inflamed with ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous desires. From which
<pb facs="12"/>two well-grounded Roots, will spring the beautifull branch of Imitation, the chiefest and only scope of all vertuous myndes, and the last marke at which all true deuotion aymeth; and vvithout vvhich both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion is fruitles, or no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion at all, and the best purposes are without ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects. Witnes that worthy saying of <hi>S. Ambrose,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Amb. l. <hi>2.</hi> de Virgin.</note>
      <hi>Quis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis Mariae exoptat praemium, imitetur exemplum,</hi> Whoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer desireth the reward of the Blessed Virgin Mary,
<pb facs="13"/>let him imitate her exāple. And S. <hi>Bernard</hi> giueth vs to vnderstand, that the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect imitation of her excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vertues must be the only conduict to conuey vnto vs her louing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours,<note place="margin">Bern. su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s est.</note>
      <hi>Vt impetres eius orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis suffragium, ne deseras con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersationis exemplum,</hi> that thou mayst attaine to thy desired effect of her pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, leaue not to follow her laudable Conuersation.</p>
   <p>Consonant to this is the doctrine of the burning Lampe of Africke, &amp; shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="13"/>light of the vvhole Church, S. <hi>Augustine,</hi> who writing of the true festiuity of holy Martyrs, saith,<note place="margin">Aug. serm. <hi>47.</hi> de Sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</note>
      <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eis Sanctorum in veritate festi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uag audia celebrantur, qui ipso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Martyrum exempla sequū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> By those indeed festi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall dayes of holy Martyrs are truly celebrated vvho follovv the examples of their vertues. <hi>Fidelis sermo</hi> (saith <hi>S. Chrysostome</hi>) <hi>&amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni acceptione dignus &amp;c.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Chrysost. Tom. <hi>3.</hi> serm. de mart.</note> It is a faithfull saying and worthy to be receiued by all men, that we should imitate in
<pb facs="14"/>our cōuersatiō those Saints whome we honour with so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne veneration.</p>
   <p>And by reason of the excellent tytles which are most worthily giuen to the renowned Queene of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in these deuout Leta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, wherein her louing Children find exceeding Comfort and Delight; I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> haue thought good to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyt le this small worke, <hi>The Paradise of delights,</hi> or, <hi>the B. Virgins garden of Loreto.</hi> And for our better Collection, it will not be amisse to i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine,
<pb facs="14"/>a priuate Garden, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>dorned with all kind of delightfull flovvers, amid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest which the B. Virgin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>seth to vvalke, expecting the visitation of her deerest friends, and most deuoted Clyents. Vnto the gate of this mysticall garden, and Paradise, we must appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ach with all humility, desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be admitted to the pleasant vievv of those ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestiall flowers, whose dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty odours haue filled the whole world with their fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant smell. And if our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest
<pb facs="15"/>be gratiously granted by the glorious Queene of Heauē, &amp; her Angels there attending on her, humbly prostrate before her sacred feete, vve must desire, that whatsoeuer we shall gather out of this delightsome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radise, may be to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour &amp; glory of her sweet Sonne lesus, to the increase of deuotion to her grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Selfe, and to the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall happynes of our owne soules Then may we begin vvith the first flovver of this heauenly Garden, or
<pb facs="15"/>the first vvord of these <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>euout Letanies <hi>MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>IA,</hi> the most venerable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ame of the euer Blessed &amp; most happy Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f which we may frame our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>editation; imploring first <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>er dayly ayde and assis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ance in the manner follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>