<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Encomium]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118709_Fr1_8</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15807</idno>
           <idno type="STC">26068</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118709</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Encomium]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cyrupædia : The institution and life of Cyrus, the first of that name, King of Persians. Eight bookes. Treating of noble education, of princely exercises, military discipline, vvarlike stratagems, preparations and expeditions: as appeareth by the contents before the beginning of the first booke. Written in Greeke by the sage Xenophon. Translated out of Greeke into English, and conferred with the Latine and French translations, by Philemon Holland of the city of Coventry Doctor in Physick. Dedicated to his most excellent Maiesty</title>
                 <author>Xenophon</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 <publisher>Allott, Mary.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Allott, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Crooke, Andrew 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Holland, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 131, 130-213, 7, 14 pages, 1 leaf of plates, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <p>THE Translatour once caused in a faire Signet of a Gold Ring, to bee
engraven in the midst of the colit, the heart of a man all naked or
plaine, insteed of an Embleme, about which there went round this
Symbolum or double Anagram of both his Names, to wit, (<gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>)
or <hi>Philemon Holandus.</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: implying thus
much in Latine, <hi>Animus [praesens] fraudum expers.</hi> (A ready heart without
deceit) <hi>Verum Amicorum signum.</hi> Both which members of the sentence joyned
togither, make up this one Hexameter, with the addition of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> That signifieth
<hi>(est.)</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
   </p>
   <l>A ready Heart and minde thus voide of fraud,</l>
   <l>Is that true signe Vertue doth most applaud.</l>
   <p>
      <hi>Henry Holland</hi> in honour of his deerest father D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Philemon Holland,</hi> upon
the interpretation of his double Anagram, and his indefatigable labours.</p>
   <l>The <hi>Hart</hi> most ready, honest and upright,</l>
   <l>Devoyd of fraud unto each living wight:</l>
   <l>The <hi>Head</hi> diseas'd for ease of Englishmen,</l>
   <l>The <hi>Hand</hi> benumm'd with holding of its pen,</l>
   <l>The <hi>Pen</hi> unworne, though worne beyond a pen,</l>
   <l>Doe still hold out to glad their Countrimen.</l>
   <l>They rest in motion, and restlesse Rest is that,</l>
   <l>Yet may they rest, though Death doth frowne thereat.</l>
   <l>And when <hi>those Mortalls</hi> may be turn'd to dust,</l>
   <l>Th'immortall part must needs b'among the Iust.</l>
   <q>
      <bibl>PSAL. 112. vers. 6.</bibl>
In memoria <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> justus.</q>
   <p>Vpon the Translatours Pen, wherewith only hee translated and wrote all
<hi>Plutarchs</hi> Moralls, conteining above a Reame of Paper, he wrote this Dystick:</p>
   <l>This Booke I wrote with <hi>one</hi> poore Pen, made of a grey Goose quill:</l>
   <l>A Pen I found it, us'd before, A Pen I leave it still.</l>
   <p>Which Pen afterwards was begged by an auncient Gentlewoman (mother
to a Noble Countesse yet living:) who garnished it in silver, and kept it as a
Monument.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>