<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>D. SUTTONS usuall Prayer before his Sermons.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118002_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13209</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23507</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118002</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>D. SUTTONS usuall Prayer before his Sermons.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lectures vpon the eleventh chapter to the Romans. Preached by that learned and godly divine of famous memorie, Dr. Sutton, in St. Marie Overies in Southwarke. Published for the good of all Gods Church generally, and especially of those that were then his hearers</title>
                 <author>Sutton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 478, 16 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prayers</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prayer">
   <pb facs="13"/>
   <head>
      <hi>D. SUTTONS</hi> usuall Prayer before his Sermons.</head>
   <p>OH most gracious and most glorious God, before whom the Sun and the Moone become as darknesse, the blessed Angels stand amazed, and the glorious Cherubims are glad that they may cover and hide their faces, as not daring to behold that incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensible greatnesse, and that infinite goodnesse which thou art; with what considence shall wee forlorne sinners be ever once able to appeare before thy all-seeing providence, that terrible and angry countenance, that sin-revenging justice of thine, which is so fierce and terrible, that it will shake the heavens, melt the mountaines, dry up the seas, and make the tallest Cedars in Lebanon to trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: Good Lord, where shall we hide our selves from thy presence? masses of corruption, mountaines of sin, dead and dry trees, fit fuell for thy fierce wrath to worke upon: If wee should climbe up into heaven to hide us from thee, thou art there; or goe downe into the bottome and depth of hell, thou art there also; or take the wings of the morne, and fly to the utmost part of the seas, even there also will thy all-seeing eye behold us, and thy right hand will quickly visit and finde us out: wee will therefore here dissolve and melt our selves into a floud and fountaine of many teares, bewailing and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moaning our wofull and miserable estate; for albeit by reason of that foule Chaos, and staine of naturall corruption and originall sin, wee have deserved long since to have had the sweet issue of all thy good blessings to be stopped and dried up, thy milde and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle corrections to bee turned into the sudden execution of bloudy to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>utes and fearefull judgements upon us even in this life, and at ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> departing out of this world to be plunged everlastingly into a pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> destruction, there to be fried and scorched with Sata<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and his Angels for evermore. And yet for all this, O Lord, we have never ceased to adde oyle unto this flame, and to blow up the coales of thy fearefull displeasure, through the hot and eager pursuit of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny loud crying actuall sinnes and transgressions; so that from the crowne of the head to the sole of the foot, there is not one place sound or whole within us, but we are full of sores and swellings, and botches, full of sinne, full or corruption: our understandings
<pb facs="14"/>which should have knowen thee to bee our true God, and him whom thou hast sent Jesus Christ our Redeemer, these are blinded and mis-led with ignorance and doubting, our affections which should have beene good guides to have directed our feet into the way of peace, they are become swift messengers of Satan to buffet us; our bodies which should have been sweet Temples for thy bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Spirit to dwell and lodge in, they are sinks of sin, and cages of filthy birds: Our eyes, O God, are like open windowes, and doores to receive sin, our hearts like common Innes to lodge sin, our heads like skilfull Politicians to contrive sinne, our tongues smooth and sweet Orators to plead for the maintaining of sin, and all our hands like stout Souldiers and couragious Champions to fight in the defence of sin. Thus have we waged and managed war against thee our God, ever since wee were borne, so that now thou maist justly sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e us out of thy mouth, cut us off in the midst of our sins, come amongst us this verie present, and binde us hand and foot, and at the end of these few and miserable dayes send us all into hell together, that so Satan might pay us our wages only, whom thus long we have obeyed and served: thus emptying our selves from all trust and confidence in the arme of flesh, wee fly unto thee, O God, the anchor of our hope, and the tower built for our defence, with many deepe sighes and groanes from our perplexed conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and diseased soules, most humbly intreating thee to be gracious and mercifull to all our sins, for they are wondrous great, make it thy glorie to passe by and to winke at them; poure into our soules the oyle of thy mercie,, supple our hard and dry hearts with the sweet influence of thy best graces, and cure all our swelling wounds with the true balme of Gilead; Purge (good Lord) and cleanse all the polluted and infected corners of our hearts, that though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> this day our sins be as old as <hi>Adam,</hi> as numberlesse as the stars o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as high as the tallest Cedars in the Forrest, Lord plucke them up by the roots, burie them in everlasting forgetfulnesse, that they may never stop the issue of thy blessings, nor draw downe upon us the vials of thy wrath, nor be a wound and griefe to our troubled consciences in this life, or worke despaire in us at the end of our dayes, nor stand up in judgement to be the utter ruine and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of our soules and bodies at the last day. Good Lord pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare
<pb facs="14"/>us all for a better life, sit us all for the Kingdome of thy Sonne Christ Jesus, guide us all with thy blessed Spirit, tutor us out of thy holy Word, humble us by thy mercifull corrections, and by thy fatherly blessings, wed our affections, and knit our hearts more neere unto thee in newnesse of life, than ever heretofore they have beene: that living as becommeth thy obedient children and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants an holy and a religious remnant of our dayes, we may by thy grace and mercie be partakers of a joyfull and a comfortable death, and after death of a glorious resurrection to everlasting life and peace among thy Saints. Neither doe wee pray to thee for our selves onely, but for all people and Nations of the earth, but more particularly for the place in which wee live, and therein according to our bounden dutie for thy servant and our Sovereigne, <hi>Charles.</hi> by thy speciall Providence, King of Great Britaine, France, and Ireland, Defender of the most true, ancient, Catholike and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolike faith, and in all causes, and over all persons, within these his Majesties Realmes and Dominions next under thee and thy Sonne Christ Jesus supreme Governour, adde unto his dayes, as thou diddest unto the dayes of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> that he may enjoy a long and a prosperous reigne over us; and in the meane time remember him in goodnesse for the good he hath done already to thy Church. Bestow the sweetest of thy blessings upon our gracious Queene <hi>Marie,</hi> our hopefull Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> and the Lady <hi>Marie,</hi> and the rest of those royall Branches beyond the seas; season them in their young and tender yeares with thy feare, that they may bee great in thy favour: and if it may stand with thine eternall Decree, let us never want an holy and a religious man of that house and line, to governe the Scepters of these Kingdomes, and to maintaine the preaching of thy glorious Gospell within these his Majesties Realmes and Dominions, so long as the Sun and Moone endure. Blesse <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> King with an honourable valiant, and a religious Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>obilitie, blesse him with a learned, painfull, and a zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Clergie, by what names or titles soever they be called, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be Arch-Bishops, or Bishops, and all other painfull La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers in this thy Vineyard: blesse him with a wise, prudent, and a religious Gentrie: blesse him with a peaceable, a loyall, and a religious Commonaltie, and good God wee beseech thee to
<pb facs="15"/>showre downe thy blessing upon the right hand and upon the left, to them whom it hath pleased thee to send to this Congregation, that by the blessing of thy good Spirit, whensoever they shall stand on thy Mountaine to deliver a Message from thee. give them good Father, (what wilt thou giue them?) give them wise and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing hearts, that they may open to thy people the wondrous things of thy Law; good Father touch their tongues with a coale from thine holy Altar, that by the blessing of thy holy Spirit they may be able to worke some holinesse in the hearts of a sinfull and unbeleeving people: and cut downe the head and strength of some sinne that remaineth in us: and to this end and purpose make them sound in thy Doctrines, terrible in thy threatnings, sweet in thy comforts, powerfull and effectuall in all thy perswasions; and mercifull Father make thy word like the bow of <hi>ionathan,</hi> and like the sword of <hi>Saul</hi> or <hi>Gideon,</hi> that never returned emptie from the bloud of the slaine, and the fat of the mightie.</p>
   <p>Lastly, wee come unto thee for our selves againe thy most un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy servants, that are here assembled in a reverent feare of thy most holy and blessed name, most humbly intreating thee in Jesus Christ to be gracious and mercifull to all our sinnes, and to be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually present with thy blessed Spirit in the midst of us all, and grant that thy word may drop and distill upon our tender consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, like raine upon the mowen grasse, and as dew comes downe from Heaven to water the earth; take away the scales of ignorance from all blinde and darke understandings, remove farre from us all lets and hinderances, whereby the blessed seed of thy Word hath beene too many and sundry times made unfruitfull in the hearts of sinfull and unbeleeving people: and to everie soule that is present in thy house this day, or at any other time, grant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> all holy diligence to seeke thee, godly wisdome to know the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and sanctified understanding to finde thee aright; that so th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Word may prove the the sweet savour of life unto everlasting lift <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ough Jesus Christ our Lord and onely Saviour; in whose most holy and blessed name wee are bold to conclude these our weake and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect prayers in that perfect forme of prayer which Christ hath taught us, saying; <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>