<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1564</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118539_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13977</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24290</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118539</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Thabridgment of the histories of Trogus Pompeius, collected and wrytten in the Laten tonge, by the famous historiographer Iustine, and translated into English by Arthur Goldyng: a worke conteynyng brieflie great plentie of moste delectable hystories, and notable examples, worthie not onelie to be read, but also to be embraced and followed of all menne</title>
                 <author>Justinus, Marcus Junianus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1564</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>21, 57, 56-111, leaf 103, leaf 110, 112-136, leaf 127, leaf 125, leaf 147, leaf 147, leaf 125, 144-147, 160-162, leaf 173, leaf 147, leaf 152, 167-182 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsydering ther is not a more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Iewell geuen vs of God then tyme: and that nothynge reioyseth a mans mynde more then the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of the well spendynge, nor any thinge more greueth, then the remembraunce of the ydle &amp; vaine bestowynge therof: It ought to be the chiefe regarde and indeuoure of all men, in suche wyse to employ the same, as maye most redownd to the vtilitie of others, (for the which intent we be chiefely borne into this worlde) to thaduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Uertue, and to the purchasing towarde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues a laudable name and monument of their well doynges. To aspire vnto the whiche, we se it hath be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> and is the studie and trauell of all good and vertuous men: some by doyng thynges thēselues wherby others myght take good ensample, &amp; some by puttyng thactes of other men in writyng, to the profit and cōmoditie of suche as shulde come after. Wherin albeit the trauell be not lyke of the wryter and of the dooer: yet thone deserueth not muche lesse cōmendacion then thother. For lyke as their could haue ben no Historiographer, if noble actes and enterprises had not ben atcheued: so if no man shulde haue put suche dedes in wryting, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sydes that the fame of the dooers shulde after a whyle haue vtterlie ben condemned to obliuion, the frutifull example of their doynges, (whiche nowe remaineth to posteritie) must also nedes haue perished. Therfore are we not a lytell beholdyng to Chronaclers, as to them
<pb facs="6"/>
that are the guydes, instructours, and maisters of oure lyfe: by whome we are not onelye admonished of oure duties: but also by euident and playne demonstracions tolde before, and as it were pointed to with the fynger, what we ought to eschewe, what we ought to doo, and in what maner to enterprise and bring euery thyng to effect, as may be most to the praise and be hoofe of the dooer. In suche wise annexing and enterlacinge, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, varietie, and delectacion, with vtilitie and profit, that I can not deuise how a man shuld lightly fele any wearinesse. Howbeit euen as the cōmoditie is great if we reade and peruse Histories aduisedly: so it nothyng auayleth, if we purpose not to put in vre thxamples of the true &amp; vndistayned vertue lefi in thē for the rerefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiō of our liues. For lyke as whē a mā cōmeth into a goodly Garden plentifully replenished with all kinde of holsome herbes, sweete Flowers, and pleasant no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryshyng fruites, if he neither gather of the herbes and flowers, nor tasteth of the fruites, but runneth vp and down negligētly, feding his eyes with the vaine sight and beholdyng of them onely, he taketh neyther bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite nor pleasure of the same: Euen so if a man reade ouer Histories, not myndynge to put then samples in practise, but onely contenteth himselfe with the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sauntnesse of thenditing, or with the straungenes and varietie of the matters, he loseth his labo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>r and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spendeth his lyfe. Neither is there any difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene such a one, and him that looketh vpon his owne ymage in a glasse, the whiche he forgetteth assoone as his backe is turned. For all our lyfe consisteth wholly in vertuous act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>s &amp; exercises: the residue thero befing otherwise misspent, differing nothyng at al from deth.
<pb facs="6"/>
Diuerse noble personages therfore, (as well for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thynesse and excellencie of the worke, as to thentent to wynne double honour, and therby to gyue good En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sample to suche as shulde come after, to contend by the lyke industrie to aspire to the lyke glorie and renown,) haue not onely done noble feates and aduentures them selues, but also put in writyng as wel their own dedes as the doynges of other men. Iuba king of Mauritanie made a Collection of Thistories of sundrie Nacions: Iulius Caesar compiled his owne actes. Trogus Pō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peius wrate Thistories of the whole worlde: from the beginnyng of the Monarchie of Allyria, vnto the reign of Themperour Augustus. Thabridgement of whose woorkes, gathered oute by Iustine (who partely by his owne industrie, but more by the decay and losse of his Aucthor Trogus, obteined the name of a famous Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storiographer) I haue translated out of Latin into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish, thoughe not so eloquently as a nōbre could hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> done: yet (I trust) accordyng to the true sence and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of Thaucthor: wherin albeit I maye seeme to iome, to haue taken in hand a vaine and friuolous tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, namely to put forth that thyng in rude Englisshe whiche is written in good &amp; pure Latin: Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standynge (as well for thauoydyng of Idlenes the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; nourissher of al vice, as also for the zeale I beare to this my natiue countrie, desyrous to gratifie yea and to profite suche as haue not vnderstandinge in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin tong yf I coulde) I haue not stopped my race, vntyll suche tyme as I had atteined to the finall scope of my prepensed purpose: folowynge the Ensample of diuers wyse and well learned, both of old tyme and also of our
<pb facs="7"/>
age of all sortes of Nacions, whose studie and trauell hath alwayes ben to bryng into their mother tongue, such workes as they founde eyther in the Greke (the head and welspryng of all Philosophie, connyng and lernyng) or in any other language, worthy to be knowē and had in memory. And in lyke maner as oftentymes beautifull and welfauored persones, turned out of their gorgeous apparell &amp; costly attyre, into simple raiment, doe lyke the beholders as well as they dydde in theire gayest garmentes: Euen in lyke wyse (I trust) it may so comme to passe, that this my rude translation voyd of ornate termes and eloquent indityng, may (as it were) in his playne and homely English cote, be as well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of the fauorable reader, as when it were richely clad in Romayn vesture: consy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deryng that the valewe an estimacion of Thistory, is no more abased thereby, then should the vertue of a precious stone, by settyng it in brasse or yron, or by carying it in a closur of Leather. If any errours haue escaped me in the doyng herof (as I doe not thynke, but that some thynges worthie to be corrected, may haue escaped my hande, I desyre the ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Reader, as well to admonishe me frendly of myne errour, as also to put his helpyng hand to thamendmēt of the same. In doyng wherof as he shal greatly bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte others, so let him assure himself, he cannot doe me a greater pleasure, nor a higher frendshippe. And thus wishyng that my trauell and labour in doyng hereof, may turne to thy commoditie and profyte, I bid the, Fare well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>