<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Ad Lectorem.</title>
           <author>B., A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118507_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13884</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24188</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118507</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Ad Lectorem.</title>
                 <author>B., A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Vindiciæ Ecclesiæ Anglicanæ: or A iustification of the religion now professed in England : VVherein it is prooued to be the same which was taught by our Sauiour Iesus Christ, and by his holy Apostles; written for their vse that haue desired such proofe. By W.T</title>
                 <author>Travers, Walter</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Cotes, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Cotes, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 80 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Ad Lectorem.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, this booke comming forth into the world, offereth it selfe to thy view: the very title whereof may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite thee to reade it: and may iustly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise (if not challenge) future hopes of matter worth the obseruation. It is entitled a Iustifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Religion professed in <hi>England;</hi> and the worke doth make good the title: for in it thou shalt finde these propositions learnedly prosecuted against the Pseudo-Catholiques.</p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1.</hi> That the adoration of Images representing the persons, either of the Trinity, or of Saints, or Angels, is dissonant to the word of God.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2.</hi> That Diuine Seruice ought to bee administred to the people in the vulgar tongue (not in an vnknowne language) according to the practise of Christ and his Apostles.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3.</hi> That the word of God (not Pharisaicall traditions, or the Legends and Fables of men) ought to be read, and expounded to the people, according to the custome of the Scribes and Pharises: who while they sate in <hi>Moyses</hi> chaire read and interpreted the Law and the Prophets.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <hi>4.</hi> That the Sacraments of the New Testament are not seauen, as Anti-Christ that seauen-headed beast af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth: for Christ instituted but two; Baptisme, and the Lords Supper; which succeeded those two Legall ones; Circumcision, and the Pascha.</p>
   <p n="5">
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>5.</hi> That Baptisme, ought to be celebrated according to the commandement of Christ, without Exorcisme, or any superfluous and superstitious Ceremony.</p>
   <p n="6">
      <hi>6.</hi> That the Lords Supper ought to be administred to the people in both kindes, without Eleuation, Adoration, Reseruation, and pompous carrying it abroad in the streets: and that in it there is neither Transubstantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Consubstantiation, or Reall presence.</p>
   <p n="7">
      <hi>7.</hi> That Prayer ought to be made onely to God, by the onely mediation of Iesus Christ: And that it is an hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible impiety to make gods of creatures, in giuing them Gods worship: or to mocke with Christs mediation, in seeking for new Intercessors, whether Saints or Angels.</p>
   <p n="8">
      <hi>8.</hi> That the Martyrs of the Primitiue Church suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vnder the prophane Emperors, for the same Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which we now professe: To which our Martyrs, as <hi>Cranmer,</hi> &amp;c. (not <hi>Garnet</hi> and his adherents) haue borne witnesse, vnder that Whore of <hi>Babilon,</hi> euen to the death; laying downe their liues for the Testimony of Iesus.</p>
   <p>A defence of these Truths, thou hast here in a short view; comprised by a learned Author, whom I neuer knew, but in his workes; whose writings doe seeme to beare witnesse to his labours, and indefatigable paines in Study: The fruites or effects whereof doe in part ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in this, which hath beene locked vp in priuate Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binets, like sire raked vp in ashes, almost buried in obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uion; but now comes forth to see the light for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like good. First reade, then censure.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in all Christian duties: <hi>A.B.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>