<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118816_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14155</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24472</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118816</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tvvo learned sermons : The one, of the mischieuous subtiltie, and barbarous crueltie, the other of the false doctrines, and refined hæresis of the romish synagogue. Preached, the one at Paules Crosse the 5. of Nouember, 1608. The other at the Spittle the 17. of Aprill. 1609 In the first, are examined diuers passages of that lewde English libell, written by a prophane fugitiue, against the Apologie for the Oath of Allegeance. In the seconde, are answered many of the arguments published by Rob. Chambers priest, concerning popish miracles; and dedicated (forsooth) to th Kings most excellent Maiestie. By Robert Tynley, Doctor of Diuinitie, and Archdeacon of Ely</title>
                 <author>Tynley, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Adams, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hall, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Reader. It is the fashion of some men that write or speake, that they are ready and desirous to haue the same put in Print. It fared other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise with the Author of these two godly &amp; learned Sermōs: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he hath beene intreated by diuers his good friends to publish them, yet hee could hardly bee brought therunto, vntil such time as hee was perswaded, that as they did edifie, and cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent many hundreds that heard them preached, so would they, being printed, instruct, and strengthen many that should reade them, against the subtiltie, &amp; impietie of Poperie, which secretly is buzzed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heads of the simpler sort. Vpon which resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that so they might bee beneficiall vnto God his church, he hath at the last condiscended to the putting of them in print. And I doubt not but as to his credit, so to the cōfort of all that shal read them. And so I leaue thee to God his bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, and holy protection.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>