<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118047_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13222</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23521</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118047</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Swedish intelligencer· The first part. Wherein, out of the truest and choysest informations, are the famous actions of that warlike prince historically led along: from his Majesties first entring into the Empire, vntill his great victory over the Generall Tilly, at the Battell of Leipsich. The times and places of every action being so sufficiently observed and described; that the reader may finde both truth and reason in it</title>
                 <author>Watts, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 128 pages, portraits (metal cut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Vdicious and favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Reader. Out of our high respect vnto that <hi>Caesar</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> of our times, that admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly victorious King of <hi>Sweden:</hi> wee haue here (and for thy pleasure too) adventured vpon an Essay of his Story; which if liked, may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage vs to continue it. Not out of any confidence, that ours is a Chronicle worthy enough, for such heroick performances (a <hi>Polibius,</hi> or a <hi>Tacitus</hi> were little enough for that) but our intention chiefly is, to provoke some abler Pen, some better instructed In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligencer, to doe it: and if such a one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troll
<pb facs="3"/>
or mend vs, wee will not be angry. If you here demaund, out of what Instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions wee haue furnisht our <hi>Intelligencer;</hi> be pleased to know; that nothing is willingly feigned, or wilfully falsified. The errors that be in it, are errors of ignorance, all. Some part of it was received from the papers of an honourable personage; a Commaunder of prime credit and activitie, with that victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious King. Wee haue beene made to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand much of these Actions, by discourse with another gallant Gentleman: and he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so a great Commaunder in the Army. Some printed <hi>High Dutch</hi> bookes wee haue had. For some things we haue had private wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and from good hands too. In other things we haue made vse of <hi>Gallobelgicus:</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially where he deales vpon publick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and where we thought the poore man durst speake freely: Some times, sure, he writes but by Commission; and is every where sparing in reporting the Emperours losses. And yet in this, to take away all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, we haue followed him too; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding wee by others found greater numbers and defeates, specified. Very good
<pb facs="3"/>
vse haue wee made of the <hi>Weekely Currantoes</hi> too: which if a man of judgement reades, he shall for the most part finde (especially of latter times) very true, and very punctuall. Whosoever will be cunning in the <hi>Topogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> and would vnderstand these warres, let him not despise <hi>Currantoes.</hi> All this, lastly hath passed the allowance of a Gentleman (of the best judgement and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence for these matters) in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
   <p>Wee haue every where dealt candidely, not magnifying the King, nor derogating from his enemies: not left out, or put in, for favour or advantage. Our methode is this: to handle every Story by it selfe, and then to bring all together at the day of Battell. Carefull haue we beene, (yea no small paines haue we taken;) to note the times and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe the places of the most famous actions. We haue examined the dates with diligēce; and still had fiue Maps before vs of the same place. The <hi>Imperiall Dyet</hi> of <hi>Ratisbone,</hi> w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> was well hoped would haue mended all, leaving things farre more desperate on the <hi>Protestants</hi> partie; necessitated a Resolution in the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="4"/>
of that Confession; rather to dye free, then to liue slaues. Hence their <hi>Dyet</hi> of <hi>Leip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sich.</hi> And because these Leaguers were at first of an Vnion by themselues; we haue briefly therefore, and vpon the Bye, first handled their warlike preparations; vntill the day of their joyning with the King. The same haue we done with the Kings Story: gone along with it from his Majesties first landing. The Kings having of many Armies in the field at once, troubled vs not a little at the first, to finde with which of all these Armyes the King in person should be: but wee after a while perceived, that this most industrious Chieftaine, was able to serve more Cures at once then one: and that he was so vigilant vpon every occasion, that there were few great Actions which himselfe was not at one end of. Many a brave Generall he hath; The Lord <hi>Oxensterne,</hi> a <hi>Sweden</hi> borne, and Lord Chancellor of that Kingdome; Generall all this while of a particular Army in <hi>Prussia,</hi> to waite vpon the <hi>Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e,</hi> and his motions: The Lord <hi>Falkenburg,</hi> a <hi>Germane</hi> borne, and Lord Chamberlayn of his Majesties houshold; vnfortunately slaine in <hi>Magdenburg.</hi> The Lord
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>Gustavus Horne</hi> a <hi>Finlander:</hi> and still Generall of a particular Army by himselfe: with whom the Lord Marquesse <hi>Hamilton</hi> is associated, The Lord <hi>Otho Todt,</hi> for brevities sake call'd <hi>Otty-todt,</hi> or <hi>Todt,</hi> a <hi>Swede,</hi> Generall of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Horse; Sir <hi>Iohn Bannier,</hi> a <hi>Germane,</hi> and a braue Souldier, Generall of the Foote or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantery: all these you finde frequent and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable mention of; and yet hath the King himselfe beene at the most of the businesse. All particular actions it had beene impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for vs to haue toucht vpon; therefore haue we endevored to relate the famousest: whether Sieges, Battels, Marches, Encam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings, or Removings: orderly leading all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto the great day of battell. It would haue perplexed our methode to haue men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned every particular supply that the King hath had: those therefore wee desire the Readers to imagine. For example: he landed but 11. Regiments or thousands of Foote at first: yet within a moneth was his Army full 20000. strong: which daily increased also.</p>
   <p>His numbers, indeede, were never great: he had but 5000. men, for the most part, and
<pb facs="5"/>
never aboue 7000. in all his late warres of <hi>Prussia</hi> against the <hi>Pole:</hi> and yet with them hath he fought severall Battels, beaten out, or wearied out, two <hi>Imperiall</hi> Armies; taken in the great and strong Citie of <hi>Elbing,</hi> with others: and obtained his purpose finally, vpon his enemy; who was able at once to haue come downe with such a power of Horse vpon him, as had beene sufficient to haue carryed away himselfe and fiue such Armies. That which hath made his Majestie so victorious, (next to the assistance of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God,) is his most exact observing of military Discipline; wherein with an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable temper, he is both strict and sweete: the Majestie of a King in him, commanding more willing obedience from his Army, then the awfull directions of a bare Generall alone, possibly could. Adde to his strict Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, his many poynts of new invented Discipline, peculiar vnto himselfe, too long here to describe. His justice, finally, and his mercy; his exemplary and his indefatigable industry: his affabilitie, and his easinesse of accesse: the goodnesse of his cause, and the common Libertie which his victories bring
<pb facs="5"/>
with them: haue conquered more then his sword. What now shall hinder this braue and princely Warriour, to arriue vnto that height of reputation which <hi>Gonsalvo</hi> did in the warres of <hi>Naples;</hi> whom the Historians of that age, worthily stile, <hi>the great Captaine?</hi> yea so great a Conquerour hath the King hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto beene, that I dare challenge the skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullest Historian, to set (for all particulars) such another by him. God blesse the King of <hi>Swedens</hi> Majestie: and thoroughly enable him, to be the glorious <hi>Assertor</hi> of the <hi>Germane</hi> Libertie. <hi>Vale.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>If the Readers desire the continuance of our Relations: our</hi> Intelligencer <hi>shall be much the better furnished to giue Content, if they please to send vs in their owne Intelligence.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>For that it seemes impossible for vs</hi> English <hi>to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyde that observation of</hi> Philip de Commines, That in all great actions, wee are still hark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning after Prophecies; <hi>which the taking of some things in this kinde, hath even now verified: wee will therefore feede the humor of the times a little, with a</hi> Prediction <hi>of a great Astronomer of our owne Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, vpon that great</hi> Conjunction <hi>of</hi> Saturne <hi>and</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
Iupiter, <hi>Iuly</hi> 18▪ 1623. <hi>And the second a</hi> Prophecy <hi>of the famous</hi> Paulus Grebnerus <hi>his Booke, now in</hi> Trinitie Colledge <hi>in</hi> Cambridge.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>The Astronomers judgement is this. That the effect of that</hi> Conjunction <hi>would be felt in the North and Northeast parts of</hi> Europe <hi>in particular: and in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall over all. That it would produce Famines, Plagues, Warres, &amp;c. Places subiect to this, he nameth</hi> Italy, France, Bohemia, Silesia, <hi>and</hi> Germany. <hi>Of Provinces he nameth</hi> Prussia, Brandenburg, Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, Hassia, <hi>and</hi> Saxony. <hi>Yea he descends to Cities: naming</hi> Rome, Prague, Magdenburg, Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents <hi>betwixt</hi> Mentz <hi>and</hi> Cullen, Vlmes, Bruns<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick, Ausburg, &amp;c. <hi>He sayes it is likely to goe hard with the</hi> Romane <hi>Empire, Clergie, and</hi> Iesuites. <hi>He speakes of a King of a true Religion that should doe all this: and of much happinesse that should succeede it. The whole Discourse will perchance shortly be imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>