<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE EDWARD Lord Russell Earle of BEDFORD, and to his most Noble and reli∣gious Consort, the Lady LVCY Countesse of BEDFORD.</title>
           <author>Burges, C.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118864_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17269</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4110</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118864</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE EDWARD Lord Russell Earle of BEDFORD, and to his most Noble and reli∣gious Consort, the Lady LVCY Countesse of BEDFORD.</title>
                 <author>Burges, C.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A chaine of graces : drawne out at length for reformation of manners. Or, A briefe treatise of virtue, knowledge, temperance, patience, godlinesse, brotherly-kindnesse, charitie. So farre forth as they are vrged by the Apostle in 2 Pet. 1. verse 5,6,7. By C. Burges P. of Watford</title>
                 <author>Burges, Cornelius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Samuel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 260, 4 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE EDWARD <hi>Lord Russell</hi> Earle of BEDFORD, and to his most Noble and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Consort, the Lady LVCY Countesse of BEDFORD.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the Dedication of Bookes can be any testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Personages, to whom
<pb facs="3"/>the Authors are most engaged, your Honours first vouchsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing to admit mee a meere stranger to the office of a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mestique Chaplaine in your Noble Familie, affording mee much respect, and constant encouragement beyond desert and expectation; And your Honour, <hi>Madame,</hi> beginning to take care of my further preferment from the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of my Seruice; and after a little waiting, procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring me a setled comfortable abode, and Pastorall imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, so neere your owne Mansion, and vnder your wing, by your gratious and effectuall mediation to that Honourable Knight, and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronet, <hi>Sir Charles Morison,</hi> my Noble, and vncorrupted
<pb facs="3"/>Patron, (for whose compleat prosperitie, my witnesse is in heauen, that I daily pray vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my bended knees:) lastly, obtaining, out of your honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable disposition, that further accession of credit, and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to my Ministerie, which now I hold; will easily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide the question, to whom these First fruits of mine doe chiefly appertaine. I therefore humbly present the same, as a small expression of that thanksgiuing which I gladly would, but cannot sufficiently render vnto you, most Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Founders (vnder God) of all that good I doe possesse.</p>
   <p>I know well that things of this nature doe rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, then pay the debts of men ranged in so great a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance
<pb facs="4"/>below your sphere: yet withall I finde the greatest Oceans willing to embrace the smallest streames that runne vnto them, tendring their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and acknowledgement from whence they sprang.</p>
   <p>And though it be most equall that such as publish any thing vnfit, should beare the whole burden of the shame, and losse vpon their owne backs, who euer be their Patrons; yet it is an honour to such as need no Patrons to helpe them out of brakes, to haue their writings graced by Noble Persons of eminent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect for learning, iudgement and Religion, and to vse their Names in such a publike act, whereby the world may know they be not destitute of friends
<pb facs="4"/>that will vphold them in any Worke well done.</p>
   <p>This Treatise was chiefly intended for the benefit of mine owne Charge; but now, by consequent, I haue put my selfe vpon the censure of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious dispositions, and doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the common Lot of all Writers. My only care is, to giue content to such as reade to profit. If any peece hereof shall, by Gods blessing, adde the least mite to your rich stocke of Graces, or to any well-affected, which is my highest ambition, I haue enough.</p>
   <p>But remembring that now I present your Honours with a Booke, I must not make a booke of an Epistle. What further addition of thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb facs="5"/>for your continued fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, my prayers, obseruance, labours in any kinde, my life it selfe, may make, shall not be wanting, but gladly for euer tendred from, and by</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours most firmly bounden in the strongest bonds, to be commanded, C. BVRGES.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>