<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118836_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01735</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11868</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118836</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A short reply vnto the last printed books of Henry Barrow and Iohn Greenwood, the chiefe ringleaders of our Donatists in England : vvherein is layd open their grosse ignorance, and foule errors: vpon which their whole building is founded. By George Gyfford, minister of Gods holy worde, in Maldon</title>
                 <author>Gifford, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Cooke (Coke), Toby</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 98 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here were (good Christian Reader) foure haynous accusatiōs laid against the Church of England, for which the accusers haue condemned her, &amp; all her publique assemblies, as most wicked Antichristian Idolatrons sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues of Sathan. I shewed how falsely they doo accuse, and howe presumptuously agaynst God they doo condemne: And that indeede they are the very same with the auncient Donatists. They haue replyed and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed in print their defence, but their bookes are intercepted: yet some few haue escaped, and are dispersed among theyr fellowes. Wherefore I hold it needfull to publish some an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere, not dealing with euery error and absurditie, (for that would aske the trauaile of some yeares) but onely with the chiefe grounds of their Schisme. In this, I trust euery sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple man that hath a Christian heart, shall see the effectuall power of Sathan, when he turneth himselfe into the likenes of an Angell of light, to seduce ignorant men, which are lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp in their mindes, with opinion of their knowledge: For being men vnlearned (onely some little froth excepted, I speake thus because they peruert that little which they haue read in other means writings, in sundry poynts) yet as if they were sent from heauen with reuelations, or as great Apostles, they take vpon them to confute, and controll, and condemne all Churches, and all the most worthy Instruments which GOD hath raysed vp in these last times. For knowe this (good Reader) that the foure accusations which they haue brought agaynst the Church of England, to condemne her,
<pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> also (though with some differences) brought against all Churches in <hi>Europe,</hi> and that in expresse wordes in these their last bookes. For the prescript formes of prayers, which all the Reformed Churches doo vse, they condemne as most horrible and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> blasphemie. The people (they say) are prophane multitudes. They say, that in all <hi>Europe,</hi> &amp; in all these knowen partes of the world there is no minister of Christ. The gouernment by Elderships, they condemne as a most proude thing, as being without any warrant of Gods word. Doo but readeouer these fewe things which I haue noted out of their booke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and iudge how fit they be for such a work as they haue taken in hand, &amp; whether it be like that GOD hath sent them, euen as it were <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> to conduct his people out of <hi>Aegipt,</hi> from vnder the bondage of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> for so they take it; as appeareth by their owne wordes, speaking of those which cleaue vnto them. Many they see by Gods mightie hand (say they) escaped, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching with the banner of the Gospell displayed, before all the inchaunters of <hi>Aegipt,</hi> and <hi>Pharaoh</hi> his troupes, <hi>pag.</hi> 5. of the Epistle. And if it seeme lost time to stand vpon such grosse things: yet take this profit, as to see how needfull it is not to be high minded▪ and presumptuous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bolde in Gods matters, but to feare and tremble with Humilitie.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>