<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Maden, R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118495_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13835</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24142</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118495</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Maden, R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The saints humiliation : Being the substance of nine profitable sermons upon severall texts. viz: 1 The nature of a fast; on Iudges 20.26. 2 The Christians watchfulnesse; on Mark. 13.37. 3 Gods controversie for sinne; on Hosea 4.12. 4 The remedy of distresse; on Gen. 32.9.11. 5 The use of the covenant &amp; promises; on Gen. 32.10. 6 The broken sacrifice; on Psalme 51.17. 7 Good wishes for Sion; on Psalme 51.17. 8 Motives to repentance; 9 An exhortation to repentance; on Math. 3.7.8. First preached and applied by Samuel Torshel, minister of Gods Word at Bunbury, and now published for the common good</title>
                 <author>Torshell, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Overton, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Young (Junius), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40, 116, 69, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Epistle to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S God is the Author of all blessings, so likewise of all judgements; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speritie and adversitie, sweete and bitter waters, both these proceede from the same fountaine, but in a different manner: he begins with blessings, and then onely proceedes to judgements, when these are not answered with dutifull obedience, he doth not first come in stormes and tempests, but in the still, and gentle voyce of his mercies, because he would rather haue men to magnifie the riches of his mercies, than complaine vnder the severitie of his judgements; accounting it more glory to be loved for his goodnes, than feared for his greatnes: besides the blessings of God, they haue no motiue to stirre him vp to the bestowing of them; but within himselfe and in his owne nature, but his judgements haue their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall and foundation in mans sinne, blessings and judgements they come from God, as hony and the sting doe from the Bee; the Bee makes hony natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but stings not vnlesse she be provoked; so it is su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and connaturall to the goodnes of God, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate it selfe in the bestowing of blessings; but not to inflict judgements vnles he be provoked vnto it, <hi>He punisheth not willingly, neyther takes he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light
<pb facs="4"/> in afflicting the children of men. LAM. 3.33.</hi> and the reason is, because the bestowing of blessings it is his proper worke: <hi>Quod in Deo est sufficit ad completam ejus rationem,</hi> as the Schoole speakes, all that is required for the exercise of it is in God himselfe, no merit or motiue at all in the creature: but the inflicting of Iudgements, it is his strange worke. <hi>Esai. 28.21.</hi> It is <hi>opus suum alienum,</hi> so his worke that another also hath a hand in it, it cannot come from him alone, but by occasion of the creatures disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and it is the common fault of men in times of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitation, when the hand of God is vpon them, and his judgements abroad in the world, that they doe not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue such impressions on their soules, as those passages of Gods providence towards them are apt to beget, but are either secure and sensles of the hand of God which is out against them; or neglectiue in vsing the meanes for the removall of it, till they haue outstrayed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, and it be too late. Of the former sort are those who are taken with a sleepie Lethargie of sinne, and cannot be awaked; or rather with a dead Palsie, as men that haue no vse of their spirituall sense and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, they sleepe securely in the midst of the Sea, and on the top of the Mast: when they are smitten they perceiue it not, and when they are beaten they feele not the smart; <hi>Pro. 23.24.</hi> Of such the Prophet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines to God; <hi>Thou hast smitten them, but they haue not grieved; thou hast consumed them, but they haue refused to receiue correctiō; they haue made their faces harder than a stone, and haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused to returne; Ier. 5.3.</hi> Of the latter sort are those, who never thinke of preparing to meet the Lord with
<pb facs="4"/> submission, and supplication, with prayers and teares, so long as the Iudgement hangs in the Clouds, or fals besides themselues, or doth but lightly touch them, till God make way through their bowels for his owne prayse, and out of the ashes of their ruine rayse vp glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to himselfe. So it was with the <hi>Israelites,</hi> God fore-warned them of his wrath, and set his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments daily before them, but they stopped their eares, and would not heare, they hardened their hearts and would not be reformed, till vnavoydable judgement fell vpon them, and <hi>there was no remedie: 2 Chro. 36.16.</hi> O marke and consider well, that expression; <hi>there was no remedie!</hi> If the <hi>Israelites</hi> would haue layd it to heart before, <hi>there was a remedy,</hi> they might haue prevented it by timely repentance; but now the sentence being past, and the decree put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, <hi>there was no remedie;</hi> So it was with the old world, notwithstanding all the warning which <hi>Noah</hi> had given them of a future Iudgement, they neither humbled themselues, nor reformed what was amisse in them, till the Floud came and swept them all away, and <hi>there was no remedie,</hi> so that Iudgement threatned, it may be neglected so long, till it become vnavoydable, and <hi>there be no remedie.</hi> Two things there are then which God especially aymes at when his Iudgements are abroad in the world first to giue them notice that himselfe is highly displeased with their sinnes; secondly, that it is now high time for them to thinke of agreeing with their Adversary, and making their peace with him.</p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1.</hi> When God warres out of <hi>Zion,</hi> and reveales his wrath from heaven against the sinnes of his people,
<pb facs="5"/> it is a signe he is highly displeased with them; for God is knowne by executing Iudgement. <hi>Psal. 9.16.</hi> That is, he makes it knowne to the sonnes of men, how he stands affected to them, and to their sinnes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Gods visitations are termed <hi>Iudgements,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they doe not come casually but Iudicially; there is great cause moving him to it, because men are deafe against all the sweet charmes of his mercies, and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure against all the thunder of his threatnings, and therefore he is constrained as it were to speake vnto them in a strange language, even the language of his hands; to speake words that may be felt, even swords, famines, plagues, pestilence, that men might know that his Word of threatning it is no vaine Word, but as he hath said vnto them, so he meanes to deale with them; according to that of <hi>David,</hi> Psal. <hi>48.8. As we haue heard so haue wee seene in the Citie of our God.</hi> (It is true both of his mercies and judgements, <hi>God will not alter the word that is gone out of his mouth,</hi> whether it be a word of promise or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination,) such is the hardnesse of mens hearts, that though they heare the Word daily sounding in their eares, and telling them that <hi>the wrath of God is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed from heaven against all vngodlinesse and vnrighteousnesse of men. Rom. 1.18.</hi> Yet they will not beleeue it, except they see some reall examples of it, they are ready to say of Gods threatning, as <hi>Thomas</hi> did of Christs Resurrection, <hi>Ioh. 20.24. Except I see in his hands the print of the nayles, &amp; put my finger into his sides, I will never beleeue it;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God stretches out his hand against them, he powres his wrath and indignation vpon them, that
<pb facs="5"/> when they lie bleeding vnder his hand, then they might be sensible of his high displeasure; when they feele the sharpnesse of his arrowes, then I might say with the Prophet; <hi>Who can stand before his indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation? Who may abide the fiercenesse of his wrath? Nah. 1.6.</hi> When they see his lips full of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, and his eyes sparkle out flames of fire vpon them; then they might call to minde that of <hi>David; As wee haue heard, so haue wee seene in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of our God;</hi> as we haue heard his high displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure threatned, so haue we seene it executed.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2.</hi> When God is vp in Armes (as it were) against his people, it is to let them know, that it is now high time for them to thinke of returning to him, and making their peace with him, and that considering the season, that it is now high time they should awake from sleepe. <hi>Rom. 13.11.</hi> There is no time vnseasonable for the duties of repentance and humiliation, but when the face of Heaven begins to frowne vpon men for their vnthankfulnesse and disobedience, when his Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are seene abroad in the earth; then it is high time to reforme what is amisse, and returne vnto him, because this is the last meanes God will vse for their good; if they will yet stand out and not submit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues; if they will not for all this come in and lay downe their weapons of rebellion; if they will not onely fit out his mercies, but his judgements too; then he will be to <hi>Ephraim</hi> as a Lyon, and as a young Lyon to the house of <hi>Iudah:</hi> He will teare and breake in peices; He will carry away &amp; none shall deliver; <hi>Hos. 5.14.</hi> And therefore when God begins to draw forth his glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Sword, and his hand layes hold on Iudgement;
<pb facs="6"/> When he begins to speake in his wrath, and say; Thus will I doe to thee O <hi>Israel,</hi> O then let every one thinke it high time to prepare to meet the Lord his God; <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos 4.12.</hi> It is his great happines that through Gods mercy, he can say, it is yet time, that it is not yet too late; that as yet it is not without hope to returne; God might haue cut him off long agoe, and if he had done so, it had but beene justice on Gods part, and desert on his owne; but the doore of mercy yet stands open, God is yet willing to receiue his people, if they would be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled vnto him; for to that end he speakes to them, to that end he deales with them, to that end he expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stulates the matter with them on this manner; Is there no hope? Will nothing worke vpon you? No meanes? no mercies? no threatnings? No Iudgements? will yee not flie from the wrath to come? O why will yee not? why will yee die O ye house of <hi>Israel?</hi> Will yee not returne vnto mee? Oh my people why will ye not returne? What haue I done vnto you? Wherein haue I grieued you, that yee should bee so vnwilling to lay downe your weapons of rebellion that yee haue taken vp against mee? These and such like expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions from God; what doe they imply? but that there is yet a time of mercy, euen while the heauens seeme to bee clouded ouer with indignation, that when no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but wrath shewes it selfe, there is yet a time wherein mercie may bee found if it bee sued for; if euer there bee a time that should bring men vpon their knees, and make them earnest in sueing for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, surely then it is high time aboue all other times to cry mightily to God, because this is the last time that ever he will waite to haue mercy vpon them; and
<pb facs="6"/> never doe men shew themselues more vnlike to men, that is, to reasonable creatures, than to stand out when God summons them to come in, and submit themselues. What more vnreasonable then to make him an enemy, who is the fountaine of all that good which they haue, or can hope for? What more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable then when they haue prouoked him to wrath and made him their enemy, and now even lie at the foote of his mercie, then to capitulate and stand vpon tearmes with him? yea, with him who when he might let loose his hand, and dispatch them at one blow; yet offereth to spare them, if yet at last they would even now close with him. There be two sorts of arguments whereby God convinceth his people of the vnreasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenesse of their sinfull courses; First, by sending them to the Heathen, who might be thought the most vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable amongst men; and yet even they would be ashamed, and thinke it most vnreasonable to deale so with their Idols, as many doe with the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. <hi>Goe ye now to the Iles of</hi> Chittim <hi>and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, and send to</hi> Kedar <hi>and take diligent heed, and see whether there be any such thing; hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Nations changed their Gods, which yet are no Gods? But my people haue changed their glory for that which profiteth not;</hi> Ier. <hi>2.10.11.</hi> Secondly, not finding any amongst men so vnreasonable with whom he may sort them; he seekes amongst the vnreasonable and senselesse creatures, to see if there be any there with whom he may suit them; he compares them to the bruit beasts, and if there be any more brutish than others, it is to those bruits that are most blockish, to the Horse and Mule, to the Oxe
<pb facs="7"/> and Asse: Psal. <hi>49.20. Man being in honour un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandeth not, but is like the beast that peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth:</hi> and it is no small disparagement to mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be matched with the vnreasonable beast, for to be like unto a beast in that sense is worse then to be a beast indeed; to be a beast indeed it is without any fault in the Creature, it was God that made it so, but to be made a man &amp; to be like a beast, that is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his owne fault, without his great sin; which makes him a reasonable beast, or rather an unreasonable man; yea such is the unreasonablenesse of men in their sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full courses, that they are not onely compared to the bruit beasts, but those unreasonable creatures prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before them; <hi>Isay 1.3. The Oxe knoweth his owner, and the Asse his Masters crib; but Israel hath not known, my people haue not understood.</hi> God sets men to schoole to the very bruit Creatures, that they might learne of these how to carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues. <hi>Pro. 6.6. Goe to the Pismire O sluggard, behold her wayes and be wise.</hi> These silly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible Creatures, they are set before men as pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes, they are set over them as Tutors, to teach them wisedome. Yea more, when God finds none amongst bruit beasts so unreasonable in their carriage as obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate sinners be, he goes one step further, and tryes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the insensible creatures, if there he might find any prints or footsteps of such demeanure, and there he finds them more sensles than stockes and stones; for the stones cleaue asunder, and the rockes are moved when God is angry; yea the hills melt and the mountaines shake &amp; tremble before him, &amp; yet many men though they both heare and see the Iudgements of God; though
<pb facs="7"/> there be enough spoken many times both to the eye and to the eare, to cleaue the very rocke asunder, and to moue and affect the very mountaines, if possibly they were capable of any morall impressions; yet are they no more moved and affected with it than the very stones and earth which they stand vpon. And when men are thus farre degenerate and gone from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, that they come not onely below the nature of men, and of bruit beasts, but even of stockes &amp; stones and sensles creatures; Is it not high time for man to returne into himselfe, and to returne vnto God with submission and supplication; that God may repent him of the evill and turn from his fierce wrath that he pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish not? And this is the summe and substance of this insuing Treatise; which is spent upon some speciall portions of holy Scripture, whereby these sacred Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercises may be actuated and enlivened: of the Author himselfe, being no further knowne to me, than by his Labours and the reports of others, I will say nothing, but leaue his Workes to <hi>prayse him in the gates.</hi> The severall passages of the Discourse being drawne into a Table, and layd out in their generall Heads, prevents my labour in shewing the vse and profit that may be made of it; the matter it selfe as it was seaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and proper for the time and places in which it was delivered, so being spent vpon those common Theames, of <hi>Fasting, Watching, Prayer, Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, Humiliation, &amp;c.</hi> which are the daily imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of penitent sinners, it cannot be vnseasonable for any time; nor is it any prejudice to the Treatise that diverse haue written of the same subject vpon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Texts and portions of Scripture; for the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie
<pb facs="8"/> of gifts, phrases, and expressions is most suitable to the diversitie of severall mens dispotions, that will suite well with one that likes not another; It is no hurt to a man that comes into a Cookes shop, to haue his choyce of severall dishes, the varietie of dressing is no hinderance to his nourishment, he may feed vpon that which liketh him best; If a man were to provide a suit of apparell, it were no hurt to him to see diverse pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes, out of which he may please himselfe in his own choyce; even so he that would provide a mourning suite for his own sorrowfull heart, it is no hurt to him that out of the diverse patternes of godly mens La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, he may make choyce of those which are most suitable to his owne desires. Amongst which, this modell may happily sort better with thy affections <hi>(Christian Reader)</hi> than some others; blesse GOD for the varietie of his goodnesse in this kinde; out of this varietie make thine owne choyce, and the God of Heaven giue a rich blessing vnto it for thy soules good.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord, R: MADEN.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>