<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO The Christian Reader, all Christian Graces.</title>
           <author>G., A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118374_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01691</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11829</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118374</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO The Christian Reader, all Christian Graces.</title>
                 <author>G., A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The lands mourning, for vaine swearing: or The downe-fall of oathes : Declaring how this land groneth vnder the burthen of this sinne, and of Gods fearefull iudgements that attend it. A sermon preached at Paules Crosse, the 11. of Iuly. 1613. By Abraham Gibson, Mr. of Arts</title>
                 <author>Gibson, Abraham</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 118 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO The Christian Reader, all Christian Graces.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian <hi>Reader,</hi> for my selfe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready to be seene in the <hi>Presse,</hi> will be to some as great a wonder, as <hi>Saul</hi> among the <note place="margin">1 Sam. 19. 24.</note>
      <hi>Prophets.</hi> I must confesse, that in regard of the small number of my yeres, (being so few moneths aboue the age <note n="*" place="margin">24</note> required to our calling,) I might iustly haue incurred the censure of presumption both to Preach at the <hi>Crosse,</hi> and to
<pb facs="4"/>
come into the <hi>Presse,</hi> had I not to the former beene inioyned by <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie,</hi> and to the latter pressed by <hi>importunitie.</hi> After many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nials I was forced to yeeld to the continuing <hi>requests</hi> (and no lesse earnest, then godlie) of such Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, Worshipfull, and worthy intreaters: Whose liking thereof, had it beene no better then my owne, the place of <hi>Birth</hi> had bene the place of <hi>Burial;</hi> and the <hi>Crosse</hi> had beene the <hi>Graue,</hi> wherein to leaue it. But the rather haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers desires for publishing this <hi>Sermon,</hi> at length preuailed and ouercome me, because the good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, &amp; incouragement, which it had of the <hi>hearers</hi> giueth mee hope that some benefit may ensue to the <hi>Readers,</hi> and that it shall be profitable to some, hurtfull to
<pb facs="4"/>
none. It layeth open a sinne very dangerous and <hi>detestable;</hi> and yet (the more pitty) too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and <hi>customable.</hi> If here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I may reclaime but one from it, I haue my reward: that is the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly marke I ayme at, not <hi>affectation</hi> not <hi>ostentation.</hi> Plaine it was in the <hi>Preaching,</hi> more plaine it is in the <hi>Printing:</hi> some <hi>Quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> I haue omitted, and interposed in the <hi>Margent,</hi> to the end it may no way be obscure, but plaine to the plainest. Thus (with <hi>Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome)</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pro. 9. 2. 5.</note> I haue prepared <hi>cheare</hi> for thy <hi>soule;</hi> and now (with her also) I inuite thee to <hi>eate</hi> of it. When I can prouide better thou shalt haue it. In the meane time <hi>accept</hi> this, and <hi>welcome</hi> to it. If thy <hi>sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke</hi> be curious, it is not for thee: If otherwise, much good doe
<pb facs="5"/>
it thee. If any good hereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to thy <hi>Soule,</hi> let God haue thy <hi>prayse,</hi> and mee thy <hi>prayers.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>Waldingfield parua. <hi>Suffolke.</hi>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Thine in Christ Iesus, A. G.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>