<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the thrice Honourable, and most worthie Lord, George Baron of Huns∣don, Lord Chamberlaine of the Queenes house: Cap∣taine of her Maiesties Gentlemen Pensioners, gouer∣nour of the Ile of Wight, Knight of the Ho∣norable order of the Garter, and of her Highnesse nost honorable priuie Counsell.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118698_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14028</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24335</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118698</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the thrice Honourable, and most worthie Lord, George Baron of Huns∣don, Lord Chamberlaine of the Queenes house: Cap∣taine of her Maiesties Gentlemen Pensioners, gouer∣nour of the Ile of Wight, Knight of the Ho∣norable order of the Garter, and of her Highnesse nost honorable priuie Counsell.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The policy of the Turkish empire. The first booke</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 <publisher>Stansby, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 82 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the thrice Honourable, and most worthie Lord, <hi>George</hi> Baron of Huns<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, Lord Chamberlaine of the Queenes house: Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of her Maiesties Gentlemen Pensioners, gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Ile of Wight, Knight of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable order of the Garter, and of her Highnesse nost honorable priuie Counsell.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable: The remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of your forepassed fauors, And a desire to make knowne my honest thankefulnes: hath encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged me to present you Lorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship with a collection of Turkish Histories: Discouering the policie of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire both in the state of their Religion, and in the manner of their ciuill Gouernment, and marshall Discipline. The which my labour, though it may seeme an Idle worke, and farre vnworthie of so Honorable a Patron: Yet as the pure and fine Gold being artificially layed vpon Copper or some such base mettall, doth make it seeme ritch and glorious, gracing the basenesse of the stuffe, with the excellencie and ritchnesse of her colour: So the least aspect of fauour and good countenaunce from your Lordship towards the gracing of this work, may make
<pb facs="3"/>
others to haue it in some regard and estimate, though of it selfe it bee reputed worthlesse and of no accompt. Howsoeuer it bee, my hope is that your Lordship will accept of it, as a signe of my good affection: And in that respect vouchsafe it your good liking. For as a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine cunning Geometrician in the games of <hi>Olimpus,</hi> by the view of the proportion and bignesse of <hi>Hercules</hi> foote, did giue a coniecture of the quantitie &amp; stature of his whole body: So, by the consideration of my well willing minde in so meane a matter, your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship may measure the redinesse of my heart and most inward affections. Which (being wholly deuoted to doe you seruice) doe tie me to be euer both an assured follower of your Lordship, and a vowed Orator for the continuaunce and encrease of your most happie fortunes: vnder the which I rest euer to be commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>