<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118987_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02435</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12567</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118987</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A description of the Church of Christ, with her peculiar priuiledges, and also of her commons, and entercommoners : With some oppositions and answers of defence, for the maintenance of the truth which shee professeth: against certaine Anabaptisticall and erronious opinions, verie hurtfull and dangerous to weake Christians. Maintained and practised by one Master Iohn Smith, sometimes a preacher in Lincolneshire, and a companie of English people with him now at Amsterdam in Holland. Whome he hath there with himselfe rebaptised. By I.H</title>
                 <author>Etherington, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Fosbrooke, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 119, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="65"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>ANd if any man thinke heere is not so much said against them, as their faults deserue: Let him consider, if one should lay open to others all his faults at once, with their due deserts, he would take it very vnkindly, and very hardly euer receiue an admonition (at his hands) in good part that should so serue him. Therefore to preuent this euill, I haue rather laboured to tell them what they should be, then to lay open what they are, for loue hopeth the best, till it see the worst. And this I assure both thee &amp; them, that no man euer was more forward and strict in outward obseruations, nor more ready to contend about the forme and manner of religious exercises, and carnall washings, and all other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Kingdome, then the very hippocrite, that neuer intended the purging of his heart, nor yet to partake in her peculiar things, though vnder the cloake of the one, he doth pretend the greatest part in the other. Make cleane then the inside first, and the out-side shall bee cleane; for whosoeuer is cleansed in heart, neede not bee taught to wash his hands.</p>
   <pb facs="65"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>