<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1550</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118174_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17651</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4407</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118174</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An epistle both of Godly consolacion and also of aduertisement : written by Iohn Caluine the pastour &amp; preacher of Geneua, to the right noble prince Edvvarde Duke of Somerset, before the tyme or knoweledge had of his trouble, but delyuered to the sayde Duke, in the time o his trouble, and so translated out of frenshe by the same Duke</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1550</date>
                 <publisher>Baldwin, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Whitchurch (Whytchurch), Edward</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>68 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat nothing is more odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or detestable afore god then the disobedience of subiectes against their Kynges and Gouernours, maye partly by moste open testimonies of holy Scripture euydentlye appeare, and partly by thys argument be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestly proued, that it hath neuer yet vnto thys daye, neyther in goddes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected people the Israelytes, nor yet in anye other common weale, eyther Heathen or Christyan, escaped with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out moste grieuous plages and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishmētes. Yet neuertheles so merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a god he is, of so long sufferance, so lothe to stryke, and so desyrous of mans amendment: that it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed his diuyne maiestie, ere he will take extreme vengeaunce for tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous dysobedyence of the people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynste theyr heades, to geue manye sondrye kyndes of warnynges for vs to beware by. First he hath nowe in these last daies, reysed vp many god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preachers, who cease not daylye to
<pb facs="3"/> publish (as it were) gods proc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion in thys behalfe, plainely decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng to all estates and degrees, what theyr duety is. He hath prouided ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny godly exhortacions and treatyses dayly to come forth to the same effect &amp; purpose. Yea, and leste any manne should thinke y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he will daly in suche a matter, he made vs y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> last Soomer here in England to feele a littel touch of his sharpe rod, by the kinges regal sworde, beyng a most euydent token of hys great wrath and indignacy on agaynste all Rebelles, and sedicious murmurers. God hath of his infinite goodnes not only made litle Englāde strong enoughe to withstand al forein puissaunce, (yf we holde togethers, and agree well emonges our selues, obeying the king and magistrates as we ought to dooe:) but also by many vndoubtable tokens hathe declared that he myndeth (as it were) to make hys habytacyon and dwellyng place here emong vs, of purpose to be our sure defence and proteccion, yf we wil
<pb facs="3"/> receiue him accordyngly. But in case we wilbe so hard herted, as wilfully to refuse the grace of his gospell most mercyfully and most fatherly offered vnto vs: it cannot bee doubted ne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded, but that thextreme plages of gods wrath and vengeaunce will at length lyght vpon all such as eyther of an vngodly hearte will swell and stryue agaynst the grace and trueth of hys woorde, which he hath sent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monges vs: or els of a malicious fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes wil repine, and murmure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynst theyr heades &amp; rulers. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou has<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> here set furth vnto the, good Christian reader, an Epistle of Iohn Caluyne, written in frenche vnto the ryght noble prynce Edward Duke of Somerset, and sent hither into Englande immediately vpon the late commocion here in thys realme. And by thys Epistle it maye to the godly reader very wel appeare, how tenderly god of hys goodnes dooeth embrace vs, and doeth (as it were) set vs in hys owne lappe, myndyng to
<pb facs="4"/> kepe vs safe frō al perils of outward enemies, vnder the shadowe and sure defence of his own winges. He decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth himself so mercifully to prouide for vs, (if we will gladlye and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglye receyue hys grace, and stande therein) that he maketh them care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for vs that neuer wer in Englād, nor neuer had to doe with vs, sauing onely that (as the nature and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of christian charitie is) they wishe and daylye praye, that we maye haue grace so to vse oure selues, that the blessing of god which he hath so plē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouslye powred vpon vs, maye not through our vnthankefulnes bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away agayne: whiche forasmuch as it so is▪ let not vs be lesse carefull for our selues, than other straungers be. Let vs not haue receiued the grace of God in vayne. Let vs stand in the trueth, and cleaue to Christes gospel, and by the same, lette vs practise (as it teacheth vs) to obeye quietely and willingly our rulers and gouernours by him appointed. Which it we do, he
<pb facs="4"/> wil so defende vs with his almighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful arme, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> al foreyne enemies (what euer they be) shal eyther bee vnhable to doe vs any scathe: or els shall be turned in theyr heartes, and of eager enemies shall beecome oure earnest frendes and folowers. Whiche thinge GOD graunte.</p>
   <p>To whome be all honor and prayse, worlde without end.</p>
   <closer>AMEN.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>