<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118026_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01011</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11117</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118026</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The totall summe. Or No danger of damnation vnto Roman Catholiques for any errour in faith : nor any hope of saluation for any sectary vvhatsoeuer that doth knovvingly oppose the doctrine of the Roman Church. This is proued by the confessions, and sayings of M. William Chillingvvorth his booke</title>
                 <author>Floyd, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>104 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Discourse was intended at first, as the Conclusion and closing vp of the Treatise I termed, <hi>The Church Conquerant ouer human VVit</hi>: but being when I wrote it, in great doubt, that the sayd Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise was lost in the transporting therof from one place to another (which often happens in Countries which are infested with warre) I resolued to make this Discourse more large, by the discouery of many other Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in this our Aduersary, and with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of such tergiuersations, as Cauillers might deuise, to stay piously disposed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, from yielding prompt and assured assent to this most important Verity.</p>
   <p>And as they who make <hi>Bills of Account,</hi> whē they haue set downe distinctly for their dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, the particular Summes of expences; are accustomed in the end in few Cyphers to
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>
abbreuiate the <hi>Totall Summe</hi>; so this Treatise comming after the former, as the Conclusion thereof; I haue giuen it the name of <hi>Totall Summe,</hi> the Argument handled therein being worthy of that stile. For what is the <hi>finall</hi> marke, the <hi>Totall,</hi> the <hi>All in all</hi>
      <note n="(a)" place="margin">Deū time, &amp; mandata eius ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serua: hoc est enim omnis homo. <hi>Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astae c.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 13.</note> of our pious endeauours, labours, cares, sollicitudes in this mortall life, but only to find out the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, wherein one shall be sure of his Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if simply and constantly he belieue the Doctrines, and liue according to the lawes thereof.</p>
   <p>Verily this is the pith, the marrow, the Summe, the quintessence of all Controuersies ventilated betwixt Protestants and vs: and in particular it was the sole scope of that short substantiall Treatise <hi>Charity mistaken by Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants</hi>; which being by <hi>D. Potter,</hi> in his <hi>VVant of Charity,</hi> impugned, was defended and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the learned labours and elucubra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Charity maintayned.</hi> For the maine Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersy debated in these three bookes is, <hi>whether Roman Catholiques &amp; Protestants may both be saued in their seuerall Religions:</hi> or which comes to the same issue, seing Protestants grant we may be saued in our Religion, because our Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours
<pb n="5" facs="3"/>
are not Fundamentall and damnable, <hi>whether it is not want of Charity in vs, that we will not requite them with the like mild, gentle, and comfortable doome</hi>; but constantly maintayne, that Saluation cannot be had in any course of Separation, and Opposition against Doctrine proposed by the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, as matter of faith.</p>
   <p>And though this our Catholique determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation hath beene in the before named <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise</hi> demonstrated, especially in the two last Chapters thereof; which shew all Sects &amp; Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uisioners, all <hi>Protesters,</hi> and Opposers against the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to be guilty of the two most heynous crimes, <hi>Schisme,</hi> &amp; <hi>Heresy:</hi> yet I haue thought fit &amp; conuenient, to hādle this <hi>Totall of Controuersies</hi> in a particular short Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atise: wherin omitting the former two heads of proofe, I haue vrged peculiar, and proper Arguments, grounded vpon euident Truths confessed, approued, confirmed euen by this our Aduersary, whose Booke Protestants so much esteeme as they stand thereon against the cleere demonstrations for the <hi>Catholique Church</hi> brought by <hi>Charity maintayned.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If in this very Booke, in which they so
<pb n="6" facs="4"/>
much confide (which beareth the title, <hi>The Religion of Protestants a safe way to Saluation</hi>) the happy security of <hi>Roman Catholiques,</hi> and togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the vnauoydable danger of their Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers be proued, and proclamed; if no <hi>safe</hi> path to Saluation for English Protestants be shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his Treatise; but they be forced to goe the <hi>broad way,</hi> wherein the most damned He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques that liue vnder the cope of Heauen, not onely <hi>Anabaptists</hi> and <hi>Arians</hi>; but also the new <hi>Samosatenians,</hi> or <hi>Socinians</hi> may be saued aswell as they: this being shewed, our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants will be compassed about on euery side with the light and euidence of this eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally importing Truth, <hi>No hope of saluation out of the Catholique Roman Church.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And then, God forbid, they should not yield vnto so cleere Euictions, but fall into the extreme misery of peeuish obstinacy, whereof <hi>S. Augustine</hi> sayth, <hi>Nihil infelicius homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lib <hi>3.</hi> contra l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t Petil c. <hi>13.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>qui non vult cedere veritati, quâ ita conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur, vt exitum inuenire non possit</hi>: Nothing more vnhappy and wretched, then the man that will not yield vnto that truth, wherwith he is so concluded and inclosed, as he knowes not which way to get out.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>