<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To painted women.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118556_Fr1_3_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14007</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24316a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118556</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To painted women.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discourse against painting and tincturing of women : Wherein the abominable sinnes of murther and poysoning, pride and ambition, adultery and witchcraft are set foorth &amp; discouered. Whereunto is added The picture of a picture, or, the character of a painted woman</title>
                 <author>Tuke, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marchant, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 62 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <head>To painted women.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>STay women-Gallants, cast an eye aside,</l>
      <l>See where a mirrour represents your pride.</l>
      <l>Not that your fardingales fill too much roome,</l>
      <l>Nor that your loftie tires you misbecome:</l>
      <l>Nor paps embossed layed forth to mens view:</l>
      <l>(Though that be vaine too, if wise men say true)</l>
      <l>But that ye haue renounc'd your natiue face,</l>
      <l>Vnder a colour that paint adds a grace,</l>
      <l>To your intising lookes. But ist no sinne,</l>
      <l>When Vermeil blushes to belie your skinne?</l>
      <l>Alas what comfort can your looking glasse</l>
      <l>Yeeld you, fond creatures, when it comes to passe</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="4"/>
That o're the paint is blurd, which makes you fret,</l>
      <l>Or yee see nought else but a counterfet,</l>
      <l>A shadow of your selfe? Why should you seeme</l>
      <l>Fairer then women? Men oft misesteeme</l>
      <l>Your sweetest beauties: for because they know</l>
      <l>Some of you are lesse beauteous, then they show.</l>
      <l>And who would willingly her beauty saint,</l>
      <l>Whose face ill-colour'd is clouded o're with paint?</l>
      <l>If ye be faire, what need of new complexion?</l>
      <l>If blacke, or wrinckled, learne what a confection</l>
      <l>The first, that was a Moralist doth learne you;</l>
      <l>Be vertuous, a bad face will nothing yerne you.</l>
      <l>Who would be vgly in heauens piercing sight,</l>
      <l>To seeme faire to some mortall partiall wight?</l>
      <l>Yet none so partiall, but he needes must see</l>
      <l>Vpon your brow folly and vanitie</l>
      <l>In their owne colours: and 'tis hard to find</l>
      <l>A painted face sort with a single mind.</l>
   </lg>
   <byline>Ed. Tylman.</byline>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>