<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE Sir IAMES LEY Knight and Baronet, Lord Chiefe Iustice of his Maiesties Bench.</title>
           <author>Gataker, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118743_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01554</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11681.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118743</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE Sir IAMES LEY Knight and Baronet, Lord Chiefe Iustice of his Maiesties Bench.</title>
                 <author>Gataker, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tvvo sermons : tending to direction for Christian cariage, both in afflictions incumbent, and in iudgements imminent. The former on Psalm. 13. 1. the latter on Hebr. 11. 7. By Thomas Gataker B. in D. and pastor of Rotherhith</title>
                 <author>Gataker, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 77, 11, 81-130, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE Sir IAMES LEY Knight and Baronet, Lord Chiefe Iustice of his Maiesties <hi>Bench.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LBEIT Speech</hi> haue no small aduantage of <hi>Writing;</hi> in that <note n="a" place="margin">Habet nescio quid latentis <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> viva vox; &amp; in aures disc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>puli de autoris ore transfusa fortius sonat. Hiero. ad Paulin. Viva illa, ut dicitur, vox lectione pleni{us} alit. Quintil. institut. l. 2. c. 2. Quod memoria lapsus ciccroni quasi ex Tuscul. l. 2. tribuit Erasm. in Hieron. &amp; in Adag. Atqui Cic. epist. ad Atlic. lib. 2. epist. 8. Ubi sunt qui aiunt, <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>; Quanto magis vidi ex tuis literis, quàm ex illius ser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>one quid ageretur?</note>
      <hi>it hath a greater viuacitie</hi> accompanying it, than the other hath by much: the latter seeming to be but as <note n="b" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Greg Naz. epist. 52. Et <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. idem epist. 38.</note>
      <hi>a dead shadow</hi> of the former; <hi>Elocution</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">Actio quasi vita quaedam est orationis. Quintil. institut. lib. 11. cap. 3.</note> the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>vitall spirit</hi> and <hi>chiefe grace</hi> of <hi>an Oration,</hi> and
<pb facs="4"/>
that, which <note n="d" place="margin">O' <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Dionys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Halicar. de Demost<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hene. Oratorem pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nè perfectum, &amp; cui nihil admodum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sit, Demosthenem facilè dixeris. Cic. de clar. Orat. Quo ne Athenas quidem ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sas magis credo fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>isse Atticas. Idē de perfect. Orat. Grae. corum Oratorū prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantissimi sunt <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> qui fuerunt Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis; corum autem princeps facilè Demosthenes, admirabile est quantum inter omnes unus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellat. Idem de opt. gen. Orat. Cujus commemorato nomine maxima eloquentiae consummati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> audientis animo oboritur. Val. Max. memorab. l. 8. c. 7.</note> that <hi>most eminent Orator</hi> and <note n="*" place="margin">Quomodo Facundiae Parentem Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceronem. Plin. hist. nat. l. 7. c. 30. Atqui, cùm Demos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>enes Graecae, Cicero Latinae eloquen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>▪ Principes extiterint; Demosthenes &amp; prior fuit, &amp; exmagna parte Ciceronem, quantus est, fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit. Quintil. institut. l. 6. c. 3. &amp; l. 10. c. 1.</note>
      <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Elo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> not <hi>the Prime pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> only <hi>of Oratorie,</hi> but in effect <note n="e" place="margin">Acti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> in dicendo una dominatur. Huic prima<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dedisse Demosthenes dicitur, cùm rogaretur, quid in dicendo esset primum, huic secundas, hui: tertias. Cic. de Orat. l. 3. &amp; declar. Orat. Val. Max. memor. l. 8. c. 10. Quintil. instit. l. 11. c. 3. &amp; Aug. epist. 56.</note>
      <hi>all in all,</hi> and <hi>the summe of al,</hi> being <note n="f" place="margin">Hinc Val. Max. lib. 8. cap. 10. In Demosthene magna pars Demost<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henis abest, quia legitur potius quàm auditur.</note> wanting in it: In regard wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it is not wont to make so deepe an impression, or to worke vpon the affections so powerfully as <note n="g" place="margin">Nulla res magis penetrat in animos, eosqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> fingit, format, flectit. Cic. declar. Orat. Tantum dictis adjicit gratiae, ut infinitè magis ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem audita quam lecta delectent. Quinti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>l. instit. l. 11. c. 3. Multo magis, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>t vulg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> dicitur, viva vox affic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>t. Nam, licet acriora s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>nt, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> legas, altius tamen in animo sedent, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciatio, vultus, habitus, gestus etiam dicentis adfigit. Plin. epist. 4. lib. 2. Hinc <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mosthenis orationem, quàm eis recitasset, ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>antibus Rhodijs, <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>; Quidsi ipsum, vel, Quid si bestiam ipsam audivissetis? Cic. de Orat. lib. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. nat. lib. 7. cap. 30. Val. Max. lib. 8. cap. 10. Plin. jun. ep. 4. lib. 2. Quintil. instit. l. 11. c. 3. &amp; Hieron. ad Paulin.</note> that doth; &amp; it is accounted therfore but <note n="h" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Ignat. epist. 1. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>stath. ad Odyss. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> ex Pausania.</note>
      <hi>a second shift,</hi> and as sailing with <hi>a side-winde,</hi> where a direct <hi>fore-winde</hi> faileth. Yet herein hath <hi>Writing</hi> the ods of <hi>Speech;</hi> in that by it we may speake as well to the <hi>absent</hi> as to the <hi>present;</hi> by it men restrained by sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, weaknesse, or otherwise from publike <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>mploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet may notwithstanding much profit the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, &amp; sitting themselues still at home, benefit others abroad; yea by it, not the <note n="i" place="margin">Sola <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>es est que homines absentes praesentes facit. Turpilius de vicissitudine literarum. Quid enim tam pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sens est inter absentes, quàm per epistolas &amp; alloqui &amp; audire quos diligas? Hieron. ad Nit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>. Sunt literae doctrina quaedam, qua quisque valeat quamvis longè absenti verba mitter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facta in silentio, quae rursus ille cui mittuntur, non auribus, sed oculis colligat. Aug. de Trinit. lib. 10. cap. 1. Voces signa sunt, per qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> praesentibus loquimur: inventae sunt literae, per qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>s possemus &amp; cum absentibus colloqui. Ibid. l. 15. c. 10.</note>
      <hi>liuing</hi> only may conuerse
<pb facs="4"/>
with the <hi>liuing,</hi>
      <note n="k" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Homer. Iliad. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> though neuer so farre both by <hi>sea and land</hi> seuered either from other, but the <hi>liuing</hi> also may haue profitable commerce and dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with the <hi>dead,</hi> as <note n="l" place="margin">Hinc illud Luc. 16. 29. Habent Mosem &amp; Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas: audiant illos. Mortui siquidē lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur adhuc: quod de Abele Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus Sanctus Heb. 11. 4. &amp; de Samue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le Siracides Eccles. 46. 20.</note> we haue by meanes of their <hi>writings</hi> still extant with those that died and depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this world, euen thousands of yeeres since, to our exceeding great comfort and inestimable gaine. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore moued by some that heard of it, and the matter deliuered in it, but could not be present at the deliuery of it, to make <hi>this weake discourse,</hi> by helpe of <hi>Pen and Presse,</hi> more publike, as dealing in <hi>an Argument</hi> not vnfitting the present times, and such as they desired to be more fully either instructed or directed in, which by meanes thereof they supposed that both themselues and many other might be; I was the rather induced to condescend to this their desire, that by presenting of it to your Lordship, <hi>the prime Member</hi> of that <hi>graue and reuerend Societie,</hi> where it was by word of mouth deliuered: I might giue some poore pledge and testimonie of my due and deserued respect to your Honour, and of my thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full acknowledgement of such fauours, as haue from time to time, by your Lordship beene shewed me, as well during the time of mine employment at <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colnes-Inne,</hi> (where your Lordship was one of the first whom I receiued kinde acceptance from, being <hi>Reader</hi> at the time of my first accesse thither,) as since also. Hauing therefore during my late restraint by some infirmitie and weaknesse that constrained me to keepe home, and to intermit my publike im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, taken some time to reuiew, supply, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large my former Meditations of the Subiect then
<pb facs="5"/>
handled, (which I could not so well finde time for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) I make bold to tender them here (such as they are) vnto your Lordship, and intreating onely your courteous acceptance of them, without further troubling your Honour amids so many weightier af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, commit both your selfe and them to the grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous protection and holy direction of the Highest.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships to command in the Lord,
THOMAS GATAKER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>