<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO ALL THOSE THAT HAVE BEENE, ARE, WILL, OR WOVLD BE, Masters of a SHILLING or TWELVE-PENCE.</title>
           <author>Taylor, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118272_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13495</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23793</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118272</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO ALL THOSE THAT HAVE BEENE, ARE, WILL, OR WOVLD BE, Masters of a SHILLING or TWELVE-PENCE.</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A shilling or, The trauailes of twelue-pence</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Gosson, Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO ALL THOSE THAT HAVE BEENE, ARE, WILL, OR WOVLD BE, Masters of a SHILLING or TWELVE-PENCE.</head>
   <p>SIR <hi>Iohn Mandeuill,</hi> an English Knight, a famous Trauailer, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerer of forraigne Maners, Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Rarieties; <hi>Christopher Collumbus, Magellane, Hernan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do Cortez, Don Diego de Almagro, Drake, Hawkins, Frosbushir, Baskeruile, Cauendish,</hi> and many more worthy Trauailers of our owne and other Nations, whose honourable, dangerous, and laudable atchieuements, haue made their meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious names to be Recorded, to the admiration of the time past, present, and to future posterity: yet if
<pb facs="3"/>
it be well considered, it will plainely appeare, that all their laborious endeuours had an end with their liues. But the Trauailer that I treate of, the Thrice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trebble tryumphant <hi>Troynouantine Twelue-pence,</hi> is like a perpetuall motion in continuall trauell, to whose Iourney there can be no end, vntill the world come to a finall dissolution and period. For the progresse of <hi>Coriat</hi> was but a walke in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of my <hi>Shillings</hi> perambulations: and if all the Inke and Paper-murdering fictions should be true of <hi>Amadis de Gaule, Huon,</hi> Sir <hi>Egre, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis, Guy,</hi> the <hi>Mirrour of Knighthood,</hi> the <hi>seauen champions, Chinon,</hi> Sir <hi>Dagonet, Triamore, Launcelet, Don Spatterlash</hi> of <hi>Toledo, Monsieur Mallegrindo,</hi> Knight of the frozen Ile: If it were possible that all their lyes should be true, of the great Trauels of these imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie and neuer seene Worthies, yet must they all come short of the praise that is due to my trauelling <hi>Twelue-pence.</hi> I could haue busied my braines
<pb facs="3"/>
about many other Subiects, as quick <hi>Epigrams,</hi> biting <hi>Satyres,</hi> sharpe <hi>Iambicks,</hi> soothing <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies,</hi> pleasant <hi>Pastorals, Odes, Madrigalls,</hi> or <hi>Roundelayes;</hi> alluring <hi>Sonnets,</hi> flattering <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thalamiums,</hi> or lying <hi>Epitaphs, Panegericks,</hi> or name-seruing <hi>Acrosticks,</hi> and <hi>Annagrams,</hi> lofty <hi>Tragedie,</hi> lowely <hi>Comedie,</hi> ridling <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,</hi> or stately <hi>Heroicks:</hi> either of all these I could haue poorely handled, but that my Muse stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by chance vpon this <hi>Twelue-peny</hi> subiect, wherein I would haue the Reader to consider, that in some places I speak only of a <hi>Shilling</hi> or <hi>Twelue-pence,</hi> and in some places generally of <hi>Money.</hi> I haue set downe the manner of my <hi>Shillings</hi> shif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Masters, more often then the Serieants do; for they vse the old Sheriffs like Almanacks out of date, and yearely serue the new : but <hi>Twelue-pence</hi> hath sometimes <hi>12. 16. or 20.</hi> Masters in a day. In a word (Reader) I doe not beg your fauour, craue your acceptance, entreat your kindnes, implore
<pb facs="4"/>
your loue, or request your friendship; for it is not any of these in particular that I seeke or care for: but generally at all I ayme, and for all I hope, and being in that hope, I leaue you to Reade and Iudge of my insuing Labours, and my <hi>Twelue-pences</hi> Trauels.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Yours, as you please to be mine,</salute>
      <signed>IOHN TAYLOR.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>