<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Author'S Addendum]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118291_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13509</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23803</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118291</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Author'S Addendum]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Taylor on Thame Isis: or The description of the tvvo famous riuers of Thame and Isis, who being conioyned or combined together, are called Thamisis, or Thames : With all the flats, shoares, shelues, sands, weares, stops, riuers, brooks, bournes, streames, rills, riuolets, streamelets, creeks, and whatsoeuer helps the said riuers haue, from their springs or heads, to their falls into the ocean. As also a discouery of the hinderances which doe impeache the passage of boats and barges, betwixt the famous Vniuersity of Oxford, and the city of London</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 <publisher>Gosson, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_addendum">
   <p>
      <pb facs="15"/>
I <hi>Haue almost finished another small booke which I will name,</hi> ALL WATERS, <hi>wherein I haue treated of the strange diuersities of waters, and also I haue described and explained the various di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spositions of watermen, their lawfull vses, and their vnlawfull abuses, neither flattering, sparing, or wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any good or ill, which I know either by them or my selfe, not omitting any thing that may tend in the praise of their honest trade and conditions, nor inserting any thing to couer their causlesse iniuries, which many of them haue done to me and others; for they haue late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cast out scandalous libels, and defaming speeches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst me, and I must make them know, that I am not of that tame patience to forbeare them, who are knowin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> to be nothing but rumour and rabble; therefore vpon such I must right my selfe in print.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="15"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>