<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An Aduertisement vnto the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118523_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19394</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5822</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118523</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An Aduertisement vnto the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An apologie for svndrie proceedings by iurisdiction ecclesiasticall, of late times by some chalenged, and also diuersly by them impugned : By which apologie (in their seuerall due places) all the reasons and allegations set downe as well in a treatise, as in certaine notes (that goe from hand to hand) both against proceeding ex officio, and against oaths ministred to parties in causes criminall; are also examined and answered: vpon that occasion lately reuiewed, and much enlarged aboue the first priuate proiect, and now published, being diuided into three partes: th first part whereof chieflie sheweth what matters be incident to ecclesiasticall conisance; and so allowed by statutes and common law: the second treateth (for the most part) of the two wayes of proceeding in causes criminal ... the third concerneth oaths in generall ... Whereunto ... I haue presumed to adioine that right excellent and sound determination (concerning oaths) which was made by M. Lancelot Androvves</title>
                 <author>Cosin, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barker, Christopher, Deputies of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 130, 10, 140, 2, 4, 255, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="160"/>
   <pb facs="160"/>
   <head>An Aduertisement vnto <hi>the Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      <hi>Haue not quoted (gentle Reader) any Pages in the</hi> Treatisours <hi>or</hi> Notega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers <hi>writings, which I haue occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to alleage: because those which I fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, are but priuate written copies. but when I had almost finished the reuiewing of this Part; I was credibly tolde, that the sayd</hi> Treatise <hi>was put foorth, and spred abroad in Print: from</hi> Scotland, <hi>or from</hi> Middleburgh. <hi>and I haue since seene the same in print: howbeit varying in certaine places from my Copy, namely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the latter ende thereof. For there bee some additions, which (in my iudgement) differ no lesse from the stile of the rest; then they doe from the written copy.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>