<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118340_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18092</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4733</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118340</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The hammer for the stone : so named, for that it sheweth the most excellent remedie that euer was knowne for the same. Latelie deuised by Walter Carie Maister of Art, and student in physicke</title>
                 <author>Cary, Walter</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsidering with my selfe (gentle reader) how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon a disease the stone is, and how little helpe the parties grieued haue by the vsvall means of Physicians in this our time, and of long time haue had: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so hearing it diuerse times obiected, that the most learned Physician can neither preuent the stone, in those, who naturallie are inclined thervn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, neither cure it in those in whom it is ingendered, I did endeuor my selfe with all studie and diligence, to find out somthing, which might far excell the remedies now dailie vsed for the cure of the stone.</p>
   <p>VVherevpon taking mine inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from <hi>Etius,</hi> who vsed very much the powder of Goats bloud for cure of the same: also being further persuaded therevnto by authoritie of diuerse,
<pb facs="3"/>
writing of the nature of goats bloud: I did with my great charge attempt to draw a pure and cleare liquor out of the bloud of the male goat, which with the patience of the Physicians, I will be bold to call a Quintessence.</p>
   <p>And hauing made experience ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of now two yeares, and better, with diuerse: I thought good to publish the same, to the reliefe of many, which are grieued with that disease, and that in such sort, as it shall appeare vnto the world, that I rather seeke herein to benefite my Countrie, than anie pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate gaine to my selfe.</p>
   <p>For whereas no man troubled with that disease, can haue the helpe of the Physician, without his great charge: I haue deuised that meane, that anie man so diseased may haue such ease with verie small charge, as I dare boldlie auouch, cannot be had by anie vsuall meanes.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>
But for the commendation hereof I leaue it rather to be commended by the helpe and ease of those, who feele the passions of that most terrible dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease, than vse anie long Rhetoricall persuasions, knowing that good wine needs no garland, &amp; that the fairest garland can be no long credite to sowre wine.</p>
   <p>But for better performance of my promise, I thinke it verie necessarie, to signifie vnto such as are inclined to the stone, and to those that are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie troubled with the same: First, <note place="margin">The diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the booke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to foure Chapters.</note> the causes of the stone, and whereof it is ingendered. Secondlie, the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of stones ingendered in mans bodie. Thirdlie, the vsuall way, both to preuent and cure the stone. And fourthlie, the way or meane now late deuised for preuenting and curing of the same. VVherin being somwhat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed, they shalbe the better able to
<pb facs="4"/>
gouerne themselues, in auoiding and curing the disease, as not needing the Physicians continuall counsell, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Physicians to themselues.</p>
   <p>Yet I would not haue anie man think, that I mind to make any long or curious discourse of the stone, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching all the deepest pointes of the same, as endeuoring to make the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders perfect Physicians herein: but onelie to shewe them a superficiall knowledge, sufficient to direct them in the taking of my Quintessence, both for the preuenting and curing of the stone.</p>
   <p>And thus (gentle Reader) haue I diuided that, wherof I mind to write into foure partes, wherein I will not endeuor my selfe to speake whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer may conuenientlie be spoken: but rather to speake nothing that maie conuenientlie be left out.</p>
   <p>W. C.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>