<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣nourable, Sir Richard Boyle, Knight, Lord Boyle, Baron of Youghall, Viscount Dun∣garuan, Earle of Cork, and one of his Maie∣sties most Honourable Priuie Councell of the Kingdome of Ireland, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Cockeram, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118706_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19044</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5461.2</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118706</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣nourable, Sir Richard Boyle, Knight, Lord Boyle, Baron of Youghall, Viscount Dun∣garuan, Earle of Cork, and one of his Maie∣sties most Honourable Priuie Councell of the Kingdome of Ireland, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Cockeram, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The English dictionarie: or, An interpreter of hard English vvords : Enabling as well ladies and gentlewomen, young schollers, clarkes, merchants, as also strangers of any nation, to the vnderstanding of the more difficult authors already printed in our language, and the more speedy attaining of an elegant perfection of the English tongue, both in reading, speaking and writing. Being a collection of the choisest words contained in the Table alphabeticall and English expositor, and of some thousands of words neuer published by any heretofore. By H.C. Gent</title>
                 <author>Cockeram, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <distributor>Weaver (Wever), Edmund</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>332 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, Sir <hi>Richard Boyle,</hi> Knight, Lord <hi>Boyle,</hi> Baron of <hi>Youghall,</hi> Viscount <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garuan,</hi> Earle of <hi>Cork,</hi> and one of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties most Honourable Priuie Councell of the Kingdome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Art of euery desertfull birth, (Right Honourable) in any man his Country may challenge, his Soueraigne a part, his Parents a part, &amp; his friends another. As I cannot be vseful in euery respect to each of those, so I will striue to expresse at least a will, if not a perfection in abilitie to all. Where a generall voice warrants an approbation, there euery ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice is a duty. The truth of it both concernes and inuites me, out of the fame and applause of your Noblenesse, to make a particular dedication of some serious houres to your suruey, whom the world speakes both noble and learned, wherein as I haue done my best to accommodate discourse
<pb facs="3"/> with the choisest language, so I desire that my ambition of being knowne vnto your Lordship may not be imputed either vnto an errour of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence, or an impudence in erring. Please you to know thus much of me, that I am partly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldned hereunto, by the assurance of your loue and fauours to that noble Gentleman, Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Hull,</hi> to whom as I am tied in double bonds of bloud and friendship, so, I am so much obliged vnto him, that I cannot deuise a better rent than to doe you seruice: But chiefely the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of your owne honourable merit and iust commendations, encourage mee to this duty, though otherwise vnknowne, not questioning but you will be pleased to take notice of one who loues and honours vertue in all Personages for vertues sake. Vouchsafe (Right Honourable) this poore testimonie of my obseruancie, intended only to serue you, not to instruct you, and you shall not onely largely requite my endeuours, but may also expect a more steady and particular du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours most ready seruant, Henry Cockeram.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>