<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, IOHN EGERTON, Lord ELSMERE, Earle of Bridgewater.</title>
           <author>Tejeda, Fernando de</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118363_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13640</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23921</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118363</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, IOHN EGERTON, Lord ELSMERE, Earle of Bridgewater.</title>
                 <author>Tejeda, Fernando de</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Miracles vnmasked : A treatise prouing that miracles are not infallible signes of the true and orthodoxe faith: that popish miracles are either counterfeit or diuellish. Euidently confirmed by authorities of holy Scripture, of antient doctors, of graue and learned Spanish authors, by weighty reasons, manifest examples, and most true histories which haue happened in Spaine, and appeare in bookes there printed. By Ferdinando Texeda, Batchelar in Diuinity</title>
                 <author>Tejeda, Fernando de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Blackmore (Blackamore), Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 31, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, IOHN EGERTON, Lord ELSMERE, Earle of <hi>Bridgewater.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His small TREATISE which I composed in my owne language, I now set forth in the English tongue; vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thereunto by the importunate entreaty of some friends of mine, who perswaded mee that it would be no lesse for the good instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of faithfull Christians, then the destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of them which are not so. The many benefits, and charitable fauours which I haue receiued at your Lordships liberall hands, seeme to call vpon mee, and tell mee that I ought (to cumply in part with the strict obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation wherein I stand bound to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour) to dedicate the same to your Noble selfe: hoping that the same reason by which I offer this small manifestation of my grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="3"/>heart to your honourable protection, will be a sufficient motiue to your Lordship to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it, and giue it a fauourable aspect: For where a Noble minde hath once conferred benefits, those benefits may lawfully be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as seales to an obligation of future fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour. Since the sacrifice which Iesus Christ made of his precious bloud for our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is acknowledged by his diuine Maiestie as a most powerfull inducement whereby we may expect euery day new blessings from the same fountaine. And I haue a most strong hope that your Lordship will not reiect this piece of seruice, because small in respect of your greatnesse; for your breast is Princely, <hi>Et non minus est regium, atque adeo humanum paruula accipere, quam largiri magna;</hi> And your Lordships gracious acceptance hereof will impose a new bond vpon me, to pray the Almighty to enrich your Noble soule with continuall infusions of diuine graces, and to powre down on your honourable estate and family, hourely showres of transitory bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships deuoted in all humble duty, <hi>FERDINANDO TEXEDA.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>