<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY REVEREND AND LEARNED FRIEND Dr. RALEIGH Chaplaine in Ordinary to his Majesty, and Rector of Chedsey in Sommerset.</title>
           <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118116_Fr8_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13272</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23573</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118116</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY REVEREND AND LEARNED FRIEND Dr. RALEIGH Chaplaine in Ordinary to his Majesty, and Rector of Chedsey in Sommerset.</title>
                 <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sermons vpon solemne occasions : preached in severall auditories. By Humphrey Sydenham, rector of Pokington in Somerset</title>
                 <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Robinson, Humphrey</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 240, 251-316, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="141"/>
   <pb n="275" facs="141"/>
   <head>TO MY REVEREND AND LEARNED FRIEND Dr. RALEIGH Chaplaine in Ordinary to his Majesty, and Rector of <hi>Chedsey</hi> in <hi>Sommerset.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Onder not, that in such a <hi>troope</hi> of <hi>Dedications,</hi> I set a <hi>Learned Doctour</hi> in the <hi>Reare;</hi> for it is my custome in publike Epistles, as in my private Letters, <hi>To remember my choisest Friend in a Postscript.</hi> Besides, you know I am a <hi>Divine,</hi>
      <pb n="276" facs="142"/> and no <hi>Herauld;</hi> and therefore should not so much study priority of <hi>place,</hi> as <hi>merit;</hi> or had I done both, in these, I should have met with no great disparity, since <hi>vertue</hi> was ever thought a companion for <hi>bloud</hi> and <hi>fortune,</hi> especially in <hi>them</hi> which can challenge as well an eminency of <hi>Descent,</hi> as <hi>Knowledge.</hi> And therefore to suppose a distance here, were but to distinguish men at <hi>Ordinaries,</hi> and make an <hi>upper end at a round Table.</hi> To you then I cannot but send this wandering <hi>Pastor</hi> of mine, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst my other <hi>Pilgrims</hi> abroad, hopes to find countenance &amp; entertainment <hi>frō you,</hi> and from you in a just claime and interest; where (like seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall streames in a full channell) <hi>Integritie, Learning,</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> meet, and what else may speake a <hi>Pastor,</hi> good; or a <hi>good man,</hi> glorious. In confidence whereof I tender this, with <hi>my selfe</hi> (and you can have no more of your best <hi>votaries</hi> than <hi>all</hi>) assuring you that you have not a truer honourer any where, than with</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your most respective Friend, and Servant, HUM. SYDENHAM.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>