<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118367_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13641</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23923</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118367</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Texeda retextus: or The Spanish monke his bill of diuorce against the Church of Rome : together with other remarkable occurrances</title>
                 <author>Tejeda, Fernando de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 34 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint <hi>Ierome</hi> relating <hi>Iacobs</hi> Vision,<note place="margin">Epist. ad Ager. <hi>11.</hi>
      </note> in which he saw Angels ascending and descending on a Ladder reaching from the earth to heauen; gathers these profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and comfortable lessons from thence, That no man should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spaire of grace to recouer him from sinne, for <hi>Iacob</hi> saw Angels ascending; nor yet any presume of his owne strength, for <hi>Iacob</hi> saw Angels descending, as well as ascending; his owne words are, <hi>Videbat scalam per quam ascendebant Angeli et descendebant, vt nec peccator desperet salutem, nec iustus de sua virtute fecurus sit.</hi> The Church of Christ in this respect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembles the Sea, which, what it looseth in one place, it alwaies gaines in another. And therefore let no weake Christian be scandalized at the reuolt of so many now a dayes to Popish errors and superstitions. For the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit speaketh expresly, <hi>That in the latter times,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.1.</note>
      <hi>some shall depart from the faith, giuing heed to seducing Spirits and doctrines of Diuels;</hi> yea, <hi>that many shall follow their pernitious waies, by reason of whom, the way of truth shall be euill spoken of.</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.2.</note> When there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="4"/>we see the truth of these Prophecies fulfilled, in the falling away of many from the truth, euen this their falling away from the truth, ought to confirme vs in the truth; the rather because wee finde by experience, that the Apples that fall from the tree with the least shog,<note place="margin">De simplicitate praelatorum.</note> or smallest puffe of winde, are rotten at the core. This was Saint <hi>Cyprians</hi> obseruation, long agoe; <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo aestimet bonos de Ecclesia posse discedere; triti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum non rapit ventus, nec arborem solidâ radice fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datam procella subuertit: inanes paleae tempestate iactantur, inualidae arbores turbinis incursione euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuntur:</hi> Let no man imagine that good men can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the Church; The winde blowes not away the Corne, neither doth a storme throw downe a tree that hath sure rooting in the earth; it is but light chaffe which the winde scattereth abroad, and they are but hollow and rotten trees which are ouerturned with a blustring winde. And Saint <hi>Austen</hi> and Saint <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> make good this obseruation of Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding all those from the number of Christs Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and the true Sonnes of God, whose reuolt and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postacie euidently proues their hypocrisie. Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten</hi> speakes definitiuely,<note place="margin">Decorrept. et <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>9.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Qui non habent perseueran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, sicut non verè discipuli Christi, ita nec verè filij dei fuerunt, etiam quando esse videbantur, et ita vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabantur:</hi> Those who perseuer not in the truth, as they were neuer the true Disciples of Christ, so neither were they euer truely the Children of God, no, not when they seemed so to be, and were so called also: And Saint <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> is as peremptory; It may trouble, saith he, a weake Christian,<note place="margin">Moralium in ob l. <hi>34.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi>
      </note> that this Leuiathan hath such power, <hi>vt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, hoc est, viros sanctitatis claritate fulgentes, quasi
<pb facs="4"/>lutum sibi vitijs inquinandum subijciat:</hi> That he can trample Gold vnder his feete like dirt; that is, men shining with a bright lustre of sanctitie, by defiling them with viciousnesse: <hi>Sed citiùs respondemus, quia aurum quod prauis Diaboli persuasionibus sterni sic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ut lutum potuerit, aurum ante oculos dei nunquam fuit; et qui seduci quandoque non reuersuri, possunt, quasi habitū sanctitatisante oculos hominū videantur amittere, sed eam ante oculos dei nunquam habue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt:</hi> But we readily answere, That that gold which by the wicked perswasions of the Diuell, could be thus trodden vnder foot by him like dirt, was neuer gold in the sight of God; and whosoeuer may so be led away from the true Church, that they neuer returne thither backe againe, well they may seeme to lose an habit and shew of sanctitie before men, but the truth is, in the eyes of God they were neuer indued with any sanctitie at all.</p>
   <p>If this suffice not to keepe the weake from stumbling at this rocke of offence, I meane the Apostacie of see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Saints, and reuolt of outward professors of the truth, let them consider in the last place, that this losse of the Church (if it be any) is in some measure repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the daily accesse of new conuerts. Not to goe farre for instances at this present, for an Italian Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stata, we haue a Spanish Conuert; for a loose Bishop, we haue a strict Augustine Monke; the former lately left Christ, to follow his preferments in the Court of Antichrist; the latter hath left all his hope of prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in this world, and stript himselfe of all his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall meanes, to follow Christ naked: whose solid mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues set downe in this short and pithy relation, if thou
<pb facs="5"/>weigh diligently, thou canst not but afford this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise a like commendation, to that which <hi>Homer</hi> giues <hi>Diomedes,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: A lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Man, but a great Souldier. For thou shalt finde in it arrowes taken out of the Romish Quiuer, drawne to the head against the Romish faith; besides, diuers rarities touching the fopperies and ridiculous superstitions of that Church. There are not many leaues in this Treatise, but there is much fruit, yet this is but a tast: The Author hath furnished alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy a Table richly with such kinde of fruit, to which he wil shortly inuite thee: In the meane while, let this stay thy stomacke, and if any thing herein please thy appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, blesse God for the Author; if any thing distaste thee, pardon the Author for Gods cause; for which the more losse he hath, and doth sustaine, the more he deserues to gaine thy loue and charitable opinion of him.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in Christ,</hi> D.F.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>