<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE, MOST worthie of all Honour, and truelie Religious, The Countesse of EINZIE, Ladie GORDON, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Guild, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118648_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02349</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12479</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118648</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE, MOST worthie of all Honour, and truelie Religious, The Countesse of EINZIE, Ladie GORDON, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Guild, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A compend of the controversies of religion : wherin trueth is confirmed, and errour convinced, by authoritie of Scripture, witnessing of antiquitie, and confession of partie. Most necessarie for all, in this backe-slyding age. By W.G. minister of God's word</title>
                 <author>Guild, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Raban, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Aberdeen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>3, 6-217, 9 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE, MOST worthie of all Honour, <hi>and truelie Religious,</hi> The Countesse of EINZIE, Ladie GORDON, &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MADAME,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE sedulitie of the emis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries of that Aposta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> who like the <hi>Pharisees</hi> of olde, did compasse Sea and Land, to make a proselyte to them-selues, should teach vs, who are Teachers of the Trueth, to bee ashamed to bee lesse <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>iligent in a better Cause, and for a better Master. These are busilie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spersing their <hi>Manuels,</hi> and sowing
<pb n="6" facs="3"/> their <hi>Pople</hi> and <hi>Tares</hi> (lyke that wicked Adversarie) secretlie in the LORD'S Field, to draw men from the Trueth: and why then should no wee bee busie by Voyce, and Writ also, in sowing the good Seed of th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> Word, to keepe Men with the Trueth This hath moved mee to pen thi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>COMPEND OF CONTROVER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIES,</hi> which the simplest may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand clearly, the busiest-employe<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> may peruse frequentlie, and the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kest memorie may retaine easilie: for it is not vnknowne to anie, how our greater Bookes of <hi>Controversies,</hi> penned by their graue and godlie Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, are neglected for the most part, and thought a tedious Taske, once to reade over: but as for this, each on<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> (who hath but the least care to know or byde by the Trueth) may count i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> but an easie exercise, there-by to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>create them-selues at anie occasiona<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> vacancie. And therefore I haue here in put GOD'S Sword chiefelie i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="7" facs="3"/> Man's hand, to maintaine GOD'S Cause, and contented with the most selected places onlie in each head of Doctrine; which for the solide secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Conscience, in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Trueth, and powerfull convincing of seducing Errour, as the Gleanings of <hi>Ephraim</hi> were better than the Vintage of <hi>Abie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer;</hi> so are these few smooth Stones, taken out of the Brooke of the Booke of GOD, more fit for the little <hi>Davids</hi> of the LORD'S People, to sling against the fore-head of brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and blaspemous Errour, than <hi>Saul</hi>'s vnwealdie Armour, or the wearisome weight of cunning forged reasons, and hudge heape of humane testimonies.</p>
   <p>And yet, lest that <hi>Antiquitie</hi> (where-of <hi>Babel</hi>'s brood causeleslie braggeth) should seeme al-together eyther neglected by vs, or not to make for vs, I haue joyned some testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of <hi>Fathers,</hi> that are clearest
<pb n="8" facs="4"/> for vnderstanding, shortest for me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, most punctuall for convincing, and a few of manie, to avoyde te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diousnesse.</p>
   <p>Where-vnto is at last added, for the full triumph of Trueth, the cleare <hi>Confession of our Adversare Partie;</hi> that so out of his owne mouth, the wicked servant may bee condemned, and it may be seene what is the force of prevailing Trueth, even our Enemies being Iudges. And so in summe, that there is no point of <hi>Papall</hi> doctrine, but that <hi>First,</hi> it is against <hi>Scripture: Secondlie,</hi> contrarie to the fayth of the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church: and <hi>Last,</hi> taught, and acknowledged with vs, by the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors in the <hi>Romane</hi> Church it selfe, farre other-wyse than the <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suits</hi> now anie-where professe: such is their bragging of <hi>Vnitie,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the confusion of the speach of those builders of <hi>Babell.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Which paines of mine heere-in,
<pb n="9" facs="4"/> for the profit of others, I haue hūbly dedicated to your religious honour, whome all the godlie who knoweth you, as a Patterne of zeale, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancie, affecteth dearlie, praysetb truelie, admireth justlie, honoureth deservedlie, prayeth for earnestlie, and thanketh the LORD for his rare Graces bestowed vpon you vnfeigned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, to the great good of his <hi>Church,</hi> and your eternall glorie. Where-with also mine heartliest apprecations shal joyntlie concurre, that the bountifull hand of that good GOD, whome in the zeale of His Trueth, ye haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantlie followed, may beape vpon your honour, your most noble, and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicke Husband, and that happie off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spring of those hopefull Oliue Plants, which the Lord hath givē vnto you, all the blessings what-so-ever, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Heaven can afford, or mortalitie may bee capable of.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honours most</hi> humblie devoted, <hi>WILLIAM GVILD.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>