<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONOVRA∣BLE, EXCELLENT∣LY VERTVOVS, and truely Noble, the Ladie VILLIERS, Wife to the wor∣thy, and euery way accomplisht Knight, Sir EDVVARD VILLIERS.</title>
           <author>Harsnett, Adam</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118322_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17457</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4278</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118322</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONOVRA∣BLE, EXCELLENT∣LY VERTVOVS, and truely Noble, the Ladie VILLIERS, Wife to the wor∣thy, and euery way accomplisht Knight, Sir EDVVARD VILLIERS.</title>
                 <author>Harsnett, Adam</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The euer-burning lamps of pietie and deuotion : Kindled by many excellent and heauenly prayers, deuided into the seuerall dayes of the weeke, and other occasions: To auoide which weake man hath continuall cause to retire into himselfe, and humbly confer with Almightie God By I.C</title>
                 <author>I. C.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Hawkins, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>36, 252 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HONOVRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE, EXCELLENT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY VERTVOVS, and truely Noble, the Ladie VILLIERS, Wife to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and euery way accomplisht Knight, Sir EDVVARD VILLIERS.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MADAM,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> Haue not chosen this Text to paint your Vertues, but
<pb facs="3"/>
cure mine owne infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, who desperately ill of a surfet, and giuen ouer by the best Doctor of my fortunes, found no comfort but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiring, and asking counsell of that heauenly, and neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erring Physician, who came into the world to cure all manner of Diseases; which euer intending to publish for the good, I hope, of others, that dare take so much time, to thinke of their sickenesse, and practise a recouerie: I did not long labour for a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication,
<pb facs="3"/>
knowing no La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die (as far be it from arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy, as I know it is from flatterie) that deserueth tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier and realler, to bee a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron (being the subiect of all vertues) then your selfe; your life and manners better commending you, then can my pen, who may expresse my owne Deuotions, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reach yours: Though to those who onely know, or, to speake properly, haue onely seene you, in the colours and attire of the Time, equally
<pb facs="4"/>
grac'd and behau'd with the best of those that affect Court most, it may appeare other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, who neuer seeking Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, but in rough and wilde places, imagine Solitarinesse, and Neglect surer compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of him, then State and Ceremonie: Yet since the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of goodnesse, (as the Sunne in foulest weather) in all Callings, maintaineth her owne perfection, and that in publique and great persons, singularitie and nicenesse of Attire, would rather boast
<pb facs="4"/>
then forward Ʋertue, you wisely and most Religiously, follow that precept of our Sauiours, to wash your face, and put on your Ornaments, that in your chiefe austerity and retiring, you may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare not to proclaime it: For those light braines (full of fault-finding, and as faulty) who may accuse mee to haue giuen good time to so excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Musick, which soundeth well in Ladies eares, when I should haue applyed my selfe to my subiect, in setting out
<pb facs="5"/>
the excellencie, height and reward of prayers: I would hee could vnderstand, there be such <hi>Myrrors</hi> as I heare speake of, and that your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diships practice can better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deliuer these things, then my rude precepts, hauing beene an eye-witnesse, for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of twelue Months, of your inward and holy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collection, from which dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no businesse, nor other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation had power to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw you, to whose holy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spirations, and wonder-working
<pb facs="5"/>
feruour, I leaue your good and great for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, assuring my selfe, your vertue cannot fall so guided, nor your fortune so accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, but that you shall still remaine a sweete-smelling sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to God, and an attrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue and flourishing example to men, amongst whom, though not onely, I chiefly, at least most desirously, remaine</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Vertues honorer and Obseruer: I. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>