<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Tyrell, Anthony</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118810_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14157</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24474</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118810</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Tyrell, Anthony</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A fruitfull sermon preached in Christs-Church the 13. of Iulie. Anno 1589. By Anthony Tyrell sometime a seminarie priest. But by the great mercie of God made a true professor of the Gospel, and preacher of his holy word: conteining an admonition vnto vertue, and a dehortation from vice. Taken by characterye</title>
                 <author>Tyrrell, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 <publisher>Kitson, Abraham.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>78 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was not my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning I must confesse trulie (Good Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Reader) to haue this short and briefe exortation which I made for my priuate exercise to come forth thus in publicke, partlie for that I know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mine owne ignorance and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectiō might seeme a great deale more bold then wise to set forth so simple and slender an action vnto the view of wise and learned men, and partlie least I might be cōdem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of manie, either for want of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion in not iudging of spirituall actions more maturely and soberly, or that I gaped after vaine glorie, which would condemne mee of greater follie among al Godlie mē, but chieflie for that I had no iust or good occasion to induce me to the same. The cause therefore why it
<pb facs="7"/>is come forth, in briefe was this. At the time I made my exhortation publicklie in Christ his Church in London, my wordes were no so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner out of my mouth but a yong youth had penned my Sermon <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batim</hi> by Characterie, an art newly inuented. It was this youthes plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, for the manifesting of his skill in that swift kind of writing, to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish my Sermon in print, yet hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stlie he came vnto me, to enforme me first of the matter. Hee was to me a meere straunger, of whom, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I had vnderstood his intent and purpose, I craued respite to pause of the matter before I would giue my consent. I considered first of my selfe what might be thought or spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, &amp; rather I should be esteemed foolish and vainglorious thā to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue commendation of anie man. Secondlie that the youth did it but to shew his skill and cunning in the
<pb facs="7"/>dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of his owne handewriting, and that it was not simply for the health of soules or spirituall profite of any man, and after I had debated thus to &amp; fro with my selfe, I was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to haue staied his copie, and to haue let all alone. Yet remē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring my selfe, that the workes of the Lorde are wonderful, and that he vseth such means for bringing of thinges to passe which are verie strange and to me vnknowen, That the matter might perhaps be profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto some, that whereas I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but newly cōuerted, &amp; of many suspected for my synceritie in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, it might bee an occasion to giue some farther testimonie then I haue done, and that some thinges it may please the Lord to worke by this simple actiō for the benefite of his Church, which vnto me was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen, I altered my purpose and intent, so far forth as I would not
<pb facs="8"/>be iudge of mine owne doing, but commit it to some other. I did write my letters therefore vnto a graue &amp; learned man, I told him what had happened, and I set downe mine owne mislike, for feare that thinges might not be well &amp; orderly done, subiecting my selfe and my matter vnto his vertuous, wise, and learned censure. It pleased him to returne me my copy again approued: what should I do? should I conceale it? so I might perhaps contristate the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirite. For the comming of it forth might yeelde perhaps some deuout and penitent soule some comfort and profite. For thy sake therefore (good Christian Reader) who so euer thou art, without all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther respect I haue permitted this slēder endeuor of mine to come to light, in hope that although I may be subiect vnto blame of manie, yet I may do some good therby to few.
<pb facs="8"/>To teach them how they ought to detest and hate sinne, to walke wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relie before the face of the Lord, that receiuing the manifold graces &amp; mercies at his hands, they be not vngrateful, &amp; hauing once throwne out the foule spirit of sinne out of their soules by true repētance, they permit him not to returne again by their great fault and negligence, for if they do, what will follow thereof they shall vnderstand by the future discourse. Thus hauing giuen thee a full satisfaction of the cause of the publishing of this present dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, I am to admonish but one other thing, and so I end. He that penned my Sermon as I vttered it in Pulpit, did it most exactly, writing it word for word: Yet when I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that it should come to the print, I did onely peruse it againe, altering some words, but nothing of the matter: and thus much I
<pb facs="9"/>thought good to aduertise, least they that heard me when I pronoū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced it, should thinke it was not the same, but some other. And this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all that I am to say at this time by way of preface, if any spirituall comfort redound thereby vnto thy soule, Gods name be glorified, and it is all that I require: and so I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thee vnto the Lord, &amp; my selfe to thy good prayer. From my chā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in London. 1589. 1. Nouemb.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thy faithfull Brother, and fellow-labourer in Christ,</hi> Anthony Tyrell.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>