<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Gataker, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118307_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13569</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23860</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118307</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Gataker, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The ballance of the sanctuarie : shewing hovv vve must behaue our selues when wee see and behold the people of God in miserie and oppression vnder the tyranny of their enemies. Written by William Teelinck, minister of the Word of God at Midlebrough in Zealand</title>
                 <author>Teellinck, Willem</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Sheffard, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newbery, Nathaniel</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 99, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧ To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Reader, as well the worth of this Worke, as the respect that I deseruedly beare to the Author thereof, both for his singular pietie, and other good parts, hath encouraged mee to commend it to thy careful view, as that whereby thou maist reape no small spirituall profit, if the fault be not thine owne. The Doctrine contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in it is both sound and seasonable, being (as any judicious eye will easily dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne) exceedingly wel fitted to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent times. And <note n="a" place="margin">Pro. 25. 11.</note>
      <hi>a word,</hi> saith <hi>Salomon, spoken in due time, is as apples of gold, with pictures of sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer;</hi> both precious and pleasant▪ True it is, that some truth indeede is neuer out of season; though more seasonable at some times then at other. But yet as true it is, that <note n="b" place="margin">Falsum ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap> dicere licet, at veri aliquid ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere aliquando est utile. <hi>Aug.</hi> ad Gal. c. 2. &amp; de bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> persever. ▪ 16. &amp; in Psal. 5. &amp; Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>br. epist. 23. ex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>. 16. 12.</note> some truth also is at some times alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither unseasonable▪ To propound Gods mercy to an obstinate sinner, or to aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate his wrath to a poore dejected peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, were with those false Prophets, (who deliuered yet nothing, it may be,
<pb facs="3"/>
but truth mis-applied and mis-placed) <note n="c" place="margin">Ezech. 13. 19, 22.</note>
      <hi>to make sad the heart of the humbled,</hi> whom God would haue cheared, and <hi>to strengthen the hand of the wicked,</hi> who ought rather to haue beene humbled; <hi>to slay the soules of such as should not die, and to giue life to such as should not liue.</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">Esa. 22. 12, 13. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Sophocl. Mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ca in luctu intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pestiva narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio. Sirac 22. 6. Et Sophod. Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dip. Tyra. <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap> Apud. Plut. de ethic. vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>. &amp; Sympos. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. l. 1. c.</hi> 5.</note> Matter of mirth and delight, though <note n="e" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Greg. Naz. ad Eunom. l. 1. <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap> Menand. Bonum malum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>it tempore haud datum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>, Eras<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> tempestiva aliqua volupta, nisit, nocet. H. St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ph. <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>. Isocr. ad D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>mon. Et data non apto tempore vina nocem. Ovid. remed. l.</hi> 1.</note> good and honest otherwise, yet is as fish or flesh out of season, neither wholesome nor wel-relished, when God calleth for mourning by judgements either incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent or imminent. As also on the other side, <note n="f" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>Greg. Naz. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>m. l.</hi> 1. Nehem 8. 9. Luk. 15. 31.</note> mourning is no lesse unsauoury, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause unseasonable, when it pleaseth God to giue just occasion of mirth. <note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 9. 15. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 2. 19. 20.</note>
      <hi>The Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the bride-chamber,</hi> saith our Sauiour, <hi>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>t fast so long as the bride-groome is with them: But the time shall come when the bride-groome shall be taken away from them, and then in those dayes shall they fast.</hi>
      <note n="h" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Pind. Pyth. ode 19. <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>. Man. Pal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>ol. ad fil praecept.</hi> 6.</note> Each thing therefore is mostpoo
<pb facs="3"/>
pleasant and most profitable, when it commeth in his due season and good things doe then most good, when they are seasonably administred Now if wee shall but slightly cast our eyes on the rue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and lamentable face of Gods Church in most parts at this present, wee may soone see how seasonably this Discourse commeth abroad. Wherein the Author thereof very learnedly and religiously enstructeth us, how to judge aright of Gods Iudgements either on our selues or others, how to be affected with them, and what use to make of them▪ ministring comfort unto, and confirming the hearts of the afflicted and distressed; urging to compassion with them, and commisera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, those that be yet free; and endeuouring by a due consideration of <note n="i" place="margin">Lament. 3. 37, 38. Esa. 45. 7. Amos 3. 6. 2 Sam. 12. 11. And 16. 10. Iud. 3. 8, 12. And 4. 2. 1 King 11. 14, 23.</note> Gods handy-Worke in all those events that befall both, eyther for good or euil, to bring benefit unto both, as <note n="k" place="margin">Et magis pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candus Deus est in adversis, &amp; minus laedendus in secundis: pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cari quippe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> cum irasci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; laedi non debet cum pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catur. Adversa enim nobis per iracundiam Dei veniunt, secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da per gratiam Sal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ian. de Provid. l. 6.</note> being prouoked to a greater measure of sincere thankfulnesse by the one, and pressed to a more serious renewing of their repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and reformation of life and courses
<pb facs="4"/>
by the other. But I feare to doe thee wrong, by detaining thee too long, from that which thou shalt here finde far more fully and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ffectually discussed and discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, then I can easily relate unto thee. Much race, onely I doubt, the Treatise may haue lost by change of its owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue weede. Few translations haue the happinesse to match their Originals. And each Language hath its peculiar formes and phrases, which in other Tongues can hardly be so fitly or so pregnantly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed. But what may this way be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, the matter (as I hope it is) faithfully expressed may sufficiently countervaile. Which respecting, I shall entreate thee to pardon and passe by the defects that may be in the Translation (wherein what Work-mans hand was used I know not) and so to reade this religious Worke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for thy good, that thou maist not misse of the benefit by the Author there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in intended. Which the Lord grant both to thee and to all others that shall meete with it for his mercies sake, Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ Iesus,
THO: GATAKER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>