<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY DESERVEDLY honour'd, IOHN HELE, of Wembury, Esquire; the great hope of his NAME, and expectation of his COVNTRY.</title>
           <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118102_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13271</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23572</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118102</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY DESERVEDLY honour'd, IOHN HELE, of Wembury, Esquire; the great hope of his NAME, and expectation of his COVNTRY.</title>
                 <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sermons by Humph. Sydenham late fellow of Wadham Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 26, 29-38, 2, 8, 38, 4, 44 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO MY DESERVEDLY honour'd, IOHN HELE, of <hi>Wembury,</hi> Esquire; the great hope of his NAME, and expectation of his COVNTRY.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR;</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His flies not to you for <hi>peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall</hi> barely, and <hi>suruey,</hi> but for <hi>protection;</hi> I want not a a <hi>Reader,</hi> but a <hi>Vindicator;</hi> such a one, as can aswell <hi>iustifie</hi> Jnnocence, as <hi>shrine</hi> it: an <hi>Agent</hi> remark'd, no lesse for <hi>Goodnes,</hi> than for <hi>Power.</hi> And, in this my Appeale to <hi>Worth</hi> and <hi>Iustice,</hi> J sincerely wish, that, whilest I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake your <hi>Charity,</hi> I pull not on you <hi>Enuy,</hi> or <hi>Dishonour;</hi> 'tis not my <hi>intention,</hi> but my <hi>feare.</hi> For, amongst other my weake endeuours
<pb facs="6"/>which haue formerly aduanc'd me to the <hi>vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued applause</hi> of many. <hi>This</hi> had the <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse to displease,</hi> and I thinke it not my <hi>wound,</hi> but my <hi>Glory.</hi> Impartiall discourses are equally <hi>blunt,</hi> and <hi>honest;</hi> and tho' some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, they haue their relish and farewell in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stast, yet that is their <hi>Crowne,</hi> and not their <hi>Fate.</hi> Howeuer, an <hi>affected Stoicisme</hi> I euer loath'd, and not onely as a <hi>Stoicisme,</hi> but as <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</hi> There is nothing so open to contempt and laughter, as a <hi>compos'd sullennesse.</hi> 'Tis true, a natiue roughnes and austeritie of language, I haue pupill'd from my youth, That's <hi>mine owne,</hi> J confesse, but I dote not on it; my <hi>Child</hi> but I lull it not; and therefore, if it sometimes proue way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and offensiue, <hi>Nature</hi> praevaricates, and not <hi>will.</hi> I was neuer yet guiltie of a premedita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted trespasse on mens Names, or Honours; J haue neither so much <hi>time</hi> for rancour, nor <hi>disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> or had I both, I should haue here strangled them for <hi>his</hi> deare memory, to whom I owed, not onely my seruices, but <hi>my selfe.</hi> Hee was nobly your <hi>Associate,</hi> (my honoured Sir) and (for J must still boast in the liuery) my <hi>Master;</hi> nay, my <hi>Patron;</hi> and, what is higher yet, my <hi>friend,</hi> my <hi>vnshaken friend.</hi> These haue so ingag'd me
<pb facs="6"/>both in <hi>Ciuill</hi> and <hi>Religious</hi> bonds, that should I labour to dissolue either by any Reall affront, or discourtesie to <hi>his Tribe,</hi> I were neither <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall man,</hi> nor <hi>Christian;</hi> and yet, loe, I am more than both, a <hi>Diuine;</hi> but, a <hi>saucie one</hi> ('tis ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour'd) and a <hi>Cruell;</hi> a <hi>sordid</hi> also, and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuous;</hi> and, (O my impossible guilt! my vniust calamitie!) a <hi>false one,</hi> and <hi>vnthankfull.</hi> Such Liueries I can weare with as much <hi>patience</hi> as the the former, tho not <hi>triumph;</hi> and yet these, againe are not my <hi>Crosse,</hi> but my <hi>Laurell;</hi> I grow <hi>greene</hi> in the opinion of mine owne <hi>inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, tho'</hi> wither, perhaps, in the Respects of others; who, if they were not so hot as to rauish words vnnaturally, and force them from the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest intentions of the Speaker, they should finde, I am a <hi>Leuite,</hi> still, and not a <hi>Libeller;</hi> and, what I preach'd, was not an <hi>Inuectiue,</hi> but a <hi>Sermon.</hi> Me thinkes, it is neither <hi>Charitie,</hi> nor <hi>Iudgement</hi> in a hearer, to wrest <hi>Diuinity</hi> to the disuantage of his owne honour; 'twas n'ere my Custome to rubbe harshly, on particulars; my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofes were, as they should be, <hi>of sinnes,</hi> and not of <hi>Persons;</hi> and <hi>those</hi> too, ran <hi>generally,</hi> which no Circumstances can reduce to <hi>paticulars,</hi> but where the Parties are either <hi>preiudicate,</hi> or
<pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>guiltie;</hi> And, if any such I met with, (as I hope I did not) let them learne to <hi>reforme,</hi> and not to <hi>censure;</hi> and thanke him for his home-spun ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertisements, who was rather a <hi>Remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi> of their errors, than <hi>a Iudge.</hi> This is the way to rescue their <hi>honour,</hi> and my <hi>innocence;</hi> which, as it hath beene euer taught to magnifie worth in others; so, to presume on yours, that, when you haue read impartially <hi>this sad peece of mine,</hi> you will say that I haue beene a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Seruant to <hi>my</hi> dead friend, and <hi>yours,</hi> whose noble respects to mee, I haue found to suruiue in you; whom, for many solid and materiall fauours, I am captiu'd to obserue, whilest I am</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours most thankfully deuoted, HVM. SYDENHAM.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>