<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Gouge, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118072_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13280</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23584</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118072</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Gouge, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lifes preservative against self-killing. Or, An useful treatise concerning life and self-murder : shewing the kindes, and meanes of them both: the excellency and preservation of the former: the evill, and prevention of the latter. Containing the resolution of manifold cases and questions concerning that subject; with plentifull variety of necessary and usefull observations, and practicall directions, needfull for all Christians. By John Sym minister of Leigh in Essex</title>
                 <author>Sym, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Dawlman (Dolman), Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawne, Luke.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>36, 326, 18 pages, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>OLON,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cic. in orat. pro Rosc. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merin.</note> the wise Law-maker among the <hi>Athenians,</hi> being as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the reason why hee made no penall law against such as should kill their parent, returned this answer, that he supposed no man would doe it. He was thought to doe wisely,<note place="margin">Sapienter fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisse dicitur, cum de co nihil sanxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, quod an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tea commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum nō erat, ne non tam prohibere, quam admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere videre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp;c.</note> in enacting no penalty against that which had not then beene done; lest he might seeme rather to put men in minde to do such a villany, than to restrain the doing of it. But after that wofull experience had given too great evidence of mens impudency in committing this inhumane and unnaturall sinne, most severe lawes were made against the same. In like case hath more woefull experience given more abundant evidence of the more then most in
<pb facs="9"/>humane and unnaturall sinne of <hi>Self murder.</hi> And I suppose, that scarce an age since the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world hath afforded more examples of this desperate inhumanity, than this our present age, and that in all sorts of people, Clergie, Laity, Learned, unlearned, Noble, meane, Rich, poore, Free, bond, Male, Female, young and old. It is therefore high time that the danger of this despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, devilish and damnable practice be plainly and fully set out: which to my best remembrance hath not before this beene performed by a full and just Treatise.<note place="margin">Chrysost. Hom. <hi>84.</hi> in Ioh. <hi>19.</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustin. epist. <hi>61.</hi> alisque in locis. Hier. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in Ion. cap. <hi>1.</hi> Cic. de Fin. bon. &amp; mal. l. <hi>5.</hi> &amp; Somn. Scipion. <hi>Proxima de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inde tenent moesti loca qui sibi le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thum Inson<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes peperere manu &amp;c.</hi> Virg. Aen. 6.</note>
   </p>
   <p>It hath in sundry Sermons preached, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished, and in other printed Treatises, beene spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken against, and the hainousnesse and danger there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, somewhat to the quick, yea and life too, beene declared: and that both by the Ancient <hi>Fathers,</hi> and also by late Divines. Yea Heathen men by the light of nature have damned it to the pit of bell: where they have placed <hi>Self murderers,</hi> making them againe and againe to wish them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves alive on earth, though there, poverty, griefe, shame and all other evills should befall them.</p>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <p>Surely most seasonably is this Treatise here pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished by an Author well fitted and enabled thereto. For he is an expert <hi>Casuist,</hi> by learning and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience so fully accomplished, as he hath for many yeares beene accounted an Oracle where be lives: and by all sorts, resort is made to him to be resolved in intricate doubts. In handling this Treatise, like a skilfull Artist and wise builder,<note place="margin">Luke 6.48.</note> be hath digged deep to lay his foundation sure: he hath begun with life, and artificially distinguished the severall sorts thereof, and shewed the excellency of every sort, that the hainousnesse of taking away so pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious a thing, might thereby be the more aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Many pertinent cases are here and there, yea every where in this Treatise judiciously discussed and resolved. So good is the wine here to be had,<note place="margin">Vino vendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili non opus est hederâ.</note> as there needs no bush to draw thee to it. Let mee but perswade thee to taste it, I shall need to set no greater commendation upon it. I make no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion but that wheresoever it findeth entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it will prove a most soveraigne preserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive against this horrible temptation to <hi>Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murder.</hi> The Lord give such a blessing to it, as it may be a meanes of keeping men from laying
<pb facs="10"/>violent hands upon any, especially upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and of directing and inciting them so to preserve their temporall and spirituall life, as they may bee reserved unto eternall life.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>18. Apr. 1637.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>VVILLIAM GOUGE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>