<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the READER.</title>
           <author>Guild, W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118973_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02352</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12481</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118973</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the READER.</title>
                 <author>Guild, W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ignis fatuus. Or, The elf-fire of purgatorie : Wherein Bellarmine is confuted by arguments both out of the Old and New Testament, and by his owne proofes out of Scriptures and Fathers. Also an annexe to this treatise of purgatorie, concerning the distinction of sinne in mortall and veniall. By M. William Guild, Minister at King-Edvvard</title>
                 <author>Guild, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Budge, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 57, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the READER.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>COVRTEOVS READER,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsidering the grossenesse of this vnwarrantable, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, and couetous conceit of Purgatorie: so that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who in other poynts rests yet in <hi>Babell,</hi> yet in this confesses the vanitie of this prop of <hi>Bethauen.</hi> And perceiuing notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, how peremptorie the Aduersary is, not onely against all opposers to this their fatning Kitchin, by their thundring Sentence; but also a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all those who giues not full assent vnto it, by their condemnatory Decree, adiudging all such to Hells fire for euer. So that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> spares not (as vsurping Gods chaire) determinatly to afflirme,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Bell. l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Purg. c.</hi> 15.</note> that it is such an article of faith, <hi>adeo vt qui non credit Purgatorium esse, ad illud nunquam sit peruenturus, sed in Gehenna sempiterno incendio sit cruciandus.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I thought my paines should not bee bestowed, nor my Penne imployed amisse, if according to my penury, I should contribute somewhat heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to the Lords Treasurie, that they who stand in the olde way of trueth, may bee strengthened,
<pb facs="6"/>
and these who are any one footstep come out of <hi>Babell,</hi> may be helped forward; and if it were no more but as <hi>Augustine</hi> sayes,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Aug. li. de trin. c.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp; cont. Mend. c.</hi> 6.</note> that heretikes may vnderstand, that there are not onely one or two, but many in the campes of orthodox Catholikes, who dare with open face meet them.</p>
   <p>As they then who coupled an Oxe and an Asse together, against that command of God to the Iewes, and sowe their field with diuers seeds: or as the children of those of the Captiuitie, spake partly in the Iewish Language, and partly in the Language of <hi>Ammon</hi> and <hi>Ashdoa:</hi> Euen so, how that false Prophet, who hath borrowed likewise the semblance of the Lambs hornes, calling him his Vicar (that vnder that he might the more craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily vent the speech of the Dragons tongue, whose mouth hee is, and whose priuiledge he claimes <note n="*" place="margin">Math. 4.9.</note>.) How he (I say) hath vnequally yoked, monstrously mixed, vniustly coupled, and impiously matched, that matchlesse, free, full, and perfect satisfaction of Christs, with humane satisfactions in an imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary fire, which Auarice hath hatched, Ignorance fosters, and Crueltie with fire and faggot main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines: Loe here, Courteous and charitable Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, presented to thy view.</p>
   <p>As <hi>Dauid</hi> then came against <hi>Goliath,</hi> armed with the Name of the Lord, when that Gyant stood betweene the two Hostes, and was a terrour to the Army of Israel: So for consternation like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise of this Monster, which they situate likewise betweene the place of the damned and glorified, to the terrour of simple soules, armed with that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, which experimentally hath euer giuen vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie both in the head and members, (and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with therefore we are bidden be girt continually)<note place="margin">Ephes. 6.</note>
      <pb facs="6"/>
euen with that Sling and Sword of the Spirit, doe we chiefly meane to come against this grand Errour of Poperie, the very <hi>Diana</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> that by the very presence of the Arke of God set vp, that Idoll <hi>Dagon</hi> may fall to the ground.</p>
   <p>Next, that <hi>Goliahs</hi> head after his ouerthrow, may bee cut off with his owne Sword: Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments God willing of their owne great Warriour <hi>Bellarmines,</hi> (though adduced by him for another purpose, whether taken from Fathers or Reason) shall bee clearely drawne foorth, as <hi>Sauls</hi> Sword, or <hi>Hamans</hi> Halter, to kill and strangle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues.</p>
   <p>And last, their proofes for Purgatorie, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially such as they vpbraid vs with, out of wrested and wronged Scripture, wee shall faithfully, God willing, relate, as they are set downe in their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said Champion, (whom cheefely I oppugne) and punctually shall answere: so that they shall bee seene to bee like short stubble, that was gathered vpon necessitie by those vnder <hi>Pharaohs</hi> bondage, who otherwise could not get long straw to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues.</p>
   <p>And to instance the same here in one particular: what will they not bring to proone Purgatorie? when <hi>Bellarmine</hi> brings for it,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Bell. l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Purg. c.</hi> 14.</note>
      <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.27. and sayes, that that place is a notable proofe of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory; which speakes of a fearefull looking for of iudgement, and fiery indignation, which shall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure the aduersaries; and wherein the cleare words, and consent of all antiquitie doth shew, that Gods aduersaries are spoken of, and not his friends, who shall bee deuoured, and not purged, and whom fearefull damnation, and consuming wrath abides; which is not the lot nor expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="7"/>
of the godly, neither heere nor hence: but theirs of whom the Apostle speakes clearly of; to wit, who treads the Sonne of God vnder foot, and hath counted the blood of the Couenant an vnho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thing, and done despite to the Spirit of Grace. So that such cleare places speaking of the wicked, and of hell, he will impudently bring to speake of the godly, and of Purgatory.</p>
   <p>Accept then (courteous Reader) with a chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table hand, what with a humble one I present, and proue not a censorious Waspe, but a hony-gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Bee; and that God and common Sauiour of ours, who gaue approbation to the widowes mite, and will not suffer vnrequited a cup of cold water giuen in his Name, giue thee a like minde, and blesse the perusall of this, and of all other helps to thy edification.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in the Lord,</hi> W. GVILD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>