<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To al Christians, zealous in holy Prayers.</title>
           <author>Simson, Patrick</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1181_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09974</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2023.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1181</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To al Christians, zealous in holy Prayers.</title>
                 <author>Simson, Patrick</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Maister Bezaes houshold prayers translated out of French into English</title>
                 <author>Bèze, Théodore de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Barnes, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>368 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
      <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To al Christians, zealous in holy Prayers.</head>
   <epigraph>
      <q>
         <bibl>
            <hi>Luke</hi> 21.</bibl>
         <p>The Kingdome of God is at hand, watch therfore, praying at all times.</p>
      </q>
   </epigraph>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F wee are indued with the true knowlege of our estate, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, as also, the efficacie of holy prayers, wee shoulde not neede to be aduertised often, to present our selues before God, to offer vnto him our vowes, and to beseech his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loue, or dilection, for
<pb facs="7"/>guiding vs, by his good spirit, vnto the light of his trueth, to encrease in our heartes, faith, loue, constancie, humilitie, and other his heauenly giftes, to forgiue vs our debts, to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the corruptions of our nature, to clothe vs with his spirituall armour, against the assaults of the diuel, the world &amp; the flesh, to prouide for our necessities, to preserue vs from infinite dangers, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe vs round about: to be short, to graunt vs his holie spirite, to guide the whole course of our life, to the glorie of his name, and the peace and saluation of our owne soules. For, he who hath not a feeling
<pb facs="7"/>of the great want of all these graces, or blessings, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, the necessitie of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers vnto God, for obtaining the same, knoweth not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, but is senslesse and voyd of all feeling. By prayer wee blesse God for his goodnesse, power, wisedome, iustice, and mercy towardes vs: because of our prayers, he blesseth vs, in doing vs good, and distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting his benefites amongest vs: it is vnto vs, as the soule of our soules: for that prayer quickeneth our affections, and lifteth vppe our heartes vnto heauen; which otherwise wold be dead in sinnes and trespas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, by following the vanities
<pb facs="8"/>of this wicked world. Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is as it were the key which openeth vnto vs the treasury of our heauenly Father, as faith is the hand, laying holde vpon those sure and perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent possessions of eternall life, the desire whereof, should cause vs continually to pray vnto, and feruently to loue God. Prayer maketh, that in the miseries of this life, wee comfort our selues, by looking for the benefites of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God. Prayer refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth vs through the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his gracious promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, which confirme vs in the same, and of the blessings al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready receiued at his hands,
<pb facs="8"/>which moue vs in our necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to hope for the like, and wait for it, with al patience. It augmenteth in vs, a desire to be conioyned with him, throgh our Lorde Iesus Christ, in whome all our good doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist. It cheereth vs in those workes, which the holy ghost worketh in vs, &amp; by vs, yeeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a sweet smell to our souls, and is moreouer vnto vs, as a strong Tower, and most assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red fortresse, against all that might astonish vs, in this our earthly habitation: yea which is more, prayer doth somtimes stand vs insteede, to obtaine of Almighty God, most eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent testimonies of his glorie,
<pb facs="9"/>in matters supernaturall, which our reason should iudge impossible, as it befell vnto <hi>Moses,</hi> praying for the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory of the Israelites, against the Amalekites: to <hi>Ioshuah</hi> when at his praier, the course of the Sunne was stayed: to <hi>Elias,</hi> bringing fire down from heauen, and to <hi>Ezechias</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored to helth after sentence given of his death: not that wee should simply attribute so great and profitable effects to the woorke of prayer: but to the goodnesse, loue, power, and counsell of God, who worketh so, and by such meanes as hee pleaseth in his creatures: and of his free mercie, crowneth
<pb facs="9"/>the prayers of his elect with rewardes, and with grace for grace. These therefore are the fruits and benefites we are to looke for from our good god and father, when reposing our selues vpon his loue in Christ, and with humble and penitent hearts, wee doe prostrate our selues before his face, to san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie his name, crauing his mercie, and beseeching him to blesse vs, teach and guide vs as his children, to beleeue his word, euen as he whom we cal vpon, doth desire our good, bicause he loueth vs, may giue vnto vs that we aske, because he is almighty: and is willing to heare vs, for his Sonnes
<pb facs="10"/>sake, because hee hath so pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised. But it is also most true, that acording to his wisdome, he knoweth the time and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient meanes, to let vs ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enioy the efficacie of our praiers. Let vs perseuer, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly asking those things which are to his glorie, and hee will not faile to helpe vs in all our necessities. Wee are moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to note, that it is not the sound of the lippes which the Lord requireth of vs, vnlesse the same be also guided with the holy affections of the soule: for he harkneth rather to the heart than to the voyce, and giueth to vs openly that which he seeth vs in secret to desire
<pb facs="10"/>with our affections mortified in his sight. Therefore wee must (praying carefully) lift vppe our heartes with a true zeale to GOD, banishing out all other thoughts, aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning Sathan with all his baites, opening our harts, that our Heauenly Father may thereinto infuse and powre downe his blessings. Neyther ought our prayer to bee bare or naked, but conioyned with reading, and meditation of Gods holy worde, as also fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in all goodnesse.</p>
   <p>But alas, if it bee most true, that in all our exercises of piety wee be neuer able to seperate our selues from our
<pb facs="11"/>selues, but that our corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wil stil euidently appeare, it is sure, the same will especially befall vs, when wee prepare our selues to pray vnto God, and frame our petitions, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will: for besides that the diuel doth at al times lie in waite, to seduce vs, so doeth hee, especially, at such times, seeke to creepe into our minds, to diuert our thoughts elsewhere, that they may bee polluted with many blemishes: notwithstanding, that they of themselues, sufficiently goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stray: yea our vanitie, imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and coldnesse, doeth many wayes bewray it selfe, that we may well say, in one
<pb facs="11"/>word: no man prayeth right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but he, whose mouth and minde Christ doth direct with his spirit. And therefore hath he deliuered vnto vs, a sacred forme, for all holy prayers, in that prayer which is vsually termed, <hi>The Lords Prayer,</hi> wherein, hee hath set downe, the perfect rule, whereby, we may rightly forme our petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and keepe them within their bounds: that is, <hi>the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, &amp; our saluation.</hi> And this are wee dilligently to note, as being assured, that so we shall be heard, albeit our frailty do hinder vs, from pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing with that zeale, feeling, and feruency of faith, which
<pb facs="12"/>true prayer doth require. Let vs winne from our selues so much as wee may, calling to minde, for our comfort, that we do offer our prayers, to the father, in the name of his wel-beloued sonne, and by his own mouth, couered with his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse: who therefore will accept of them, according to his promise, but withall, let vs also remember, that such, who vse many times to say, <hi>O Lord help vs,</hi> do not, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding, thereby obtaine saluation: but they, who doe his will, and to that end, doth he command vs, that we haue his word dwelling peaceably in our hearts, that we may be
<pb facs="12"/>ready to performe euery good worke.</p>
   <p>These things, therefore, being by God conioyned vnto prayer, let vs take great heed, that wee seperate them not, considering, that by the same, we conuerse with our father which is in heauen, and so en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy, the fulnesse of his bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings: for whensoeuer we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our eyes, or our eares, to those things, which he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vnto vs, in the holy scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, hee speaketh vnto vs, and calling vpon his name, we speake vnto him.</p>
   <p>Moreouer, in asmuch as, naturally wee are but little inclined, or rather vtterly
<pb facs="13"/>carelesse, of these spirituall exercises, it will not be amisse, if we restraine our selues, to praier, at certaine houres of the day: not for superstition, but to withstand our slouth, slackenesse, and other worldly matters, which otherwise might induce vs, to ouerslippe diuerse dayes, without any practise of this duetie. <hi>Dauid</hi> bearing vppon his shoulders the burden of a great King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, prayed, morning, at noone, and at night: yea seauen times a day, did he sing prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses to God, day and night me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating in his Lawe. Nowe therefore (gentle Readers) feeling my self toward the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining
<pb facs="13"/>euening of my dayes, with a taste of so many solide, and permanent ioyes, as are daily to be found in prayer: &amp; withall, being inflamed with a desire, to finish the rest of my course, in this sweete labour, which I finde to be accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, with so large a recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, I haue here formed for my selfe, and for any other, that list to reade it, this small mannell, of holy, short, and familiar prayers, grounded vpon the texts of scriptures, such as are indeed, to instruct, comfort, and make vs perfect, in faith, loue, constancy, and to be short, in all christian life. Be of good cheere then, (all
<pb facs="14"/>godly soules) and let vs v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite all our petitions, in this so deuoute, and profitable an exercise, of all true faithfull people. Let vs pray, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate, if not incessantly, yet at the least, dayly at certaine set houres, and as often as wee may, as well in the congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as in our families, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and euening amongst our houshold, as also in our secret chambers. Thus shall wee with our lippes, vpon the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars of our hearts, offer vp, many acceptable sacrifices of sweete sauor before his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, whereof, the benefite will redound to our selues, in that God will blesse vs, in our
<pb facs="14"/>vocations, workes, and labors. Oh, how happy shall these men then be, whom the Lord shall finde thus watching, and praying! for they shall depart vnto him in peace, in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of his glory; which grace, God graunt vnto vs all. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>