<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE NOBLY-INGENIOUS, EDVVARD SEYMOVR, Esquire. This.</title>
           <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118116_Fr7_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13272</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23573</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118116</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE NOBLY-INGENIOUS, EDVVARD SEYMOVR, Esquire. This.</title>
                 <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sermons vpon solemne occasions : preached in severall auditories. By Humphrey Sydenham, rector of Pokington in Somerset</title>
                 <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Robinson, Humphrey</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 240, 251-316, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="122"/>
   <pb facs="122"/>
   <head>TO THE NOBLY-INGENIOUS, EDVVARD SEYMOVR, Esquire. <hi>This.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Is acriticall age we live in, where <hi>Divines</hi> and <hi>Poets</hi> have alike fate and misery, most men frequenting <hi>Churches</hi> as they doe <hi>Theaters,</hi> either to <hi>clap</hi> or <hi>hisse;</hi> and it is with the <hi>Auditors</hi> of the one, as with the <hi>Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> of the other; sometimes they bestow their <hi>Laurell,</hi> sometimes their <hi>Thistle;</hi> Applause sometimes, sometimes censure. Vnhappy Creatures that we are to be thus fed with <hi>Aire,</hi> as if we no longer liv'd <hi>by the Spirit of God,</hi> but the <hi>breath of the people.</hi> And if this Ayre were either <hi>pure or temperate,</hi> it were a passable calamity; but it is for the most part, <hi>poyson'd</hi> and <hi>corrupt.</hi> Loose men breath their rottennesse and filth upon us; and it is not <hi>wit</hi> (for sooth) nor <hi>bravery,</hi> except it be drivell'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Priest,</hi> whom they all besmeare with calumny, and rake the very kennell for dirt to fling at him, as if he were the only prodigy of the times, S. <hi>Paul's</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> , or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> , the very <hi>dung of the world,</hi>
      <note place="margin"> 1 Cor. 4.</note> and the <hi>off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scouring of all things unto this day.</hi> This is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon misery of our <hi>Tribe,</hi> and it was <hi>mine,</hi> in opening the
<pb facs="123"/>
      <hi>folly</hi> of this <hi>Pseudo-Prophet;</hi> which hit so unhappily with the temper of those <hi>holy Monopolizers</hi> (which pretend so much to be the <hi>only men of the Spirit</hi>) that the <hi>Catharist</hi> was up in Armes, and <hi>Demetrius,</hi> and the Zealous <hi>Crafts-men</hi> were about mine eares; who put me (without mercy) to the push of their <hi>Pike,</hi> and <hi>shot their</hi> poyson'd <hi>Arrowes,</hi> even <hi>bitter words against me,</hi> such as malice could only sharpen, or falsehood levell. But notwithstanding the <hi>Spirit of Rabshakeh,</hi> and the venome of those <hi>sanctified Raylers,</hi> I wanted not my Propugners amongst the impartially judicious, both Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines and Layicks; and with the latter of these, more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently, your selfe. And had I had no more, it was enough that there was <hi>Seymour</hi> in it, a name that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volves <hi>Nobility,</hi> and the better part of <hi>it, Vertue;</hi> and the better part of <hi>vertue, humility</hi> and <hi>courtesie,</hi> and all these temper'd in you with a religious observance of the <hi>Rites</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> you live in; so that you are not transported with change and novelty; not apt to be misted with any <hi>false light</hi> of the times, not with the <hi>Ignis fatuus</hi> of our <hi>Prophet</hi> here, no <hi>Proselyte</hi> of <hi>Schisme</hi> or <hi>Innovation,</hi> but a man fast to your selfe, constant and resolv'd in all your actions; which is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent temper to make a <hi>Christian</hi> of, and a sure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to build <hi>true friendship</hi> on, especially in this <hi>age of words,</hi> where <hi>Integrity</hi> and <hi>Goodnesse</hi> are so rarely met with, by me (I am sure).</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your unhappy, but true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted Servant, HVM. SYDENHAM.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>