<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TOMY HIGHLY HONOUR'D FRIEND Sr. JOHN STAVVELL, Knight of the BATH, THIS.</title>
           <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118116_Fr4_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13272</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23573</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118116</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TOMY HIGHLY HONOUR'D FRIEND Sr. JOHN STAVVELL, Knight of the BATH, THIS.</title>
                 <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sermons vpon solemne occasions : preached in severall auditories. By Humphrey Sydenham, rector of Pokington in Somerset</title>
                 <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Robinson, Humphrey</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 240, 251-316, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="67"/>
   <pb n="117" facs="67"/>
   <head>TOMY HIGHLY HONOUR'D FRIEND Sr. JOHN STAVVELL, <hi>Knight of the</hi> BATH, THIS.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>UST promises are just debts,</hi> and <hi>debts</hi> (though delayed) ever come <hi>acceptably,</hi> if they come with <hi>advantage.</hi> I long since promised you a <hi>transcript</hi> of this <hi>Sermon</hi> (which was the <hi>Principall</hi>) and now I send it you with a <hi>Dedication</hi> (which is the <hi>Interest;</hi>) and such an <hi>Interest,</hi> I presume, you will not refuse, though presented by the hand of your <hi>poore Servant.</hi> Now it is yours indeed, but it is yours chiefly to <hi>peruse,</hi> not to <hi>protect;</hi> for such a <hi>subject</hi> will looke above all <hi>humane
<pb facs="68"/> Patronage,</hi> there being nothing fit either to <hi>owne</hi> or <hi>protect Omnipotence,</hi> but <hi>GOD</hi> himselfe; to whom I consecrate both <hi>my selfe</hi> and <hi>It.</hi> And yet, though the <hi>subject</hi> be <hi>Sacred,</hi> and points directly at the <hi>Creator</hi> of us all, yet there <hi>may be</hi> (and are by all likelihood) <hi>frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> in the <hi>discourse;</hi> which as they will meete with some <hi>cavill</hi> or <hi>opposition,</hi> so they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a <hi>Bulwarke</hi> and <hi>defence</hi> also, and from whom more properly, than from a <hi>Great man!</hi> who both in <hi>place</hi> and <hi>nature</hi> is nearest to his <hi>God</hi> (if <hi>Goodnesse,</hi> as it ought, shake hands with <hi>Greatnesse;</hi>) and of that no man dispaires in a <hi>Noble disposition,</hi> where but to <hi>questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> vertue, were to <hi>profane</hi> it. Your Countrey hath often tasted of the <hi>Greatnesse</hi> of your <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> and where there is <hi>Spirit,</hi> truely there must be something that is <hi>divine</hi> also; which cannot but speake your <hi>Goodnesse</hi> without controule, from <hi>me</hi> especially,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your old, and (if you please to preserve him) constant Servant, HVM. SYDENHAM.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>