<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Swinburne, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118058_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13252</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23547</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118058</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Swinburne, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe treatise of testaments and last willes : very profitable to be vnderstoode of all the subiects of this realme of England, (desirous to know, whether, whereof, and how, they may make their testaments: and by what meanes the same may be effected or hindered,) and no lesse delightfull, aswell for the rarenes of the worke, as for the easines of the stile, and method: compiled of such lawes ecclesiasticall and ciuill, as be not repugnant to the lawes, customes, or statutes of this realme, nor derogatorie to the prerogatiue royall. In which treatise also are inserted diuers statutes of this land, together with mention of sundrie customes, aswell general as particular, not impertinent thereunto: besides diuers marginall notes, and quotations not to be neglected, especially of Iustinianists, or young students of the ciuil law: vvith two tables, the one analyticall ... the other alphabeticall ... By the industrie of Henrie Swinburn, Bachelar of the Ciuill Lawe</title>
                 <author>Swinburne, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 <publisher>Windet, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 293, 14 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Reat and wonderful is the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the manifolde writers of the Ciuill and Ecclesiasticall lawes, and so huge is the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of their sundrie sorts of bookes; as lectures, councels, tracts, decisions, questions, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations, repetitions, cautels, clausules, common opinions, singulars, contradictions, concordances, methodes, summes, practickes, tables, repertories, and bookes of other kindes (apparant mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of their endlesse and inuincible labours) that in my conceite, it is impossible for any one man to read ouer the hundred part of their works, though liuing an hundred yeeres hee did intende none other worke. Wherfore by the publishing of this testamentarie trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, I may be thought to powre water into the Sea, to carrie owles to Athens, and to trouble the reader with a matter altogether needlesse and superfluous: But yet for all this, in case this one litle booke may serue in steed of many great volumes; then I hope that in the equal iudgement of such as be indifferently affected, the same is rather to be admitted as commodious, then reiected as superfluous.</p>
   <p>And nowe, beleeue me, (gentle reader) I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired earnestly and endeuoured carefully (according
<pb facs="9"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="9"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="10"/> to the measure of such slender skil as God hath vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safed me, and as conuenient leisure from other occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of needfull profite and healthfull disport haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted,) that this one litle booke which heere I do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent vnto thy courteous handes, may stand in steed of many bigger bookes.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The causes wherefore the Author of this booke vndertooke this worke.</note>For whereas by the supreme authoritie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiolable power of the high court of Parliament, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the xxv. yeere<note n="a)" place="margin">Stat. H. 8. an. 25. c. 19.</note> of the reigne of the most renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med King of this lande <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight, of famous and happie memorie: It was enacted and established (amongest other Statutes then made, and since that time reuiued in the first yeere of her Maiesties<note n="b)" place="margin">Stat. Eliz. an. 1. c. 1.</note> most gracious reigne that nowe is) that such lawes ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticall being then alreadie made, which bee not hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or preiudiciall to the prerogatiue roiall, nor repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the lawes, statutes, and customes of this Realme, shall still be vsed and executed as they were before the making of that acte, vntill such time as they were viewed, searched, or otherwise ordred or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by two and thirtie persons, or the more part of them, according to the tenour, fourme and effect of the saide acte: Which lawes so established, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiued, and confirmed, and not without good cause, and deepe consideration (in diuerse statutes, made during the reignes as well of the saide most noble king <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> the eight<note n="c)" place="margin">Stat. H. 8. an. 27. c. 20. &amp; an. 32. c. 7.</note>, as of the most godly prince <hi>Edwarde</hi> the sixt<note n="d)" place="margin">Stat. Ed. 6. an. 2. c. 13.</note>, are termed or intituled, for the more honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble account thereof, with the reuerend and sacred name of <hi>the Kinges ecclesiasticall lawes:</hi> Like as in those countries and Churches of <hi>Germanie,</hi> which haue receiued the Gospell, the Canon lawe is admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and obserued so farre foorth, as it is not repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb facs="10"/> to the newe Testament<note n="e)" place="margin">Schuediwinus Tracte de nuptijs. part. 4. tit. d diuort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. n. 13 fol. 48.</note>, and is at this day the Ecclesiasticall law of their consistories.</p>
   <p>Whereas also the Ciuill law euer since the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall law was made, had beene deemed and iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for part and parcell of the same Ecclesiasticall law, in cases wherein it dooth not differ from the same<note n="f)" place="margin">c. 1. de no. op. num. c. clerici. de iud. extra c. f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>n auditorium. dist. 10. §. si vero ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum. in Auth. vt clerici apud. propr. Episco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>: For where these two lawes be not contrarie, the one is suppletorie of the other, and being mutually incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated doo both make one bodie<note n="g)" place="margin">Panor. in d. c. 1. de no. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>p. num. Valquius. de success. creat. lib. 3. §. 26. n. 70. Benedict. Cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a. Thesaur. com. op. verb. leges. fol. (mihi) 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>3. n. 23.</note>, otherwise the Ciuill law being contradicted by the Ecclesiastical law, ought to be silent in the Ecclesiasticall court<note n="h)" place="margin">d. c. 1. de no. op. nun. gloss. in c. 2. de arb. lib. 6. Arc. in d. c. clerici de iudic. extra. quae sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentia communiter approbatur, teste Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedict. Capra. vbi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>pra</note>.</p>
   <p>And forasmuch as these foresaide lawes, haue not as yet beene viewed, searched, or otherwise ordered or determined by xxxij. persons, or the more part of them, according to the forme and effect of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saide act of Parliament: which thing neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse hath beene (I confesse) attempted<note n="i)" place="margin">Vide licet, per Gualt. Haddon, legum Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem consul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. (&amp; omnium quos vnquā tulit Anglia legistarū dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>simum. lib. de Reformatione legum ecclesiastic.</note>, yet not so sully effected, but may bee and that shortly if God vouchsafe prosperous successe to that notable and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable worke of that graue and learned man <hi>Doctor Percie,</hi> now well towardes accomplishment.) By oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of which defect of the viewe, examination, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or determination of the saide two and thirtie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, those Ciuill and Ecclesiasticall lawes testamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie not repugnant to the lawes, statutes and customes of this Realme, are yet (euen as hither to they haue beene) scattered and dispersed here and there, and secretly hidden from the subiects of this realme in corners of many bookes of straunge Countries, and forreine language, intangled also and incombred with long dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses of farre different argument, and no lesse num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of lawes vtterly impertinent to the gouernment of this common wealth: so that the knowledge thereof
<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="11"/> fewe in comparison of the rest, whom otherwise I might happily benefite: Albeit I had once begunne, and laid the foundation of the whole tract, in such tearmes as I found it deliuered by others, preferring publique commoditie before particular vtilitie, or mine owne commendation (in case it be lesse commendable, rather to seeke the benefite of the common wealth, then to hunt after priuate praise) I did easily alter my former purpose.</p>
   <p>That lawes transformed from their natural shape, must needs in some sort be either damnified or disgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, I do not thinke to be perpetually true: But if it be a thing so necessarily incident to all translations, that it cannot be auoided, it ought therefore to be the rather tolerated.</p>
   <p>Sufficeth it therefore these Latin Iustinianists, that those marginall notes especially proper to their studies, be left in Latin: The rest, because it belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to all, meete it is that it be written in such a language, as may be vnderstood of all.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Inter causam sinalem &amp; impulsiuam quid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest praeclare Tira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quellus in regulam cessante causa, &amp;c. limitac. prima.</note>Thus (courteous reader) I haue discoursed vnto thee, the end wherefore I vndertooke this labour, the cause which mooued me so to do, and wherefore I haue published the same in the vulgare tongue. Now it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth that I craue thy fauourable acceptance of my good will, and endeuour, which if thou shalt vouchsafe to bestow, I shall not onely thinke my selfe sufficiently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compensed but greatly enriched.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine most willingly to his vttermost power, <hi>Henry Swinburne.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>