<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Honora∣ble, and vertuous LADIE, the Ladie Anne Harington.</title>
           <author>T., D.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118789_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14087</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24396</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118789</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Honora∣ble, and vertuous LADIE, the Ladie Anne Harington.</title>
                 <author>T., D.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Essaies politicke, and morall. By D.T. Gent</title>
                 <author>D. T. (Daniel Tuvill)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Matthew</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 130, 2 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and vertuous LADIE, the Ladie <hi>Anne Harington.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adam,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>The desire I had to manifest my seruicea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble affection towards your Honour in outwarde Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, hath on such idle houres, as remained free to mee from your imployments, begot this young and tender Infant; whom I presum'd, vpon his birth (beeing yet an <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brio</hi> in his fathers braine) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vote, &amp; consecrate wholly to your honourable Selfe, as to the chiefe,
<pb facs="3"/>and finall end of his beeing. His ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie is not of the weakest: and therefore, howsoeuer hee may now seeme altogether vnfashion'd, I make no doubt, but by conversing with your Ladiship (whose bosome the hand of heauen hath so richlie furnisht with all exemplary ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, that from among so many, Wisdome selected you, to be the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernesse, from whom the Princely issue of a royall bed might receiue instruction) his ruder ignorance may be reduced to a better forme. <hi>Essaies</hi> are the things hee vttereth. His yeeres deny him that length of breath, which should enable him to holde out in a continued, and long discourse. My selfe haue imparted vnto him, part of that beauty and
<pb facs="3"/>Perfection, which Art, &amp; Nature hath bestowed on me. Such therfore as he is, I present him to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours view; who, I hope, will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorde him such worthy entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as may hold some euen corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spondencie, with his desires, as well as his deserts. And so in the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blest degree of service, that either loue, or dutifull observance can imagine, I kisse your Honourable handes; desirous of nothing more, then alwaies to be reputed,</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Madam,</salute>
      <signed>Your Honors most affectionate seruant, <hi>D. T.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>