<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR ROBERT SIDNEY Lord Viscount Lisle, and Earle of Leicester: Grace and peace from God the Father, through our mer∣cifull Redeemer Christ Iesus.</title>
           <author>Sweeper, Walter</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118005_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B16007</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23527</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118005</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR ROBERT SIDNEY Lord Viscount Lisle, and Earle of Leicester: Grace and peace from God the Father, through our mer∣cifull Redeemer Christ Iesus.</title>
                 <author>Sweeper, Walter</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Israels redemption by Christ : Wherein is confuted the Arminian vniuersall redemption</title>
                 <author>Sweeper, Walter</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 59, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR ROBERT SIDNEY Lord Viscount <hi>Lisle,</hi> and Earle of <hi>Leicester:</hi> Grace and peace from God the Father, through our mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Redeemer Christ Iesus.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>My Lord,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> First intended to haue dedicated this little Treatise of <hi>Israels re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption by Christ,</hi> to your truly noble Sister the late deceased Countesse of <hi>Pembrock,</hi> in token of my thankfulnesse for her conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall fauours shewed me euer since she and my Lord her husband pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced me in <hi>Bewdly,</hi> where she first drew in her happie breath; which place of her birth is styled by an ancient Poet, <hi>Delitium rerum, bellus locus.</hi> To this your Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Sister I may with the change of the last word apply the olde verse penned to the praise of the Empresse <hi>Matildis; Ortu magna, viro maior, ter maxima prole, Hic iacet Henrici, filia, sponsa, parens.</hi> She was the daughter of the truly noble, wise and religious Lord President of <hi>Wales</hi> Sir <hi>Henrie Sidney;</hi> Wise of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly spirited and religiously affected the late Lord <hi>Henry</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/> Earle of <hi>Pembrock</hi> of happie memory, whose zeale and sincere loue to the truth, appeared in his life and death, as the Bishop of <hi>Sarum</hi> told vs at his funerall; She was the mother of two great Lords and Peeres of this Realme, the Earles of <hi>Pembrock</hi> and <hi>Mountgomery;</hi> lastly, she was Sister to that valorous learned Knight Sir <hi>Philip Sidney, Delitiae mundi,</hi> shedding his blood for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Gospell, <hi>Hunc tantum terris ostendent fata, nec vltra esse sinent;</hi> and Sister to you (my Lord) who haue so well deserued by your seruices of warre and of peace, of your country and neighbour states abroad, imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating your noble Vncle the late Lord <hi>Robert Dudley</hi> Earle of <hi>Leicester,</hi> and far excelling the two <hi>Simons de Monte forti,</hi> long since Earles of the same place. Your noble Sister (if we respect the rare endowments of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture art, learning humane and diuine, accompanied with a most heroicall spirit) doth adde a true lustre to all your Honours. Now that the Lord hath taken her away, I thought good to dedicate to your Honour this litle Book, treating of the vertue and efficacie of Christs death, and confuting the Vniuersall Redemption of the Arminians; humbly beseeching your Lordship in your noble Sisters stead to patronize it; which shall cause the Author e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to pray for your inward and outward happinesse in Christ. And thus humbly taking my leaue, I shall still rest at</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships seruice and command, Walter Sweeper.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>