<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A preface before the Sermon.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118869_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17866</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4533</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118869</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A preface before the Sermon.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise upon death : first publickly delivered in a funerall sermon, anno Dom. 1630. And since enlarged By N.C. Preacher of Gods word in Scotland at Kilmacolme in the baronie of Renfrew</title>
                 <author>Campbell, Ninian</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Wilson, John 3.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Young (Junius), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>128 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>A preface before the Sermon.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>E are all here conveened this day to performe the last Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian duties to a respected and worthy Baron, with his honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Lady, who both have lived amongst you in this land, and whose embalmed corps, both yee now honour with your mourning presence, and happy farewell to their grave. I am here designed to put you all in minde by this premeditate speech, that the next case shall be assuredly ours, and perhaps when we think least of it. Therefore that I may acquaint these who need information in this point with the nature and matter of such exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, let them remember with me that there are two sorts of funer all sermons, approved and authorized by our reformed churches in Europe: The first whereof, I call, for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders sake, <hi>Encomiastick,</hi> or <hi>Scholastick,</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>
because it is spent in the praise of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funct, and only used in schooles, colledges, academies, and universities, by the most learned; And this is ordinarily enriched with pleasant varietie of strange lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, lively lights of powerfull or ato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, fertile inventions of alluring poesie, great subtilties of solid Philosophie, grave sentences of venerable fathers, manifold examples of famous histories, ancient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes of memorable peoples and nations; and in a word, with all the ornaments of humane wit, learning, eloquence. Which howbeit I might borrow for a while, yet I lay them down at the feet of Jesus, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing sent hither not by man, but by God, whose interpreter and ambassadour I am, I prefer before them the smooth words of <hi>Moses,</hi> the stately of <hi>Esay,</hi> the royall of <hi>David,</hi> the wise of <hi>Salomon,</hi> the eloquent of saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and the ravishing of saint <hi>John,</hi> with the rest of divine writers, Gods pen-men, out of whose inexhausted treasurie of heavenly consolation, and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb facs="10"/>
knowledge, I wish to be furnished with the secret preparation of the san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie, and to be accompanied with the full power and evidence of the spirit of my God. For there is another second sort of funerall sermons, which I call <hi>Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stick,</hi> or popular, viz. when the judicious and religious preacher, only for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction and edification of the living, frequently assembled at burials, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly desiring at such dolefull spectacles to be rejoyced in the spirit of their mindes, taketh some convenient portion of scripture, and handleth it with pietie, discretion, moderation, to his private con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation, the edification of his hearers, and the exaltation of the most high name of God. So that having no other ends but these three, and taking God to be my wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse that I abhor all religious or rather superstitious worship given to the dead, and being naturally obliged to come here, and oftentimes requested by my near and dear friends, yea abundantly warranted
<pb facs="10"/>
by these who have the prioritie of place in church government above me, and as it seemeth by your favourable silence, and Christian attention, invited to speak, I have purposed by the speciall concurrence, and assistance of the spirit of my God, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver unto you a brief meditation upon death. Pray ye all to God to engrave it by the finger of his all-pearcing spirit in the vive depth of my heart, that again by way of spirituall communication, I may write it upon the tables of your hearts (as it were) with a pen of iron, and the point of a diamond, that both preacher and hearer may lay it up in their memories, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise it in their lives and conversations. And I intreat you all (and most of all these who are of a tender conscience) I entreat you I say, in the tender bowels of mercie, not to misconstruct my coming hither, which ought rather to be a matter of singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar comfort, then of prejudged censure; a matter of profitable instruction, rather then of envious emulation; a matter of
<pb facs="11"/>
pious devotion, then of repining conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I think not shame, with the glorious apostle to preach in season, and out of sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, for the converting, winning, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gathering of soules. I do not say this, That I consent to these who contemne and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne altogether such meetings; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit I would confesse unto them, that the time, place, and persons were extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie (as indeed they may seem to these who have not travailed out of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roch churches, or seen forrein countries) yet the customes of the primitive church (see <hi>Nazianzen, Ambrose, Jerome,</hi> &amp;c.) and of our reformed churches in France, Genevah, Germanie, upper and lower, in great Britaine, and elsewhere, maketh all three ordinarie; and the subject of this present meditation, viz. <hi>Death,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the same to be common.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>