<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE IESVITES CHALLENGE.</title>
           <author>B., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118933_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14227</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24542</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118933</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE IESVITES CHALLENGE.</title>
                 <author>B., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvver to a challenge made by a Iesuite in Ireland : Wherein the iudgement of antiquity in the points questioned is truely delivered, and the noveltie of the now romish doctrine plainly discovered. By Iames Vssher Bishop of Meath</title>
                 <author>Ussher, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Ireland--Dublin</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>—Irish Stock.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stationers’ Society, Dublin</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 527, 9 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="challenge">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>THE IESVITES CHALLENGE.</head>
   <head type="sub">How shall I answer to a Papist, demaunding this Question?</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Doctors and Masters graunt that the Church of Rome for <hi>400</hi> or <hi>500</hi> years after Christ, did hold the true Religion. First then would I faine knowe, what Bishop of Rome did first alter that Religion, which you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend in them of the first <hi>400</hi> years? In what Pope his dayes was the true Religion overthrowne in Rome?</p>
   <p>Next, I would faine know, How can your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be true, which dissalloweth of many chiefe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, which the Saints and Fathers of that primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church of Rome did generally hold to be true?</p>
   <p>For they of your side, that have read the Fathers
<pb facs="11"/>
of that unspotted Church, can well testifie (and if any deny it, it shall be presently shewen) that the Doctors, Pastors, and Fathers of that Church doe allow of Traditions; that they acknowledge the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al presence of the body of Christ in the Sacrament of the Altar: that they exhorted the people to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse their sinnes unto their ghostly Fathers: that they affirmed, that Priests have power to forgive sinnes: that they taught, that there is a Purgatory: that prayer for the dead is both commendable and godly: that there is <hi>Limbus Patrum,</hi> and that our Saviour descended into Hell, to deliver the ancient Fathers of the Old Testament; because before his Passion none ever entred into Heaven: that prayer to Saints, and use of holy Images was of great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count amongst them: that man hath free-will, and that for his meritorious works he receiveth, through the assistance of Gods grace, the blisse of euerlasting happinesse.</p>
   <p>Now would I faine know whether of both haue the true Religion, they that hold all these above said points, with the Primitive Church; or they that doe most vehemently contradict, and gaine-say them? They that doe not disagree with that holy Church, in any point of Religion; or they that agree with it but in very few, and disagree in almost all?</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="11"/>VVill you say, that these Fathers maintained these opinions, contrary to the word of God? why you know that they were the pillars of Christianitie, the champions of Christ his Church, and of the true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Religion, which they most learnedly defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded against diverse heresies; and therefore spent all their time in a most serious studie of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Or will you say, that although they knew the Scriptures to repugne, yet they brought in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said opinions by malice and corrupt intentions? VVhy your selves cannot deny but that they lived most holy and vertuous lives, free from all maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous corrupting, or perverting of Gods holy word, and by their holy lives are now made worthy to raigne with God in his glory. In so much as their admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble learning may sufficiently crosse out all suspition of ignorant error; and their innocent sanctitie free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us from all mistrust of malitious corruption.</p>
   <p>Now would I willingly see what reasonable an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer may be made to this. For the Protestants graunt, that the Church of Rome for <hi>400</hi> or <hi>500</hi> yeares, held the true Religion of Christ: yet do they exclaime against the abovesaid Articles, which the same Church did maintaine and uphold, as may bee shewen by the expresse testimonies of the Fathers of the same Church; and shall be largely laid down,
<pb facs="12"/>
if any learned Protestant will deny it.</p>
   <p>Yea, which is more, for the confirmation of all the aboue mentioned points of our Religion, wee will produce good and certaine grounds out of the sacred Scriptures, if the Fathers authority will not suffice. And we do desire any Protestant to alleage any one Text out of the said Scripture, which condemneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the aboue written points: which wee hold for certaine they shall never be able to doe. For indeed they are neyther more learned, more pious, nor more holy then the blessed Doctors and Martyrs of that first Church of Rome, which they allow and esteeme of so much, and by which we most willingly will be tryed, in any point which is in controversie betwixt the <hi>Protestants</hi> and the <hi>Catholicks.</hi> VVhich wee desire may be done with christian charity and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, to the glory of God, and instruction of them that are astray.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>W. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>