<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1576</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118853_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17244</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4096</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118853</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvhole summe of Christian religion, giuen forth by two seuerall methodes or formes : the one higher, for the better learned, the other applyed to the capacitie of the common multitude, and meete for all: yet both of them such, as in some respect do knit them selues together in one. By Edmund Bunny Bacheler of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Bunny, Edmund</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1576</date>
                 <distributor>Bishop, George</distributor>
                            <distributor>Harrison, Luke (Lucas)</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 70, 2 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing already made de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of my purpose and meaning in setting forth these two Summes of Christian Religion (as appeareth in the Preface that goeth before) I shal not neede; gentle Reader, to recite any part thereof agayne vnto thee. Neuerthelesse some thinges there are, wherein it shall not be amise, to direct my penne a little to thee.</p>
   <p>First of all therefore I nothing doubt, but that some there will be, that wil hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly like, that Religion shoulde be geuen forth after the maner of these two Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodes. Because the former doth so pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisely put by man for any agent in those matters, and gathereth the whole glory of all onely to God: the other, lying within the bounds of the ten-Commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, will seeme vnto them to be no more but only some parte, in no wise the whole by any good order. Thou therefore per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
<pb facs="9"/> wilt loke, that I should ioyne here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto some defence of my dooing. and in deede I do not denie, but that, not onely the eyes of the common multitude do as yet remayne so dazeled, that they are not able to perceiue either of these very plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: but also, that certayne hostile mindes cannot in any wise be content to yeelde to the former of them, or, in these matters of spiritual glory, that they shuld haue none, and God should haue all. Howbeit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I will not be tedious to thee, I will holde of my hande from that kinde of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and say no more but this only: that whensoeuer it shall please God to open the eyes of the one, and to kill the cankre of pride in the harts of the other, then shal they also playnly perceyue, that they haue here no cause of misliking. Tyl that time, we leese but our labour, if we looke that the blinde should see; or that the proude should freely geue all glory to God.</p>
   <p>An other thing, wherein I thought it somewhat needeful to content thy minde, is to preuēt a doubt, that otherwise might happily arise vnto thee. For I think thou wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> looke, that I should haue furnished
<pb facs="9"/> my Margent with so conuenient a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Scriptures, as were sufficient to confirme the truth that is heere set down: as it is the maner of many to do. as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching which matter, thus much I say, that I do accompt such dealing, then especially to be needefull, when we deliuer suche poyntes of doctrine, as are hardly recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of euery one. For who seeketh profe in a matter that is apparant inough? Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therfore that in these two treatises I write no newe thing, but onely gather to an other Method such things as others haue already sufficiently proued; and are nowe (almost) of all men receyued, that haue a good will and loue to the trueth: I wote not, howe I might haue giuen an accompt vnto God, if eyther nowe I had bestowed my time therein, when I haue other more needefull busines; or should haue kept in this that I haue done, vntill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eysure mighte haue serued to haue done the other. Neuerthelesse my purpose is, if it shall please God to geue me strength <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd oportunitie therevnto, and if none other shall well preuent me, not onely to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>estowe some vsuall number of quotatiōs
<pb facs="10"/> on it: but to geeue the attempt, to reduce the whole scriptures therevnto, &amp; the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of euery membre therof to some part of it. that so it may be a more profitable method to those that shall studie it more exactly. But as I am not able as yet to do it (especially tyll I haue gottē some other things out of mine hāds) because I know the worke will grow to a great labour, &amp; require no small quantity of time thervn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: so I do not thinke it best in any other respect, to be so hastie for that matter. that so I may win a further tyme of delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the methode it selfe. trusting that time, and the help of others, shall at lēgth bring it to better perfection: and so make it meter to be furnished with quotations. In the meane season, sith now I haue not opportunitie to doe it as I woulde, or to mine owne cōtentatiō, I can be very well content altogether to hold off my hands from it. yf any others to their priuate vse shall in their reading, sort the scriptures &amp; other good authors therevnto, on their behalfe, &amp; to their encouragement, thus much will I not sticke to say, that, vnless<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> I be farre deceiued, their paynes shal
<pb facs="10"/> returne with so happy encrease, that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>her shall they euer repent them of it, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>asily finde, howe they might otherwise <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aue bestowed their labour to muche bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er purpose. And whensoeuer a student <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hal find any part of al scripture, or of any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ther good author, or any example or te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>timonie of others, that can not aptly be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>educed, to some parte of this method, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hen let him be sure of one of these two, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hat eyther the methode is vnperfect, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r els him selfe doth not vnderstande <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t. whiche sorting of the Scriptures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hervnto, will also he a very good way to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>erfect the method. For so sone as we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ght on any place, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we can not perceaue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o come within the cōpasse of it, then fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing out where it ought to be, we may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>olde to conclude, that in that place it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> vnperfect. But so farre as me selfe can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>et see, I am not aduised of any parte of Scripture, that may not very aptly be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uced to some parte or other of this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hod. Neither coulde I content me selfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ith it, tyll I had brought it to that order.</p>
   <p>And therfore to speake something more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>irectly of the vse of it, I trust that the vse
<pb facs="11"/> therof may be double. wherof the first is vniuersall, or comon to all that haue no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> yet atteined to sufficiēt knowledge of the Christian faith. And that is this; to geu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> thē a generall sight of all religion, &amp; to lay in them the foundation of it. For my hop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> is, that whosoeuer shall well digest these two little bookes (a thing we may see of no great labour) he, by the helpe thereof may be so well grounded in Christian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that there cannot lightly be moued a point of any great importance, but that he shalbe able to goe to the truth thereof and to see the place whence it doth arise to the better confirmation of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therin: as also it shall ease a good part of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> paines in reading y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> holy scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> otherwise would be found there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, whosoeuer shall first be grounded in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whole body of religion, eyther by these, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> by any other to the like effecte. The other vse hereof is more speciall: but suche as is of good importaunce. It doth apperteine to all those, that specially shall geue them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selues to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> study of Diuinitie. For who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer shal so do, they shal finde it a thing very nedefull, not onely to haue a note<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>booke,
<pb facs="11"/> whereinto they may gather the floure of their reading, and the titles ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of prescribed vnto them: but also to haue those titles so to be deuised &amp; disposed, as may be aptest to cōprehend the thing that they seeke. and therfore many haue labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to gratifie studentes in this behalfe: &amp; in that respect haue deserued very well of thē. As touching which matter, I for my part do not see, how a student of Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie might better furnishe his note-booke with titles, then to set downe the mēbers hereof in order as they followe: doing the same with aduisement in choyce, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to euery one such as a proportion of space, as he shall gesse y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> matter will nede. No matter of diffcultie (to speake of) to suche as know what a note-booke mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. And my trust is, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> there are not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny matters of importaunce, not only, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n the scriptures, but also, not in the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, or in other good writers, appertei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the substaunce of religiō, that may not aptly and naturally be referred to some suche title as is conteined in these two bookes.</p>
   <p>For the better accomplishment of this
<pb facs="12"/> matter, as also for the better prouocation of al others to search out the sense of these litle books, I haue annexed herevnto such a demonstratiō therof &amp; so liuely a repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentation to the eye of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> principal parts, &amp; of euery particular point cōteined therin, as I was able to deuise in so smal a rome, expressing y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> former booke vnder y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> forme of a tree roote; and the latter by a couple of other trees. The former haue I made the roote, for that it is by nature the very groūd worke of the other: as may appeare in the opening of the firste commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. In whiche Roote euery prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Master-Roote doeth expresse the chiefe and principall partes of the whole discourse: as also the lesser doo betoken inferiour members, euen to the laste and leaste of all. And as for the Trees, my meaning is this. the one of them represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth such thinges as are forbidden by the cōmaundements, &amp; therefore is called the tre of death: the other, such things as they require, and therefore is called the tree of lyfe. The roote aforesaide, diuersly taken, is roote vnto both. For the ignoraunce of
<pb facs="12"/> those things y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it conteineth, is roote vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the tree of death: and the knowledge of them, the roote vnto the tree of lyfe. And therfore haue I somewhat bared y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rootes of both these trees: y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> (so far as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> discourse therof doth lead) euery one may see it to be the selfe same roote, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> before is descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. This also I haue prouided both in the Roote, and in the trees, that there be neither mo, nor fewer diuisions or braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of any, then there are seuerall partes or mēbers in the discourses that belong thervnto: nor otherwise growing or issu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth, thou the diuisions or mēbers of these discourses doo arise one vpon an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. As it shalbe an easy matter for those to espie, that will conferre them and the booke together: so that euer they remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to kepe this order, (which I haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually obserued) to beginne at their lefte hande in all Diuisions, and to go to the right.</p>
   <p>Which that they may the better finde out, I haue not only lefte my trees with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out eyther fruite or leaues (as in deede the tree of lyfe hath seldome any store of fruite amōg vs: &amp; then why should not the tree
<pb facs="13"/> of death be so much the rather spoyled of this?) that so the Braunches them selues may better appeare how many they are &amp; how they arise: but also haue added certen letters both to the Roote, and to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Trees to bring y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> demōstration &amp; the bookes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. that so, not onely those that will more diligently study religion, may soner espie what titles to chuse: but all others also, that will but read these bookes with aduisement, may better perceiue, what pointes religion geueth forth vnto thē to be considered. But herewithall must they know, that this demonstration doth not extend to the Preface, conclusion, or mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall notes in eyther of the bookes: nor to those things y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> in the text are added to the second, third, fourth, &amp; fifte cōmaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> latter booke. Otherwise there is not (to my remēbraunce) any one mē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre of eyther of these books, that hath not his proper demōstratiō, either in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> roote, or in one of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Trees: and that in such sort, as I trust will be welcome to the diligent reader, for the light y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it doth carie with it. As also I dare be bold to say thus muche, that if any of those that loue imbrodering
<pb facs="13"/> or nedle worke, shall thinke good to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row their flowers or Braunches hence, sure I am that the best of vs all may here haue inow, to put in napkins to wipe our noses.</p>
   <p>As for the songes that are set herevnto, they doe so resemble y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> matter it selfe, that euery one may see my meaning therein. The former of them is made vpon y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> song of the Angell that brought y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> shepheardes word of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> birth of Christe, geuing y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> glory of that our redēptiō only to God: a thing that cometh very neere to the argumēt of the former booke. The other goeth vpon the sense of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ten-cōmaūdements, &amp; doth more precisely comprehend the effect of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whole latter booke: teaching the way that we should walke. Seing therfore y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes we are naturally bent to refreshe our selues with song, &amp; some, not onely are desirous to sing by thēselues, but also couet to haue others to sing with thē, and therwithall to haue such recreation as the harmonie of musicke can bring therevnto (which is veri much to most mēs nature) whereas before I had a note of a freind of mine in foure parts, which well agreth
<pb facs="14"/> to this kind of making, and is not vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the author of it, I thought it good to set all those partes downe to the one, and to procure the like for the other: that, if so it shall please thee, thou also mayst haue the vse of them. and if thy hart shall goe with thy song, then dare I promise thee, that god him selfe shall like thy melodie.</p>
   <p>These (gentle Reader) are the things that I had to imparte vnto ther. These if thou take with the bookes them selues, thou hast therwithall my whole meaning. Of what accompt it shal be with some others, as yet I knowe not, so also I care not. But who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer shal geue foorth better, I shal be as glad to receiue that, as I was readie in the same respect to publishe this. God geue vs al grace, to be thankful to him for this great light, that it hath pleased him to cōmaunde, to shine out of darknes in these our dayes: and while we haue it, to walke as becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the children of light. The night (mee thinketh) approcheth neare, then shall we hardly be able to walke. Time must be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, when time is offred. for time will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. And so in the Lord I bid thee hartily well to fare. this 20 of Aprill. 1576.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>