<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A FEW LINES, TO SMALL PVRPOSE, against the Scandalous Aspersions, that are either maliciously, or ignorantly cast vpon the Poets and Poems of these Times.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118281_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13500</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23796</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118281</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A FEW LINES, TO SMALL PVRPOSE, against the Scandalous Aspersions, that are either maliciously, or ignorantly cast vpon the Poets and Poems of these Times.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Superbiæ flagellum, or, The vvhip of pride. By Iohn Taylor</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>66 pages, illustrations (metal cut), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>A FEW LINES, TO SMALL PVRPOSE, against the Scandalous Aspersions, that are either maliciously, or ignorantly cast vpon the Poets and Poems of these Times.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>THere doth a strange, and true opinion runne,</l>
      <l>That Poots write much worse then they haue don:</l>
      <l>And how so poore their daily writings are,</l>
      <l>As though their best inuentions were threed bare.</l>
      <l>And how no new things from them now doth spring,</l>
      <l>But all hath refrence from some other thing.</l>
      <l>And that their daily doings doe reueale,</l>
      <l>How they from one another silch and steale,</l>
      <l>As if amongst them't were a statute made,</l>
      <l>That they may freely use the theeuing trade.</l>
      <l>And some there are that will not sticke to say,</l>
      <l>That many Poets liuing at this day,</l>
      <l>Who haue the Hebrew, Latine, Greeke, at will,</l>
      <l>And in th' Italian and thè French haue skill,</l>
      <l>These are the greatest theeues they say, of all</l>
      <l>That vse the Trade (or Art) Poeticall.</l>
      <l>For ancient Bards, and Poets in strange toungs,</l>
      <l>Compiled haue their verses and their songs:</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="8"/>
And those to whom those tongues are rightly knowne,</l>
      <l>Translating them, make others verse their owne,</l>
      <l>As one that steales a Cloake, and presently</l>
      <l>Makes it his owne, by alt'ring of the dye.</l>
      <l>So whole boookes, and whole sentences haue bin</l>
      <l>Stolne, and the stealers, great applause did win,</l>
      <l>And by their filching thought great men of fame,</l>
      <l>By those that knew not the right Authors name.</l>
      <l>For mine owne part, my Conscience witnesse is,</l>
      <l>I ne're was guilty of such theft as this,</l>
      <l>Unto such robbery I could neuer reach,</l>
      <l>Because I vnderstand no forreigne speach.</l>
      <l>To prooue that I am from such filching free,</l>
      <l>Latin and French are heathen-Greeke to me,</l>
      <l>The Grecian, and the Hebrew Charactars,</l>
      <l>I know as well, as I can reach the Starres.</l>
      <l>The sweete Italian, and the Chip Chop Dutch,</l>
      <l>I know the man i'th Moone can speake as much.</l>
      <l>Should I from English Authors, but purloyne,</l>
      <l>It would be soone found counterfeited coyne.</l>
      <l>Then since I cannot steale, but some will spy,</l>
      <l>Ile truely use mine owne, let others lye.</l>
      <l>Yet to excuse the writers, that now write,</l>
      <l>Because they bring no better things to light:</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="8"/>
Tis because bounty from the world is fled,</l>
      <l>True liberality is almost dead.</l>
      <l>Reward is lodg'd in darke obliuion deepe,</l>
      <l>Bewitch't (I thinke) into an endlesse sleepe,</l>
      <l>That though a man in study take great paines,</l>
      <l>And empt his veines, and puluerize his braines,</l>
      <l>To write a Poem well, which being writ</l>
      <l>Wthall his Iudgement, Reason, Art, and Wit,</l>
      <l>And at his owne charge, print and pay for all,</l>
      <l>And giue away most free, and liberall</l>
      <l>Two, three, or foure, or fiue hundred bookes.</l>
      <l>For his reward he shall haue nods and lookes;</l>
      <l>That all the profit a mans paines hath gat,</l>
      <l>Will not suffice one meale to feed a Cat.</l>
      <l>Yet Noble Wcstminster, thou still art free,</l>
      <l>And for thy bounty I am bound to thee:</l>
      <l>For hadst not thou, and thy Inhabitants,</l>
      <l>From Time to Time relieu'd and helpd my wants,</l>
      <l>I had long since bid Poetry adieu</l>
      <l>And therefore still my thankes shall be to you.</l>
      <l>Next to the Court, in generall I am bound</l>
      <l>To you, for many friendships I haue found.</l>
      <l>There (when my purse hath often wanted baite)</l>
      <l>To fill or feed it, I baue had receite.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="9"/>
So much for that, I'le now no more rehearse,</l>
      <l>They shew their loues in prose, my thankes in verse,</l>
      <l>When death, <hi>Mecaenas</hi> did of life depriue,</l>
      <l>Few of his Noble Tribe were left aliue,</l>
      <l>This makes Inuention to be meane and hard,</l>
      <l>When <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Auarice</hi> doth killreward.</l>
      <l>And yet me thinkes, it plainely doth appeare,</l>
      <l>Mens writings are as good as e're they were.</l>
      <l>Good lines are like a Banquet ill imployd,</l>
      <l>Where too much feeding hath the stomack cloyde.</l>
      <l>Good verses fall sometimes (by course of fate)</l>
      <l>Into their hands that are preiudicate.</l>
      <l>And though, the Writer ne're so well hath pend,</l>
      <l>Yet they'le find fault with what they cannot mend.</l>
      <l>Thus many a learned well composed line,</l>
      <l>Hath bin as Pearle that's cast before a swine.</l>
      <l>Or more familiarly to make compare,</l>
      <l>Like Aquauitae giuen vnto a Mare.</l>
      <l>These fellowes, (glutted with variety)</l>
      <l>Hold Good lines in a loath'd saciety,</l>
      <l>Whiest paltry Riming, Libells, Iigges, and Iests,</l>
      <l>Are to their appetites continuall feafts.</l>
      <l>With which their fancies they doe feed and fill,</l>
      <l>And take the Ill for good, the Good for ill.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="9"/>
Whilst like to Monkeyes, (scorning wholesome meate)</l>
      <l>They grredily doe poysnous spiders eate.</l>
      <l>So let them feed vntill their humours burst,</l>
      <l>And thus much bold to tell them heere I durst.</l>
      <l>That Poetry is now as good as euer,</l>
      <l>If bounty, to relieue her would endeuer.</l>
      <l>Mens mindes are worse then they haue bin of yore,</l>
      <l>Inuention's good now, as it was before.</l>
      <l>Let liberality awake, and then</l>
      <l>Each Poet in his hand will take a pen,</l>
      <l>And with rare lines inrich a world of paper,</l>
      <l>Shall make <hi>Apollo,</hi> and the Muses caper.</l>
   </lg>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>