<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Iudicious, Enuious and foolish Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118401_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B12182</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5672</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118401</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Iudicious, Enuious and foolish Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Epigrames : Serued out in 52. seuerall dishes for euery man to tast without surfeting. By I.C. Gent</title>
                 <author>Cooke, Jo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Cotton, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>58 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Iudicious, Enuious <hi>and foolish Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O you al<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> but to thee Iudicious Reader, as most respected, I submit my twelue nights tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles, (for so I may truely call them) being then made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of Christmas Carrols; I know thou sha't finde manie errors in them, but I will not intreate thee to mend them, being too great a taske for thee, and my selfe hat<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> forborne to doe it. I publish them not to purchace fame, nor reward, for I protest I haue beene as carlesse in writing them, as any reader can be in reading them, therefore I would desire thee to thinke cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably. As for you enuious Reader, I know your
<pb facs="4"/> mallice and ign<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rance is such, that were they the choicest flowers that grow vpon the mount of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>us</hi> you would spitte your poyson vpon them, therfore I haue preuented you and sent you netles. But for my simple plaine dealing Reader, I know if he could here but a baudie iest he'd grin like his owne picture, and sweare he had a good wit that made it, (I would be loath he should be forsworne) yet I shal stil hold him <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>imselfe when he has spoke his best of me. But to my first Reader againe, the Romanes in their Epigrames did vse the true names of those they write of, and our Epigrami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists do borrow their names of them, but I haue vsed bastard names, such as my fancie was fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of, not waying whether they were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the nature of the Epigrame, as indeede there is no such ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie. So fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>