<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONO∣norable and his singuler good Lord Sir Henry Sidney Knight of the moste Hono∣rable Order of the Garter, Lord President of VVales, &amp; Marches of the same.</title>
           <author>F., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118412_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13763</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24062</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118412</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONO∣norable and his singuler good Lord Sir Henry Sidney Knight of the moste Hono∣rable Order of the Garter, Lord President of VVales, &amp; Marches of the same.</title>
                 <author>F., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Newes from the north. Otherwise called The conference betvveen Simon Certain, and Pierce Plowman, faithfully collected and gathered by T.F. student</title>
                 <author>T. F., student</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and his singuler good Lord Sir Henry Sidney Knight of the moste Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> Order of the <hi>Garter,</hi> Lord President of <hi>VVales,</hi> &amp; <hi>Marches</hi> of the same.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough there can be no Freendship (right Honorable and mysinguler good Lord) to speak properly vvhere there is no equalitie betvveen the parties, yet may the simplest and the meanest looue and honor the highest and greatest, yea somuch the more as their inequalitie is the greater. But that is not properly called freendship but rather a dutyful looue &amp; is harder to be expressed and shevved for the inequalitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid. For Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ndship is betvveen equalls, or at the least vvhere the inequalitie is not so very great that the Offices and Duties of Freendship vvhich are the bonds and sinevvs therof can haue no entercourse. I speak this for my self that haue long desired occasion to shevv my hartie goodvvil and affection vnto your Lordship vvhich hath been somevvhat hard for mee to doo for the cause abooue remembred. And therfore hauing gathered this little conference: I made bold to dedicate it vnto my good Lord, A thing meeter to be my gift then vvoorthy to be presented vnto your Honor or to go further vnder the name of such a Patron. Hovv be it, my trust is that your Lordship of your accustomed clemency vvil accept a simple thing of him at vvhose hands nothing at all vvas looked for, and vvill aloovv my goodvvil tovvards the reparation of such faults and Imperfectiōs as are heerin.</p>
   <p>So praying God to blesse your Lordship and prosper you. From London the tvventie six of Nouember. 1579.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships in all humilitie T F.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>