<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118753_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14083</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24393</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118753</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Asylum veneris, or A sanctuary for ladies : Iustly protecting them, their virtues, and sufficiencies from the foule aspersions and forged imputations of traducing spirits</title>
                 <author>D. T. (Daniel Tuvill)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lisle (L’isle, Lyle), Laurence</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 64, 75-162 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know this age to be very Stoicall and Criticall, and that many will cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure the Author to haue seriously busied himself in an idle subiect; as making no account of vertue in women, though they come farre short of it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues. But I haue <hi>Plutarke,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worthy persons for my Precedents, Besides I considered with my selfe that if the Trophies of <hi>Miltiades</hi> were of power to recall <hi>Themistocles</hi> from his effeminat and wanton courses, much more should their Perfections &amp; Sufficiencies, whom we account the weaker Vessels, bee of force to stir vs vp to all heroicall attempts
<pb facs="4"/>
and atchieuements. And blessed S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> doth most ingenuously confesse, That from their constancy hee receiued much encouragement in his first conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion. But the slight approbation I make of it my selfe, may bee witnessed by my long suppressing it. And but to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent others, who had gotten from mee some imperfect copies, I would neuer haue published it now. Carelesse ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of all snarling Cynicks &amp; their tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, with <hi>Horace</hi> I onely court the lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned and the good.</p>
   <lg>
      <l>—quibus haec sint qualia cunqne</l>
      <l>Arridere velim; doliturus, si placeant spe</l>
      <l>Deterius nostra.—</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>