<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE WELL
affected, and loyall hearted
Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118537_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13961</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24270</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118537</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE WELL
affected, and loyall hearted
Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fierie tryall of Gods saints (these suffered for the witnes of Iesus, and for the word of God, (vnder Queene Mary,) who did not worship the Beast ... As a counter-poyze to I.W. priest his English martyrologe. And the detestable ends of popish traytors: (these are of Sathans synagogue, calling themselues Iewes (or Catholiques) but lie and are not ... Set downe in a comparatiue collection of both their sufferings. Herewith also the concurrance and agreement of the raignes of the kings of England and Scotland, since the first yeare of Q. Mary, till this present, the like before not extant))</title>
                 <author>Burton, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Johnson (Jonson), Arthur</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 40, 24, 10, 2 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="1" facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE WELL
affected, and loyall hearted
Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S to the spirit and soule
of man nothing inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally
then a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science
can bee more
comfortable; so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally,
then a good
report from others no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
can be more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.
And as for the
first, euery one that will enjoye it, must himselfe
alone by the vprightnesse of his owne actions,
assure it vnto himselfe in the sincerity of his own
heart; so, for the secōd, as it depends not vpō ones
selfe alone, but vpon the tongues and reports of
others, euery Christian by the rules of his profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
is chargeable to his power to seeke the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation
thereof towards others, whome hee
knoweth to be wronged. This being graunted
(as it cannot be denyed) if euery priuate mans
good name so neerely touch him, as that for the
<pb n="2" facs="4"/>
preseruation thereof wee are all of vs to others
reciprocally bound, and by law diuine obliged.
How much more strictly then are all faithful sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects
tyed, as much as in them lyeth, to maintaine
the good name, honour, and reputation of their
lawfull Soneraignes, by traytors, rebels, And an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichristians,
so vniustly, jmpiously, and jmpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently
taxed both in words and writings. For
as his Majestie is our King, by God appoynted
to rule ouer his British and Irish <hi>Israell,</hi> both in
Church and common wealth: and as in dignity
he is <hi>nulli secundus,</hi> nay more (for that may seeme
to admit an equall) <hi>Primus inter omnes,</hi> without a
mate, highest: euen so the blemish of good
name, honour, and reputation in his Majestie, is
of all others most dishonourable, most scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous;
as his Majesty is of all others most eminent,
most conspicuous; and therefore by euery good
subiect as occasion offereth it selfe <hi>(pro viribus)</hi>
to be maintained. If a naturall father haue a bad
name, though vndesernedly, yet is that in the
worlds eye (that cannot iudge thereof, but by
report) a scandall vnto the children. Our King
is more, for he is not onely <hi>Pater familiae,</hi> a father
of a priuate family, but he is, <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of our Country; nay more, he is, <hi>Pater mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum
gentium &amp; regnorum,</hi> a father of many
Kingdomes <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi>
and which is most, hee is a good Christian, <hi>&amp;


Christianae fidei Defensor,</hi> the chiefe Champion for
defence of Christian faith, through whose sides
<pb n="3" facs="4"/>
the enemy seeketh to wound the whole Church
of Christ, and to lay aspersions of bloud and tyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
vpon all such as with him professe the gospell
of Christ.</p>
   <p>The consideration whereof (as also a feruent
desire to doe my Country some publique seruice,
in helping (as much as in me lyeth) to stop the
mouths of our common aduersaries the Papists,
whose lauish tongs haue spit out aboundance of
venome, and their pennes stung like Scorpions,
not onely our late most gracious and woorthy
Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> (of euer-blessed memorie, for
the many vnspeakeable blessings that God with
and through her bestowed vpon this and other
Kingdomes) But also our present Soueraigne
Lord and King, with both their state Ministers,
by charging them as falsely, so maliciously with
cruelty, breach of promise, bloud, and bloudy
persecution for conscience) hath mooued mee
to jmploye the best talent of my small ability to
convince them of jmpudent and lying malicious
slaunders and reproachfull vntruths. First in a
few following lynes directed vnto all Romish
fauorites, clearing my present gracious Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
of breach of promise with Recusants, for
toleration of Popery, wherein also I haue tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
the ground of that slaunder, with the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
and Authors thereof, with some other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
of speciall moment. Secondly, in a tabular
computation; by a comparatiue collection of all
such Martyrs as were burned in Queene <hi>Maries</hi>
      <pb n="4" facs="5"/>
days, with all such Priests, Iesuites, &amp; popish Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusants,
as their Pseudomartyrologist <hi>I. W.</hi> Priest
pretends (&amp; but pretends) to haue byn executed
in England <hi>(Religionis ergò)</hi> since the beginning of
Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> raigne vntill this present yere 1608.
I haue cleared the second accusation of cruelty,
bloud, and bloudy presecution for conscience,
evidently proouing by their owne account, vnto
the vnderstanding of the most simple, that is not
wilfully blind, that many more of the first sort suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
death, and were in fire consumed onely
for their conscience, within the lesse then six
yeares raigne of Queene <hi>Marie,</hi> then of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond,
third and fourth sort (to wit, Priests, Iesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites,
and Recusants) in 52. yeares since, and
that not for Religion, but<note n="a" place="margin">Ʋide Tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram Torti. paginis. 131. 132.</note> Treason. Whereby
it appeareth how vnjustly our late woorthy
Queene, our present gracious King &amp; their State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministers,
haue been and are most jmpudently &amp;
falsely of bloud &amp; cruelty accused &amp; taxed.</p>
   <p>Nor haue I ought herein written to giue satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
to any such (for let them sincke in their
owne sinnes) as being ouer deeply bewitched
with <hi>Romes</hi> jdolatry, doe hold that all Treasons,
all Rebellions, all Attempts, <hi>vi, aut fraude,</hi> against
the persons and states of our late Queene <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi>
and our now present King, both were and
are not only lawfull, but meritorious: But to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
such of them as being of a milder temper,
(and yet looking that way) willingly confesse
and acknowledge, that all such as haue beene or
<pb n="5" facs="5"/>
are guilty of such crimes, haue deseruedly been
punished; but yet doe, or at least seeme to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue
that their Priests and Iesuites haue suffered
onely for their Consciences, and therefore their
persecution (they being many in nomber) is (in
their judgement) great and lamentable. Which
were it graunted, or could (as it neuer can) bee
prooued that they all dyed for their conscience
onely, (which yet is a conscience mis-enformed)
yet doth the nomber of our true Martyrs in lesse
then 6. yeres of Queene <hi>Maries</hi> raigne, (although
it should be permitted vnto them to take also in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
their number those fifty and two lay persons,
(for so many I thinke there are) registred with the
Priests and Iesuites in their owne Martyrologe)
not onely equallize, but exceed the number of
theirs in full fifty yeares since, by the number of
almost 100. persons. Insomuch, that if the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
of persons suffering, and the number of
yeeres of both sorts wherein they suffered bee
compared, and the cause of all their sufferings ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
to be alike just or vnjust (of which there
is no comparison) yet did the cruelty of Queene
<hi>Marie</hi> and her popish Clergie, out-strip Queene
<hi>Elizabeth</hi> and king <hi>Iames</hi> conjoyned, more then
tenne for one; and therefore learne, you that
haue any sparke of grace remaining in you, to be
good subiects to your King, and cease now at
last to taxe your soueraigne any more of persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō,
whose heart bleeds that he is forced to draw
bloud from others for their jntollerable demerits.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="6" facs="6"/>
As for the truth of these collections whereat
perhaps (and not vnlike) some popish spirits will
take<note n="b" place="margin">Three con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versions of Eng: part 3. in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> exception; vnderstand that <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Foxe</hi> that
sometime reuerend Father of our Church, is my
Author, whome for the number of such pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors
of the Gospell as were burned in Queene
<hi>Maries</hi> dayes, I haue soly followed, who albeit
happily (for it is almost jmpossible to bee other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise)
in some things in so large a volume, hee
might commit some small errour in some parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
cicumstances, because no Historian can
possibly be present euery where with his owne
eyes and eares, but must of necessity giue cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite
vnto the relations of others in many poynts;
Yet the granity of his person, his excellent lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
his great reading, his worthy and sober ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,
his sound judgement, and therein his wise
choyce of Authours, and the generall report of
his honest and religious mind, by an vniforme
consent of all such as knew him, freeth him from
taxation of any wilfull and grosse errour, or wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
mistaking, and from any malicious aslertion
against the Papists without a probable ground,
throughout his worthy woorke, in whose be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe
I thinke it needlesse to bestowe much
paines, because the honester and greater sort
are honestly already of him perswaded, and
for the rest as they are for number fewer, and
their honesty little worth, so ate they many of
them wilfully obstinate and will not bee perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="7" facs="6"/>
As for the other sort, to wit, popish Priests,
Iesuites, and Recusants, such as haue beene
executed since the beginning of Queene <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths</hi>
raigne (as <hi>I. W.</hi> pretendeth for religion) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
the yeare 1608. they are coppyed word for
word out of a booke called <hi>The</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">English Martyrologe by <hi>J. VV.</hi> Priest Anno. 1608.</note>
      <hi>English Martyro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loge,</hi>
by the authority of the popish supervisors (as
it should seeme) allowed, vnles the nameles au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
thereof <hi>I. W.</hi> Priest doe belye them. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
I haue dealt as truely with them to a letter as I
could, saue onely that I haue left out one person,
and in steed thereof added two, to wit, <hi>William
Watson</hi> and <hi>William Clarke,</hi> both Priests executed
at<note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>VVatson,</hi> and <hi>Clarke,</hi> executed at <hi>VVinchester</hi> in An. 1603. Novemb. 29.</note>
      <hi>Winchester</hi> Novemb. 29. 1603. I know not
how by the Pseudomartyrologist omitted, for he
might as well haue enrolled them as those which
he hath done, being all alike, traytors to their
Prince and Country. Noram I disposed to cauill
for that I find diuers of their Priests noted in that
his Martyrologe by one name which yet I find
set downe in our Chronicles by an other name,
as for example, in An. 1585. Ianuary 21. <hi>Edward
Transam,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Stowe.</note> and <hi>Nicho. Wodfine,</hi> so by this our Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrologist
noted, are by others named <hi>Edmund
Barbar</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Deuorax,</hi> which I note chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
for this end, that none might be deceiued in
thinking that more haue been executed, then in
deed haue been, because one and the same per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
are in their and our writings noted by dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
names, for they haue so many false names,
that amongst them all I find not one good and
<pb n="8" facs="7"/>
true. He that at<note n="e" place="margin">Henry Garnet <hi>had 6. names, to wit,</hi> Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, VValley, Darcy, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts, Farmer, <hi>and</hi> Phillips. <hi>Likewise</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Hall <hi>ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> Oldecorne. <hi>Likewise</hi> Os<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>esmund <hi>alias</hi> Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. <hi>Likewise</hi> Thomas Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net <hi>alias</hi> Rook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, <hi>alias</hi> Sayer, <hi>with many others.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>London</hi> is called <hi>Richard,</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi>
is called <hi>Iohn,</hi> he that at <hi>Rhesmes</hi> and <hi>Doway</hi> is
called <hi>Peter,</hi> in <hi>England</hi> is called <hi>Saul;</hi> he that in
the Iesuites cells is Sainted for his resolution, is at
Tyburne hanged for his treason. I haue I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse
transposed some of both sorts, both of our
Martyrs and their traytors, but only for this end
that I might reduce them to our account, which
beginneth the yeare on the 25. of March, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to the tabular Register following, whereas
both <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Foxe</hi> &amp; the Pseudomartyrologist began
the yeare the first of Ianuary; As for example,
<hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Foxe</hi> hath noted <hi>Iohn Rogers</hi> the first Martyr
in Queene <hi>Marie</hi> her dayes, to haue suffered
February 4. 1555. which yet according to our
account was in the yeare 1554. Likewise the
Pseudomartyrologist hath in his Martyrologe
noted <hi>William Richardson</hi> to haue beene executed
Feb. 27. 1603. which might seeme to be in the
first yeare of King <hi>Iames,</hi> which yet was in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
end of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and in the yeare of
our Lord 1602. according as in that yeare in the
table following you may see.</p>
   <p>Now hauing compared their numbers toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
I could not but admire their jmpudency in
that voyde of shame, modesty, religion, christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity,
they dare so publiquely and vnjustly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
blushing, reuile and slaunder so gracious a
Princesse as was noble Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and so mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull
a King as is our Soueraigne Lord K. <hi>Iames,</hi>
considering that so many more suffered in the lesse
<pb n="9" facs="7"/>
then six yeares raigne of Queene <hi>Marie</hi> onely for
religion, then haue sithence by their owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
beene executed in fiftie yeares of two
succeeding Princes (and those not for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
but for their treasons) the number of
the true Martyrs noted in print, being in all by
this account almost 300. and the number of their
Seminary Priests, Iesuites, and Recusants, by their
own account not fully 200. which (number and
time considered) is more then tenne for one. Nor
is there a greater disproportion in the number,
then in the causes of their sufferings, the former
suffering only for their conscience, the latter for
their treasons.</p>
   <p>I am not ignorant that our aduersaries do taxe
<hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Fox</hi> of many<note n="f" place="margin">Three con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versions of England in page 426. and many pages therof besides</note> vntruths and many strange
matters, whose errors, if any such were, I will not
maintaine, but somewhat excuse by way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimination,
by cyting out of this my popish Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
some such stories of his Saints Miracles, as I
find in his sayd Martyrologe expressed (which he
hath diuided according to the moneths of the
yeare) leauing the truth and likely-hoode to thy
censure.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>¶ Popish Miracles.</head>
      <p>ANd first in the moneth of Ianuary;<note place="margin">Ianuary 7. Page 7.</note> I find
this storie, that when Saint <hi>Chad</hi> Bishop of
<hi>Litchfield</hi> dyed, his brother <hi>Ceds</hi> soule (who was
before Bishop of <hi>London)</hi> was seene to descend
<pb n="10" facs="8"/>
from heauen with a troupe of Angels, to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
the same to heauen.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Another.</head>
      <p>ST. <hi>Egwine</hi> Bishop of <hi>Worcester,</hi>
         <note place="margin">Ianuary. 11. Page 10.</note> made a payre
of Iron shackles, locked them close about his
legges, then cast the keyes therof into the Riuer
of <hi>Seuerne,</hi> and so went to <hi>Rome</hi> with <hi>Offa</hi> King
of <hi>Mercia:</hi> desiring of God, that the said shackles
might not be loosed from his legges, vntill he had
made satisfaction for all the sinnes of his youthfull
yeares: and in his returne backe, as he came o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
the sea, vpō a soden a fish leaped into the Ship
wherein he sayled, which being taken and killed,
the foresayd keyes of the shackles that hee had
throwne into the Riuer, were found in the fishes
belly, which hee applying to his shackles, forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
vnlocked them.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Another.</head>
      <p>IN <hi>North-wales</hi> the commemoration of <hi>S. Beno</hi>
Priest,<note place="margin">Ianuary 14. Page 12.</note> who leading an Eremiticall life in the
west parts of <hi>England,</hi> was by an Angell admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed
to goe into <hi>Wales</hi> to a Noble man called
<hi>Trebuith, S. Wenefrides</hi> Father, who gaue him a
part of his lands and possessions to build a Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie,
as also his Daughter <hi>Wenefride</hi> to be instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
and brought vp in a religious manner: whose
head being soone after cut off by <hi>Cradocus</hi> sonne
<pb n="11" facs="8"/>
to <hi>Alane</hi> King of the same Country, for not
yeilding to his vnlawfull lust, he miraculously set
on againe, shee liuing fifteene yeares after.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Another.</head>
      <p>ST. <hi>Elsted</hi> virgin,<note place="margin">Ianuary 20. Page 18.</note> and afterward Abbesse; it
happened vnto her that before shee was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen
Abbesse, shee being in the Church at Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins
before day, with the rest of her sisters, going
into the middest according to the custome, to
reade a lesson, the candle wherewith shee sawe
to read chanced to be put out, and therevppon
wanting light, there came from the fingers of her
right hand such an exceeding brightnesse vppon
the suddaine, that not onely her selfe, but all the
rest of the Quire might see to read by it also. And
hauing another time giuen much to relieue the
poore, whereby her chests were emptyed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
therefore for her lauishnes checked by the
Procurator of the house, she made moane to the
Lord, and her Chests were againe myraculously
filled as before.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Another.</head>
      <p>ST. <hi>Wereburge;</hi>
         <note place="margin">February 3. Page 32.</note> she vpon her death bed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
her body to be buried at <hi>Hamburge,</hi>
but contrary to her will it was carried to the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nastery
of <hi>Trickingham,</hi> where (the gates fast loc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked)
the same was kept and watched very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.
<pb n="12" facs="9"/>
But see a woonder, they that kept it fell
into a sleepe, so as the people of <hi>Hamburge</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
in the night to fetch the bodie away, the
gates of the Church and Monasterie were ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
without hands, of themselues, and so they
carryed the bodie and buried it at <hi>Hamburge,</hi> as
before she requested.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Another.</head>
      <p>ST. <hi>Patrick:</hi>
         <note place="margin">March 17. Page 17.</note> he obtained by his Prayers, that
no venomous creature should liue or breed
in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Another.</head>
      <p>ST. <hi>Richard</hi> Bishop of <hi>Chichester:</hi>
         <note place="margin">Aprill 3. Page 86.</note> he dyed at
<hi>Douer</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> his body being brought to <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chester,</hi>
so shined with Miracles that (besides o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers)
he raysed vp three dead men againe to life.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Another.</head>
      <p>ST. <hi>Frithstan;</hi>
         <note place="margin">Aprill 9. Page 92.</note> one euening as hee was saying
Masse, as he walked in the Churchyard, when
he came to the words, <hi>Requiescant in pace,</hi> the
voyces in the graues round about, made answere
aloud and said, Amen.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Another.</head>
      <p>ST. <hi>Pyran:</hi>
         <note place="margin">May 2. Page 116.</note> he sustained tenne Armies of men
for eight daies with the flesh of three Kine,
and also raysed diuers dead men to life.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <pb n="13" facs="9"/>
      <head>Another.</head>
      <p>ST. <hi>Sewell:</hi>
         <note place="margin">Maye 18.</note> he for his integritie and innocency
of life was such, and so acceptable to God, that
it pleased his diuine Maiestie in signe thereof, to
worke miracles by him both aliue and dead; and
among others, it is recorded, that lying on his
death-bed he turned water into wine, by onely
blessing it.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Another.</head>
      <p>KIng <hi>Henrie</hi> the sixt:<note place="margin">Maye 22. Page 134.</note> his veluet Hat which he
vsed to weare, being put on mens heads that
were troubled with the head-ache, they were
presently cured.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Another.</head>
      <p>ONe of the souldiers that led S. <hi>Alban</hi> to his
death,<note place="margin">Iune 22. Page 167.</note> repented when he saw the constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
of the Martyr, &amp; asked him forgiuenes, which
the persecutors beholding, they grieuously tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented
him for the same, but he following S. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi>
to his death when S. <hi>Albans</hi> head was cut off,
he tooke it vp and embraced it in his armes, and
thereby was immediatly cured of all his wounds.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Another.</head>
      <p>ST. <hi>Swithine:</hi>
         <note place="margin">Iuly 2. Page 178.</note> he, when by a mischance a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
had broken all her egges, made the signe
of the crosse ouer the same egges, and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atlie
they all became whole againe.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <pb n="14" facs="10"/>
      <head>Another.</head>
      <p>THe heads of <hi>Wiaman,</hi>
         <note place="margin">Iuly 25. Page 202.</note>
         <hi>Vnaman,</hi> and <hi>Sunaman,</hi>
being cut off and cast into a poole by the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
of Christ, S. <hi>Sigfride</hi> on a time walking by
the poole and deploring their deaths, on a sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine
there appeared three miraculous lights vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
the water, which encompassed the vessell
wherein their sayd heads were; which he seing,
presently leaped into the poole, and embracing
them wept and sayd, <hi>Vindicet Deus.</hi> Whereto
one answered, <hi>Vindicatūerit;</hi> another replyed, <hi>in
quem?</hi> the third added, <hi>in filios filiorum.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Another.</head>
      <p>A Monke of a certaine Monastery whereof
S. <hi>Alexander</hi> was,<note place="margin">August 6. Page 216.</note> comming to the said <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexanders</hi>
tombe to pray, and hauing an vlcer in
his breast which was now growne to a fistula; <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi>
appeared vnto him brighter then the
Sun, with two Crownes, one on his head, and
another in his hand. The Monke demaunded
what that double Crowne meant? he answered:
The Crowne in his hand is for the temporall
Crown which he forsook for Christs loue (for he
shold haue bin king of <hi>Scotland,</hi> being next heire
thereto, as the story reporteth) the other on my
head, is that which I haue receaued common
with other Saints. And that you may be assured
of the verity of this vision, you shall be presently
cured of your infirmity; and hauing thus spoken
<pb n="15" facs="10"/>
and the other jmmediatly healed, he vanished a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Another.</head>
      <p>ST. <hi>Decuman</hi> first passed ouer the Riuer of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne</hi>
miraculously with a faggot in steed of a
boate,<note place="margin">August 27. Page 233.</note> and afterwards was slaine by a <hi>Pagan</hi> and
his head cut off, which hee tooke vp from the
ground and carryed it to a fountaine where hee
was woont to wash it.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Another.</head>
      <p>ST. <hi>Dunstan:</hi>
         <note place="margin">September 7. Page 244.</note> hee on a time, when the diuell
appeared vnto him in the likenesse of a yong
woman tempting him to vncleanesse, tooke
a paire of pincers which lay by him, and caught
the diuell by the vpper lippe, and so holding him
fast, and leading him vp and downe his chamber,
after diuers jnterrogatories droue him away.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Another.</head>
      <p>ST. <hi>Osith:</hi> shee after that the Danes had cut off
her head,<note place="margin">October 7. Page 372.</note> tooke it vp in her hands and carryed
it three furlongs to a Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and S.
<hi>Paul,</hi> whither when she came all jmbrued in her
owne innocent bloud, she fell downe, and so en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
the course of her Martyrdome.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Another.</head>
      <p>ST. <hi>Keyna:</hi>
         <note place="margin">October 8. Page 374.</note> she by her prayers turned a wood
full of Serpents into stones, still retayning the
likenesses of Serpents: Also she being ready
<pb n="16" facs="11"/>
to depart out of this world, an Angel came downe
from heauen, and put vpon her a white garment
wrought with Gould, bidding her to be in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinesse
to enter into the kingdome of her cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiall
Spouse.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Another.</head>
      <p>ST. <hi>Edmund:</hi>
         <note place="margin">Nouēber 20. Page 320.</note> hee hauing his head cut off by
the Danes, and cast into a wood neere by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
bryars and bushes, the Christians af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards
seeking for the same, lost themselues in
the same wood, and calling one to another, where
art? where art? the head answered, Here, Here,
Here, by which they found out the same.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Another.</head>
      <p>ST. <hi>Inthware:</hi>
         <note place="margin">Decēber 23. Page 350.</note> she hauing her head cut off by
her owne brother <hi>Bana</hi> vppon a day as shee
came from Church, because shee was accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
by her stepmother to be an harlot, her jnno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency
was presently testified by this, for that she
presently tooke it vp in her owne hands and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed
it to the Church from whence shee came.
Adde hereto also their late coyned (Death deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
for the fact) woonder of <hi>Garnets</hi> face in a
wheat strawe. <hi>Vide librum cuius titulipars est, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra
historia de admirabili spica.</hi> Rightly englished,
A fabulous story of a fained straw, first divulged
by a foolish Iack-daw.</p>
      <p>Many more such grosse and palpable lying
woonders are therein expressed, which I am
<pb n="17" facs="11"/>
weary to recount, and I almost wonder that
they themselues are not ashamed to record for
truths; but as herein, so also in their false accusati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and King <hi>Iames,</hi> by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justly
and maliciously taxing them with bloud,
breach of promise, and bloudy persecution for
conscience, they are most jmpudent and shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse,
yea past shame and past grace; for as a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend
<note n="g" place="margin">D. <hi>Barlow</hi> in his answere to M. <hi>Brough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi>
         </note> Father of our Church elsewhere vpon
another occasion (though more rightly applya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
to this generation) said, <hi>Qui semel modestiae
limites transilijt, knauiter fit impudens.</hi> But the
Priests and Iesuites in this poynt of jmpudency
surpasse, and one maine reason hereof, as I take it,
is because they hold the laye Papists, of whome
they haue their maintenance, in such a thraldome
of jgnorant obedience, as that they dare not for
feare of damnation read any booke whereby to
enforme them in the truth, but only such as their
traiterous and seditious vn-ghostly leaders shall
permit: And so if they can hold the good opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of their maintainers, they will neuer blush at
whatsoeuer themselues say, or whatsoeuer bee
said of them by others.</p>
      <p>If any friend shall thinke that this my labour
might well haue beene spared, because the liues
of the Martyrs, the proceedings against them, &amp;
the times and causes of their sufferings are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
by <hi>M</hi>
         <seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Foxe</hi> in his large Booke thereof
more fully expressed; or otherwise should thinke
that I do the Papists too great a grace, by placing
<pb n="18" facs="12"/>
them in the same Booke with the true Martyrs of
Christ; to him in friendly manner I thus replye,
and first to the first. That though his allegation
bee indeed true (for I willingly confesse that hee
hath deserued much for his extraordinary paines
that wayes, and hath compassed so much and
such variety of matter therein, as that I cannot
say whether were greater,<note place="margin">1610.</note> his labour or the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
profit) yet cannot euery mans purse reach
so great price as is that<note n="h" place="margin">The booke at large (wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tē in letters of gould) is this yeare newly and well prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Companie of Stationets in London.</note> Booke at large; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides
I haue not medled with any matter of Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storie
contained therin, but only haue borrowed
out of him the names of such as were in Queene
<hi>Maries</hi> daies burned, as I haue likewise out of their
Martyrologist the names of their Priests, Iesuites,
and Recusants, for vnlesse I should set downe
their names, I could make no good comparison
of their numbers in opposition one to the other;
which is the especiall end whereat I aime.</p>
      <p>Secondly, although that twentie or thirtie
yeares, since many hundreds of Thousands of
persons were liuing that could <hi>viva voce</hi> beare
record how cruelly and vnmercifully the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors
of Christs truth were dealt withall in
Queene <hi>Maries</hi> daies, and could also (if any sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
Priest or Iesuite had accused their Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
of cruelty) haue thus replyed, <hi>Away
vild harlots, belie her not, fox Queene</hi> Elizabeth <hi>was
a mercifull Queene, but mine eies haue seene the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance
of bloud shed in Queene</hi> Maries <hi>raigne
onely for conscience, wherwith ye were neuer glutted,</hi>
         <pb n="19" facs="12"/>
but now these <hi>Viue-speakers</hi> in Christs cause be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
by time consumed, it is more needfull to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue
by these neuer-dying memorials, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance
of their sufferings, especially seeing
the aduersarie is so busie by all meanes that the
Pope, the Diuell, or hell it selfe can possibly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise
to exalt their faction, and to bring a scandall
both vpon our Soveraignes, vs, and them.</p>
      <p>And to the second poynt; That it is a Grace
vnto the Papists and Romanists to haue their
Priests and Iesuites ranked with the true Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors,
I answere thus: It is not the punishment,
nor the place, but onely the cause that maketh
a man famous for vertue, or for vice jnfamous,
loued of God for his owne free graces, or hated
of God and good men for their villanies.</p>
      <p>If the Iron barres whereon <hi>Catesbies</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi>
heads are fixed and nailed on the Parliament
house, be a grace vnto them or any of their fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites,
because they possesse the highest places of
that Honourable house; such grace haue all the
kings enemies. If <hi>Garnets</hi> scaffold because it was
raysed aloft for more publique view, were an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
vnto him or any of his Iesuited society, such
honour haue all that are, were, or hereafter shall
be his partakers. If <hi>London</hi> bridge or Newgate
grace that faction, because their friends dismem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred
limbes are so highly thereon aduanced; let
Crowes and Rauens likewise deuour all them
that deserue the like grace for the like jnfidelity.
Lastly, if <hi>Iudas</hi> their fellow-traitor can any whit
<pb n="20" facs="13"/>
at all grace them because he is noted in the booke
of God, (but with this foule addition, Traitour)
let them likewise take him and make him a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of their Company, or rather jncorporate
themselues into his Society, but let all that beare
ill will to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Kings
Majestie as a principall member thereof; let I
say, their ends (oh God) be like vnto their master
<hi>Iudas,</hi> and let their bowels breake in sunder that
would eat out the bowels of thy Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi>
and let this blacke word of Traitour bee
the jndelible spot, neuer to bee washed away,
wherewith I brand all English Italionated Priests
and Iesuites, and their Abbettors. Adde to these
also the <hi>Iacobine</hi> Fryer and <hi>Rauilack,</hi> the two mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers
of two French kings <hi>Henry</hi> 3. &amp; <hi>Henry</hi> 4.
(for these are also Sons of one Father the Pope,
the Deuill their Grandfather, and those before,
their brethren in iniquity, neuer to be spoken of
but to their shame with posterity,) the felicity of
whose Raigne (namely <hi>Henrie</hi> the 4.) and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
gouernment, free from danger of any despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
attempt of stabbing or poysoning, or other
attempt of perill to his person by any of <hi>Romes</hi>
fauourites, our english Popish Recusants <hi>(scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
loquor)</hi> before that inhumane and hellish fact
committed pleaded and strongly argued to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
from that lenitie of his, in permitting a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
of conscience to his subiects in matter of
Religion; whereby they would inferre, that if our
Kings Maiestie would desire to liue securely
<pb n="21" facs="13"/>
from any such attempts, not needing to feare pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill
either by stabbing, poysoning, powder, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise,
then let a toleration begraunted; but
how sound their conclusion is, <hi>France</hi> hath felt,
<hi>England</hi> may feare, and all the world is amazed
thereat.</p>
      <p>For if the King of <hi>France</hi> being a Papist, and at
most but suspected to affect the Protestant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
could not yet be secure in his person, how
much lesse can our King expect any assurance
of saftie by a toleration, his Majesty being him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
a professed Protestant, and directly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site
in Faith and Religion. Nay it might rather
bee much feared, that it would bee a meanes to
pull Gods just judgements vpon him and vs, for
permission of such false worshippe of the true
God; for so wee may read in diuers places of
the Old Testament, that when the Rulers of the
people fell away from God, God sent vpon them
many plagues, miseries, and oppressions by
their enemies. And thus much in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere
to the second poynt, which
my friend may obiect.</p>
      <closer>
         <signed>Thine in all Christian loue, <figure>
               <figDesc>monogram incorporating the letters 
FRANCIS BTO (?and U)</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>