<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118690_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00544</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10682</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118690</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discouery of the abhominable delusions of those, who call themselues the Family of loue : Wherein their false Christ, and false profession is plainely laide open; and all their grosse cauils cleerely confuted</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 17-99, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>AMong the many Tares that the Enuious man hath sowen in these last Dayes of the world; there are two principall ones, by which he so preuayleth (among them that acknowledge a Christ) that hee bringeth many millions of soules to eternall perdition; which wee earnestly beseech may be seriously considered. One is: a perswasion he worketh in many, that if they haue the knowledge of Christ in wordes, and doe make a profession of him with their lips &amp; mouth. and so are accounted Christians by name, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing some obseruations, which haue a shew of his sacred Commaundements, although in deede and Truth they bee the inuentions of Men; this they thinke &amp; are perswaded is Christianity effectuall, and will serue sufficiently to bring them to heauen.</p>
   <p>A second is: that when the Deuill seeth he cannot preuayle with diuers in this perswation, but that they see Christianity is another thing, then a bare profession of Christ; then by little and little hee throweth them vpon these fearefull rockes of Familisme; to beleeue and be perswaded, that true Christianity, and the worship of God, is onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the heart, &amp; not at all in any outward ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruatiō, or Bodily performance whatsoeuer: and that the knowledge of a Christ, who by his bodily Death suffered for our sinnes, is needlesse; which being effectually wrought in their hearts, they growe presently to a loathing of the true Christ.
<pb facs="3"/>and the bodily obseruation of all Christs Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for the gathering of his Church: for his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery: for his Worship: and for his Church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, and all the appertainings thereof: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and contending against all, that in the feare of God, stand for the maintainance of them. And not so onely, but also defend with a high hand, that men may be saued, without knowledge or Faith in the Blood of the man Christ; and that Christians ought to subiect their bodyes at the Magistrates commaund, in all outward reuerence, at any Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous abhomination, Mahometisme, Papisme, or whatsoeuer, keeping their hearts to God: all which commaunds of the Magistrates, they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count but Idle vanities, as shall be shewed.</p>
   <p>And for the spreading of these, and many other most fearefull thinges; the Deuill hath raised vp <hi>H.N.</hi> the most skilfull workman of this Craft: and for his Successors (though botchers in respect of their Master) <hi>M.P.</hi> who calleth himselfe the mighty Prince of the <hi>Hebrewes;</hi> and his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant; who writeth thus:<note place="margin">Seruant of M.P. a true Certif. cap. <hi>1.</hi> sect. <hi>10.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>It is not the pride of our manly being, that wee meane to be equall in this or that, but onely we meane God to be the very fame in</hi> M. P. <hi>and the seruant of</hi> M.P. <hi>that he was in</hi> H.N. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> These hauing written diuers Bookes, many of which wee haue read, by which they haue gotten many Disciples, especially such, as hauing knowne much truth (which vsually is accompaned with the Crosse of
<pb facs="3"/>Christ) haue not onely forsaken that truth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they were enlightened, but now doe most wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully blaspheme it; whose vniust accusation of vs, and proude boasts, occationeth the publishing of this little worke.</p>
   <p>And although these especially be delt with, yet there are diuers others (who will not be called Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milists) that are deeply tainted with diuers of these things; some, called the scattered flocke, who agree with the former, <hi>that they may remaine in</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon,<note place="margin">A litle booke to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> pa. <hi>113.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>and there mourne &amp; tarry, &amp;c.</hi> And what account they make of the Lords Ordinances, may appeare by that they write of Baptisme,<note place="margin">In T.L. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertis. pa. <hi>5.8</hi>
      </note> which they say, <hi>is teares: teares is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> water in Baptisme, &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Another sort there are, who although they haue not the name of Familists, in that they dislike ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their blasphemies, yet are dangerously affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with one of their maine grounds: They cry out against outward Church: Ministery: Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship: and Church gouernment: and feeke and sue to the Magistrate for reformation thereof; which when they cannot obtaine, they submit, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly perswade others to submit to those thinges, (which being against their Consciences) they cry out of, onely to auoyde the crosse of Christ; and they perswade the people, that seeing they haue had comfort in that estate, although the thinges they practice be most vile, yet they may remaine in the practice thereof: and they being reproued for speaking euill of that they practice, and submit to,
<pb facs="4"/>they haue Fig-leaues to couer this their naked hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie; and when the examples of the Disciples and Churches of Christ are brought to reproue their courses; they answer: These were inuisible Churches; the Elect in the outward Church; and diuers such fancies, whose courses herein, are met withall in this writing following.</p>
   <p>The meane betwixt these we desire to walke in, not approuing it sufficient for iustification, to haue a Fleshly knowledge of Christ onely; or to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect to any outward obseruation or bodily seruice where the soule or affection is wanting: For in all the Ordinances of Christs Gospell, <hi>nothing auay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth but a new creature:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gal. 6.15. 2. Cor. 5.17 Ioh. 3.5.</note>
      <hi>and if any be in</hi> Christ <hi>he is a new creature: &amp; none can enter into the kingdome of heauen, except he be borne again.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But we doe abhorre any hypocriticall conceipts, which indeed are deceits, where the knowledge and Faith of Christ after the flesh, and those bodily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruations that Iesus Christ cōmaundeth, is dispi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and made of none effect; yea where in stead thereof any manner of Idol-seruice is set vp and outwardly reuerenced. Christ telleth vs, <hi>It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth vs to fulfill all righteousnes,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math. 3.</note> in bodily washing or <hi>Baptizing:</hi> and <hi>as often as wee eate that bread of Cōmunion,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.26.</note>
      <hi>and drinke that Cup, we shew forth the Lords death, till hee come.</hi> God hath made our Bodies, redeemed them, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serueth them,<note place="margin">Psal. 119.113.</note> and will glorifie them; so as we will glorifie him with both, in <hi>abhorring vaine inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb facs="4"/>and louing his Law.</hi> Christ hath coupled soule and body together, and let no man seperate them, in his seruice. If bodily obseruations be aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned in the Cōmandements of the first table con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the worship of God,<note place="margin">Mat. 23.38.</note>
      <hi>which is the great Commandement:</hi> and that we may with our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes performe any worship, why is not the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the second Table, our duty towards man abandoned in all bodily obseruations? and that our bodyes may steale, Whore, Lye, Murther, and what not? which thing the oldest Father of this Family doth not sticke at, as is shewed. Pag. <hi>54.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In dealing with this wofull people, let none take offence that wee speake sharply to them, but consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the causes thereof. They haue bene and are the greatest enemies of righteousnes that euer were, faining a God, and a Christ, according to their owne fleshly hearts: and haue more peruerted the straight way of the Lord, then euer did any; and therefore we hauing Christ and his Apostles for our example herein, wee trust none will condemne vs, but those that are touched: for if any be offended at this our Discouery, it is testimony suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient what they are; wee mention the names of none, least they should haue colour to say we perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute them. The wicked and hypocriticall <hi>Scribes and Pharises for whom was reserued the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Hell.</hi> Elimas <hi>the Sorcerer,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 23.33.</note> Iannes <hi>and</hi> Iambres, Hymeneus <hi>&amp;</hi> Philetus, and all the rest, whose fearefull iudgements are written; are not so
<pb facs="5"/>wicked in their blasphemies as these are, as shall plainely appeare; and therefore let all pronounce against them the iudgements that are written, that others may heare and feare, and doe no more such wickednes.</p>
   <p>It is meerly for want of loue of the Truth that men are giuen vp to such fearefull delusions; from which, that we may be deliuered, let vs follow the Truth, and that in loue; which truth is contained in the holy Scriptures, and not in the Dreames of <hi>H.N.</hi> or any other.<note place="margin">Heb. 1.2.</note>
      <hi>In these last dayes the Father hath spoken by his Son</hi> Iesus Christ; <hi>who was faithfull as</hi> Moses.<note place="margin">Heb. 3.2. Act. 3.22. Mat. 17.5. Act. 3.23. Gal. 1.8.</note> Moses <hi>sends vs to him. The Father sends vs to him. And hee that will not heare this</hi> Prophet <hi>shall be destroyed.</hi> And <hi>cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed shall he be, that teacheth otherwise</hi> then hee hath taught by himselfe &amp; his Apostles. <hi>And his Name shall be taken out of the booke of Life, that taketh from it,<note place="margin">Reuel. 22.18.19.</note> and the plagues which are writen shalbe added to him, that addeth to the wordes of this Sonne of God.</hi> All which the Lords mouth hath spoken.</p>
   <p>Thus haue we taken this paines for the sake of those that are ignorant of these things; to the and that they seeing the Pit, may be warned, and saued from falling into it; which God for his Christs sake, Grant to euery soule. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>