<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the vnresolued Reader, Peace and Profit.</title>
           <author>H., C.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118919_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14210</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24526</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118919</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the vnresolued Reader, Peace and Profit.</title>
                 <author>H., C.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Romane conclaue : VVherein, by way of history, exemplified vpon the liues of the Romane emperours, from Charles the Great, to Rodulph now reigning; the forcible entries, and vsurpations of the Iesuited statists, successiuely practised against the sacred maiestie of th said empire: and so by application, against the residue of the Christian kings, and free-states are liuely acted, and truely reported. By Io. Vrsinus ante-Iesuite</title>
                 <author>Beringer, Joachim</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Jaggard (Jagger), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 167, 176-243, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶To the vnresolued Reader, Peace and Profit.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N <hi>Disputations</hi> words multiply words: In tedious Discourses (for the most part) groūded vpon the sole Authority of running reason, small satisfaction is afforded to weake consciences. In this Argument, I must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, matters of weightie consequence are debated; The <hi>Romish Prelates</hi> are accused of <hi>Intrusion</hi> and <hi>Vsurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> And they againe, as stiffely maintaine <hi>faire</hi> and <hi>filiall vsage,</hi> with <hi>successiue diuolution.</hi> To what purpose were it then, for any man how learned, or zealous soeuer, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force his vtmost indeuours, to put end to a Controuersied question; If when all hath beene said, that <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> can alleadge: Euery passionate and discontented Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morist may take vpon him with colours and cunning di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctions, to oppose and contradict his opposites Assertions. In this case, what conscience can but remaine distracted in <hi>vtramque partem</hi>? The Disputants on either side, are men of admirable reputation for their learning. Both of them bring warrant (or at least) seeme to bring warrant to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their partie. Yet oftentimes vpon priuate passion, so impertinently and maliciously, that either they seeme not to haue read the Authours whome they quote; Or hauing read them, they doe not vnderstand them, or vnderstanding them, they doe of purpose misconster them. Vpon which conceite it should seeme, that this our <hi>Ante-Iesuite,</hi> in as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured
<pb facs="3"/>
hope to worke more by <hi>Example,</hi> then <hi>Discourse,</hi> hath purposely declined these ambiguous Disputations; And in liew therof hath brought vpon the stage of <hi>Iudgement, Time</hi> and <hi>Testimonie, Veritatis parentes,</hi> to pleade no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for themselues, but <hi>matter on Record.</hi> A course that hath seldome in so doubtfull a Controuersie beene pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to Audience. The <hi>Remembrancers</hi> were men <hi>without Exception,</hi> and some of them by testimonies on either side, <hi>Genere, pietate, &amp; eruditione Nobilissimi, at{que} harum rerum Testes pene oculati</hi>: Their names and credits you are acquainted with; your vnderstandings will informe you of their Maners, and the Times, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and vnder whome they flourished. Nothing then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth, but a rectified conscience, to make true vse of the Application. Which to effect, behold our <hi>Ante-jesuite,</hi> hath not onely runne the truest and plainest Path-way to confidence, but also in old and auncient fashion, hath of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose thus attired his Actors, that the busiest-headed Iesuite that euer put pen to Paper, may rather with impudencie cauill at <hi>Antiquitie,</hi> then with his fierie wit, become a stumbling-blocke to the wauering, by <hi>Excepting</hi> to his Pen or Person. You your selues sit Iudges; and as vnpreiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated Arbitrators examine the Pleas: Both parties are at the Barre, and shall produce their best Titles, euen Titles of prescription. Whereunto, how-euer <hi>Paul</hi> plant, or <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo</hi> water, Let that great God who searcheth the reines, and loueth nothing but Trueth, giue a plentifull increase to the restauration of his reformed kingdome, <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in Assurance,</hi> C. H.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>