<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the moste renoumed Prince, Lewes of Borbon, Prince of Condey, &amp;c. and other famous and noble Dukes, Mar∣queses, Erles, Barons &amp; Lordes of the Nobilitie, that embrace the true Gospell of Christe in the realme of Fraunce. Theodorus Beza Vezelius a minister of the Church of Geneua, wisheth grace and peace, from God the Father and our Lorde Iesus Christe.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1568</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118060_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13257</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23554</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118060</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the moste renoumed Prince, Lewes of Borbon, Prince of Condey, &amp;c. and other famous and noble Dukes, Mar∣queses, Erles, Barons &amp; Lordes of the Nobilitie, that embrace the true Gospell of Christe in the realme of Fraunce. Theodorus Beza Vezelius a minister of the Church of Geneua, wisheth grace and peace, from God the Father and our Lorde Iesus Christe.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A confession of fayth : made by common consent of diuers reformed churches beyonde the seas: with an exhortation to the reformation of the Churche. Perused and allowed accordinge to the Queenes Maiesties iniunctions</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wykes (Wekes), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Harrison, Luke (Lucas)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1568</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>42, 112 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="exhortation_to_reformation_of_church">
   <pb facs="13"/>
   <head>To the moste renoumed Prince, Lewes of Borbon, Prince of Condey, &amp;c. and other famous and noble Dukes, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queses, Erles, Barons &amp; Lordes of the Nobilitie, that embrace the true Gospell of Christe in the realme of Fraunce. Theodorus Beza Vezelius a minister of the Church of <hi>Geneua,</hi> wisheth grace and peace, from God the Father and our Lorde Iesus Christe.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Present vnto</hi> thée most renoumed Prince, and to the <note place="margin">VVhat is true nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie?</note> residue of you that are made noble by the true knowledge of Christe, through the mercie of our most mercifull and heauenly Father, the bookes of the newe Testament: which were translated into Latine by me, a fewe yeares by passed, &amp; are now againe perused by me, with as great
<pb facs="14"/>
fidelitie and diligence as I could possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and set foorth with certaine briefe summaries of the doctrine therein cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehēded, a present vnto the Churches of God (of whome you are the tutors fosters and norishinge Fathers by the <note place="margin">The noble are the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishers of the church.</note> decrée of the moste Christian Kinge) would to God so profitable, as I truste vnto you it shal be pleasant and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. For why should not I promise my self this of you, who haue so stoute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and constantly declared before the whole worlde that you are not asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the Gospell of Christe: and to whome (I woulde knowe) rather then to you (whiche doo not onely approue &amp; allowe the doctrine here taught, but set it at libertie, and restore it) shoulde I dedicate these my poore trauayles? But what néede we these trauayles shal some say? Beholde therfore I will recite the reasons more at large that haue moued me hereunto.</p>
   <p>Those men are altogether intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and in no case to be suffered, who for the desire of Nouelty, doo cōdemne <note place="margin">Antiquitie may not be</note> Antiquitie, like as also those are woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie
<pb facs="14"/>
great reproche, whiche can finde <note place="margin">condemned onely for desire of Noueltie.</note> taste in nothinge but in that whiche is olde and auncient. For I praye you, were they not al once new which now are olde &amp; auncient? And this can not be denied of any, that will confesse the truth without contention, that euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more in all worldes there were some, <note place="margin">Errours are olde.</note> that either of ignorance, or of set pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, did darken and obscure the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest truth of God. And also this is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dēt (though God did neuer so seuerely punishe the infidelitie of the worlde, that he did leaue his Churche vtterly destitute of the true knowledge of his woorde) yet that there was not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies the like measure of knowledge, no not in those things y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> are the chiefe pointes of our Religion. So that some most false and daūgerous errours are very auncient, in so muche that <hi>Paule</hi> him selfe of olde time did write vnto the <hi>Thessalonians,</hi> sayinge: Nowe the misterie of iniquitie is already in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge. And <hi>Iohn</hi> saide, that euen then were many Antichristes in the world. <note place="margin">Antichriste is olde.</note> Howbeit no man can easely finde sure
<pb facs="15"/>
and certaine remedies for these euels <note place="margin">The wante of the woorde is the cause of all errour.</note> and diseases, saue onely that knoweth the right and true causes of them, the whiche causes in déede are many, but they flowe all as it were foorth of one fountaine: that is, because that men turne from the woorde of God, frō the woorde I saye, that is conteined in the bookes of the Prophets &amp; the Apostles, vnto theyr owne dreames and inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. For that light beyng once ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away (the whiche who so doth not sée to be the onely and singuler light, seeth nothinge at all) what can folow, but that like blinde men, they shoulde grope in darkenesse? Neither are they in any wise to be hearde, that are of a contrarie opinion. For what say they, doo not the Heretikes pretende the woorde of God? therefore stande we néede of some one rule whereby y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> false interpretations of the woorde whiche sometime is ambiguous and doubtful, maye be discerned from the true: But <note place="margin">What rule will serue.</note> what rule shall this be?</p>
   <p>One sorte doo here obtrude vnto vs, that their most vaine name of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb facs="15"/>
or Vniuersall, whiche at all times <note place="margin">Catholike.</note> and in euery place; and with all men hath bene receiued. Of whome if thou goe further to aske the question, what is so Catholike? there of necessitie they muste sticke faste in the myre, when the demaūde is made of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> most parte, of the matters that are in cōtrouersie.</p>
   <p>Another sorte set before them selfes the Councels &amp; olde Canons: to whom <note place="margin">Councelles and Canōs.</note> they geue glorious titles, as though thereby the concorde of the Churche might be recouered, but all in vayne: for I doo thinke that no man is now so ignorant, but that he doth know, that many Synodes and Councels (I doo speake of them that are not openly cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned) haue decreed euen in thinges concerning doctrine, not onely darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but also vnlearnedly. Wherfore of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes the Prouincials haue bene corrected by the Generall, and yet the Prouinciall hath sometimes iudged more vprightly then the General. And that the truth was so, euery one maye easely perceiue, that can compare <hi>Gā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grensis</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gangrensis Synode, taught more pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cramentes, &amp;c.</note> Counsell with many that they
<pb facs="16"/>
call generall. I passe ouer that thinge whiche the very History of those times doth moste manifestly proue, that in those which we may call the best times (if they be compared with the latter) there was partly such ambition of the Bishops, partly suche a vaine babling ignorance, and of many of them suche an open and desperate malice, that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <note place="margin">Sathā hath bene the president of some Coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels.</note> blinde men may easely sée that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan was the president of these assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies. What now then if we doo sette before vs the Councels assembled for a rule? since that time that most mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest tyrannie hath oppressed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Church, suche as that late Councell of Trent was? Yea what if those best and moste approued Coūcels determine nothyng of any of the chiefe pointes of Religiō, onlesse it be of one pointe or twaine? Agayne, what if some be corrupted, their Epistels falcified, their decrees fayned, &amp; forged Canons an infinite number cropē into place? That fraude <note place="margin">Pope Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niface did falcifie the Nicene Councell.</note> and crafte of <hi>Boniface,</hi> then Bishop of Rome, whiche was perceiued in the time of <hi>Augustine,</hi> in the <hi>Aphricane</hi>
      <pb facs="16"/>
Councell is not vnknowen: the which yet a certaine foolishe and most wicked <hi>Apostata,</hi> whose impudencie also is wel knowen, went about of late to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse before thée (most noble Prince) To conclude, what haue not these wicked men attempted? and what durste they not take in hande in these Countreis, in the whiche thinges were lawfull that they lusted? Thus muche then for the Councelles.</p>
   <p>Others doo flie vnto the writinges <note place="margin">Those that call moste for the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vvill not allovve the Fathers in all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</note> of those that they call the auncient and Catholike Fathers, but of so greate a nūber of those, whome I pray you shal we choose? for we haue but fewe very ancient (that is to say vnto the time of <hi>Constantine)</hi> emonge whome the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines vndoubtedly were the chiefe: yet are they such as thei that haue the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in most reuerence, will not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether agrée vnto, without many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions.</p>
   <p>Then <hi>Arius</hi> firste occupied the age that folowed, vnto the manifest fall of the Romaine Empire: and after him <hi>Macedonius,</hi> deniyng the holy Spirit
<pb facs="17"/>
to be God, and therefore was called <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. But chiefly <hi>Nestorius</hi> and <hi>Eutyches</hi> in the East, vnto whom the principall &amp; moste excellent wittes did answeare and oppose them selues: neither was there any age that had more plenty of learned Bishops. The secte of the <hi>Pelagians</hi> did occupie the West, whose dregges to this daye doo still destroy the Churche. Here now I require that without the iniurie of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, I maye vtter the matter as it is. Therefore I demaunde this question: <note place="margin">VVhiche of the Fathers shall iudge these con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersies.</note> which one chiefly, or whome of al these Fathers, they wil haue for the iudges &amp; desciders of these controuersies that are at this daye emongst vs? Firste of all, thei them selues (as becōmeth them well) refuse this authoritie: for they crie with one voice, that they doo bring that, whiche the Lorde hath taught: <note place="margin">The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vvill haue the vvoorde of God iudge.</note> and that they will haue their doctrine no farther mainteined then it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the woorde of God written. The saiynges of <hi>Cyprian, Augustine,</hi> and <hi>Chrysostome,</hi> chiefly of all others are euident in this point: wherby they
<pb facs="17"/>
call vs to the onely holy Scripture. I will saye a little more also by the licēce of them, that haue studied their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges. Euen at that time in <hi>Grecia,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Fathers permitted foule er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</note> did Satan lay the first foundations of the inuocation of the dead: the whiche errour the Bishops of moste reputatiō did not onely not resist, neither yet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther godly and learned men (saue for suche faultes) but were occupied to set foorthe their eloquence al together in writinge of their prayses. Others of lesse learnyng busied thēselues wholy in certaine vaine studies, whiche that nation of the Grekes was alwayes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermuche geuen vnto: as to the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge of glorious temples, for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noring of the memories of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Martyrs, and to the heapynge together of cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies. Another sort partely of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rāce, partely of couetousnesse and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, &amp; in the ende of a manifest wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednesse, did not onely not represse those open superstitions, as they did grow, but altogether did norish them. Howbeit in that time, thrée euels did principally reigne: first, that they that
<pb facs="18"/>
had bene brought vp in Philosophie, <note place="margin">Three euels in the dayes of those Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Philosophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note> did not remēber that moste graue and Apostolicall sentence: Take you héede, least any doo spoyle you through Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophie. For besides that thei had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vaine speculations, as in the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng to the Angels the imaginatiōs of <hi>Plato,</hi> concerninge the intelligences &amp; <note place="margin">Platoes su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitious dreames.</note> spirites (the whiche errour séemeth to haue cōtinued from the Apostles time, who cōdemneth plainely the supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion about the Angels) they did mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festly wraste the woorde of God vnto those lessons, that they had learned of the Philosophers. Hereof sprange the opinions, of the powre and frée will of man, whiche are altogether <hi>Aristoteli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aristotels Diuinitie.</note> wherwith at this day the Churche of God is shaken, and had bene troden downe longe ago, had not <hi>Augustine</hi> (prouoked by <hi>Pelagius)</hi> set him selfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainste it: yet to passe many other thinges (whiche I would gladly to be couered as the faultes of the Fathers) he him selfe also sometimes bearing to highe a faile, rusheth vpō the rockes of humane Philosophie. Yet was there
<pb facs="18"/>
an other euell the worst of al, that like <note place="margin">The thirde euell of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legories.</note> as w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> a deadly disease, all mens mindes were infected, with a meruelous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to turne and transforme all the Scriptures into allegories: in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention whereof, euery man thought euery thing in this point to be lawfull to him selfe. <hi>Origene</hi> surely séemeth, to <note place="margin">Origene.</note> haue geuen occasiō to both those euels, of folowyng the Philosophers, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so of the Allegories: whiche was the most vnpure writer (as I do take him) that euer did write vppon the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: whome though many (as he wel deserued) did abhorre, yet some, of the other side, had him in great admiratiō because he was very excellent in the knowledge of the languages, artes and sciences: and some did pursue him rather of enuie then of vpright iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But this euell did not staye in the East, but spredde through <hi>Africke, Italy, France</hi> and <hi>Spayne:</hi> so that all the Scripture was transformed into perpetuall Allegories. In the meane reason <hi>Pelagius</hi> &amp; <hi>Donatus</hi> did arise, against whome God set vp <hi>Augustine</hi>
      <note place="margin">Augustine.</note>
      <pb facs="19"/>
and caused the chiefe pointes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Religion (as of the prouidence &amp; Predestination, of frée will, of faithe, and of Iustificatiō by frée grace, which were almost oppressed by the Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicall Gloses of the <hi>Gretian</hi> bishops, to be knowen and published: and yet notwithstandinge at the same time (whiche is wonderfull) prayer to the dead did growe into vse, and also that foolish opinion of single life: the which shamefull errours <hi>Hyerome</hi> is not <note place="margin">Hierome.</note> ashamed to defende. And the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Ceremonies did encrease, as <hi>Augustine</hi> complayneth to <hi>Ianuarius:</hi> and many did honour the Monkes as they had bene Angels, especially in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> and <hi>Syria,</hi> the most superstitious of all nations: and then began prayers to be made for the dead: &amp; the question of <hi>Plato</hi> of the fire of Purgatorie did <note place="margin">Plato his Purgatory.</note> then arise, the whiche yet was not ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally receyued in the Church, as the writings of <hi>Augustine</hi> doo manifestly declare. Wherefore to returns to the matter, whom of so great a multitude shall we especially choose for iudges: if
<pb facs="19"/>
we will heare that <hi>Apostata</hi> of whome I haue spoken, we muste chouse them that liued about the time of <hi>Theodosi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> the great. And surely I graunt that there was at that time very learned Bishoppes, but yet dare I affirme this thinge (the whiche I doo protest that I doo not speake for the reproche of any) that scarcely any of them cā be named which doth not bothe dissent from him <note place="margin">The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors dissēt one from another.</note> selfe, &amp; from others in many thinges, and those of no small importance. And if peraduenture that <hi>Apostata</hi> (that I did speake of) shall denie it, then let me be counted a lier, onles I doo plainely proue it. But here I knowe what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception he will make: at the leaste by these wryters saith he, it shal appeare, what was the forme &amp; outwarde face of the Catholike Churche. As though <note place="margin">VVhat neede vve seeke for formalitie.</note> this were the chiefe pointe of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie, &amp; not rather of the doctrine it selfe: or as though at all times, al rites &amp; Ceremonies are to be receiued with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, whiche the Apostolike Church it selfe hath vsed either as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable or necessarie for their times:
<pb facs="20"/>
and as though they were not playne <note place="margin">Buylde thy house be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou paynte it.</note> fooles which when the foundations of the houses were al fallē downe, would be so carefull for building vp the roofe? And what néede many woordes? I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose that many of you (most excellent &amp; noble Lordes) haue in your remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance how when we did treate of this matter at Poissy (where we had rather a triflynge skirmishe &amp; alteration then a serious and earnest disputation) we did thus cōclude in fewe woordes: that the waie and meane to finish the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and controuersies, whiche some froward Newtrals and halfefaced mē <note place="margin">Agree of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine then talke of the comely Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies.</note> (to name them no worse) doo so impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunately craue, was first of al, that we should dispute and agrée by the woorde of God, of the doctrine it selfe, and of Faith, the whiche beyng once establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, then should we agrée much more easely about the Ceremonial matters: of the whiche we would reiect some as vaine and foolishe, some as superstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, either by them selues or by circū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances, some as altogether wicked, and some finally we would willingly
<pb facs="20"/>
admit: whiche coulde be proued either profitable or necessarie. What then doo these men require any more? assuredly most noble Prince, they séeke this one thinge, that they may bringe into ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred <note place="margin">Many that seeme qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifiers of these con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersies seeke to spoyle the flocke still vvithout checke.</note> the faithfull Ministers of God, as men seditious, ambitious, and louers of changes, suche as woulde haue all thinges new, that they thēselues may still spoyle and destroy the poore flocke of Christe without controlment. For they are like those without doubte of whome the Lorde speaketh: that they neither will enter into the Kingdome of Heauen thē selues, nor suffer others to enter in. Thei are the most perilous men vndoubtedly, that are suffered <note place="margin">VVho are the moste perilous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies?</note> to liue this day vnder the Sūne: more daungerous by muche, then the open enemies of the Gospell, and therefore ought you principally, that are the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trones and defenders of the Churches of God, (by the most Christian Kinges decrée) to auoyde such men and beware of them: who partely for their bellies sake, partly for lucre, partly for enuie and malice, partely for fauour of them
<pb facs="21"/>
whom they flatter, lie in waite to trap you. But I sée that I haue bene som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what longe in confutinge this opiniō: therefore I doo returne to the matter. For what shall we say or doo to those, which imagine that the publike errour <note place="margin">Publike er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour cā not be the rule of Religiō.</note> muste be folowed for the rule of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion? whiche set the bare names of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and custome against all reasons and proufes? whiche finally doo sticke onely to that one Churche, whiche no <note place="margin">The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists calling one church Vniuersall, ioygne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries.</note> lesse foolishly then falsely they call the Catholike Romish Churche (that is to say an Vniuersall particular Church?) surely I doo thinke that we muste let them alone, least we shoulde séeme to labour to cure madnesse with reason. But now if none of these that we haue <note place="margin">God is the Iudge.</note> spoken of, may sitte as Iudges in this cause, but rather muste be iudged of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in what courte then shall this great controuersie be pleaded? Verely before the iudgemēt seate of God one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Then will they say, let him be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <note place="margin">VVhere shall vvee finde him.</note> downe from his Heauenly palace. Nay why doo they not draw him foorth of these their Chancels and holy cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners?
<pb facs="21"/>
forsooth because we stande in no néede of a dumbe God, that can doo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge but kéepe silence, suche one as their crusted God is in the wafer cake: but of that good God y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> speaketh cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and plainely vnto vs. And I praye you where shall we finde him? no <note place="margin">Not in the Boxe. But in the Scriptures.</note> where doubtles saue in the writinges of those mē of God, who (as <hi>Peter</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesseth) haue bene stirred vp by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost to speake vnto vs: of those I saye vpon whose doctrine as vpon the foundation, the Apostle crieth that the Churche is builded, euen vppon the bookes of the Apostles &amp; the Prophetes whiche are conteined vnder the name of the Olde and new Testament. But say they, the doubt standeth of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation <note place="margin">Obiection.</note> of this woorde whiche we say must be sought at the Church. But first of all we must agrée whiche is the <note place="margin">Ansvveare.</note> Churche: for the Synagoge of Satan also doth abuse that fayre and beutiful name of the Churche. And howe canst thou iudge this same thinge but by the kinde of the doctrine? And how canst <note place="margin">The worde is iudge of the Church</note> thou put a difference betwixt the true
<pb facs="22"/>
doctrine and the false, but by the holy Scriptures? As for that succession wherein some sette all their succour, it hath ceased lōge ago to haue any force or valure, seyng this is most certaine, that the most ignorant and wicked mē haue bene the successours for many yeares vnto the good and learned Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops: <note place="margin">Successiō of doctrine not of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site.</note> and that there doth appeare no steppe or token of any lawfull vocatiō in the Churches now for a longe cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. Furthermore we doo require a succession of doctrine, not of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, euen of the Propheticall and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolicall doctrine, so that of necessitie we must runne againe to the bookes of the Prophetes &amp; the Apostles, for the proofe of the true succession.</p>
   <p>As for the name of Traditions, the <note place="margin">The bare visar of Tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ditions ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not.</note> whiche some also that feare nothinge more then the triall of the Scripture, doo holde foorth as the terrible face of <hi>Gorgon,</hi> what is it els I pray you, but a bare visar? for if it be vnderstande of the doctrine, seyng we haue the woorde writen, what néede we any thing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writen? for surely this vnwriten is
<pb facs="22"/>
more vncertaine thē that writen, and no man maye séeke a proofe at the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaintie of that whiche is certaine. How be it here I doo sée, that many thinges maye be obiected against vs. For first of all they will say, that they vnderstande by the name of Traditiō, <note place="margin">An obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> not that whiche was not writen by no man at all, and onely deliuered from hande to hande, but that which though it be not comprehended in those holy bookes which men call Canonicall, yet may be proued by some other woorthie wryters: so that though at the firste it was vnwriten, yet may nowe woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely be called writen: and suche they call the Traditions of the Apostles. Moreouer they will also alledge that they vnderstand by this name Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, certaine plaine and manifest ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicatiōs of the Christian Faith, which were receiued in the olde Churche, as of Christe, how he is of the same Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance with the Father: and of the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitinge of these two natures, and such like: for these men vse to choose foorth such thinges as are certaine and moste
<pb facs="23"/>
plansible. Now though I suppose that I haue sufficiently answeared vnto these thinges heretofore, when I did speake of the Councels and of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Fathers: yet haue I more <note place="margin">The ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vveare.</note> to answeare. For first of al, they them selues will graunt that all suche Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions are not to be receiued without exceptiō. What rule then shal we kéepe herein? Againe if we depende of mens writinges and authoritie, when the <note place="margin">Mens vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges can not be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</note> question peraduenture is of the rites and ordinaunces, howe many thinges shal we finde not onely diuerse one frō another, but cleane contrarie? when that controuersie of kéepinge the feast of <hi>Pasche</hi> or Easter was in the Church of most ancient time, whiche proued &amp; tried most manifestly the vayne iang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, the ambition, the ignorance, and the frowardnes, of the moste parte of the Bishoppes of the whole worlde: so that the whole worlde was shaken to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, none otherwise then if the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie had bene of the whole Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of our faithe: and bothe parties doo alleadge the Traditiōs of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles:
<pb facs="23"/>
what came to passe at the length, but that both parties hauyng on their side (as thei said) the Apostles, the strife was more styrred. Let y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Epistle of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus</hi> be red, not to one coūted a Pope <note place="margin">By the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus vve may see the libertie in Traditions.</note> &amp; the Vniuersall Bishop of the whole worlde, but to the most foolish &amp; ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious B. of Rome: &amp; therby it may easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be knowen, what libertie hath bene in al Churches hertofore in these rites &amp; ceremonies, vntill by the tiranny of some y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Churches were oppressed. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meane I here to recōpte vp euery thinge, for we had néede of a whole booke so to doo. What then shall we fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low here? That (say they) which shal be foūde euery where to be receyued of al men, as the oyle &amp; creame as they call it, the signe of the Crosse and such like. Thē let vs cōclude this one point, that the particular Traditions beyng shut out and secluded, onely the Catholike and Vniuersall maye be receaued: and of these we shall speake afterwarde.</p>
   <p>Let vs come to the Traditions of <note place="margin">Tvvo good kindes of Traditions.</note> doctrine. They are such, that either to resist the Heretikes, doo make playne
<pb facs="24"/>
certayne thynges taught in the holy Scriptures, whiche the Heretikes doo vse to darkē as thei doo the most cleare matters: or els they doo set foorth suche thinges as may be gathered by the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paringe of the places together, though they be no where writen in the selfe <note place="margin">Euell Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</note> same woordes. Either are they such, as doo either adde or diminishe or alter and change either openly or priuely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thinge in the Propheticall and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolicall writinges. Both those first kinde of Traditions (suche as are the expositions or confessions of the faithe of the foure Councels) we are so farce from refusinge of them, that contrary wise with open armes (as they say) and most willinge mindes we doo embrace all suche.</p>
   <p>But for the thirde kinde of Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions how can we iudge that to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted? <note place="margin">The Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditiōs that adde to the vvorde.</note> for if any thinge ought to be added to the woorde of God written, it foloweth that all thinges necessarie to our Saluation are not writen in the Lawe and the Gospell. But of the law this neither may nor ought to be spokē
<pb facs="24"/>
for then God might séeme vniuste for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddyng by plaine woordes any thinge to be added thereunto. Neither doo I here care for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
      <hi>Cabalistes, Talmudistes,</hi> and all that kinde of shamelesse men. For what can be spokē more plainely by the Lorde? And howe seuerely God hath aduenged this rashnes when any thing was added not onely in doctrine but also in rites, &amp; ceremonies, so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny proclamatiōs of the Prophetes the interpretours of the lawes, criyng out against them, and all the Historie of the Bible, finally Christe him selfe is a sufficiēt witnesse. And shall we thinke y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> God hath cared lesse for his Church, or prouided worse for it, when he sent <note place="margin">Christe and his Apostels sufficient teachers▪</note> his sonne downe into the Earth? or cā we suppose that the Apostles were lesse diligent in this pointe then the Prophetes? <hi>Paule</hi> dothe protest vnto the <hi>Ephesians,</hi> that he had holden no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge backe, but had declared all the counfasle of God vnto them, so farre foorth at the least as appertained vnto their eternall Saluation. Lette them shewe then what <hi>Paule</hi> hath taught
<pb facs="25"/>
that he hath not writen: or els let them confesse the full doctrine of the Gospell (which he calleth the power of God to saluation) to be comprehended in his writinges. But what néede so many woordes? when we come to the pointe what can they bringe foorth that is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in matters of faith by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles and the Euangelistes? Peraduē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that the blessed virgin Mary was <note place="margin">Obiectiōs for Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> not conceiued in Originall sinne: that she continued all hir life longe a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that children muste be Baptised, that Baptisme is not to be reiterated, that men muste fast in Lente, the holy oyle and chreme, the Holy water, that Altars muste be hallowed, the Crosse must be woorshipped, and what ye wil. For they confesse that none of those thinges are founde in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. As for Transubstantiation, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricular confession, praying vnto Sain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes &amp; purgatorie fire, they haue nowe a good while sought thē in Scriptures but all in vaine. But concernynge the maner of conception of the virgine Marie, not onely the holy Scriptures
<pb facs="25"/>
doo not teache it, but neither any of the auncient writers doo make mention of it. And although I doo willingly and reuerently beleue her perpetuall Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginitie vnto death, yet (as I once an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sweared <note place="margin">Ansvveare.</note> to an impudēt Munke in thy presence most noble Prince) this thing perteineth nothinge to the mysterie of our Saluation. For it is sufficient for vs to beleue that whiche is done in déede, &amp; declared by the Euangelistes that Christe our Sauiour was concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the holy Ghost, and borne of the virgine Mary. And that the infantes ought to be Baptised, &amp; that Baptisme may not be reiterate, we doo not gether of any bare Tradition without the woorde of God. As for those other thinges howe can the holy Scriptures expresse them? the which coulde not be established in the Church, but that the authoritie of the woorde of God muste firste be ouerthrowen, as maye be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with moste euident reasons. But this muche at this present, for we doo not vndertake nowe to declare euery particular matter. Wherefore I come
<pb facs="26"/>
to that kinde of Traditions, whereby <note place="margin">Traditions that dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishe.</note> somethinge is taken from the doctrine of the woorde of God written, as when the one parte of the Supper of the Lorde is taken awaye from the Laye men: and when vnto the woordes of <hi>Paule</hi> that calleth the forbiddynge of mariage, and the lawe of forbiddinge of meates, the doctrine of Diuels: there is added the exception of an aduised vowe, and an other generall exceptiō, whiche many will haue to be auaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in all pointes, <hi>Except it please our Lorde the Pope othervvaies.</hi> But who <note place="margin">Blasphemy.</note> I praye you that tendereth the glory of God as he ought to doo, can suffer suche cursed sacriledge? for assuredly if it be lawfull to take away any thing from that doctrine written, then is it necessary that like as these men haue compted the doctrine taught by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghost a littell before, to be haltyng and vnperfecte, and to wante some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, so nowe in other thinges, they may say, that it is redoundant &amp; super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous: neither of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which two things any good mans eares can heare with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="26"/>
great offence. But yet they saye, that no man can denie, but that the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of the lawe are altogether already taken away. Howbeit we doo not treate nowe of the rites and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies; but of the very substāce of the woorship of God, whereof though we doo iudge y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Ceremonies of old to haue bene a portiō, yet serueth this nothing to defende their bolde sacrilege. For what meruell is it, though the lawe whiche was made to shadowe those things whiche were hoped for to come at the time apointed, did vade and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish away at the light and sight of the same? but if these men bringe against vs that the loue feastes called <hi>Agape.</hi> &amp; that Apostolicall decrée of things offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to idols &amp; the strangeled, was takē away by commen consent, &amp; the anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge Apostolical which we haue now abolished. I doo answere againe, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> these are externall thinges of which we shal dispute afterwarde. But this we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude for certaine, that the doctrine of Saluatiō conteyned in Gods woorde, must be mainteyned safe &amp; sounde, not
<pb facs="27"/>
onely in the whole substance but in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery the least and smalest parte therof without addition or diminution.</p>
   <p>Now why should we once name or <note place="margin">VVicked Traditiōs.</note> make mention of that thirde kinde of Traditions, which doo either shake the fundations of the Saluatiō by Christ, eyther ouerthrowe the thynges that are builte vpon that foundation. Such as are the Supremacie of the Bishop of Rome, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> praying to sainctes, prayer for the dead, the makyng and the woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippyng of Idols, the Magistrall and Doctorall determinations (as thei call them) of frée wil, of merite, of pardons and of such other filthinesse, the which thinges séeinge they coulde neuer be established so longe as the authoritie of the Heauenly doctrine stoode vnsha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in his full force, so are they ouer impudent, whiche doo thinke that these thinges maye be established, eyther by the false forged title of the Church, or by the prescription &amp; length of time.</p>
   <p>Goe to then, lette vs conclude this <note place="margin">All Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are not alvvaies to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovved.</note> place, that they are farre deceyued which thinke that the Catholike rites
<pb facs="27"/>
are of necessitie to be receyued, for there be also some Catholike errours, whiche haue crepte into the Churche, partely by the ignoraunce of many of the Bishops, partly by their negligēce, partly by their blinde zeale and apishe imitation of others, and also by theyr ambition &amp; couetousnes, but chiefly by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> moste gréedy desire of honour which was in the Romish Bishoppes. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore wheras in the appointing of <note place="margin">Externall rites and ceremonies whiche are perticular may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvaies chaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and muste be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolished vvhen they become su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitious or Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous.</note> rites &amp; orders, wise men alwaies haue had regard to the time, place, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons: who dothe not sée, that they are moste foolishe, who in these kinde of thinges, when the circumstances are changed, will not onely haue nothyng chaunged, but also such thinges as are for iuste causes abolished, either by the continuāce of time or other waies, yet because they are aūcient, thei wil haue them to be againe reuoked? but what shall we saye of those thinges that are degenerate into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> most manifest mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of Idolatrie? the whiche in that most cursed time whē God was angry with our sinnes did preuaile, though a fewe in the beginninge (but in vaine)
<pb facs="28"/>
did resiste, the whiche thinges finally though they were not at this present vtterly polluted, yet are they such, as can scarsely (no not all) be kepte pure any longe space.</p>
   <p>But here cometh to my minde the <note place="margin">Politike Gentlemē.</note> voice of these mē, that thinke thēselues most witty of all others, which thinke that the Churche ought to be reformed but not transformed. And they call the reformation, a restorynge agayne of those rites, whiche were in vse in the florishyng time of the Church, as they terme it (takinge awaye some thinges which by the wickednes of times haue bene abused) the whiche except we doo receyue, they crie that the Churche is transformed, and depriued vtterly of hir beautie and comelinesse. Surely their woordes haue a greate shewe and a beautifull, but it procedeth from the spirite of Satan, whiche then bewray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it selfe, when we come to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: for thē there is nothyng so shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that they dare not couer vnder the colour of antiquitie and obtrude it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs for comely and beautifull. Those Rapsodies moste vayne and foolishe
<pb facs="28"/>
written of these matters by <hi>G. Cas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sander</hi> that bablynge <hi>Apostata</hi> (with whose name I woulde not defile these papers) doo declare these matters.</p>
   <p>How be it I folowynge the example of Kinge <hi>Ezekiah</hi> (so greatly commended) had much rather to imitate such, which doo Iudge that the offence and daūger that lieth in the high way, ought to be abolished and taken away, though at sometimes there hath bene or maye be some vse therof: rather then to appoint monitores to stande by, which may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monish the passengers lest they at vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares doo fall into suche perilles. For what if they that are admonished doo not obey? or the Monitors doo not their office? Moreouer besides that in many of their suppositiōs I doo not onely dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent from them, but I doo vtterly ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre them, so in their proposition I cā not agrée vnto them. For if we séeke <note place="margin">The chiefe patterne of the Church is in Christe and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles.</note> the most beautifull face of the Church &amp; most perfect patterne, I suppose that is it, which was not onely begonne (as these men imagine) or shadowed out with the firste pouncinge or paintinge draughtes, by the Apostles thēselues
<pb facs="29"/>
(which were the chiefe workemaisters y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> euer y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Church hath had or shall haue hereafter) but portered foorth moste beautifully &amp; most diligētly, with most liuely colours: from the which the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that thou strayest, so farre wide wanderest thou more &amp; more from the rule of thy worke. And after what sort that forme was, &amp; why I should thinke that we ought to séeke it no where els, saue onely in the writings of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles &amp; the Apostolical Historie writen by <hi>Luke</hi> (whome I doo graunt to haue <note place="margin">The cōtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie and lies of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichristes Churche.</note> painted this foorth most excellētly) not onely the contrarietie emonges them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues doth cōpel me vnto it, but also to speake plainly, the fonde vanitie of thē which haue either perticularly recited or wholly collected y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Apostolical Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions (as they terme them) suche as those foolishe &amp; most false descriptiōs of them attributed vnto <hi>Clement,</hi> &amp; those that thei call the Canons of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Apostles whiche haue bene a greate while ago counted emonge the bookes y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> are to be reiected. But if some will obiect that al thinges are not written by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Apostles and by <hi>Luke:</hi> I praye you why doo they
<pb facs="29"/>
thinke so, because there be but fewe <note place="margin">Christ con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented him selfe vvith fevv ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies, and so did his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles.</note> thinges conteined in their writinges? Nay would to God y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they which boste thēselues to be the successors of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles could haue contented thēselues with this smal nūber. For God would neuer haue had the rites &amp; ceremonies of Moises abolished to the intēt that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers shuld be put in their places: &amp; if it were not lawful to imitate the Iewes, <note place="margin">Ievves nor Idolaters may nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovved.</note> much more vnlawful is it to folow the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> the which thing if the Anciēt Bishops had remēbred, Christian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiō had neither swarued so soone nor so shamefully, first into vaine ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies &amp; triflinge Liturgies, after y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> into manifest superstition, &amp; last of all euen degenerate into an <hi>Atheisme.</hi> For <hi>Paule</hi> woorthely doth call thē <hi>Atheists</hi> &amp; Godlesse, whiche doo not woorship the onely true God as he ought to be woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped. But shal we say that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles did not properly treate of this argument &amp; matter? Nay certainely it were a certaine kinde of impietie, to thinke that the holy Ghost had not so great regard of the Church as was cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniēt: and this dare I affirme that he
<pb facs="30"/>
which readeth diligētly the History of <hi>Luke,</hi> and the Epistles of the Apostles, shall therby very wel learne, not only the chiefe pointes of the Ecclesiasticall <note place="margin">Folowe the Scriptures and thou shalte not neede vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvrittē tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</note> order, but also almost euery part ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, so that no place néede to be lefte at all, to those vnwritten Traditions. Notwithstādyng how so euer this be, seinge we stāde néede of a most perfect distinction to discerne the diuersitie of those infinite Traditiōs, by what rule <note place="margin">By vvhat rule shall vve trie the diuersitie of Traditions and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</note> I praye you shall we trie them? for we haue declared that there cā be no suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient argument concluded, neither by the Antiquitie nor Authoritie of the writers, neither by the multitude of thē by whome thei haue bene allowed: Therfore stāde we néede of the woorde of God onely, euen of that woorde of God (I say) whiche is published by the Prophetes and the Apostles, and as it were, sette foorth in publike Tables: wherby we may disseuer the holy from the vnholy, the profitable from the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable and hurtfull, the necessarie from the superfluous, and to establishe those Traditions by good reason that are thus disseuered. Now then if it
<pb facs="30"/>
be necessary y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> the light of Gods woorde <note place="margin">Gods vvoorde is the touche stone of doctrine.</note> writen must be our guide, to iudge the rites &amp; Ceremonies: howe muche more necessarie is it vnto the knowledge of the doctrine it selfe, that the same light muste be our guide, in the whiche do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine men are much more blinded and doo erre with farre more daunger? For if nothing, as we haue declared hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may be folowed of vs in doctrine, but that either is expressed by playne woordes in the Scriptures of God, or els is gathered necessarily by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferringe together of places, howe can I beware of the false Prophetes, onles I doo compare the doctrine pronounced by thē, with the woorde of God it selfe? But thou wilt saye, what if he brynge foorth the woorde of God also? for so did <note place="margin">An Obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note>
      <hi>Arrius</hi> vrging this texte. My father is greater then I: and so was the dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with <hi>Macedonius</hi> of the persone of the holy Ghost, with <hi>Nestorius</hi> and <hi>Eutiches</hi> of the vnion of the two na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and with <hi>Pelagius</hi> of Grace and Nature: So is the controuersie at this daye of the sacramentall Phrases and maners of speach, whiles that one sort
<pb facs="31"/>
of the same woordes, and those moste fewe in number (that is to say) this is my Bodie, this is my Bloud, doo finde out Transubstantiation, others Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>substantiation, others onely a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Coniunction. Finally saye these mediatours, these halters in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that would séeme to appease the controuersies, when the controuersie falleth, not of the woorde, but of the sence, whether shall we runne rather then to the Churche, to the writinges of the Catholike fathers, that were of sounde iudgement, finally to the true and lawfull Councels? To the whiche I doo aunsweare as before, that I doo <note place="margin">The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>svveare.</note> not thinke that the testimonies of the Church, nor of the Fathers, nor of the Councels are to be reiected, but I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose that in them men muste vse great warynesse.</p>
   <p>First of all if any thinge be affirmed <note place="margin">Bare names of mē vvith out Gods vvoorde cā not staye our faith.</note> without the woorde of God, the bare names of the Churche, of the Fathers, of the Coūcels, are pretēded in vaine: seyng that in this pointe the very An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels are not to be harde. For that say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of <hi>Paule</hi> stādeth still in force, that
<pb facs="31"/>
if any Angel frō heauen should preach an other Gospell let him be accursed. Neither is it the duetie of the Churche to speake in this, but to here her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande what he speaketh.</p>
   <p>And the Godly learned Fathers would haue their writings none other waies to be redde, neither with any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther condition, but that they should be examined by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rule of the woorde wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. Finally this is not the office of the Councels to make any newe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, but to confirme by Gods woorde that which is already made and ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by him: those Synodes that haue done otherwaies, are the chaires of the wicked and the seates of the scorners, the whiche we are commaunded to flie that we may be blessed. Moreouer if <note place="margin">Doctors and Councels, may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led as vvit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses so that vve do iudge by the vvorde.</note> there be any doubte of the interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the woorde writen, I doo not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse thē to be witnesses as I haue said, but I suppose that first of all we muste diligently discerne the true Churche from the Synagoge of Satan: the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that are not suspected in Faithe nor cōdemned, from such as either are mē manifestly without knowledge, or
<pb facs="32"/>
Heretikes, or otherwise suspected: and the lawfull and vndoubted faithfull Councels, from the Synodes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenticles assembled against Christes truthe: finally the true bookes must be warely Iudged from the forged and counterfaite.</p>
   <p>These thinges beinge determined, <note place="margin">God is only iudge by his vvorde.</note> then doo I saye, that all these are to be hearde, not as iudges (for God is only y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> iudge by his written woorde) but as witnesses cited and sworne, and that certainely, after the same maner as witnesses are heard by skilfull Iudges in publike controuersies: euen so vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that they shew the causes &amp; reasons of their testimonies, causes I say not borowed any where els, but foorthe of the same woorde, of the interpretation wherof the questiō is moued. For <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> renouncinge humaine reason saith very wel: by the holy Scriptures we walke much more safely, the which <note place="margin">Augustine.</note> beinge shadowed with borowed spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, when we wil search them, either that cōmeth foorth whiche is without controuersie, or if it haue any doubte, it may be determined by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb facs="32"/>
by the gatheringe and finding of testimonies &amp; witnesses of euery side. Thus saith he, and that very wel. For if we must onely haue our wisdome by the onely writen woorde, then may not the interpretation of this woorde be fetched any other where: For as the same <hi>Augustine</hi> saith, so hath the holy spirite tempered &amp; ordered the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> that thyng which is spoken in some place somethinge darkly, in some other place is declared more plainly.</p>
   <p>Finally what other man shal we fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <note place="margin">VVho ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be folovved then Christ and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles. Heretikes ouercome by the Scriptures.</note> then Christ him self and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles? and Christe did confute Satan abusinge the Scriptures, by no other meanes but by the same Scriptures. The Apostles confirme their doctrine by the writings of the Prophets: And the Iewes of <hi>Beraea</hi> are praysed, that whē they had hearde y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> doctrine taught by <hi>Paule,</hi> they cōpared it with the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges of the Prophetes, to trie whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther those thinges were so or no. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely the Councels of Nice did with none other weapon cut the throte of <hi>Arrius,</hi> nor that of <hi>Cōstantinople, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonius,</hi> nor the <hi>Ephesine Nestorius,</hi>
      <pb facs="33"/>
nor the <hi>Chalcedonian Eutiches,</hi> nor <hi>Augustine, Pelagius,</hi> &amp; <hi>Donatus:</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they that counte the Scripture so doubtfull and darke, that it standeth néede to haue light brought thereunto some other wayes, are woorthie of all good men to be spitted vpō as blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and vtterly to be abhorred.</p>
   <p>Yet doo I not disprayse the writings <note place="margin">Doctors al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovved of God.</note> of the Doctors and their interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, seinge that he that hath ordeined pastors and doctors to the edificatiō of the bodie, hath Authorised them bothe by woorde and by writinges to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretate the same: but I declare howe farre we must sticke vnto them, euen so farre as they doo bringe nothinge of their owne, no not at y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> time when as the controuersie is of the sence and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretatiō of any place of Scripture, but that they by the Scriptures doo interpretate the Scriptures, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the proportion of Faithe: the whiche who so dothe, whether he be newe or olde, a Priuate person or Publike officer in the Churche, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he come alone or with many, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be an olde man or a yong man,
<pb facs="33"/>
let hym bee heard. For though order <note place="margin">Order is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary, but not so that we binde Gods grace to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone &amp; place, but measure all by the rule of gods word</note> must nedes be kepte in the Churche of God, yet are no men so farre deceiued, as thei that dooe binde the grace of the holie ghost, to certaine places and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones. For who murdered the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes? Who crucified Christe? Thei vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedlie, that should haue been the chief pillers of true religion. Therfore doeth not the Prophete, sende the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, to those godlesse Priestes, but to the Lawe and the Prophettes. Neither assuredlie hath the condicion of the Churche, a long while béen any otherwaies, whiles the corner stone hath been reproued, by the verie chiefe builders, and Antichrist hath sitten in the temple and place of God hym self. What shall we now conclude? Vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, that by the woorde of God, all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersies muste bee ended: and that it is necessarie, that the false and forged <note place="margin">The worde of God ende of all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersies.</note> woorde, bee iudged from the true, like as also the true churche, from the false and adulterous: and the Synodes and coūcelles, gouerned by the holie ghost, from those wherein Sathan was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidente:
<pb facs="34"/>
Finallie, the truthe from lyes and errours, by Gods holie woorde. For we muste beleue, that in thynges concernyng our saluaciō, we haue no <note place="margin">The want of the word the original of all errours.</note> where els the truthe reueiled. The whiche thynges beyng true, if follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth that that thyng is moste certain, whiche I said in the beginning, moste noble Prince, to bee the originalle, whence all these euils did flowe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with in our fathers daies, the churche was almoste oppressed, and therefore that this onelie is the waie and mean, to raise it vp again, if by the pure word of God, these controuersies maie bee decided.</p>
   <p>For so will it come to passe, that of the moste parte of those thynges, there shal bee no question at all: aboute the whiche, yet at this daie verie many, partly by ignoraunce, partly through malice and frowardnesse, dooe moste stubbernely contende and striue. And those thynges, whiche shall seme to be staied, by the testimonies of scriptures, if thei be iudged not by custome (which when it departeth from the woorde,
<pb facs="34"/>
hath no aucthoritie at all in matters of religion) neither by the bare aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of certaine menne, bee thei newe or olde, but by the comparison of the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces together, all the interpretaciōs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng examined by the proporcion and rule of faithe: then finallie, no thyng shal bee founde so harde, that shall not easily be vnderstand, nothing so darke that shall not be made cleare, nothyng so doubtfull, that shall not bee made plaine and euidente. But who shall binde men to this order: who shall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte this action, and who finallie shall treate these thynges by common auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie? It is not our purpose, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute these matters at this presente, although whiles I often and many ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes dooe thinke of this matter, some thynges dooe come into my mynde, of the whiche it maie be, that I shal haue occasion to speake at some other time. Now lette vs treate, that wee haue in hande.</p>
   <p>Seyng then all these controuersies, must be discussed by gods holy worde, I suppose that this thing, ought chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="35"/>
to be prouided for, that seing all can not haue the knowledge, to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande the woorde of God, in those pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar <note place="margin">A good and true copy of the scriptures very necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> languages, the Hebrue and the Greke (whiche were to be wished) that there should be some true and apt trā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slacion, of the olde and newe Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente made: the whiche diuers haue alredie laboured to bryng to passe, but no manne hath yet sufficiētly enough performed it. For the olde translacion, <note place="margin">The old texte</note> (whose so euer it is) although it ought not to bee condemned, yet is it founde bothe obscure, and vnperfit and super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous, and also false in many places, to speake nothing of an infinite varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, almoste of the copies. The whiche text therfore, for good cause many god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and learned menne, haue laboured to amende, but not with like successe. And yet how necessary a thing this is, <note place="margin">The learned Grecian fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did not attain to the Hebrue veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note> whosoeuer shall read those moste lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned writers of the Grecians, and shall compare their interpretacions (which are many tymes farre frō the purpose) with the Hebrue veritie, he shall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse it with greate sorowe. And the▪
<pb facs="35"/>
same euill was not onelie hurtefull, emonges the Latine writers, but also the ignoraunce of the Greke tongue, <note place="margin">The Latin writers wer troubled for wāt of know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue &amp; greke.</note> where with many of them were trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled: whiles thei did depende of the common translacion, thei often times seke a knot in the Rushe (according to the prouerhe) and fall into moste foule errours.</p>
   <p>This cause therfore hath moued me to compare moste diligētlie, the diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie of copies, and to weigh the senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and iudgemētes, of the moste part of the learned men, especially of theim that this age hath brought forthe skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the languages, who are moe in nomber doubtles, and better learned then the Churche hath had, since the time of the Apostles: and so to ease thē <note place="margin">The nombre of the lerned.</note> somewhat, that desire a more pure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretaciō. And that it might be doen with the more profite, I haue also ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded annotacions, in the whiche I haue also conferred together, the diuersitie of interpretacions, and as muche as I could, I haue laboured to make plain and euidente, the sense and meauyng,
<pb facs="36"/>
of all the moste darke places.</p>
   <p>But when as I did see, that thicke woorke (and very painfull, as I muste nedes by experience confesse it) growe so greate, when it came againe to the Printyng, that many could not haue the commoditie of it, I caused it to bee Printed alone, without those annota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions: In the place whereof yet I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, that I haue sette suche thynges, the which (if I could haue doen them, as thei oughte to haue been dooen) I would not doubt to commende them, not onely as profitable, but also as ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie necessarie.</p>
   <p>There bee twoo kindes of interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taciōs: The one is of that sorte, which <note place="margin">Two kinds of interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note> doe not consider properly the thyng it self, and what is spoken, but take in hande to declare, with what woordes any thyng is spoken, chaungyng one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the phrases, &amp; the maner of speache. The whiche kinde of interpretacion, although it can scarsly, no not at all rightly be performed of hym, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandeth not the thyng it self, yet standeth it in the woordes.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="36"/>
The other kinde is of them, whiche dooe declare the thyng and matter it <note place="margin">Caluine.</note> self with many woordes, and geue the reasons. In the whiche kinde of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretacion (in my iudgement, and as I suppose in the iudgemente of all the learned, that haue read his bokes) that noble Ihon Caluine, that man of bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed memorie, and my father in. Christe shal be founde (so that no manne enuy my saiyng) farre to haue passed and excelled all the writers, bothe did and new. Therefore, though I some times in certaine places, not in any poinct of his doctrine (the whiche I haue alwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes marked, to be moste pure &amp; sounds in his writynges, as in any other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter besides) but in the explicaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of certaine places, doe dissent from hym: yet dooe, I iudge of his commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, that which <hi>Cicero</hi> did iudge of <hi>Iulius Caesars</hi> commentaries, in a kind of writing farre vnlike (that is to saie) that he made all menne of any witte, affraied to write after him. And would to God that wée, that are ministers in Christes churche, through the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="37"/>
of God (and I my self especially) might be occupied in learnyng and teaching rather then in writing. But what shal we doe? The importunitie of certaine of our aduersaries (against whose pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctises it is necessarie, that the louers of the truthe, by all meanes oppose them selues) doeth partly driue vs herevnto, least the simple bee trapped at vnwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res: and partly Charitie, whiche doeth admonishe vs, to applie to the profite of our brethren, what soeuer we haue receiued. Now verie many haue see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnto me (either because it is so, or because I am deceiued) to faile muche in this, that in the particular rehersals of the Euangelicall, and Appostolical <note place="margin">The cheife points of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Religiō and the order of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are to be obserued.</note> historie, in to that whiche is diuided; doubtles by moste diuine arte, thei do not marke nor cōsider to what poinct chiefly of christian religiō, euery thing ought to bee referred: muche lesse also in those moste graue disputacions, in the Epistles of thapostles, whiche are written (as is moste true) with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellente order, do thei cōsider, what is the state of theim, what is the order: or
<pb facs="37"/>
finally, what is the ende and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose: herof commeth it that in some of their writinges, neither hed nor foote appereth many tymes. And thei lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng the scope and purpose, wander to certaine notes and obseruacions, confusedly and without order heaped together: So that in many places of moste importaunce, no regarde is had to the sentence it self.</p>
   <p>This is the cause that in Paule cheif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (who yet had as great a skill &amp; iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement in writing as any writer that <note place="margin">Paul of most diuine iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath written most orderly.</note> euer did write) vnlearned and vnskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men haue dreamed hertofore to be infinitie <hi>Hiperbatons</hi> and <hi>Anantapo dotons,</hi> sentences and wordes not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering out to an other, and haue in their commentaries vpon him, euery where to their owne shame still incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated the same: in so muche that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly this moste excellent, declarer of gods secrets, was no more knowen in the scholes, then if he had lefte no monumentes nor writinges, yea ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny did flye from him as from a rocke, for feare of shipwrake. Wherfore that
<pb facs="38"/>
I might fynde a remedy for this mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, I haue endeuored my selfe as much as in me lyeth, to note the brefe <note place="margin">Bezas anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</note> summaries of doctrine in the historie matters: that who so euer shall saile as it were in that see, maye marke a hauen before their eies where vnto thei may directe their course. And in the Epistles I haue labored that the scope and order of arguments, and the methode and all other thinges beinge set in their places, the natiue exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions maye be knowen. And if God <note place="margin">His expositiō and the hard wordes &amp; cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune places.</note> graunt me that I may hereafter adde hereunto twoo other thinges whiche I am about nowe, that is to say a breife exposition of the wordes that offer thē selues in the texte, &amp; commune places beside euery one noted with a word, in their proper places, then truly shall I thinke that I haue done some thynge worthie trauell. But it may please god once to graūt these: In the meane seasō (most noble Lords) I thought it good to writte and dedicate vnto you, chiefly that haue embraced true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in Fraunce, my natiue countrie,
<pb facs="38"/>
all that whiche God hath giuen met bothe that I might shewe forthe some token, of a thanckfull minde (for what dooe we not allowe vnto you, whiche with the bucklers of your own bodies haue defēded the poore miserable shepe againste the rage of the Wolues) and also that I maie cōfirme you more and more, to perseuer in this heroicall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and stoutenes, whiche becometh your noble courage. Lo then most no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prince, those holy teachers of that heauēlie doctrine, for the defēce wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, thou haste not doubted to offer thy life (I saie) to so many and so great pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilles and daungers. Lo, vnto you ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and noble Lordes, those ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie misteries of that eternal wisedome the whiche the more that you shall knowe, the more glad shall you bee, though you bee driuen to shedde your blood again, for him whiche hath rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med you with his moste precious blood. These are the excellēt ensignes of the victorie, of your faithe and zele, euen before the verie Angelles of heauen: in the settyng vp whereof, yet would
<pb facs="39"/>
to God, O would to God, I saie, like as your desire was, you might onelie haue vsed Spirituall weapons. But now when peace is restored, you haue greate nede of a spirituall constancie, and an inuincible power and force of faithe, that this woorke that you haue begonne, maie bee finished with your euerlastyng laude and praise. And the Lorde will minister this vnto you, by the continuall and diligente hearyng of his woorde, and meditatyng of the same. For that, whiche meate is vnto <note place="margin">The exercise in gods word necessary.</note> our bodies, the same do these heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie dainties, minister to our myndes: that is to say, not onely that we should liue by the liuelie iuice of theim, but also that we should grow and encreace to full age, whiles at the length, we be made perfite at that last daie. And here I dooe desire your honours, that you would vouchsafe with quiet myndes, to heare certain thinges of me, whiche belong to your charge. If so bee that <note place="margin">Beleue faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full teachers that bring no thinge but Gods worde.</note> you be fullie perswaded, that we whō you haue heard, and of whom you are begotten in the Lorde, doe teache true
<pb facs="39"/>
and holie thynges, I beseche you suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer not your selues, to be drawen from <note place="margin">Beware of crafty hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites.</note> thēce one iote. And I haue great cause thus to admonishe you. For though I doe knowe the fortitude of your myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: yet doe I also knowe, how greate the craft is of certain that lie in waite to berciue you of your saluacion, and what is their impudencie and malice. I doe not speake of those opē and kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen enemies of the truthe, but I doe meane those Sinons and craftie coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfaictes, <note place="margin">Sinon a Gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciā vnder the pretence of re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligiō betraied Troye.</note> who partely would haue a certaine meane and mingled religion (I knowe not how) and partely waite for the occasion, to sowe discorde emō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges you, by those infortunate discor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and controuersies, about the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des Supper. What saie thei, is it all one to transforme the Churche, and to reforme it? Wer our fathers al blind? Are these felowe (that come we knowe not whence) onely wise? Are not these the', that all the beste learned dooe call Sacramētaries? and vtterly abhorre? <note place="margin">All true gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers are ready to geue accomptes.</note> Now what we haue to aunswer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, you are not ignoraunt, and wée
<pb facs="40"/>
will neuer refuse, to shewe the causes before the whole worlde, of this that thei cal a trasformacion. But it is wō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if al menne doe not see, what these menne goe about: seyng some of them dooe seruice to those, that are openly the moste deadly enemies of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell <note place="margin">Beware of crafty tourne cotes.</note> of Christ, others are notorious, by plaiyng so oftē the Apostatates, others of them haue vttered al their life long vnto the whole worlde, their incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancie, and their babblyng, and that thei haue no iudgemente at all, seyng in thirtie yeres space, thei haue not yet learned, that menne maie not halt nor wauer in religion.</p>
   <p>These are thei that I admonish you chiesly to take heede of: and you shal be safe from them, if you stedfastlie conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newyng in that faithe, that you haue receiued of your faithefull Pastours, whiche is sealed with the bloode of so many martyres, whereof a plaine and euidente confession is published, will either presently chase awaie these poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned plagues, or if that you haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined ones to heare theim, then
<pb facs="40"/>
that you dooe heare theim before suche Pastours, by whom their craftes may bee opened, and their lyes conuinced and confuted.</p>
   <p>Neither is there any cause, why <note place="margin">Ther muste nedes be con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trouersies &amp; contrarieties alwayes.</note> these cōtrouersies should trouble you. For the Lorde hym self our maister, hath diligentlie admonished vs, that this is the condicion of this Churche, and the continuall experience of al ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes doeth confirme the same. Thus in our tymes did the Anabaptistes arise, beyng deuided into many sectes.</p>
   <p>Thus at this daie, dooeth the stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernnesse of certaine, in defendynge moste manifest errours, so boile forthe, that thei openlie dare dissolue the twoo natures of Christ with <hi>Nestorius,</hi> and confounde the properties with <hi>Euty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> whose pestilente bookes, I dooe forewarne you, are alreadie transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Frenche. In other places, as in Polonia, the cursed <hi>Tritheits,</hi> that imagine three Gods are risen vp, and haue almoste destroyed the countrie: and Sathan styll forgeth other se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete misteries, againste the whiche
<pb facs="41"/>
it is necessarie, that you doe resiste and stande stedfaste, by the sinceritie and pure simplicitie of Christian doctrine.</p>
   <p>But nowe because that neither the <note place="margin">Ecclesiastical Discipline ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cessary.</note> offences, wherewith the wrathe of GOD is many tymes prouoked, nor the heresies whereby the true doctrine is oppressed, can bee taken awaie in due tyme, excepte a true and lawfull order of Ecclesiasticall discipline bee appointed: therefore I dooe require this of you, by the name of the soonne of GOD: I craue this thing, I saie of you, that you dooe not reiecte this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, as any inuencion of man, but that you would establishe it with al di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligéce, and earnest affection, and kepe and retaine it, being ones established, <note place="margin">The redres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>singe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners is the one halfe of the scriptures</note> as the ordinaunce of GOD: without the whiche, the whole buildyng muste come to ruine of necessitie. For what? Is not this the other halfe of the word of God? Surely he that denieth this, denieth the Sonne to shine at the mid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>daie. And I praie you, what common wealthe, what citie, what house, or familie, shall not straight waies, bee
<pb facs="41"/>
dissolued, vnlesse it be knit together with <note place="margin">The churche the scolehouse of honestie, maie not bee the denne of vnthriftes.</note> the bondes of Lawes and Order. What? Shall wée suffer the Churche of Christe, that teacheth all holinesse and honestie, to bée transformed into a schoole of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and licencious life? But if we take awaie this discipline, that wée speake of, if euery one bee permitted to preache publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kely, if there be no examinacion of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and maners of the Pastours, if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man bee receiued without difference vnto the Sacramentes, if it be not lawful to reproue those that synne with the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of others, and seuerely to correcte those that resiste stubbernely, and also in the ende (if nede be) by the example of the Apostle, to thrust suche forthe of the flocke, leaste thei infecte others: and also vnlessé there be prouision for the poore, and almo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses bée distributed by the order appoincted by the holy ghost: vnlesse finally all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges bee rightly and orderly dooen, in the house of God, what will the Churche bee streight waies for the moste parte, but an assemblie of men, geuen to libertie and all licētious life? But will some saie, these <note place="margin">An obiection. The answer.</note> are the duties of Magistrates. As though wée
<pb facs="42"/>
wee would haue temporall and yearthly thinges, suche as are onely for this world to come into question by any meanes, in the Ecclesiasticall Consistorie, or that we would exempt, either Pastours them sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, or any others from the aucthoritie or commaundemente of the Ciuile Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates, as those doe, whom men call Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes.</p>
   <p>Christ aunswered vnto them, that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <note place="margin">Christe hath established the discipline of the church.</note> vpon hym, to deuide their heritage: who saieth he hath appoincted me youre Iudge? But he saieth also, he that heareth not the Churche, let hym bee as an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then &amp; a Publicane: wherfore those thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are to be disseuered, that GOD hath deuided, but thei maie not be takē awaie, that he hath established. Naie certainly, it is so farre from the truthe, that this Discipline, dooeth hinder or lessen the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthoritie of the Magistrates, if it bée law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully (that is to saie) by the worde of God onely placed and ordered, that contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise it dooeth as muche as maie bée esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishe it: séeyng that nothyng is able so muche to maintain publike tranquilitie, as this one thyng, that the conscienses of
<pb facs="42"/>
all maie bée retained in the feare of God. But it is to bée feared, least that olde Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pishe <note place="margin">An obiection.</note> tyrannie bée brought again into the Churche. So it is, howbeit this is greate <note place="margin">The answer.</note> foolishenesse (saieth the Poet) so to auoide vices, that thou doe fall into the contrary extremities. Wherefore wee maie not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide <note place="margin">Christs yoke of Discipline moste sweete to the godlie.</note> mannes tyrannie, shake of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes yoke, but we muste receiue it, for it is onely vnpleasaunte vnto the wicked and prophane persones, and is to the good and godlie moste swéete and comfortable. And wée are so farre from coumptyng the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates, <note place="margin">The Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates, the sheldes of the Churche.</note> and you (whom God hath made the foster fathers of his Churche, by the Kinges Maiesties Decrees) Laie men (as certaine dooe) and so to separate you, as straūgers frō this discipline that I speake of, that contrary wise, wée doe iudge that this poinct chieflie belongeth vnto you, to punishe most seuerely, those troublesome contemners of the Churche, and by your aucthoritie, to procure that the worship of God, maie moste purely bee maintained. And seyng this regimente of the Elders, must bee appoincted, not onely of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stours, but of suche also, by whom the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stours
<pb facs="43"/>
theim selues (if néede bée) maye bée corrected, who is so madde, but that in the chusyng of the Elders, he muste thinke, that greate consideracion must bee had, of those, that besides the commendacions of their godlinesse, haue also aucthoritie and proeminence in the Churche? But parad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture I haue spoken to muche of these thynges, vnto you especially of whose good willes, I can nothyng doubt. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I make an ende, besechyng the moste merciful and mightie God, that he would strengthen thee, moste noble Prince, with his mightie power, and you the rest of the renouned Lordes, endued with his holie and excellente spirite, and with the true knowledge of his soonne, and vouchsafe to adorne you cōtinually more and more, with all his moste excellente giftes: that he maie finishe that greate worke, that he hath begonne in you, to the full restoryng of his heauenly kyngdome, moste blessed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with your immortall praise and glorie.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>At Geneua <date>the .x. of the Calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of Marche. The yere from Christes incarnaciō for vs. 1565.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>