<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Author, and his Booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118582_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02622</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12750</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118582</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Author, and his Booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Time is a turne-coate. Or Englands three-fold metamorphosis : VVherin is acted the pensiue mans epilogomena, to Londons late lamentable heroicall comi-tragedie. Also a panegyricall pageant-speech or idylion pronounced to the citie of London, vpon the entrance of her long expected comfort. Written by Iohn Hanson</title>
                 <author>Hanson, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hanson, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Potter, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 71, 11 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dialogue">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>The Author, and his Booke.</head>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Book.</speaker>
      <lg>
         <l>
            <hi>HElpe, helpe, alas, else am I quite vndone,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>O shroud me close from sight of these blacke feends,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Who wound with Scorpions stings: I cannot shunne;</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Alas for ayde, some ayde, sweet gentle friends!</hi>
         </l>
      </lg>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Aut.</speaker>
      <lg>
         <l>Why, how now <hi>Booke,</hi> what newes? what, dost thou dreame?</l>
         <l>Or art thou quite distract, of sense bereaued?</l>
         <l>Or do thy Thoughts discusse on dolefull Theame?</l>
      </lg>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
      <lg>
         <l>
            <hi>Yea sure, I dream'd, yet not by Dreames deceiued:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>For in my Dreame, me thought thou badst me post</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Through euery Countrie, Citie, farre and neare,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>To take my lodging with each erabbed Host,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>And beare the lash of each lend Censurer.</hi>
         </l>
      </lg>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Aut.</speaker>
      <lg>
         <l>Why, so thou must: then run, no time delay:</l>
         <l>Stand not amaz'd at euery carping braine;</l>
         <l>And if thou meetst a Cynicke by the way,</l>
         <l>If he looke grim, looke sterne on him againe.</l>
         <l>But if graue <hi>Cato</hi> chance to meete with thee,</l>
         <l>And deigne on thine his Iudgement to suspend;</l>
         <l>Do thou him reuerence low, with cap and knee:</l>
         <l>Tell him, for learn'd aduice to him I send.</l>
      </lg>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Book.</speaker>
      <lg>
         <l>
            <hi>What if proud</hi> Argas <hi>meet me in the street,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Who robs</hi> Apollo <hi>of that sacred Fire,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Which kindleth ardent rage in his cold sprite,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>And driues his muddie-frost-bit-Braine t'aspire:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>He'le turne me ore, and tosse me in his snare,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Chopping my Subiect in his snarling chaps;</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>And in his turning, turne my coate threed-bare,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Within the pocket of his threed-bare stops.</hi>
         </l>
      </lg>
   </sp>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Aut.</speaker>
      <lg>
         <l>What, that staru'd hungrie catch-pole-paper knaue,</l>
         <l>Who ne're durst looke harsh <hi>Horace</hi> in the face?</l>
         <l>That stealing-Sense, that Sentence-snatching slaue,</l>
         <l>Who feeds on fragments scraped from each place?</l>
         <l>What he, that doth his Braines a begging send,</l>
         <l>For some ragg'd Theame to comment on at large,</l>
         <l>Catching a puddle-wharfe-Discourse by th'end,</l>
         <l>Chaunts it like whore-house tales in westerne Barge?</l>
         <l>Who he, that still his Sun-burnt Sense inclines</l>
         <l>To turne his state, till faine to turne his purse;</l>
         <l>And teares his huing from lasciuious lines,</l>
         <l>Turnes Good to Naught, and Naught doth turne to worse?</l>
         <l>What he, whose Wit the whore and strumpet plaies,</l>
         <l>Got great with child by <hi>Latines</hi> two or three;</l>
         <l>And then cries out, (for midwife neuer staies)</l>
         <l>Deliuerd of some monstrous Bastardie?</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Turne him off to the whipping-post of <hi>Time;</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Tell him, his loathsome stinking breath infects thee:</l>
         <l>Then turne his chaps to chop some rascall Rime,</l>
         <l>To chew some hobling doggrell Balladrie.</l>
         <l>But if he sweares, he'le turne thy coate with spight,</l>
         <l>And turne thee leafe by leafe, and line by line:</l>
         <l>Bid him go turne his nap-lesse coate by night,</l>
         <l>Who turnes his coate more oft, then thou turn'st thine.</l>
      </lg>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Book.</speaker>
      <lg>
         <l>
            <hi>But he that on his Sattins seates his Thought,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Sinking to hell betweene his Dockesies armes,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Will turne his Fore-top, sweare by heau'n,</hi> t'is nought,</l>
         <l>
            <hi>As though that oath coniur'd, like Magicke charmes.</hi>
         </l>
      </lg>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Aut.</speaker>
      <lg>
         <l>Turne that word <hi>(Naught)</hi> downe to his heart againe,</l>
         <l>From whence that viprous terme forc't free accesse,</l>
         <l>Where caues of vgly venim'd Snakes remaine:</l>
         <l>There let <hi>(naught)</hi> sting his soule without redresse.</l>
      </lg>
   </sp>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Book.</speaker>
      <lg>
         <l>
            <hi>Yet will Carnalitie, the vsuring Atheist,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>The Murtherer, the immane Sodomite:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>The Cruell man, and terr ene Sensualist,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Turne are my leaues and teare them in despite:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Turne backe with scorne my wholesome Counsell giu'n,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Turning me off, my graue aduice expell.</hi>
         </l>
      </lg>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Aut.</speaker>
      <lg>
         <l>Then turne them vp into the hands of Heau'n,</l>
         <l>Who'le turne them downe into the chaps of hell.</l>
         <l>Now get thee hence, post on with turning Rime,</l>
         <l>Turning thy sense to all, thy selfe to paine:</l>
         <l>And turne thy hap to euery turne of <hi>Time,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Though to thy selfe returnes the smallest gaine.</l>
      </lg>
   </sp>
   <epigraph>
      <q>Vade, ambula, volens iusta.</q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>