<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118564_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15599</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25864</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118564</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The general practise of physicke : conteyning all inward and outward parts of the body, with all the accidents and infirmities that are incident vnto them, euen from the crowne of the head to the sole of the foote: also by what meanes (with the help of God) they may be remedied: very meete and profitable, not only for all phisitions, chirurgions, apothecaries, and midwiues, but for all other estates whatsoeuer; the like whereof as yet in english hath not beene published. Compiled and written by the most famous and learned doctour Christopher VVirtzung, in the Germane tongue, and now translated into English, in diuers places corrected, and with many additions illustrated and augmented, by Iacob Mosan Germane, Doctor in the same facultie</title>
                 <author>Wirsung, Christof</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 790, 122 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the true scope of all actions and endeuours ought chiefly to tend to the glorie of God, and to the good and common vtilitie of manie: so are those men wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of great praise and commendation, who not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding their priuate gaine or glorie, haue laboured their wits, and spent their studies, in composing, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slating, and publishing in our vulgar tongue either their owne workes, or such learned writings of others, as they thinke most necessarie for the publique weale; imitating therein the most famous Authours of auncient and moderne age: namely such as Hippocrates, Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, Auicen, Paracelsus and others, that haue in their natiue tongues ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and reuealed to posteritie the verie depths and secrets of that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent arte of Physicke: which as it is more auncient, more necessarie, more profitable, and more pleasant, than anie other arte or knowledge whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer (except the knowledge of true felicitie:) so it may boldly be sayd (though not without apprehension of griefe) no arte more falsified nor more abused in these dayes, as well by the presumptuous intermedling of audacious and vnskilfull persons; as for lacke of good and wholesome writings in English for the instruction and safe direction of all those that haue not alwayes a good and learned Physition at hand. Therefore (gentle Reader) that you may the better auoide these and such like mischieuous inconueniences, here is presented to your view the learned worke of that worthie Physition CHRISTOPHER VVIRTZVNG, first written and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished by himselfe in the high Dutch or Germaine language, wherein it hath bene more often printed there, than anie other VVorke of like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: Afterwards translated into the low Dutch or Flemmish tongue, by CAROLVS BATTVS Doctor in Physicke, whose iudgement and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, the Citie of Dort in Holland doth willingly acknowledge: and now likewise Englished for the publike benefite of our countrey, by IAMES
<pb facs="3"/>
MOSE Doctor in Physicke. VVhat paines and labour hath bene taken in the translating, it is referred to your owne fauourable censure, after you shall haue perused and made tryall of it. Onely this for the present may with your good fauour be boldly added out of the testimonies of men lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and skilfull in this facultie, that there is not published in our English tongue the like worke, wherein the whole bodie of Physicke is so succinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, so absolutely, or so artificially digested and compiled. For whether you consider the matter therein deliuered, or the manner of the deliuerie it self, which as it is altogether profitable, so is it easie and methodicall, descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the head to the foote, shewing all manner of diseases incident to each part of our bodie, and setting downe first the causes from whence they spring, secondly the signes and tokens whereby they are knowne, and thirdly the remedies and helpes whereby they may be cured and eased. There is no doubt but when you haue indifferently perused, and heedfully noted the same, you will not onely concurre in iudgement with others, but also accept in all kindnesse the worke it selfe, and make such fauorable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of the good indeuours of those that haue laboured for your preseruation, as your selfe would looke to be rewarded withall in the like.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>