<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE HENRY LO: VISCOVNT FALKLAND, ONE OF THE LORDS OF HIS MAIESTIES MOST HONOURABLE PRIVIE COUNCELL.</title>
           <author>Synge, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118086_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13298</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23604</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118086</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE HENRY LO: VISCOVNT FALKLAND, ONE OF THE LORDS OF HIS MAIESTIES MOST HONOURABLE PRIVIE COUNCELL.</title>
                 <author>Synge, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A reioynder to the reply published by the Iesuites vnder the name of William Malone. The first part. Wherein the generall answer to the challenge is cleared from all the Iesuites cavills</title>
                 <author>Synge, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Ireland--Dublin</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 345, 348-418 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE</hi> RIGHT HONOVRABLE HENRY LO: VISCOVNT FALKLAND, <hi>ONE OF THE LORDS OF HIS MAIESTIES MOST</hi> HONOURABLE PRIVIE COUNCELL.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable my singular good Lord,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was <hi>Tertullian's</hi> observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Heretickes, Nostra suffodiunt ut sua aedificent</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">Tertull de praescript a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> vers. haeret. cap. 42.</note>: Your <hi>Lordship</hi> is well infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by experience, that the <hi>Romish</hi> Clergie who disdain the stile of <hi>Hereticks,</hi> are like <hi>Ʋnderminers,</hi> like <hi>Builders:</hi> For what kinde of <hi>Ʋndermining</hi> is left unpractised to make way, <hi>ut sua aedificent,</hi> that they may build up their <hi>Babell,</hi> and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance their <hi>ROMAN</hi> See? The <hi>Scripture</hi> the <hi>Rule of Faith</hi> they <hi>undermine</hi> by their <hi>Ʋnde scis?</hi> allowing it neither authority nor Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, but because their <hi>Cheife Pastour</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares it, expounds it. The <hi>Church</hi> they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine by assuming her Name, defiling her Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. <hi>Councels,</hi> by denying their lawfulnesse,
<pb facs="3"/> unlesse called and approved by <hi>Rome: Bishops</hi> &amp; <hi>Preists,</hi> by making them Delegates to his supposed <hi>Holyness,</hi> rejecting their Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on received from CHRIST. Neither cease they here, but <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> they <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> also, sometime by raising open <hi>VVarre,</hi> sometime by <hi>Bosome-conspiracies, Powder-plots,</hi> &amp; other secret attempts. Nor doe these <hi>Ʋnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miners</hi> looke alway like <hi>Faux</hi> in the <hi>Vault,</hi> but they will appeare somtimes as it were <hi>Angels of Light: Princes</hi> shall have <hi>Thousands</hi> of their <hi>Pennes</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Iesuite <hi>Fisher</hi> in his Epistle to the King.</note>, but I thinke rather <hi>Pen-knives:</hi> They wilbe <hi>strongly tyed and united</hi> to his Majesties <hi>Crowne,</hi> &amp; the <hi>more familiaritie</hi> they <hi>have with him by whom Kings do raigne, the more awfull will</hi> they be <hi>found unto his Holy annointed</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">The Iesuite in his Epistle Dedicatory.</note>, and all this, as the <hi>Divell</hi> to our <hi>Saviour, ut sua aedifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi> that Princes may <hi>fall downe and worship</hi> their <hi>Beast.</hi> We may goe further; None escape them. They <hi>undermine &amp; Populum &amp; Primates Populi,</hi> by subverting their Estates, Proselyting their Children: and yet the keeping backe of these <hi>Ʋnderminers</hi> from his <hi>Majesties pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence</hi> is censured by M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>Malone</hi> (our <hi>Iesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ite</hi>) to be the fruite of <hi>waspish emulation</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">In his Epistle Dedicatory.</note>, as
<pb facs="3"/> if these things might be done, and yet they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine faithfull to their <hi>Prince,</hi> his <hi>State and Dignitie.</hi> But their <hi>Allegiance</hi> may well be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned by their <hi>Obedience:</hi> For, besides their immediate addresse to <hi>Rome,</hi> their acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging a <hi>PROTECTOƲR</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">In a letter of <hi>LVD. CAR. LVDVISIVS S. R. E. VI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CECANCEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LARIƲS,</hi> superscribed thus, <hi>Rev. P<seg rend="sup">P•i</seg>..</hi> Praefect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> p. P. <hi>Car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> Excalceaterum in Reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> Hiber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia.</hi> Dated. <hi>Rome 10. Kal. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>ii,</hi> 1631. which is in my hands, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth the quarrels of the Regulars and Seculars in the points censured by the Doctors of <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>bon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>an.</hi> 1631. Vt rei veritas innotes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>at scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptum est ad quosdam illius Regni Praelatos â qu. bus expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatur infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matio. Interim v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sum est sacrae Congreg.<seg rend="sup">ni</seg> ut nos ex munere PROTECTORIS quo fungimur admoneamus, &amp; rogemus V. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> ne ex dolore aut vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicta illatae, ut praetenditur, calumniae quid quam agat erga tumultus authores, ne maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>xcitentur turbae, sed offensiones &amp; injurias suas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uorumque re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ittat s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greg. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> quae plenè satisfaciet, &amp; justâ censurâ corripiet, ac poenâ afficiet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap>mniae dum constire it Architectos.</note> there, and abusing his Majesties Subjects by pressing their Consciences to yeeld subjection (against his sacred Commaunds) to none but from thence, There is dayly resisting of his <hi>ROYAL Commaunds,</hi> in matters that are not absolutely <hi>Spirituall:</hi> For there being Publication of <hi>His Maiesties ROYALL</hi> pleasure for the chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the <hi>Popish Calendar,</hi> which ever since the times of <hi>Rebellion</hi> was observed in the <hi>Province of Vlster,</hi> Did they obey? This it may be they will glory in; But for what other then <hi>Politick</hi> respects? How was the Titular <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate</hi> advised by his Councell learned Was he not pressed to disobey? Was it not reputed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient to alter the same? Did he not cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure the receiving of the <hi>Kings command</hi> against
<pb facs="4"/> this their disobedient practise to be no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise then to <hi>obey men more then GOD!</hi> That if <hi>obedience</hi> should be yeelded herein, their <hi>Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries</hi> (so he stiles his <hi>sacred Majestie</hi> &amp; <hi>Councell</hi>) wilbe encouraged to publish more severe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts against them, <hi>&amp; sic paulatim serpet Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">In a letter written partly in Irish, partly in Latine, to the Titular Primate, super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed, <hi>To his much esteemed assured loving fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ind M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Bitagh these in haste where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever. These are the points for which it were inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to alter the time heere praes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>rtim hoc anno. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>, quod videamur obs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dire hominibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> magis quam Deo, recipiendo TEMPORA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIVM Potesta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tum mandata contra r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ceptam Ecclesiasticam lgem, idque <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>dium religionis nostrae; und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> ADVERSARII animentur ad alia magis nociva praecepta can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ra nos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>denda, dum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>iderent nos minoribus praeceptis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
               <desc>•••</desc>
            </gap>emperare, &amp; sic paulatim serpet Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer &amp;c.</hi>
      </note>. Doe they apprehend his <hi>Majestie</hi> &amp; <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell</hi> for <hi>Adversaries?</hi> Who can then esteeme thē for Friends? Shall a rebellious intrusion bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steemed the <hi>Oracle of GOD</hi> and checke the Regall Power, as proceeding from <hi>Men,</hi> and yet <hi>Subjection</hi> not violated, but their <hi>Obedience</hi> must remaine firme?</p>
   <p>Much more in this kinde may be presented to your <hi>Lordship,</hi> if it were not superfluous, but by this it may appeare, how that (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing their pretences) <hi>Princes</hi> are relished or distasted by them <hi>in ordine ad spiritualia,</hi> as they countenance, or exalt their <hi>Popish</hi> Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For to omit other things, the Iesuit his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuous reproaching of the learned defence of his <hi>Majesties supreame power,</hi> made in the <hi>Castle-Chamber</hi> in the time of your <hi>Lordships</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/> Government here, doth declare how invious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they heare of his <hi>Maiesties</hi> eminent and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Prerogatives.</hi> But the more they declare themselves enemies to our <hi>Faith</hi> &amp; her <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> the more I doubt not, but all sacredly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected will arme themselves to resist them, in these their contrivings &amp; secret imaginations.</p>
   <p>I doe not come with this <hi>Dedication</hi> to move your <hi>Lordship</hi> hereunto, for it hath beene your <hi>VVorke;</hi> &amp; who is or hath beene more <hi>Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full amongst all the Servants</hi> of my <hi>Lord the</hi> KING <note n="*" place="margin">1. Sam. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>? And for your pious affection to the true <hi>Religion</hi> I could speake more then I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose your modesty would be willing to heare; so that I doubt not, but in this way you will prosper and flourish, (<hi>Ʋnus Deus &amp; plures A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mici</hi>) being confident that there will never be wanting Blessings &amp; Honour to him that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther walkes with <hi>GOD</hi> or for him. Neither is it a light Argument of your loue to <hi>Pietie</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> that in the time of your <hi>Lordships</hi> Government (imitating herein <hi>BOTH</hi> your most glorious <hi>MASTERS</hi>) you were a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> to the <hi>Cleargie and Ministers of GOD;</hi> your last Act amongst us shewing with how sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
<pb facs="5"/> an esteeme you reverenced their Persons; when by your practise you taught the most <hi>Honourable</hi> of the Kingdome to acknowledge them for men appointed by <hi>GOD to blesse in his Name.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I will now draw to an end, excusing my presumption in offering this to your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship;</hi> but I could doe no lesse, in regard I have no other meanes to acknowledge your libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall favours and bountie to mee, and to give your <hi>Lordship</hi> an Accompt, that although they can never be deserved, yet they are not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther misplaced or cast away. The <hi>LORD</hi> multiply his Blessings upon your <hi>Lordship,</hi> and inflame your affections more and more to his <hi>Glory,</hi> that hee may crowne you with his mercies here, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie hereafter; which he shall ever pray for that is</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships most humble servant and Chaplaine GEO: SYNGE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>