<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Ʋnto the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>O., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1568</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118060_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13257</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23554</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118060</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Ʋnto the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>O., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A confession of fayth : made by common consent of diuers reformed churches beyonde the seas: with an exhortation to the reformation of the Churche. Perused and allowed accordinge to the Queenes Maiesties iniunctions</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wykes (Wekes), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Harrison, Luke (Lucas)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1568</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>42, 112 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Ʋnto the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He subtill Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, our deadly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie Satan, laieth many snares to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangeil mankinde, to withhold him frō cōming to the truth: but especially two, whiche be of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther most perilous, Wilfull ignorance and Slaūderous reportes: wherwith, if once man be ensnared, say, what you liste, doo what you please, he lieth still in his errours, and will not be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: for wilfull ignorance so blindeth his eyes from readinge, slaunderours reportes so stoppe his eares from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe the truth, that not knowynge the clerenesse of the light, he estemeth the darknes of a cloudie night, as the brightnes of noone daies, and giuinge light credite to false rumors, beleueth forged lies as vnfallible truthes. Thus many a Christian ketcheth his
<pb facs="3"/>
bane: and no maruell. For, what di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sease is cured by increasing the corrupt humors, whereon the sicknes féedeth? howe is it possible, that he shoulde be wonne to the Gospell, that wittingly &amp; wilfully doth blindesielde him selfe, dothe stubbernly refuse to Reade the truthe, dothe frowardely disdayne to peruse any other bookes, then suche as nussell him in his errours? What good successe, trowe you, is that Capitayne like to haue, that considereth his owne powre onely, and is not desirous to know his enemies strength also? what wise and trustie Lawier will harken to his Clientes tale alone, and would not gladly (if opportunitie were offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) scanne his aduersaries writinges also? If the iudge will giue eare to the first accuser, &amp; beleue all that he sayeth to be true, and either wil not heare the defendant, or if he doo, estéemeth his woordes as lies, howe can he iudge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righte? if thou wander in Poperie as in darknes, and wilt not walke in the light of the Gospell: if thy soule be poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned with venimous superstitiō, and
<pb facs="3"/>
wilte not tast the preseruatiue of God his woorde: if thou consider Antichrist his powre onely, and wilt not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stāde Christe his might and puisance: if thou defende thine errours as an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill cause, and wilt not regarde thine aduersaries proufes to mayntaine his righte: if thou wilt credite the first do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that euer thou hardest, which is nothinge els but mens Traditions, &amp; wilt not harken to any other truthe: no maruell, if thou be blinde, if thy soule be poisoned, if thou be cōquered, if thou lose thy cause, if thou iudge wrongefully in weightie matters of Faith and true Religion. Suche was the wilfull ignorāce of the Idolatrous Iewes, who sayed to <hi>Ieremie:</hi> The woorde, that thou haste spoken to vs in the name of the Lorde, we will not heare it of thée, but we will doo what soeuer thinge goeth out of our owne mouth, we will burne incense to the Quéene of Heauen, we wil powre out drinke offerings vnto her, as we haue done, bothe we and our Fathers, our Kinges, and our Princes: for then had
<pb facs="4"/>
we plentie of vitayles, and were well and felte no euill: so, they that now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies will not heare the Preacher of God his woorde, that wil doo what thei liste, that will offer to theyr Ladie of heauen, that will sence to their worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaten Images, that will doo as their forefathers, their Kinges and Princes haue done, bosting, that then they had plentie of all thinges, that then it was a merie worlde, that then they felte no euill, doo wilfully, as it were, hyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winke themselues frō seing the truth: No maruell if <hi>Iehoiakim</hi> runne hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe into his destruction, when he woulde not vouchsafe so muche as to giue <hi>Iehudie</hi> the hearyng, while he red the booke of the Lorde, written by <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruch,</hi> but cut it with a penknife, hurled it into the fier, and brente it to Ashes. <hi>Ahab</hi> was content at the length to heare what <hi>Michah</hi> woulde saye, but estemyng his woordes as lesinges, and beleuing his flattering false Prophets hasted to his miserable ende. And as <hi>Michah</hi> then saide, that a spirite went out, &amp; was a false spirit in the mouthes
<pb facs="4"/>
of al his Prophetes, so in this our age, not one but many spirites are broken lose, and be false Spirites bothe in the mouthes, tounges &amp; hartes of our Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mishe cole Prophetes. For how many lies coyne they? howe many slaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <note place="margin">Sclaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portes.</note> reportes forge they to deface the Gospell and the true professours ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? Doo thei not laye to our charge (as y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Iewes did to Christ) that our doctrine is newe learnynge? that we are <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptistes, Pelagians, Libertines,</hi> dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable <hi>Heretikes?</hi> that we contemne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinge, neglect prayinge, doo no Almes déedes, dispraise good woorkes? that we denie God his powre, beleue not his woordes, defie Christe his Image, and are enemies to his Crosse? that we fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie the Scriptures, refuse y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Doctors, deface the Councels, sette at naught Traditions? that we honour not the Sainctes, estéeme not the Mother of Christe, nor his blessed Martirs? that we care not for the dead? that we make God the auctor of sinne, and man as a stocke or a blocke, voide of all goodnes? that we passe not for the Churche, and
<pb facs="5"/>
rayle against the head therof? that we abuse the Sacramentes? that we are rebelles, and teach subiectes to disobay their Prince, inferiours to resist their superiours? that we preache nothinge but libertie, libertie? to be shorte, that we cannot agrée amonge our selues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the chiefest pointes of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. These and many such like slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous reportes; haue lyinge spirites put into the mouthes of the Romishe Cleargie, and their adherentes, which if thou credite to be as true as the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell, it wil be longe before thou beleue the truth of the Gospell.</p>
   <p>But if thou wilt voutchsafe, good Christian Reader, diligently to peruse in the feare of the Lord, this litle trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, not condemnynge it before thou reade it, nor wrestynge euery woorde to an euill sence, but with indifferēcie ponder eche thyng and iudge vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: then, then I hope that God will opē thine eies, and giue thée grace to sée &amp; to acknowledge his truth, wil enriche thée with wisedome, to discerne the Spirite of truthe, from the Spirite of
<pb facs="5"/>
errour, light from darknesse, Christe from Antichriste.</p>
   <p>To those slaunderous reportes I néede not to answeare particularly, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they be confuted by this woorke it selfe, as by readinge thou maist vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstande. But two pointes, I cannot omitte vntouched, which are often vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and neuer proued: that we falcifie the Scriptures, and agrée not emonge our selues; in the weightiest matters of Religion. Touchynge the firste, we gather the true meaning of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures <note place="margin">Expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge of Scripture.</note> by the circumstances of the text, by reconcilinge it with other places of God his woorde, to the confirmation of the truth, and not to the establishinge of our owne deuises: as some wreste them &amp; racke them, to maintaine their fonde phantasies, inuented of their foolishe braynes. We alledge not the <note place="margin">Racking of Scripture.</note> sayinge of Christe to Peter, <hi>Ego oraui pro te &amp;c.</hi> I haue prayed for thée, that thy faith fayle not, to proue that the Pope cannot erre: Nor, <hi>Nemo accen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit candela, &amp; ponit eam sub modio:</hi> No man lighteth a candell, and hideth
<pb facs="6"/>
it vnder a bushel, to shew that candels should be set at none daies on the Aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: nor, <hi>Lumen ad reuelationem gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium,</hi> a lighte to lighten the Gentils, for carriyng of candels on Candelmas daye: nor, <hi>Deus creauit hominem ad i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginem sui,</hi> God created man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to his owne image, for erectinge of images in Churches: nor Abrahams circumcisinge, for sole and chaste life: nor, <hi>Omnia munda mūdis:</hi> nor, <hi>Qui in carne sunt Deo placere non possunt,</hi> Al thinges are cleane to the cleane, They that are in the flesh cānot please God, to proue that Priests may not marry: Nor, <hi>Nisi abundauerit Iustitia vestra plus quam scribarum &amp; pharisaeorū, nō intrabitis in regnum coelorum,</hi> Excepte your rightuousnes excéede the rightu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnes of the Scribes and Phariseis, ye shal not enter into the kingdome of Heauē, to declare, that a Bishop muste haue more garmentes at his masse, thē Aaron had at his sacrifice. After suche a phantasticall childishe sorte, we vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently wrest not the holy Scriptures, to that sence whiche the holie Ghoste
<pb facs="6"/>
neuer meante. Now touchinge our disagrement emonge our selues in the <note place="margin">Disagre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</note> weightest matters of Religion. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if we agrée no better then Papistes doo, then were we at a great Iarre: wherefore, I counsell them to plucke the beame out of their owne eyes, and then indeuer to remoue the mote from their brothers sighte: be they so blinde that they sée not the ciuill warre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt thēselues, and that for the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest Articles of their Religion? Is not y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Popes supremacie a principall point <note place="margin">Papistes disagree, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie.</note> of their doctrine? And neuer harde thei that Pope Clement denieth that it is lawfull for a Bishoppe to beare bothe swoordes: saiynge, If thou wilt haue bothe, thou shalte disceaue thy selfe, &amp; those y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> heare thée? Contrary wise, that Pope Boniface the. 8. was in a solēne day decked in his <hi>Pontificalibus,</hi> and caried about Rome on mens shoulders (the great lobberly Babie woulde not goe alone, but must be borne) the next day glitteringe in his Imperiall robes he mounted on his Mule (an vncomely sight to beholde an Asse ridyng vpon a
<pb facs="7"/>
Mule) &amp; commaūdyng a naked swoords to be borne before him, he him selfe cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge with a loude voice, <hi>Ecce. duo gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dij hic,</hi> beholde here are two swoordes: bostinge him selfe to be Lorde of the whole worlde (muche like to Satans bragge) bothe concerninge Temporall &amp; Spirituall matters. Pope <hi>Pelagius</hi> affirmed, that the Supremacie of the Bishoppe of Rome, was ordained nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Men nor of Counsell, but by Christe his owne appointment. Pope <hi>John</hi> the. 3. his next successour vtterly denied it. Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the firste cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him the forerunner of Antichriste, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> would be named Vniuersall Bishop. Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the. 3. woulde be so cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, manger the téeth of his Cleargie, and obtained that proude title by the mischieuous ayde of the impious Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Phocas</hi> that Trayterous mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer, and murtheringe traytour. Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the. 3. acknowleged it to be the Emperour his right, to elect &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, whome he liste to be Bishoppe of Rome. Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> the thirde for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad the people to waight for the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours
<pb facs="7"/>
pleasure therein, deniyng that he had any thinge to doo in suche mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Beholde these Popes agrée for their Headship like cattes &amp; dogges.</p>
   <p>Is not erectinge of Images a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall <note place="margin">Papists dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agree a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages.</note> poincte of Popishe Diuinitie? how happened it then, that the Gréeke Churche, and the Latine Churche fell at such variance about thē, that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as before thei agreed friendly in other matters, &amp; were vnited as one Church, for Images they were seperated, and neuer sithens ioyned againe? Howe well agreeth Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the firste, who would in no wise haue Images to be woorshipped, or knéeled vnto, with Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the third, who decreed that they shoulde be woorshipped &amp; had in greater reuerence then euer they were before, &amp; that, whosoeuer were of a contrarie opinion, shoulde be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned as an Heretike? Is not Trā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>substantiation <note place="margin">Disagre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt about Transub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiation.</note> a chiefe, a principall, &amp; most necessarie Article of Popishe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie? how chaūced it then, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> not lōg after the reigne of <hi>Carolus</hi> the great, 840. yeares after Christe his incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="8"/>
there beganne suche maruelous great contention about it, and the best learned could not agrée in the matter, as the writinges and doynges of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tram, Iohn Scot, Paschasius, Lātfranke,</hi> &amp; diuers others witnesse? <hi>Lantfrancke</hi> confessed, that the earthly substaunce of breade is turned into the essence or substaunce of the Lorde his Bodie, so that it may truely be saide, that we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue bothe the selfe same true Bodie, which Christ toke of the virgin Mary, and that we receaue not the selfe same Bodie? Many of our late Transubstā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiators affirme, that the substance of Breade vanisheth away, and the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of Christe his Bodie cōmeth in place thereof. <hi>M. Hardyng</hi> biddeth vs <note place="margin">
         <hi>Articl.</hi> 12. <hi>Diu.</hi> 7.</note> beware, that we thinke not that the Bodie of Christe is made of Bread as of a matter, but sayeth y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> where bread was before, after Consecration there is the very Bodie of Christe, this good counsel he giueth, least we should mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conster his Augustine, who, (as he say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, albeit we can not reade it in him) writeth that the Bodie and Bloude of
<pb facs="8"/>
Christe is made of the Substaunce of Bread and Wine. The counsell called <hi>Concilium Vercellense</hi> allowed &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed the opinion of the saide <hi>Lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>franke:</hi> the Councell holden at <hi>Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gane,</hi> and an other at <hi>Turone,</hi> condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that <hi>Vercellense Concilium.</hi> Pope <hi>Innocentius.</hi> 3. in his <hi>Laterane</hi> Sinode added to the. 12. articles of our Christē Faith, Transubstantiation, as the. 13. Article, wheras diuers other Papistes thinke not that we are bounde to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue it in payne of dānation, or as the Articles of our beliefe. Some say, that the true and naturall Bodie of Christe is in the Sacrament, but not natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and sensibly: some other, that it is there naturally and sensibly, as it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident by <hi>Berengarius</hi> his recantation that Pope <hi>Nicolas</hi> &amp; the moste parte of the Cleargie present at the second coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell assembled at Rome then were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded. A late writer not so wise as hardie, shoting his croked bolte, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoteth his fellowes and him selfe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a straūge sorte: saying, that Christ his Bodie is present in the Sacramēt,
<pb facs="9"/>
(not as a Creature, nor as a Creator, but) after a māner as a thing betwene both, not after a grosse &amp; carnall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but spiritually and supernatural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and yet substantially, not by locall, but by substantiall presence, &amp;c. and to mende the matter, he inferreth at the laste, but in such a māner as God one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knoweth. Well fare a good helpe at a dead lifte, disputinge of Christe his presence, in the Sacrament, &amp; tellyng how he is there &amp; how he is not there, concludeth that he can not tell how he is there, for God onely knoweth &amp; not he, but blindely I leaue this blinde guide, and ignorant Doctor stumbling ignorantly in darknes, and teachynge in ignorance he seeth not what.</p>
   <p>It is a world to beholde, how shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully they disagrée about <hi>Hoc est Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi>
      <note place="margin">Disagremēt about the vvoordes of Consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>
      <hi>meum,</hi> This is my Bodie<hi>:</hi> some say they be not the woordes of Consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but that Christe did Consecrate, whē he Blessed: most parte denie that, some saye by the woorde <hi>Hoc,</hi> this is meante, Bread &amp; not his Bodie: some his Bodie and not Bread: some nether
<pb facs="9"/>
Bread nor his Bodie, but <hi>Indiuidüum vagū, indiuidüum in genere, indiuidüum entis, indiuidüum insignitū, Indiuidüum indiuidui,</hi> &amp; I know not what phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall vnknowen, vncertaine, vnsen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible thinge. Vouchsafe, good gentle Reader to peruse the answeare of the godly learned pretious <hi>Iuell</hi> and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rende father in Christe <hi>B.</hi> of <hi>Sarum,</hi> to <note place="margin">
         <hi>Articl.</hi> 24.</note> M. Hardinges <hi>Indiuidum vagū,</hi> and thou shalte finde, vij. or. viij. sundrie opinions or expositions aboute these woordes of Consecration, <hi>Hoc est Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus meum,</hi> this is my Bodie: which ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth either their blinde ignorance, or their obstinate malitiousnesse. Thus all men may sée, howe they dissent in Trāsubstantiatiō, one of the Articles of their beliefe. I néede not to declare the vehemencie of Pope <hi>Gelasius</hi> to <note place="margin">The Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in bothe kindes.</note> haue the Sacrament ministred in both kindes: affirminge, that he, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided the <hi>Euchariste,</hi> &amp; when he taketh y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> one parte, absteyneth frō the other, doth wickedly &amp; committeth sacrilege. For you know that Pope <hi>Innocentius</hi> thought it no sacrilege, but highe ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice
<pb facs="10"/>
to God, to commaunde that the Cuppe shoulde not be ministred to the Laye people. It were to long to shew, how pitifully thei dissent, &amp; how vncō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly they answeare, when they be vrged with absurdities, which necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilie foloweth their Transubstātiatiō.</p>
   <p>It were to tedious to trouble your <note place="margin">Disagre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt about the Masse.</note> good eares with the iarring discorde of Pope <hi>Leo,</hi> who helde it vnlawfull to saye any more then one Masse, in one Churche, in one daye: and our later Popes, who defende it to be merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to say a Trētall of Masses, in one forenoone, in one place, whereas in déede one halfe Masse were to manie. It were bootelesse to put you in remē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce that you shall finde very few, or none, but mislike some pointe or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Popishe inuentions: some the Latine seruice, some praier to Saincts, some the Popes Supremacie, some Purgatorie, some Iustification by woorkes, some ministring in one kind, some sole receauinge, some crepinge &amp; offering to Images, some the makyng the picture of God the Father, and the
<pb facs="10"/>
most parte Pilgrimage, pardons, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, with such like trumperie: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit they will openly defende the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Romish Churche, &amp; boldly talke their pleasure against the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers thereof. Hereby thou maiste per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, good Christian reader, what cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite should be giuen to thē, who would accuse vs of discorde, when they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues agrée not emonge them selues, but with shame inough, be at great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance for their Princely Supremacie, for the frée election, sure confirmation, and absolute iurisdiction of their holy Father the Pope, for the glorious ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of their wodden images, for their meruailous miracle of their straunge Transubstantiatiō, for the vnnatural presence of Christes Bodie in their hoste, for the coniuringe Woordes of their diuine Consecration, for the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege robbing of the lay people of the Cuppe, for to often sayinge of their I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous Masse, for the greatest mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries, highest pointes, strōgest keies, and chiefest Articles of their opinions. <hi>Turpe est doctori, cum culpa redarguit</hi>
      <pb facs="11"/>
ipsum. It is a foule faulte to rebuke an other for that, wherein thou thy selfe most offendest. If they answeare that the truth of their doctrine is one, albeit in some pointes, a few dissent, and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour a little of errours, &amp; so ascribe the blame to men, and not to Religion, it might please them to alledge the same excuse for our defence. For, as here in this confession thei may reade: the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of our doctrine dissent not one from the other. If thē any cominge out of Egipte, desire to woorshippe God in the forme of a Calfe as the Egiptians did: or beinge lately weaned from the breste of Gentilitie, longe to lap some sower whigge of <hi>Paganisme:</hi> or beyng turned from <hi>Iudaisme,</hi> delight in sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie of <hi>Aarons</hi> gorgious ceremonies: or beynge conuerted from Papistrie smell fulsomely, sauer ranckely, yea stinke filthelie of some dunge of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie, blame the mē, and not the truth. For wine is not to be dispraysed, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause dronkerdes distemper thēselues therewith: nor meate to be refused, for that gluttons surfaite thereby. The
<pb facs="11"/>
vndoubted veritie of God his woorde is pleasaunt meate, and comfortable drinke to that Christian soule, whiche doth hunger &amp; thirste after rightuous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, albeit y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> queasiè stomackes of the vngodly cannot brooke it, or the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of weakelings, wil not kéepe al, but caste vp some, that it receaueth. As for vs, it may plainely be perceaued by this little treatise, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we dissent not in any Article of our beliefe: in any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of saluation or damuation: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ceremonies, in trifelinge and indifferent thinges, yea &amp; in such sort, that notwithstādyng we al consent in this, that they may be altered, remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and quite abolished without any great hinderāce to Christ his Church.</p>
   <p>Thus haue I giuen thée warning, good Christian reader, of two daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous snares: wilfull Ignorance, and slaunderous Reportes, wherwith thy craftie enemy Satan woulde intangle thée, and withholde thée from cōminge to the truth. Now then it resteth, that thou wilfully doo not blindefield thine eies, from beholding the clere light of
<pb facs="12"/>
the Gospel, least wittingly thou stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble into perilous ginnes, nor lightly open thine eares to beleue forged slaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, least thou be faste tied, with the stronge cheynes of diuelishe illusions, but that thou willingely marke the proufes on bothe sides, &amp; indifferently heare, what we teache, and so vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iudge our cause: whiche thinge that euen the simplest might the better doo, I haue done mine indeuour faithfully to trāslate out of Latine into English the Confession of the Christian faith, cōpiled by the generall consent of sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie Christian Churches, as by the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle thou maist vnderstande. I liste not at large to cōmēde their godly Zeale, who woulde not couetously hoorde vp from their poore bretherne so greate a treasure, but liberally deuide it emong them to the enritchinge of their soules with heauenly riches, for so thei might lose the chiefest parte of their deserued prayse, by the folye of a slender cōmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Neither minde I to extoll the woorthinesse of their woorke: for pure Golde cōpared with rustie brasse pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth
<pb facs="12"/>
it selfe, and néedeth no prayser. This onely I affirme, that by readyng this booke, the learned may refresh his memorie, with profitable repetinge of that he hath bene taught, the vnskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full may learne that he neuer knewe, the faithfull maye be confirmed in the truth, the infidell reclaymed from his errour, the Parent, the Childe, the Maister, the seruaunt, the Prince, the subiect, instructed to serue God, to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in his vocation, to fulfill his due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, so that muche profite may ensue to all, except any mā beyng blinded with the darke miste of superstition &amp; ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, disdayne to reade the truthe, whome iustly we maye accuse of wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ignorance: or els, beinge wedded to his lewde phantasie, cōdemneth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he readeth, who declareth him self to be of a malitious frowardenesse, stubbernlie bente against Christe and his woorde. God (if it be thy will) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert all such from theyr sinfull waies: God giue them the spirite of wisdome, to consider, that it is harde for them to kicke againste the pricke: God soften
<pb facs="13"/>
their stonie hartes, least the preachyng of thy Gospell be to them, <hi>Odor mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis in mortem,</hi> a sauour of death vnto death and eternall damnation. God indue vs all with his heauenly grace not onely to heare and reade this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible truth, but to beleue it also: that beleuing it, we may openly professe it, and openly professing it, may cōstant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly continue therein, &amp; constantly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuynge therein, may leade our liues accordingly, to the profite of our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, the edifiynge of thy Churche, the defacinge of Hippocrisie, the rootinge vp of iniquitie, the establishinge of thy woorde, the aduaunsinge of thine ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and our soules Saluatiō: Graūt this O mercifull Father for thy déere sonne Iesus Christ his sake, to whome with thée and the holy Ghost, be praise and glorie for euer and euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>q, I. O.</signed>
   </closer>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>