<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO ALL THAT WISH WELL TO OVR SY∣ON, HEARTILY AND VN∣fainedly: Grace be multiplied and peace in our Lord Iesus Christ.</title>
           <author>Jemmat, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118180_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13544</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23838</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118180</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO ALL THAT WISH WELL TO OVR SY∣ON, HEARTILY AND VN∣fainedly: Grace be multiplied and peace in our Lord Iesus Christ.</title>
                 <author>Jemmat, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A mappe of Rome : lively exhibiting her mercilesse meeknesse, and cruell mercies to the Church of God: preached in fiue sermons, on occasion of the Gunpowder Treason, by T.T. and now published by W.I. minister. 1. The Romish furnace. 2. The Romish Edom. 3. The Romish fowler. 4. The Romish conception. To which is added, 5. The English gratulation</title>
                 <author>Taylor, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bartlet, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Thomas 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 100 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO ALL THAT WISH WELL TO OVR SY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON, HEARTILY AND VN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly: Grace be multiplied and peace in our Lord Iesus Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Rethren, beloued in the Lord: You see by the Title, what you may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect in the booke following. I hope what it promiseth, shall be indeede performed. I wish it were more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete and accurate for your sakes: as it might haue beene, if the graue and diligent Author could himselfe haue set it forth: but blessed be God, that his weightier employments doe not giue him leaue or leasure. I am glad I haue it for you as it is, through my earnest request to him: whose modesty thought it vnworthy the publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and my paines in writing it.</p>
   <p>Reasons of this my request and paines, I can giue you many. First, I thinke it necessary, that our God, our gracious and louing God, may haue the praise of all his mercies (and namely that of <hi>this day</hi>) still reserued to himselfe wholly. His workes are glorious, and the benefit of them not confined to a scantling of time. Therefore these
<pb facs="3"/>
Gratulations cannot be lesse seasonable now than they were at the day of Deliuerance. Secondly, this I hoped might be a meanes to restraine our <hi>declining times</hi> from gazing and doting on that pompous Harlot, the Church of Rome. For when our nation shall see, and consider a fresh, how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satiable she hath alwaies beene of blood, and Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish blood! I cannot thinke we can be so inconsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate, as to dreame of any toleration, much lesse any sound reconcilement with so implacable an enemie. Thirdly, I thought it not altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible hereby to stop the slanderous mouthes of misse-conceiuing persons, scattered abroade through all the Country, yet pleasing themselues in the common error: who seeing in some good men a difference of iudgement in some small mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, presently conclude them enemies of the State, &amp;c. For this I will say of the Author, <hi>(and I say the truth in Christ,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.1.</note>
      <hi>I lie not, my conscience bearing me witnesse in the holy Ghost:)</hi> that hauing beene partaker of his Ministery some hundreds of times, I neuer heard him more earnest, or more faithfull, than in this Argument. And the whole Towne of Reding will testifie with me of his holinesse, low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse, peaceablenesse, vnweariable painfulnesse, and other graces beseeming his calling: which no ill-willer could euer yet impeach. Fourthly, and lastly, my intent is hereby to stirre vp our drowsie and forgetfull hearts to due thankfulnesse for so great a Deliuerance. And this (me thinks) is more than necessary. For when I behold the generall view of the Land, and the quality of peoples man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
<pb facs="3"/>
the memory of that <hi>wonderfull day</hi> seemes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me quite blotted out: And I know not whō bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to resemble our selues vnto, than those of whō the Psalmist speakes, Psalm. 106.11.12.13.14. <hi>The waters couered their enemies: there was not one of them left. Then beleeued they his words: they sang his praise. But they soone forgat his workes: they waited not for his counsell: but lusted exceedingly in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernesse, and tempted God in the Desert.</hi> Doe we not so euen in our Canaan, a Land flowing with milke and hony? What horrible prouocations are there daily and hourely amongst vs, in all places, in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry corner? Who can complaine sufficiently of the grieuous temptings and out-brauings of God, which our eyes doe see? Who would iudge by our strange demeanours, that God had euer done any thing for vs, either by sea or land, either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst water-workes or fire-workes? Ah sinfull na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, laden with iniquity! Doe we thus requite the Lord for his louing kindnesse? Is this his reward for so great fauours?</p>
   <p>Hearken ye children of Syon, and consider: <hi>Though Israel play the harlot, yet let not Iudah trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse.</hi> Though carnall persons,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Hos.</hi> 4.15.</note> who haue no true sence of the grace of Christ, set themselues out in their colours, and fashions, and Epicurisme, and Heathenisme, yet let it not be so with them that professe the feare of God. Though others loathe the word, and the meanes of saluation, yet let not Professors loathe them. Let it neuer be said, that Professors are proud, earthly, contentious, vaine, fantasticall, or willingly sweruing from the Rule
<pb facs="4"/>
of Piety.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.5.</note> You are his <hi>peculiar</hi> people: and if hee lose his honour in you also, he loseth it altogether. Therefore consider you the workes of the Lord, and his intent in them. Stirre vp your hearts, and frame your liues to a <hi>reall thankfulnesse.</hi> Let your moderation and discretion be quickned by zeale: and let your zeale be bounded by discretion. You shall (perhaps) mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e with <hi>shame,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2.</note> that is, reproches and ignominies: <hi>despise</hi> these. You shall meet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so with the <hi>crosse,</hi> that is, persecutions and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages: these <hi>endure.</hi> Here is patience, and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namity. Let your patient minde be knowne to all men: yet let it be valorous in the causes of your God: saint not, neither be afraid. You may well take occasion to grow the faster by this <hi>Antiperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stasis,</hi> and vnite your forces the more strongly. Are you so spighted and maligned on euery side by profane Ismaelites? then let your loue toward one another encrease the more solidly, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound toward your selues mutually <hi>in the fulnesse of the blessing of the Gospell.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.29.</note> Liue fruitfully and peaceably in the Communion of Saints: here the Lord hath appointed the blessing, and life for euermore. Watch against Satan and his eldest sonne <hi>that Antichrist:</hi> pray for the dissolution of their Kingdome: especially see it be vtterly defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in your selues and yours. Giue all diligence to leaue an holy seede behinde you, which shall praise the Lord in earth, while your selues praise him in heauen.<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> A disgrace it is to godly Parents to haue vngodly children, especially by their owne default. Make your houses, houses of God,
<pb facs="4"/>
by setting vp, and then establishing his pure wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship therein. Cast vp your accounts before-hand, and prepare for the comming of Christ in the clouds. Accept my endeauours for your good, and helpe me with your prayers.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>Reding.
<date>Oct. 12. 1619.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your seruant in the Gospell of Christ, <hi>WILLIAM IEMMAT.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>