<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>In laudem Authoris. To the Helliconian Water-Poet, my honest friend, Iohn Taylor.</title>
           <author>Davies, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118287_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13512</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23806</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118287</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>In laudem Authoris. To the Helliconian Water-Poet, my honest friend, Iohn Taylor.</title>
                 <author>Davies, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Taylors Vrania, or His heauenly muse : With a briefe narration of the thirteene sieges, and sixe sackings of the famous cittie of Ierusalem. Their miseries of warre, plague, and famine, (during their last siege by Vespasian and his son Titus.) In heroicall verse compendiously described</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Butter, Nathaniel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomia">
   <lg>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <head>In laudem Authoris. To the Helliconian Water-Poet, my honest friend, <hi>Iohn Taylor.</hi>
      </head>
      <l>IN euery Art, saue Poetry, the meane</l>
      <l>Is praisd: but therein meanely-well to do</l>
      <l>Is base, too base: then Iudgment cannot leane</l>
      <l>On whats too base, but base it must be too.</l>
      <l>Then each man that his Reputation huggs</l>
      <l>For Iudgment, praise no lines of but meane Reach:</l>
      <l>And laude but what drawes dry <hi>Mineruaes</hi> duggs,</l>
      <l>Lest they their Iudgments might thereby impeach.</l>
      <l>Then is my Iudgment <hi>Iack</hi> perplext in thee;</l>
      <l>For thou dost write so well with meanes so ill</l>
      <l>That thine Admirer I confesse to be,</l>
      <l>Much rather then the Iudger of thy skill:</l>
      <l>Art makes not Poetry, thou dost plainly proue,</l>
      <l>But supernaturall bountie from aboue.</l>
      <closer>
         <signed>Iohn Dauis.</signed>
      </closer>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <head>In Vraniam <hi>Iohannis Taylor</hi> Encomium.</head>
      <l>IT is disputed much among the Wise,</l>
      <l>If that there be a water in the skies:</l>
      <l>If there be one: no Waterman before</l>
      <l>Was euer knowne to Row in't with his Oare.</l>
      <l>If none; such ic thy high surmounting pen</l>
      <l>It soares aboue the straine of Watermen:</l>
      <l>Whether there be or no, seeke farre and neere</l>
      <l>Th'art matchles sure in this our hemispheare.</l>
      <closer>
         <signed>William Branthwaite Cant.</signed>
      </closer>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <head>In Vraniam <hi>Iohannis Taylor.</hi>
      </head>
      <l>IN sport I hitherto haue told thy fame,</l>
      <l>But now thy Muse doth merit greater Name:</l>
      <l>Soares high to Heau'n, from earth and water flies,</l>
      <l>And leauing baser matters, mounts the skies.</l>
      <l>Where hidden knowledge, she doth sweetly sing</l>
      <l>Carelesse of each inferiour common thing.</l>
      <l>Oh that my Soule could follow her in this,</l>
      <l>To shun fowle sin, and seeke eternall blisse,</l>
      <l>Hir strength growes great, and may God euer send</l>
      <l>Me to amend my faults, as she doth mend.</l>
      <closer>
         <signed>Robert Branthwaite.</signed>
      </closer>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <head>To the honest Sculler <hi>Iohn Taylor.</hi>
      </head>
      <l>THe water Nimphs that do the Thames frequent</l>
      <l>(The dearest daughters of the <hi>Driads</hi> old)</l>
      <l>Concluded once, with one combyn'd consent</l>
      <l>A day of Sacrifice abroad to hold.</l>
      <l>With which they did old <hi>Innachus</hi> so please</l>
      <l>(The God of Riuers, Fountaines, Wells, &amp; Springs:)</l>
      <l>That he to giue his sacred Nimphes some ease</l>
      <l>Inuites the Muses to their offerings.</l>
      <l>For which, agreed it was by all the Nine,</l>
      <l>That since so well the watry Dames did sing:</l>
      <l>Some one of theirs, with power most deuine</l>
      <l>They would inspire, as Guerdon of the thing.</l>
      <l>Then chus'd they thee, and on thy nimble braine</l>
      <l>Pow'rd out a draught of Heliconian wine:</l>
      <l>Which when <hi>Apollo</hi> saw, he did refraine</l>
      <l>To guide the light, and with a sharpe Ingine</l>
      <l>He crown'd his daughters gifts, and with a Bay,</l>
      <l>That then was twinde about his golden haire</l>
      <l>Which he from his belou'd had pluck'd that day</l>
      <l>He wreath'd thy browes, and bad thee that to weare.</l>
      <l>Since when thy Muse aspir'd to things deuine,</l>
      <l>Still grac'd by <hi>Phoebus,</hi> and the Sisters nine.</l>
      <closer>
         <signed>Henry Sherlye.</signed>
      </closer>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <head>To my honest friend <hi>Iohn Taylor.</hi>
      </head>
      <l>WHat shall I say, kind Friend, to let thee know</l>
      <l>How worthily I do this worke esteeme:</l>
      <l>Whereof I thinke I cannot too much deeme</l>
      <l>From which I finde a world of wit doth flow.</l>
      <l>The poore vnpollisht praise I can bestow</l>
      <l>Vpon this well deseruing worke of thine,</l>
      <l>Which here I freely offer at thy Shrine</l>
      <l>Is like a Taper, when the Sunne doth show,</l>
      <l>Or bellowes helpe for <hi>Eol's</hi> breath to blow,</l>
      <l>For thou as much hast soard beyond the straine,</l>
      <l>Whereto our common Muses do attaine</l>
      <l>As <hi>Cinthyaes</hi> light exceeds the wormes that glow.</l>
      <l>And were my Muse repleat with learned phraise,</l>
      <l>The world should know thy work deserueth praise.</l>
      <closer>
         <signed>
            <hi>Thine in the best of friendship,</hi> Richard Leigh.</signed>
      </closer>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <head>To the Author <hi>Iohn Taylor.</hi>
      </head>
      <l>WAst euer knowne to any time before,</l>
      <l>That so much skill in Poesie could be</l>
      <l>Th' attendant to a Skull, or painefull oare,</l>
      <l>Thou liu'st in water, but the fire in thee;</l>
      <l>That mounting Element, that made thee chuse</l>
      <l>To Court <hi>Vrania,</hi> the diuinest Muse.</l>
      <l>Row on: to water-men did neuer blow</l>
      <l>A gale so good, none so much goodnesse know.</l>
      <closer>
         <signed>Thomas Brewer.</signed>
      </closer>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <head>To my freind <hi>Iohn Taylor.</hi>
      </head>
      <l>ROw on (<hi>good Water-man</hi>) and looke backe still</l>
      <l>(Thus as thou do'st) vpon the <hi>Muses Hill,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>To guide thee in thy <hi>course:</hi> Thy <hi>Boate's a Sphaere</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Where thine <hi>Vrania</hi> moues <hi>diuinely-cleere.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Well</hi> hast thou <hi>Plyd'e,</hi> and (with thy <hi>learned Oare</hi>)</l>
      <l>Cut through a Riuer, to a nobler <hi>shore</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Then euer any <hi>landed-at.</hi> Thy <hi>saile</hi>
      </l>
      <l>(Made all of <hi>clowdes</hi>) swells with a prosp'rous <hi>gale.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Some say, there is a <hi>Ferryman</hi> of <hi>Hell,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>The <hi>Ferryman</hi> of <hi>Heau'n,</hi> I now know well,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="6"/>And that's thy Selfe, transporting <hi>Soules</hi> to <hi>blisse,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>VRANIA sits at <hi>Helme</hi> and <hi>Pilot</hi> is;</l>
      <l>For <hi>Thames,</hi> thou hast the <hi>lactea via</hi> found,</l>
      <l>Be thou with <hi>bayes</hi> (as that with <hi>starres</hi> is) crown'd.</l>
      <closer>
         <signed>Thomas Dekker.</signed>
      </closer>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>