<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the deuout and Chri∣stian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118144_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03778</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13898.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118144</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the deuout and Chri∣stian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Great Brittaines resurrection: or the Parliaments passing bell : By vvay of psalmodie, against the tryumphing of the Papists, in their seuen psalmes. And in imitation of the song of the three nobles of Israel, deliuered out of the fierie ouen of Babell. By VVilliam Hubbard, Chaplaine to the Kings Maiestie, in his Highness Tower of London. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Hubbock, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Johnson (Jonson), Arthur</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the deuout and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Foundation and direction of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing my thoughts, by way of Psalme, hath beene the Apostles holy canon and sanction:<note place="margin">Col. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>Let the word of Christ dwelt in you plenteously in all wisedome▪ teaching and admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing your owne selues in Psalmes and Himnes,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Why this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise by way of Psalme.</note>
      <hi>and spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall songs.</hi> And I finde that our Lord and Maister Iesus Christ, after he had kept his passeouer with his disciples, and washed their feet after supper:<note place="margin">Ioh 13.2. Math. 26.30.</note> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted &amp; performed the sacrament in an excellent sermon or sermocination reaching from <hi>Iohn,</hi> cha. 13 31. thorough the whole 14.15.16. chapters, with a prayer annexed, containing the whole 17. chap. he thought not this heauenly feast and banquer, suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently furnished, vnlesse hee closed vp their spirituall stomack with a Psalme, as some precious marm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>let<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> For so saith the scripture: <hi>When they had sung a Psalme,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math 26.2.</note>
      <hi>they went out into the mount of Oliues. A most Christian exercise, and too much neglected among professours.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in great varietie of inuention in verse &amp; prose, in Latine and English, in sermon &amp; otherwise, haue trauelled in this argument laudably and fruitfully: some memorably euen by the voyce of a dolefull
<pb facs="4"/>
Pyramis demolished in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> crauing restitution in noble great <hi>Brittaine:</hi> yea the Theater and English <hi>Roscius</hi> himselfe hath pourtrayed this work of God, and set it aloft, <hi>tanquam in arce Phidiae,</hi> as it were in the turret of the famous caruer <hi>Phidias,</hi> to the view of all men. But I tooke this course, the rather, because I obserue the friends of the Romish Pioners, to haue had a secret seauenfold Psalmodie, as a claudestinarie orison frō hand to hand, in which they solace them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues with strange notes, and tunes, and ditties, and hopes of newes:<note place="margin">Select senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces out of the Popish newe Psalter. In their 4. Psalm.</note> as in an insolent Paean, triumphing before hand, for a Iubily &amp; golden day at hand. I will set downe some of their words, because the booke is not in manie hands. And I by a good friend came by the most of it. Of innocent King <hi>Edward,</hi> thus they speake: <hi>England,</hi> ah vngratefull <hi>England,</hi> forgat the liuing God, and felt the curse of hauing a child to her King.</p>
   <p>Of our late Queene, of thrice blessed memory, thus they seeme to say: The nobility to their owne vtter extirpation shamefully forsooke their Bishops, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out assistance.</p>
   <p>Of our noble Soueraigne they seeme thus: Alas, O Lord: that thou hast suffered a parching winde to blow from the North:</p>
   <p>Which made the boughes of thy planting to wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the flourish thereof to decay:</p>
   <p>And yet as it were recomforting themselues, thus they seeme to prophecie.</p>
   <p>In a moment canst thou crush her bones, and lay her pride in the dust:</p>
   <p>And: The earth is infected with the wickednes
<pb facs="4"/>
of the Inhabitants, and crieth vnto thee for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance:</p>
   <p>And possibly would swallow them as it did <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>re</hi> and his company: were it not for thine elect sake:</p>
   <p>Reuenging fire of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomor</hi> might bee iustly feared:</p>
   <p>And: Confirme the heart of those thy labourers: endue them with strength from aboue, and giue suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse vnto their endeuours:</p>
   <p>Againe: Embolden our hearts with courage, to concurre with them freely in furthering thy seruice.</p>
   <p>And in another place: Confirme your hearts in hope, for your redemption is not farre off.<note place="margin">In their second Psalme.</note>
   </p>
   <p>The yeare of visitation draweth to an end: and Iubilation is at hand:</p>
   <p>And: <hi>Ierusalem</hi> shall be built vp againe: and the second glory thereof, shall be greater then the first.</p>
   <p>And: Righteousnes shall prosper, and infidelity shall be plucked vp by the rootes.</p>
   <p>God will arise as from a long slumber, &amp; establish againe the arke of his sanctification.</p>
   <p>And: The roote which hath waxen olde vnder ground, man shoote vp againe as a fresh plant by the riuer side:</p>
   <p>False errour shall vanish as smoake:</p>
   <p>And they which sawe it, shall say: Where is it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come?</p>
   <p>Iust iudgment &amp; holy lawes shall be restored, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>Againe: His tabernacle he will spred againe; and dwell amongst vs as in times past.</p>
   <p>And: Sacred songs shall break their long silence, the lamp of our Lord shall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="5"/>And: The resemblance of heauen shall be renu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the resemblance of hell shall be destroyed.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>England</hi> shall be called a happy Realme, a blessed Country, a religious people.</p>
   <p>Those which knewe the former glory of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, shall lift vp their hands for ioy, to see it returned againe.</p>
   <p>Those that neuer saw it shall be strucken with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation: wishing that they had sooner knowne the truth: condemning their fathers which forsooke it.</p>
   <p>Men shall say of it, one to another: heere is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede the house of God, and the gate of heauen.</p>
   <p>How great diuersitie is betweene truth and false<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, deuout solemnities, and counterfet ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies?</p>
   <p>From the East point to the West, men shall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse their errors.</p>
   <p>They which thought themselues wisest, shall say they knew nothing:</p>
   <p>Gladly shall people walke in their auncient steps of truth and equitie, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>The Prince of peace will breake the exactors rod. &amp;c.</p>
   <p>No longer will he dissemble the oppression of his people▪</p>
   <p>He is bent to reuenge their cause.</p>
   <p>The daughters of <hi>Babylon</hi> shal be cast downe: and in the dust lament their ruine.</p>
   <p>Proud heresie shall strike her sayle: and groane as a beast crushed vnder a cart wheele.</p>
   <p>Againe: The omnipotent hath sworne to make
<pb facs="5"/>
her stoupe: and that he will abase her haughtines.</p>
   <p>Againe: The memorie of nouelties shall perish with a crack: as a ruinous house falling to the groūd.</p>
   <p>And: Hee will come as a flame that bursteth out beyond the surnace.</p>
   <p>His fury shall flie forth as thunder: and pich on their tops that maligne him.</p>
   <p>Againe: A second <hi>Cyrus</hi> hath he stirred vp: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming his Scepter for the good of his people.</p>
   <p>He shal likewise bring the Infants of <hi>Sion</hi> from all quarters of their banishment: Ioyfully shall they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne from forraine lands.</p>
   <p>And those Countries, where now they harbour, shall finde succour in this Ile for their necessities.</p>
   <p>Againe: The tempestuous night being passed: a perpetuall day shall be our comfort.</p>
   <p>His truth, his iustice, his Priests, his sacrifice shall be no more taken away.</p>
   <p>I haue beene the larger: that the reader might see, &amp; obserue the Papists expectation out of their owne many words without equiuocation. But <hi>Mutatis mutandis</hi> the prophecie shal be inuerted vpon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues: as is in part alreadie: Magnified be the name of God therefore.</p>
   <p>Now for this my methode, as it were a letanie or procession: and a kinde of spirituall preambulation thorough the whole <hi>England,</hi> as men doe to keepe their bounds: so we to see in particular and generall how much we are bound to God:<note place="margin">Exod. 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ud. 5.</note> wee haue excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent presidents to omit <hi>Miriams</hi> song, and <hi>Deborahs,</hi> which both stand vpon the resolution into particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars: but in <hi>Dauid,</hi> himselfe more notably: <hi>Dauid</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
the sweet singer of <hi>Israel,</hi> the king of singers, first Psal. 136. which vsed to be sung of the Leuites in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:<note place="margin">1. Chro. 16.41.</note> In which Psalme as it were by a logicall or theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall predicament, hee beginning with the great works of GOD in generall, hee after diuideth his thoughts into the works of creation, and administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:<note place="margin">
         <p>
            <hi>Odê Epae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticos, ê anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strophos.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Why repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
         <p>Presidentes of particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capitulation, and a burdē of words in songs of thanksgiuing See also Psalm. 118. in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</p>
      </note> hee goeth from the heauens to the earth: hee particularizeth in the great lights the sunne and the moone. In the works of administration he exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifieth in the Lords destroying <hi>Aegipts</hi> first borne: in bringing <hi>Israel</hi> out thence: in cutting sea into two parts: in bringing <hi>Israel</hi> thorough the midst: and not at the shore and in some shallowe place: In ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing <hi>Pharao</hi> and his hoast there: In leading this people thorough the Desart: In smiting great kings for their sakes: particularly <hi>Sihon</hi> and <hi>Og</hi>: in giuing his people their land: in remembring not their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serie onely, but in feeding all flesh. The burden of all which to euery verse is:
<q>The mercy of the Lord endureth for euer.</q>
   </p>
   <p>That is to say: Gods mercy appeared not then onely and in those particulars, but for euer: And that these particulars were stakings downe, that they had had Gods mercy from time to time, and might be sure of it for euer: euen as <hi>Esay</hi> the Prophet saith: Heare,<note place="margin">Esay, 55.</note> and your soule shall liue: and I will make an euerlasting couenant with you: the sure mercies of <hi>Dauid</hi>: What is this else, but you shall be as sure of my loue as euer <hi>Dauid</hi> was: And in a neerer exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,<note place="margin">A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. president.</note> Psal. 148. hee rangeth and marshalleth the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in order, with redoubling the same wordes: praise him all ye his Angels: praise him all his armies:
<pb facs="6"/>
praise him sunne and moone: praise him heauen of heauens, and ye waters that be aboue the heauens, let them praise, &amp;c. praise ye the Lord frō the earth, Dragons, depthes, fire, hayle, snow, vapours, winds, mountaines, hills, beasts, creeping thinges, and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered fowles, Kings and all nations, Princes, and all Iudges of the earth: young men and maydes: olde men and children: Let them praise the name of the Lord, &amp;c and why all these? For the particular mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie (saith <hi>Dauid</hi>) in exalting the horne of his people. Euen as <hi>Esay</hi> on the other side in the impenitencie of the people contesteth heauen and earth:<note place="margin">Esay. 1.2.</note> attesteth Oxe and Asse against <hi>Israels</hi> ingratitude.</p>
   <p>And hence no doubt was deduced the canticle of the three children, though apocrypha,<note place="margin">The song of the three chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: O all ye works of the Lord, &amp;c.</note> yet very aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and inserted for the worthines of it into the liturgie of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Where the three great noble men and rulers of thy Prouinces them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues personally stand forth, and beginning from the generall workes of God, discend to specials: in heauen to Angels, sunne &amp; moone: and passe along the cloudes in their spirits, to showers, windes, fire, heat, winter, sommer, dewes, and frosts, yce &amp; snow: and knock at the dore of euery creature in the earth: mountaines, green things, wells, seas, floods, whales; fowles, beasts, particularly summoning men: more particularly <hi>Israel</hi>: among them the Lords Priests and seruants: the soules of the righteous: and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men that walke with God, and indure any thing or euery thing for him:<note place="margin">O'A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aria, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaria &amp; M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ael: doe you praise the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> the Lord.</note> and by name they call vpon themselues: As though all the creatures were obte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted to helpe them to praise God, &amp; to acknowledge
<pb facs="7"/>
this Creator and preseruer of them: and that they who had the chiefe deliuerance, though men of care, knowledge, and vnderstanding in all learning and wisedome, yet were vnsufficient without worlds of helpe.<note place="margin">Dan. 1.17. &amp; 2.17.18.</note> Therefore as God presented all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures before <hi>Adam</hi> their Lord &amp; owner vnder God: and at another time all the creatures of the earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Noah,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gen. 2, 19.20. &amp; 7.14.</note> their preseruer vnder the same God: And as Landlords haue their tennants to shew their poll, and to pay head siluer to their Lords in their Courts yearely: And as sea-men scaping shipwrack, offer vowes,<note place="margin">Ionas 1, 16.</note> and hang vp tables of deliuerance: so haue I endeuoured by these holy examples, and the like to present in all humble duty all degrees and estates before this Lord their preseruer, with crownes of sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation on their heads, palmes of victorie in their hands, Psalmes of thanksgiuing in their mouthes. For when the funerall men of <hi>Rome</hi> tolled our last knel among thēselues:<note place="margin">To the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments passing Bell.</note> so certainly that they thought all the Physitions of great <hi>Brittaine</hi> could doe her no good: and that God himselfe had forsaken her: say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, now the Protestant shall die, &amp; his name perish: did not the Lord of life cause the bel to stay on a sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine:<note place="margin">Psal. 41.5.</note> and hath hee not spirited her againe with a fresh life,<note place="margin">Great Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. Heb. 11.19.</note> and made her the daughter of a ioyfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection. As it is said of <hi>Isaac,</hi> that <hi>Abraham</hi> after a sort receiued him frō the dead, when he was so neare vnto death and yet deliuered. My meaning was to stirre vp all our spirits, mine owne and others, and to keepe vs somewhat waking, least security the bane of all should creepe in. For if right vse be made of this: what doth let but we may write: <hi>Aeterna Britannia
<pb facs="7"/>
magna</hi>: wherein no doubt a princely and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble monument from this Senate in a festiuitie ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for euer to be kept (which shall be like a marble piller, with a real,<note place="margin">Parliament holy day.</note> and compendious inscription of the matter and occasion ingrauen walled about, and a keeper of it as of other monuments for all to visite) to Gods glory and increase of our faith and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, shal reuiue our anniuersarie thankfulnes to all posteritie. And me thinkes I obserue a new edge vpon many louers of religion since,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.19. 1. Sam. 5.4. <hi>Vt ingulent homines sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt de nocte latrones: vt temet serues non exper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giscere?</hi> Theeues rise by night to kill: and thou to saue thy selfe by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king hast no will.</note> when they see God hath so prouoked them by a foolish and idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous people desperately zealous for the setting of <hi>Dagon,</hi> that thereby with greater inflamed hearts the friends of <hi>Sion</hi> labour to resetle the arke of God vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our center for euer. In which for my part I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but praise God for the feruour and ardent spirit of the most honorable and zealous lower house, like the spirit of famous <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> and a fierie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>globation in their holy and deuout dispositions in many notable propositions, and yet also giue God most hartie thanks for the graue, moderate, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture considerations of the most honourable &amp; high part of the vpper house, as the sage spirit of melanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thon, and a refrigeratiue constellation: whose ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and influences shal by Gods grace haue hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly and mighty effects very beneficiall to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like good in due time, and their sweet aspect and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing respect vnto one another, and to the whole by their happy and peaceable coniunction shall profit, vpon further occasions that which is behind of their faith, wisedome, and zeale, which shall be the better effected, if we could all goe one way. For I perceiue
<pb facs="8"/>
in many cases, as the Lamprey and serpent ingender, so some professors so named (for I except the graue, humble, modest, and fatherly, whom I know many) and the Papist with diuerse ends ioyne to debase him, that without respect of factions in his honest simplicity and plainenes, opposeth himselfe to two extremes:<note place="margin">Aristotle li. 1, eth. ca. 6.</note> Great was the light of wisedome, that shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Gentiles: He that wil preserue truth, must not only confute other mens opinions, but his own. And would to God al sides could learne of the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of wisedom, not to do any thing for displeasure against any supposed tares,<note place="margin">Math. 13.</note> as to pluck vp wheat: and all sides so to denie themselues and their own name, that we might thinke it no disgrace, but good deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to say in a common voyce: Thy name be sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,<note place="margin">Math. 6.</note> O Lord, whatsoeuer become of our name. And heere I most humbly desire as in this last passage, so in the whole processe the friendly christian and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable construction &amp; indulgence of all men: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in any thing by omission or addition is mistaken, which in such variety of degrees to sort euery one with their proper attributes and offices is easie for a contemplatiue man, labouring according to this place &amp; my function, to be a remembrancer among many: knowing that as in a race though men runne swiftly of themselues, yet the clapping of hands of other obseruers, &amp; of them that blowe the trumpets, addeth a new courage and vigour to them. The sum of my desire is:<note place="margin">Cantic. 4.2.</note> that all our people of great <hi>Brittaine</hi> hereafter may be like one flocke of sheepe, as the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost speaketh: as in good order come vp from their washing: a peculiar people abundant and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<pb facs="8"/>
of good works: euery one bearing twins and none barren among them:<note place="margin">Tit. 1.14. 2. Cor. 5.11.</note> that our Church know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the terrour of the Lord, heereby as Christ spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, may be purged, and bring forth more fruit; that it may grow as the Lily, and haue rootes of <hi>Lebanon</hi>:<note place="margin">Ios. 15.2.3.</note> that she may looke forth from her sleepe,<note place="margin">Hos. 14.5, 6, 7.8.9.</note> as the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning faire as the moone, pure as the sunne, terrible as an armie with banners, that all the world may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse: what nation is so great vnto whom God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth so neare in all that we neede,<note place="margin">Cantic. 6.9.</note> euen before wee call vpon him: What nation so great,<note place="margin">Deut 47. Esa. 65.24.</note> that hath ordinances and lawes so wise and so righteous, as they haue set out in this their day. <hi>Amen.</hi> April. 29. 1606.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>