<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Translatour to the Readers.</title>
           <author>Codrington, </author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118646_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20943</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7321</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118646</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Translatour to the Readers.</title>
                 <author>Codrington, </author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of the knovvledge of God, as excellently as compendiously handled by the famous and learned divine, Peter Du Moulin, late minister of the Reformed Church in Paris, and professor of theologie in the Vniversitie of Sedan. Faithfully translated out of the originall by Robert Codrington, Master of Arts</title>
                 <author>Du Moulin, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sheares, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 72, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_readers">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The <hi>Translatour</hi> to the <hi>Readers.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Treatise needs not a Preface to entertaine you, or encourage you; the title it self is eloquent enough, yet Custome expecteth that some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing should be spoken of the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, &amp; the Author: and it were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannerly besides, at my first comming abroad, to presse into your acquaintance without saluting you. As there is nothing then more excellent than this Subject; so there is no man that could discourse on it more excellently then the Author, the Author abounding with the Subject, and directing the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding to that knowledge by which he wrote it. The Atheist may here learne as well how to worship as to believe a Deity, and reading the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode of his wisedome in the Characters of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, may as well be convinced by Reason as Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. The Epicure may acknowledge the loose impiety of his Idoll pleasures, and engaged in more holy and high devotions may performe no more homage to his pursive God. The Recusant may perceive that Heaven is not to be bribed by his merites or his money, but may here finde his salvation more cheape, and certaine. The Treatise is but small, but what wants in the volume is sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed
<pb facs="4"/> in the Subject: it was borne in the English aire, though not in the English tongue, this is the Fate of Bookes to be eloquent at first, and to speake in variety of tongues, the diversity of languages being by them promoted into a blessing, and they seeme like so many inspirations, and to be Prophets of that knowledge which our understandings all shall enjoy hereafter. This then being so expert in other languages, it was pitty me thought it should want his own, and had only the power to perswade me to this work attended with a desire which I had by the imparting of our Authors knowledge to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove your owne, a desire which (where they are legible in earnest) can excuse absurdities, and even sanctify the Errours; but I write an Epistle, not an Apology, and am neither doubtfull of mine owne integrity, or indulgent to the faults of others, whom I am so farre from flattering, that I must pronounce to excuse them is a sacriledge, and to conceale them the lowdest slander, these are they who with impure hands doe translate themselves into their Authors papers, and deprived of their native glories, doe present them to the world in their owne deformities; they disguise their beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in those accents they would advance them, as if our language was either too dull or too stubborn to expresse them, and Eloquence was onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined unto France; nay, so delicate is their impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that it attempteth only the choycest Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, and the rarest of Authors have the leasure to repent their miserable Eloquence: but such is
<pb facs="4"/> the vertue and the happinesse of learning, that from hence shee hath receiv'd incouragements, it being an addition to her glory to be admir'd by all; and being prais'd by Ignorance, from the mouth of her enemy she becomes more fruitfull. The Sunne forbeares not to impart his beames because they draw up clouds, which doe as much obscure his beauty, as expresse his power, and these lights of Learning continue still their illuminating influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, though those guilty shaddowes doe invade them, and conscious of the vertue that did attract them, they doe rather forgive then suppresse their splendour. But the workes of this our Author be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as rich in substance as in beauty, are able to carry their owne strength and light through all the defects of a rude Interpreter; this piece onely of all his Labours lay almost forgotten, and hid from observation, which being set forth by so divine a hand, and in such perfect colours, I thought it some religion in me to draw the curtaine, and to present it to the publike view, wherein if I have satisfyed you, it shall be new honour unto me, that I have fulfill'd with all the desire of goodnesse, which is to communicate her selfe, and obeyd her incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations as</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Ambitious of your best prosperity. Codrington.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>