<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, THE Lord Maior of London, the Right Worshipfull the Sheriffes and Alder∣men, and the rest of the Godly Citizens and Offiers, who haue eyther stayed in their Places and Duties during this Visitation: or sent their large and comfortable Bene∣uolence for the Poore. The Blessings of this and a better Life.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118685_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19581</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6017.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118685</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, THE Lord Maior of London, the Right Worshipfull the Sheriffes and Alder∣men, and the rest of the Godly Citizens and Offiers, who haue eyther stayed in their Places and Duties during this Visitation: or sent their large and comfortable Bene∣uolence for the Poore. The Blessings of this and a better Life.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Londons lamentation for her sinnes : and complaint to the Lord her God. Out of which may bee pickt a prayer for priuate families, for the time of this fearefull infection. And may serue for a helpe to holinesse and humiliation for such as keepe the fast in priuate: together with a souereigne receipt against the plague. By W.C. pastor at White chappell</title>
                 <author>Crashaw, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Fairbeard (Fayerbeard), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>60 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, THE Lord <hi>Maior</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> the Right Worshipfull the <hi>Sheriffes</hi> and <hi>Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and the rest of the Godly Citizens <hi>and Offiers, who haue eyther stayed in their</hi> Places and Duties during this Visitation: or sent their large and comfortable Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolence for the Poore. The <hi>Blessings of this and a better Life.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT HONORABLE:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the Ordinance and Appointment of GODS owne Wisdome in the Law, that all his Sacrifices and burnt Offrings should be seasoned with Salt, the Fire impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Zeale, by which euery Sacrifice
<pb facs="3"/>
must be offered, and the <hi>Salt</hi> signifying <hi>Discretion</hi> with which it must be seaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: If it wanted eyther of these; it could not bee accepted. Now, as this literall Fire and Salt belonged to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> so the Spirituall is both commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and commanded to vs, that liue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the sweet yoke of the <hi>Gospell</hi> euen to the Worlds end: Namely, that all our Sacrifices &amp; Seruice, if we mean to haue them acceptable to God, or auaileable to our selues, must not onely bee offered with the Fire of holy <hi>Zeale;</hi> but tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with holy Wisdome, and seasoned with the Salt of due <hi>Discretion;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore sayth▪ Christ euen in his Gospell,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Mark.</hi> 9. 49</note>
      <hi>Euery one shall bee salted with Fire, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Sacrifice shall bee seasoned with Salt:</hi> Whereunto Saint <hi>Paul</hi> alluding exhorts<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 2.</note> all Christians to see that <hi>Their Seruice and Sacrifice, bee not only holy and liuely, but also reasonable.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Hence it is Right Honourable, and Worshipfull, that as our gracious King, out of his Humilitie and holy Zeale, commanded publike Fasting &amp; Prayer, for the diuerting of this publike Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
<pb facs="3"/>
So now, out of holy and deepe discretion hath suspended for a time those publike meetings within the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: Out of no dislike of Fasting and Prayer, nor any wearinesse of those ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Exercises, as some Malignant Spirits malitiously traduce Him. But out of conscience to his God &amp; care of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects liues: wisely considering (&amp; in our knowledge most truely) that seeing the sick &amp; sore (do what we Ministers could to the contrary) mingled themselues confusedly, with the sound (by which meanes its more then manifest, many thousands haue perished in this Citie and Suburbs.) It therefore lay vpon him as Supreme Magistrate and Gods Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant to looke to the <hi>liues</hi> as well as to the <hi>Soules</hi> of all his people, and to take order, that the Fasts ordained for the bettering of the <hi>Soule,</hi> should not so be vsed, as to tend to the destruction of the <hi>body.</hi> Leauing vs therefore in this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stressed Citie, the Lords Day or Sunday for our soules, which being of Diuine Institution, can admit no Dispensation by humane power, and still commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="4"/>
and commanding vs that Day to fast &amp; pray in priuate, and all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome else to doe it in publike for vs: And for the sauing of our liues, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd the tempting and prouoking of God. Hath wisely forbidden all other publike meetings of dangerous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course in places Infected, till order can be taken (which is no easie thing to doe) to keepe the sound and sicke asunder.</p>
   <p>Now as all those that be well are not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding to repaire to the Church, to be partakers of the publike Prayers &amp; the holy seruice appointed for that day, so, for a helpe, of Humiliation and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Deuotion to them that stay at home, whereof also many thousand Families especially in our Suburbs are not able to buy the Booke, I haue therefore beene perswaded to make publike this Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, Confession, and Prayer, which in these dayes of publike Calamitie, I walking hourely through the valley of the shadow of Death, (burying forty, fifty, sometime sixty a day, and in the Totall, more then two thousand alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die) I poured out in the presence of my
<pb facs="4"/>
God: First, in priuate for my selfe, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards for the vse of those many thousand sicke soules that are or haue beene in my great poore Parish: And lastly, that hereby I might offer some Sacrifice and speciall piece of Seruice in way of holy thankfulnesse to the Lord our God, who hath hitherto pleased to preserue me, and my Brethren the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors of this Citie by his owne hand and power, beyond all humane helpe and hope; walking continually, euen in the midst of the fiery flames alwayes in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and neuer in more perill then in the Pulpit: wherein the Lord hath beene so marueilous, &amp; so magnified, his loue and power vpon vs, as if he should now take vs away, yet hath hee so deliuered vs, in discharging our duties, and by his holy Angels kept vs, thus being in our way, till hee hath literally made good that promise in the Psalme, yea, and much more: for alas wee haue not only seene a <hi>thousand fall at one side of vs, and ten thousand at another,</hi> but (alas, alas, that our sinnes should so prouoke our God) euen more then ten thousand on
<pb facs="5"/>
the one, and more then twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand on the other. Which mighty work of God, if wee should sit still and swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and superficially passe ouer, and not commend it, to our Brethren in the Countrey, whose turnes must follow God knowes how soone, as sure as God hath begunne with vs; and if we did not preserue the memory of it, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent it to Posterity, for their instruction, and that the Generations yet vnborne may prayse the Lord; all holy men would accuse vs, Gods Church would censure vs, our own Consciences would condemne vs, and God himselfe take vengeance of vs, as most vnthankfull Caitiffes, euen Monsters of Mankind, &amp; vnworthy to breath vpon the Earth.</p>
   <p>Being therefore in some sort touched with the sense of this hand of our God, both of his hand of Iustice and of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and being euerymoment put in mind of our mortality, eyther by the sound in our eares, or sights in our eyes; can we but be moued (vnlesse we were senselesse <hi>Stocks &amp; Stoicks)</hi> to take into our serious and continuall Consideration, the now
<pb facs="5"/>
most lamentable Case, of this late so flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing a Citie, and of this whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome into which this wild-fire of Gods wrath begins so fast to flie, and can wee but lay to heart so great a sorrow? Or dare wee for our soules but deale truly with our God, in seeking sincerely and carefully searching out the true cause in our selues, in our people, and in the whole Kingdome that should thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke the Lord against vs? Certainly some heauy judgement must fall vpon vs if we doe not, and will follow them whoeuer they bee that double and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble with their God in this case.</p>
   <p>And if any that be abroad and yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visited, thinke I deale too farre and too freely in this Confession. I aske no more but to forbeare his judgment, til they be vnder the hand of God, as we haue bin now three moneths and more, and then they will iudge I am too short: The while God in mercy pardon that, and wherin I may be thought to go too far, I shall easily answere it to God or Gods Anointed: &amp; shal sigh &amp; sob in secret to consider the wrath &amp; woes that wait for
<pb facs="6"/>
those wicked ones, who as they deeply haue had their hand in pulling downe this Plague, so carelessely seeke to passe it ouer, and looke not after the God that hath smitten them, and the whole Land for their sakes, and will if they turne not betimes, smite them downe to Hell: What stony hearted Stoicke can he be who sees more then forty thousand Christians, many as good, and some better then Himselfe laid in the dust, in little more then twice forty dayes, and is not humbled vnder the Hand that did it, and sensible of the Sin that did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure it? Can hee bee a good Seruant of God or Subiect to his Souereigne, that besides ten thousand aged, weake, and poore, shall see an Army of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand more, braue, lustie, and seruiceable young men, and tenne thousand more comely and mariageble young women, and ten thousand more young Infants, whose proofe and hope had beene still before them, already taken out of one Corner of this Kingdome, and sits not downe in dust and ashes mourning to that God that tooke them, for that King
<pb facs="6"/>
that lost them, with that Land that wants them. For that Sinne that pluckt them from vs? I dare pronounce vpon him from God whoeuer hee bee that can or dare thus sleightly and sliely passe by the workes of God, and laughes in his sleeue at such a judgement as this, is markt vp by God for some greater vengeance as sure as the fourteenth of <hi>Ezekiel</hi> is Gods true Word. For if hee that mournes for sinne be the man that is Markt by God for blessing and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance, whats hee that makes a sport of sinne; and layes from his heart the Iudgements thereby procured, but one thats sealed vp for confusion and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction: O therefore that my heart were a Fountaine, and my eyes Riuers of teares, that I might worthily bewaile the sinnes of our Nation together with mine owne, and weepe for the slaine of the Daughter of my people: So cried the holy Prophet of the abundance of his holy Zeale; and so I am sure in their seuerall measures doe all the Ministers and men of God amongst vs, that haue but tasted of the same spirit, mourning
<pb facs="7"/>
for the desolations of this Citie; and more for the Contagion that causeth it, and most of all, for the sinnes that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured them both: And who would not care to sacrifice themselues what way the Lord should please, so the wrath of God might bee pacified towardes this Church and Nation, and those plagues remooued which are the cause of this Plague: And till these be remooued, we shall find the Prophets tell vs true, that eyther this Plague shall stil stay &amp; creep like a Canker ouer our whole body, or else only make make way to some more fearefull that shall follow after it.</p>
   <p>That this may be preuented, he cannot be a Christian that will not both cry to God, and confesse to him the publike, and priuate, and personall sinnes that be the cause thereof. And as all that are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled and taught by the holy Spirit of God; to poure out their soules in hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prayer, and hearty Confession, will in holy obedience to the holy Prophets<note place="margin">Hos. 14. 2.</note> counsell; <hi>Take vnto themselues words, and returne vnto the Lord:</hi> So for those that cannot open their mouthes as they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire,
<pb facs="7"/>
and yet haue hearts that groane af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God, and soules that seeke the Lord. For their assistance only haue I beene perswaded to publish this, which now I leaue to them, and them and it together, with our selues to the mercifull accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and gracious blessing of our <hi>Good God:</hi> who grant vs all in these dayes of danger (when somtimes almost a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand a day are pickt vp, and pluckt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way before our faces) So to liue and so to dye, as when we dye we may be sure to liue for euer. And so to part with one another here, as we may be sure to meet in Heauen: And here so to confesse our sinnes, as at the last Day Christ may confesse vs to be his owne. And so to pray here as we may prayse God eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>