<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Advertisement for the following Drogs.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118966_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01934</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12070</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118966</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Advertisement for the following Drogs.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Pharmaco-pinax, or A table and taxe of the pryces of all vsuall medicaments, simple and composed, contayned in D. Gordon's apothecarie and chymicall shop : within Mr Robert Farquhar's high lodging, in New Aberdene. Together with certayne approved remedies against diseases, which now most reigne amongst the commons. All for the vse of the people; proportionate both to rich and poore, learned and unlearned; and profitable to all</title>
                 <author>Gordon, D., apothecary</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Raban, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Aberdeen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="advert_for_medicines">
   <pb facs="21"/>
   <head>Advertisement for the following Drogs.</head>
   <p>SEeing this Arte hath ever hither-to vnder-lyen the slander, That poore Folkes cannot bee benefited by it; wee haue for their Solagement prepared some cheape Medicaments, which indeede worketh the same effect as those of the Rich: but the Ingredients are not so exactlie refined, nor the Composi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions so delicate in taking, or pleasant in working, <hi>Tales habent labra lactucas.</hi> Wee haue lyke-wyse framed some approved Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meadies, to the most frequent Diseases of the People: who if they cannot endure a methodicall eradicating cure, at least, they shall receiue an Empericall Remead, <hi>quasi vnum pro omnibus,</hi> which wee hope shall doe their turne in a good measure, as they will record that pleases to essay them.</p>
   <p>Also, wee haue provided, good store of Cordiall Waters, and Antidotes for the Pest, which now ravaging our Neighbour Kingdomes, may invade vs next: considering the maligne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, the vnconstancie and vnkindlinesse of the Aire, sudden death, and vnacustomed symptomes of Sowning, that followeth Diseases this yeare: but aboue all, our lewd lyues; if fervent Repentance, and frostie Winter, interveining, prev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ane not. GOD of His Mercie maintaine vs this Peace and Plentie, that wee may safely throng into the House of GOD, and breathe in others Faces, with-out danger.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>