<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A godlie Preface made by him, whosoeuer he was, that translated this booke out of the Latin tongue into French.</title>
           <author>G., A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118358_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13680</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23973</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118358</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A godlie Preface made by him, whosoeuer he was, that translated this booke out of the Latin tongue into French.</title>
                 <author>G., A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of the imitation of Christ, three, both for wisedome, and godlines, most excellent bookes; made 170. yeeres since by one Thomas of Kempis, and for the worthines thereof oft since translated out of Latine into sundrie languages by diuers godlie and learned men: now newlie corrected, translated, and with most ample textes, and sentences of holie Scripture illustrated by Thomas Rogers</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Seres, William, Assignee(s) of</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 277, 11 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>A godlie Preface made <hi>by him, whosoeuer he was,</hi> that translated this booke <hi>out of the Latin tongue</hi> into French.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F this booke, which concerneth the following Christes example, haue heretofore yeelded some frute to such as haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them-selues to the reading thereof; I thinke it wil yeeld no lesse hereafter, specialie now that it is rid and clensed from a number of imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that were in it afore.</p>
   <p>And although it be apparent, that the conuersation of such as cal themselues Christians, is woonderfulie corrupted: yet notwithstanding because God is so good, that he wil euermore drawe some one or other of an infinite multitude from it: it maketh me that I am not altogether out of hope.</p>
   <p>Againe, like as in great and sore disea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, al the best remedies that can be deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, are wont to be applied with al speede: euen so the more we see wickednes and vngodlines to abound, the more ought we to consider by what meanes they may be remedied, that some may be saued among so manie thousands, which are hardharted and enimies to al good warnings.</p>
   <p>It must needes be granted, and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence prooueth it sufficientlie; that there was neuer anie age, wherein Christians
<pb facs="12"/>
haue bin more out of order, nor haue had lesse regard of godlines, than they haue at this daie: yet notwithstanding, this ought not to bar vs, from hoping that God wil drawe some continualie to himselfe. On the other side, like as among a great sort that are striken with extreame sicknesses and diseases, some doe alwaies scape as it pleaseth God: so is it to be hoped, that among an infinite number of false Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, God wil touch some to bring them backe from the filthines and corruptions of the world, and to leade them to the fearing of himselfe.</p>
   <p>Moreouer, it is not to be doubted, but that God hath alwaies some seruants of his, as it were couered vnder the great number, which by the power of his holie spirit, doe liue continualie in al purenes &amp; vndefilednes, without cleaning or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting to the vngodlines &amp; disordered<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the wicked.</p>
   <p>And this is it which confirmeth me in my hope, that this little booke shal not be vnprofitable nor fruteles.</p>
   <p>Neuertheles, this booke is not ful of great cūning, nor beautified with flowers of humane wisedome, neither doth it dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course or treate of high or darke things▪ neither is it stuffed with subtil questions and arguments, nor indited with eloquent style, as those commonlie be which are propounded and set foorth to the world, rather for boasting and vainglories sake, than for anie desire to doe other men good. This booke is plaine, and without anie great gainesse; but yet so ful of good
<pb facs="12"/>
and wholsome instructions, that I dare wel auow, that whosoeuer readeth it with a right disposed mind, without respect to<note place="margin">Profit of this booke.</note> anie other thing than God and the salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his owne soule, which is the onelie marke that we must leuel at: he shal reape singular profit thereby.</p>
   <p>As for my part, I can witnes of my selfe, that God hath oftentimes made it to serue me for a spurre, to quicken and waken me vp from my slothfulnes and dulnes, and to kindle in me a desirousnes of his seruice; and I hope that the like shal befal to al such as shoote at none other mark, but to knowe, feare, and loue him with a pure, right meaning, and single minde; and to leade a holie conuersation before him.</p>
   <p>And in good sooth, it may wel be said,<note place="margin">Good bookes as ladders to climbe vp to heauen.</note> that vnto true Christians, good and holie bookes are as ladders to climbe vp to heauen; as sparks to kindle the heate of the spirit, when it is quenched or waxed colde in them; and as props to staie vp their faith that it may take increase.</p>
   <p>I speake of true Christians. For as for them that are Christians but in words and ceremonies: some of them be so bereft of al true feeling of God and of their owne conscience, that they neuer enter into the considering of the thing that might be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailable and necessarie to the wel instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of them in the truth, and to the trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of them to some godlie behauior; but are wholie giuen to the things of this life, as though there were none other after it▪ And othersome haue their mindes so tied to the letter, that they can make none ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb facs="13"/>
of anie other bookes, but such as may make them skilful, eloquent, sharpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witted, and subtile, and consequentlie woonderful among men, despising al such works as may make them better by moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them to the exercises of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession. And of this sort the number is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie grear nowadaies; of whom nothing can be said, sauing that (as the Apostle speaketh of them) they can welynough say with their mouth that they knowe God, but in their deedes and workes they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce him <note n="a" place="margin">Tit. 1, 16.</note>.</p>
   <p>And trulie we be come to a time, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we be more giuen and more hastie to reason and dispute of our religion, than to be religious in deede; more giuen to make great and large discourses of it, than to put it in practise, and to shew the truth and purenes of it by our holie conuersati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; &amp; at a word more giuen to talke than to doe: insomuch that we may wel per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that the Christian profession is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else nowadaies, but a lipwisedome, and a skil to hold talke among such as make their vaunts of it.</p>
   <p>But what▪ doe I terme it a lipwisdome▪ Nay, would God it were not rather turned into a fleshlie and licentious loosenes▪ as we may partlie see alreadie by too manie effects thereof.</p>
   <p>But so doth it alwaies befal to such as hauing receiued Christs doctrine, applie not themselues foorthwith to the forsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of themselues, without the which it is not possible for vs to be Christs true disciples <note n="b" place="margin">Matth. 16, verse. 24.</note>. For as the light cannot match
<pb facs="13"/>
with darknes <note n="c" place="margin">▪2. Cor. 6, verse. 14.</note>: so cannot Christs Spirit match with sin and the lusts of the flesh: insomuch that if the practise thereof be omitted, there is none other thing to be looked for, but a kind of libertie where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by men shaking off al yoke, shal giue them selues ouer to al euil, &amp; sooth themselues in their sinnes. Not that they keepe not stil some outward shew and countenance of godlines: for vnles it be some Epicures and godles men, they neuer proceede so far as to doe awaie and to giue ouer al ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God.</p>
   <p>But yet are al such shewes and outward countenances in vaine, &amp; of none account before him which requireth mens harts <note n="d" place="margin">Deut. 6, 5. Matt. 22, 37</note>, and contenteth not himselfe with the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie outward deedes <note n="e" place="margin">Iohn. 4, 22. 23.</note>, wherewith notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing they thinke to quiet their owne consciences, and to auoide the feeling of Gods wrath for their sinnes▪ which thing may wel serue for a time in the behalfe of the ignorant, and of such as haue no better skil; but as for those which knowe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the seruing of God consisteth, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be maruelouslie abashed, if they fal to examining of their owne wicked conuersation.</p>
   <p>For then there is no ceremonie (howe faire a shew so euer it beare, no not euen though it be of the number of those which God hath inioined for the keeping of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in his Church) that can satisfie the conscience which is trobled with the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of it owne sinne, and make it sure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the iudgement of God, who wil not iudge vs according to ceremonies, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb facs="14"/>
to our works <note n="f" place="margin">2. Cor. 5, 10</note>.</p>
   <p>We reade what Iesus Christ wil saie to such as shal haue cast out Diuels in his name <note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 7, 23</note>, prophesied in his name, and wrought manie other great things in his name: Away from me (wil he saie to them) yee workers of wickednes. How much more then wil he saie so, to such as occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieng themselues alonelie in some cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, &amp; not in the true godlines which the Apostle saith is profitable to al things <note n="h" place="margin">1. Tim. 4, 8</note>, shal haue giuen themselues to folowe their flesh and the world!</p>
   <p>To be short, we must come to this point, that forasmuch as Christianitie is not an outward profession, ne a thing that consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth in outward ceremonies, (so as it may suffice to busie our selues about it,) or in words (as who would saie it were ynough to haue the skil to talke and discourse of it as men doe of other worldlie sciences;) but it is the verie power and might of God <note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 1, 16. 1. Cor. 1, 18.</note>, whereby God intendeth to renew, and as it were to create againe his owne image and likenes in man, who is falne from it by his owne fault, and to set it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in the former brightnes and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that he may attaine againe to the blessed immortalitie: it is not to be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but that the same is the thing whereon we ought to fixe and settle the eies of our mind, and wherevnto we ought to applie al our wits, straining them earnestlie and to the vttermost of their powers to attaine therevnto. Otherwise we shal but lose our labor in seeking after this or that; and al that euer we can doe shal serue to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose,
<pb facs="14"/>
but onelie to traine vs the further from the marke that is set before vs.</p>
   <p>I knowe wel it wil be replied herevnto, that the thing which I speake of can not be obteined in this life, wherein we be sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to so manie infirmities <note n="k" place="margin">Genes. 6, 5.</note>, and are so corrupted and fraile, that it is vnpossible to attaine thereto.</p>
   <p>Neither doe I say, that we can attaine so farre as to be set perfectlie againe in our former vncorruptnes, so long as we be hild wrapped in this mortal bodie <note n="l" place="margin">Wis. 9, 15.</note>: That is reserued for the world to come, wherein al things shal be reduced to the highest perfection <note n="m" place="margin">Reu 21, 1. 2, &amp;c.</note>. But my meaning is onelie to declare, that the thing which shal be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished there, must be begun in such wise here, as we may not cesse to drawe neerer and neerer vnto it <note n="n" place="margin">Phil. 3, 13. 14.</note>, by shortening our waie continualie.</p>
   <p>And surelie the Scripture teacheth vs manifestlie, that none shal become parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the glorious rising againe <note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 6, 5. 4.</note>, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in consisteth the ful measure of our felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but those which haue endeuored here to die vnto sin, and to liue againe in new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of life, (which is called the first resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,) euen by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Spirit of Christ whom al true Christians haue clothed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues withal: which haue mortified the deedes of the flesh <note n="p" place="margin">Gal. 5, 19. 20. 21. Roman. 8, 4. 5. 2. Corin. 7, 1. Coloss. 3, 5.</note>; which haue put off the old man <note n="q" place="margin">Eph. 4, 22. 24.</note> with al his works; and put on the new man according to the image of him that created vs; and which haue clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed themselues here from al vncleannes both of bodie and soule.</p>
   <p>And that is the reason why saint Paule <note n="r" place="margin">Colos. 3, 4. 5.</note>,
<pb facs="15"/>
hauing said that when Christ appeereth, we also shal appeere with him in glorie; doth foorthwith warne vs to mortifie our members that are vpon earth: whereby he doth vs wel to vnderstand, that this morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication must go afore in vs here, if we purpose to attaine to glorie.</p>
   <p>The same Paule telleth vs that our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies shal be quickned by reason of Christs spirit <note n="s" place="margin">Rom. 8, 11.</note> which shal haue dwelled in vs here, and whereby we shal haue repressed al our froward affections.</p>
   <p>Also Saint Iohn protesteth <note n="t" place="margin">1. Ioh. 3, 3.</note>, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer putteth his trust in Christ, doth purge himselfe after y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> example of Christ.</p>
   <p>To be short, there are infinite texts tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this point in the holie Scriptures. And though there were no mo but this one which they vtter so often, namely that the vnrighteous shal not inherit the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God <note n="u" place="margin">1. Cor. 6, 9.</note>; it might be ynough to content vs withal, &amp; to put vs in feare, and to moue vs to the true and earnest repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
   <p>But alas▪ We be so loth to yeeld to this point, and our flesh breedeth vs so manie hinderances, that we doe what we can to eschew that burthen, and to shake it from our shoulders. But in so doing what do we else, but striue against our owne soule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>helth, and resist Gods grace, who cōmeth to saue vs, howbeit by such meanes as he himselfe hath ordeined, and by such waie as he commandeth vs, and not by meanes or waies of our owne choosing!</p>
   <p>Wel said, God hath commanded vs to beleeue in his Sonne, and for our belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="15"/>
on him he promiseth vs euerlasting life, so as al they which beleeue in Christ, taking him for their Sauiour, and applieng to themselues al the benefites which he hath purchased for vs by his death: are in the right waie.</p>
   <p>But who be these beleeuers▪ Euen they (saith the Apostle) which walke not after the flesh but after the spirit <note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 8, 1.</note>; they which take paine to frame themselues to the wil of Christ; into whose bodie they be graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed, and vnto whom they be knit together as his liuelie members <note n="y" place="margin">Eph. 3, 17. 18. 19. Ephes. 4, 15. 16.</note>; they which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuor to loue God, and to giue ouer the loue of themselues <note n="z" place="margin">Luk. 9, 23.</note> and of the world <note n="a" place="margin">1. Iohn. 2, verse 15. 16.</note>; they which haue their whole conuersati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in heauen <note n="b" place="margin">Phila. 3, 20</note>; they which loath their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer life, and for feare of falling thereinto againe, doe the more watch, and looke the warelier to their thoughts, deuises, words, and deedes: they which feeling their owne weakenes and infirmitie, make incessant praier to God for the spirit of strength and stedfastnes <note n="c" place="margin">1. Thes. 5, verse. 17.</note>; &amp; which feeling their cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and vnlustines, doe craue the spirit of feruencie and earnestnes; they which in aduersitie do keepe themselues from mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring, and endeuor to be patient <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 5, 3. 4. 5. Iames. 1, 3. 4.</note>; they which bethinke themselues of Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, and yeeld him thankes for them <note n="e" place="margin">Psal. 116, verse. 12. 13.</note>; they that straine themselues to succur their neighbors both in bodie and soule <note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 12, 4. 5, &amp;c. 1. Cor. 12, 12 13, &amp;c.</note>; and at a word, they which crucifie the flesh with the affections and lusts thereof <note n="g" place="margin">Colos. 3. 5.</note>.</p>
   <p>Insomuch that they in whom these fruts are not found, ne make not the talent of faith to preuaile in such maner as I haue
<pb facs="16"/>
told you, cannot be said to be in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the true beleeuers &amp; faithful ones, notwithstanding that they pretend some countenance of honestie, and therefore much lesse can those be said to be of that number, in whom the works of the flesh <note n="h" place="margin">Gal. 5, 19. 20. 21.</note> are apparent.</p>
   <p>But some fleshlie Christian wil saie stil,<note place="margin">Imputation of righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> that as for him, he is clothed with the righteousnes of Christ; that the perfect obedience which Christ hath yeelded to God his Father in satisfieng the law, is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted vnto him, as if he himselfe had yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it; and (to be short) that he is recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for righteous by his faith, so as none of al his imperfections are to be made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of.</p>
   <p>If thou listest to beguile thy selfe, thou maist: but it wil be to thy harme and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion. In deede Christ laieth not our sins to our charge, if we beleeue aright in him, neither shal al our imperfections hinder the vertue and efficacie of his death. But to beare thy selfe in hand, that Christ hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thee for righteous, when thou giuest thy selfe to vnrighteousnes, and hast none other care but to follow thine owne inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate lusts: it is not onely a dooing of great dishonor vnto him, but also a scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of him for his redeeming thee.</p>
   <p>And I praie thee, what man of good and sound iudgement, dareth say, that Christ holdeth him for lowlie, which is puffed vp with pride▪ Or for liberal and charitable, which is ful of niggardlines, distrust, and vnkindnes▪ Or for a louer of God, which is ful of selfe-loue and loue of the world▪ Or
<pb facs="16"/>
for a worshipper of God, which maketh no right account of him▪ Or for a deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in God, which hath none other care but to satisfie his owne pleasures and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights▪ Or for a man mindful of Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, which is vnthankful▪ Or (to speake more homelie) a whooremonger for a chaste person, or a glutton and a drunkard for a sober and moderate feeder▪ I beleue that euen thou thy selfe (if thou consider it throughly,) wouldest be ashamed to thinke it, and much more to speake it. For how is it possible y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> a man shoulde be righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous without righteousnes, good with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out goodnes, vertuous without vertue!</p>
   <p>Saint Iohn saieth manifestly, that as Christ is righteous <note n="i" place="margin">1. Ioh 3, 7. 8.</note>; so he that worketh righteousnes is righteous; and that he which sinneth is of the Diuel: yea and he saith moreouer, that the thing wherein the<note place="margin">10.</note> children of God doe shewe themselues to differ from the children of the Diuel, is that the one sort worke righteousnes, and the other sort worke sinne.</p>
   <p>And of a truth, I cannot tel how Gods true children, who are al true Christians, coulde otherwise be better marked out, thā by their applieng of themselues night and daie, to do whatsoeuer is pleasant and acceptable to their heauenlie Father; whom because they knowe to be righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, they also doe wholie endeuor them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to do righteous things, wherin they shew themselues to be borne of him, as S. Iohn sheweth yet further. If ye knowe (saith he) that God is righteous, knowe ye also that whosoeuer worketh righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb facs="17"/>
is borne of him <note n="k" place="margin">1. Iohn. 2, verse. 29.</note>.</p>
   <p>Moreouer, how can it come to pas, that the true Christians should not giue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to righteousnes, seeing they haue Christs spirit, (for he that hath not Christs Spirit (saith the Apostle) is no Christian,) which being holie of himselfe, cannot but driue forewarde the partie to al holines, whom he possesseth? It cannot be but that he must needs bring forth his fruts, which are <note n="l" place="margin">Gal. 5, 22. 23.</note> louingnes, gladnes, quietnes, merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, meekenes, faithfulnes, mildnes, and staiednes. To be short, it cannot be, but that he must needes alter the whole man both within and without, to make a newe creature of him.</p>
   <p>But see to what point Satan and our owne nature bring vs: namesie, to fal a sleepe, and to sooth our selues in our vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to make vs to let the bridle lie loose on our necks, &amp; al vnder color that Christ imputeth not our sinnes vnto vs <note n="m" place="margin">2. Corin. 5, verse. 19.</note>, Naie, he imputeth them vnto vs if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in them <note n="n" place="margin">Tit. 2, 11. 12.</note>. For he died not to leaue vs in them stil, but to take vs out of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and in very deede <note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 6, 5. 6, &amp;c.</note>, as witnesseth fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther saint Iohn, who telleth vs plainlie <note n="p" place="margin">1. Ioh. 3, 5.</note> that Christ appeered to take awaie our sinnes. In which place he intendeth not to speake (as I take it) of the forgiuenes of our sinnes past, but to saie that Christ doth really and in verie deede take away their sining in works, which do beleeue on him; which cannot be done, but that he must al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so therewith put into them, and imprint in them the loue of righteousnes.</p>
   <p>Neuertheles, I will not straine my selfe
<pb facs="17"/>
any further about this matter, which would require a whole booke rather than a Preface. And in good sooth, I had not spoken so largelie thereof, but that I ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped to do some men good therby, who vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence that they deserue not aught at Gods hand, do make so smal account of the good works which God requireth at our hands, that they giue ouer the exercise of al godlines, and do weede out of their harts al regard of good life, and of seeking their soulehelth with feare &amp; trembling <note n="q" place="margin">Phili. 2, 12 Rom. 11, 20.</note> as they shew wel ynough by the sequele.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, I thought by that meanes to drawe on the readers to the receiuing of this little treatise the more willinglie; wherein as there is not anie thing contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but such as may serue to teach vs to order our life wel; so was it also requisite to shew, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> there is no point of Christiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in vs, vnles we set our whole hart ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon. And on the other part, forasmuch as the ground hereof is how we may folowe the example of Christ: it was verie conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to warne Christian folke to inforce thēselues thereto, without flattring them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, &amp; without foding themselues with vaine opinions that might turne them frō the right waie, or hinder them in it.</p>
   <p>For sith hat Christes life was not set foorth vnto vs alonely to make a legend of it, or to make a wondring at it in words, but to be followed by vs: it is the marke wherevnto we must tend, in drawing to perfection as neere as is possible, and as much as our frailtie can affoord. And o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise, seeing we be tolled there vnto by
<pb facs="18"/>
Iesus Christ himselfe, not onelie in words but also by examples, which are as liuelie portraitures of the life which we ought to leade here, in waiting for his glorious cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming againe; we cannot exempt our selues from it without preiudice of our saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, no nor yet without bewraieng that we haue no list to it. For were we rightlie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous to become happie, and to attaine to the endles life which is promised vs in Christ: we could not shew it better, than in taking the waie thereto, whereby we both may and must attaine vnto it.</p>
   <p>And that waie is none other, than to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in Christ, and to walke as he walked. And that is Saint Iohns meaning where he saith <note n="r" place="margin">1. Iohn. 2, 6</note>, that he which saith he dwelleth in Christ, ought to walke as he walked, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to say, he ought to indeuer to liue as he liued.</p>
   <p>There are alwaies ynow which boast<note place="margin">Boasting Christians.</note> themselues to beleeue in Christ, or to be Christians. But the verie meane to knowe them, is to mark whether their whole en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuer be to folowe Christ or no, which is as the badge of this so excellent professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or as it were the faire colored liuerie whereby we shewe and declare our selues to be the same in deede which we report our selues to be.</p>
   <p>And certes it is not possible that they which are vnited and knit vnto Christ as his members, should not be touched with a desire to resemble him and to folowe his steps. For the verie thing wherein the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and coniunction are shewed, is that the members doe shewe themselues to be of the selfe same that the head is. And where
<pb facs="18"/>
that is not done, it is an euident proofe that the member is rotten, senseles, and void of the life which is in the head.</p>
   <p>And in this behalfe I report me but to the iudgement of man, who is wise ynough of himselfe to attaine easily to this reason.</p>
   <p>Not without cause therfore doth Saint Paule saie, that wee must be of the same minde which Iesus Christ was of <note n="s" place="margin">Philip. 2, 5.</note>. For thereby his meaning is to do vs to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, that we which are mēbers of Christ, must be answerable to him in vnitie of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and wil. Which thing he teacheth yet more plainly in another place, where he saith <note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 6, 5.</note> that we be graffed into Christ af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the likenes of his death and resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; meaning thereby, that we which are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oined vnto Christ as an imp is to the stock of a tree, ought so to liue of his life, as there may not appeere any deformitie in vs; but that as he hath died, so we must die also; and as he is risen againe, so we must rise againe likewise: we must die (I say) vnto sin, and rise againe vnto newnes of life; for that is the death and the life which he speaketh of.</p>
   <p>Which thing I haue said to the end that we which boast our selues to be Christes members, should vnderstand that our van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of that title is in vaine, if we labor not to resemble him in al our whole life. And in what things? Not in raising the dead <note n="u" place="margin">Ioh. 11, 43</note>; in giuing sight to the blinde <note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 9, 28 29▪ 30.</note>; in healing the sick <note n="y" place="margin">Mark. 2, 3. Luke. 5, 18. Matt. 4, 23. 24.</note>, or in fasting fortie daies <note n="z" place="margin">Luke. 4, 1. 2, &amp;c.</note>; (for these are miracles which he wrought both by himselfe, and by his Apostles, for the confirming of his doctrine among men,
<pb facs="19"/>
that they might receiue it as heauenly and comming from God; and he wrought them once for al, without any neede of hauing them done againe by vs;) but in folowing his virtues, as his faith, his obedience, his patience, his constancie, his temperance, his lowelines, meekenes, mildnes, gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, perseuerance, diligence, earnestnes in praieng and thanksgiuing, and many other things.</p>
   <p>Al the which he did, not to make a shew of them to vs, but to traine vs to the same by his owne example: not to impute them after such a sort vnto vs, that we should be hild sor such as he himselfe is, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so in deede; but to the intent that as he did them, so we should do them too, as he himselfe saith <note n="a" place="margin">Matt. 11, verse. 28. 29.</note>; and as Peter saith <note n="b" place="margin">1. Peter. 2, verse. 21.</note>, to the end we should folow his footesteps.</p>
   <p>And how shal we knowe that we be in him, and are made partakers of his graces; but by our endeuoring of our selues to keepe his commandements? And soothlie the onelie meane to knowe and to be assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in our selues that we dwel in Christ &amp; Christ in vs; is our keeping of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, as Saint Iohn teacheth <note n="c" place="margin">1. Ioh. 2, 3. 4. &amp;c.</note>; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding further, that our knoweing that he dwelleth in vs, is by the Spirit which he hath giuen vs; because that by that Spirit, we endeuor to folowe him, and to frame our selues to his wil, whereby we yeelde proofe of the vnion that is betweene him and vs. For euen as the children of this world, do witnes themselues to be al one with the world, by folowing their worldlie lusts <note n="d" place="margin">1 Iohn. 2, verse. 15. 16.</note>, ambition, couetousnes, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures,
<pb facs="19"/>
which thing I saie also of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Satan: so in like case, the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans shew themselues to be made one with Christ by his holy Spirit, when they folow Christ step by step, and make his life to serue them as a most perfect rule to leade their life by.</p>
   <p>What remaineth then to be done in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ase? Soothly that we on our part doe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force our selues, by eschewing al slothful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which being hurtful and noisome in al things, is most hurtful and noisome in this behalfe, forasmuch as it is of such impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that we cannot neglect it without wilful disappointing our selues of our sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation and soueraigne felicitie.</p>
   <p>This waie is narrow and rough, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse it is so, as al Christians doe, and so doth Christ himselfe say it also <note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 7, 14.</note>. For in asmuch as thereby we must sorsake our selues to folowe Christ <note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 9, 23.</note> (which is verie painful &amp; hard to the flesh which desrreth nothing but hir owne pleasures and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities:) no doubt but we feele it to be very bitter and burthensome. But what for that? Yet must we take that waie, without stepping aside one waie or other. For that is the onelie way which after many labors and hard pinches, leadeth in the end vnto life. As for the other way, it is very broade <note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 7, 13</note>, faire, &amp; accompanied with great plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures but the end thereof (saith he) lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vnto death. Now, it is much better to go by labor to rest, by tribulation to ioie, and by death vnto life: than contrariwise to go by rest to labor, by ioie to tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and by life to death: for looke what
<pb facs="20"/>
things commeth last, shal be euerlasting.</p>
   <p>What thing then should hold vs back or hinder vs in this race? If it be the world with al the goodes, honors, and pleasures thereof; let vs vnderstande that al those things passe awaie <note n="h" place="margin">1. Co. 7, 31. 1. Ioh. 2, 17.</note> like an arrow which is shot at a white, the trace whereof is not perceiued any more when it is once past. If it be the roughnes and vneasines of the waie: let vs consider how there is nothing so vneafie, nor so rough, which becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not easie and smooth by continual vse. If it be the infirmitie and weakenes of our nature; let vs thinke vpon him which hath promised to stand by vs, to helpe vs, and to strengthen vs; who being good wil helpe vs; and being almightie wil also strengthen vs, conditionalie that we praie to him continualie. Aske (saith he <note n="i" place="margin">Luk. 11, 9.</note>) and it shal be giuen vnto you; seeke, and ye shal finde; knocke at the doore, and it shal be opened vnto you. Prouided alwaies that we on our side doe straine our selues <note n="k" place="margin">Matt. 11, verse. 12.</note>: for he helpeth not them that are idle and doe nothing. He giueth his Spirit; but it is to such as feeling their owne feeblenes, and being displeased with it, doe earnestly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire and craue his Spirit <note n="l" place="margin">Luke. 11, verse. 13.</note>. To such as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing aske, nothing he doth giue. It is euen he that worketh in vs; howbeit, not so long as we our selues sleepe, not so long as we fold our armes acrosse, and much lesse so long as we resist him.</p>
   <p>The kingdome of GOD, (saith Iesus Christ,) suffereth violence <note n="m" place="margin">Matt. 11, verse. 12.</note>, and the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent plucke it to them. And who be those violent? Those which being inflamed with
<pb facs="20"/>
great desire and zeale to facion them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues like to their head, do offer violence and force to themselues, to the intent that their nature and flesh being restrained and brideled, may not cast any impediment in the way of Gods Spirit, which worketh in them; which feeling themselues cold and lasie, whether it be in praieng to God, or in giuing him thankes for al things, or in any work of godlines either towards God or towards their neighbors, doe quicken and stir vp themselues, without suffering themselues to go on, and to be ouercome of their flesh; which take paines to marke al their owne thoughts and affections, and to restraine them frō passing their bounds, &amp; from rouing astray, setting a sure watch vpon their mind, and folowing the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel of the wise, because that from the mind commeth the welspring of al euil <note n="n" place="margin">Matt. 15, verse. 11. 18. 19. 20.</note>; which knowing how easie it is for them, to slip aside at euery least occasion in the world, doe set good gard vpon themselues conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nualie, laboring to subdue aud ouercome themselues; and finalie which by Christs Spirit do incessantly crucifie the flesh with the lusts thereof.</p>
   <p>And of a truth, we be of our owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture so contrarie to God, and so bent to the seeking of our owne selues; and our affections are so heady and vehement, and we be haled vnto euil with so great force by our flesh, that we must not thinke that God can haue his dominion in vs, vnles we vse great force to ouercome and subdue our selues to him.</p>
   <p>Yet notwithstanding, there are some
<pb facs="21"/>
nowadaies, yea and a great some, who without taking much paine, (I wil not say, without taking any atal) cesse not for al that to brag afterwarde, that they be of Gods kingdome. But they deceiue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues. For seeing that Gods kingdome is righteousnes, peace, and ioie through the holie Ghost (as saith saint Paule <note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 14, verse. 17.</note>:) how can it haue place in them which suffer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteousnes to raigne in them! And ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilie it is a suffering of it to raigne, when they represse it not, according also as they shew in effect by their cōuersation, which is no better than the conuersation of those whom they condemne.</p>
   <p>I know wel they haue their shifts for it, saieng that we haue no power atal, that we shal be flesh stil, as long as we be in this life, and that we cannot proceede far for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in this great frailtie and weaknes of our nature; but that Christ wil supplie al our wants, and not lay our sinnes to our charge. Yea verily; but when they say so, or rather flatter themselues after that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; perceiue they not how they disgrade themselues from the degree of Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans? For if they cannot obey God, and do the thing that he commandeth, they haue not Christs Spirit <note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 8, 5.</note>: and if they haue not Christs Spirit, then are they not Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. Saint Paule saith wel, that the flesh neither wil nor can obey Gods lawe: but<note place="margin">9.</note> yet he addeth therewith, that Christians are not in the flesh, but in the Spirit. You be not in the flesh, (saith he) but in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; at leastwise if Gods Spirit be in you.<note place="margin">8.</note> Whervpon it must needes folow, that they
<pb facs="21"/>
which cannot obey God are in the flesh, and those (saith he) cannot please God.</p>
   <p>Which reason may serue also to this saieng of theirs, that we shal alwaies be flesh. For if we be alwaies flesh, we shal al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies<note place="margin">Who are fleshlie.</note> be stil vnchristianlike, because that to be flesh, and to be Christians, are things that can by no meanes match together, I meane to be flesh in such wise as to make none other trade than to folowe a mans owne lusts. For otherwise I denie not, but that the flesh is stil in vs, (so long as we be wrapped in this mortal bodie) to prouoke vs vnto euil, and to make war against the Spirit: but not to folow the froward mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of it any more. For this standeth true, that whosoeuer foloweth them, is not to be registred in the number of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians. And therefore Saint Paule threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth euerlasting death, to such as liue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the flesh <note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 8, 13</note>, specialy after they haue bin taught that they be alwaies subiect to damnation.</p>
   <p>As touching our frailtie and weakenes, wherewith they thinke to preuaile conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nualie against such as presse them with their dutie: surely I confesse with them, that it is great, and such as maketh euen the holiest to be ouerthrowen and van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quished oftentimes by Satan and their owne flesh, which thing they lament and bewaile: but as for to make a sheeld or a defence of it to sooth themselues in their vices, and to take licence to folowe their lusts; it is for such folke to do, as seeke al maner of occasion to doe euil, and to rid away al regard of vpright dealing &amp; righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnes:
<pb facs="22"/>
which thing cannot agree with true Christians, whose whole studie is to maintaine themselues in good workes, as they that know how il it beseemeth those which professe themselues to be made cleane by the blood of Iesus Christ <note n="r" place="margin">Heb. 9, 14.</note>, to turne back to the defiling of themselues againe.</p>
   <p>Moreouer, to say that Christ wil supply al our wants, and not charge vs with our sinnes, wherevnto we haue yeelded our selues so freely and willingly after we haue knowen him, seemeth in my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to tend to none other thing, than to make Christ a cloake for our vices, and to take occasion of his grace, to flatter and maintaine our selues in them: which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be done without manifest wickednes. For seing that Christ maketh vs partakers of his grace, vpon condition that we shal leade a life both pure, holie, and besee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming him; and to bring the same to passe, doth promise vs his Spirit, so we aske it of him in faith: if we doe the contrarie, it wil not be without dooing him wrong. Wherethrough it wil come to pas, that we shal bereue our selues of the benefite of our redemption, and make our selues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie thereof. For (as Saint Iohn tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs,) Christes blood maketh none cleane, saue those which walk in the light as God is light <note n="s" place="margin">1. Ioh. 1, 7. 9.</note>.</p>
   <p>But I beseech these men in the name of God, to consider these things aduisedlie, and to think earnestlie vpon this saicng of Christs, That not al they which say Lord, Lord, shal be saued, but they which do the
<pb facs="22"/>
wil of his heauenlie Father <note n="t" place="margin">Mat. 7, 21</note>. Neither words nor ceremonies do proue folke to be Christians, children of God, faithful ones, members of Christ, and chosen of God, (which are titles wherewith they deck themselues as with things which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long peculiarly and alonely vnto them) but their deedes, and their loue procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from a pure hart, from a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, and from an vnfained faith.</p>
   <p>Let vs then conclude, that the onelie true marke of Christians and right belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, is loue; without the which, a man may wel talke of Christ, and of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and he may wel haue the Sacraments, and al the godlie ceremonies that can be deuised; and yet al shal be nothing <note n="u" place="margin">1. Co. 13, 1 2. 3.</note>.</p>
   <p>And would God that the Christians of our time, as wel the one sort as the other; (for alas they be diuided asunder) had put it wel in vre these former yeeres. For then should we not see now so much hatred, hartburning, crueltie, medling, sedition, part-taking, treason, trecherie, desire of reuenge, and other infinite mischeues that raigne among vs. Neither should blood haue bin shed after such a sort and in so great aboundance as it is; and yet stil shalbe, vnles God vsing his absolute pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er restraine mens mindes, which are now fiercely bent and fleshed one against ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as they may not be able to bring their desires and passions to passe: and that they also on their side do suffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to be bowed by acknowledging their faults, and by hauing recourse to the remedie of repentance, which is the only
<pb facs="23"/>
meane to appease Gods wrath so kindled against vs; and (at a word) doe turne their rage and crueltie into mildnes &amp; charitie.</p>
   <p>And to lay foorth the matter yet more<note place="margin">Markes of christianitie.</note> particularlie; the Christians are those which crucifie the flesh with the lusts and affections there of <note n="x" place="margin">Gal. 5, 24.</note>. The children of God are they that are led by Gods Spirit <note n="y" place="margin">Rom. 8, 14.</note>, and not by the Diuels spirit, nor by their owne affections. The faithful are they, which not onely repenting themselues truely, doe trust in Gods mercy through Iesus Christ, but also do exercise themselues in al good works, and (as saith Saint Peter <note n="z" place="margin">2. Pet. 1, 5.</note>) do inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to shew, in their faith, strength; in their<note place="margin">6.</note> strength, skil; in their skil, staiednes; in their staiednes, patience; in their patience,<note place="margin">7.</note> godlines; in their godlines, brotherlines; and in their brotherlines, louingnes. The members of Christ, are they that take paine to frame and facion themselues like to their head, as much as can be in this life; assuring themselues that it is not possible for the head to be of one wil, and the members of another <note n="a" place="margin">Eph. 1, 22. 23.</note>. Gods elect or chosen, are they that endeuor to be holie and vnblamable before him in loue.</p>
   <p>Those, those be the markes where by a man may &amp; ought to discerne them from the vnbeleeuers, the heathenish, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holie, the children and lims of the Diuel, &amp; finalie from al kinds of false Christians.</p>
   <p>In respect whereof it is not amis to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the saieng of S. Augustine. The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man (saith he <note n="b" place="margin">August. de laude chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis.</note>) may haue baptisme; he may haue the gift of prophesieng; he may receiue the Sacrament of the bodie
<pb facs="23"/>
and blood of our Lord; he may beare the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ame of a Christian &amp; haue Christs name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n his mouth; and he may haue other vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues: but charitie is the thing which the wicked cannot haue; it is peculiar to the true Christians. And therefore (saith he) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>et euerie man examine himselfe what he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oueth <note n="c" place="margin">1. Cor. 11, verse. 28.</note>, and thereby he shal find to what citie he belongeth. If he loue the world and worldlie things, that is to wit, fleshli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, monie, or honor; he is a citizen of Babylon: but if he loue God, he is a citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen of Ierusalem. He is good and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and therefore he must not doubt, but that God wil at that day▪ giue vnto him the crowne of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnes, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>A. G.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>