<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118657_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02880</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13019</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118657</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Heauens ioy, or, Heaven begun vpon earth : Wherein there is discouered more plainely then euer formerly. The happy and surpassing glorious estate of a iustified person, or a saint on earth. Also that greater happinesse at the day of iudgement. And a small tast of that greatest and most glorious estate prepared for vs in the highest heauens. Also the writer will bee ready to defend what is here written against all opposers whatsoeuer</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Harrison, John 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 159, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloued Reader if thou be desirous of Nouelties, heres <hi>Newes</hi> worth thy hearing. It is the Report of the <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation,</hi> the <hi>Beauty,</hi> and <hi>comlinesse</hi> of a Citizen of <hi>Newe Hierusalem:</hi> which I shall shewe thee the rather I doe attempt it because of the slanders that <hi>generation of Hypocrites</hi> doe cast vpon this <hi>Citie.</hi> They doe tell thee <hi>faintly,</hi> that here is much good to
<pb facs="3"/> be found: but when thou hearest their <hi>vncertaine relation,</hi> and viewest their <hi>tottred Habite,</hi> and conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest their <hi>leannes,</hi> and how much they are distracted; it makes thee much to question the trueth of their <hi>Report.</hi> They tel thee they are inhabitants of it. And if thou question further of the qualities of those <hi>Citizens:</hi> Thou shalt heare them say, they all are <hi>Peacemakers, Ioyfull, Holy, Wise, bold, Rich,</hi> and <hi>Humble</hi> people. But when thou takest a viewe of their <hi>Pride,</hi> seest their <hi>Pouertie,</hi> perceiuest their <hi>feares,</hi> obseruest their <hi>folly,</hi> knowest their <hi>filthinesse,</hi> considerest their <hi>heauinesse,</hi> and are acquainted with their <hi>contentions,</hi> This I say, makes thee to question the trueth of their report. Wherefore in hope of thy desire to get this <hi>Possession,</hi> I was em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldened to rehearse, what by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence I <hi>knowe,</hi> and by diligent triall
<pb facs="3"/> I <hi>vnderstand</hi> of that <hi>Royall Citie.</hi> Thou shalt haue nothing here but <hi>wordes</hi> of <hi>trueth</hi> and <hi>sobernesse,</hi> and that which thou thy selfe shall finde written in the <hi>Booke of Life.</hi> And because there are many inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of this <hi>City,</hi> that being but new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entred, are scarce acquainted with the <hi>Glory, Maiestie,</hi> the <hi>Content, Riches, Wisdome,</hi> and <hi>safetie</hi> it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foords: I haue desired to impart to <hi>such</hi> what they may finde, if they <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede</hi> in the <hi>course</hi> they haue well begunne. And I doe the rather ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour it, that as men are holpen by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to discouer <hi>counterfaite Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellers:</hi> so men may be assisted to find out the false <hi>brags,</hi> and vaine <hi>boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stings</hi> these <hi>Hypocrites</hi> doe make: and howbeit I knowe some of them will learne by this Booke, the more craftily to deceiue, and wil be able bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>colour</hi> their estate to others: yet
<pb facs="4"/> knowing also that <hi>Heauen</hi> shal reueile <hi>such iniquitie,</hi> and the <hi>God of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance</hi> will take <hi>vengeance</hi> of the abuse of such paines. I commend it to the protection of that most <hi>Power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God,</hi> and rest yet a while.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>