<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader whosoeuer, be he a true
Catholicke, or a Romish.</title>
           <author>Crashaw, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118191_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19589</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6028</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118191</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader whosoeuer, be he a true
Catholicke, or a Romish.</title>
                 <author>Crashaw, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The sermon preached at the Crosse, Feb. xiiij. 1607. By W. Crashawe, Batchelour of Diuinitie, and preacher at the temple; iustified by the authour, both against Papist, and Brownist, to be the truth: wherein, this point is principally intended; that the religion of Rome, as now it stands established, is still as bad as euer it was</title>
                 <author>Crashaw, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Lownes, Matthew</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 173, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader whosoeuer, be he a true
Catholicke, or a Romish.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O preuent all misconceits
that might arise vpon the
so late comming forth of
this Sermon, (so many
weekes expected) I desire
thee good Reader be satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,
that the cause thereof, was a long &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looked
for iourney. And now that you haue
it, let mee desire all men in the reading and
iudging thereof, to deale with that ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
and sincerity, as I haue indeuoured in the
writing of it. My conscience speakes for me,
I haue forged no new Author, I haue falsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
none, I haue corrupted none, I haue
to my knowledge misalledged none: I haue
taken no proofe vpon bare report, nor
haue I produced our men to proue what I
lay against them: nor is there one quotation
<pb facs="6"/>
of any Author of theirs, which I haue not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently
perused afore-hand, and the whole
scope of the place. If any should think of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere,
I desire him let passe all personall ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
and by-matters, and come directly to
the points in issue: which be these;
<list>
         <item>1 Whether the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> teach &amp;
practice in these xx. or xxi. points, as I
haue charged her withall, or no.</item>
         <item>2 If she do, whether they be healed of these
wounds as yet, or no.</item>
         <item>3 If she be not, then how she can be the true
Church, which is so wounded, and will not
be healed.</item>
      </list>
   </p>
   <p>If they do not teach and practise so, I will
yeeld the Cause. And hee that can shew mee
that either she is healed since, or beeing not
healed, how she can bee the true Church, I
shall willingly hear him, &amp; thank him. I desire
al that professe thēselues papists, or their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourers,
not to be so wilfull as to condemne
what they know not; but only to giue it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
&amp; then iudge as they see cause. <hi>Wright,</hi>
in his Articles, layeth to our charge manie
strange Paradoxes: as, that <hi>we are all Atheists,
and Infidels by our doctrine;</hi> that <hi>wee are
bound by our doctrine to doe no good workes,</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
&amp; many such. And <hi>Kellison</hi> in his Survaie,
thrusts vpon vs that <hi>wee deny Christ to bee the
only Sauiour, and Iudge of quick &amp; dead,</hi> and
many such abhominations; all which we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce,
and detest: yet, do what we can, wee
must haue them laid vpon vs; and our writers
&amp; teachers haue their speeches wrung and
wrested, beyond their meaning to make thē
sound that way. I dare appeale to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of Gods Church, and al iudicious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
heereof, that I haue not done so with
them, nor taken vantage of their words, whē
it's apparant they meant otherwise; but char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
them only with such points of doctrine
&amp; practice, as thēselues cannot deny but to
be their own: &amp; that not of one or two, but
(for the most part) generally receiu'd. Cōmē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
it to thy reading, &amp; my selfe to thy prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
I leaue vs all to Gods blessing. At the
Temple. May, 21. 1608.</p>
   <signed>Thy brother in the Lord,
<hi>W. Crashawe.</hi>
   </signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>