<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the READERS.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118682_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04391</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14512.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118682</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the READERS.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Seauen helpes to Heauen : Shewing 1. How to auoid the curse. 2. How to beare the crosse. 3. How to build the conscience. 4. How with Moses to see Canaan. 5. Simeons dying song, directing to liue holily and dye happily. 6. Comforts for Christians against distresses in life, and feare of death. 7. Feruent prayers, to beare sicknesse patiently, and dye preparedly. The second edition: much enlarged by Steuen Ierome, late preacher at S. Brides. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Jerome, Stephen</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 16, 517, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="apology_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="282"/>
   <head>To the READERS.</head>
   <p>FRiendly Readers these Errours, with others, whether in words or syllables, in misse-quoting or wrong pointing of some places, which haue past the Presse in my absence, by reason of the close writing of my Copie, I pray you censure fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and correct friendly.</p>
   <p>Also I desire you to take notice, that as I haue added (more then I did preach) some Historicall Amplifications from pag. <hi>273.</hi> to <hi>278.</hi> as also, from pag. <hi>305.</hi> to pag. <hi>318.</hi> so I haue left out the Merginall Quotations as needlesse for the vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that neyther read nor regard them: as for the learned I referre them to <hi>Zwinger</hi> his <hi>Theatrum humanae vitae, Lonicer</hi> his <hi>Theatrum Histori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, Grosij Historicae Tragicae, Osiander</hi> his <hi>Epitome of the Centuries, Textor his Officina, Diogenes Laertius, Valerius Maximus, Fulgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus &amp;c.</hi> From all whom I haue epitomized these Histories, as they from others.</p>
   <div type="errata">
      <head>ERRATA.</head>
      <p>PAge 60. line 20 for <hi>Bolserus</hi> read <hi>Bolsecus.</hi> p. 123. l. 23. for dispertment r. disportment. p 133. l. 13. for Segor r. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>or. p. 169. l. 17. for <hi>renijs</hi> r. <hi>remis.</hi> p. 182. l. 8. for <hi>Licinus</hi> r. <hi>Licinius.</hi> p. 283. l. 12. for. <hi>Cressus</hi> r. <hi>Cresus.</hi> p. 314. l. 11. for Gods r. God. <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 28. for <hi>Oreseence</hi> r. <hi>Crescence.</hi> p. 456. (<hi>in mergine</hi>) for <hi>Heidou</hi> r. <hi>Chambers.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>