<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN REI∣der,
ane Epistle generall.</title>
           <author>Hume, A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118804_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03827</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13943</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118804</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN REI∣der,
ane Epistle generall.</title>
                 <author>Hume, A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ane treatise of conscience : Quhairin divers secreits concerning that subiect, are discovered, as may appeare, in the table following</title>
                 <author>Hume, Alexander</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>128 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN REI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
ane Epistle generall.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Will vse na vther Epistle Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorie
of thir my litle treatises
(gude Christian Reidar) saue
onely this vnto thee, to quhais
knawledge thay sall come: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
do I seek ony praise, thanks
or recompense of men, for ony
thing that I haue done. The on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
thing that I craue for my labour, is, that the praise &amp;
glory heirof may be giuen vnto God, and that the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moditie
may redound to the members of his Kirk. Now,
to declair schortly the circumstances, and occasion of
my writing: the trueth is, that being in great affliction,
and assaulted with many temptations, (as the godly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
runnes to God in time of trouble) I took purpose to
compose somewhat to his glory, and to the comfort &amp;
edification of gude men. And the subject quhilk I chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
wes, how to resist the temptations of pouertie, sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
schame, and sorrowes of this lyfe: Siklyke, of the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie
of the life to come, and certaine discourses in
praise of the mercie, justice, power, and providence of
God. Al these I conceived, first by a general notion, and
for helping of my memory, I set them downe in writ, in
maner of a table, or memoriall: ever awayting the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
quhen, and how I micht followe them forth in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
as I had devised. But I was so hindred and drawne
away with warldly affaires, that mair nor the space of
<pb facs="3"/>
half a ʒeir, I came but litle speid in my interprised wark
Quhill at last, in the ʒeir 1592. it pleased God to visite
me with a Feuer alterne, quhilk vulgarly wee call the
Excesse, In sik sorte, that all warldly cares and impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
were remooued, and my mind altogether setled
on the seruice of my God. Neuertheles, my infirmitie
was so great, that during the time of my sicknes (quhilk
lasted thre Moneths) I wes vnable to compose or write
any thing: saue only at sometime to read the Scripturs,
or cause them to be redde to me: Alwaies, being viuely
touched with the Lords rod, It brocht forth gud effects
in me: For thereby I was farre humbled, and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
great feeling baith of mine awin sinn, and of Gods
mercie: my cheif exercise wes to meditate on the lawe
of the Lord, and to clenge my defiled heart. But sa sone
as the Feuer began to slaik, and I to convalesse▪ sa soone
did I search out my memoriall, and put my hand to the
pen, earnestly prosecuting my interrupted warke. And
beginning at the resistance of temptations, I thocht
thay micht all be commodiously comprehendit vnder
a generall treatise of affliction: quhilk by reason I had
laitly before tasted: It micht appear that by gods grace
I micht write the more feelingly thereof. Hauing then
accomplished the first treatise, I proceeded without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay
to the second: And in the meane season, while I wes
in hand thairwith: behold, I contracted ane vther hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie
disease: even a swelling, and a defluction of a putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
humor in my legges, and vther partes of my bodie
(quhilk commonly followis that kind of Fever) So that
I was thereby made vnable for ony trauell: But for the
maist part, and by reason of the cold supervenient win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
I was tyed to the bed, mair nor the space of sax Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths.
This made baith my self, and the time mair pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
for the accomplishing of the wark begunne: For I
was grim, and brocht wondrous lowe with paine in my
<pb facs="3"/>
flesh: And being seperat from the companie of men, my
delectation for the maist part wes, to bee occupied in
contemplation, in composing, and serving of my God.
So hauing finished the second treatise, I proceid it to
the discourses or praises: And last, for coronation of my
litle wark, to the effect that the inward trouble of the
minde might be alsweill discouered, and resisted, as the
externall troubles of the warld, I beganne a treatise of
Conscience: all the quhilk treatises, it pleased the Lord
to prosper and accomplish in the waik hands of his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant,
as thou may see in halfe a ʒeirs space: quhilk be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
out-runne, the extremitie of my paine did cease, &amp;
the Lord from day to day restored me: In sik sorte, that
appearantly, he had casten me on the bed, to the effect,
that he micht warke this his wark in me: Nowe as to the
treatise of affliction, it may perhaps appeir, through the
multitude and prolixitie of egressions, to be lesse me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodicall
nor the rest: But I hope gif you marke it nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly,
and richtly discerne the digressions, from the
lineal point of the treatise, as they are set downe in the
Argument thereof, thou sall find it not without cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
and the amplification not without profite. The
treatises of praise, and of the lise to come, are a large
field: by reason quhairof many thinges may bee eiked
thairto. But the treatise of Conscience, because it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
in Chapters, I esteeme it to be of best methode,
and maist solide doctrine. Finally, I wil assure thee, that
I neuer entred to meditate on this my little warke, nor
put my hand to the pen, without earnest invocation on
the Name of the Lord, for the assistance of his spirite,
That I micht vtter the wordes of knowledge, and of
trueth, to his glory, and to the comfort of my brethren.
Therefore, that I may end, as I beganne, whatsoeuer
comfort or instructioun thou receiue (my Brother) of
these treatises, giue the praise thereof only to the Lord,
<pb facs="4"/>
and to his vndefiled Lambe Christ Iesus, seing to them,
all glory justly apperteinis for euer. God graunt you
may be na lesse mooued in the reiding, nor I was in the
writing of these treatises: the grace and peace of our
Lord Iesus Christ bee with thy spirite. Amen. At my
chamber the 26. of September. 1593.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>By me, a louing Brother of al them that
loues the second comming of the
Lord Iesus. <hi>A. Hume.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>