<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ A second Epistle concerning the trans∣lation and correction of this Booke.</title>
           <author>Rogers, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118358_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13680</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23973</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118358</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ A second Epistle concerning the trans∣lation and correction of this Booke.</title>
                 <author>Rogers, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of the imitation of Christ, three, both for wisedome, and godlines, most excellent bookes; made 170. yeeres since by one Thomas of Kempis, and for the worthines thereof oft since translated out of Latine into sundrie languages by diuers godlie and learned men: now newlie corrected, translated, and with most ample textes, and sentences of holie Scripture illustrated by Thomas Rogers</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Seres, William, Assignee(s) of</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 277, 11 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div n="2" type="letter">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>¶ A second Epistle <hi>concerning the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> and correction <hi>of this Booke.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ebastian Castellio</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing translated this booke into Latine, thought it good by waie of Preface to giue some reasons, both why he had translated the same being in Latine alreadie; and why so he had translated it, leauing somewhat of the Autor out.</p>
   <p>The case standeth with me as it did with <hi>Castellio.</hi> Therfore am I to yeeld some reasons both why I haue translated this book into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish being in English alreadie; and why so I haue translated it, leauing somewhat out, as I haue done.</p>
   <p>For the first I saie, that neither is my doing for noueltie strange; nor am I (as I trust) to be reproued therefore. For both I haue exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of good men in al sciences, and professions, who to their great cōmendation haue done the like; as maie witnes the sundrie and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
<pb facs="8"/>
interpretations of the workes of <hi>Aristotle,</hi> and <hi>Plato</hi> for philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie; of <hi>Demosthenes</hi> and <hi>Isocrates,</hi> for Oratorie; of <hi>Galen</hi> and <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> for Physick; for Diuinitie of the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Bible: and also I haue taken the translation thereof vpon me, not so much to translate, as to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate the same with places of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. For doubtles great pittie was it, that a booke so plentifulie, or altogether rather fraighted with sentences of the Scripture, was ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther no whit, as in some, or no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as in the best impressions, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Besides, I haue not onlie shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the chapter, but the verie sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence also of euerie chapter where what is written maie be found: a thing which, that I heare of, none afore me hath done. The bringing of which to passe, how paineful it hath bene to me, he alone can best report, who either hath done or doth go about the like; how not comfortable onelie, but profitable besides it wilbe to others▪ they shal finde that zelouslie do reade the same.</p>
   <p>And this whatsoeuer I haue done, was taken in hand at the motion of
<pb facs="8"/>
the Printer hereof; whose zeale to set forth good bookes for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of virtue, and care to publish them as they ought to be, would some printers folowe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would the sale of good workes be mard manie-times for lack of wel handling; nor vaine and vile bookes to the dishonor of God, the infamie of this land, to the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the wicked in naughtines, and alienating of the wel disposed from virtue, I saie, to the discredite of the Gospel, and abuse of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting would not dailie be so broacht as they are.</p>
   <p>In which my translation I haue rather folowed the sense of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, than his verie wordes, in some places; the which also I haue stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died, as nigh as I could, to expresse by the phrase of the holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, supposing it to be a cōmenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as to <hi>Ciceronians</hi> to vse the phrase of <hi>Cicero:</hi> so to Christians most familiarlie to haue the words of the holie Scripture in their mouthes, and bookes.</p>
   <p>Now touching my correction, I trust no good man wil mislike the same. For I haue left out nothing
<pb facs="9"/>
but what might be offensiue to the godlie. Yet is it neither for quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie much, nor for number aboue foure sentences. The first whereof is this <note n="a" place="margin">In the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond booke, chapt. 12, in the beginning almost.</note>
      <hi>Hoc signum crucis erit in coelo, cùm Dominus ad iudicandum venerit.</hi> According to <hi>Castellios</hi> translation: <hi>Atque hoc erit signum crucis in coelo, cùm Dominus ad iudicandum veniet.</hi> In the English copie set foorth by <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Hake,</hi> thus, <hi>And this signe of the crosse shalbe in heauen, when the Lord shal come to iudge the world.</hi> Which sentence, for somuch as I see neither the Scripture, nor anie good writer doth confirme the same, I haue left out altogether.</p>
   <p>The second is this <note n="b" place="margin">In the foresaide chap.</note>, <hi>Sed nec ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micum Diabolum timebis, si fueris fide armatus, &amp; Iesu cruce signatus.</hi> Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Castellio, Quinne Diaboli qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem inimicitias timebis, si fide armatus, &amp; Iesu cruce signatus eris.</hi> In the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish translation, <hi>Naie thou shalt not feare the enimitie of the Diuel neither, if thou be armed with faith, and marked with the crosse of Iesus.</hi> What needes these words, <hi>And marked with the crosse of Iesus?</hi> I haue therefore not mentioned them.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="9"/>The third is <note n="c" place="margin">In the same chap.</note>, <hi>Non enim flat meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum nostrum, &amp; profectus status nostri in multis suauitatibus, &amp; consolationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp;c.</hi> According to <hi>Castellio, Ne{que} enim in copia voluptatum &amp; consolatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num situm est meritum nostrum, offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cij{que} profectus, &amp;c.</hi> In the English translation, <hi>Neither is our merit, and the comming forward in our dutie consisting in plentie of pleasures and comfortes▪ &amp;c.</hi> Which I haue thus Englished, <hi>Neither doth our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming forward consist in the stoare of pleasures, and comfort, &amp;c.</hi> leauing out the worde merit. Because both the scripture is cleene against our meriting, and the Autor too in manie places <note n="d" place="margin">As most principalie in the third boke chap. 26, cha. 52, pag. 227, chap. 58.</note> condemnes the same.</p>
   <p>The fourth <note n="e" place="margin">In the 3. booke chapt. 20, in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle thereof.</note>, <hi>Sed neque qui tunc iusti erant, &amp; saluandi ante passionem tuam, &amp; sacrae mortis debitum, coeleste regnum poterant intrare.</hi> According to <hi>Castellio: Quinetiam qui tunc iusti, seruandi{que} erant, ij ante supplicium tuum sacrae{que} mortis meritum in coeleste reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num intrare non poterant.</hi> In <hi>Hakes</hi> translation, <hi>Naie also euen those who then were iustified, and in the state of saluation could not enter the kingdome of heauen before thy passion, and the</hi>
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <hi>merit of thy pretious death.</hi> Where then were they? In hel? I thinke none wil saie it. In Abrahams bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some, as some <note n="f" place="margin">Catech. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. vpon these words of the Creede, Descendit ad inferos. Bern. in festo omnium Sanct. serm. 4</note>, in <hi>Lymbo patrum,</hi> as other Papists <note n="g" place="margin">D▪ Tho. in 4. dist. 45. q. 1. Art. 3. Jauellus philosoph. Christ. p. 8. Tract. 4. cap. de locis infoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licium dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat.</note> do saie? but that wil not easilie be proued. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as that which otherwise might offend the godlie, I haue cleane omitted, &amp; left out that sentence.</p>
   <p>And as I haue ouerpast with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mentioning these, which sauor of superstition: so haue I added some godlie sentences, which haue bene omitted both by <hi>Castellio,</hi> and such as folowed him, as maie ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peere both in the 47. according to <hi>Castel.</hi> as in mine the 48. chap. with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in three sentences of the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; and also in the 63. as in mine the 64. chap. somewhat after the midle thereof.</p>
   <p>So that I maruel, both why these were omitted, and the rest not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by such as haue taken the translation of this booke vpon them. I grant they haue done the dutie of translators: yet sure I am they haue neglected a greater du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie than of translatorship. For my part I had rather come into the displeasure of man, than displease
<pb facs="10"/>
God; and rather moue the obstinat heretike, than offend the weake &amp; simple Christian.</p>
   <p>It maie be obiected that I might haue giuen some note by the waie, and so let them passe; as doth <hi>Eras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> in his translations. Surelie <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rasmus</hi> might better do so in Latine, than I maie in English. For asmuch as most are learned, &amp; haue iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which read his; and I do that which I do for the simpler sorte. And were other bookes, that I could name, excellent for manie good points, yet for some things su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitious, purged and corrected, sure I am, both God would greatlie like therof, and manie men would then reade them, who now reiect them; and much profit would be reaped, whereas now there is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther litle or no profit at al taken.</p>
   <p>One chapter you shal find in this my translation more than is in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bookes. Yet haue I added no chapter, but diuided the 6. chapter of the third booke. For asmuch as it comprehendeth partlie a thankes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing vnto God for his benefites, and partlie a commendation of charitie, which aptlie, me thinkes,
<pb facs="11"/>
makes two chapters.</p>
   <p>Now he, who principalie both stirred the Autor to make this booke, and me to do what I haue done, euen God almightie grant that both you, and I, and euerie of vs maie vse it to the comfort of our soules, <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in Christ Tho. Rogers▪</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>