<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Dedication]</title>
           <author>Hodson, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118753_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14083</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24393</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118753</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Dedication]</title>
                 <author>Hodson, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Asylum veneris, or A sanctuary for ladies : Iustly protecting them, their virtues, and sufficiencies from the foule aspersions and forged imputations of traducing spirits</title>
                 <author>D. T. (Daniel Tuvill)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lisle (L’isle, Lyle), Laurence</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 64, 75-162 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <p>
      <hi>with all variety of Graces and Abilities. Euery thing growes there in so good order, that the searching eye of Malice can finde nothing to be lopt, little to bee pruned. The hand of Heauen hath made it as it were a Nursery, frō whence many Virtues &amp; Perfections are oft times transplanted into others.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>This inward Beauty, graced with an outward comelinesse, makes me thinke you, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat</hi> Heroine, <hi>which</hi> Venus <hi>spake of, when she said;</hi>
   </p>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="2"/>
      <l>Haec est caeruleis me cum consurgere digna</l>
      <l>Fluctibus, &amp; nostrâ potuit considere Conchâ. <note rend="inter">
            <l>Well was she worthy on the seas to ride,</l>
            <l>And in our Shell sit with vs side by side.</l>
         </note>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <p>
      <hi>Hence, Madame, I presume to place you, like an armed Cherubin, at the very entrance of this Sanctuary, to put backe such, as haue not on the Liuery, which your selfe doe weare.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>That seruiceable Loue, wherewith I haue alwaies ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured your noble Familie the</hi> Spencers, <hi>&amp; their Allies, directing it selfe vpon some re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects in a more particular
<pb facs="3"/>
manner to you, was the chiefe occasion that I first erected it. Protect it, and hauing kissed your worthy hands, I will euer rest,</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your affectionate Seruant,
D. T.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>