<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right VVorshipfull my vvorthy and esteemed Friende, Lewes Lewkenor, Esquire; one of the honorable band of her Maiesties Gentlemen Pensioners in ordinarie.</title>
           <author>Walker, Ferdinando</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118471_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13830</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24135</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118471</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right VVorshipfull my vvorthy and esteemed Friende, Lewes Lewkenor, Esquire; one of the honorable band of her Maiesties Gentlemen Pensioners in ordinarie.</title>
                 <author>Walker, Ferdinando</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Spanish Mandeuile of miracles. Or The garden of curious flowers : VVherin are handled sundry points of humanity, philosophy, diuinitie, and geography, beautified with many strange and pleasant histories. First written in Spanish, by Anthonio De Torquemeda, and out of that tongue translated into English. It was dedicated by the author, to the right honourable and reuerent prelate, Don Diego Sarmento de soto Maior, Bishop of Astorga. &amp;c. It is deuided into sixe treatises, composed in manner of a dialogue, as in the next page shall appeare</title>
                 <author>Torquemada, Antonio de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Mattes, Edmund.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 158, 2 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the right VVorshipfull my vvorthy and esteemed Friende,</hi> Lewes Lewkenor, <hi>Esquire; one of the honorable band of her Maiesties Gentlemen Pensioners in ordinarie.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE famous Architect of Greece, weary of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained abode in the Court of the Crotish tyrant, fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all other endeuours vaine for his escape, compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed at length with singuler excellence of Arte, two payre of artificiall winges, made with borrowed fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of sundry sorts, which when he had cunning lie ioyned together vvith waxe, hee fastened one payre of them to his owne body, and another to his sonnes, and so bequeating both himselfe and his sonne to the ayre, began to take his flight; but the audacious courage of the youth, presuming to approach neere vnto the glorious rayes of the Sunne, the waxe melted, his feathers dissolued, and he by his memorable fall and folly, gaue name to the Seas wherin he perri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed. The case is mine, and I cannot (worthy Maister Lewkenor) but with a great fordooming of my selfe, attende the like, or a greater downefall. For hauing long striued beyond my forces, to creepe out of the lothsome Caue of ingratitude, wherein I haue so long lyen obscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and knowing all my owne abilities too weake to carry me thence, I haue at length with these feathers, which I haue borrowed frō you, endeuoured to make my flight. But I feare me much, that my ill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position of them, and my too much aduenturous presuming to flie with them, being not myne owne, shall no sooner appeare before the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of such a iudgement as yours, but that all my tackling wil faile, and my selfe be vnrelieuably throwne downe into the incurable gulfe of confusion, ignorance, and disgrace. Onely my chiefest hope and comfort is, that your gentle and alwayes best construing disposition, to which onely I appeale, will not entertaine the hardest conceite of thys my bolde and strange attempt. Receaue therefore, gentle Maister Lewkenor, this poore Treatise, hauing so many long yeeres lien ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scured among your wast papers, and lately by your cruell sentence condemned to the fire, now with a milder conceit vnder your protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; For though you thinke it vnworthy of the worlds view, as beeing the fruite and exercise of your youngest yeeres, yet I assure you, it hath
<pb facs="4"/>
passed the censure of graue and learned iudgements, and receiued ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent allowance; thorough whose encouragements I haue presumed to giue it life, and no longer to depriue the world of a discourse so wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be knowne and published; whatsoeuer therein is faultie, let the same lie vpon my shoulders. As for your selfe, your owne worthinesse of desert, your great learning, your excellent skill in languages, your many times approoued valour, your long experience in martiall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, and generally the great worth wherein the worlde holdes you both abroade and at home, will be for you a strong and sufficient war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and Bulwarke against any whatsoeuer calumniation. And so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning vnto you this Treatise of your owne, with the intrest of a loue that shall neuer cease to manifest it selfe, in any occasion wherein it shall please you to employ me, entreating your fauourable censure and best construction of this (as I must cōfesse) ouerbold endeuour, I cease, wishing that the successe of your fortunes, may be equall to the deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of your vertues.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours euer faithfully deuoted, Ferdinando VValker.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>