<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Argument and meaning, of this following History.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118219_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13457</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23762</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118219</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Argument and meaning, of this following History.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The great O Toole</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Gosson, Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Argument and meaning, of this following History.</head>
   <p>IN all Ages and Countryes, it hath euer bin knowne, that Famous men haue florished, whose worthy Actions, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minency of place, haue euer beene as conspicuous <hi>Beacons</hi> Burning and blazing to the Spectators view: the sparkes &amp; flames wherof hath sometimes kindled Courage in the most coldest and Effeminate Cowards; as <hi>Thersites</hi> amongst the <hi>Grecians, Amadis de Gaule,</hi> and Sir <hi>Huon</hi> of <hi>Burdeaux</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> Sir <hi>Beuis, Gogmagog, Chinon, Palmerine, Lancelot,</hi> &amp; Sir <hi>Tristram</hi> amongst vs heere in <hi>England,</hi> Sir <hi>Degre,</hi> Sir <hi>Grime,</hi> and Sir <hi>Gray Steele</hi> in <hi>Scotland, Don Quixot</hi> with the <hi>Spaniards, Gargantua</hi> almost no where, Sir <hi>Dagonet,</hi> and Sir <hi>Triamore</hi> any where, all these, and many more of the like Ranke
<pb facs="5"/>
haue fill'd whole Volumes, with the ayrie Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their vnknowne and vnmatchable worthes; So <hi>Ireland</hi> amongst the rest, had the Honor to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce and breed a sparke of Valour, Wisedome, and Magnanimity, to whom all the Nation of the World must giue place. The Great <hi>O Toole,</hi> is the toole that my Muse takes in hand, whose praises (if they should be set forth to the full) would make <hi>Apollo</hi> and the <hi>Muses</hi> Barren; To whom the Nine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyes were neuer to be compared: betwixt whom, and <hi>Haniball, Scipio,</hi> the Great <hi>Pompey,</hi> or <hi>Tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine,</hi> was such oddes, that it was vnfit the best of them should holde his stirrop, and who (by his owne Report) in whome <hi>Ireland</hi> may reioyce, and <hi>England</hi> be merry, whose Youth was Dedicated to <hi>Mars,</hi> and his Age to <hi>Westminster,</hi> which ancient Citty, is now honour'd with his beloued Residence.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>