<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the indifferent Reader.</title>
           <author>Granger, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118079_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13288</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23592</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118079</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the indifferent Reader.</title>
                 <author>Granger, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Pisgah euangelica : By the method of the Reuelation, presenting to publike view those Cananites ouer whom our Lord Iesus Christ and his holie Church shall triumph after seuerall battailes. That which is past is shewed in a briefe ecclesiasticall historie, containing most of the mutations which haue befallen the Church, from the yeere of our Lord 97, vnto the yeere 1603. as they haue been shewed vnto S. Iohn in Patmos, and recorded by such historiographers as are of least suspected faith. Gathered by William Symonds, sometimes fellow of Magdalen Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Symonds, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Weaver (Wever), Edmund</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 25, 24-266, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>To the indifferent Reader.</head>
   <p>THou seest (gentle Reader) that by the weight of <hi>Athanasius</hi> Arguments, the Papists are excluded from the number of true <hi>Christians</hi> and <hi>Catholikes,</hi> as well as the <hi>Arians,</hi> so farre forth as they obtrude any doctrine which was not from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but hath been deuised at seuerall times. Of this sort are the points in which we differ from them. It remaineth therefore that thou conclude, that either <hi>Athanasius</hi> and his fellowes, or the Pope with his followers are to be auoyded. The Lord blesse thy hunger and thirst after righteousnesse.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>