<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           <author>W., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118017_Bo1_1_9</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14721</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25024</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118017</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 <author>W., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Theologicall questions, dogmaticall observations, and evangelicall essays, vpon the Gospel of Jesus Christ, according to St. Matthew : Wherein, about two thousand six hundred and fifty necessary, and profitable questions are discussed; and five hundred and eighty speciall points of doctrine noted; and five hundred and fifty errours confuted, or objections answered: together with divers arguments, whereby divers truths, and true tenents are confirmed. By Richard VVard, sometimes student in the famous vniversities of Cambridge in England: St. Andrews in Scotland: and Master of Arts of both the kingdoms; and now a preacher in the famous city of London</title>
                 <author>Ward, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Cole, Peter</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Cotes, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Parsons, Marmaduke</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 280, 289-364, 391-460, 463-466, 465-528, 2, 78, 81-226, 231-411, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="249"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HRISTIAN READER,</hi> If thou knowest me, I know thou standest amazed (and no wonder) to see the insolencie of this our Age; and how truly the Poet prophesied, when he said, <hi>Scribimus indocti, doctique poemata passim.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>That with the <hi>Cripple</hi> in the <hi>Acts,</hi> we are running, and leaping,<note place="margin">Acts 3.8. Hebr. 5.12</note> assoon as ever we have found our legs: yea, undertaking to teach others, when we have need our selves to be taught. Indeed, great may their boldness be thought, that seek without fear to set forth their <hi>knowledge,</hi> (or rather, as I have done, their <hi>ignorance</hi>) and suffer their doings to be seen, they care not of whom. For, not onely thereby do they bring men to think, that they stand much in their own conceit; but also they seem to assure themselves, that all men will like whatsoever they write, which is a great folly to imagine. Now the best way for an Offender (in this kinde) to finde favour, is to pretend a good intent, and if a good intention happen to produce an evill action, then to accuse himself, and not to stand upon his own justification. And therfore (having by this Book both betrayed my own folly, and given great occasion unto others to talk largely of me) that thy censure may be the lighter, I will Article against my self: My intention in the publication of this imperfect Peece, was sincere; namely, that by these my weak endeavours, God might gain some Glory, and his people (my Country-men) some profit; and these were a pair of such sharp Spurs, and prevalent Motives in, and unto me, that I fear many will either say, or think, <hi>that</hi> (according to the Proverb) <hi>I made more haste than good speed.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Skilfull Musicians are hardly induced to play, but unskilfull Fidlers will scrape before they be entreated, verifying the old Proverb, <hi>None so bold, as blinde Bayard.</hi> Our great and learned Schollers (when they write) excuse themselves in their <hi>Epistles Dedicatory,</hi> or to the Reader, that they were unwilling to be seen in print, and were induced to write, being overcome with the importunity of their friends, who would take no <hi>Nay:</hi> But I cannot thus <hi>excuse</hi> my self (and therefore am so much the more <hi>inexcusable</hi>) for I was not provoked, nor perswaded to make my self a publike Spectacle to all English eyes, by any friends, but willingly put my self upon it, deserving therefore the whole blame for it. Indeed the first Movers of this work, was Gods glory, and the Churches good; and therefore (whatsoever I deserve) let me intreat thee <hi>(Christian Reader)</hi> not to take that with the <hi>left hand,</hi> which was given with the <hi>right;</hi> nor <hi>sini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterly</hi> to censure what was <hi>dexterously</hi> meant, but to accept it in good part. The Lord commanded, that those who could not bring gold, or silver, or purple, or scarlet, or fine linnen,<note place="margin">Exod. 25.3, 4, 5.</note> for the making of the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, should bring Goats hair, or Rams skins, or Badgers skins; and promised, that their offerings should be accepted, not according to the worth of the thing offered, but according to the ability, and estate of the offerer. Yea, God is graciously pleased to accept of a <hi>Mite,</hi> at a poor womans hands, and of two Talents encrease, where he gave no more: Wherefore do thou imitate thy Father herein, taking thankfully, and blessing God for a weak work, from a weak workman: And as Charity covers a multitude of sins, so shew thou thy self to be endowed with this Christian vertue, by being more ready to <hi>cover,</hi> than <hi>discover</hi> a fault, more ready to <hi>excuse,</hi> than <hi>accuse</hi> the faulty.</p>
   <p>I will entreat thee briefly to take notice of two or three particulars, and so I will commend thee to the Lords gracious protection, and this Book to thy Christian consideration.</p>
   <p>First, I do not propound in this work, to teach Teachers, or to instruct those from whom I might receive instruction; for both the language, and method, and matter, and stile thereof shew, that it was written <hi>ad vulgus,</hi> onely for the help, and benefit of the unlearned, although perhaps the wise may learn some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing therein.</p>
   <p>Secondly, I do not professe my self to be an Interpreter; and therefore I do omit some Verses wholly, and some in part; picking and chusing what I understand best my self, and what I conceive may be most profitable and usefull for thee.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, a Gentlewoman having wrought in silk a curious Rainbow, another viewing of it, thus carped at it, that the Rainbow should have all colours in it, and this was defective, not having such or such: To whom the skilfull Sempster thus subtlely answers, <hi>That she saw but one side of the Bow, and therefore those colours she could not see, she must suppose them to be on the back-side.</hi> Let me entreat thee (courteous Reader) to do thus, and if thou meetest with any Question, or Objection sleightly answered,
<pb facs="250"/> to suppose that it is either more fully answered in some other place of this Tractate, or is to be handled more amply in the ensuing Evangelists.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, some places I have handled herein something largely, either because I have publikely treated of them, and so my Meditations have been enlarged, or because my helps have been more therein. Now if in those places some necessary things (as thou conceivest) be omitted; Remember, I saw onely with my own dim eyes, and conceived with my own dull heart; and if I had the eyes, fancies, and understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all, the work certainly would have been by much better than it is.</p>
   <p>Fiftly, if thou meetest with any thing which thou canst not understand and at once reading over, then reade it twice, that thou maist understand what thou readest; for otherwise thou wilt not benefit thy self by thy reading: <hi>Legere &amp; non intelligere negligere est;</hi> A man reades no more to purpose, than he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stands. And if thou canst not reade the divisions, and subdivisions which ever and anon thou shalt meet withall, then repair to any Minister, or Scholler, and they will easily teach thee.</p>
   <p>Sixtly, if thou findest any thing which dislikes thee, either in the Method, or Matter; Remember, this is not the work of any of our Antistites, or mighty men, or Worthies of our Church; but of one who is no old man in yeers, and but a childe in Vnderstanding. And therefore (I say) if thou spiest any faults in this untimely and imperfect Booke (as many will be spied by seeing eyes) then doe with them as Appelles did who covered <hi>Venus</hi> mole with her finger that it might not be spied. Where the beare cannot find Origa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num to heal his grief, he blasteth all other leaves with his breath: So many reject whatsoever they reade, if their expectation be not fully answered in every thing: But this is no pious practise, and therefore I entreat thee not to imitate it; but make use of that which is good, and labour to hide and conceal what is amisse.</p>
   <p>Seventhly, refuse not to buy this Book because the Author is alive; for thou needst not fear any additions at all.<note place="margin">Epistle to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</note> Master <hi>Wilson</hi> having set out the Art of Rhetorique and in <hi>Rome</hi> being in danger of his life for it, was entreated when he came home, to <hi>amend</hi> it, that it might be re-printed: Whereunto he answered, That his Book should <hi>mend</hi> it self, if it would, and make him <hi>amends</hi> for the danger he was brought into by reason of it; for, for his part he would own it no more. So say I, take this as it is, for I assure thee, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving exposed it to the wide world, I will never receive it, nor intertain it any more; but as Beggars do with their Brats, let it shift for it self. Artificers are sometimes enamoured of their own works, as <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus</hi> of his woodden Dove, <hi>Pigmalion</hi> of his Ivory Image, and <hi>Arachne</hi> of his wooden Swan: resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling herein <hi>Narcissus,</hi> who d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ated upon his own shadow. Beleeve me, I am none of these, for I am so sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible of my own inabilities, that none can dislike what comes from me, more than I do in my self; neither have a lower conceit of me, than I have of my self. When I call to minde, how the Arabians, being stuffed with perfumes, burn Hemlocks; and in <hi>Hybla,</hi> being cloyed with honey, they think it dainty to feed on Wax; and how the Eagle, fearing to surfet on spices, stoopeth to bite on wormwood: Then I confesse I have some hope that this Book will please some pallat; for we do so surfet, and are so cloyed with rare, learned, and Scholler-like Books, that plain ones, and unlearned perhaps will relish with us.</p>
   <p>Eightly, although there be many defects which may occur unto thee in this <hi>Miscellany,</hi> yet excuse them and me, thus; That as the Vine is more regarded, that beareth Grapes, than the Ash that hath nothing but leaves; and the Deer that encreaseth the Park, more than the barren Doe; and the Orchard that is fraught with fruit, than that which hath nothing but Bloom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>▪ So it is better for a man to have but a little Learning, and to employ it wholly to the good of others, than to have much buried in him, and learned onely unto himself: for <hi>Bonum quo communius eo est melius.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Ninthly, some scapes thou wilt meet withall, which were committed through the negligence and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight of the Printer: but they are rectified and amended in the end of the Book, in the Errata, whereunto I intreat thee to turn, when thou findest any fault, and having found the correction, to amend it with thy Pen.</p>
   <p>Tenthly, and lastly, thou hast a profitable Index at the end of the Book, wherein thou maist see what is contained in the whole Work, and how readily to finde out any of the things contained. Thus intreating the Lord to enlighten thy understanding, that thou maist understand what thou readest; and to sanctifie thy affections, that thou mayst put in practise what good duties thou understandest; I bid thee in the Lord,</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell.</salute>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in CHRIST IESU,</hi> R. W.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>