<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader on this Vocabulary of his good friend, Master Henry Cocke∣ram of Exeter.</title>
           <author>Hore, Bartholomew</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118706_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19044</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5461.2</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118706</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader on this Vocabulary of his good friend, Master Henry Cocke∣ram of Exeter.</title>
                 <author>Hore, Bartholomew</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The English dictionarie: or, An interpreter of hard English vvords : Enabling as well ladies and gentlewomen, young schollers, clarkes, merchants, as also strangers of any nation, to the vnderstanding of the more difficult authors already printed in our language, and the more speedy attaining of an elegant perfection of the English tongue, both in reading, speaking and writing. Being a collection of the choisest words contained in the Table alphabeticall and English expositor, and of some thousands of words neuer published by any heretofore. By H.C. Gent</title>
                 <author>Cockeram, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <distributor>Weaver (Wever), Edmund</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>332 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <head>To the Reader on this Vocabulary of his good friend, Master <hi>Henry Cocke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram</hi> of <hi>Exeter.</hi>
   </head>
   <lg>
      <l>IF things farre fetch'd are dearest, most esteem'd,</l>
      <l>which by times sweatful houres haue been redeem'd.</l>
      <l>Of what count's this, of which sort like was neuer,</l>
      <l>Praise it of force you must, and loue him euer.</l>
      <l>The <hi>Adage</hi> is far sought, deare bought, please ladies,</l>
      <l>You must yeeld to this Maxime, or proue babies.</l>
      <l>Then giue worths due, that worthinesses guise,</l>
      <l>If not, my Motto is, you are vnwise.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Bartho. Hore.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>