<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST
WORTHILY HONO∣RED▪
MY SINGVLAR
GOOD LORD, ROBERT,
Earle of SOMERSET,
Lord Chamber∣laine,
&amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118235_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03515</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13637</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118235</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST
WORTHILY HONO∣RED▪
MY SINGVLAR
GOOD LORD, ROBERT,
Earle of SOMERSET,
Lord Chamber∣laine,
&amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Homer's Odysses. Translated according to ye Greeke by. Geo: Chapman</title>
                 <author>Homer</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 193, 3, 195-376, 4 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST
WORTHILY HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RED▪
MY SINGVLAR
GOOD LORD, ROBERT,
Earle of SOMERSET,
Lord Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine,
&amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue aduentured (Right Noble Earle) out of
my vtmost, and euer-vowed seruice to your
Vertues, to entitle their Merits to the Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage
of <hi>Homers</hi> English life: whose wisht
naturall life, the great <hi>Macedon</hi> would
haue protected, as the spirit of his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,</p>
   <l>That he to his vnmeasur'd mightie Acts,</l>
   <l>Might adde a Fame as vast; and their extracts,</l>
   <l>In fires as bright, and endlesse as the starres,</l>
   <l>His breast might breathe; and thunder out his warres.</l>
   <l>But that great Monarks loue of fame and praise,</l>
   <l>Receiues an enuious Cloud in our foule daies:</l>
   <l>For since our Great ones, ceasse themselues to do</l>
   <l>Deeds worth their praise; they hold it folly too,</l>
   <l>To feed their praise in others. But what can</l>
   <l>(Of all the gifts that are) be giuen to man,</l>
   <l>More precious then <hi>Eternitie</hi> and <hi>Glorie,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Singing their praises, in vnsilenc't storie?</l>
   <l>Which No blacke Day, No Nation, nor no Age;</l>
   <l>No change of Time or Fortune, Force, nor Rage,</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="3"/>
Shall euer race? All which, the Monarch knew,</l>
   <l>Where <hi>Homer</hi> liu'd entitl'd, would ensew:</l>
   <l>
      <q>—Cuius de gurgite viuo</q>
   </l>
   <l>
      <q>Combibit arcanos vatum <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> turba furores,</q> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Fx Angeli Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiani Amb<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a.</note>
   </l>
   <l>From whose deepe Fount of life, the thirstie rout</l>
   <l>Of Thespian Prophets, haue lien sucking out</l>
   <l>Their sacred rages. And as th'influent stone</l>
   <l>Of Father <hi>Ioues</hi> great and laborious Sonne,</l>
   <l>Lifts high the heauie Iron; and farre implies</l>
   <l>The wide Orbs; that the Needle rectifies,</l>
   <l>In vertuous guide of euery sea-driuen course,</l>
   <l>To all aspiring, his one boundlesse force:</l>
   <l>So from one <hi>Homer,</hi> all the holy fire,</l>
   <l>That euer did the hidden heate inspire</l>
   <l>In each true Muse, came cleerly sparkling downe,</l>
   <l>And must for him, compose one flaming Crowne.</l>
   <l>He, at <hi>Ioues</hi> Table set, fils out to vs,</l>
   <l>Cups that repaire Age, sad and minous;</l>
   <l>And giues it Built, of an eternall stand,</l>
   <l>With his all-sinewie Odyssaean hand.</l>
   <l>Shifts Time, and Fate; puts Death in Lifes free state;</l>
   <l>And Life doth into Ages propagate.</l>
   <l>He doth in Men, the Gods affects inflame;</l>
   <l>His fuell Vertue, blowne by <hi>Praise</hi> and <hi>Fame:</hi>
   </l>
   <l>And with the high soules, first impulsions driuen,</l>
   <l>Breakes through rude Chaos, Earth, the Seas, and Heauen.</l>
   <l>The Nerues of all things hid in Nature, lie</l>
   <l>Naked before him; all their Harmonie</l>
   <l>Tun'd to his Accents; that in Beasts breathe Minds.</l>
   <l>What Fowles, what Floods, what Earth, what Aire, what Winds,</l>
   <l>What fires Aethereall, what the Gods conclude</l>
   <l>In all their Counsels, his Muse makes indude</l>
   <l>With varied voices, that e<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>en rockes haue mou'd.</l>
   <l>And yet for all this, (naked Vertue lou'd)</l>
   <l>Honors without her, he, as abiect, prises;</l>
   <l>And foolish Fame, deriu'd from thence, despises.</l>
   <l>When from the vulgar, taking glorious bound,</l>
   <l>Vp to the Mountaine, where the Muse is crownd;</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="3"/>
He sits and laughs, to see the iaded Rabble,</l>
   <l>Toile to his hard heights,<note place="margin">Thus far Angel. Politianus, for the most part translated.</note> t'all accesse vnable. &amp;c.</l>
   <p>And that your Lordship may in his Face, take view of his Mind: the
first word of his Iliads, is <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>wrath:</hi> the first word of his Odysses,
<gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>Man:</hi> contracting in either word, his each workes Proposition. In
one, <hi>Predominant Perturbation;</hi> in the other, <hi>ouer-ruling Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome:</hi>
in one, the Bodies feruour and fashion of outward Fortitude, to
all possible height of Heroicall Action; in the other, the Minds inward,
constant, and vnconquerd Empire; vnbroken, vnalterd, with any most
insolent, and tyrannous infliction. To many most souer aigne praises is this
Poeme entitled; but to that <hi>Grace</hi> in chiefe, which sets on the Crowne,
both of Poets and Orators; <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: that is,
<hi>Parua magnè dicere; peruulgata nouè; ieiuna plenè:</hi> To speake
things litle, greatly; things commune, rarely; things barren and emptie,
fruitfully and fully. The returne of a man into his Countrie, is his whole
scope and obiect; which, in it selfe, your Lordship may well say, is ieiune
and fruitlesse enough; affoording nothing feastfull, nothing magnificent.
And yet euen this, doth the diuine inspiration, render vast, illustrous, and
of miraculous composure. And for this (my Lord) is this <hi>Poeme</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred
to his <hi>Iliads:</hi> for therein much magnificence, both of person and
action, giues great aide to his industrie; but in this, are these helpes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
sparing, or nothing; and yet is the Structure so elaborate, and
pompous, that the poore plaine Groundworke (considered together) may
seeme the naturally rich wombe to it, and produce it needfully. Much won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derd
at therefore, is the Censure of <hi>Dionysius Longimus</hi> (a man o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise
affirmed, graue, and of elegant iudgement) comparing <hi>Homer</hi>
in his <hi>Iliads,</hi> to the Sunne rising; in his <hi>Odysses,</hi> to his descent or set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.
Or to the <hi>Ocean</hi> robd of his aesture; many tributorie flouds and
riuers of excellent ornament, withheld from their obseruance. When this
his worke so farre exceeds the <hi>Ocean,</hi> with all his Court and concourse;
that all his Sea, is onely a seruiceable streame to it. Nor can it be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
to any One power to be named in nature; being an entirely wel-sorted
and digested Confluence of all. Where the most solide and graue, is made
as nimble and fl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ent, as the most airie and firie; the nimble and fluent, as
firme and well bounded as the most graue and solid. And (taking all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether)
of so tender impression, and of such Command to the voice of the
<hi>Muse;</hi> that they knocke heauen with her breath, and discouer their foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations
as low as hell. Nor is this all-comprising <hi>Poesie,</hi> phantastique,
<pb facs="4"/>
or meere fictiue; but the most material, and doctrinall illations of <hi>Truth;</hi>
both for all manly information of Manners in the yong; all prescription
of Iustice, and euen Christian pietie, in the most graue and high-gouernd.
To illustrate both which, in both kinds, with all height of expression, the
Poet creates both a Bodie and a Soule in them. Wherein, if the Bodie (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the letter, or historie) seemes fictiue, and beyond Possibilitie to bring
into Act: the sence then and Allegorie (which is the Soule) is to be sought:
which intends a more eminent express<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re of <hi>Vertue,</hi> for her louelinesse;
and of <hi>Vice</hi> for her vglinesse, in their seuer all effects; going beyond the
life, then any Art within life, can possibly delineate. Why then is <hi>Fiction,</hi>
to this end, so hatefull to our true Ignorants? Or why should a poore
Chronicler of a Lord Maiors naked <hi>Truth,</hi> (that peraduenture will last
his yeare) include more worth with our <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oderne wizerds, then <hi>Homer</hi>
for his naked <hi>Vlysses,</hi> clad in eternall Fiction? But this Prozer <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nysius,</hi>
and the rest of these graue, and reputatiuely learned, (that dare
vndertake for their grauities, the headstrong censure of all things; and
challenge the vnderstanding of these Toyes in their childhoods: when e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
these childish vanities, retaine deepe and most necessarie learning e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
in them, to make them children in their ages, and teach them while
they liue) are not in these absolutely di<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ine Infusions, allowd either voice
or relish: for, <hi>Qui Poeticas ad fores accedit, &amp;c.</hi> (sayes the Diuine
Philosopher) he that knocks at the Gates of the <hi>Muses; sine Musarum
furore;</hi> is neither to be admitted entrie, nor a touch at their Thresholds:
his opinion of entrie, ridiculous, and his presumption impious. Nor must
Poets themselues (might I a litle insist on these contempts▪ not tempting
too farre your Lordships <hi>Vlyssean</hi> patience) presume to these doores,
without the truly genuine, and peculiar induction▪ There being in <hi>Poesie</hi>
a twofold rapture, (or alienation of soule, as the abouesaid Te<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cher
termes it) one <hi>Insania,</hi> a disease of the mind, and a meere madnesse, by
which the infected is thrust beneath all the degrees of humanitie: <hi>&amp; ex
homine, Brutum quodammodo redditur:</hi> (for which, poore <hi>Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie,</hi>
in this diseasd and impostorous age, is so barbarously vilified) the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
is, <hi>Diuinus furor;</hi> by which the sound and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> healthfull, <hi>su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra
hominis naturam erigitur, &amp; in Deum transit.</hi> One a perfection
directly infused from God: the other an infection, obliquely and degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately
proceeding from man. Of the diuine <hi>Furie</hi> (my Lord) your <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi>
hath euer bene, both first and last <hi>Instance;</hi> being pronounced ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely,
<gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>; the most wise and most diuine
<pb facs="4"/>
Poet. Against whom, whosoeuer shall open his prophane mouth, may wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily
receiue answer, with this of his diuine defender; (<hi>Empedocles,
Heraclitus, Protagoras, Epichar: &amp;c.</hi> being of <hi>Homers</hi> part) <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>,
&amp;c. who against such an Armie, and the Generall <hi>Homer</hi> dares attempt
the assault, but he must be reputed ridiculous? And yet against this hoast,
and this inuincible Commander, shall we haue euery <hi>Besogne</hi> and foole
a Leader. The common herd (I assure my self) readie to receiue it on their
hornes. Their infected Leaders,</p>
   <l>Such men, as sideling ride the ambling <hi>Muse;</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Whose saddle is as frequent as the stuse.</l>
   <l>Whose Raptures are in euery Pageant seene;</l>
   <l>In euery Wassall rime, and Dancing greene:</l>
   <l>When he that writes by any beame of Truth,</l>
   <l>Must diue as deepe as he; past shallow youth.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Truth</hi> dwels in Gulphs, whose Deepes hide shades so rich,</l>
   <l>That <hi>Night</hi> sits muffl'd there, in clouds of pitch:</l>
   <l>More Darke then Nature made her; and requires</l>
   <l>(To cleare her tough mists) Heauens great fire of fires;</l>
   <l>To whom, the Sunne it selfe is but a Beame.</l>
   <l>For sicke soules then (but rapt in foolish Dreame)</l>
   <l>To wrestle with these Heau'n-strong mysteries;</l>
   <l>What madnesse is it? when their light, serues eies</l>
   <l>That are not worldly, in their least aspect;</l>
   <l>But truly pure; and aime at Heauen, direct.</l>
   <l>Yet these, none like; but what the brazen head</l>
   <l>Blatters abroad; no sooner borne, but dead.</l>
   <p>Holding then in eternal contempt (my Lord) those short-liued Bubbles;
eternize your vertue and iudgement with the <hi>Grecian</hi> Monark; estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming,
not as the least of your New-yeares Presents,</p>
   <l>
      <hi>Homer</hi> (three thousand yeares dead) now reuiu'd,</l>
   <l>Euen from that dull Death, that in life he liu'd;</l>
   <l>When none conceited him; none vnderstood,</l>
   <l>That so much life, in so much death as blood</l>
   <l>Conueys about it, could mixe. But when Death</l>
   <l>Drunke vp the bloudie Mist, that humane breath</l>
   <l>Pour'd round about him (Pouertie and Spight,</l>
   <l>Thickning the haplesse vapor) then Truths light</l>
   <l>Glimmerd about his Poeme: the pincht soule,</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="5"/>
(Amidst the Mysteries it did enroule)</l>
   <l>Brake powrefully abroad. And as we see</l>
   <l>The Sunne all hid in clouds, at length, got free,</l>
   <l>Through some forc't couert, ouer all the wayes,</l>
   <l>Neare and beneath him, shootes his vented rayes</l>
   <l>Farre off, and stickes them in some litle Glade;</l>
   <l>All woods, fields, riuers, left besides in shade:</l>
   <l>So your <hi>Apollo,</hi> from that world of light,</l>
   <l>Closde in his Poems bodie; shot to sight</l>
   <l>Some few forc't Beames; which neare him, were not seene,</l>
   <l>(As in his life or countrie) Fate and Spleene,</l>
   <l>Clouding their radiance; which when Death had clear'd;</l>
   <l>To farre off Regions, his free beames appear'd:</l>
   <l>In which, all stood and wonderd; striuing which,</l>
   <l>His Birth and Rapture, should in right enrich.</l>
   <l>Twelue <hi>Labours</hi> of your <hi>Thespian Hercules,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>I now present your Lordship: Do but please</l>
   <l>To lend Life meanes, till th'other Twelue receaue</l>
   <l>Equall atchieuement; and let Death then reaue</l>
   <l>My life now lost in our Patrician Loues,</l>
   <l>That knocke heads with the herd: in whom there moues</l>
   <l>One blood, one soule: both drownd in one set height</l>
   <l>Of stupid Enuie, and meere popular Spight.</l>
   <l>Whose loues, with no good, did my least veine fill;</l>
   <l>And from their hates,<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> I feare as little ill.</l>
   <l>Their Boun<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>es nourish not, when most they feed,</l>
   <l>But where there is no Merit, or no Need:</l>
   <l>Raine into riuers still; and are such showres,</l>
   <l>As bubbles spring, and ouerflow the flowres.</l>
   <l>Their worse parts, and worst men, their Best subornes,</l>
   <l>Like winter Cowes, whose milke runnes to their hornes.</l>
   <l>And as litigious Clients bookes of Law,</l>
   <l>Cost infinitely; taste of all the Awe,</l>
   <l>Bencht in our kingdomes Policie, Pietie, State;</l>
   <l>Earne all their deepe explorings; satiate</l>
   <l>All sorts there thrust together by the heart,</l>
   <l>With thirst of wisedome, spent on either part:</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="5"/>
Horrid examples made of Life and Death,</l>
   <l>From their fine stuffe wouen: yet when once the breath</l>
   <l>Of sentence leaues them, all their worth is drawne</l>
   <l>As drie as dust; and weares like Cobweb Lawne:</l>
   <l>So these men set a price vpon their worth,</l>
   <l>That no man giues, but those that trot it forth,</l>
   <l>Through <hi>Needs</hi> foule wayes; feed <hi>Humors,</hi> with all cost,</l>
   <l>Though <hi>Iudgement</hi> sterues in them: <hi>Rout: State</hi> engrost</l>
   <l>(At all Tabacco benches, solemne Tables,</l>
   <l>Where all that crosse their Enuies, are their fables)</l>
   <l>In their ranke faction: Shame, and Death approu'd</l>
   <l>Fit Penance for their Opposites: none lou'd</l>
   <l>But those that rub them: not a Reason heard,</l>
   <l>That doth not sooth and glorifie their preferd</l>
   <l>Bitter Opinions. When, would <hi>Truth</hi> resume</l>
   <l>The cause to his hands; all would flie in fume</l>
   <l>Before his sentence; since the innocent mind,</l>
   <l>Iust God makes good; to whom their worst is wind.</l>
   <l>For, that I freely all my Thoughts expresse,</l>
   <l>My Conscience is my Thousand witnesses:</l>
   <l>And to this stay, my constant Comforts vow;</l>
   <l>You for the world I haue, or God for you.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>