<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY HONOURABLE Friend, JOHN COVENTRY, Esquire, Sonne to the Right Honorable THOMAS, Lord COVENTRY, Baron of Alesborough, and Lord Keeper of the Great SEALE of England.</title>
           <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118116_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13272</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23573</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118116</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY HONOURABLE Friend, JOHN COVENTRY, Esquire, Sonne to the Right Honorable THOMAS, Lord COVENTRY, Baron of Alesborough, and Lord Keeper of the Great SEALE of England.</title>
                 <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sermons vpon solemne occasions : preached in severall auditories. By Humphrey Sydenham, rector of Pokington in Somerset</title>
                 <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Robinson, Humphrey</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 240, 251-316, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>TO MY HONOURABLE Friend, JOHN COVENTRY, Esquire, Sonne to the Right Honorable THOMAS, Lord COVENTRY, Baron of <hi>Alesborough,</hi> and Lord Keeper of the Great SEALE of <hi>England.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> Presume a <hi>musicall Discourse</hi> can neither bee improper, nor unseasonable for him, that hath so much <hi>harmony</hi> in himselfe, that holds such a <hi>consonancy</hi> with the practice of the <hi>Church</hi> he lives in. And <hi>this</hi> is both your <hi>happinesse</hi> and your <hi>ayme.</hi> Too many there are which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy their <hi>wit</hi> and <hi>greatnesse</hi> a contrary way, and delight altogether <hi>in the jarring of the string,</hi> as if there were no <hi>Melody but in Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords;</hi> but such are not within your <hi>finger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/> nor, indeed, your <hi>fancie;</hi> knowing that a <hi>Song</hi> of <hi>Sion,</hi> is a Song of <hi>Peace;</hi> and he that <hi>keepes not time</hi> in the <hi>Hosannah</hi> below, shall hardly <hi>sing his part</hi> in the <hi>Hallelujah</hi> above. I could whisper something in your eare, but being in part a stranger, I may be thought to gloze; and therefore I will tell't abroad, where I am conceiv'd to be a little blunt, and therefore unapt to flatter. You have besides your accurate speculations both in <hi>Divinity</hi> and <hi>Arts,</hi> a way to sweeten them. <hi>an humble and courteous affability,</hi> by which you have given so much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to those more canonically devoted in our (commonly despised) Tribe, that you have made them even tributary, and captive; so that they equally study their owne <hi>thankefulnesse,</hi> and your <hi>honour;</hi> to which if these poore scrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of mine may give either <hi>lustre</hi> or <hi>advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> (you having beene formerly pleased to afford them not only the <hi>charity</hi> of your faire o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, but the <hi>approbation</hi> also) I have done something to <hi>glory in;</hi> and amongst the <hi>Troop</hi> of your other <hi>Honourers</hi> and <hi>Admirers,</hi> shall persist as the most humble, so</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>The most Faithfull, HVM. SYDENHAM.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>