<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HO∣NOVRABLE AND HOPEFVLL YOVNG Gentleman, Sir ROBERT CARR, Barronet, W. H. wisheth increase of all honorable ver∣tues.</title>
           <author>H., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118882_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03687</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13814</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118882</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HO∣NOVRABLE AND HOPEFVLL YOVNG Gentleman, Sir ROBERT CARR, Barronet, W. H. wisheth increase of all honorable ver∣tues.</title>
                 <author>H., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Hornbyes hornbook : Iudge not too rashly, till through all you looke; if nothing then doth please you, burne the booke. By William Hornbye, gent</title>
                 <author>Hornby, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bailey (Baily, Baley, Bayly), Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>38 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE AND HOPEFVLL YOVNG Gentleman, Sir ROBERT CARR, Barronet,</hi> W. H. wisheth increase of all <hi>honorable ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues.</hi>
   </head>
   <lg>
      <l>MY honest, humble, harmlesse horning-book,</l>
      <l>From whence young Schollers their first learning tool</l>
      <l>To you I dedicate (true generous spirit)</l>
      <l>Your early towardnesse, and vertues merit</l>
      <l>A farre more worthy worke, then here I can</l>
      <l>Set out, that ne're was Accademian:</l>
      <l>Yet in my homely verse (perhaps) you'l find</l>
      <l>Something, a little which may please your mind.</l>
      <l>My booke's but Harden to some Holland wit,</l>
      <l>And so with home-spun plainest best doth fit;</l>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <l>For in a plaine and honest simple stile,</l>
      <l>There lurkes no craft, no subtiltie, nor guile.</l>
      <l>Here is no vaine, nor yet prophane discourse,</l>
      <l>To make you by the reading be the worse;</l>
      <l>I would not staine your thoughts with such a booke,</l>
      <l>Nor haue your chaste eyes on such follies looke.</l>
      <l>This in a manner doth but plainely show</l>
      <l>How Schollers doe begin, and how they grow</l>
      <l>To <hi>Learning</hi> by their industrie and paine,</l>
      <l>That rich inestimable Iem to gaine.</l>
      <l>(The <hi>Horn-book</hi> is at first Arts Nurce, frō whence</l>
      <l>We suck the milke of our intellîgence)</l>
      <l>We must be perfect in our letters all,</l>
      <l>E're we to spelling, and to reading fall.</l>
      <l>By this Originall, we win (indeed)</l>
      <l>The <hi>Muses</hi> glory, if we so proceede:</l>
      <l>And as this booke (sweet Sir) but young appeares</l>
      <l>So tis respondent vnto youthfull yeares,</l>
      <l>Fit for your young dayes and minoritie,</l>
      <l>Vntill you come to senioritie.</l>
      <l>Into my mind this cogitation came,</l>
      <l>Vnto your selfe to dedicate the same,</l>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <l>Presuming of your fauour, and your loue,</l>
      <l>That what I write your vertues will approue</l>
      <l>Vpon your face, although your yeares be greene,</l>
      <l>The portrature of modestie is seene.</l>
      <l>Though in the Teenes you scarce haue enterd yet,</l>
      <l>You haue a manly Carriage, pregnant Wit.</l>
      <l>God be your good guide, and your happy speede</l>
      <l>Euen as you haue begun, so to proceede</l>
      <l>In honourable vertues worthy <hi>Car,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>To make your name shine like the Morning-Star.</l>
      <l>Thus Honourable Sir, I take my leaue,</l>
      <l>In hope you kindly will (this mite) receiue.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in all humble seruice, <hi>W. H.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>