<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118538_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13872</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24175</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118538</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Gods love-tokens, and the afflicted mans lessons : brought to light, and layd before him in two fruitfull and seasonable discourses upon Revel. 3. 19. Comforting under, and directing unto a right use of our personall, and publike crosses and calamities. By John Trapp, M.A. and preacher of Gods Word at Luddington in Warwick-shire</title>
                 <author>Trapp, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Badger, Richard 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40, 216, 219-222, 6 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is, I must needs say, an over-just complaint of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend writer<note n="a" place="margin">D. King <hi>Lect. upon</hi> Ionas Prof.</note>, that <hi>Presses are already op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prest,</hi> the world abounding with bookes even to satiety, and surfeit. And of Another, that the <hi>untimely brats of mens braines fly thicke up and downe the world, in this scribbling Age</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Passim cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvolitant in hoo feraci chartarum saeculo huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni cerebelli Minervae. <hi>D. Prid. Lect.</hi>
      </note>. And of a Third, that too many set forth in print, some, <hi>their owne wit,</hi> more, <hi>their owne folly</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">Hezek. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>v.</note>. Whilest, with <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/> in St. <hi>Hierome</hi> they care not <hi>What,</hi> but <hi>How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much</hi> they utter<note n="d" place="margin">Non quid, sed qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>um &amp;c. <hi>Hier.</hi> in <hi>Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>l.</hi> ad <hi>Domnionem.</hi>
      </note>: with <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibiades</hi> in the Moralist, they talke much, but speake little<note n="e" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. plutar.</note>: or with those triflers in the Gospell, they hope to be heard, for their much hab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling<note n="f" place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 6 7. confer <hi>Ec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>les.</hi> 10.14.</note>. These forget, belike, that Writers should set forth not <hi>Treatises,</hi> but <hi>Treasu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">Amhores non debere libros, sed the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sauros com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponere. <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitius Piso.</hi> Sic <hi>Pli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>j</hi> Opus <hi>Erasino</hi> thesaurus est, imò verè mundus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum cognitu dignissimatū</note>: and that words (as monies) are valued by their matter, not by their multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude<note n="h" place="margin">Idem ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moni congru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it quod num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> &amp;c. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>hyox.</hi>
      </note>: and (as suffrages) they passe not among wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, by tale, but by weight<note n="i" place="margin">Non nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>arda suff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia, sed expen denda.</note>. Great talkers, indeede, would be thought eminent: and some that publish much, affect to be publike; albeit they sound, many times, from their emptinesse onely<note n="k" place="margin">Vasa quae magis conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, minus sonant. <hi>Sen.</hi>
      </note>.
<pb facs="5"/> Whereas the deepest waters are le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st heard<note n="l" place="margin">Lene fluit Nilus, sed cunctis amni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus extat Vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lior, nullas confessus mutmure vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. <hi>Claudian.</hi>
      </note>: and those orient starres, the higher they are set, the lesse they are seene. The best and biggest of them, as they appeare not at all by day; so by night, they shew themselves but small in their hugest Orbes, and but slow in their swiftest moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons<note n="m" place="margin">In maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma sui mole se minimùm ostendunt stellae.</note>: besides many a goodly one, that because of height comes not within our ken or account. I wot well, there's never a mothers child of us that is not too much the true child of our great grand-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. We have each of us (saith our English <hi>Seneca</hi>) an <hi>Eues</hi> sweet-tooth in our heads, and would be more than we are: Every man would be either (<gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>) or (<gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>)
<pb facs="6"/> The man, or Some body<note n="n" place="margin">B Hall. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist.</note>. The sweetest hearing (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever dissembled) is ones owne commendation<note n="o" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Xo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noph.</note>: and he is a rare man that hath not some <hi>Babel,</hi> whereon he bestowes paines and cost, either to be pointed at<note n="p" place="margin">digito mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strari, &amp;c.</note>, and talked of, as <hi>Demosthenes</hi>
      <note n="q" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>, or to curry favour with the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sort, as <hi>Herod</hi>
      <note n="r" place="margin">Legatur <hi>Bez An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>t.</hi> in <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.20.</note>. For my selfe, truly, as I looke not to please all (mens fancies being as different as their faces<note n="s" place="margin">D. Haukw. Atol.</note>) so, if I may approove my poore paines to Christ <hi>the Judge of all</hi>
      <note n="t" place="margin">
         <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.</note>, and to his <hi>Hidden ones</hi>
      <note n="u" place="margin">
         <hi>Psal</hi> 83.3. Equidem plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis secerim justam com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendationem unius alicujus pij &amp; boni viri quàm ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirationem stultam totius multitudinis. <hi>Host.</hi> in <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.28.</note>, the godly ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious, I have enough, and shall well enough comfort my selfe with that white-stone, <hi>Rev. 2.17.</hi> against the blacke coales (if any such be) of the
<pb facs="6"/> more malevolent<note n="x" place="margin">Malis dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicere, lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dari est. <hi>Sen.</hi>
      </note>. It was a sweet and savoury saying of <hi>Occolampadius:</hi> I should be loth to speake, or write ought that Christ should disallow<note n="y" place="margin">Nolui ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid loqui vel scribere, quod improbatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum putem Christum.</note>. He (truly) is that master to whom every man stands or falls<note n="z" place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 14 4.</note>: and one good look from him, is insteed of all acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. For, <hi>not he that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth himself,</hi> saith that great Apostle; nor he whom the world cōmends, <hi>is appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but he whom the Lord commendeth. Wherefore, let him that glorieth, glory in the Lord, 2</hi> Cor. <hi>10.17, 18.</hi> There are, that glory in themselves, as those ancient Gnosticks<note n="*" place="margin">Gnostici se solos fontem veritatie hau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sisse, &amp;c. <hi>Iren. lib.</hi> 1 <hi>cap.</hi> 24</note>, and our moderne Iesuites<note n="a" place="margin">Iesuita non potest esse haereticus: &amp; Imperium li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terarum est penes Iesuitas Casaub. ex Apologista. They vaunt that the Church is the soule of the world, the clergy of the Church, and they of the Clergy. <hi>Sand. rela.</hi> of West. relig.</note>; sacrifice to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, as <hi>Sejanus</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Seianus</hi> sibi sacra facere solebat. Dio in vita <hi>Tiber.</hi>
      </note>, and those Babylonians, <hi>Hab. 1.16.</hi> set
<pb facs="7"/> up, and serve themselves of Christ and his service, as <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> and his successours; that rob him of his rent, and run away with his glory: dealing with his worke, as once <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias</hi> the famous Carver, did with the Shield of <hi>Minerva,</hi> wherein hee so cunningly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chased his owne countenance, that it could not be defaced, but the Shield must be disfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured. Such were those flaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Preachers of <hi>Philippi,</hi> that to carry away the bell from a better man<note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.16.</note>, sought to set up themselves in the hearts of their hearers. And such are those <hi>deceitful wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13.</note> now a daies, as preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to be Christs spokesmen, will needs bee his corrivalls (upon the matter) whiles they
<pb facs="7"/> give out themselves for some <hi>great ones</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">Testis est Iustinus, quod hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> statuam habuerit inter pontes <hi>Tiberis</hi> cui insculpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur, <hi>Simoni</hi> Deo Sancto.</note>, with <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> Act. <hi>8.9.</hi> and interest themselves (as he, too far) in the peoples affections, <hi>ver. 10 11.</hi> These cannot preface to their works, as those ancients did <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <note n="f" place="margin">Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>l. Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dig. <hi>ex</hi> Pausa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia.</note>: but may justly betwitted, as that Pope was pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily; when he had engraven upō the gates of his new-built Colledge: <hi>Vtretent</hi> (where he was borne) <hi>planted mee; Lovain</hi> (where he was bred) <hi>watered mee;</hi> but, <hi>Caesar</hi> (who had promoted him to the Popedom) <hi>gave increase:</hi> A merry Passenger under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrote; <hi>Here God did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">Papa <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>àrtatus</hi> cum <hi>Lovanij</hi> col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legium mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no sumptu struxisset. &amp;c. Hommis va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit item re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>gait alius subs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ribens, Hic Deus ni h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>l fecit. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reus</hi> in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3 6.</note>. So, God is not in all the tho ghts<note n="h" place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 10.4.</note> of these <hi>selfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seekers,</hi> that thus i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tervert one part of the price; with
<pb facs="8"/> that ill couple, <hi>Acts 5.2.</hi> whiles they <hi>turne Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry into shame, loving vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, seeking after lyes</hi>
      <note n="i" place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 4.2. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>. The word there used, signifieth such a lye, as deceiveth mens expectations, <hi>Psal. 89.35. Isa. 58.11. 2 King. 4.16.</hi> Of w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> sort, by a specialty, is that smoke of popular applause, which the higher it mounts, the sooner it vanisheth. <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely,</hi> saith our Saviour to such, (and it is fearfull) <hi>they have their reward</hi>
      <note n="k" place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 6.</note>: all they are over like to have; let them make them merry with it. But what speake I of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment? when the best that can come of such mens wood, hay, stubble, laid upon the common foundation, is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to salvation<note n="l" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.</note>, <hi>yet so
<pb facs="8"/> as thorough the fire</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Inferiore gradu gloriae quàm alij <hi>Pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reus.</hi> quem consule.</note>: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the losse of their worke, if not of some part of their wages, <hi>when the day shall declare it</hi>
      <note n="m" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.12 13.</note>: that is, when the light of the Truth, <hi>Rom. 13.12.</hi> or Time the father of Truth, or that Day of death, (when many recognize, and recant their errors) shal shew them their Sin. Good S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin</hi> cryed to God, to pardon the vanities of his youth, and especially this, that hee had preached <hi>ut placeret,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Confess.</note>
      <hi>non ut doceret,</hi> to delight the eare, more than to smite the heart. A faire glasse for such to look in, a faire copie for such to write by, as write nothing but as in a frame. Every word is so marshalled, and every sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence with its apt cadencie,
<pb facs="9"/> lies in such comely equipage.<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> In these mens discourses, you cannot see matter for words<note n="o" place="margin">Melaneth. <hi>apud</hi> Laert.</note> as in some mens againe, scarse words for matter. <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripides,</hi> saith the Oratour, hath more sentences than sayings<note n="p" place="margin">Plu es sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentias quam verba. <hi>Cic.</hi>
      </note>: and <hi>Thucydides,</hi> hath so stuft every syllable with substance<note n="q" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>, that the one runs along paralell with the other<note n="r" place="margin">Adeò plenus referrus{que} re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, ut pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe verborum numerum nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero rerum exaquet. <hi>Cic.</hi>
      </note>. <hi>Lysias</hi> his workes are so well coucht, that you cannot take out the least word, but you take away the whole sense with it<note n="s" place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ex Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis oratione aliquid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, manes{que} de elegantia tantum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traxeris; si ex <hi>Lysiae,</hi> de sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia. <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verinu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> apud Gell.</hi>
      </note>. And <hi>Phocion</hi> had a speciall sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie of speaking much in few<note n="t" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch.</note>. Those best of Greekes were the short spoken par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans<note n="u" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>; and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ans in <hi>Pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ces</hi> time, (however de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi>
      <note n="x" place="margin">
         <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.12.</note>;
<pb facs="9"/> were more waighty than wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy<note n="y" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Plat.</note>. <hi>Timanthes</hi> is famous for this, that in his pictures more things were intended than deciphered<note n="z" place="margin">Plin. li. 35. cap. 10.</note>: and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> that none could ever peere him for Poetrie, nor match him for matter<note n="a" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Xenophon.</note>. How much more apt and apposite are these high praises to the Booke of God, rightly called <hi>The Bible?</hi> as if it were (as indeed it is, both for fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of termes, and fulnesse of truth) the onely booke; to which, all other bookes in the world are but waste paper<note n="b" place="margin">Ego odi meos libros, &amp; saepé opto eo, interire, quod metuo ne morentur lectores à le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione ipsius Scriptura quae sola namis saptentiae sons est. <hi>Luther</hi> in <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.</note>. Called it is also, <hi>The Word,</hi> (by an excellencie) because it must be the But, and boun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dary of our words: and, <hi>The Scriptures,</hi> as the standard of all humane writings. Yea,
<pb facs="10"/> that princely Preacher stiles them <hi>Princes,</hi> or <hi>Leaders</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>Prov.</hi> 8 6. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> in one place, and <hi>Lords of Collections</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.11. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> in another, because they are as Leaders, and Lords <hi>Paramount</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all other words or wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of men, collected into volumes. Here we are bound to bestow our day and night-studies<note n="e" place="margin">
         <hi>Iosh.</hi> 1.8.</note>: and hence wee may well gather flowers, and phrases to polish our spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches with; even those <hi>sound words</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> in Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> that have a healing property in them, farre above all filed phrases of humane elocution. <hi>To the Law</hi> therefore, <hi>and to the Testimonie</hi> (saith that rare Rhetorician) <hi>for, if any speake not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this Word, it is
<pb facs="10"/> because there is no light in them</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">
         <hi>Isa.</hi> 8.20.</note>. This is the c rtaine <hi>Cynosura,</hi> the Lampe and Lanterne, the Rule, and Rudder, the Wise-men, starre, that leades men to Christ, and without which, all their learning and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage doth but light them into utter darknesse. Good therefore, and worthy of all acceptation is the counsell of Saint <hi>James: So speake yee, and so doe, as those that shall be judg'd by the law of libertie</hi>
      <note n="h" place="margin">
         <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.12.</note>. And of Saint <hi>Paul: Let the word of Christ dwell richly in you, in all wisedome, &amp;c.</hi> that, <hi>whatever yee doe in word or deed, yee may doe all in the Name</hi> (that is, in the word and warrant)
<pb facs="11"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="11"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="12"/>
      <hi>of our Lord Jesus Christ</hi>
      <note n="i" place="margin">
         <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16, 17.</note>. And of Saint <hi>Peter: If any man speake,</hi> saith hee, <hi>let him speake as the oracles of God</hi>
      <note n="k" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11.</note>: there's his pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne. Neither need wee feare, as some prophane mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creants have done before us<note n="l" place="margin">Longolius, Pon p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n Lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Poli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Florent: qui odas Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daricas psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis Davidiers pratulit, ausit nelario. <hi>Spuinx Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los.</hi> p. q.</note>, lest our smoother and purer stile should be marred or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired, by the interlacing of Scripture solecismes<note n="l" place="margin">Longolius, Pon p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n Lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Poli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Florent: qui odas Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daricas psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis Davidiers pratulit, ausit nelario. <hi>Spuinx Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los.</hi> p. q.</note>. The vulgar Translation, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, is so pesterd with Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barismes, that, not onely Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> would dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avow it, but <hi>Priscian</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe would call for his <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rula.</hi> But read, as it was written, or rightly rendered (besides that, for the matter, it is that <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>2 Tim. 3.16.</hi> that<note n="m" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> ut ille olim de Liblioth. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
               <desc>•••</desc>
            </gap>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note> Physick for the
<pb facs="12"/> soule, that crystall brooke, out of which, nay out of that one booke of which, nay al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most out of that one sixth chapter of that one booke of <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> Our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>David</hi> chose all those stones, wherewith he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated the <hi>Goliah</hi> of hell<note n="n" place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.</note>) there is a divine majesty (that character of the deity) shining through the humility and simplicity of the phrase: And oh the happinesse of that man, that can aptly utter his minde in pure Scripture! God himselfe, I am sure (the greatest Master of speech, and Maker of it too, <hi>Exod. 4.11.</hi>) when he spake from heaven, made use of three severall texts in a breath<note n="o" place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.5</note>.
<pb facs="13"/>
      <hi>This is my beloved Sonne, Psal. 2.7. in whom I am well pleased, Esay, 42.1. heare ye him. Deutero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomie, 18.15.</hi> Which you may note against the curious queasinesse of such nice ones, as disdaine at the slately plainnesse of the Scriptures (saith one<note n="p" place="margin">Cart. in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note>) And to shew of what au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority Scripture phrase is with God, saith another expositour<note n="q" place="margin">Malcolm. in <hi>Act.</hi> 3.</note>. I yeeld, there is a latitude, and a liberty lest here, wherein to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiate. Neither am I of <hi>Spiridions</hi> spirit, that could not brooke it in a Bishop of his time (more el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>quent, haply, then himselfe) that he should vary the least tit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in his text, though for
<pb facs="13"/> another of selfe-same sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification<note n="r" place="margin">Voce <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> cum usus es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set in istius historiae e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narratione. <hi>Mar.</hi> 2 4. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscopus qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, tam fuit offensus Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>dion, celo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> &amp; lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tasse morosior Episcopu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, ut in media con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cione in rexe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. <hi>Beza in l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>. ex Niceph.</hi>
      </note>. They that stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at such strawes, must first get their cares healed<note n="s" place="margin">Demost. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. de o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d. civ.</note> (as the Oratour told his country-men) before they will be in cas to beare with fruit, or reade with profit. Let men be so ingenious, saith a Father, as to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that in others which they cannot finde in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. Eloquence is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely a singular gift of God, if not affected, abused, idolized: and becomes no man better then a Divine: whose part it is, by the tongue of the learned <hi>to time a word</hi>
      <note n="t" place="margin">
         <hi>Esay</hi> 50 4. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>, <hi>and to set it upon its circumferences</hi>
      <note n="u" place="margin">
         <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.11.</note>: <hi>to declare unto Man his righteousnesse,</hi> when not
<pb facs="14"/> one of a thousand<note n="x" place="margin">
         <hi>Iob</hi> 33.23.</note> can doe it like him: <hi>to seeke to finde out pleasant words</hi>
      <note n="y" place="margin">Eccles. <hi>12.10, 11. Verba deside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rata:</hi> Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. delectabilia. Tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. expeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilia. Va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ab.</note>, <hi>and an upright writing:</hi> such words as have <hi>goades, and nailes in them,</hi> being neither <hi>lecta</hi> nor <hi>neglecta,</hi> too curious, nor too carelesse. Not this; for where hony is forbidden for sacrifice, yet, there the first-fruits of hony are commanded, and call'd for. <hi>Leviticus, 2.11.12.</hi> Not that; because Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things must be handled <hi>sanctè magis quàm scitè,</hi> with feare and reverence ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then with wit and dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance, as he once told the wanton vestall. Holy <hi>Moses</hi> covers his glistering face with a vaile when he speakes to the people: and hath more
<pb facs="14"/> glory by his vaile then by his face. Those profoundest Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets accommodate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to their hearers capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities, fetching discourse from that the people were most acquainted with, and accustom'd to: as from fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes to the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> from droves of cattle to the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bians,</hi> trade and traffique to the <hi>Tyrians,</hi> &amp;c. So our blessed Saviour tells his fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sher-men they shall be fishers of men. And after many plaine parables to the people, cries out <hi>Marke 4.13.</hi> (as if the wisedome of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the essentiall word, had beene at a fault for a fit word, familiar and low enough for our slow and shallow appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensions) <hi>Whereunto shall
<pb facs="15"/> we liken the Kingdome of God? or with what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison shall wee compare it?</hi> Yea, 'tis well observed, that th'Evangelists speake vulgarly, many times for their Hearers sakes, even to a manifest Incongruity, <hi>Joh. 17.2</hi>
      <note n="z" place="margin">Manifestum <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Sed Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listae multa di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>endi gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra è medio petierunt, ut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>udi vulgò s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da ent. <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap> in loc.</hi>
      </note>. <hi>Rev. 1.4. &amp;c.</hi> In after-ages (those two great lights of the Church) S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin</hi> confesseth that hee was fain to use some words, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, to those Roman Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in <hi>Africke,</hi> where hee preached, that were not La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, to the end they might understand him<note n="a" place="margin">As <hi>essum</hi> for <hi>os, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>lus</hi> for <hi>dolor, stor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>et</hi> for <hi>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>rebit.</hi> Bice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>voods enq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ties. p. 29.</note>. And Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> is for this much commended, that remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring he was a Minister, hee stood not alwaies upon the purenesse of his stile, but was
<pb facs="15"/> farre more solicitous of his matter, than of his words<note n="b" place="margin">L. Vives. lib 2. &amp; 3. de t. ad. discip.</note>. Children, wee see, use money to gingle with, and men use slowers onely for sight and scent: but Bees for hony and waxe; not to guild their wings, as the Butter-flie, but to fill their Combs, and feed their Yong. In like sort, others store their heads, and tip their tongues, some for shew, and some for delight: but, Divines have these ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents in trust, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they may <hi>save them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and them that heare them</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16.</note>; whiles they become all things to all men, in Saint <hi>Pau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> sense, that they may win some<note n="d" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.22.</note>. And this (to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>y sooth) is the just in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and indeavour of this
<pb facs="16"/> tumultuary Treatise, hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led up, and scribled out in great haste and heat of Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and Compassion (a paire of ill Speakers, as wee see in <hi>David,</hi> Psal. <hi>116.11.</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> Math. <hi>16.22.</hi>) for mine own<note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Antonin.</note>, and some few o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers support and solace, in the sad losse of our dearest friends, and sweetest chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by the last-yeares mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality. Since then, it fell (or ere I wist) into the hands of Authority, by meanes of such as ever-ween'd it: Being got abroad, how it will take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Many, I know not, feare not, force not<note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Hero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ot l. 7.</note>. Those that have a blemish in their eye, think the skie to be ever cloudy: and nothing's more common with weaker spirits,
<pb facs="16"/> than to be criticizing, and contending. The matter (I conceive) is sound and seaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable; much of it borrow'd from the best Authors I have met with; and I shame not, yee see, to professe by whom I have profited<note n="f" place="margin">Ingenuum est prositeri per quos pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feceris.</note>. Neither need I, when I call to mind, how the Prophet <hi>Zachary</hi> (as some will have it) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits to writing that which the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> had preached<note n="g" place="margin">Pareus in <hi>Math.</hi> 27.9.</note>; <hi>Obadiah</hi> (I am sure) that which the same <hi>Ieremy</hi> had penn'd, before them. S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Iude</hi> transcribes S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Peter</hi> in many things: S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Marke</hi> abbreviates the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Evangelists, but yet, ever with Vsury, as one speakes<note n="*" place="margin">The blessed Virgin hath much of her <hi>Magnificat</hi> out of <hi>Esay</hi> 29.</note>. <hi>Clemens Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrinus</hi> is call'd <hi>Contex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi>
      <note n="h" place="margin">Clem. Alex <hi>a</hi> Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>iedoro <hi>appellatur</hi> Contexter. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ste<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nol. <hi>p. 434.</hi>
      </note>,
<pb facs="17"/> and a latter man, <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mestor,</hi> for their often alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations and authorities<note n="i" place="margin">Ibid. <hi>p.</hi> 450.</note>. I will indeavour (saith <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> and I with him) out of other mens good Meditations and Collections, to frame to my selfe, with the busie Bee, some sweet Hony-comb of Truth, by mine owne art and industrie, in mine owne words and method<note n="k" place="margin">Enicar ut ex bene inventis, &amp; doctrinis altotum ego men verbis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>coordine, savum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quem verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, &amp;c. De la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>de sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ipt.</note>: and then be bold to say with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Omne meum, nihil meum</hi>
      <note n="l" place="margin">Macrob.</note>; All's mine, though 'twere none of it m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e. But something, I take it, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ave learn'd by the things I have suffer'd<note n="m" place="margin">
         <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.8.</note>. Affliction is a good helpe to experimen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ll knowledge<note n="n" place="margin">Zox practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca. <hi>Pareus.</hi>
      </note> as <hi>Job</hi> fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd it <hi>chap. 42.5.</hi> And there shall be onely feare, saith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,
<pb facs="17"/> to make you understand the hearing. <hi>Isay, 28.19.</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Nonn.</note>
      <hi>Vnderstand yee these things?</hi> saith our Saviour: <hi>yes. Therefore every Scribe that is instructed to the kingdome of God is like unto a housholder that thrusteth forth</hi>
      <note n="o" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>Math.</hi> 13.51, 52. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> (that is freely and fully im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth) <hi>out of his store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house</hi> (called here a <hi>treasu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> because we cast <hi>pearles</hi> afore men<note n="p" place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 7.6.</note>, if they be but as ready to take them as we to tender them) <hi>things both new and old:</hi> that is, not onely out of the New and Old testament (as sonne would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straine it) but new for the nice, and old for the stronger stomacke. A good stomacke, we see, falls to the same dish
<pb facs="18"/> oft and afresh, againe and againe, to day and to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and feeles no satiety, nor cries out, he is cloyed: No more doth a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian. And this meetes with those that demaund, <hi>what neede this waste after</hi> so much written already of the same subject<note n="*" place="margin">Quasi post Homerum Iliada.</note>? The Heathen answers: <hi>What forbids to say the same good things over once and againe</hi>
      <note n="q" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>;</note>? Our Saviour, I am sure, (in whose one exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is a globe of precepts) preacht the same thing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, and bad his disciples doe the like, that <hi>Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist</hi> had done before him<note n="r" place="margin">Quod uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>j per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penderent quib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> ade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> placent, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>id ab alijs didicisle vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deantur. <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes.</hi>
      </note> So he twice over, taught his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles the Lords prayer; nay, that whole sermon, as
<pb facs="18"/> some probably gather by the circumstances, as they are severally set downe by the two Evangelists<note n="s" place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 6. <hi>Luke</hi> 6.</note> And when at twice, he drove those mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny-merchants out of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he both times made use of the selfe-same allegations, and arguments<note n="t" place="margin">
         <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Marke</hi> 11.17.</note>. Most sure it is, that that can never be too much taught, that's ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver sufficiently learn'd<note n="*" place="margin">Nunquam satis dicitur quod nungaā satis discitur. <hi>Sen.</hi>
      </note>. And how others have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited in Afflictions Schoole<note n="u" place="margin">Schola cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, schola <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis.</note>, they can best tell: but for mine owne part; though I feare not lest <hi>while I preach to others, my selfe should be a castaway</hi>
      <note n="x" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. <hi>ult.</hi>
      </note>; Yet I have cause to feare lest some man say unto me, <hi>Physitian heale thy selfe:</hi> or twit me in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest (as one did <hi>Erasmus</hi> in
<pb facs="19"/> jest, touching his <hi>Enchiridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>) that there's more good sound in my booke, then in my bosom<note n="y" place="margin">Plus sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n onix con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spici in ipso libello quam in l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>belli au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thore. <hi>Eras.</hi>
      </note> The comfort is, I am chiefly to approve my selfe (and so art thou, <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>) to him that takes goates-haire from some hands as well as Iewells; and two mites from a meane body<note n="z" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>uc.</hi> 19 2. id est, irquit Sy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>us, duas octavas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e licet, oboli.</note> in as good part, as two millions from those that are more able. A female was allowed in peace offerings: to note, that a ready heart sets an high price with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>od upon a low p esent. <hi>Araunah</hi> was but a su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ject, yet because of that little he had, <hi>he gave like a King, 2 Sam. 24.23.</hi> his piety is renowned, and registred to all posterity, <hi>Zach. 9.7. Ekron</hi> (that is the barbarous
<pb facs="19"/> people of <hi>Palestina) shall be as the Iebusite:</hi> that is, as this famous proselyte <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunah,</hi> as <hi>Iunius</hi> interprets it. <hi>Saul</hi> had but five pence in his purse to give the Seer: the Seer, after much good cheare, gives him the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome<note n="a" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9 8. &amp; 10.1.</note>. Loe such is Gods dealing with the sonnes of men. Doth <hi>Iob</hi> serve God for nought? <hi>chap. 1.9.</hi> doth any so much as <hi>shut the doore or kindle a fire upon his altar for nought? Mal. 1.10.</hi> I trow not. God is a liberall paymaster, and all his retributions are more then bountifull. <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> the tyrant going upon Gods errand, shall have <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> as his pay, for his paines at <hi>Tyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Ezek.</hi> 29.18, 19.</note>. And <hi>Simon</hi> of
<pb facs="20"/>
      <hi>Cyrene,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.8.</note> with his two sonnes <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Rufus,</hi> have a naile and a name in Gods ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se better then of sonnes and of daughters<note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>Isa</hi> 56.5.</note>, for that involuntary service he did our Saviour, in carrying his crosse, <hi>Mar. 15.21</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Lege <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
               <desc>•••</desc>
            </gap>n</hi> ad locū. &amp; ad <hi>Act.</hi> 20 4. Nec illum tantùm sed filios ejus <hi>Rufum,</hi> &amp; <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrum</hi> ad Ecclesiam aggregatos &amp; inter discipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los probe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos. <hi>Luc.</hi> 23.26.</note>. How much more then will he gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciously accept, and liberally reward the small offerings of his weake servants, when he seeth them to proceede from great love? 'Tis of his owne alas that we give him, as <hi>David</hi> gladly acknowledgeth when the people had given their best<note n="e" place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.14.</note>. And what are we Ministers, but the voice of another that crieth<note n="f" place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 3.3.</note>, as <hi>Iohn Baptist:</hi> the pen in Gods hand as <hi>Moses,</hi> and the prophets, <hi>2 Pet. 1.2.</hi> vessels to beare
<pb facs="20"/> Gods name, as <hi>Paul,</hi> Act. <hi>9.15. Brethren</hi> (said hee, <hi>Act. 13.15.) if there be in you</hi> (as in so many vessels of honour, <hi>2 Cor. 4.7.) any word of exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, say on.</hi> Spirituall nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse is the next degree to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulnesse. If thou have not fine Manchet (said <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi> to <hi>Bradford</hi>) yet give the poore people Barly-bread, or whatsoever else the Lord hath put into thy hand<note n="g" place="margin">Fox Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrolog.</note>. Hee hath concredited unto us these precious talents, not to hide them, but to trade with them<note n="*" place="margin">Agricol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> è sterco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ibus quaestum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt, quantò magis in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciosis de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis nihil non exercendum?</note>: which if wee doe faithfully, ascribing all the gaine and glory to God, as those good Servants did, <hi>Luke 19.16.</hi> when they said; Not we, but <hi>thy talents
<pb facs="21"/> have gained other five,</hi> and other two, &amp;c. (which is pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallell to that of Saint <hi>Paul, Howbeit, not I, but the grace of God that was in mee, 1</hi> Cor. <hi>15.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>0.</hi>) hee will surely reward our labour of love,<note n="*" place="margin">Secundum labor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m, non secu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>dum proventum. <hi>Bern.</hi>
      </note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, not according to our accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the world which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>fiea little enough) but according to our honest in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour of serving the Lord Christ. Who will in that name▪ put upon us the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, <hi>Coloss. 4.24.</hi> and in that day meet us with an <hi>Euge bone serve,</hi> Well done <hi>good servant, thou hast beene faith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ull in a little,</hi> (so hee calls the largest mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure here, even ten talents, in comparison of that sarre
<pb facs="21"/> more exceeding and eternall waight<note n="h" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. Alludit ad Heb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> &amp; Chal leu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> nomen gloriae <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> came ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> hereafter) <hi>be thou master of much;</hi> whether five, or ten, or two Cities ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy proportion, and capacitie; besides, a lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesse of joy to boot; <hi>Enter into thy masters joy</hi>
      <note n="i" place="margin">
         <hi>Math</hi> 25.21 Non ita mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tales, <hi>Luc</hi> 17.7. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>raba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>us</hi> cum oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum fideliss: haberet, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e tamen tulit illum sibi h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re lem, libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rotum o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, conseri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendum. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, Ierobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amum, &amp;c.</hi>
      </note>. A joy more like the joy of God than of Man, a joy more meet for the master than for the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant; yet, such a master doe wee serve, as will crowne us with such a joy. Oh how should the serious considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hereof, fire up our hearts, and force open our eyes, to see with all Saints, what is the bredth, and length, and depth, and heighth; And to know the love of Christ, that passeth knowledge, that wee might be filled with all
<pb facs="22"/> the fulnesse of God<note n="k" place="margin">
         <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.18, 19.</note>! But I must contract, for if a great booke be a great vill<note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Callimachus apud Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naum.</note> (as he said once) how much more a long Preface to a little book? I shall therfore suddenly shut up with the same Apostle, in the words next following those afore cited: <hi>Now, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him that is able to doe exceeding abundantly, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all that wee aske or thinke, according to the power that worketh in us; Vnto him be glory in the Church, by Christ Jesus, throughout all ages, world without end</hi>
      <note n="l" place="margin">ver. 20.21.</note>. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>