<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his honest friend Iohn Taylor, Poeta Nascitur.</title>
           <author>Jones, Sa.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118233_Fr1_4_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13479</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23779</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118233</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his honest friend Iohn Taylor, Poeta Nascitur.</title>
                 <author>Jones, Sa.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The nipping and snipping of abuses: or The woolgathering of vvitte : With the Muses Taylor, brought from Parnassus by land, with a paire of oares wherein are aboue a hundred seuerall garments of diuers fashions, made by nature, without the helpe of art, and a proclamation from hell in the Deuils name, concerning the propogation, and excessiue vse of tobacco. By Iohn Taylor</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <head>To his honest friend <hi>Iohn Taylor, Poeta Nascitur.</hi>
   </head>
   <lg>
      <l>I Oft (with other men) haue wondred why</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Horace</hi> should write an Art of Poetry:</l>
      <l>Since all men know, a Poets borne a Poet,</l>
      <l>And no man's borne an Artist: all men know it:</l>
      <l>And knowing this, I wonder who should scorne</l>
      <l>A Poet without Art, that so was borne.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Who thinks thy name, or watry education,</l>
      <l>Is to thy verses any derogation,</l>
      <l>Is far deceiu'd in both, for all men kno,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Taylors</hi> are makers, Poets all are so.</l>
      <l>Nor i'st thy education thee abuses.</l>
      <l>T'as brought thee vp a <hi>Taylor</hi> for the Muses.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>I could Apollogize, but thou hast don't</l>
      <l>If Poets borne haue glory, thou hast won't:</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="4"/>Thou hast describ'd the seuerall signes of Heauen,</l>
      <l>Wherein the sunnes whole Progresse is made euen.</l>
      <l>Thy Epigrams; and Anagrams of late</l>
      <l>Are Philomels sweet notes, let Parrats prate.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>I dare compare thy Genius with some men</l>
      <l>That vaunt in <hi>Tempe's</hi> well t' haue dipt their pen:</l>
      <l>For (truly) they do falsly steale translations,</l>
      <l>And speake in our tongue things of other Nations.</l>
      <l>Thy Oares and Sculls hath far out row'd their fames</l>
      <l>For thou hast row'd from <hi>Hellicon,</hi> to <hi>Thames.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Let them vpbraide thee with a Scullers name,</l>
      <l>And with that title thinke t' obscure thy fame:</l>
      <l>They cannot <hi>Iack</hi> for Marriners at seas</l>
      <l>Take paines, whilst passengers do sit at ease.</l>
      <l>Thy owne true labour tugs thy verse a shore,</l>
      <l>Though fooles in each mans boate will haue an Oare.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <salute>Thine, whether thou wilt or no.</salute>
      <signed>Sa: Iones.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>