<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118208_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19266</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5681</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118208</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true and most dreadfull discourse of a woman possessed with the Deuill : who in the likenesse of a headlesse beare fetched her out of her bedd, and in the presence of seuen persons, most straungely roulled her thorow three chambers, and doune a high paire of staiers, on the fower and twentie of May last. 1584. At Dichet in Sommersetshire. A matter as miraculous as euer was seen in our time</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Nelson, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   
   <pb facs="2"/>
   
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloued and curtious rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, we haue to consider by this strange discourse, how redy Sathan is to take hold on vs if we fall from God neuer so little. He cōtinually runneth vp and downe seeking whom he may deuour: But notwithstandyng his temptations which are great, the mercie of God is greater, who neuer faileth to send comfort in temptation, if we accept thereof.</p>
   <p>Great are the examples, both of Gods mercy and might, to put vs in remembrance of our sinnes which are infinite and lothsome, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in if we continue, let vs vndoubtledly looke for the reward thereof, which is an euerlasting destruction both of bodie and soule.</p>
   <p>Let not this which is here declared seeme a fained fable vnto thee, but assure thy selfe that all such thinges are sent as warnignes for our wickednesse: and to put vs in mynd of the
<pb facs="3"/>
      staie of our saluation, which is an assured faith in Christ Iesus: from which piller if wee once shrinke, the Tempter is redie to driue vs in to dispaier of Gods mercie.</p>
   <p>Many are the woonders which hath lately happened, as of suddaine and straunge death vpon periured persons, straunge sights in the Aier, straunge birthes on the Earth: Earth quakes, commetts and fiery Impressions, and all to put vs in mynde of God, whose woorkes are wonderfull.</p>
   <p>Remember the late storme of haylstones in which many thinges were slaine and beaten to to the ground, which Hailestones were equall in greatnesse to a Goose Egge, of eight inches about.</p>
   <p>These and suche like examples (good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) warneth vs to be watchfull for the day of the Lorde which is at hand, least sodainly his wrath be kindled against vs. Let vs therefore pray to almightie God to hold backe his Rod, to be mercifull to vs, and to forgiue vs all that is past: that through the assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staunce of his Spirite, we maie with penitent hartes liue in his feare to our liues ende.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>