<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Abbot, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118749_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02764</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12894</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118749</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Abbot, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The examinations, arraignment &amp; conuiction of George Sprot, notary in Aye-mouth : together with his constant and extraordinarie behauiour at his death, in Edenborough, Aug. 12. 1608. Written &amp; set forth by Sir William Hart, Knight, L. Iustice of Scotland. Whereby appearet the treasonable deuice betwixt Iohn late Earle of Gowry and Robert Logane of Restalrig (commonly called Lesterig) plotted by them for the cruell murthering of our most gracious Souereigne. Before which treatise is prefixed also a preface, written by G. Abbot Doctour of Diuinitie, and Deane of Winchester, who was present at the sayd Sprots execution</title>
                 <author>Hart, William, Sir, Lord Justice of Scotland</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bradwood, Melchisidec</publisher>
                    <distributor>Aspley, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 60, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="1" facs="2"/>
   <head>A PREFACE to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong those troubles &amp; cros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, wherewithall our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie Father is pleased to exercise his best children, while they remaine in this Tabernacle of their flesh, there is no one more frequent, than such e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and slanderous reports, as the virulent tongues of malicious persons, out of a ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to their vertues, are desirous to lay vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. For there was neuer Age nor Countrey, wherein either man or woman was adorned with rare and eminent quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, for the seruice of God, and aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of true religion, but immediatly such as were ill-affected began to imploy their wits, and beat their braines, how by calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niation
<pb n="2" facs="3"/>
and forged imputations, they might obscure the lustre of those singular parts, which their quicke but enuious eye had dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered in them. That worthy <hi>Moyses</hi> the meekest <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Num.</hi> 12.3.</note> man vpon earth is reproched as ambitious, and charged by <hi>Core,</hi> to <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Num.</hi> 16.3.</note>
      <hi>take too much vpon him.</hi> That admirable <hi>Daniel</hi> was <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.13.</note> accused to the King as a contemner of his Greatnesse, and violater of his Lawes. It was obiected to zealous and iust <hi>Nehemiah</hi> by <note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>Neh.</hi> 6.6.</note>
      <hi>Sanballat,</hi> that himselfe and the people of <hi>Iuda</hi> intended a rebellion. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> two great instruments of Gods glory, were complained vpon as seditious persons, and <note n="e" place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 16.20.</note> disturbers of the peace and quietnesse of the city. The old Christians, men no doubt of vertuous behauiour, yet because in time of persecution they assembled themselues together in the night, for the worship of their God, and profession of their faith, were reported by the Gentiles to haue the Feasts of <note n="f" place="margin">
         <hi>Euseb. Eccl. Hist. lib.</hi> 4.7.</note>
      <hi>Thyestes,</hi> (that is, to eat the flesh of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren) and to do as <hi>Oedipus</hi> did, that is, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miscuously to commit fornication with their mothers, sisters and daughters. Yea, their owne <note n="g" place="margin">
         <hi>Lib.</hi> 5.1.</note> seruants were brought by the
<pb n="3" facs="3"/>
terrours of the Infidels to accuse them of such crimes. <hi>Tertullian</hi> complaineth of this, declaring that it was obiected to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians; <note n="h" place="margin">
         <hi>Tertull. Apolog. cap.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>that they killed a babe new borne, and in the blood thereof did dip their Eucharist,</hi> and so eat it; as also, <hi>that suffering their dogs of purpose to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerturne their lights, they</hi> in the darke <hi>committed incest with their mothers and daughters.</hi> Hence it grew, as a kinde of Prouerbe, That it was the part of Christians to doe good, and yet to be ill spoken of. So <note n="i" place="margin">
         <hi>Euagrius Eccl. Hist. lib.</hi> 3.40.</note>
      <hi>Euagrius</hi> reporteth, touching that holy and blessed Emperour <hi>Constantine the Great,</hi> that the Ethnicks laded him with many false criminations:, because he tooke away their Heathenish superstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and in place thereof aduanced the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of Christ Iesus.</p>
   <p>In all which accusations, and other of like nature, (if we looke aduisedly into them) we shall perceiue, that both Sathan hath his worke, and euill men haue a part, yea that God himselfe hath a finger. Sathan hath his worke, because (as <hi>Cyprian</hi> writing of <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> saith) <hi>It is</hi>
      <note n="k" place="margin">
         <hi>Cyprian. Epist. ad Antonian. Lib.</hi> 4.2.</note>
      <hi>euermore the worke of the Diuell, that he may with lies <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eare the seruants of God, and by false opinions spread concerning them may defame
<pb n="4" facs="4"/>
their glorious name; that such as are bright in the light of their owne conscience may be sordidated,</hi> or dimmed, <hi>by the reports of other.</hi> Euill men haue their part, either because with <hi>Zoilus,</hi> when <hi>they</hi>
      <note n="l" place="margin">
         <hi>Aelian. Hist. lib.</hi> 11.10.</note>
      <hi>can do not hurt</hi> to the good and vertuous, <hi>at least they will speake ill of them;</hi> or els, because (as <hi>Hierome</hi> writeth) <note n="m" place="margin">
         <hi>Hieron. Epist.</hi> 10. <hi>ad Furiam.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>It is the solace of euill men to carpe at the good, thinking that by the great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of offenders the guilt of their faults is diminished and abated.</hi> Nay, God hath a finger in it, to trie &amp; sharpen men, and by that meanes to fit them to himselfe. For slanders haue that force in them, as <hi>Gregory</hi> well noteth, speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus: <note n="n" place="margin">
         <hi>Gregor. Hom.</hi> 38. <hi>in</hi> 40. <hi>Hom.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Going thorow almost all examples, we finde, that there hath not beene one good man whom the naughtinesse of euill men hath not tried: for, that I may so speake, the sword of our soule is not brought to the exactnesse of sharpnesse, if the file of other mens naughtinesse hath not rubbed and fretted it.</hi> Againe, in as much as we should grow into deepe and dangerous securitie, if it were not for such remembrances, our heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is contented that by such calumniations we should be rowzed from the sleepinesse and drowzinesse of the world. <note n="o" place="margin">
         <hi>Plin Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Hist. lib.</hi> 8 16.</note>
      <hi>Pliny</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that the Lion is subiect to no sicknesse,
<pb n="5" facs="4"/>
but only a <hi>fastidium,</hi> or fulnesse of stomacke: wherewithall when hee is oppressed, the way to cure him is to offer him some con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumely; which is by tying an Ape neere him: for the Lion is so moued and vexed for the time, with the tricks which the Ape plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that he riddeth and putteth ouer that, which so much before offended him. Euen so God vseth the contumelies of base per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, &amp; the reproches of the vilest, to rowze vp men of excellent spirits, that they surfet not in voluptuousnesse, and so consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be lulled asleepe in idle securitie, to their owne harme and peraduenture ruine.</p>
   <p>But be it for one or all these reasons, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it is, that in our age as well as in times by-past, the deerest children of God haue tasted of this triall, and haue been forced to endure very horrible imputations &amp; staining aspersions, which the venomous tongues of vngodly men haue striued to cast vpon them. It were no hard matter to name very strange calumniations which haue been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented by the vassals of Antichrist, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished by the adorers of the beast in diuers books (which are no better than defamatory
<pb n="6" facs="5"/>
libels) against Gods seruants of the highest ranke vpon earth, because they ouer-turned the strong holds of idolatry, and gaue free passage to the Gospell of Christ Iesus. But I forbeare to giue such particular instances, and rather leaue to the consideration of the wise, whether it may euer be hoped, that such irreligious creatures (who haue solde themselues to Sathan the accuser of the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) will make spare to lash and scourge such single persons as stand in their way, &amp; hinder their designes; when they make no conscience to brand our holy faith, and the generalitie of our profession, with reports most odious, and such as must needs be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged for abominable, if they should be true: but in sooth are in the sight of God, of Angels and men, before heauen &amp; earth▪ but plaine fictions and forgeries, conteining in them no parcell of veritie. Of which sort are those defamations▪ which a countryman of ours, without all shame, auoucheth in a <note n="p" place="margin">Certaine Articles or forcible rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons printed at <hi>Antwerpe</hi> 1600:</note> Pamphlet not long since put out, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished to the world; <hi>That the Protestants are bound in conscience, neuer to aske God forgiuenesse of their sinnes: That the Protestants are bound in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science
<pb n="7" facs="5"/>
to auoid all good works: That the Protestants make God the author of sinne; the only cause of sinne: that man sinneth not; that God is worse than the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell.</hi> And that of <note n="q" place="margin">
         <hi>Ross. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Henri<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. Gallum. cap.</hi> 4.5.</note>
      <hi>Rosseus</hi> writing against the French King now reigning: <hi>Hominum animas cum corporibus interire, &amp; homines a brutis pecori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus nihil differre, Euangelicorum infinita millia cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt. Infinite thousands of Protestants doe beleeue that the soules of men die together with their bodies, and that men do nothing differ from brute beasts.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Such truthlesse, shamelesse, and gracelesse assertions they haue not sticked to proclame openly in the face of the Sunne. The know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge whereof should cause all men indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently affected, not to be credulous or light of beleefe, when they finde gall and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse cast out of the mouth or penne of an enemy of the Gospell against any contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the truth, though it be but a priuate man; but especially to suspend their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, when persons of highest quality, for maintaining Gods cause, are traduced by an enemy, or defamed by some vile one, whose tongue and pen indeed is no slander, as we commonly speake. For these great ones are the special marke whereat malice doth aime;
<pb n="8" facs="6"/>
and as poison ordinarily hasteneth to the heart, so doth enuie let driue at the head, at those who be most eminent in the State and Common-wealth. When <hi>Cato</hi> the elder li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, there was not in all <hi>Rome</hi> so woorthy a man as he: for (as <note n="r" place="margin">
         <hi>Plin. Na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tur. Hist. lib.</hi> 7.27.</note>
      <hi>Pliny</hi> noteth) he was <hi>the best Orator, the best Leader or Generall in the field, the best Senatour or Counseller</hi> that was in that Citie: yet was he so intreated as neuer man was, being publikely called to his answer foure and fortie seuerall times, whereby one while his fame was hazarded, another while his life: and yet alwayes he was honorably, or as the yoonger <hi>Pliny</hi> hath it, <note n="s" place="margin">
         <hi>Plin. de viris illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strib.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>gloriously</hi> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solued and acquited. Doubtlesse there was against him a great deale of spleene, a very great deale of malice. From the touch wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, euen Kings and Princes are so farre from being free, that they are more subiect to it than any other persons: which made <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Diog. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ert. in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisth.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisthenes</hi> to say, <hi>That it was a Kingly thing, when thou hast done wel, to be ill spoken of</hi> for thy labor. And if we be desirous to see a famous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of this, there is no one more notable than that of holy <hi>Dauid,</hi> who being first a Prophet, and afterwards a King, (but in both
<pb n="9" facs="6"/>
most vnspotted touching the crimes layd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him) yea being a man after Gods own heart, yet was accused and charged with many hainous iniquities; which caused him to complaine both before and after his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the Crowne: as vnto <hi>Saul</hi>: <note n="t" place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.10.</note>
      <hi>VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore giuest thou an eare vnto mens words, that say: Beholde, Dauid seeketh euill against thee?</hi> And to God himselfe: <hi>O</hi>
      <note n="u" place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 7.3.</note>
      <hi>Lord my God, if I haue done this thing,</hi> meaning, which they layd vnto him; <hi>if there be any wickednesse in my hands,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending, such as they would fasten vpon him, <hi>then let the enemie persecute my soule and take it.</hi> And in another place, speaking to the slandering Aduersarie, <hi>Thy</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 52.2.</note>
      <hi>tongue imagineth mischiefe, and is like a sharpe razor that cutteth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully.</hi> And yet further: <hi>The</hi>
      <note n="x" place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.69.</note>
      <hi>proud haue ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined a lie against me.</hi> So in the next Psalme: <note n="y" place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 120.2.</note>
      <hi>Deliuer my soule O Lord from lying lips, and from a deceitfull tongue.</hi> These things, and that the <note n="z" place="margin">
         <hi>Psal</hi> 69.12.</note> drunkards did make songs vpon him, did many times exceedingly grieue him, that he who laboured to seeme innocent, should be reproched as nocent; that he who was but the Patient, should be held for the Agent; that the man wronged, should be reported
<pb n="10" facs="7"/>
to do wrong vnto other; that he whose life was sought, should be termed by <hi>Shimei,</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7.</note>
      <hi>a man of blood, and a murtherer.</hi> This troubled &amp; grieued him aboue measure. For it is the property of innocency and integritie, that if it may finde no other reward, yet it would gladly shine in the simplicitie and sinceritie of it selfe. But when there was no other helpe to be freed from those slanders, <hi>Dauid</hi> had one assured remedie; that was, to retire himselfe to the Lord, &amp; commend his cause to his Maker: As he excellently doth in the three and fortieth Psalme, where being op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed by the malice of his aduersaries, and complaining of it in the first verse: <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 43.1.</note>
      <hi>Iudge me O God, and defend my cause against the vnmercifull people: deliuer me from the deceitfull &amp; wicked man,</hi> he helpeth himselfe in the last verse, rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the impatiency which he found in his owne soule, and directing his affections vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another course, <note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>vers.</hi> 5.</note>
      <hi>VVhy art thou cast downe my soule? and why art thou disquieted within me? wait on God: for I will yet giue him thanks: he is my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent helpe and my God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Many men haue been desirous to haue their fame cleered from the reproches of
<pb n="11" facs="7"/>
their enemies, and haue sought meanes to haue their hearts eased from the disturban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and distempers whereinto false accusati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons haue put them. <hi>Zeno</hi> is much commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that with such calmnesse he could turne aside those bitter taunts which some bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on him: for being asked, how he did bear himselfe against euil speeches: <note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>Diog. La▪ ert. in Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>I do,</hi> saith he, <hi>as if an Embassadour should be sent vnto me, and I should returne him without an answer.</hi> This for a Philosopher, who was but an heathen man, was an excellent resolution. But in these words of <hi>Dauid,</hi> there is a way more noble than <hi>Zeno</hi> could conceiue; that is, to looke vp to our great God, and commit all to him, expecting his good leasure. It is not enough when a man being priuy to his owne inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie doth not boile within himselfe, or fret against the wicked (which are things <note n="e" place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 37.1.</note> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden vnto vs) but he must goe a step far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and propose to his owne heart some more notable example. And in this case who is rather to be imitated by a Christian, than our Sauior Chirst? Concerning whom <hi>S. Chrysostome</hi> said well: That <note n="f" place="margin">
         <hi>Chrys Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil.</hi> 1. <hi>de in<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
               <desc>••••</desc>
            </gap>treh. Dei natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>when he cast out diuels, and did innumerable good things, and yet was
<pb n="12" facs="8"/>
ill spoken of; against those men who said, that he had the Diuell, he did not send any thunderbolt, he did not ouerthrow those blasphemous mouthes, he consumed not with fire those vnchaste, vngratefull, vnworthie tongues of theirs: but only with these words put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side those euill speeches; I haue not the Diuell, but I honour him who sent me.</hi> This is most truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated of our Sauiour: but there was in him somewhat els, which is better obserued by <hi>S. Peter:</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.23.</note>
      <hi>VVhen he was reuiled, he reuiled not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; when he suffered, he threatened not, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted it to him that iudgeth righteously.</hi> And this, committing it to him that iudgeth righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously, was the course which Dauid vsed: to wait patiently on the Lord, to cast vp his eies to heauen, and commending to God the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of his waies, to leaue all to his dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing. And this is the very Lesson which hee teacheth both himselfe and other. For in the seuen and twentieth Psalme, hauing spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of his <note n="h" place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 27.12.14.</note> aduersaries, of false witnesses which rose vp against him, and such as speak cruelly, he concludeth with this document, <hi>Hope in the Lord; bee strong, and hee shall comfort thine heart, and trust in the Lord.</hi> Which is the most sound instruction, that any creature
<pb n="13" facs="8"/>
can haue: to looke vp to his Creator (to whom all hearts are open, and no priuie thing can be secret) and to commend to his prouidence, to his fatherly care and wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the vnspottednesse of his waies, and the simplicity of his conuersation. And as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suredly that God who is the God of truth, will bee the patron and protectour of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie in his seruants. It is a strong conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation which Dauid giueth in this case; <note n="i" place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 37.5.6.</note>
      <hi>Commit thy way vnto the Lord, and trust in him, and he shall bring it to passe. And hee shall bring foorth thy righteousnesse as the light, and thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as the noone day.</hi> But it followeth: <hi>Wait patiently vpon the Lord, and hope in him</hi>: As if that must bee the meanes to attaine thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire: not to run before thy Maker, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point him the time when thy integrity shall bee cleered, and the dimming clouds of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie shall be blowen from thy estimation; but to leaue that to his managing, to his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spose and direction. For as <hi>S. Chrysostome</hi> telleth vs; <note n="k" place="margin">
         <hi>Chrys. in Psal.</hi> 129.</note>
      <hi>If it be in the power of God to giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, it is also in his power to giue when himselfe pleaseth.</hi> It is said of him, that hee doth all things in <note n="l" place="margin">
         <hi>Sapient.</hi> 11.17.</note>
      <hi>measure, number and waight.</hi> But if
<pb n="14" facs="9"/>
before the number bee full, or the measure be vp, thou wilt limit him the time when thy innocencie must appeare: thou takest on thee to be wiser than the Lord, and in a sort mounting vp into his throne in heauen, thou doest iustle him out of his seat of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty and eternity. If thou wilt set downe the decree for time or place, or the maner of purging thy selfe, or how the wickednes of thine enemies must be displaied, thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kest thy selfe the Iudge, and the Lord of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth shall be but thy executioner. Leaue the maine then to him (which doth not fore-close thee, but that thou mayst vse all honest meanes to lay open thy vnspot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tednesse) and thou shalt haue reason with <hi>Dauid</hi> to thanke him, and say: <note n="m" place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 43.5.</note>
      <hi>He is my present helpe and my God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And in truth it is strange to see the Lords worke in this behalfe, how, when the fame of his seruants hath beene vniustly denigra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by false accusations, hee taking the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into his hands hath in his good time dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled all mists of slander. Heereof <hi>Dauid</hi> himselfe had singular experience. For when <hi>Saul</hi> was informed that <hi>Dauid</hi> sought his life,
<pb n="15" facs="9"/>
and by the often ingeminations of maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men this was taken for a truth, and <hi>Dauid</hi> was accordingly persecuted, and in danger to be murdered, God put <hi>Saul</hi>
      <note n="n" place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.4. <hi>c.</hi> 26.7.</note> two seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall times into the hands of <hi>Dauid,</hi> that easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hee might haue slaine him: which being entertained as an inuincible argument of <hi>Dauids</hi> fidelity, <hi>Saul</hi> himselfe by the irrefra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable euidence of truth was forced to crie out, <note n="o" place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.18.</note>
      <hi>Thou art more righteous than I: for thou hast rendered me good, and I haue rendered thee euill.</hi> And a second time: <note n="p" place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.21.</note>
      <hi>I haue sinned: come againe my sonne Dauid, for I will doe thee no more harme, because my soule was precious in thine eies this day: behold I haue done foolishly, and haue erred excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. Eusebius</hi> hath such another example, of <note n="q" place="margin">
         <hi>Euseb. Ecel. Hist. lib.</hi> 6.8.</note>
      <hi>Narcissus</hi> the Bishop of <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> who was a vertuous and worthy man, and yet by three persons was accused of a hainous crime. The story doth not cleerely deliuer what it was: but by circumstances it may be gathered to bee incontinency. These three to giue the more reputation to that accusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherewithall they charged him, did vse diuers imprecations and execrations on themselues, if those things were not true
<pb n="16" facs="10"/>
which they obiected against him. As the one wished that himselfe might be burnt, the second that he might die of a loathsome disease, the third that he might lose the sight of his eyes. This constant and consenting crimination so affected <hi>Narcissus,</hi> though priuy to his own vprightnesse, that he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew himselfe from his abode, and liuing priuately commended his righteous cause to God: which had such effect, that not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry long after, the first of his accusers was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed consumed with fire, the house being burnt in which he remained: the second di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the same disease which he wished vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himselfe: and the third being much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted with the punishment of his fellows, had remorse of his sinne, and came and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly acknowledged the conspiracy of them three against innocent <hi>Narcissus</hi>: but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, he had such feeling of his owne iniquity, that powring out continuall teares, hee lost the sight of his eyes with the rheume that descended. A most memorable narration to their comfort, who, being wronged by men in their fame or good name, commend their cause to God. Like to which is that of
<note n="r" place="margin">
         <pb n="17" facs="10"/>
         <hi>Theodor. Eccl. Hist. lib.</hi> 1.20.21.</note>
      <hi>Theodoret,</hi> who reporteth, that <hi>Eustathius</hi> the Patriarke of <hi>Antioch</hi> had many combats with the <hi>Arrians</hi> for defence of Christs truth: and when he still preuailed against them, they out of their malice suborned a harlot to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse him of fornication, and openly to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that a childe was his which she held in her armes: by which meanes hee was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained to flie to the same succour that <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cissus</hi> formerly had done; which had such force with Almighty God, that within a while after the harlot was stricken with a grieuous sicknesse, which wrought in her so powerfully, that shee freely confessed the combination of the <hi>Arrians</hi> against the holy man: and how shee was suborned to accuse him wrongfully, whereof she was now sory. But whereas she had said that <hi>Eustathius</hi> was the father of her childe; that indeed was true of another <hi>Eustathius,</hi> but not of the Bishop of <hi>Antioch.</hi> Wherein we may beholde, that euen so long agone Equiuocation was in vse, but it was with leaud persons, as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes and harlots: but withall Gods worke appeareth, that he will not euermore suffer innocencie to be oppressed, and truth to be
<pb n="18" facs="11"/>
wronged; but at the last veritie shall breake forth, as the Sunne which was darkned with a cloud. And this mercifull fauor of God to his seruants was not onely in the ages past, but our dayes haue experiments of the very like occurrents; as in a famous case lately a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted at <hi>Edenborough</hi> may sensibly be discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: whereof, because I was an eye-witnesse at my late being there by the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Maiestie, I haue thought it my dutie, in honor to God and loue to his truth, to declare what I saw and heard; that this following Treatise penned by an honorable personage of <hi>North-Britaine</hi> might not goe forth vnaccompanied with the Declaration of one of <hi>South-Britaine,</hi> for so much as hee beheld.</p>
   <p>There are few in this Iland of any vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, but haue heard of the traiterous and bloodie attempt of the Earle <hi>Gowrie</hi> and his brother against the person and life of our most blessed Souereigne. Wherein albeit there were such euidences and arguments, as that any man who would haue taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice thereof, might haue been sufficiently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed therein euen at the very first▪ and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward
<pb n="19" facs="11"/>
by the cleere depositions (for most pregnant circumstances) and ample attesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of many persons of honour and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the Parliament of that Kingdome tooke full knowledge thereof, and accordingly proceeded to the forfaiting of the whole e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state of that Earle, and of his heires for euer: yet some humorous men, whom in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect I may iustly terme vnthankfull vnto God, and vndutifull to their King, out of fond imaginations, or rather, if you will, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious suppositions of their owne, did both at home and abroad, by whisperings and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret buzzings into the eares of the people (who were better perswaded of them than indeed there was cause) imploy their wits and tongues to obscure the trueth of that matter, and to cast an imputation where it was least deserued. Which when God had permitted for the space of some yeeres to ranckle and foster in the bowels of those who were the Authours of it; the same God in his wisdome at last meaning to cure them if they would be cured of that maladie, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, that in the same treason, although caried neuer so secretly, there were other
<pb n="20" facs="12"/>
confederates, of whom hitherto the world had taken no kinde of knowledge. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit two of the persons interested in that bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesse were lately dead, and departed vnto far greater torment than all the earth could lay vpon them (vnlesse they died repentant) yet it was apprehended that a third partie remained, who had fore-knowledge of that conspiracie, and was able to vtter much of the secrets of it; one <hi>George Sprot,</hi> a Notarie inhabiting at <hi>Aye-mouth,</hi> a place well knowen in that countrey. Which matter, or some part thereof, being made knowen to an <note n="s" place="margin">The Earle of <hi>Dunbar.</hi>
      </note> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable person, a most faithfull seruant to his Maiestie, first by some words that fell from <hi>Sprot</hi> himselfe, and afterwards by some papers found vpon him, it was so wisely ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and so prudently brought about, by the great care and diligence of that noble man (God Almightie blessing the businesse) that so much was reueiled as followeth in this Treatise, vpon the Acts to be seene; which are here set downe at large, word for word as they agree with the processe origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and other examinations, that such as haue beene auerse may at last receiue satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.
<pb n="21" facs="12"/>
Touching all which, I shall say no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but only report that which befell vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the day of his death, when hee suffered for that treason. Hauing then the sentence passed on him vpon Friday the twelfth of August 1608 in the fore-noone, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely being warned to prepare himselfe to his end, which must be that after-dinner, he most willingly submitted himselfe vnto that punishment, which (as he then acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged) he had iustly deserued. And being left to himselfe til dinner-time was expired, then came to him into that priuate place where hee remained, some of the <note n="*" place="margin">Archb. of <hi>Glasc.</hi> Bis. of <hi>Brickh. L. Halyrudeh. L. Collector. L. Register. L. Iustice. D Maxey. M Hodson. M. P. Galo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. M. I. Hall. N. Ch. Lums<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> with others.</note> reuerend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, diuers L.L. of the Session, two of the English Ministers there imploied by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, with diuers other Ministers of the towne of <hi>Edenborough.</hi> Before whom he first acknowledged and auouched his former confession to be true, and that he would die in the same; and then falling on his knees in a corner of that roome, where he and they then were, in a prayer to God vttered aloud he so passionately deplored his former wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednesses, but especially that sinne of his for which he was to die; that a man may iustly
<pb n="22" facs="13"/>
say, hee did in a sort deiect and cast downe himselfe to the gates of hell, as if he should there haue beene swallowed vp in the gulfe of desperation: yet presently laying holde vpon the mercies of God in Christ, he raised himselfe, and strangely lifted vp his soule vnto the Throne of Grace, applying ioy and comfort to his owne heart so effectually, as can not well be described. In the admitting of this consolation into his inward man, he burst out into teares, so plentifully flowing from him, that for a time they stopped his voice. The sight &amp; hearing wherof wroght so forcible an impression in those persons of honour and learned men who beheld him, that there was scant any one of them, who could refraine teares in the place, as diuers of themselues that day did witnesse vnto me. The effect of his prayer was the aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uating of his crime in concealing the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son against the Kings Maiestie; into which, hee said, <hi>God did most iustly suffer him to fall, by reason of his former wickednesse which he had so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperately multiplied in despight of God and his holy VVord.</hi> And thereupon going on with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny sensible speeches and most feeling com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parisons,
<pb n="23" facs="13"/>
hee insisted on the fearefull and dreadfull danger wherein hee was, if the Lord in iudgement should looke vpon him. Notwithstanding, at last he proceeded: <hi>Yet most mercifull father,</hi> whereat he made a stay, and repeating the word <hi>father</hi> with a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous loud and shrill voice, he added, <hi>why should I call thee father, that haue so many wayes and so horribly transgressed thy commandements, in all the course of my life, but especially in concealing this vile, fearefull and diuellish treason against my most gracious Soueraigne? Lord, Lord, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing belongeth to me but wrath and confusion:</hi> and so went on in a strange vnaffected current of words, liuely expressing the sorrow of his heart. Yet there he stayd not, but spake for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to this purpose: <hi>Notwithstanding, Lord thou hast left me this comfort in thy VVord, that thou hast sayd, Come vnto me all ye that are weary and laden, and I will refresh you. Lord I am weary, Lord I am heauily laden with my sinnes, which are innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable: I am ready to sincke Lord euen to hell, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thou in thy mercy put to thy hand and deliuer me. Lord thou hast promised by thine owne word, out of thine owne mouth, that thou wilt refresh the weary soule.</hi> And with that he thrust out one of his
<pb n="24" facs="14"/>
hands, and reaching as high as hee could, with a louder voice and a strained, cried, <hi>I challenge thee Lord, by that word, and by that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise which thou hast made, that thou performe and make it good to mee, that call for ease and mercie at thy hands. Lord heare mee, Lord pardon mee, Lord comfort me by thy holy spirit: assure my conscience of the forgiuenesse of my sinnes, &amp; say to my soule, that thou art reconciled.</hi> And so after many zealous petitions vttered to the like effect, he appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to himselfe the mercies of God in Christ Iesus, in whom he assured himselfe of Gods fauour, with earnest request, that he might continue in that assurance to the end, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he nothing doubted.</p>
   <p>Afterward, being brought to the scaffold, where he was to die, he vttered many things, among which I obserued these: <hi>He acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to the people, that he was come thither to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer most deseruedly; That hee had beene an offender against Almightie God in very many respects; But that none of his sinnes was so grieuous vnto him, as that for which he must die: wherin, notwithstanding he was not an Actor, but a Concealer only. That he was ingyred in it by the Laird of</hi> Rastalrig <hi>and his seruant the Laird of</hi> Bour, <hi>both which,</hi> hee sayd,
<pb n="25" facs="14"/>
were men <hi>that professed not religion.</hi> Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he exhorted men <hi>to take heed how they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with such as are not religious; because,</hi> sayd he, <hi>with such as make not profession of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there is no faith, no trueth, no holding of their word, as himselfe had tried and found.</hi> But tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the treason for the concealing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he was condemned, he added, <hi>That he was preserued aliue to open that secret mysterie which so long had layen hidde; That God had kept him since that attempt of the Earle</hi> Gowrie <hi>from very manie dangers, but notedly from one, when being in appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent hazzard of drowning, he was strangely deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: which,</hi> said he, <hi>was Gods worke, that I might remaine aliue vnto this happie and blessed day, that the trueth might be made knowen. And now I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse my fault to the shame of my selfe, and to the shame of the Diuell; but to the glorie of God. And I doe it not either for feare of death, or for any hope of life, (for I haue deserued to die, and am vnworthie to liue) but because it is the trueth, which I shall seale with my blood. My fault,</hi> sayth hee, <hi>is so great, that if I had a thousand liues, and could die ten thousand deaths, yet I might not make satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that I should conceale such a treason against so gracious a King.</hi> These and the like words,
<pb n="26" facs="15"/>
when hee had spoken vpon one side of the scaffold, hee turned him to the second side, and afterward to the third, (that all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple might heare) where he spake to the same purpose as formerly he had done. And here it may not be forgotten, that in the vttering of these things his tongue serued him verie well, with words readie and significant, his memorie was perfect, his countenance rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonably erect and full of alacritie, without all feare of death, his voice was loud and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible on euery part: which was the more strange, because at the times of his examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as also that very fore-noone, at the houre of his arraignment, his speech was low and weake; but now so strong, as if God of purpose had giuen him power to deliuer his words in such a maner, that all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple might heare and vnderstand.</p>
   <p>When this aboue-mentioned declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had beene made, <hi>Sprot</hi> returned to that part of the scaffold where he first began to speake, and there falling on his knees, he vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered a prayer to the same purpose as is set down in this ensuing Treatise. And hauing ended the same, one of the Ministers praied
<pb n="27" facs="15"/>
againe, and the prisoner ioyned with him, <hi>That God would forgiue his sinnes, and receiue his soule to mercie.</hi> After which, <hi>Sprot</hi> standing vp made diuers requests: First that what he had deliuered by this Confession on the scaffold, might be put into his Processe, that the world might take notice of it. Secondly, that such as were present (as they might haue opportunity) would be suters vnto the King, that his Maiestie would forgiue him this offence, for the which, he sayd, <hi>he cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued pardon of God, of his Souereigne, and the world.</hi> And thirdly, hee desired those of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie which were present, that wheresoeuer they, came they would proclame in the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit his confession of his crime, his sorow for the same, and his full hope that God would pardon him. And to the end that this might be performed, hee tooke the hands of such Ministers as stood neere about him, so bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a promise on them. And heere, being told by the said Ministers and other persons of qualitie, that being so neere his departure out of the world, it concerned him to speake nothing but the trueth, and that vpon the perill of his soule: he answered, that to the
<pb n="28" facs="16"/>
end that they should know, that hee had spoken nothing but the veritie, and that his Confession was true in euerie respect, hee would (at the last gaspe) giue them some apparent token for the confirmation of the same. Then fitting himselfe to the ladder, the Executioner commeth to him, and, as the maner is, asking forgiuenesse of him; <hi>VVith all my heart,</hi> saith hee, <hi>for you doe but your office, and it is the thing I desire; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause suffering in my bodie, I shall in my soule be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto my Sauiour.</hi> Ascending vp to the lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, he desired the people to sing a Psalme with him, which they did with many a wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping eye. Hee named the sixt Psalme, and beginning it or taking it vp himselfe, in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie verse or line thereof hee went before the people, singing both lowd and tunably vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the very end. Then once againe confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and auowing his former confession, he couered his owne face, and commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his soule to God, hee was turned off the ladder; where hanging by the necke some little while, hee three seuerall times gaue a lowd clap with his hands, that all the stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by might heare: which was the signe
<pb n="29" facs="16"/>
or token (as it seemeth) which he a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had sayd that hee would giue at his last gaspe, for the ratification and auowing of those things, which by his confession hee had so many times declared and deliuered. These things were done in the open sight of the Sunne, in the Kings Capitall towne, at the Market-crosse in <hi>Edenborough,</hi> in the presence of diuers thousands of all sorts: of the Nobilitie, of the Clergie, of the Gentrie, of the Burgesses, of women and children, my selfe with the rest of the English Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters standing by and looking on, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing GOD the glorie, that after so long a space as eight yeeres and eight dayes (for so it was by iust computation after the attempt of <hi>Gowrie</hi>) he was pleased to giue so noble a testimonie vnto that, which by some ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligners had beene secretly called in question without any ground or reason. I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported at length those particulars which I heard and saw, which that honourable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonage, who wrote this Treatise following doth somewhat more briefly deliuer, but yet both of vs very truly, as thousands can witnesse.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="30" facs="17"/>Out of both these narrations there may <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> diuers obseruations be gathered. As first, how hainous a thing it is in the sight of God himselfe, for subiects of what nature or qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie soeuer, to enter into conspiracie against the life and person of the Lords Anointed: for Almightie God hath threatned to disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer these traiterous enterprises; and if no other way, yet by some strange and miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous fashion. Hee who spake against cruell imaginations of the heart, <note n="t" place="margin">
         <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.20.</note>
      <hi>Curse not the King, no not in thy thought: for the fowle of the heauen shall carie the voice, and that which hath wings shall declare the matter;</hi> what will he do, when acts of hostilitie in rebellious maner shall be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into? And doth his Diuine Maiestie dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>close it, and will he not also punsh it? The example of that Earle <hi>Gowrie</hi> among thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of others may be a sufficient instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this behalfe, who for his Soueraignes loue and gracious fauour testified in many respects, and intended many more wayes vnto him, returning nothing but vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse and traiterous resolutions, digged a pit for another, but by Gods iudgement fell into it himselfe: and did not only lose in
<pb n="31" facs="17"/>
one day his fidelitie, estimation and life, but ouerthrew his house and all the honour of his familie, thorow succeeding generations. Therefore farre be it at all times from any noble heart to walke in his wayes, or vpon any occasion to entertaine such discontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as may grow to vndutifulnesse: for when the wrath of God shall ouertake men offending in this kinde, and the iustice of a King shall once proceed against them, what horror must there needs be in their bowels and conscience? what trembling &amp; affrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in their very soule? If this poore man <hi>Sprot,</hi> for concealing that odious combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, found such touches in himselfe, and such remorse in his heart, what quaking and dreadfulnesse may we thinke will fall on him who is guiltie of the highest act of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and rebellion?</p>
   <p>Secondly, wee heere may see the Lords <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> protection ouer Christian Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; whom as hee placeth next himselfe in maiestie and authoritie, and calleth them by his owne name, <hi>I haue said,</hi>
      <note n="u" place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 82.6.</note>
      <hi>Ye are Gods</hi>; so he blesseth and vpholdeth them as his Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Vice-gerents, men representing
<pb n="32" facs="18"/>
himselfe, especially if sincerely they serue and feare and loue him. He is a God of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and loueth subordination in all King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Countreys, where if hee grace, countenance and protect inferiour Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates, what will hee doe to the heads and chiefe gouernours of his people, who are next to his owne greatnesse? Hee hath set them aboue other in honour and glorie, which causeth them to be more obserued according to their state: but withall, the prayers of their subiects are powred out for their welfare, day &amp; night, and at all times; which concurring with their owne requests to God, do find acceptance with the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est to their noted prosperitie and eminent felicitie. It preserueth from many perils, to haue at all houres and seasons the prayers and supplications of faithfull men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men houering ouer their heads, which may be perpetuall Remembrancers for them to their heauenly Father, if by humane fragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and vnauoidable imperfections they should forget themselues.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, we may note more particularly the sauing health of God vpon our graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="33" facs="18"/>
Souereigne; to whom as the Lord hath giuen many blessings and much happinesse beyond all his Progenitours, so hee hath mainteined and protected his person in a maruellous and strange maner, not onely from his cradle vnto this day, but (as it is very well knowen) from before his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the world. And how did the Lord free his seruant euen from the brincke of the pit, and from the gates of the graue at the time of <hi>Gowries</hi> attempt? as also since that day, when those wicked sonnes of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial,</hi> the staine of the Land and Countrey wherin they were borne, intended that Powder-treason? Which as on the one side it expecteth at the hands of his Maiestie a greater thankfulnesse to God the King of kings, so on the other side it calleth for of vs who sit peaceably vnder his shadow, euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting tokens of gratefulnesse to so mercifull a Lord, and heartie obedience to our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne, whom God hath raised vp, defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, protected, maintained, vpheld with his extraordinarie fauour to no common end; but to the enlarging of his Church, to the further ruine of Antichrist; to the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="34" facs="19"/>
of Kingdomes, to the comfort of all the godly dispersed thorow <hi>Europe.</hi> And happy is hee, not who can finde deuices, and cast imaginarie perils to hinder such a worke, but who in his poore place can with a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heart giue furtherance to the same.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, as many blessings from heauen haue been powred on the head of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, so it is not the least, that <hi>tanquam è postli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minio,</hi> after so many yeeres, and that as from the bones of a dead man, when liuing men would not beleeue it, God hath giuen far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther light to the opening of the conspiracie of that vngodly Earle <hi>Gowrie</hi>; which some few persons, affected more to a rebell that is dead, than to their liuing Souereigne, did endeuour to disguise and maske at their owne pleasure. The strange conceits of whom I can neuer sufficiently woonder at; that men professing conscience and zeale to the trueth, should vpon no kind of ground or shew of probabilitie, suffer such vnreue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent thoghts to enter into their hearts; espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially against his sacred person, whose life hath beene so immaculate and vnspotted in the world, so free from all touch of vicious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb n="35" facs="19"/>
and staining imputation, that euen malice it selfe (which leaueth nothing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>searched) could neuer finde true blemish in it, nor cast any probable aspersion on it. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst his sacred person, whom as they must acknowledge to be zealous as <hi>Dauid,</hi> learned and wise as the <hi>Salomon</hi> of our age, religious as <hi>Iosias,</hi> carefull of spreading Christs faith as <hi>Constantine the Great</hi>; so if they will speake trueth, they must confesse to be iust as <hi>Moses,</hi> vndefiled in all his wayes as <hi>Iehosaphat</hi> or <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechias,</hi> full of clemencie as another <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius,</hi> farre from spilling the blood of any of his Nobilitie, but rather sparing those who haue lift vp their hand against him. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding, when preposterous affection had so blinded these men, that they would not see this truth, the Lord hath giuen light yet once more to the rectifying of their iudgements. A singular example of Gods vnlimited and vnbounded wisdome, who will doe things as he liketh. That when as <hi>S. Iohn</hi> sayth, <note n="u" place="margin">
         <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.11.</note>
      <hi>Qui sordescit, sordescat adhuc,</hi> He that lift to be peeuish and refractarie and selfe-conceited, did thinke hee might haue persisted and died in that peeuishnesse and
<pb n="36" facs="20"/>
refractarie conceit, and supposed that neuer any thing in this world should haue beene able to reforme him, may see before his face so illustrious a testimony of his misconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted fancie, and almost vnsatisfiable vnduti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse, that vnlesse his face be hardened and his heart obdurated against both hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, he must cease to be peruerse. God is the God of truth: and he who is the protectour of innocency in the poorest, will certainly be the mainteiner and defender of integritie and sinceritie in his noblest and dearest seruant. It is fit that he should haue his owne will, to put off and prolong his mercies till the time which seemeth good to himselfe, that men may wait vpon him, and patiently expect, and still tarie the Lords leisure: yea that his power may be knowen, who can bring light out of darknesse, and good out of euill, and truth out of treason; who can giue hope beyond hope. But when hee is once resolued that things acted in secret shall be preached vpon the house top, that iniquitie shalbe opened, that sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie shall be cleered, and innocencie dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burdened of scandalous imputations, if
<pb n="37" facs="20"/>
men would not speake, or children sound out the trueth in the streets, <note n="x" place="margin">
         <hi>Luc.</hi> 19.40.</note> yet the verie stones shall crie, as our Sauiour once answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the maligning Pharisees. Blessed be the GOD of iustice, who cleereth vp the fame of his holy ones, when malice would obscure it.</p>
   <p>Lastly, heere may be a warning to men <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> of mine owne profession, I meane the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of the Gospell, that in cases of high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est nature between a King and his rebell they conceiue not things to the woorst, and (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they will be opposite to him whom most of all they should honor) by buzzings and whisperings, and secret suggestions, without all ground of trueth, labour to sow sedition in the eares of women and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or in the mindes of men either weake or ill disposed. For as the <note n="y" place="margin">
         <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.7.</note> lips of the Priest should alwayes preserue knowledge, so should they preserue trueth. And we are to go before our flocks and Congregations in obedience and obsequiousnesse vnto the Christian Magistrate, not in sowing sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or making of mutinies, to the distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of the State. Who should sticke clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser
<pb n="38" facs="21"/>
to <hi>Moyses</hi> welding so huge a charge, than <hi>Aaron</hi> and his tribe? And who should rather labour to doe his Prince all right, than the Minister of the Gospell, who next after tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching men their dutie to GOD, is made to teach obedience and respectiuenesse vnto Kings? And who more deserueth to be cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stised than he, if he wilfully transgresse?</p>
   <p>These things I thought not amisse to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue to thee, Christian Reader, before thou come to the perusing of this plaine and true narration, touching the examination, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignment and death of the person here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed. GOD Almightie blesse the Kings Maiestie, grant vnto him many dayes full of pietie and felicitie; and after this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall life expired, send him an euerlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Crown of glorie, through Iesus Christ our Lord. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in the Lord,</hi> GEORGE ABBOT.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>