<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Premonition from the Author to the Reader.</title>
           <author>C., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118706_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19044</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5461.2</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118706</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Premonition from the Author to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>C., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The English dictionarie: or, An interpreter of hard English vvords : Enabling as well ladies and gentlewomen, young schollers, clarkes, merchants, as also strangers of any nation, to the vnderstanding of the more difficult authors already printed in our language, and the more speedy attaining of an elegant perfection of the English tongue, both in reading, speaking and writing. Being a collection of the choisest words contained in the Table alphabeticall and English expositor, and of some thousands of words neuer published by any heretofore. By H.C. Gent</title>
                 <author>Cockeram, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <distributor>Weaver (Wever), Edmund</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>332 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>A Premonition from the Author to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am not ignorant of the praise-worthy labours which some Schollers of deserued memorie haue heretofore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed on the like subiect that I haue here aduentured on: howsoeuer it might therefore seeme a needlesse taske of mine, to intrude vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a plot of study, the foundation of whose buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hath beene formerly leuel'd and laid, yet the Iustice of defence herein is so cleere, that my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours may bee truly termed rather a necessity of doing, than an arrogancie in doing. For without appropriating to my owne comfort any interest of glory, the <hi>vnderstanding</hi> Readers will not, the <hi>ignorant</hi> cannot, and the <hi>malicious</hi> dare not, but acknowledge that what any before me in this kinde haue begun, I haue not onely
<pb facs="4"/> fully finished, but throughly perfected. To write an Apologie of iustification would argue rather a distrust of my Worke than a confidence of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: Be pleased therefore (honest and (therin) learned Reader) to suruey a short Premonition for the order of the ensuing Vocabularie. First the method is plaine and easie, being alphabeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, by which the capacity of the meanest may soone be inlightened. The first Booke hath the choisest words themselues now in vse, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with our language is inriched and become so copious, to which words the common sense is annexed. The second Booke containes the vulgar words, which whensoeuer any desirous of a more curious explanation by a more refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and elegant speech shall looke into, he shall there receiue the exact and ample word to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse the same: Wherein by the way let me pray thee to obserue that I haue also inserted (as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion serued) euen the <hi>mocke-words</hi> which are ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culously vsed in our language, that those who desire a generality of knowledge may not bee ignorant of the sense, euen of the <hi>fustian termes,</hi> vsed by too many who study rather to bee heard speake, than to vnderstand them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues. The last Booke is a recitall of seuerall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, Gods and Goddesses, Giants and Deuils, Monsters and Serpents, Birds and Beasts, Riuers, Fishes, Herbs, Stones, Trees, and the like, to the intent that the diligent learner may not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb facs="4"/> the defect of any helpe which may informe his discourse or practice. I might insist vpon the generall vse of this worke, especially for La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and Gentlewomen, Clarkes, Merchants, young Schollers, Strangers, Trauellers, and all such as desire to know the plenty of the English; but I am confident, that experience will be the truest Herauld to publish to the world on my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, how as my debt to my countrie is to bee challenged, so my Country shall not altogether boast of any immunity from being indebted to my S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>udies. Thus what I haue done is (Reader) for thy benefit, accept it and make vse of it, so shall I finde reward in my labours, and rest thy friend,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>H. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>