<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Prooemium.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118774_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14084</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24394</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118774</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Prooemium.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The doue and the serpent : In which is conteined a large description of all such points and principles, as tend either to conuersation, or negotiation</title>
                 <author>D. T. (Daniel Tuvill)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lisle (L’isle, Lyle), Laurence</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 92 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>Prooemium.</head>
   <p>THat vnaduised Rhetorician, whose iudgement being so ouersway'd with selfe-conceite, as that he durst most arrogantly presume, in presence of one of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Commaunders, and best experienced Captaines, that those times afforded, with many tedious and friuolous Discourses to determine the office and dutie of a Generall, was recompenced, as he deserued, with a disdainefull smile: which being accompanied with these words, that <hi>had those things beene handled by a Swallowe, hee would haue done the like; but if by an Eagle, haue lent them the best attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that he could,</hi> did more manifestly make knowne, how much he had distasted his ouerdaring weakenesse. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I may seeme at first in many mens iudgements wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the like censure and reprehension: but all things right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly considered, I hope I shall easily auoyde it. For though the course I take seeme somewhat preposterous in regard of that of the sacred <hi>Vestalls,</hi> who first learned what they were to doe; secondly, did what they had learned; and last of all instructed others: yet is it answerable to that of the <hi>Pythagorians,</hi> who after three yeeres of silent contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, were permitted to entermeddle with publike acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to reduce their long conceiued speculations, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to practise. Now therefore with the Poet,
<q>
         <l>— Fungar vice Cotis,<note place="margin">Horat: de arte Poët.</note> acutum</l>
         <l>Reddere quae ferrum valet, exsors ipsa secandi;</l>
         <l>Munus &amp; officium faciens nil, ipse docebo,</l>
         <l>Quid deceat, quid non; quò virtus, quò ferat error:</l>
      </q>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>