<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
           <author>S., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118010_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13238</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23531</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118010</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>S., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The paradise of delights. Or The B. Virgins garden of Loreto : With briefe discourses vpon her diuine letanies, by way of meditation. For the comfort of all such, as be deuout vnto her; and desyre her holy patronage &amp; protection. By I.S. of the Society of Iesus</title>
                 <author>Sweetnam, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 217, 7 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, If thou be of the Blessed num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of those, vvhose com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and proffit I seeke in this little Treatise; let me desire thee to plucke of thy deceitful spectacles of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riosity,
<pb facs="8"/>and peruse my plaine lines vvith deuout simplicity; othervvise thou art like to finde thy labour of as little effect, in regard of vvhat thou seekest of me, as I shal find my hopes of small expectation, for vvhat I desire to vvorke in thee.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Moyses</hi> vvith admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration did see the <hi>Bush,</hi> in vvhich Almighty God appeared, burning, but not consuming, vvhich
<pb facs="8"/>made him the more desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to behold that great and vvonderous vision; but yet vvas commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to plucke off his shooes before he might haue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse. The like counsell I find giuen by <hi>S. Bernard,</hi> to those vvho curiously de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to behold the diuin mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries, vvhich the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall VVisdom of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God hath vvrought in this mysticall Bush, the most Blessed Virgin his
<pb facs="9"/>Mother. Thou wilt not so much admire the <hi>Gedeon</hi> Fleece besprinckled vvith devv, as to behold a vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man clad vvith the sunne, yet not consumed vvith so great an heate. <hi>Meritò quidem admiraris Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> (saith he) <hi>&amp; curiosiùs desideras in tueri;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Bern. serm. in Apoc. <hi>12</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>verum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamen solue calceamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta de pedib us tuis, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolucra pone carnalium cogitationum, si acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere concupiscas.</hi> Not
<pb facs="9"/>vvithout cause thou dost admire (O holy Moyses) &amp; more curiously dost de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to behold; but cast of thy shooes from thy feete, and bridle the inordinate desire of thy flesh, if thou desire to approach.</p>
   <p>No curious conceite but a pure intention, no earthly affection, but true deuotion, no faygned loue, but a dutifull respect must bring thee to the presence of this sacred Queene, to the
<pb facs="10"/>sight of this blazing starre, into the most esteemed fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of the euer Blessed mother of God. Read ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vvith desire of proffit, &amp; my best vvishes shalbe as my intentionis, that it may turne to the great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, and his thrice happy Mother, and to the Eternall good of thy soule. And in thy best deuotions pray for me.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>I. S.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>