<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118583_Fr2_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15631</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25900a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118583</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A collection of emblemes, ancient and moderne : quickened vvith metricall illustrations, both morall and divine: and disposed into lotteries, that instruction, and good counsell, may bee furthered by an honest and pleasant recreation. By George VVither. The first booke</title>
                 <author>Wither, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Grismand (Grismond), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Grismand (Grismond), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 62, 6, 63-124, 6, 135-196, 6, 209-270, 10 pages, illustrations (engravings, woodcut), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F there had not beene some <hi>Bookes</hi> concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly composed, and sutable to meane capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities, I am doubtfull, whether I had ever beene so delighted in reading, as thereby to attaine to the little Knowledge I have: For, I doe yet remember, that, things <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly pleasant,</hi> brought mee by degrees, to love that which is <hi>truely profitable.</hi> And as <hi>David</hi> said, His <hi>Heart shewed him the wickednesse of the Vngodly;</hi> (meaning perhaps, that hee felt in himselfe, some <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments,</hi> of the same naturall Corruption, by which they are overcome, who resist not evill suggestions at their first motions:) Even-so, I may truly acknowledge, that mine owne <hi>Experience</hi> hath showne mee so much of the common <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> in mine owne person, that it hath taught mee, how those things may be wrought upon in others, to their best advantage.</p>
   <p>Therefore, though I can say no more to disswade from <hi>Vice,</hi> or to incourage men to <hi>Ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ue,</hi> than hath already beene said in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny learned <hi>Authors;</hi> yet I may be an occasion by these <hi>Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours,</hi> to bring that, the oftner into remembrance, which they have, more learnedly, expressed· and perhaps, by such circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances, as they would not descend unto, may insinuate further also with some Capacities, than more applauded <hi>Meanes. Vini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Salt,</hi> or common <hi>Water,</hi> (which are very meane <hi>Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents</hi>) make Sawces more pleasing to some tastes, than <hi>Sugar,</hi> and <hi>Spices.</hi> In like manner, plaine and vulgar notions, seasoned with a little <hi>Pleasantnesse,</hi> and relished with a moderate <hi>Sharpnesse,</hi> worke that, otherwhile, which the most admired <hi>Compositions</hi> could never effect in many <hi>Readers;</hi> yea, wee have had frequent proofes, that a blunt <hi>Iest</hi> hath moved to more consideration, than a judicious <hi>Discourse.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I take little pleasures in <hi>Rymes, Fictions,</hi> or conceited <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions,</hi> for their owne sakes; neither could I ever take so much paines, as to spend time to put my meanings into other words than such as flowed sorth, without <hi>Studie;</hi> partly because I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light more in Matter, than in <hi>Wordy Flourishes,</hi> But, chiefely, because those <hi>Verball Conceites,</hi> which by some, are accounted most <hi>Elegant,</hi> are not onely (for the greater part) <hi>Emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Sounds,</hi> and Impertinent <hi>Clinches,</hi> in themselves; but, such <hi>Inventions,</hi> as do sometime, also, obscure the <hi>Sense,</hi> to common <hi>Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ders;</hi> and, serve to little other purpose, but for <hi>Wittie men</hi> to shew <hi>Tricks</hi> one to another: For, the <hi>Ignorant</hi> understand them not; and the <hi>Wise</hi> need them not.</p>
   <p>So much of them, as (without darkning the matter, to them who most need instruction) may be made use of, to stirre up the <hi>Affections,</hi> winne <hi>Attention,</hi> or help the <hi>Memory,</hi> I approve and make use of, to those good purposes, according as my leisure, and the measure of my <hi>Facultie</hi> will permit; that, <hi>Vanitie</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
might not, to worse ends, get them wholly into her <hi>Possession.</hi> For, I know that the meanest of such conceites are as pertinent to some, as <hi>Rattles,</hi> and <hi>Hobby-horses</hi> to Children; or as the <hi>A.B.C.</hi> and <hi>Spelling,</hi> were at first to those <hi>Readers,</hi> who are now past them. And, indeed, to desp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se <hi>Meane Inventions, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant Compositions,</hi> and <hi>Verball Elegancies,</hi> (being quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied as is aforesaid) or to banish them out of the world, because there be other things of more excellencie, were as absurd, as to neglect and root out all <hi>Herbes▪</hi> which will not make <hi>Pottage;</hi> Or, to destroy all <hi>Flowers</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ch are lesse beautifull than the <hi>Tulip,</hi> or lesse sweet than the <hi>Rose.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I (that was never so sullenly wise) have alwaies intermingled <hi>Sports</hi> with <hi>Seriousnesse</hi> in my <hi>Inventions;</hi> and, taken in <hi>Verball-conceites,</hi> as they came to hand, without <hi>Affectation;</hi> But, having, ever aymed, rather to profit my <hi>Readers,</hi> than to gaine their praise, I never pumpe for those things; and am, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while, contented to seeme <hi>Foolish,</hi> (yea, and perhaps, more fool<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sh than I am) to the <hi>Overweening-Wise;</hi> that, I may make others <hi>Wiser than they were:</hi> And, (as I now doe) am not ashamed to set forth a <hi>Game at Lots,</hi> or (as it were) a <hi>Puppet-play</hi> in <hi>Pictures,</hi> to allure men to the more serious observation of the profitable <hi>Morals,</hi> couched in these <hi>Emblems.</hi> Neverthelesse, (if some have sayd, and thought truly) my <hi>Poems</hi> have instructed, and rectified many People in the Course of <hi>Honest-living,</hi> (which is the best <hi>Wisedome</hi>) much more than the <hi>Austerer Volumes</hi> of some criticall <hi>Authors;</hi> who, are by the <hi>Common-sort,</hi> therefore onely, judged Wise, because they composed <hi>Books,</hi> which few understand, save they who need them not.</p>
   <p>In these <hi>Lots</hi> and <hi>Emblems,</hi> I have the same ayme which I had in my other <hi>Writings:</hi> and though I have not dressed them sutably to curious <hi>Fancies,</hi> yet, they yield wholsome nourishment to strengthen the constitution of a <hi>Good-life;</hi> and, have solidity enough for a <hi>Play-game,</hi> which was but accidentally composed; and, by this <hi>Occasion.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>These <hi>Emblems,</hi> graven in Copper by <hi>Crispinus Passaeus</hi> (with a <hi>Motto</hi> in Greeke, Latine, or Italian, round about every <hi>Figure;</hi> and with two <hi>Lines</hi> (or <hi>Verses</hi>) in one of the same <hi>Languages,</hi> periphrasing those <hi>Motto's</hi>) came to my hands, almost twentie yeares past. The <hi>Verses</hi> were so meane, that, they were after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward cut off from the <hi>Plates;</hi> And, the <hi>Collector</hi> of the said Emblems, (whether hee were the <hi>Versifier</hi> or the <hi>Graver,</hi> was neither so well advised in the <hi>Choice</hi> of them, nor so exact in observing the true <hi>Proprieties</hi> belonging to every <hi>Figure,</hi> as hee might have beene.</p>
   <p>Yet, the <hi>Workman-ship</hi> being judged very good, for the most part; and the rest excusable; some of my Friends were so much delighted in the <hi>Gravers</hi> art, and, in those <hi>Illustrations</hi> which for mine owne pleasure, I had made upon some few of them, that, they requested mee to <hi>Moralize</hi> the rest. Which I condiscended unto: And, they had beene brought to view many yeares agoe, but that the <hi>Copper Prints</hi> (which are now gotten) could not be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured out of <hi>Holland,</hi> upon any reasonable Conditions.</p>
   <p>If they were worthy of the <hi>Gravers</hi> and <hi>Printers</hi> cost, being
<pb facs="5"/>
onely dumbe <hi>Figures,</hi> little usefull to any but to young <hi>Gravers</hi> or <hi>Painters;</hi> and as little delightfull, except, to <hi>Children,</hi> and <hi>Childish-gazers:</hi> they may now be much more worthy; seeing the life of <hi>Speach</hi> being added unto them, may make them <hi>Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers,</hi> and <hi>Remembrancers</hi> of profitable things.</p>
   <p>I doe not arrogate so much unto my <hi>Illustrations,</hi> as to thinke, they will be able to teach any thing to the <hi>Learned;</hi> yet if they cast their eyes upon them, perhaps, these <hi>Emblems,</hi> and their <hi>Morals,</hi> may remember them, either of some <hi>Dutie,</hi> which they might else forget, or minde them to beware of some <hi>Danger,</hi> which they might otherwise be unheedfull to prevent. But, sure I am, the <hi>Vulgar Capacities,</hi> may from them, be many waies both <hi>Instructed,</hi> and <hi>Remembred;</hi> yea, they that have most need to be <hi>Instructed,</hi> and <hi>Remembred,</hi> (and they who are most backward to listen to <hi>Instructions,</hi> and <hi>Remembrances,</hi> by the common Course of <hi>Teaching,</hi> and <hi>Admonishing</hi>) shall be, hereby, informed of their <hi>Dangers,</hi> or <hi>Duties,</hi> by the way of an honest <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation</hi> before they be aware.</p>
   <p>For, when levitie, or a childish delight in trifl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ng Objects, hath allured them to looke on the <hi>Pictures;</hi> Curiositie may urge them to peepe further, that they might seeke out also their <hi>Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings,</hi> in our annexed <hi>Illustrations;</hi> In which, may lurke some <hi>Sentence,</hi> or <hi>Expression,</hi> so evidently pertinent to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eir <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states, Persons,</hi> or <hi>Affections,</hi> as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ll (at that instant or after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward) make way for those <hi>Considerations,</hi> which will, at last, wholly change them, or much better them, in their <hi>Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>To seeke out the <hi>Author</hi> of every particular <hi>Emblem,</hi> were a labour without profit; and, I have beene so far from endeavouring it, that, I have not so much as cared to find out their meanings in any of these <hi>Figures;</hi> but, applied them, rather, to such purposes, as I could thinke of, at first sight; which, upon a second view, I found might have beene much betterd, if I could have spared time from other imployments. Something, also, I was <hi>Confined,</hi> by obliging my selfe to observe the same number of <hi>lines</hi> in every <hi>Illustration;</hi> and, otherwhile, I was thereby constrained to conclude, when my best <hi>Meditations</hi> were but new begunne: which (though it hath pleased Some, by the more comely Vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>formitie, in the Pages) yet, it hath much injured the libertie of my <hi>Muse.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>There be, no doubt, some faults committed by the <hi>Printer,</hi> both Literall and Materiall, and some Errors of the <hi>Gravers</hi> in the <hi>Figures,</hi> (as in the <hi>Tetragrammaton;</hi> in the Figure of <hi>Arion;</hi> and in the <hi>Proprieties</hi> due to some other <hi>Hieroglyphicks;</hi> but, for the most part, they are such, as <hi>Common-Readers</hi> will never perceive; and I thinke, that they who are <hi>Judicious,</hi> will so plainly finde them to be no faults of mine; that, leaving them to be amended by those, to whom they appertaine; and, <hi>You,</hi> to accept of these <hi>Play-games</hi> as you please: I bid you <hi>Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>