<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The Author to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118975_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00123</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1012</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118975</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The Author to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discourse for parents honour, and authoritie : Written respectiuely to reclaime a young man that was a counterfeit Iesuite: by his father Petrus Ærodius the renowned French ciuilian, sometimes Iustice in causes criminall and Master of Requests to the Duke of Angiers. Done into English at the instance of some worthy learned friends by Io: Budden Doctor of the Lawes, and his Maiesties Professor in the Vniuersity of Oxford</title>
                 <author>Ayrault, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 <distributor>Harper, Thomas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Harper, William</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 170 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ The Author to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing for three whole yeeres together, made continuall enquirie after my eldest sonne, and that to small purpose, (for hee is among the Iesuits) I am now deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to present that to publique view, which otherwise I should haue seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred to priuate vse. I treat with him as with an offender, that contemptuouslie refuseth to make his appearance, and as a man should doe wth a runaway, that is, by writ of outlarie, and proclamation of rebellion. Therefore I beseech thee
<pb facs="4"/>good Reader, if this expostulation and complaint of mine appeare vnto thee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together causelesse, and if it happilie so fall out, that thou meet with this poor youth, thus esloigned and seduced from me, be ameanes, that he may sometimes peruse this small treatise: then if he find himselfe resolued, to bee at his owne reines, and disposing, I passe not, father or not father, whether he so take me or so refuse me. From <hi>Angiers</hi> 1589 in <hi>October.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>