<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE SVBSEQVENT HISTORIES.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118078_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14770</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25067</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118078</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE SVBSEQVENT HISTORIES.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tvvo histories of Ireland : The one written by Edmund Campion, the other by Meredith Hanmer Dr of Divinity</title>
                 <author>Campion, Edmund, saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Ireland--Dublin</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Matthew.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stationers’ Society, Dublin</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 138, 2, 219, 221-223, 2, 8, 127, 9 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE SVBSEQVENT HISTORIES.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat varietie of choyse matter the affaires of this Kingdome doe affoord to an Historian, especially since the middle of the raigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII. any one that is but meanely versed in our Histories can testifie: But if we consider how little hath hetherto bin pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished, wee cannot but blame the slownes of our learned men, who have (for by-respects) forborne to take paines in so worthy a subject. England hath had the happines that some parts of her Historie have bin lately excellently performed, by the right honorable <hi>Francis</hi> late Viscount St. Alban, the right Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend <hi>Francis</hi> Lo: Bishop of Hereford, the most lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>William Camden</hi> and others. Some will here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, I hope, doe the like for Ireland: In the meane while we are to accept of these tastes, the one left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us by <hi>Edmund Campion,</hi> and the other by Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Hanmer,</hi> who died (of the plague at Dublin in the yeare M.DC.IIII.) before he had finished his
<pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="4"/>
intended worke: out of whose collections, what now beareth his name hath bin preserved by our most Reverend and excellently learned Primate. Other helpes (to passe by those which are already divulged) may be plentifully had by him who will undertake this taske, out of the auncient and moderne recordes, both in this Kingdome and in England, as also out of diverse manuscript Annales and Chartularies, which are yet extant among us, besides those authors of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish birth, as <hi>Iohn VVallingford</hi> a Monke of S<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Alban, <hi>Thomas Wike</hi> a Canon of Osney, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, (which I have seene) in that excellent library and treasury of MSS. antiquities, gathered by Sir <hi>Robert Cotton</hi> knight and Baronett deceased, who doe onely <hi>obiter</hi> touch upon our affaires. An intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there was not long since by Sir <hi>Iames Ley</hi> knight then Lord chiefe Iustice of the Kings Bench in Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, (afterwards Lord high Treasurer of England and Earle of Marleburgh) to have published some of our country writers in this kinde, for which end hee caused to be transcribed and made fit for the Presse, the Annales of <hi>Iohn Clynne</hi> a Friar minor of Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenny, (who lived in the time of King <hi>Edw.</hi> the <hi>3.</hi>) the Annales of the Priory of <hi>S. Iohn the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>list of Kilkenny,</hi> and the Annales of <hi>Multifernan, Rosse</hi> and <hi>Clonmell,</hi> &amp;c. But his weighty occasions did afterwards divert his purpose. The copies are yet preserved, and I hope ere long with other Annales and fragments of the same nature will be divulged. Wee come now to the Authors in hand.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>