<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, IOHN, BY GODS PROVIDENCE Archbishop of Yorke, Primate of England, and Metropolitane: H. S. wisheth true felicitie now and euer.</title>
           <author>Swinburne, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118058_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13252</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23547</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118058</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, IOHN, BY GODS PROVIDENCE Archbishop of Yorke, Primate of England, and Metropolitane: H. S. wisheth true felicitie now and euer.</title>
                 <author>Swinburne, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe treatise of testaments and last willes : very profitable to be vnderstoode of all the subiects of this realme of England, (desirous to know, whether, whereof, and how, they may make their testaments: and by what meanes the same may be effected or hindered,) and no lesse delightfull, aswell for the rarenes of the worke, as for the easines of the stile, and method: compiled of such lawes ecclesiasticall and ciuill, as be not repugnant to the lawes, customes, or statutes of this realme, nor derogatorie to the prerogatiue royall. In which treatise also are inserted diuers statutes of this land, together with mention of sundrie customes, aswell general as particular, not impertinent thereunto: besides diuers marginall notes, and quotations not to be neglected, especially of Iustinianists, or young students of the ciuil law: vvith two tables, the one analyticall ... the other alphabeticall ... By the industrie of Henrie Swinburn, Bachelar of the Ciuill Lawe</title>
                 <author>Swinburne, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 <publisher>Windet, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 293, 14 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, IOHN, BY GODS PROVIDENCE Archbishop of Yorke, Primate of England, and Metropolitane: H. S. wisheth true felicitie now and euer.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I had fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished this briefe Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mētarie trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, bethin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vvith my selfe (most re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerende Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,) vnto vvhose patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage I might dedicate the same: In the end I did resolue to make an offer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of vnto your Grace: Being moued there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto vvith the consideration, partlie of mine ovvne duetie, partlie of your Graces interest. For being a member of your Graces Courts Ecclesiastical, and hauing
<pb facs="3"/> novve receiued sundrie good fauours at your honours handes: This I thought might fitly serue for a probable argument of my thankfulnesse in that behalfe. And on the other side, forasmuch as before all others vvithin this prouinc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of Yorke, it apperteineth principally vnto your grace, to prouide that testamēts lavvfully made, be dulie executed, being novve by Gods merciful prouidēce Metropolitane &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie of that sea, I could not see a more vvorthie Patrone for a testamētary vvork. Partly therefore by these former conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, but especially I vvas encouraged therunto vvith the cōtemplation of those diuine graces of piety, learning, zeale, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie, bountie, benignitie, affabilitie, and al maner not onely sufficiencie, but excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of vertuous giftes, vvherevvith the giuer of all goodnesse hath vvonderfullie enriched your honourable minde. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as hitherto your vvisdome hath bene accustomed to entertaine vvith comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table countenance, such as be studious to benefite either the Church, or the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vvealth, though othervvise they bee of small reputation: so novve (most reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend) I am vvith all duetie to craue the
<pb facs="3"/> continuance of the same in mine ovvn be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, together vvith the fauourable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of these my labors, so farre as they bee agreeable to truth, right and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: vvhich thing I doo so much the more humblie desire, by hovv much I may seem ouermuch aduenturous in making choise of so honourable a patrone, for such a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling treatise. The Lorde of might and mercie multiplie his spirite vppon your grace, to the aduauncement of his ovvne glorie, and the good of his Church, vvith encrease of manie yeares in health and happinesse.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Graces most readie</hi> at commaundement, <hi>H. Swinburne.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>