<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ The Preface of Iohn Cal∣vin to a very friend of his.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118888_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17654</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4409</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118888</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ The Preface of Iohn Cal∣vin to a very friend of his.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An excellent treatise of the immortalytie of the soule : By which is proued, that the soules, after their departure out of the bodies, are avvake and doe lyue, contrary to that erronious opinion of certen ignorant persons, who thinke them to lye asleape vntill the day of iudgement. Set fourth by M. Iohn Caluin, and englished from the French by T. Stocker</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 <publisher>Day, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Day, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 66, that is 92, 4 leaves, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>❧ The Preface of Iohn Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin to a very friend of his.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough in deede it is very true, that certen godly honest men were a great while sithence earnestly in hand with me, to write somewhat for the confuting, and repressing of the foolishe, and confused opinion of some, who at this day goe about to mainteine the sleape and death of the soules, yet could they not hitherto winne me to yelde vnto their petitions and requestes, because it is cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to my nature to thrust my selfe in, to deale with matters of controuersie and debate. And surely, I had at that tyme great reason to excuse me, parte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, because I thought that in short time, this fond opinion would finde no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, and therefore be soone for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten: or els that a few Cockbrayned and lightheadded fellowes would onely keepe it in hugger mugger: and partely also, because I had no lyking to deale agaynst such aduersaries, with
<pb facs="6"/> whose power, weapons, and Ambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes I was no whit acquainted. For, as yet, I had neuer hard any speach of them, saue onely a confused kinde of buzzing of a thing, so that if I should haue had to doe with such as were not yet entred into the open playnes, I must needes haue played the part of one beating the bush (as we say) on the blinde side. Neuertheles, in the end it grewe afterward to another manner of matter then I thought it would haue done: For, these Ianglers were so bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sy and carefull to maintayne and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease their faction, as that they had already drawne into their error, I know not how many thowsands of people. And in deed to say truly, so far as I cā se this mischiefe waxeth worse &amp; worse. For at the first beginning, there were but a few that made a confused kinde of prattle of the sleaping of the soules: and therewith they would neuer let it be vnderstoode what they meant by this sleape. Now, sithence that tyme haue stept out these boucherly soule-sleaers, who at the first blow cut their
<pb facs="6"/> throates, and yet (thankes be to God) doe them no hurt at all. Notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, I verely thinke, that the error of the first sort is not to be borne withall, and besides, that this second kinde of them, is liuely to be repressed: For, neither of both sortes, haue any foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datiō, either of reason, or yet of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Howbeit, it is no easy matter to perswade others thus, except, Mauger their beards (as we commonly say) I openly refute these babling Gallauntes, and so discouer their leasings, which can no way be perceiued but by their wrytings. Now, as I heare say, they heare and there let flye (I know not in what short sceduls and pamfletts) their leasings and dolteries, vnto which I could neuer as yet once come to the sight of thē. Onely I haue receiued frō a friēd of mine certen aduertisements, which he by aduenture met withall, and set them downe in wryting as they came to his hands, or as he could here and there get them. And although one of my excuses, is as it were halfe taken from me by reason of these aduertise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes,
<pb facs="7"/> yet, remaineth the other halfe still to my selfe. But, forsomuch as they drawe vnto their error great store of people by reason of their troublesome speaches, and mighty prattle, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they so greatly deale, as if they had caused printed bookes to haue bene spread all the world ouer, I know not how I can be guiltles of treason a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynst the trueth of God, if in so great a necessitie I holde my peace, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble the matter. And truely, because I hope my trauell wil be very profitable euen to the most simple and ignoraunt, who may set themselues occupied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this matter and Argument, I will not be a feard to render vnto all honest and godly men a reason of my fayth: And yet it may be, that it is not so well furnished with all kindes of defence, able at full to geue the attempt, to the enemy: neither yet so strongly bulwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, as to keepe them from approching thereto, neuertheles I hope, not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vnarmed and defenceles. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, if the importunitie of these dreame sowers, would haue geuen me
<pb facs="7"/> some more leasure, I would with all myne hart, haue entred into this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, which can no way bring with it, so great gayne, as payne: considering especially, because I thinke that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation of the Apostle, might if it were at any tyme needefull, be suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in this behalfe, to witt, that we should be of discreete Iudgement. And although these men will not suffer vs to vse the discretion which we gladly desier, yet will I haue as great regard as I can, modestly to dispute of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Neuerthelesse, I would (if it had so pleased the Lord our God) that some other meane might haue bene found, for the soddayne cutting of, of this mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe which too too much encreaseth, least it eate in farther and farther, lyke a Cancker. Although this be not the first tyme onely of the beginning there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. For we reade, that the Arabians, were the first Aucthors of this error: who sayd: that the soule dyed together with the body, and that they should both of them rise agayne at the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment day. And within a while after,
<pb facs="8"/> Iohn, Byshop of Rome defended the same, which the Sorbonistes of Paris made him recant. Now, when this er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror had long tyme after that, bene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed, the Anabaptistes beganne late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to reuiue the same, and blow abroad certein sparkes thereof: which, spark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling farre and wide, in the end, fell out into hoat fiery flames: which, I beseech the Lord God to quench, euen at the first day with this gladsome raine which he especially reserueth for his Church. Now then, by the assistaunce of God his holy spirite, I entend to dispute hereof without bitternes of minde, without tying my selfe to any man par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, and also without desier to scoffe and slaunder, so that no man shall be able in trueth to complayne, that I haue hurt him, or yet by any meanes possible, once offended him. Though we may in deede, at this day see some men, very hoatly geuen to reprehend, sting and finde fault, whome if a man should touch but with the typp of the finger, would by and by cry out and say, that we breake the vnitie and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnes
<pb facs="8"/> of the Church, and vtterly vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late charitie and Brotherly loue. But to these men, this is mine aunswere in the first place: That we acknowledge no vnitie but such as is founded in and vpon Christ, neither yet allow we of any other charitie, then of that, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he is the bond. So that, the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall poynt and beginning to preserue charitie, is this, that our fayth remaine holy and sound emongest vs. And ouer and besides this, I say, that this dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation may very well be decyded with out any breach of charitie, if they bring with them such eares, as I determine to bring a tongue.</p>
   <p>And as for you, right worthy Syr, there are many causes to induce me to dedicate this my labor vnto you: But the chiefest is this, Because emongest these troubles of vaine opinions, by which a cōpany of fantasticall braynes disturbe the quiet of the Church, I se you most wisely and soberly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide stedfast and sound.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>Orleans. <date>1534.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>