<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Iohn Keper Student to the Vpright Reader of these pretie Pamphilets.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1570</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S118216_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03756</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13876</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S118216</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Iohn Keper Student to the Vpright Reader of these pretie Pamphilets.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Newe sonets, and pretie pamphlets. Written by Thomas Howell gentelman</title>
                 <author>Howell, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Colwell, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1570</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 32, 18 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>Iohn Keper Student to the Vpright Reader <hi>of these pretie Pamphilets.</hi>
   </head>
   <lg>
      <l>AS Feilde is none so ill, where fruitlesse weedes do groe, but y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> some herbe of vertue good, his pearyng flowres may shoe</l>
      <l>So though in Howels soyle, ilwillers seeme to see, at first nought els but thriftlesse thornes, and Thistles wilde to bee:</l>
      <l>Yet who shall vew his Feildes, and rightly them peruse, shall see that frutes and frutfull Herbes, do spryng of his sweet muse:</l>
      <l>For playnly he depayntes, the fits of youthfull loue: whose modest Pen from honest act, no mindefull man will moue.</l>
      <l>Here learne affects to rule, and youth in care to spende, beware thou mayst by others harmes, how youthly toyes do ende:</l>
      <l>Here reape, with other frutes, precepts of mortall minde. Are these no Herbs of goodly grace, in fertile Feilde to finde?</l>
      <l>Also his fined phrase, shall get deserued prayse, whose cunnyng verse of youthly yeres, graue actes of age displayes.</l>
      <l>Wysh him more workes to Pen, by this his tried skill: and hope to see by tract of time, more frutes of painfull quill.</l>
      <l>To Howels happie hande, restore thou thankes for this, and wish him after death to liue, in wittie workes of his.</l>
   </lg>
   <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>