<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Worshipfull John Reinolds Esquire, Master Gunner of England: Robert Norton Gunner, wisheth all health and happinesse.</title>
           <author>Norton, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119503_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08351</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18676</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119503</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Worshipfull John Reinolds Esquire, Master Gunner of England: Robert Norton Gunner, wisheth all health and happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Norton, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of the art of great artillery, viz. The explanation of the most excellent and necessary definitions, and questions, pronounced and propounded, by that rare souldier and mathematician, Thomas Digges Esquire : and by him published, in his Stratiaticos, and Pantometria, concerning great ordinance, and his theorems thereupon. Together, vvith certaine expositions, and answers thereunto adioyned: written by Robert Norton gunner. And by him dedicated, to the worshipfull Iohn Reinolds Esquire, master gunner of England</title>
                 <author>Norton, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Tapp (Tap), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 50 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the Worshipfull <hi>John Reinolds</hi> Esquire, Master Gunner of England: <hi>Robert Norton</hi> Gunner, wisheth all health and happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Sir, (as your sometimes Scholler, &amp; your now substitute) giue me leaue, to shew some part of my dutifull thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, for your many louing fauours re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued; your kinde instructions, your free helping hand to the beginning of my encouragement, by your louing Certificate (to the right Honourable the Lord <hi>Carew</hi> Mr. of his Maiesties Ordinance) of my sufficiency to performe the place and Office of a Gunner, for his Maiesties seruice: I therefore haue presumed to demonstrate a part of my duty herein, the rather for the louing respect you haue euer shewed vnto me, and to all others vnder your Commaund, that endeuour to become seruiceable for our King, and Countrey, by the diligent pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise in the excellent Art of great Artillery: It being my chance of late Sir, to turne ouer <hi>Mr. Digges</hi> his Bookes, intituled <hi>Stratiaticos,</hi> and <hi>Pantometria,</hi> to light vpon certaine dificill Definition, obscure The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orems, and some subtill questions, concerning the
<pb facs="3"/>
vse of great Ordinance, which as <hi>Mr. Diggs</hi> there saith, though he long since publikely propounded them, that none hath yet vndertaken to answer any one of them: wherefore in his last edition with short Marginall notes, yes and no, himselfe hath darkly resolued some of them, as hereafter in the Margent appeareth, whereof I haue vndertaken to make a more plaine Exposition of them &amp; the rest, aswell for mine own, as for others furtherance. And wheras he hath there coated certaine published Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in this Science, I haue thought fit to ioyne them together, with some other Errors that I haue also e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spied in other Authors writing of this Art: All which I haue presumed to publish vnder your iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Patronage, hoping that my willing pains shal neither incurre disgrace, nor displease, but rather that these my first Fruits wil be accepted with such loue as I truly offer them, whereby I shall be encouraged (with your good leaue) hereafter to proceed further with my Treatise of the Art of Artillery, wherein I perswade my selfe, that the most necessary particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars belonging to the Gunners Art, are more acute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly shewed, then in any other Treatise in any Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage yet extant: And so I shall endeuour to deserue the continuance of your loue and fauour, and will rest at his Lordships, and your Worships command, both whom, I pray God euer to blesse.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Robert Norton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>