<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An Admonition to the Reader, concerning the Reply of T. F. &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119081_Bo1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15317</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25606</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119081</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An Admonition to the Reader, concerning the Reply of T. F. &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A copy of the decree : wherein two bookes of Roger Widdrington an English Cathotholick [sic] are condemned, and the author commanded to purge himselfe: and a copy of the purgation which the same Roger Widdrington sent to his Holinesse Pope Paul the fift. Translated out of Latine into English by the author, whereunto he hath also adioined an admonition to the reader concerning the Reply of T.F. &amp;c. and the condemnation of Fa: Suarez booke by a decree of the Parliament of Paris</title>
                 <author>Preston, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barnes, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>67, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="admonition_to_the_reader">
   <head>
      <hi>An Admonition to the Reader,</hi> concerning the Reply of T. F. &amp;c.</head>
   <p n="1">1 THis Decree of the Sacred Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, as it is thus translated into English, I haue <hi>(Courteous Reader)</hi> taken out of <hi>M. T. F.</hi> lately published, whose
<pb n="8" facs="5"/>
vnsound, and insufficient handling this Controuersie, but yet somewhat cunning, and colourable, and therefore easie to blinde the eyes of the simple, I will, God willing, ere it be long most clearely, but modestly discouer. In the meane time, thou maiest very plainely perceiue the weaknesse of his Discourse (to omit his intemperate and vncharitable bitternesse) if thou dost but consider the true state of the Controuersie, which is betwixt vs, and that all his Replies must be either euident demonstrations, or inuincible au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities, to which no probable answer can be giuen, otherwise he onely beateth about the bush, and will neuer prooue that which he pretended to conuince; and wilt also be pleased but sleightly to reade ouer the <hi>Appendix</hi> to my Theologicall Dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, wherein I fully answered all the arguments, which <hi>Fa: Suarez</hi> bringeth to demonstrate the doctrine for the Popes power to depose Princes to be a point of faith; which Doctrine as this Authour confesseth, is the maine question between him and me: and therefore for the better confirmation of his Reply, hee nakedly vrgeth all <hi>Fa: Suarez</hi> arguments (but
<pb n="9" facs="5"/>
concealing his name) which I in that Appendix haue already fully satisfied.</p>
   <p n="2">2 For <hi>first,</hi> I plainely declared the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of that distinction, which I alledged betwixt the Popes power to command temporals, and to punish temporally by way of coërtion, which distinction see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth greatly to trouble this Author, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he perceiueth, that it satisfieth the chiefest Arguments, which are vsually brought from the authoritie of many Canons, and from the nature and effects of Excommunication, to prooue, that the Pope hath power, not onely by the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges of Princes, but also by Christ his institution, and by consequence of his Pastorall office, to dispose of temporals, and to inflict temporall punishments by way of coërcion.</p>
   <p n="3">3 <hi>Secondly,</hi> I shewed, that <hi>Marsilius</hi> of <hi>Padua,</hi> whom with other enemies of the Church, <hi>Suarez</hi> affirmeth to haue first impugned this Doctrine of deposing tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Princes by the Popes spirituall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, was not by Catholike writers of former times accounted an heretick, for that he did impugne this Doctrine, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do those Authours, who relate <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>silius</hi>
      <pb n="10" facs="6"/>
his errours, as <hi>Castro, Prateolus, D. Sanders,</hi> and others, note this for one, that the Pope hath not power to depose Princes; which is an euident signe, that before this our miserable age, that Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine for the Popes power to depose Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, was not accounted by Catholickes to be a point of faith.</p>
   <p n="4">4 <hi>Thirdly,</hi> that from the time of <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie</hi> the seuenth, who was the first Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, that cleerely taught this Doctrine, (but after he had first put it in practise) and was the first Pope, that, <hi>contrarie to the custome of his Ancestors</hi> (saith <hi>Onuphrius) deposed the Roman Emperour</hi> (for which cause he had much adoe to cleere himself euen with his own friends, as appeareth by the Letter, which <hi>Hermannus Bishop of Mentz,</hi> his deare friend, and follower in all such his proceedings, wrote vnto him, desiring to be satisfied herein, and was by <hi>Sigebert,</hi> who in those dayes was greatly esteemed by the wisest for his singular vertue, and learning, although <hi>Cardinal Baronius,</hi> and <hi>Cardinall Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> doe without sufficient ground call him a Scismatick, at that time impeached
<pb n="11" facs="6"/>
      <hi>of noueltie,</hi> not to say, <hi>of heresie,</hi> for so bee <hi>Sigeberts</hi> words) it hath been conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually euen to these our daies contradict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Catholike Authors, as appeareth by <hi>Ioannes Trithemius,</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">Jn Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nico Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterii Hir. saug. ad an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num <hi>1106.</hi>
      </note> and <hi>Iacobus Almai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">In lib. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> dominio na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turali &amp;c. inprobatione conclus 2 ae.</note> there related, but especially by <hi>the Kingdome of France,</hi> as witnesseth <hi>Petrus Pithaeus,</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">In codice libertatum Eccles. Galli canae.</note> a man greatly commended by <hi>Fa: Posseuine</hi> the Iesuit, for his singular learning and knowledge in Antiquities,<note n="d" place="margin">In Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratu verbo Petrus Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaeus.</note> and it is sufficiently confirmed by the late proceeding <hi>at Paris</hi> against the bookes of <hi>Card: Bellarmine, Becanus Schulckenius,</hi> and now lastly of <hi>Suarez,</hi> whose booke was for this Doctrine by a solemne Decree of the Parliament of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, and Printed by the Kings Printer, and with the Kings priuiledge condemned, and reprochfully burned the 27. of Iune past by the hangman, before the great Staires of the Pallace, and foure of the chiefest Iesuites of France therein named, were enioyned vnder paine of treason in their Sermons to exhort the people to the contrarie Doctrine: And doubtlesse this Authour, who in all points followeth these former mens steps, if his booke had beene printed in Latine, would haue
<pb n="12" facs="7"/>
quickly perceiued by the fruits of his own labours, whether in France there be any Catholikes, who doe impugne this Doctrine of deposing Princes by the Popes authoritie, or no: And yet this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour would cunningly perswade the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pler sort of Catholikes, therby to perplexe their consciences, that I onely am the man, who doe impugne this temporall authoritie of the Pope to depose Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; whereas hee cannot be ignorant, that besides mee, many others of our nation, as both the <hi>Barclaies,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>Blackwell,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>Warmington,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Barret,</hi> those thirteene <hi>Reuerend Priests,</hi> all by publike writings, and many others of the best learned of our Nation, both Priests, and lay-men I could name, who are of my opinion; and if it were not for the clamors, threatnings, and violent proceedings of our Aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, (I meane not Protestants) they vvould publikely professe as much as I haue done: and as for the State of France, what opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion they be of, it is manifest. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Doctrine of <hi>Ʋasquez</hi> concerning probable opinions may bee very wel ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to this my doctrine, howsoeuer this Author falsely supposing the Doctrine for
<pb n="13" facs="7"/>
the Popes power to depose Princes to be defined, would gladly perswade our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Catholikes to the contrarie.</p>
   <p n="5">5 <hi>Fourthly,</hi> I shewed in that booke, that seeing the <hi>Pope</hi> is not the Church, but onely a principall member thereof, their is to bee made a great distinction betweene the facts, and practises of <hi>Popes,</hi> and betweene the facts and practise of the Church: neither is the practise of many <hi>Popes,</hi> to bee accounted the practise of the Church, vnlesse by the vvhole Church it be allowed, as that opinion and practise for the Popes power to depose Princes, and to inflict temporall punishments by way of coërtion neuer was: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore although it be, and hath beene, the more common opinion of Catholikes for some ages past, that the Pope hath au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to depose, yet that it is certaine, and not to bee contradicted, but to bee beleeued as a point of faith, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary not to be accounted an opinion, but rather an heresie, is altogether false. To the <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Lateran,</hi> which but of late yeares hath been vrged, and that onely by some few, because <hi>Suarez</hi> did onely barely relate it, and not vrge the wordes
<pb n="14" facs="8"/>
thereof, I did remit him to the <hi>Preface</hi> of my <hi>Apologelicall Answere,</hi> wherein I largely discoursed of the Decree of that Councel. But because this Author seemeth to stand much thereon, as the chiefe pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and ground of his pretended defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I will at large in my Answere to his Reply treate of that Councell, and satisfie all the cauils (which neuerthelesse should bee cleere demonstrations, if this Author did intend to proue his purpose) vvhich hee hath taken out of D. <hi>Singletons,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Fa: Lessius</hi> his Discussion of the Decree of that Councell, and I will shew, that it cannot be sufficiently proued, <hi>first,</hi> that the Councell by those words, <hi>tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Lord,</hi> did intend to include Soueraign Princes; <hi>secondly,</hi> that although it did by those words vnderstand Soueraigne Princes, yet that it did not suppose, that the Pope had authoritie to depose Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Princes; &amp; <hi>thirdly,</hi> that although it did suppose it, yet it did not suppose it as a point of faith, and an vndoubted doctrine, but at the most as probable opinion, so that from the authoritie of this Councel it can not bee conuinced, that it is a point of faith or an vndoubted doctrine, that the
<pb n="15" facs="8"/>
Pope hath authoritie to depose Soueraign Princes.</p>
   <p n="6">6 <hi>Lastly,</hi> thou maist perceiue (Good Reader) what strange paradoxes this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor dare aduenture to maintaine by this, that he blusheth not to affirme, &amp; would cunningly perswade our State, that my manner of handling this controuersie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably, concerning the Popes authoritie to depose Princes &amp;c. <hi>is dangerous &amp; pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to his Maiestie,</hi> and therefore, <hi>that my books deserue to be prohibited, no lesse in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land then Rome, and that wise men in the parts where hee is, doe greatly maruell, how it can stand with the wisedome of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Councell to permit them to bee printed and published in England.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="7">7 But if this Author had either sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely or entirely related my opinion, or else had put in minde the Reader against what kinde of Aduersaries I doe oppose, he would presently haue perceiued, that it is too apparantly, &amp; shamefully vntrue, that my manner of handling this question probably is dangerous and pernicious to <hi>his Maiestie,</hi> as this Author doth endeuor to perswade <hi>his Maiesty,</hi> not for any loue that he is knowne to beare vnto the State,
<pb n="16" facs="9"/>
but to the end, by all likelihood, that hee and such like violent spirits, may vvrite more freely, and without being controu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led or contradicted by Catholikes, who, as hee is perswaded doe little regard the writings, and opinions of Protestants con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this or any other Doctrine. For it may be dangerous to <hi>his Maiestie</hi> to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle a question probably against one Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersarie, which will bee nothing dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to handle it probably against an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. As for example, if it were agreed vpon by all Catholikes, that the Pope hath no power to depose <hi>his Maiestie,</hi> then it were dangerous to <hi>his Maiestie,</hi> that any Catholike should call this in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion, and dispute it probably: but if on the contrarie side, all Catholikes should agree in this, that it were certaine, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questionable, and a point of faith, that the Pope hath power to depose <hi>his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie,</hi> and to absolue his Subiects of their allegiance, to command them to take armes against him, &amp;c. then if a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like should call this in question, or, which is all one, dispute it probably, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that it is not certaine that the Pope hath such an authoritie, but it is question<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,
<pb n="17" facs="9"/>
and probable, that hee hath it not, no man of any sense, or vnderstanding can affirme, that such a manner of disputing this question probably against those Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries, who hold it for certaine, can be any way dangerous, or pernicious to <hi>his Maiestie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="8">8 Now behold the manner that I haue taken in handling this Controuersie. <hi>Card. Bellarmin, Gretzer, Lessius, Becanus, Suarez,</hi> and other Diuines, especially of the Society of Iesus, whom this Authour doth in euery steppe, as though he were their Creature, follow, haue laid this for a sure and vndoubted ground, that it is a point of faith, and to be beleeued as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and vnder paine of eternall damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by all Catholikes, that the Pope hath power to depose Princes, to absolue Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects from their Allegiance, and thereupon to commaund them to beare Armes, and raise tumults against their Prince so depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed. So that you see, that they already haue layd the danger, and vndoubted o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow to his Maiesties person and Crowne, if the Pope should perchance depose him, in that they affirme, that all Catholikes are bound in conscience to
<pb n="18" facs="10"/>
forsake him, and to fulfill the Popes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, to the destruction of <hi>His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties</hi> person and State. This Doctrine, to wit; that it is a point of Faith, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted principle of Catholike Religion, that the Pope hath power to depose Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to inflict all temporal punishments by way of coercion, and that all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes are bound in conscience to forsake <hi>his Maiestie,</hi> and to beare Armes against him, in case the Pope should depose him, I haue taken vpon me, for two principall reasons, to impugne, and do not doubt cleerely to maintaine the same against the clamours of this Authour, or any other whatsoeuer. My first reason was, for that it is against the truth and puritie of the Catholike Church, <hi>She being the piller and ground of truth,</hi> that doubtfull opinions, and which among Catholikes are onely in Controuersie, and by the <hi>Parliament of Paris,</hi> haue beene condemned as <hi>scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, seditious, damnable,</hi> and <hi>Pernitious,</hi> should be enforced vpon English Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, as an vndoubted doctrine of the Catholike Faith, to the vtter ouerthrow of themselues, and their whole posterity, by mē who are in no danger to loose, but
<pb n="19" facs="10"/>
rather to gaine temporall aduancement thereby.</p>
   <p n="9">9 My second reason was, to assure <hi>His Maiestie,</hi> that all English Catholikes may, according to the grounds of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Religion, be true, and constant Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and that notwithstanding any sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of excommunication, or depriuation denounced, or to be denounced against <hi>his Maiestie</hi> by the Pope, they may with a safe conscience (marke well what I say) and also in practise they are bound, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to <hi>his Maiestie,</hi> and obey him in temporals, as still remaining their true and lawfull <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> and to resist any such sentence of Excommunication, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuation. The reason wherefore I affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that Catholikes might with a safe conscience adhere to <hi>his Maiestie,</hi> and resist the Popes sentence of depriuation, was, for that it is a probable opinion, and which with a safe conscience, and without danger of Heresie, error, or temerity, may bee embraced by Catholikes, that the Pope hath no authority to depose Princes, nor to inflict temporall punishments by way of coërcion, but that the last punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to which the Ecclesiasticall power is extended, are onely Ecclesiasticall and
<pb n="20" facs="11"/>
spiritual censures. Wherefore, that which this Author affirmeth, that I confesse, that it is probable, that the Pope can depose Princes is vntrue, vnlesse he meane that I confesse it for disputation sake, or as we vsually say, <hi>Dato non concesso, it being giuen, not graunted,</hi> for that it maketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for, or against the question which is in hand. Therefore positiuely I neither affirme it, nor deny it, neither with that part of the contradiction, <hi>Whether it bee probable, that the Pope can depose, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be probable, that the Oath may not be taken,</hi> doe I intermeddle: but whereas our Aduersaries doe with so great violence mayntaine, that it is certaine, and an vndoubted doctrine of Faith, that the Pope can depose, and that the Oath cannot bee taken, I at this present doe affirme the contrary, <hi>That it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that the Pope cannot depose, and that the Oath may lawfully be taken.</hi> Neither doe I, as this Authour imposeth vpon me, take <hi>probable</hi> in that sense, as <hi>Cicero</hi> in his Paradoxes did take it, when he affirmed, <hi>That nothing is so incredible, which by argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may not be made probable,</hi> taking <hi>proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> for that which hath som shew or color of probability, or do I take <hi>probable</hi> for that
<pb n="21" facs="11"/>
which I hold for <hi>probable,</hi> howsoeuer ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surde it be, (as this Authour absurdly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, that without doubt I doe) but I doe take <hi>probable</hi> in that sense, as Diuines doe take a <hi>probable opinion</hi> and which may be followed with a safe conscience, as I declared out of <hi>Vasquez,</hi> and hereafter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this Authour, and his confused de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of <hi>probable,</hi> which serueth onely to intangle the consciences of the simple, I will more at large declare, in which sense no Heresie or erroneous doctrine can bee made <hi>probable,</hi> the contrary being deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Church, as this doctrin for the Popes power to depose neuer was, but hath euer beene impugned by Catholike Writers vpon sufficient grounds, and now lately condemned by the State of France, as pernicious and damnable doctrine.</p>
   <p n="10">10 But the second and principall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, which I brought for the securing of <hi>his Maiestie,</hi> and which this Author <hi>T. F.</hi> fraudulently concealeth, wherefore Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Catholikes not onely may in specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the reason aforesaide, but also in <hi>practise are bound,</hi> to adhere to <hi>his Maiesty,</hi> and to resist the Popes sentence of depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, was, for that, supposing specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely
<pb n="22" facs="12"/>
it be vncertaine, whether the Pope hath any such power to depose a King, or no, it is an vndoubted rule among Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, and grounded vpon the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and principles of Diuinity, that <hi>in causa dubia, siue incerta, melior est conditio possidentis. In a doubtfull and disputable case the state of him that is in possession is the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> And againe, <hi>Cum sunt iura partium obscura fauendum est reo potius, quàm acto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, VVhen it is vnknowne, which of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that are in suite hath right, the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant is to bee preferred before the plaintiffe.</hi> Seeing therefore that from the very first beginning of this Controuersie, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the authority of Popes, and immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Kings; that is, from the time of <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the seuenth, who was the first Pope that challenged vnto him this temporall power ouer Kinges, this authority of the Pope to depose Kinges (call it temporall or spirituall, as you please) hath beene vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, disputable, and euer contradic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Catholikes, both Kinges and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and therefore it cannot be said that the Pope was euer in possession of this au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, (although we should grant, that power, right, or authority may be said to
<pb n="23" facs="12"/>
be possessed in that sense as possession is taken in Law, whereof in my Answere to this Authors Reply, I wil more at large dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course) it consequently followeth, that what opinion soeuer any Catholike fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>speculatiuely,</hi> concerning the Popes power to depose, yet in <hi>practise,</hi> vntill this Controuersie, concerning the Popes au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to depose Kings, and the immunity of Kings not to be deposed, shall be deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as yet it is not, he cannot with a good conscience endeuour to thrust out a King so deposed from the Kingdome, or Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions which he lawfully possesseth. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the end of my Apologie I wrote these expresse words, of which also in my Epistle Dedicatory to his <hi>Holinesse</hi> I made mentiō <hi>And therfore if eyther Pope, Prince, or any other forainer, should attempt to thrust an hereticall Prince out of the Kingdome which he possesseth; this Controuersie concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the deposition of Princes being vndeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, he should contrary to the rules of Iustice do himselfe most manifest wrong. And much more a Subiect cannot be excused from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest treason, what opinion so uer hee doth speculatiuely maintain concerning the Popes temporall power, who practically vnder colour
<pb n="24" facs="13"/>
perchance of deuotion to the See Apostolike, not duly also considering the bond of his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance towards his Soueraigne, should en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to thrust his lawfull Prince out of his Kingdome which he possesseth, notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any Excommunication, or sentence of depriuation denounced by the Pope against him.</hi> Wherefore it is apparant, that in practise I taught it to bee absolutely false, that the Pope hath authority to depose Princes.</p>
   <p n="11">11 Consider now <hi>(good Reader) first</hi> the vnsincere dealing of this Author, who concealeth the cheefest part of my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in securing <hi>his Maiestie</hi> of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant loyalty and allegiance, wherein all his Catholique Subiects are in conscience bound vnto him, that thereby hee may cause <hi>his Maiestie</hi> to be iealous of my fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie, and to account me no good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, as this Authour falsely affirmeth, that I am neither a good Subiect, nor a good Catholike, or Childe of the Church. But I trust in God, that it will appeare to all men, that <hi>Insurrexerunt in me testes iniqui, &amp; mentita est iniquitas sibi,</hi> That <hi>false wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses are risen vp against me, and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse hath belyed her selfe;</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>al.</hi> 26.</note> and that I will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="25" facs="13"/>
prooue my selfe to bee both a good Subiect to <hi>his Maiestie,</hi> and also a dutifull child of the Catholike Church.</p>
   <p n="12">12 <hi>Secondlie,</hi> consider the reason, why this Authour is so greatly offended, that I at this present doe onely take in hand (by answering probably all the arguments which on the contrary side are to be obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted) to shew, that it is at least-wise pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that the Pope hath no authority to depose Princes; and consequently, that any man may with a probable and safe conscience take the Oath; (for that the doctrine concerning the Popes authority to depose, is by this Authours owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, the maine question betwixt him and me, and the cheefe ground wherefore the Oath is iudged to be vnlawfull.) His reason therefore is, for that hee saw right well, what great aduantage I had against him, and what little aduantage hee had against me, in arguing or rather answering in this sort, and therefore he calleth it in heat of his zeale, <hi>The most deuolish deuice that any man could inuent.</hi> And truly if I should at this first beginning haue treated of this Controuersie in any other manner, then by handling it <hi>probably,</hi> in that sense
<pb n="26" facs="14"/>
as I haue declared, I might worthily haue beene censured of great imprudency, in giuing my Aduersary more aduantage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst mee then was needfull. For this is the State of the question, <hi>whether it can be cleerely conuinced by the authority of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, Ancient Fathers, Generall Councels, or by necessary inferences from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, as our Aduersaries pretend to conuince, that it is an vndoubted doctrine of Faith, and the contrary not be defended by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Catholike, that the Pope hath power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose Princes; and consequently that the oath cannot lawfully be taken.</hi> This is the questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Marke now the aduantage I haue: for <hi>first</hi> I am not to prooue but onely to aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer: to defend, not to oppose: <hi>Secondlie,</hi> it is sufficient for me, that my answers be onely probable; but there Replyes must not bee onely probable, but also conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and which with any probabilitie cannot bee answered. So that if I should goe about at the first to proue my opinion to be most true, which my aduersary affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not to be questionable, I should, as it is euident, greatly disaduantage my selfe. For in such Controuersies, as are so vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently maintained by the Aduersary, that
<pb n="27" facs="14"/>
he will not grant the contrary part to bee questionable, it is necessary to proceed by degrees; first to make the thing question<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and disputable, which the aduerse part will not haue to be called in question: and after this is once agreed vpon, then to examine whether opinion be the truest. For perchance it may fall out, that as the opinion for the immaculate Conception of our <hi>B. Lady,</hi> before <hi>Scotus</hi> did oppose himselfe therein against S. <hi>Thomas</hi> and his followers, was scarse accounted probable, yet afterwards it was daily more and more followed, so that now it is esteemed to be the farre more true opinion: and as <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonsus Salmeron,</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">In cap. <hi>5.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Rem. disp. <hi>51.</hi> Sect. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> inde.</note> and <hi>Fa. Suarez</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">Tom. <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi> disp. <hi>3.</hi> sec.</note> doe affirme, <hi>Agreed vpon by the consent almost of the Vniuersall Church, and of the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall writers, Bishops, Religious Orders, and Vniuersities;</hi> and as that opinion, which holdeth that the Pope hath not power to dispence in the solemne vow of religious chastitie, neither in any lawfull marriage before it be consummate, is accounted by very many learned men to bee the farre truer opinion, notwithstanding the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise of many Popes to the contrary: So it may fall out, that in processe of time this
<pb n="28" facs="15"/>
opinion that denieth the Popes authority to depose Princes, may bee embraced by almost all Ecclesiasticall Writers, Bishops, Religious Orders, and Vniuersities, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the practise of many Popes, and the vehement opposition of the Iesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites at this present time to the contrary.</p>
   <p n="13">13 <hi>Thirdly,</hi> consider how little behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding are English Catholikes to this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor <hi>T. F.</hi> who will needes enforce them euen with the temporall ouerthrowe of themselues, and of their whole posteritie to defend that doctrine to bee of faith, which the State of France hath condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for <hi>scandalous, seditious, damnable,</hi> and <hi>pernicious,</hi> and also endeuoureth to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade <hi>his Maiesty,</hi> that no Catholick can, according to the grounds of Catholike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, be a true, and loyall Subiect to <hi>his Maiestie,</hi> but at the Popes pleasure, or which is all one, so long onely as the Pope shall not depose him, which hee may doe at his pleasure. But we haue great affiance in <hi>his Maiesties</hi> singular wisedome, and clement disposition, wherof we haue had both by <hi>his Maiesties</hi> gracious Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,<note place="margin">Published after the discouerie of the <hi>Gun-powder</hi> trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</note> publike bookes, and effectuall deeds sufficient triall, that he will not bee
<pb n="29" facs="15"/>
drawne by the false suggestion of this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, (who would haue all Catholikes to be of the same violent spirit as hee is) to haue all his Catholike Subiects, in the same degree of iealousie, but that he will euer make a distinction betwixt them, who are his true hearted Subiects, and most loyall in all temporall affaires, and wil aduenture all, that they haue, and are, in defence of <hi>his Maiesties</hi> Royall person, and dignitie, against any sentence of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuation whatsoeuer, which shall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced against him by the Pope,<note n="i" place="margin">For so much did those 13. Reuerend Priests M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
         <hi>D. Bishop,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
         <hi>Colleto</hi> &amp; the rest by a publik Act bear in date the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> of Ianuary 1602. pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mise to <hi>Queene Eli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>zabeth:</hi> the copie wher of thou maist see my Appen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dix, page 346.</note> (assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring themselues, that it is conformable to the grounds of Catholike Religion which they professe, and not repugnant to that spirituall obedience wherein they stand bound to the supreme Pastour of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church) and those other Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, who thinking it to bee a point of faith, that the Pope hath authoritie to dethrone Soueraigne Princes, will onely defend <hi>his Maiestie,</hi> and yeeld him tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall obedience, vntill the Pope, after his sentence of depriuation shall command them the contrarie. And therefore let this Author <hi>T. F.</hi> assure himselfe, that all his clamorous words, and threatning spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="30" facs="16"/>
shall nothing discourage mee from defending the truth, neither am I prest on, to write against him or any other, to shew my wit, as hee falsely affirmeth, or for hope of any temporall lucre, or prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but meerely and sincerely for the loue I beare to God, Religion, the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like truth, my Prince, and Countrey: for which causes I neither am, nor euer vvill be ashamed to be prest on, to write against this <hi>T. F.</hi> or any other such like Authour, who liuing in other countreyes, and out of danger to loose any thing, but rather in hope to obtaine aduancement by their writings, will presse English Catholikes to defend, with danger of loosing all that they haue, &amp; of incurring their <hi>Soueraigne</hi> his high displeasure, that Doctrine to bee of faith, which the State of France ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counteth <hi>damnable,</hi> and enioyneth the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suites vnder paine of treason to preach the contrarie, as thou shalt perceiue by the Decree, which followeth, which is true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly translated out of the French copie, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at Paris, vvhich I haue conferred with this English.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>