<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Gentlemen readers.</title>
           <author>Greene, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119748_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02129</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12269</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119748</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Gentlemen readers.</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Mamillia : A mirrour or looking-glasse for the ladies of Englande. Wherein is disciphered, howe gentlemen vnder the perfect substaunce of pure loue, are oft inueigled with the shadowe of lewde lust: and their firme faith, brought a sleepe by fading fancie: vntil with ioyned with wisedome, doth awake it by the helpe of reason. By Robert Greene graduate in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Woodcock, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>3, 37 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Gentlemen readers.</head>
   <p>AFter that, Gentlemen, I had neither wel furnished nor finished
this imperfect peece of woorke, but brought it to a bare ende,
whether it were for imitation or art, I haue almost forgot, but for
one it was, I chanced to reade diuers Epistles of sundrie men writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
to the readers, wherin I found the best learned of them also far
drenched in doubt of their disabilitie, &amp; almost fortified for feare
that want of skill shoulde be a blemish to their woorke, as (thinking
a flat confession should haue a plaine pardon) they cal their bookes
vanities, shadowes imperfect paterns, more meete for the Pedler
then the Printer, toyes, trifles, trash, trinkets. Some comparing thē
to cheeses, neither worth the tasting, nor eating, so their books, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
worth the reading nor hearing: and yet the worst of them all
so perfectly polished with the pumice stone of eloquence, as in them
nature and art doe striue for supremacie. If then those learned
men doe count their works but counterfeit, that were carued with
such curious cunning, and tearmed them trash which were Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant
ware: what shall I call mine, which is of such simple stuffe, as
it is neither worth the cheaping nor chaunging? Surely I wil leaue
the name to the readers gentle iudgement, because I cannot finde
one bad enough, that euery one may tearme it as their fancy lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
them. For there is no chaffer so charie, but some will cheape;
no ware so bad, but some wil buy; no booke so yll but some will both
reade it and praise it; &amp; none againe so curious, but some wil carpe
at it. Wel, so many heades, so many wittes. If Gentlemen will take
my booke as a toy to passe away the time, and weigh mere of my
meaning then of the matter, and more of my wil, then eyther of my
wit, or the worke; if I say, they shall shew me this curtesie, it shal be
both a spurre to prick me forward to attempt further, and a suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
recompence for my trauell,</p>
   <signed>Robert Greene.</signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>