<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE ANTIENT company of Blacksmiths in Lon∣don, &amp; especially to the Master, Wardens and Assistants therof, all grace &amp; happines in this and the life to come.</title>
           <author>Bachiler, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119075_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03445</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13566</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119075</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE ANTIENT company of Blacksmiths in Lon∣don, &amp; especially to the Master, Wardens and Assistants therof, all grace &amp; happines in this and the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Bachiler, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon preached before the antient company of Black-smiths in S. Marie Magdalens Church in London on Saint Iohn Baptist day last. 1611. By William Holbrook</title>
                 <author>Holbrooke, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 41, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE ANTIENT company of Blacksmiths in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, &amp; especially to the Master, Wardens and Assistants therof, all grace &amp; happines in this and the life to come.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ondering with my</hi> selfe (beloued) to whome I should dedicate this labour, I found none that had greater right or claime to it then your selues: at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest of some of you it first began to be, &amp; came to be sounded <hi>viva voce</hi> in the eares of you and many other. At the earnest request of the some it now commeth forth to a further view, which I thought should neuer haue seene the Sunne any more. Further, the matter of it in some part concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth you onely, and was perticularly dressed and serued for your instruction; though there be many dishes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to you and others to feed vpon, for these respects me thinks I should wrong you, if I should dedicate it to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other: My desire in penning it, is the same it was in preaching it, that you may be edified and taught to liue soberly, righteously, and holily, in this present world, &amp;
<pb facs="3"/>
I haue peace of conscience both in the one and the other: I affected plainenes in speaking, so I haue in writing, and therein kept my selfe as neare as I can, with the helpe of my briefe notes, to the method phrase and matter, I obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the deliuery of it. Accept it according to the worth of the matter, looke vpon that, not vpon my rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in handling it: the meat is good, though happily an other Cooke might haue dressed and serued it in more skilfully. Thus I leaue it to your charitable and christian acceptation; and you all, to the blessing of him who is blessed for euer: To whome I will pray (that as in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing this labour, I haue satisfied some of you) you all may according to the desires of my heart, receaue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and instruction by it.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Christian friend, and hearty wel-wisher: WILLIAM HOLBROOKE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>