<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my dearest Cousins, A. B. C. D.</title>
           <author>U., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119623_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68832</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24508.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119623</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my dearest Cousins, A. B. C. D.</title>
                 <author>U., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe vievve of the weake grounds of popery : as it was propounded to D. Norrice, priest, by T.V. gent: and returned without answere</title>
                 <author>Udall, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <publisher>Cooke, Matthew.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Macham, Samuel 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 101, 9 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To my dearest Cousins, A. B. C. D.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y dearest Cousins: with what zeale and feruencie (both in my prayers, and other indeuours) I haue euer desired wee might be of one mind &amp; heart, God,<note place="margin">Act. 6.</note> and mine owne conscience can best testifie, and your selues may partly witnes with me. For, as touching the means to this our atonement (namely, conference with the learned of ech others side, and reading their bookes) you know well, I (for my part) haue neuer refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed it, but euermore gladly imbraced, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently sought after it: that so, if truth (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of great vaunts were made) had been found on your side, my heart first, &amp; then my hand, might readily haue subscribed thereto. But, when I consider the doctrine of your Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists,<note place="margin">Tit. 3. Sect.</note> (and the answerable practise of their disciples) forbidding you not onely to reade our bookes, but to hold conuersation (much more to haue conference) with vs, (who must
<pb facs="3"/> be Heretikes because they tearme vs so): yea, when I see they blush not to affirme, That <hi>we are not to be heard;</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>r. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ect. 2.</note>
      <hi>no, not though we speake the trueth:</hi> I almost despaire of your conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion; seeing the means are prohibited. Now, how much meeter it were, in a case of such consequence (being no lesse than the eternal safegard of your soules) to leaue them, with their errors; and to hearken rather, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme your faith, to the doctrine of Christ and his Apostles, I referre it to any seeing iudgement. For, the vniuersall consent of all the ancient Fathers, alloweth <hi>the Scriptures for the onely Rule of faith; as conteining in them, all doctrine necessary to saluation.</hi> And albeit I haue sufficiently (among others) cleared that question in this smal Treatise following; yet will I somewhat inlarge the proofe of it in this place; to the end you may better knowe, That though you send vs (for instruction) to to the Fathers: yet they send vs backe again to the <hi>Scriptures, as the onely and sufficient Rule to direct vs.</hi> And, in handling this point, I will not much insist vpon diuine authority; since I know you relye chiefly (if not wholly) on the Fathers. Onely I will vrge these few te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonies of Scripture: which ought to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile more with euery true Christian, than all
<pb facs="3"/> the Fathers, how learned soeuer. First, our Sauiour willeth vs, <hi>to search the Scriptures, for that in them we thinke to haue eternall life.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Io. 5.39. Mark. 1224.</note> And he taxeth the Pharises of error, because they were ignorant of the Scriptures.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.15, 16, 17.</note> S. <hi>Paul</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise affirmeth that they are able to make vs <hi>wise vnto saluation; that the man of God may be perfite, instructed to euery good worke.</hi> And if this perswade you not, I haue no hope that any Father can: for as Christ saith,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.29, 30, 31.</note>
      <hi>They haue Moyses and the Prophets, if they will not heare them, neither will they beleeue if one rose from the dead.</hi> Now, as to the Fathers, though your side pretend so much to reuerence them, yet in this question, they wholly reiect them, and that indeede not without cause; seeing their authority in this one point, might proue the downefall of your whole Religion: it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing confessed by some great Champions on your side, That many and most of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines wherin you varie from vs, are groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on Traditions, and not on the Scriptures: as any that will take the paines to reade, may see, in <hi>Peter Soto,</hi> against <hi>Brentius;</hi> in the fift chapter of <hi>Canisius</hi> Catechisme, &amp; in the<note n="*" place="margin">In fine fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulae, 6.</note> 5 booke of <hi>Lyndans Panoply:</hi> yea,<note n="*" place="margin">Scripto su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> aedito tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore Trid. Concil.</note>
      <hi>Andradius</hi> saith, That the greatest part of <hi>Catholike Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is left vnto Traditions of the Church not
<pb facs="4"/> written.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>anopl. li. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 22. demē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ssimae insa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>iae,</note> And the said <hi>Lyndan</hi> saith, <hi>It is most extreme madnes to think, that the whole &amp; entire Body of Euangelicall doctrine is to be fetched out of the Apostolike letters written with inke, and out of that little booke of the new Testament.</hi> And therefore so much the more are your leaders &amp; seducers to be taxed, who perswade their folowers, that the greatest differēce between them and vs, is touching the <hi>Sense of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> wheras euery man of common sense wil easily iudge, that, <hi>where there is no Text, there needs no Interpreter.</hi> But let vs briefly see what opiniō the Fathers were of, in this cōtrouersie betweene vs, and how they haue vnderstood that Scripture, which D. B. P. calles the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants <hi>Achilles,</hi> which hee onely barkes at, without further hurt.<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> B. booke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>gainst M <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>erkins, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ed the 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>im. 3. the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rot. Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>es. Hom. 9.</note>
      <hi>Chrysostome</hi> vpon the same Text sayth, <hi>If any thing be needefull for vs to learne, or to be ignorant of, there</hi> (meaning in the Scriptures) <hi>shal we learne it: If to reproue falsehood, from thence shal we draw it; if any thing lacke to be corrected or rebuked; which must be had vnto exhortation, vnto comfort: there also doe we learne it.</hi> Likewise Ho. 8. vpon the 15. verse he saith, <hi>The scriptures do teach both what things are to be done, &amp; what not to be done. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoret</hi> vpō the same place saith, <hi>The scripture is inspired of God, Therfore he teacheth the kinds
<pb facs="4"/> of vtilitie: It is profitable to teach; for, whatsoeuer we know not, we learne out of it: To reproue; It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth our wicked life: To correct; for it exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that they which haue gone astray, returne to the right way: To instruct in righteousnesse; for it teacheth vs the kinds of vertue, that the man of God may bee perfit, furnished to all good workes. All these things doe attribute and ascribe perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the God of all. Primasius</hi> saith, <hi>Out of the scriptures he that is ignorant is taught; Hee that is insolent, is reprooued; He that erreth, is corrected; He that can keep no measure, is instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to Iustice; to euery good worke, not vnto one. Oecumenius</hi> sayth, after he hath rehearsed the particular vtilities, to teach all true opinions, and good works, to reprooue errors &amp; vice, he concludeth, that the man of God may be, <hi>not onely partaker after a vulgar maner of euery goodworke, but perfect and compleate by the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the scriptures. Not to some kind of good worke, and to some not: But to all and euery good worke,</hi> saith <hi>Theophilact. Athanasius</hi> saith,<note place="margin">Atha. contr. gent. Chrys. ope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> imperf. in Mat. Ho. 41. Aug. in Ioh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Tract. 44.</note>
      <hi>The holy scriptures inspired from heauen are suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for all instruction of trueth. Chrysostome</hi> saith, <hi>whatsoeuer is requisite for saluation; all that is fully laid downe in the Scripture.</hi> S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi> sayth, <hi>There were chosen to be written, such things as seemed (to the holy Ghost) sufficient for
<pb facs="5"/> the saluation of the faithfull.</hi> And in his second booke against <hi>Cresconius,</hi> the Grāmarian, he saith, <hi>That there is an Ecclesiasticall Canon or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, whereunto belong the bookes of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apostles: By which bookes, we iudge all other writings both of the faithful, &amp; of the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hier. sup. Agge. cap. 1.</note>
      <hi>Hierom</hi> sayth, <hi>Those things which of their owne heads they deuise, as though they came by Apostolike Tradition, without the authority and testimony of the holy Scriptures, the sword of Gods word striketh.</hi> Infinite be the Authorities of the Fathers, which might be brought to this purpose: but I will conclude the point with <hi>Vincentius Lirinensis</hi> (whome D.B.P. in his booke against M. <hi>Perkins,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Vincent. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Haeres.</note> beleeueth not to haue any such wordes) who saith, <hi>The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of the Scripture is perfect and sufficient, and more then sufficient to al things.</hi> And again, <hi>Not that</hi> (saith he) <hi>the Canon alone is not sufficient for all things.</hi> These Fathers I hope knew the Scriptures aswell as D.B.P. or any other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist: and yet notwithstanding al his (&amp; their) obiections, the Protestāts <hi>Achilles</hi> (as he tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it) stands vnimpeacht by any thing that this (or any other) cauiller hath said. And yet notwithstanding these euident places, brought by the general consent of all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers against the <hi>fundamētal Ground of Popery:</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/> Your Rhemists wil tel you,<note place="margin">Rhem. Test. 2. Thes. 2. sect. 18.19.</note> if you wil beleeue them, that they haue (to the contrary) <hi>plaine Scriptures, all the fathers, most euident reasons, that wee must either beleeue Traditions, or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all.</hi> And that S. <hi>Augustine</hi> often wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, <hi>That many of the articles of our Religion, and points of highest importance, are not so much to be prooued by Scriptures, as by Tradition.</hi> But if we aske them where S. <hi>Austine</hi> wrote this <hi>(often),</hi> and that <hi>(of many articles of Religion and poynts of highest importance)</hi> it must be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned with <hi>Non est inuentus; Not to be found in S.</hi> Austin. But they perceiuing the whole waight of their cause to lie in this,<note place="margin">Rhem. Test. fol. 559.</note> haue mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shalled nine Fathers in a ranke, to proue, <hi>that we must either beleeue Traditions, or nothing:</hi> And yet the very same Fathers haue shewed, That no matter of faith, or of any moment to saluation, must bee receiued or beleeued without the Scriptures;<note place="margin">Cypr. ad Pomp. cont. epist. Stepha. Basil. contr. Eunomium. lib. 3.</note> and the Fathers often times by <hi>Traditions</hi> vnderstand matters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained &amp; proued out of the scriptures, &amp; that in regard the same was deliuered also by word. And many times by <hi>Traditiōs</hi> they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstād ceremonies and customs. Now chuse whether you will grant, <hi>a flat contradiction in the Fathers;</hi> or reconcile them thus; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with vs, <hi>Ergo, the Traditions they meane,
<pb facs="6"/> be no parts or points of the Christian faith:</hi> For we haue their plain confession, <hi>That all things necessary to saluation, are comprised in the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures:</hi> you produce them to witnes, <hi>That your Traditions be not comprised in the scriptures. Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi> by your owne deponents wee conclude, <hi>That your Traditions be neither necessary to sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, nor points of the Catholike faith.</hi> Looke wel to this <hi>Issue,</hi> They must either dissent frō you, or from themselues. Now if you will compare the late doctrine of the <hi>Romish Church,</hi> with these Fathers; it shal be euident, That they haue not only dissented frō them, but also vttered open blasphemy against the sacred Scriptures. First Cardinal <hi>Cusanus</hi> inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuleth his booke, <hi>De authoritate ecclesiae &amp; Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilij supra &amp; contra scripturam: Of the the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Church &amp; Coūcel aboue &amp; against the scriptures. Syluester Prierias,</hi> master of the Popes palace,<note place="margin">Contr. Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. cōclusi. de pot. Papae</note> saith, <hi>That indulgences are war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted vnto vs, not by the authority of the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but by the authority of the Church and Pope of</hi> Rome, <hi>which is greater.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Boniface</hi> the Archbishop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> saith, <hi>That all men so reuerence the Apostolike See of</hi> Rome, <hi>that they rather desire the ancient institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Christian Religiō from the Pope, than from the holy scripture.</hi> This saying the Pope hath
<pb facs="6"/> so approued, that he hath caused it to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serted into the Cannon lawe.<note place="margin">Dist. 40. c. Si Papa.</note>
   </p>
   <p>Another saith, <hi>whosoeuer resteth not on the doctrine of the Roman Church, and B. of</hi> Rome,<note place="margin">Syluest. Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. contr. Luther.</note>
      <hi>as the infallible rule of God; à qua sacra scriptura roburtrahit &amp; auctoritatem: from which the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred scripture draweth strength and authority, he is an heretike. Eckius</hi> saith,<note place="margin">De Ecclesia.</note>
      <hi>Scriptura nisi eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siae auctoritate non est authētica: The scripture is not authētical, but by the authority of the church.</hi> Cardinal <hi>Hosius</hi> saith,<note place="margin">De expresso verbo Dei.</note>
      <hi>If any man haue the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>concerning any place of scripture, although he neither knowe, nor vnderstand, whether, and how it agreeth with the words of the scripture, notwithstanding he hath</hi> ipsissimū verbū Dei, <hi>the very word of God.</hi> Cardinal <hi>Cusanus</hi> saith,<note place="margin">Nicol. Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>san. ad Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem. epi. 7.</note>
      <hi>It is no maruel though the practise of the Church, expound the scriptures at one time one way, and at an other time another way: for the vnderstanding or sense of the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture runneth with the practise: And that sense a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with the practise, is the quickening spirit:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Henric. do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster sacripa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latij Romae ad Legatos Bohemicos sub Felice Papa 1447. Ad Bohem. ep. 2.</note>
      <hi>and therefore the scriptures follow the Church; but contrariwise, the Church followeth not the scriptures.</hi> Another saith, <hi>The Pope may change the holy Gospel, and may giue to the Gospel ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to place and time another sense.</hi> To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude therfore with Cardinal <hi>Cusanus, This is
<pb facs="7"/> the iudgement</hi> (saith he) <hi>of all them that thinke rightly, that foūd the authority &amp; vnderstanding of the Scriptures, in the allowance of the Church: and not contrariwise lay the foundation of the Church in the authority of the scriptures.</hi> I will not mention others that haue blasphemously said,<note place="margin">Vid. Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. exa. par. 1. pag. 47.</note>
      <hi>That the scriptures without the authority of the Church are no better than</hi> Aesops Fables. Thus you see how the Grounds of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giō are iustified by the Fathers, against these blasphemies of the Romish Church. And for that I knowe it commonly obiected, that we refuse in disputation &amp; conference to handle the groūds of Religion: I haue thought good in this smal Tract to examin (though briefly) the Grounds of your Romish Religion, dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue-wise; to the end, the truth may be the more liuely discerned, by the obiections and answers. Wherein if I haue not truely laid downe the Groūds of your Religion for the substance therof: Or that they haue either bin mistaken by me; or, that (vsing that breuity I haue done) they might be more strongly or effectually vrged on your side; or, that the reasons vrged on our behalfe, be either falsly alleaged, or not truly handled: I shall take it as a speciall grace done vnto me; &amp; an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt of a reciprocal loue in you, that the faults
<pb facs="7"/> thereof may bee shewed and manifested by some of the great Rabbies of your side: to the end that the weaknes of our cause being laid open, I may be drawen to ioine with you in the religion you professe; &amp; may be brought home to that fold, out of which, &amp; frō which I am sure in your iudgemēts I am departed &amp; gone astray as a lost sheep. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>is is a charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble request, &amp; ought not with any colours or sleights to be refused by any of those learned Priests in whom you haue interest; since they know of how great merite the winning of soules is. And they may the rather be incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged thereto, because these things as they are collected by me, are but the doings of a meere lay man; &amp; therfore (if at all) may with greater facility be refuted. But if the same shall be past ouer with general tearms (as heretofore it hath bin in the like) as a thing vnworthy the answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: Or that I am an heretike &amp; obstinate, and not to be dealt with: thē may you easily iudge, that either your credit is small with those of your profession: Or your loue &amp; charity very little to me, that so earnestly out of the simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of my heart desire an answer: Or else that the weaknes &amp; badnes of your cause, cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide the touchstone of truth; notwithstanding their great &amp; swelling brags, of challenging vs
<pb facs="8"/> to dispute with them, be so often sounded i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> your ears. And I would to God I might truly say of you, that I presume of my self, that yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> would reade &amp; ponder these things with in differencie, &amp; abandon partiality. To the ef<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fecting wherof, besides my praiers, I haue no better meanes than the <hi>Apostles doctrine,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Thess. 5.21 Iames. 1. Cor. 2.5. 2. Cor. 13.5 Iohn 4.1. Act. 17.11.</note> who willeth you &amp; vs all <hi>to examine all things, &amp; to hold fast that which is good, and not to haue the faith of our Lord Iesus Christ with respect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons; but to try the spirits whether they be of God</hi> therein following the example of the men o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Berea, who searched the scriptures daily,</hi> whether those things were so. Thus hauing some hope you wil folow this Councel &amp; cōman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement comming from so high an authority as the Spirit of God: and also for my satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction (if not for your owne) effect this my so charitable &amp; reasonable a request, as the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering hereof, I shal stil continue my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to opē our eyes that we may see the truth, and that we may be made one flocke &amp; one fold of that great Shepherd Christ Iesus, the Bishop of our soules: To whome, with the Father and the holy Spirit, be all honor, and praise, now and for euer. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours, in the Lord, T. Ʋ.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>