<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the curteous and friendly Reader.</title>
           <author>M., C.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119676_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06673</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17127</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119676</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the curteous and friendly Reader.</title>
                 <author>M., C.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second part of the historie, called The nature of a woman : contayning the end of the strife betwixt Perseus and Theseus. Compiled by C.M</title>
                 <author>C. M.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Joan</publisher>
                    <distributor>Knight, Clement</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the curteous and friendly <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it fares in the estate of al things that are so chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from their first, as if the Fathers of the first world liued to reuise this last, they should hardlie learne to know that wherein then they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. So fares it in this vse of these triuiall toyes, which men were wont to cal by the names of some personages, whose liues or deaths were deciphered therein: but now framing their fancies to a new fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion, they will needes haue them named according to their natures, <hi>Sicut trahit sua quemque voluntas.</hi> And for my selfe was loath to breake square, I haue intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led this Historie, <hi>The nature of a VVoman:</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
which though therein it answer not eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie mans priuat expectation in what they meane, yet could not I fit it better to the matter, containing indeede nothing but the enuious practises of two wicked wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: wherein if any take offence, let him for this time winke at my fault, as rather affecting to frame my selfe to the new fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion, that it should be accounted new stuffe, then following the old be esteemed as too stale.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours. C. M.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>