<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL and truely Religious, HENRY WALLOPE, Knight; the fat of Earth, and the dew of Heauen.</title>
           <author>B., M.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119308_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16943</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3836</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119308</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL and truely Religious, HENRY WALLOPE, Knight; the fat of Earth, and the dew of Heauen.</title>
                 <author>B., M.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The house of God : The sure foundation, the stones, the vvorkmen and order of the building. The incomparable strength of that house, and the vaine assaults and batteries of Satan and all his power. In a sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, December 24, 1626. By Matthevv Brookes</title>
                 <author>Brookes, Matthew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Cartwright, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL and truely Religious, HENRY WALLOPE, Knight; the fat of Earth, and the dew of Heauen.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Worshipfull:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>eneca</hi> will not haue it denyed, that a good Pylot is skilfull, albeit it be on dry land; his reason is, because being endowed both with contemplatiue and practicke knowledge, so much as may be thought necessary both to make him positiuely, and comparatiuely sufficient for that Art he is onely destitute of opportunity to bewray his iudgement, and ability. My case is iust so: I must sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely confesse my due respect euer since I was first known vnto you, and haue wanted nothing with the good Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, but occasion to shew it; let me this way call the world to witnesse that I honour you.</p>
   <p>That which put me vpon this Text, was the request of some of my friends made vnto me, for some reasons best knowne vnto them and me. How I haue answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their expectation, I know not; whatsoeuer this poore
<pb facs="3"/>discourse seemes to be, I shall desire you to accept it with the same affection that I bestow it on you; the gift is too light, if it be waighed against your fauours: but I hope you will respect the minde and ability of the giuer, imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating <hi>Augustus,</hi> who with as ready a hand receiued those few verses presented vnto him by a poore <hi>Greeke,</hi> as that great <hi>Arabian</hi> Courser giuen him by <hi>Titinius.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If I haue not meddled with any controuersed points (as the words of the Text seeme to promise, and as I presume it was expected) conceiue in charitie that I aimed chiefely at the present profit of my hearers: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, it had beene somewhat too presumptuous, conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the worth of all those who haue both disputed and written of these things. Howsoeuer, let me say this place of Scripture to be like vnto that leafe which beareth both the <hi>Antidote</hi> and the <hi>Aconiton:</hi> for certainly our aduersaries possessed with the spirit of slumber, doe most vilely abuse this Text, and are therefore baned in the same place were others are preserued.</p>
   <p>There remaineth nothing, but that I commend you and all yours to God in my prayers, which I will neuer cease to doe, and remaine euer,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours humbly at command, <hi>M. B.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>