<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MVCH HONORED AND RE∣VEREND, SIR HENRY WOTTON Knight, : Provost of Eaton Colledge, and to the Reverend and Right Worshipfull Mr. Doctor Collins, Vice-Provost: Mr. Weaver, Mr. Hales, Mr. Bateman, Mr Doctor Stokes, Mr. Harrison, and Mr. Clever; Fellowes of the same Colledge: his ever honored Patrones.</title>
           <author>Watts, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119538_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14832</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25129</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119538</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MVCH HONORED AND RE∣VEREND, SIR HENRY WOTTON Knight, : Provost of Eaton Colledge, and to the Reverend and Right Worshipfull Mr. Doctor Collins, Vice-Provost: Mr. Weaver, Mr. Hales, Mr. Bateman, Mr Doctor Stokes, Mr. Harrison, and Mr. Clever; Fellowes of the same Colledge: his ever honored Patrones.</title>
                 <author>Watts, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Mortification apostolicall : Delivered in a sermon in Saint Pauls Church, upon summons received for the Crosse: on the last Sunday in Easter terme, May 21. 1637. By VVilliam VVats, Rector of St. Albans Woodstreet London</title>
                 <author>Watts, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Cowper (Cooper), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MVCH HONORED AND RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEREND, SIR HENRY WOTTON Knight, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: Provost of <hi>Eaton Colledge,</hi> and to the Reverend and Right Worshipfull M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Doctor <hi>Collins,</hi> Vice-Provost: M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Weaver,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Hales,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Bateman,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Doctor <hi>Stokes,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Harrison,</hi> and M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Clever;</hi> Fellowes of the same <hi>Colledge:</hi> his ever honored Patrones.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Either my <hi>Affection,</hi> nor <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition,</hi> could consult happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyer for my <hi>Booke;</hi> then to make it <hi>partner</hi> with me in <hi>condition</hi> even to <hi>live Both,</hi> by the same <hi>Patrones.</hi> The <hi>livelyhood</hi> I by <hi>you</hi> enjoy; I value at a <hi>double Benefice▪</hi> for being conferred by the <hi>free,</hi> and <hi>cheerefull,</hi> and <hi>unexpected, undeserved</hi> consent;
<pb facs="3"/> of so <hi>many,</hi> and so <hi>approved</hi> Iudgements: my <hi>Credit</hi> also hath received a <hi>Preferment. Your liberall</hi> minds, (as <hi>free</hi> and <hi>royall</hi> as your <hi>Foundation)</hi> endure no other <hi>Simony,</hi> then the <hi>Thankfull Acknowledgements</hi> of <hi>your Beneficia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries:</hi> which to make <hi>tender</hi> of, in the most <hi>publike</hi> and <hi>hearty</hi> manner of expression; is the <hi>Instructions</hi> wherewith <hi>This</hi> is addressed to <hi>you.</hi> Honor it, (I beseech you), with <hi>your Livery:</hi> as <hi>you</hi> have the <hi>Author,</hi> with <hi>your Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</hi> And if the excellently learned <hi>Society</hi> of <hi>Eaton Colledge,</hi> shall vouchsafe a <hi>second Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence</hi> to my <hi>Booke:</hi> having one <hi>Fold</hi> more, then <hi>Ajax</hi> Buckler had; I shall well hope, it will be full <hi>Censure proofe.</hi> Quickly will eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Peruser</hi> understand, how <hi>able</hi> each of <hi>you</hi> is, to examine both my <hi>Reasons</hi> and <hi>Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties:</hi> and that I durst not enscribe any thing unto <hi>you;</hi> but what were <hi>Iustifiable.</hi> Vnder <hi>your Patronage,</hi> therefore; the <hi>Readers</hi> may be <hi>confident:</hi> that they are not abused. By <hi>you,</hi> then, shall they receive <hi>advantage,</hi> as well as the <hi>Author.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>To my <hi>Patrones,</hi> am I bound to give <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count;</hi> both of my <hi>Purpose,</hi> and my <hi>Title.</hi> that from <hi>you,</hi> the <hi>Readers</hi> may understand me.
<pb facs="3"/> My <hi>Intention</hi> is, to stirre up the <hi>Times</hi> to doe <hi>that:</hi> which by the <hi>Sermon</hi> they may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; the <hi>best men</hi> have done <hi>thus.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>My <hi>Title</hi> pretends to <hi>Apostolicall.</hi> for upon the <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Examples</hi> of the <hi>Apostles;</hi> is the <hi>Mortification</hi> founded, which I here <hi>preach</hi> for. Had I fetcht it from the <hi>Austeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> of the <hi>Prophets:</hi> it might, perhaps, have beene put off for <hi>Iewish.</hi> Had I derived it no <hi>higher</hi> then the <hi>Primitives:</hi> it might (so <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicate</hi> are some mens Iudgemens) have beene censured for <hi>superstitious.</hi> Therefore have I entitled it to the <hi>Apostles:</hi> who both revived the <hi>Mortifications</hi> of the <hi>Rechabites</hi> and the <hi>Prophets:</hi> and recommended them unto the <hi>Primitives.</hi> What-ever <hi>examples</hi> might also have beene produced, from the <hi>Essens</hi> or the <hi>Cynicks</hi> (which by many <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings,</hi> I could have enlarged) must yet also have resolved, into <hi>mortification Apostolicall.</hi> for 'twas the <hi>Apostles</hi> which did <hi>perfect,</hi> and (if I may so say) which did also <hi>Christen;</hi> that <hi>severe Philosophy.</hi> The <hi>lives</hi> of the holy <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitives,</hi> being the <hi>practicallest Expositors,</hi> of the <hi>Apostles:</hi> from them have I deduced the frequentest of my <hi>examples.</hi> This I can as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure,
<pb facs="4"/> that this same <hi>selfe denying, world-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> way of <hi>mortifying:</hi> was not, in those <hi>Ages,</hi> censured to be <hi>Popery.</hi> of which had this <hi>mortification</hi> any <hi>tack</hi> or <hi>relish:</hi> both my <hi>Iudgement</hi> and <hi>affection,</hi> would be averse enough; from becomming <hi>Brokers</hi> for it. Most knowne it is, that the examples of those plot-lesse <hi>Mortifiers;</hi> brought uncredible ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesses unto <hi>Christs</hi> Kingdome: and that in the most licentious <hi>Nations</hi> and <hi>Ages.</hi> And how highly God almightie expressed his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>pleased</hi> with them: the many <hi>miracles</hi> and <hi>blessings,</hi> which by them he vouchsafed to his <hi>Church;</hi> are abundant witnesses. And these not storyed, in uncertaine <hi>Legends:</hi> for which of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> hath not written them with <hi>admiration?</hi> Ill luck should both <hi>they,</hi> and I encounter with, (and the <hi>Readers</hi> with worse) should their <hi>examples</hi> now onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>unfruitfull.</hi> A more <hi>unhappinesse</hi> were it, for any to <hi>maligne</hi> them. which I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident none will doe, but the <hi>guiltie.</hi> Such, as maintaining too magnificent an opinion of their owne <hi>holinesse:</hi> shall like, <hi>Pachomius</hi>
      <note place="margin">Palladius; in Histor. Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siaca. in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cario.</note> disciples, grumble at the more mortified <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carius;</hi> for out-doing them in the <hi>austerities</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/> they professed. But the number of these, will be lesse, if this <hi>Doctrine</hi> takes.</p>
   <p>My <hi>Intentions,</hi> (God knowes) are honest. and with the same diligence I have <hi>written,</hi> will I <hi>pray:</hi> that God <hi>would vouchsafe a bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to them.</hi> For the more hopefull attaining whereof, I most humbly intreat the joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>your</hi> zealous prayers: <hi>ô you beloved of God.</hi> Vnto whose highest <hi>patronage,</hi> I hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily commend <hi>you</hi> all: my most honored <hi>Patrones.</hi> Resting</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From your Patronage, and my Parish, of Saint</hi> Albans <hi>Woodstreet London.</hi>
         <date>Iune 8. 1637.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your ever thankfull and obliged Clerke, VVILLIAM VVATS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>