<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORTHY SIR TIMOTHIE TRVNCHION: Alias BASTINADO, euer my part-taking friende: Clunnico de Curtanio sendeth greeting; wishing his welfare, but not his meeting.</title>
           <author>Snuffe, Clunnico</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119807_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11221</idno>
           <idno type="STC">775.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119807</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORTHY SIR TIMOTHIE TRVNCHION: Alias BASTINADO, euer my part-taking friende: Clunnico de Curtanio sendeth greeting; wishing his welfare, but not his meeting.</title>
                 <author>Snuffe, Clunnico</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Quips vpon questions, or, A clownes conceite on occasion offered : bewraying a morrallised metamorphoses of changes vpon interrogatories: shewing a litle wit, with a great deale of will; or in deed, more desirous to please in it, then to profite by it. Clapt vp by a clowne of the towne in this last restraint, hauing litle else to doe, to make a litle vse of his fickle muse, and carelesle carping. By Clunnyco de Curtanio Snuffe</title>
                 <author>Armin, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>White, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Ferbrand (Firebrand, Forbrand), William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORTHY SIR TIMOTHIE TRVNCHION: <hi>Alias</hi> BASTINADO, euer my part-taking friende: <hi>Clunnico de Curtanio</hi> sendeth greeting; wishing his welfare, but not his meeting.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worthy (but not Right</hi> Worshipfull, whose birth or grouth being in the open fieldes) I salute thy Crab-tree countenance with a low congeey, being stroke downe with thy fauour: whereas (kind sir) I some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time slept with thee in the fieldes, wanting a house ore my head; and that you then in kindnesse, because I was so kind, kindly to accept your kind companie, because I was vnkindly thrust out of my lodging; at that instant, you assured me to take my part in all dangers: I am now to make vse of your valloure, to protect me from insicion, or in deede from dirrision, in which I am now to wade deepely: but if I scape Monday, which is omminus to me, I shall thinke my selfe happie: and though Fryday be for this yeere Childermas day, yet it is no such day of danger to me; then on Tuesday I rake my Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney (to waite on the right Honorable good Lord my Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster whom I serue) to Hackney. Guard me through the Spit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle fieldes, I beseech yee, least some one in ambush endanger my braynes with a Brickbat vnsight or vnseene. Sweete
<pb facs="6"/> Sir <hi>Timothie,</hi> kind sir <hi>Timothie,</hi> tough sir <hi>Timothie,</hi> vse me with kindnesse, as you shall in the like commaunde me hereafter: whose Barke I will grate like Ginger, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouse it in Ale, and drinke a full cuppe to thy curtesie, when I am returnd to the Citie againe. I shalbe lesse fearefull, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing among my friendes: yet like a Burgomaister walke from Stationers shop to Stationers shop, to see what enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement my Booke hath; and who so disgrases it enuiously, and not iesting at it gently, at the least baslinado them, that bobbadillo like as they censure, so with him they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue reward. I confesse mine owne weaknesse, and will not iustifie my harebraind folly: but yet I thinke all men of my minde, gently to iudge, not rashly to reuile. Well, when my Bookes are in Paules Church-yarde, if they passe through Paules I care not, for in Fleet-streete I haue friendes that will take Lud-gate to defende me. What should I say? My trust is, that either my simplicitie of loue, or thy crueltie in cudgeling, will guard me from enuious tongues, whose teeth are all blacke with rancor of their spight; and whose tongues are milke white with hart burning heate: God keepe me from their byting; I had rather be stroken with a poysoned bullet: that were a death honorable, the other a life miserable. No more but this, say I am out of towne and heare not their ribald mockes, and by that meanes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse me from them, whose poysoned tongues will else abuse me.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine euer with true endeuour,</hi> Clunnico Snuffe. VALE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>