<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Stell, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119818_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07026</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17445</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119818</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Stell, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The bee hiue of the Romishe Church : a com [m] entarie vpon the sixe principall pointes of Master Gentian Heruet, a Romish Catholike his booke, which is deuided into sixe partes, as in the argument doth appeare. And an epistle made by the authour of this booke vnto Franciscus Sonnius, late Bishop of Antwerpe. Translated out of Dutch into English, by George Gylpen the elder</title>
                 <author>Marnix van St. Aldegonde, Philips van</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Schilders (Grapheus, Painter), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stell, Jan (Hans)</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>15, 346, 1 leave, 2 folded plates, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Christian Reader, thinke it not lost labour to reade this little booke, which as it beareth the name of a Bee hiue, so it conteineth good stoare of holesome honie. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles, take this short admonition by the way, that in reading the same, thou plaie not the parte of a Spider, which out of sweete and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doriferous floures sucketh deadlie poyson: for what is that else but to abuse a benefite, and to make that euill to thy selfe, which by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is good? I knowe it spites the Papistes, that their iuglings are espied: and I beleeue they will be so farre from singing a <hi>Requiem</hi> for his soule, by whome it was compiled, or from pitie to purchase him a pardon from the Popes good grace, that they coulde finde in their heartes, to appeale to the Spanishe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisition, and by their tormentes farre pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the paines of Purgatorie, to constraine both him, and them that shall reade it, to crie <hi>Peccaui.</hi> O charitable Catholikes. Be they such curst cattel in deede? Alas for pitie: God keepe vs out of their clawes. Will not
<pb facs="6"/>
Peter pence salue vp the sore? O, yes marie, that is meate for their mouthes. But will they frette and storme in suche sorte? Tut a pointe, they haue had the raine too long, it is time that they bite on the bridle. But farewell Papist: R▪ this pill, ô it will scowre and purge. Thus Gentle Reader (to conclude) thou hast such a booke, as will make thee pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie to all the practises of the Babylonicall beast, (Rome I meane) the denne of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons and diuels: which if it were translated into other tongues, by the industrie of the learned, as it is in none, but in Dutch and English, it would increase choler so abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Pope, the Colledge of Cardinals, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasteries of Monkes, Fraternities of Friers, Nestes of Nonnes, and the rest of the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saical Frie, as whole handfuls of Helleborus, or pounds of Colloquintida can neuer auoide: &amp; (wote you what?) that will pull downe their mother the holie Churche vppon her knees, with thought and sorowe. Well, I leaue the benefite of this booke to thy diligence in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. And thus farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in Christ,</hi> Iohn Stell.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>