<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>LENVOY.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119542_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14827</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25123</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119542</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>LENVOY.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A decacordon of ten quodlibeticall questions concerning religion and state : wherein the authour framing himfelfe [sic] a quilibet to euery quodlibet, decides an hundred crosse interrogatorie doubts, about the generall contentions betwixt the seminarie priests and Iesuits at this present</title>
                 <author>W.W. (William Watson)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 361, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>LENVOY.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE contents of this booke shall appeare in the Table of the Articles: meane while be pleased gentle Reader, to take these rules to guide you in this Discourse.</p>
   <p>First, be not hastie to censure of any part or parcell, vntill you haue read the whole booke throughout: if you will be free from partialitie, and rest reformed of errour, and quieted in Catholike vnitie, loue and peace.</p>
   <p>Secondly, if you find in some Page, the names of particular persons, places, &amp;c. expresly set downe, and in other Pages concealed: take the reason &amp; cause thereof to be this, to wit: that in the concealement, the respect is had to the hurt that might be done, by opening such matters, men, time, place, words, writings, &amp;c. and againe, in the expresse discouery of them, the respect is had to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon cause hindred by concealement of such persons, actions, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, take this for a rule infallible, that no secret is written of here in particular, which was not before publikely knowne aswell to our common ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries, as to our owne company: and that aswell by letters taken, as by their owne confessions in publike manner whom the fact concerned.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, be not too curious in these two points, vz. if you find sundry faults escaped by the Printer, as <hi>quae</hi> for <hi>quod, Malto</hi> for <hi>Malta, anno primo</hi> for <hi>actione prima,</hi> and many such like, which the prudent Reader may correct by the sense, and vpon his owne knowledge, without setting downe Errata here for euery particular. Againe, if you find some words more sharpe and biting then in your conceit is requisite, yet do not for that condemne either the whole Booke, which respecteth the matter, whereupon all our company in effect do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and not the words, sentences, or phrase of speech which respecteth the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of euery man with such a difference, as almost impossible to please all mens veines, or symbolize with their methods, conceits and meanings: neither yet do you vpon dislike of such speeches, or of the Author condemne the cause, or the rest of his brethren: for what is more common then for one man to giue censure and iudge of a case thus, and for another so: and withall euen in points of most importance, a controuersie decided in sacred synode, is set downe infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly true, but the Scribe notwithstanding in adding a reason of his owne in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planing the Text or Canon, may commit a great sinne and grosse errour, and yet not the decree of the Councell to be euer the worse thought of, or of lesse credite.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>