<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>H., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119433_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B13838</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12569</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119433</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>H., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The picture of Christ : The wonder of meditation, the earnest of eternitie, the touchstone of faith: or, A counterbuffe to despaire. Gathered from the great fountaine, and store house of liuing waters, the most ancient, sacred, holy, authenticall selfe-assuring, and canonicall scriptures, of the old and new testament</title>
                 <author>I. H.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 90, 6, 335, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="1" facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecause, gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of things inuisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, wherevpon the eternitie of life or death depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, can neuer bee too recent in memorie; things surpassing rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son being so subiect to obliuion. And that the soule of it selfe is so insatiable, neuer vpon earth ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing found any such contentment, but it still aspyred to some-what higher and more excellent; yea, euen then when it hath that, which it so earnestly but now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired, in full possession, becommeth weary of that: with <hi>Alexander</hi> when it hath all which earth can affoord, wishing for moe worlds. Thus farre the Heathen. But the
<pb n="2" facs="6"/> Soule, that is troubled with the greatnesse of sinne; that goeth crookedly, whose eyes faile (as <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruch</hi> speaketh) findeth this to be most true, when in the midst of all tentations, tribulations, crosses, and all other calamities whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer incident in this life, or rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by the Prince of darknesse; it onely hath recourse to things sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passing reason: there it stayeth: there it hopeth: there it belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth: and there onely it findeth rest; but chiefly, in the free pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises of the inuisible-visible God of all glory. This confirming pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, reposing vpon things inuisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to the Christian soule is a salue against all sores▪ no earthly thing can content it, vntill it rest vpon this promise, opposing it as a buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler against all miseries what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so euer. This doth the Prophet
<pb n="3" facs="6"/>
      <hi>Dauid,</hi> the true patterne of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity, in his booke of Psalmes notably expresse: but chiefly in that hundred and nineteenth; where he at length declareth, that all his confidence did onely relye vpon the promise: Sometimes, in these words, Remember the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise made vnto thy seruat, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou hast caused me to trust. It is my comfort in my trouble: for, thy promise hath quickned mee. Somtimes againe, Mine eyes faile for thy promise; saying, when wilt thou comfort me? And a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, How sweete are thy promises vnto my mouth! yea, more then hony vnto my mouth. In another place hee saith, I haue hid thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise in my heart, that I might not sinne against thee. How often in that Psalme doth he challenge the Lord of his promise in generall?
<pb n="4" facs="7"/> as it were, forcing the kingdom, in these words (according to thy promise.) And <hi>Iob,</hi> speaking of his obedience to the commandements, saith, that he esteemed these words more then his appointed food. All which, shew the vnexpressable power, and surpassing sweetnesse of the promise to a troubled soule, when faith hath once apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the truth of the promiser. Many are the examples, tedious to relate, how euen parcels of the promises haue exceedingly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted the children of God. The Scriptures are full of such places, where the height of consolation, is placed onely in the free promises of God in Christ: in whom (as the Apostle speaketh) all the promises of God, are yea and Amen. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is not giuen to euery one to search, nor in searching to find,
<pb n="5" facs="7"/> nor in finding to apply, nor apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to apply aright, without a harmonie. Therefore haue I (by the grace of God) as thou seest, gathered togither a heape of the cheefest promises: that when the soule in extreame anguish is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to cry out (at it is in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Isaiah</hi>) who among vs shall dwell with euerlasting burnings? and with <hi>Iob,</hi> that changes and armies of sorrows are against her; her eye casting out water, because the comforter that should refresh her soule is farre from her (as the Prophet in the Lamentation spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth) the Lord for the time seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing couered with a clowde, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than for his part hauing hid all the gratious and sweet promises of mercy, representing nothing vnto the sight, meditation, memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, but horror, curses and woe, and
<pb n="6" facs="8"/> the cruell reuenge, of a terrible thundring God, armed in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerity of his iustice, to throw it downe into the pit of hell with the deuill and his Angels for euer: She may also heerein presently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, that same God, which thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in Sinai, clothed with flesh, reconciled to vs, and his vnspeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able wrath appeased in his Sonne, who is the end and fulfilling of the law for righteousnesse to euery one that beleeueth; Finding also sufficiently therein, if the diuell assaile thee by Scripture (follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this our Sauiour Christ) to dash the lye with Scripture in his teeth againe. Which I offer vnto thy milde censure; not that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou shalt finde any perfect or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or collection of the heads ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered (for who can iudge as hee should aright, of such a bottōlesse, boundlesse, neuer-sounded depth?)
<pb n="7" facs="8"/> much lesse I, the vnworthiest of all): But onely as a morsell of some dainty dish, the sweetnesse wherof may stir vp &amp; allure thy appetite (if it be not already) to drinke at will of the great fountaine it self. But chiefly I intreat thee (who hast not onely this, but a great deale more in thy memory, euen <hi>y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
      </hi> whole frame it selfe, and canst bring it forth hand in hand, in well orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red squadrons and battel array, as time &amp; opportunity fitteth; either to confound the proud, or raise vp the humble; to beat down sinne, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish tentations, or any other thing that shall oppose it self against this mighty word) to whom the Lord reuealeth his secrets; whose lips should &amp; do preserue knowledge, to whom the spirit of prophecying is subiect; why (by thy heauen-a-spyring meditations, and then
<pb n="8" facs="9"/> Spirit-assisting power) canst, as it were, Metamorphose the hearts of the hearers, forcing some-times, a bribing <hi>Foelix,</hi> or prophane <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grippa</hi> (much more a true Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite) to tremble and cry out, thou almost perswadest me to be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, to leaue my sinnes, &amp;c.] to looke here-vpon with a gentle aspect: and (although thou thy selfe with thy Eagles winge, soa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest aboue high mountaines) not to disdeigne him, who farre off, looketh after thy flight in the low valleys: wishing to follow thee; but that fearing <hi>Icarus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, hee durst not presume with waxen wings.</p>
   <p>But to draw neerer the marke (because the promise shall auaile nothing, without assurance of the verity of the things promised)
<pb n="9" facs="9"/> thou hast first of all, a view of the perfection of the said word, by the word it selfe; the most assured te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony that may be. For, vnlesse an internall reuerence of this word (procured by it owne maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, and secret operation of the holy Ghost) assure thee of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie and verity thereof (cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing thee to cast aside all humane inuentions and reasons; onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing, and not carping, why, nor wherefore this nor that?) in vaine shall all other helpes and proofes bee. And therefore the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> in meditation thereof, had such delight therin; that hee confesseth that it was a Lanthorn to his feet, and a light to his paths: that it was most pure; the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse thereof euerlasting; the beginning and entrance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, truth and vnderstanding.
<pb n="10" facs="10"/> In another place, that it was as sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer tried in a fornace of earth se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenfold: being perfect, conuerting the soule, giuing wisdom vnto the simple, reioycing the heart, giuing light vnto the eies. And surely it is no meane assurance vnto vs of the vndoubted verity therof, that albeit it beat downe our damnable lusts &amp; affections (being so contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in all things to our vile &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature) yet notwithstanding, we reuerence &amp; imbrace it, as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Oracles: because a certain venerable maiest<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> shining therin, doth with such attractiue power, hale and draw the heart &amp; affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vnto it, beyond all other writs kindling therein ioy vnspeakable, assuring, that such strange effects as it worketh, could not proceed, but from the spirit of God. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is our part in all calamities and miseries to rest vpon this word; since the inspirer &amp; author
<pb n="11" facs="10"/> thereof is eternall, and the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and antiquity therof before al writts: and the rather if we shall a little neerer consider that well-ordred harmony of the two Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; how in the Old, the Law &amp; Prophets do all point at the Messi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as to come; all their types figures, offrings &amp; sacrifices, being to end with his comming; all their then perfectiō, consisting in his perfect oblation, sacrifice, &amp; free offering to come: Againe, how in the New, the Messias being come, requiteth their hopes, fulfilleth all their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies. pointeth back again at thē as need required, citing the law &amp; Prophets for confirmation of his doctrine; establishing the law Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, taking away the cursse there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, abrogating what was needfull of the Ceremoniall; Lastly, to make all sure, giuing, as behooued, his life for his sheepe; crying
<pb n="12" facs="11"/> vpon the crosse that all was fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed; and returning, whence (as a Father speaketh) he as God neuer was absent. This word hee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe commanded vs to search; therein to finde eternall life, <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> calleth it our life; and the Apostle <hi>Paul,</hi> the power of God vnto saluation; in another place telling, that it is able to make the man of God absolute and wise vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to saluation. What should I say of it? It is all in him, who is all in all.</p>
   <p>But heere, the monster of men, the all-abhorred Atheist (either that hee may with the more liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie cloake his knauery, or that hee will not beleeue but what by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son is demonstrated) of set purpose opposing himselfe against all that is of God, standeth vp with open mouth, denying all at the first
<pb n="13" facs="11"/> push, making a iest of this most holy word, and all the Miracles therein; dreaming of (I know not what) absurdities. The Creation hee cannot abide, because it must presently lead him to the Creator. But, if there be any so impudently wicked in this our miserable Age, let vs grant it for a while, (which yet were abhominable blasphemie to maintaine) that the heauens and all the inuironing regions of the ayre were from euerlasting, (shewing notwithstanding the contrary, by their continuall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions leading vs to the first vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued moouer): yet would I one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know of them, from whence this little world, Man, did spring, if hee had no creation? setting aside all other vnreasonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; one man leadeth vs to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, vntill by degrees wee come
<pb n="14" facs="12"/> back to the first: and here I aske where hee had his beginning? for from eternitie he was not: which, his miserable and perishing na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, so subiect to changings, well sheweth: but chiefly his dissoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; eternity and change, like light and darknesse beeing so directly contrary. It were most absurd to thinke, that the woman and he did spring like a leafe, an hearbe, or a stalke of corne out of the earth: for then why might not the earth still haue produced such fruite? what needed then this change in beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one of another? Neither dare he (for his excuse) confesse a fall, whereof alteration, misery and change might haue ensued, and so the course of nature bee changed: vnlesse hee bee also forced to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse One, from whom they had fallen. Then must we of necessitie,
<pb n="15" facs="12"/> finde for Man a Creator (since he had a beginning, and a time wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was not) who (as the Spirit of God by <hi>Moses</hi> affirmeth, and all the Christian world euer since be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeued, yea and Heathen also) onely was God. Now, that omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Power, who (with such won<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der) of a peice of earth, to his owne holy image created him, was euen as able to create all other things before him, for him. But since wee are none of these miscreants, let vs leaue these men (whatsoeuer in their disputations, life, or sayings they maintaine) with <hi>Caligula</hi> to hide themselues at a crack of thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; resting assuredly vpon these scriptures: assuring our selues, that the vnserchable Depth Soule-qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eting power, great Antiquity, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty, Vnity, perfit Harmony, Sweet Simplicity, admirable Excellency, rich Pouerty,
<pb n="16" facs="13"/> graue Modestie, most holy Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and heart-inflaming feruency of them, are sufficient proofes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all Principalities and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers opposite, of their absolute per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
   <p>Heere I would willingly haue passed to the next; but that the mysterie of iniquity, the purple whore, the mother of abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the triple-crowned man of sinne (who vnder colour of the seruant of the seruants of God, exalteth himself as King of Kings and Lord of Lords) came in with his worme-eaten and dung-hill Traditions; which hee maketh equall vnto this word, in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where his word may passe for a law, or where men will beleeue that black is white, if he will haue it so; wresting these Scriptures, to whatsoeuer crooked sense hee
<pb n="17" facs="13"/> and his Parasites pleaseth; like vnto a piece of waxe making it receiue any impression; sealing it vp in an vnknowne toung from the vulgar, forbidding it vnto them on paine of damnation (as though they had no soules to saue) not without great policie of the diuell their grand Captaine; that the poore soules (being ignorant of this heauenly food, and onely Truth) might the better receiue, as Oracles, whatsoeuer lyes should thence-forth proceed from their blasphemous mouthes: contrary to the expresse command of our Sauiour Christ; who comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs to search the Scriptures, Neither is it lawfull to say, that our Sauiour spake onely to the learned Rabbies, but also to the poore people, to all, making no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of persons; vnlesse also
<pb n="18" facs="14"/> they dare affirme, that hee came onely for the redemption and sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of such. Who, but mad-men, durst impute imperfection to this word? since the Apostle to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie,</hi> commendeth, it to be able to make the man of God absolute and perfect vnto all good workes. Yet no maruaile hee and his <hi>Baala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> dare not abide the open touch of this word, closing it vp in a strange toung, in this, shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them-selues truly to be false coyne: not daring to abide the cleare shining of that light, whose brightnesse freed from the clowds of darknesse, (where by their fals<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood it was long detained) hath so shamed this age past, and yet doth their kingdome of darkenesse. No maruaile I say, for in it they heare no rules giuen for the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersion of states, stirring vp of
<pb n="19" facs="14"/> rebellions, killing and poysoning of Princes: discharging of sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects from their lawfull obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their Princes and Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours: massacring of thousands, men, women, and children, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pease their neuer-appeased furie: no foundation of their wicked <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nales</hi> Cardinales, abhominable and idolatrous Masse, their world of prophane ceremonies: and last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (for what yeares could reckon all?) of the sanctitie of Sathans last thunder-bolts, the Locusts of the bottomlesse pitte; sent post from <hi>Belzebub,</hi> for the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propping of his now-falling king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
   <p>I meane the Iebusites,<note place="margin">Non cum Iesu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>itis, si qui itis cum Iesuitis.</note>
      <hi>A Iesu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>itis:</hi> (Iesuites I should haue said) who beeing a vermine but now (to speake truely in respect of antiquitie) creept vppe: the
<pb n="20" facs="15"/> more to deceiue the world tooke vnto them the name of <hi>Iesus,</hi> that like Wolues in this lambes skinne, they might the better de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure the flocks: since which time they haue so multiplied <hi>Proteus</hi>-like transforming themselues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to innumerable shapes: that like the Frogges and Grashoppers of Egypt, they are a plague vnto all kingdomes where they remaine: not onely to the ground, (the best whereof by their good-will they ioyne to their Colledges) but also to soules and bodies, with the breath of their venemous doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, which they euery where sow, vnder coullour of fained holinesse and long prayers, (as our Sauiour speaketh of their brethren the Scribes and Pharisees) deuouring all Lords, Knights, Ladies and Widdowes houses, who once giue
<pb n="21" facs="15"/> eare to their inchanting Syren songs. Like vnto their father the diuell, if they can but get in one foote, will shortly bring also their body: (there-after ruling the roast,<note place="margin">Bella sonat, sonat arma, minas sonat: omnia martis.</note> as the Prouerbe speaketh) But let them and their <hi>Bellum arma minans</hi> (famous like <hi>Ero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stratus</hi> for impiety) the diuell, and all, doe what they can: this word which already hath made such a breach in Babels falling towers, shall ere long finish that which it hath so happely begun.</p>
   <p>What should I say more of this barbarous, vncomfortable religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? our Sauiour Christ hath left vs a true note to know it, and them in it: (that hee that speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of himselfe seeketh his owne glory.) What I pray you hath the Church of Rome and all the Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie thereof beene doing these
<pb n="22" facs="16"/> hundreds of yeares past, but seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their owne glory? incurring that fearefull woe of the Prophet <hi>Ezekiell,</hi> to those sheapheards which neglect their flockes, feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themselues with the wooll and the fatte: killing those who are fed. And in <hi>Mathew</hi> (to know them by their fruites) where hee affirmeth, that a good tree (as they pretend to bee) cannot bring forth euill fruite. If wee shall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine some of their supereroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting fruits (to leaue Antiquitie, and haue recourse to bleeding me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie) <hi>Bartolomeus flet,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The numerall letters make the year 1572. the yeare of the massacre.</note>
      <hi>quia Gallicus occubat Atlas:</hi> leauing also <hi>Saint Bartholomews</hi> bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die massacre <hi>(quia animus me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minisse horret, &amp;c.)</hi> we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold two royall <hi>Henries</hi> wallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their dearest bloud: (would God all succeeding <hi>Henries</hi> would
<pb n="23" facs="16"/> learne to tame, and not trust, such wild beasts) the first killed by a <hi>Iacobine</hi> nouice, the seconds tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedie, most cruelly begunne by a Iesuite, who strooke him in the teeth (a bloodie presage of what ensued) and (who doubteth) fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed by their close politick knaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. But I had almost forgotten that horrible (yet silence shall best expresse it) Powder-treason: who can excuse them in this? since their Prouinciall <hi>Garnet,</hi> old in wickednesse, was cheefe Confessor to chis damnable action. Whose excuse was, that it was reueiled to him, vnder the sacred seale of confession; therefore not daring to disclose it.</p>
   <p>What monster could hee bee, which made such a lawe so direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly against the whole booke of <hi>God?</hi> was it not lawfull in such
<pb n="24" facs="17"/> a case to reueale? should so much mischiefe haue beene committed that good might haue ensued? thus might <hi>Lots</hi> daughters incest with their father, and the like bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused. But his Maiestie in his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie cleareth this c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ntrouersie, where hee prooueth that <hi>Garnet</hi> heard of it walking with another Iesuite, and what manner of fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned confession such a walking one could bee, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se who are accusto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to crouchings and kneelings to their Confessors at the like times well know. Yet why? It may be all was intended of meere loue, because our hereticall religion (as they terme it) could not haue brought vs vnto heauen: out of their cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>itable affection, chiefly to his sacred Maiestie, Queene, &amp; royall progenie, Bishops, Nobles, Barons, Iudges, and whole body of
<pb n="25" facs="17"/> state: working a worke of supere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation, like vnto <hi>Eliah,</hi> to haue sent them all vp for the more cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, like a whirle-winde, in chaires and seates conducted by fire vnto the clowds, for the more state, wearing a crowne, and in Robes. Belike to shew vnto God that royall magnificence; doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing least his all-seeing eye, which so long had spared them in the powder-mine, had now become dimne, not able other-wayes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde them.</p>
   <p>If th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se bee of the supereroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting workes of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ir perfectest, such as they esteeme their Iesuites and Iesuited ones to be; for which their powder-martyrs and tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors are so extolled, who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing haue all suffered, for high treason, contempt and breach of the lawes, let them all so perish-
<pb n="26" facs="18"/> For it is no great thing (as the Apostle speaketh) since Sathan him-selfe is transformed into an Angell of light: though his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters transforme them selues, as though they were the Ministers of righteousnesse; neither tree nor fruite beeing good. Euery tree therefore (as our Sauiour speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) that bringeth not forth good fruite, is hewen downe and cast into the fire. Cursed be that tree, and let neuer fruite grow vpon it, which barren of good fruite, hath so long deceaued the world with a faire shew of leaues onely: and let all true hearted subiects for euer beware of such a Iewish, Heathnish, Turkish, Hypocritish, Diuelish, kill-King Religion.</p>
   <p>As for the Prophecies of <hi>Christ,</hi> begun presently after the fall, continued to <hi>Abraham:</hi> that of
<pb n="27" facs="18"/>
      <hi>Iaakob, Moses, Balaam,</hi> and all the Prophets: how fully all were fulfilled is apparently in the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelists to be seene. Let the wande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, desolate, runnagat, misbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing Iew, say what hee will: as the Papists in vaine dreame of another Antichrist, so in vaine doe they looke for another <hi>Messi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as;</hi> their true, hauing come as it was prophecied, iust when the Scepter (according to <hi>Iaakobs</hi> Prophecie) was departed from <hi>Iudah: Herod</hi> a stranger, by the Romanes, hauing obtained the kingdome, ordaining what high Priests hee pleased, the abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of desolation, prophecied by <hi>Daniel,</hi> then beginning to worke.</p>
   <p>But one of the chiefe causes of this their error was, that they loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for a temporall glorious King;
<pb n="28" facs="19"/> and not for one so poore in shew, found in a cratch, entring Ierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem vpon an Asse, not hauing wherin to hide his head, his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as they supposed, not being of this world. And if we consider, how his death &amp; their blindnesse was by the Prophets fore-prophecied, by whom it was to bee act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d, that for our saluation, redemption, and eternall glorification, it must (as it was prophecied) bee finished, euen by the inhabitants of Ierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r rulers; and the cursse and vtter desolation vpon people and country euer since in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted: wee shall no wayes doubt thereof: For to vs their affliction and wandering is a most assured testimonie, that the brasen gates of death are broken a sunder: and a sure path-way for euer opened vnto the fountaine of grace. And
<pb n="29" facs="19"/> because our faith can neuer be too strong in this our pilgrimage, which is assaulted with so many doubtings: leauing Scripture, if wee will but cast our eyes vpon hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stories of all sorts, it shall be no lit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle ease: beholding the Prophecies of <hi>Sybils,</hi> hundreds of yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the incarnation of <hi>Christ:</hi> cited by <hi>Augustine</hi> out of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantîus,</hi> so venerable amongst the Romanes, dcfended by great <hi>Constantine:</hi> as <hi>Eusebius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth. How she prophecied brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of all that happened vnto him: of his comming, life, actes, abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings, death, resurrection, second comming. How at that time all Oracles did cease, giuing place to the greater. How <hi>Iosephus</hi> speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him, doubteth if it was lawfull to call him a man: saying further, (not that they said hee
<pb n="30" facs="20"/> appeared aliue vnto them the third day, according as the diuine Prophets had fore-told. How <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustus</hi> visiting <hi>Apollos</hi> Oracle when he grew aged (as <hi>Nîcepho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> reporteth) could receiue no answer but with doubled Heca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tombes. The Oracle at last answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that an Hebrew child (ruling ouer the blessed Gods) commanded him to leaue that place, departing to his infernall region. Wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on returning to Rome, hee builded an Altar in the Capitoll, with the inscription of <hi>PRIMOGENITO DEI,</hi> the Altar of the first begotten Son of God. How <hi>Plinie</hi> also reporteth of <hi>Christs starre</hi> which the wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men saw, vnder the name of a Commet: worshipped in Rome by <hi>Augustus,</hi> for that good which, as hee thought, it pretended vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: the Pagan concluding
<pb n="31" facs="20"/> as <hi>Caiphas</hi> did, though in another fort▪ that if we will confesse the truth, it was a good, hapy, &amp; helth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full presage vnto the whole world. How <hi>Appolophanes</hi> the Sophist, as it is reported, being with <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nysius</hi> at the time of that wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full darknesse and Ecclipse of the Sun, contrary to the course of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in Heliopolis a towne of Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt▪ burst forth in these words, (O good <hi>Dionysius,</hi> these are the alterations of heauenly things) as also that of <hi>Dionysius</hi> him-selfe, when that great earth-quake and darknesse was, at the passion of our blessed Sauiour, (the vnknowne God, in fleshly shape suffereth; for whose cause the vniuersall world is darkned &amp; shaken) what should I speake of <hi>Tiberius</hi> wonderfull proposition to the Senate, vpon <hi>Pilates</hi> letter? euen to receiue
<pb n="32" facs="21"/>
      <hi>Christ</hi> for a <hi>God:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Quia, vetus erat decretum, ne qui Deus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>b Impe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>atere consc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>raretur, nisi a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> atu prob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ur.</note> who, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing their deniall, gaue free passage to the Name of <hi>Iesus:</hi> as <hi>Eusebius</hi> and <hi>Nicephorus</hi> in their Ecclesiasticall stories relate. It were tedious to search, or rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon vp all, which might serue for this purpose, onely let it suffice thee, that since God himselfe, his holy word, heauen and earth, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and men, diuels and oracles, the consent of so many hundred yeares, haue all confessed that thy blessed Sauiour did once come to take away the sinnes of many (as the Apostle speaketh) as assuredly to looke for him the second time: without sinne vnto saluation:</p>
   <p>Durst I now but aduenture to touch his Eternall God-head? sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie heerein silence were best Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, in so vnsearchable a mistery.
<pb n="33" facs="21"/> Yet since the disciples of that anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent-condemned-foe <hi>Arrius,</hi> by so many generall Councels, holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and graue Bishops: dareth yet now and then, spew out some dregs of their ancient venome, heere and there in corners. It shall not be amisse, by his grace and thy patience, as I thinke, to brandish once againe aboue their heads, that sword, which long since did after a great skirmish, so ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, shame, wound, and put them to silence. How copious the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures euery where are, to set out, extoll, and maintaine this eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall God-head, is well knowne to euery indifferent reader: this word, this Angell of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament, shining so brightly in the Old. At first Creating, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coursing and appearing to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, working such wonders and
<pb n="34" facs="22"/> miracles. For what else could doe it, but his eternall wisdome coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selling, and his mighty word ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting? and when could euer this wisdome and word haue begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning? which of necessitie, from all eternity had residence in the bosome of the Father. How in so many places thereof, that name of Lord, of God, which is spoken of the Father: is also sometimes meant, and vnderstood of God the Sonne. <hi>Dauid</hi> calleth him Lord, the Lord said to my Lord, &amp;c. the Prophet <hi>Isaiah,</hi> calleth him Wonderfull, Counseller, The mighty God, the euerlasting Father, the Prince of peace. And <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> Iehouah our righteousnesse: then which what more can bee said? The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Micah</hi> also giueth him a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining, but he immediatly addeth, that that beginning was frō euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting.</p>
   <pb n="35" facs="22"/>
   <p>I omit how often through the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets there is mention made, chiefly in that of <hi>Isaiah;</hi> of <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah</hi> thy Redeemer, thy Sauiour, yea sometimes, Sauiour and Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: which two names, properly and only belong to God the Sonne. For although God the Father, as the fountaine of the Deitie, may after a sort bee said to redeeme and saue: because of the eternitie of his loue, first consulting with his eternall wisdome and word, for our redemption and saluation to be clothed with flesh, and after sending of it. Yet was there no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of performance, but in the person of the Sonne: properly ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no redemption. <hi>Iohn</hi> saith, that that word was God, and that all things were made by it: and that with-out it, was made no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that was made.</p>
   <pb n="36" facs="23"/>
   <p>Where now (O wretched <hi>Arrian!</hi>) canst thou find a beginning of the essence of this <hi>Iesus?</hi> vnlesse thou also derogate from the eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Father. Take away this <hi>Iesus</hi> eternitie, and thou shalt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer see the Father. What power could create this admirable All; but eternall? what horrible blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie were it in thee, to thinke that God created God? returning againe to Paganisme, and plura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of Gods. Which thou must needs doe, if thou deny either the Vnity or Eternity of the Sonne with the Father. This <hi>Iehouah</hi> in the forty fourth of <hi>Isaiah</hi> saith, that hee is the first and the last, and without him there is no God. Yet I hope, hee doth not there ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the God-head of the Sonne▪ who so often in the Appocalips as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumeth vnto himself to be <hi>Alpha</hi>
      <pb n="37" facs="23"/> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the first and the last: (for we must alwayes beware that one Scripture confound not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, so smelling of imperfection and lying.) The like might be said of many moe. Know vile wretch, that their vnseparable vnity can suffer no maner of deuision: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out confusion of the Dietie. This <hi>Iesus</hi> saith, That whatsoeuer the Father doth, that doth hee also. And in other places of the said Chapter; That the Father raiseth the dead, and quickeneth them: also, That the Sonne quickneth whom hee will. That all iudgment is committed to the Sonne, that all men should honour the Sonne, as they honour the Father? How commeth it now O <hi>Arrian!</hi> that <hi>Iehouah,</hi> which in the forty two of <hi>Isaiah</hi> saith; That he will not giue his glory to another, and is
<pb n="38" facs="24"/> euery where so iealious of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: is now become a sharer with another, false of his word, if thy opinion should passe for current? doth hee not heere still gather all the honour and glory vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, in honouring his Sonne? Yes verily, for Christ himselfe saith, Vnlesse hee be honoured with the same honour, the Father hath no honour: and in honouring him, we also honour the Father. Saving further, that hee that seeth him, seeth him that sent him. And to <hi>Philip,</hi> that hee that hath seene him, hath also seene the Father. And a little after, That he was in the Father, and the Father in him: which he confirmeth in that prayer a little before his passion, vnto his Father. Where, with <hi>Caluin</hi> we must remember, that so oft as hee in the person of the
<pb n="39" facs="24"/> Mediator speaketh to the Father, vnder the Name of God, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended also the Godhead which was his.</p>
   <p>Farther the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> saith, that being in the forme of God, he thought it no robbery to be equall with God. That he is the image of the inuisible God, who Created all things, beeing before all things, all things consisting in him: all the treasures of wisdome and knowledge being hid in him: the fulnesse of the God-head bodily dwelling in him, calling him fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Prince onely, King of Kings, Lord of Lords. In another place adding, That hee created the worlds, vpholding all things by his mighty word. And in the Reuelation, Hee that saith I am <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> sayeth also that hee was dead, (speaking
<pb n="40" facs="25"/> of his humane body) but now is aliue for euermore. Wonder thou brain-sick <hi>Arrian,</hi> or whatsoeuer thou art, that darest impugne this glorious eternall deitie! neither on paine of thy damnation aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to search the causes of so high a mistery: perhaps thou wilt not beleeue, because thy reason cannot find it out: but I tell thee vnlesse thou subiect thy reason to Faith, thy reason shall lead thee to hell. Knowest thou not, that wee by our owne knowledge are beasts? all the imaginations of our hearts being euill continually: all of vs gone out of the way, drinking iniquitie like water; our righteousnesse as filthy clowtes, our iniquities like the winde hauing taken vs away; Our yeares as a thought, our life like the winde, our dayes swifter then a post, of short continuance,
<pb n="41" facs="25"/> vanishing as a shadow, all of vs lyers: in our best estate altogether vanity, and what more miserable? Our miserable weaknesse beeing thus, how darest thou impugne the truth of God? or curiously search out the secrets of so high a miste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie? but if thou wilt needs bee cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, begin at his creatures, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding what the Lord saith vnto <hi>Iob,</hi> when hee made him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse his misery euen in searching of those: let be the vnsearchable misterie of the Trinity; Lay thy hand with him then vpon thy mouth, resoluing, that though thou hast spoken blasphemie, thou wilt speake so no more: repenting in dust and ashes, and with the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> confessing, that thou art fearfully and wonderfully made, and that his knowledge is too wonderfull for thee. Thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="42" facs="26"/> alleadgest Scripture, so did the diuell to our Sauiour Christ, all to one end, to diminish his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. But thou darest not abide to be tried by a harmonie, to let Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture bee expounded by Scripture: but fliest to some odde corners, like vnto the Papists, and all other the like Heretikes, who to saue their reputation in shew to the world, haue recourse to some pieces of patched Apocrypha, or other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of stented Scripture to their false glose. But if thou werest not mad, thou mightest heare that same voice which pronounced, the Father is greater then I (meaning as he was man) telling thee also, that the Father and he are one as he was God. If the one be true, shall not the other be as true? where he setteth, as <hi>Caluin</hi> saith, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the higher degree; inso<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>much
<pb n="43" facs="26"/> as the glorious perfection of brightnesse that appeareth in hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen, differeth from that measure of glory, which was seene in him, clothed with flesh. And that it was expedient thus to be, he declareth in another place, where citing <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeneus,</hi> he saith: That the Father which is vnmeasurable, is in his Sonne measured: because he hath applied himselfe to the measure of our capacity, least he should drown our mindes with the vnmeasura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenesse of his glory. To which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth that saying of the Apostle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> that he is that myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of godlinesse, God manifested in the flesh, iustified in the spirit, seen of Angels, preached vnto the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, beleeued on in the world, and receiued vp in glory. But if vaine wretch, thou wilt maintaine thy opinions against <hi>y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
      </hi> brightnes of so
<pb n="44" facs="27"/> many testimonies; know, that when this <hi>Iesus</hi> with all his holy Angels shall appeare in the clowds, in flaming fire and vengeance to all such as thou art: he shall bring with him a Scepter of yron to crush thee in pieces: when the mountaines at thy intreatie shall not couer thee from his presence. Since in thy life-time, thou wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully opposed thy selfe against such a clowde of witnesses, of the word it selfe, so many learned diuines of all ages: who all haue agreed (that euer spake truly). That he is coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, coessentiall, coequall with the Father: of one selfe-same euerlasting—eternall—substance, continuance, being, state, conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and degree: in nothing diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, but by way of relation.</p>
   <p>What should I speake of that tempest-calmer, ease of sorrow,
<pb n="45" facs="27"/> nurse of ioy, delight of the soule; heauen-forcing prayer? who did euer yet sound aright, the depth of this bottomlesse Ocean? who euer yet knew perfectly the windings, turnings, ebbings and flowings, heats and colds, mournings and ioyes, accompanying it at once, or by turnes, as the motions of diuers passions enforceth? all which, as euer by any (Christ excepted) are by the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> at large expressed in the booke of Psalmes. Some-times in his owne person, some-times in that of the Church. Sometimes mourning, confessing, requesting, in anguish demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: exhorting, comforting, and assuredly triumphing. Yea some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times when he appeareth to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together lost, and vtterly voyde of consolation▪ as it were from the pit of dispaire, and gates of hell,
<pb n="46" facs="28"/> (so lowe doth the Lord oft-times bring his owne) rising to a full as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance of mercy.</p>
   <p>Certainely this Princely Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in his booke of Psalmes, sheweth a most perfect patterne of prayer, (remembring still the former exception) and of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian praying. For if wee looke for Humility, who more humble then he? I am a worme and not a man, a shame of men, and the contempt of the people. If of Patience, who more patient then he? exhorting so to patience. If of Fearing, trust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Lord with assured con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, what heapes of places are there to this purpose? If of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, what infinit (as it were) well-framed petitions. If of a forsaken Christian, seeming neere the brinkes of dispaire: who nearer then hee? If againe, of one ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing,
<pb n="47" facs="28"/> and hoping to ouer-come all these sorrowes: who more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouslie triumphing then hee? of all which thy owne meditation shall more aboundantly satisfie thee; where thou shalt see, how alwayes hee hath recourse to the promise: thereby shewing, that there can be no well grounded prayer, but on the word applyed, nor no assurance therein, but what it hath from the free promise of mercy in Christ. Which promise, beeing rightly and in due time applyed worketh wonders, forcing that kingdome, which of it owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord suffereth violence: arming thee further to assaile it, neuer returning without mercy, or as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance thereof. To bee short, fearing I haue alreadie passed, and shall passe the bounds of an Epistle: so the grauitie, height,
<pb n="48" facs="29"/> and aboundance of the matter in hand intangled me: the waues of this bottomlesse Ocean, in which, I know not how vnawares I lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched: in tossing mee too and fro, heere and there, that as yet I could not get any sight of land: in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration whereof, yet a little while I intreate thy patience: cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to thy remembrance onely one instance (which shall serue for all the rest) of that man of God <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses.</hi> Who, when the people had grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uously transgressed, causing to bee made, and worshipping a golden Calfe in his absence with God in the mount: after that the Lord had told him of his, to <hi>Moses</hi> see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming intention, (for the miscon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struing of the second causes, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth certainly of our ignorance in the first) How doth he insinuate the memory of the promise? what
<pb n="49" facs="29"/> strong arguments doth hee vse to mooue the Lord to mercy? Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of inconstancie, crueltie, in destro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing those, whose conuoy out of a strange land, he had so graced with wonders and miracles. Of his ensuing reputation and impoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in the mouthes of the Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians. Next of his othe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise made to <hi>Abraham, Isaack,</hi> and <hi>Iaakob:</hi> and in them to all true beleeuers. And lastly to make all sure, after the Lord had gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his request, seconding it with a thing impossible, by reason of the Lords eternitie of election and loue: If hee would not, to race him out of the booke of life.</p>
   <p>If euer any, did not <hi>Moses</hi> here force this kingdome? how could hee choose but finde mercy? Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did the Lord heere change his minde indeed: but of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite
<pb n="50" facs="30"/> mercy applying him-selfe to our capacitie, speaking after the manner of men: (for how could we haue beene able otherwayes to vnderstand so high misteries in the language of that heauenly Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan? as in other places is attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted vnto him parts of a bodie: whom notwithstanding our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Christ in the fourth of <hi>Iohn,</hi> affirmeth to bee a spirit: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be worshipped in Spirit and Truth. (It being a changing one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of a threatning in mercy: and that in great equitie, after so strong a batterie,) as is before shewed. Because as Diuines agree, in euery threatning or promise of life or death: there is alwayes some secret condition annexed, either reueiled, or vnderstood: vpon the vse or abuse whereof, life or death dependeth. As was certainly in
<pb n="51" facs="30"/> this, for if the Lord had beene minded then, as at other times to destroy: when thousands, and hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of thousands perished in his wrath, nothing could haue staied their destruction. Which the Lord at first expresseth vnto <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> whom, before he threaten, hee inuiteth to intercession: in these words, <hi>(Let me alone)</hi> implying a contrary, Let mee alone and I will, Let mee not alone and I will not.</p>
   <p>As though the Lord should haue said, this people indeed hath grieuouslie sinned against mee, wherefore according to the seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of my Iustice, I will vtterly consume &amp; destroy them: vnlesse some meanes of reconciliation for appeasing my wrath be vsed: some intercession by Prayer: applying
<pb n="52" facs="31"/> my gratious promises in Christ, by thee, for them: but if this sweete incense smell once in my nose, I cannot choose but bee mercifull. Since then the Lord is so grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>öus, so willing to heare, to grant, how should it stirre vp euery one to seeke vnto the Lord for mercy, by prayer? since there are so many gratious promises to incourage vs: prouiding diligently for ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, by all meanes to offer vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence vnto this kingdome. Some may perhaps obiect, that it is a hard taske: which I willingly grant. Yet I againe appeale vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, whether the ioy after the performance, and the sweete rest and peace of conscience thereby ensuing, bee not a super-aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant recompence, for any care, for row, or other vexation they finde therein? It is true also, the Lord
<pb n="53" facs="31"/> many times suffereth his children to crie long, without any shew of hearing: yet is it as true, that hee euer hath crowned perseuerance with a ioyfull victory. This pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Iob</hi> well knew, when in the middest of all his sorrowes, hee burst forth in that wonderfull speach: Although hee kill me, yet will I trust in him, &amp;c. for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the Lord by this delay, let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them know them-selues by degrees, whereof by nature they are ignorant: teaching them hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, patience, perseuerance, the tryall of tentations: assurance of his loue, in preseruing them ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest so many dangers: assured confidence for euer in the like stormes: armeth them with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible arguments, when the forteresse of their faith is assai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by Sathans lyes: of the trueth
<pb n="54" facs="32"/> of their faith, hope, loue, constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, or the like. And further that beeing strengthned, they may strengthen their brethren. How this duty is omitted, which should bring with it all other blessings, the impietie of this frozen age well sheweth: iniquitie like a streame ouer-flowing the hearts of most, would God not of all. But yet how farre they are ignorant of these passions of prayer, and the true moouing causes, is la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable: the most part think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are fafe enough, if they doe say, Lord helpe me, in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: not caring what they doe all the day: but certainly where is no progresse, there must needs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue a back-falling.</p>
   <p>Some also, as I thinke, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son they are vnaquainted, with the extremitie of the voyce in
<pb n="55" facs="32"/> prayer, a parcell of the highest passion: thinke it strange, yea neere a fit of madnesse. For my part I dare not iudge of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries of a troubled soule. Yet why may not the extremitie of passionate sorrow, breake the bounds of moderation? the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemencie of en-kindling carying the worke of the toung with it (as one speaketh.) And who can appoint limmits, to the vnknowne mounting transported flight, of the inlightned soule, in her ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent loue to her so desired home? why should any then bee ashamed heereof hauing so much grace? for although wee read of a silent <hi>Moses,</hi> a muttering <hi>Hannah,</hi> a chattering <hi>Hezekiah:</hi> yet hast thou also a roaring <hi>Dauid</hi> for the griefe of his heart.</p>
   <pb n="56" facs="33"/>
   <p>To touch all, would fill vp a volume, I leaue them therefore, touching onely the last two: the first wheereof, to confirme all, let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thee see the trueth of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miser. The last, assuring thee, that hee who effected this great worke of Creation and Renouation, in respect whereof, all other miracles seeme nothing: is still as able to doe whatsoeuer hee in his holy word hath promised.</p>
   <p>Yet least these pearles should be deuoured of swine, prophane hated <hi>Esau,</hi> presuming to pull, as well as godly loued <hi>Iaakob:</hi> giue me leaue to warne thee, the swaggering, swearing, domineering Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or whatsoeuer thou art: the dispiser, at least, the flowter of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and professors thereof, making no conscience of thy wayes, loosing the bridle to all licenciousnesse,
<pb n="57" facs="33"/> that thou presume not to apply these promises vnto thy selfe, without repentance. It is not thy prophane life, but a broken and a contrite heart, which <hi>Dauid</hi> saith God will not refuse. Thou that canst not abide to heare of thy more then Iewish cruelty, in tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and renting that blessed bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, no part therof remaining free from thy blaspemous mouth: nay which is yet more horrible pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing vnto his very soule, of thy open and vaunting sinnes, of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, adultery, and the like: but the gentle admonisher, must receiue a mock for his paines.</p>
   <p>Doost thou thinke so long as thou continuest thus, these promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses do appertaine vnto thee? they indeed shall bee vnto thee the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor of death vnto death, and not of life vnto life: if thou presume
<pb n="58" facs="34"/> to apply them vnto thee without a true repentance. How neere in thy scoffing doest thou incurre that fearfull woe pronounced by our Sauiour Christ, against the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criticall Scribes and Pharisees: shutting the kingdome of heauen before men, neither entring thy selfe, nor suffering those that would, so farre as thy reproches may hinder? heerein gallopping on horse-back to the diuell, where others vse to goe on foote, or ride softly: vnlesse the Lord of his infinite mercie stay thee in the way, as hee did to persecuting <hi>Saul.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Shall the Prophet <hi>Dauids</hi> eyes gush out with riuers of water, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause prophane men in those daies tooke no care in obseruing the Law? Shall <hi>Phineas</hi> being zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for the glory of <hi>GOD,</hi> by
<pb n="59" facs="34"/> killing of <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cozbi,</hi> when Israel coupled themselues in fornication with <hi>Baalpeor,</hi> turne away the wrath of God, which had already destroied foure and twenty thousand of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; obtaining further, a blessing to him and his seed? And shall it not be lawfull now in this crooked age, obseruing manner, time, and place, to admonish, according to that precept of the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> to the Ephesians, to haue no fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>shipp with the vnfruitefull workes of darknesse, but euen to reprooue them rather? I deny not, but the hypocrisie and misbehaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of some, hath beene, and is, a great helpe to the reproch of all. Yet why should all bee blamed? Christ had twelue, one of them being a diuell: should he therefore be a reproch vnto the rest?</p>
   <pb n="60" facs="35"/>
   <p>And the diuell will sowe tares amongst the wheate, which will grow vp, making a faire shew: and who can helpe it? Yet our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour willed all so to remaine, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the great haruest, that hee himselfe made a separation, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering the wheat into his barne: least as it is there expressed, the indiscretion of men, should pull the wheat with the tares.</p>
   <p>My loue to all wisheth thee to forbeare betimes: and then when God shall inlarge thy heart, thou shalt wonder with those conuerts in the Actes, at that which thou now so dispisest, as contemptible in thy eyes, because of thy blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and surfet of sinne, wherin thou liuest. And remember, if thou wilt not: that the Lord is a consuming fire, that hee will not iustifie a wicked man, and that if
<pb n="61" facs="35"/> the righteous by imputation, shall scarcely be saued: where shall the vngodly and sinner appeare? If thou bee in Christ, hauing a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing striuing repenting sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, all are thine. If not I present thee with a dish of woes, feed where thou list: once more troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thy patience, with that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full saying of the author to the Hebrewes; Follow peace with all men, and holynesse, without which none shall see the Lord.</p>
   <p>I might heere bee thought par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, to spare the <hi>Ianus</hi>-faced Pharasaicall hypocrite: who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing Christianitie, yet liueth, as though there were neither hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen nor hell, God nor diuell: not caring if the out-side of the plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be cleane, how foule the in-side be: a part of the mistery of whose
<pb n="62" facs="36"/> iniquitie, I would by the grace of God aduenture to shew, but that it were presumption after <hi>Appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> pensill.</p>
   <p>Yet giue mee leaue, to warne thee also prophane hypocrite, that these promises pertaine not to thee; because thou art the most detestable wretch that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth. For if a dissembling Match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auilianist with men, be so hatefull to most on earth, what shall he bee that dareth dissemble with God, in the Court of heauen? Thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kest a shew vnto the world, of new birth, and I know not what sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie: and yet in secret, how canst thou reioyce in thy sweete darling sinnes? (I speake not of any poore humbled sinners, dayly cast downe with the horror of their sinnes: striuing continually, whither as yet they can by no meanes attaine)
<pb n="63" facs="36"/> for, (who can say I haue cleansed my heart) but of such (who haue taken vnto them-selues a setled habite of hypocrisie, beeing plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed therewith, liuing at ease with a seared conscience.) Thou canst perhaps forsake all, so farre as mortalitie may: onely with <hi>Naa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> wishing the Lord to bee mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull to thee in this, when thou bowest thy selfe in the house of diuelish <hi>Rimmon.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For all this thou (perhaps) pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est often: thou dooest well: but I aske thee, what kinde of prayer thou canst make without a true confession? what true confession, without vnfained repentance? and what true repentance, with-out it bee continuat, totall, bringing with it an vnappea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sable hatred and forsaking, which by degrees it worketh out,
<pb n="64" facs="37"/> studying all meanes, how to cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie this serpent. The diuell by thee gets double aduantage, seeing there is no sinne where-vnto hee more tempteth, then that one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing Christianity should turne hypocrite. Which conquest hauing once gained, O how hee triumphs for by thy hardened heart, which increaseth dayly more and more, as thou continuest, hee thinketh him-selfe sure of thee, and by thy dissembled life, which how close so euer thou conceale it for a time, peepeth out at last at one corner or other: slander ensueth to others. Perhaps thou thinkest, that when thy moneths of vanity are past, thou wilt amend all, and repent fully: yet remember that thou canst not tye the Keye of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to thy girdle: that there is a time, when though thou wouldst
<pb n="65" facs="37"/> seeke it as <hi>Esau</hi> did the blessing, thou shalt not finde it: when the doore of repentance shall hee shut, all the wise Virgins gone in, after which there shall be no opening to the foolish: when hee shall bee co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with a clowde that thy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er cannot passe through. The Lord loueth truth in the inward affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the Kings daughter is all glorious within (saith the Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mist) and the Lord craueth the heart chiefly (saith <hi>Salomon</hi>) yet behold, thou wilt not bestow vpon him, but a counterfet out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward shew: in what estate art thou, iudge thy selfe? What hast thou then to doe O hypocrite! to take this couenant in thy mouth, since thou hatedst to be reformed: and hast cast his words behinde thee? remember this, if thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get God; least hee teare thee in
<pb n="66" facs="38"/> pieces, and there be none that can deliuer thee. Remember if thou yet hope, what is said in the booke of <hi>Iob:</hi> that the hypocrites hope shall perish, that the hypocrite shall not come before God: that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the hypocrite shall be desolate, and his reioycing but for a moment: what fearfull woes our Sauiour Christ also thundereth in the Gospell to this purpose. If thou yet leaue, repent, forsake, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue sorrowfull, thou knowest the gates are not yet shut: all are open, all these gratious promises are thine, and Christ with them. If no, none of them belongeth vnto thee, vnlesse it be the woes.</p>
   <p>But vnto thee, vvho art cast downe with the sight of thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable sinnes, wallowing as it were in the dust, heauen, earth,
<pb n="67" facs="38"/> and hell, seeming to conspire against thee: whom crosses and afflictions, like <hi>Iobs</hi> messengers, assaile to dash thee from the for tresse of thy faith. Whom pinch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pouerty, a dissembling world, the malice of men, the falshood, or losse of friends troubleth. Who fighting against thy innumerable sinnes, art for the most part foy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: crying out with the Church-militant, (I would but cannot). In whose way the scoffes of men, the allurements of the flesh, the tentations of Satan, the ignominy of the crosse, the hardnesse, long<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nesse, and narrownesse of the way: the delaying accomplishmēt of the promises: the smalnesse of the flock the heapes of vaine delights, the weaknesse of the soule, the terrors of death, with innumerable doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings accompanying, standeth vp
<pb n="68" facs="39"/> like mountaines betwixt thee and thy Christ; doth this picture of Christ chiefly submit it selfe; wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing that once therein in thy most need, thou maist finde a word in due time: finding also at last, that all these things come for the best vnto thee, although in the meane time thou canst not see how. How by these and many moe, the Lord maketh his power per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in thy weaknesse: when by one affliction and deliuerance hee strengthneth thee more and more, with experience and patience for the next: by degrees shewing thy selfe vnto thy selfe. Euery fall of thine, <hi>Antaeus-like,</hi> redoubling thy strenghth, as thy experience best knoweth. (Yet not that any should sinne (as the Apostle speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) that grace may abound, for sinnes of presumption hardly come
<pb n="69" facs="39"/> to repentance: let be the working of any such effects.) Onely it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth the Lord, helping thy infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities and fallings, weaning thee dayly from the pleasures of this world, that thou mayest set thy heart on a better: conforming thee vnto his sufferings more &amp; more, by so rough a way to bring thee to glory: in all these spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all dissertions furthering thy sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
   <p>Let patience therefore sweeten thy whatsoeuer estate: since it is most expedient that things be so; For if the Sunne should alwayes shine, wee see how the earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth drie and barren, how euery one wisheth for raine: whose sweete distilling showers beeing come, how the hardened, drie, and barren earth becommeth fruitfull againe: returning to her former
<pb n="70" facs="40"/> mediocritie. Euen so the Sonne of righteousnesse, shining for a long time, and by his spirit hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidence in the heart: ouer cloying it as it were with ioy, the soule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth carelesse in prouision for the retaining of so glorious a guest, which it thinketh it hath after a sort in possession: with <hi>Dauid</hi> in prosperitie, saying, it shall neuer be mooued. It present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon this presumption, findeth a great alteration: her loue hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth himselfe for a time, seemeth to be gone; Thou hidest thy face said <hi>Dauid,</hi> and I was troubled. Then beginneth the soule to toile and moyle, finding that her ioy, her loue is remooued, inquiring and searching diligently the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, pondering all reasons: find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her neglect the cause, shee resolueth to seeke him againe,
<pb n="71" facs="40"/> with the spouse of the Canticl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s, neuer to leaue seeking vntill shee finde him. Then commeth <hi>Dauids</hi> roaring, then falleth the showers of teares, such as is reported of <hi>Luthers</hi> vehemencie, moystening this barren ground: then becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth shee sick of loue, then vseth shee all meanes for his returne, comforting her selfe with the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> in this dissertion, with the remembrance of the dayes of old, preparing for his next returne better intertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: importuning it, vntill at last the clowds doe vanish, her loue appeareth, shee findeth and feeleth it is so, their friendship is renued, new promises made: after which there is a great calme.</p>
   <p>Yet againe stormes ensue, he frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, remoueth, she becometh rest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse
<pb n="72" facs="41"/> (for it is a wonderfull mercy that the Lord giueth an incessant rest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sse to the soule in these spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall dissertions, vntill shee finde in some measure her wonted ioy,) hauing recourse to the former or like meanes, for her raising a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Continuing thus, falling and rising with <hi>Ezekiel</hi> in his vision of the Temples abuse, the further she proceedeth, in her selfe perceauing greater abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons then these past: vntill at last hauing foughten the good fight, and the tryall of her faith beeing found more pretious then gold: the Sonne himselfe appeare, to finish all cares, with the inco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ptible crown of perseuerance.</p>
   <p>But thou perhaps wonderest, at the prosperitie and ease of the wicked in respect of thy toile and trouble: so did it also some of Gods
<pb n="73" facs="41"/> dearest Saints, as thou knowest: some of them crying out, wherfore dooest tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> looke vpon the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressers? &amp;c. Why are all they in wealth that rebelliously trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse? wherefore doe the wicked liue? and <hi>Dauid</hi> fretted there at. Yet hee telleth thee, that they are set in slippery places: suddainly destroyed, perish<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d, and horribly consumed: and <hi>Iob</hi> saith that they are kept for the day of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, and shall bee brought forth to the day of wrath. If thou remember of this, and that thou canst not haue two heauens, and that thy Christ, as thou seruest him in spirit &amp; truth, rewardeth thee also with spirituall graces: and that there must be a moment anie temporall suffering, to auoide an eternall: that the fatted Oxen are fed in the best pastures for awhile,
<pb n="74" facs="42"/> that they may the sooner come to the butcherie: when the poore toy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling leane ones are kept aliue: that thy short sufferings, haue for reward an eternall waight of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: thou canst not choose I say, but bee most content of thy estate. But, if thy eyes with <hi>Elishas</hi> man were yet a little opened, that thou mightest behold the sword hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aboue his head by a haire, in the midst of all his pleasures: thou wouldest not change estates with him. Thou maiest then comfort thy self, that howsoeuer thy estate bee, hee that watcheth ouer thee neither slumbereth nor sleepeth: that he hath a time appointed in which he will turne thy shadow of death into the morning (as the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> speaketh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>) that if thou sow righteousnesse, thou shalt receiue a sure reward: that if thou
<pb n="75" facs="42"/> ouer-come thou shalt inherite all things: that although he chasten thee very sore, (as <hi>Dauid</hi> saith) yet hee will not deliuer thee vnto death: that if thou suffer, thy head Christ suffereth with thee: <hi>Saul, Saul,</hi> why persecutest thou mee? that as hee hath begun with thee in mercy, so hee will also make an end. That although thy portion on earth bee small, yet hee is thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance that filleth heauen and earth: though in pouertie, yet not ouer-come of pouerty; distressed but not forsaken: that thou art his sheepe, and hee knoweth thee, and hath promised vnto thee eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life: n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne beeing able to pull thee out of his hands: that his sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation is neere thee, yea nearer then when thou beleeuedst. That as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth, his louing kindnesse is better
<pb n="76" facs="43"/> then life: that as his Father hath loued him, so hath hee loued thee, and as his friend hath giuen his life for thee. What then fearest thou? how often doth he tell thee, feare not, feare not? imputing it to the imperfection of loue. Why maiest thou not rather remember what the Lord said to <hi>Caine?</hi> If thou doe well, shalt thou not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted? Things beeing so, tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> maiest assure thy selfe, that vnto the righteous, in the end light a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riseth out of darknesse: and vnto thee, light shall be the last. As that great Father well noteth of the seauenth day, wherein is no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sunne-set, or night: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause (saith he) thou O God didst sanctifie it to remaine for euer. Then trust thou for this eternall Sabbath, whatsoeuer the diuell, doubtings, the world, reason, or
<pb n="77" facs="43"/> any other thing shall suggest in the contrary. Assuring thy selfe, that the vnspeakable ioy which thou some times feelest, after that thou in dulnesse and hardnesse of heart, hast presented thy selfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the throne of grace: by sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine inspiration, kindled thou knowest not how, comming thou knowest not whence: is euen to thee a most assured testimony, that there is a greater light, and more aboundance of ioy whence that did spring: which although thou now but feelest and seest in part, when the separating clowds shall vanish away, and the vaile be taken from thine eyes, thou shalt inioy &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold fully. That thou maist bee as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured heereof, striue alwayes for the peace of a waking conscience: for if it be watchfull, it will tell thee what is amisse. This onely
<pb n="78" facs="44"/> can giue thee perfit consolation, in thy last houre vpon thy bed of sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: when other consolations shall faile, singing a sweete <hi>requiem</hi> vnto thy soule: When although thou finde not that sence of ioy which thou desirest and hopest. Yet in spight of Satan, it shall assure thee, that there is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation for thee beeing in Christ, as the Apostle speaketh. That the Iudge being thy Sauiour and Mediator, thou shalt receiue a milde sentence: that by that same word where-with hee hath tyed thy obedience vnto him, hee hath tyed his louing promises vnto thee: that according as thou to thy power by his grace, hast ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled to him: so hee to whom all power in heauen and in earth is giuen will assuredly accomplish vnto thee.</p>
   <pb n="79" facs="44"/>
   <p>Neither flatter thy selfe with delay of time, for how knowest thou when this Trumpet shall blow? a Christian must not thinke of yeares, moneths, weekes, (for this is the diuells suggestion to weary thee with the fore-thought of so long and wearie a course of Christianity to come) but of daies. To day (it is said) if you will heare his voyce harden not your hearts. &amp;c. This day (saith <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> to the children of Israel) I set before you death and life: there is no word heere of to morrow, and who knoweth whether euer there shall bee a to morrow or not? and the Author to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes telleth thee, that after death commeth iudgment. What profiteth it then to thee, how long it be to this day in respect of time? since the day of thy death is the
<pb n="80" facs="45"/> day of iudgement vnto thee: and who hath assurance of a minute of life? behold then how neere thou art to iudgment.</p>
   <p>But whensoeuer this separation shall be, death, if thou be in Christ shall not hurt thee: for as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle saith, If when thou wast an enemie, thou wast reconciled vnto God by the death of his Sonne: much more being reconciled, thou shalt be saued by his life. It is now stinglesse vnto thee, indeed I grant it is, yet loathsome like a Serpent for the sting it once had, and yet hath to the reprobate: but the feare is greater then the touch for being imbraced, it bringeth thee to thy long desired home: endeth all thy cares and sorrows, bringing thee from a filthy pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, into the glorious liberty of the sonnes of God:</p>
   <pb n="81" facs="45"/>
   <p>In the meane time the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance thereof serueth thee for a bridle to thy life, as by the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, the neglect thereof causeth much sorrow. This made <hi>Moses</hi> in his song, complaine of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Oh that they were wise! then they would vnderstand this, they would consider their latter end. And the Prophet in the Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; Her filthinesse is in her skirts: shee remembred not her last end, therefore she came downe wonderfully: she had no comforter. But since thou continually remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brest that which so humbleth thee: that thou art dust, and to dust thou must returne. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber also what thy Christ saith, when he forbiddeth thee to feare, because he is the first and the last: telling thee further, that he hath the keyes of hell and death: euen
<pb n="82" facs="46"/> that key of <hi>Dauid,</hi> which openeth where no man shutteth: and shut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth where no man openeth. If hee who hath done so m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ch for thee be thy Iaylor, who hath giuen his life for thee: doest thou thinke that he will bee so vnkinde, as to open those gates of hell and death, imprisoning thee againe? can, or will he vse thee so? whose liberty and ransome cost him so deare? Certainly no, for if an earthly Maister will not leaue his old ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants destitute in their old age, sicknesse, or extreamest extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: darest thou thinke that thy great Lord and Maister, whose loue is vnspeakable, passing the loue of women to their children: minde vnvariable, truth vnfal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible, power omnipotent, will leaue thee then in thy most need? Shall not so iust a Law-giuer in all
<pb n="83" facs="46"/> perfection obserue, what hee so strictly and dayly inioyneth vnto thee? but thou knowest that the mountaines may remooue, and the hills fall downe: but his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie shall neuer depart from thee, O thou afflicted and tossed with tempest, that hast no comfort! It is true, hee often-times stayeth vntill all other comforts be gone, that hee may bee the onely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter: and thou onely repose in him.</p>
   <p>So went hee into the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, leauing his Disciples to bee tossed in the sea: so slept hee in the shippe, yet his Deitie did wake for their safetie: beeing readie (at a help maister) to calme all tempests, and make a great calme. For hee is not absent in his seeming absence, but onelye standeth at the doore
<pb n="84" facs="47"/> knocking, to see if thou wilt open and let him in. Yet behold loue more wonderfull: hee some-times entreth when all the doores are shut. So did hee to his disciples, when hee appeared amongst them to <hi>Thomas,</hi> who had resolued without seeing not to beleeue: (yet wee read of no hast hee made to see) But his Sauiour preuenteth him, commeth vnto him, causing him put his finger into his hands, and his hands into his side.</p>
   <p>O fountaine of the gardens, O well of liuing waters! is the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable eternitie of thy loue so great towards thy elect, and their hearts so dull to seeke and loue thee againe? Haue yee no regard, all yee that passe by, vnto your soules safetie? Behold and see if euer there were any loue like vnto his loue, or sorrow like vnto his
<pb n="85" facs="47"/> sorrow, procured by the huge waight of our sinnes, or ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude like vnto ours againe. Thou maiest then assure thy selfe, that hee is the same God still: euen of all the world. And since the sting of death is gone, arme thy selfe with a good life against it: per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swading thy selfe that the faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> shal at length bring thee into his bosome, vnto the company of all the elect, to reigne with him in glory. Of which, if so small a measure, did transport the disciples vpon mount Thabar, strike <hi>Saul</hi> to the ground: nay if the reflexe of a reflexe, did so a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stonish the children of Isrell, that <hi>Moses</hi> must couer his face, when hee spoake to them: after hee had beene with the Lord in the mount. What shall the fulnesse thereof do, when thou shalt see him as hee is?
<pb n="86" facs="48"/> What can bee sufficient for at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining so glorious an eternity? For if ten hundred thousand <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thushalems</hi> were aliue, &amp; should doe nothing all their life time but multiply by hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of millions: if all the sand of the Sea, and drops of the Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, could all be numbred: yet here were no end.</p>
   <p>How short then are all these by-past succession af ages, which haue seemed so tedious and long, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of this eternitie? The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle <hi>Peter</hi> saith, a thousand yeares are but as a day in his sight: and the royall Psalmist, as yesterday, when it is past, or as a watch in the night. O the vnspeakable, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>measurable glory and ioy of that New Ierusalem! the super-aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant immensible sacietie where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, so transporteth the beholders.
<pb n="87" facs="48"/> If, I pray you, a weeke of eternitie bee so long, that all these yeares since the Creation in the sight of God, are not so much: vvhat I pray you shall moneths, yeares, thousands of yeares, nay hundred thousand millions of eternitie bee?</p>
   <p>The Apostle calleth the afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this life, but a moment in respect heereof: aduise thee then if thou darest venter this eternitie, for a moment of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. And seeing thou canst not bee a friend to the world (as the Apostle speaketh) vnlesse thou bee an enemie to God: forsake it so much as thou canst. For when neere, and in that last day, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scursion of the Sunne and Moone, the falling of the Starres, the sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the powers of heauen, the voyce of the Archangell, and
<pb n="88" facs="49"/> trumpet of God sounding, the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterings of Angels, the opening of the graues, the showtes of the faithfull, the shrickes of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, the sight of all Saints, the brightnesse of glory dazeling thy eyes, shall assure thee of his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch whom thy soule loueth: him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe lastly appearing in his chaire of triumph, to fulfill all his grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous promises vnto thee. Then shall it not grieue thee, that thou hast suffered, this, or that: the mockes of this, the scoffes of that other: or whatsoeuer calamitie or crosse, but rather that thou hast not suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered more for thy Christ: (if the extremity of ioy, do not then quite bury all remembrance of cares past.) Yet a little while then, nay a very little while, and hee that shall come, will come quickly: for there shall be an end (as <hi>Salomon</hi>
      <pb n="89" facs="49"/> speaketh) and thy hope shall not be cut off. Solace thy selfe then that this day wil come, thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est not how soone, when thou shalt tread downe the wicked, they (as <hi>Malachi</hi> speaketh) beeing dust vnder the soles of thy feete; after which to thee there shall bee no more night, but euerlasting sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shine: euer with <hi>Hierome</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring of this voice &amp; trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet sounding, more fearefull a great deale, then that which erst sounded on mount Sinai: when all the people of the campe were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraide. And because the soule (as <hi>Augustine</hi> speaketh) as it cannot be inlightned of it selfe, neither can bee filled with it selfe: a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible body beeing heauie vnto it: because it is naked (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle speaketh) longing to bee clothed from heauen. Euer to
<pb n="90" facs="50"/> finish the Catastrophe of thy song, with that mourning and loue-sick spouse of the Canticles: to which also agreeth that of the whole Scriptures. O my welbeloued! flie away, and be like vnto the Roe, or to the young Heart vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the mountaines of spices.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in the All-sufficient, Not-chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, wonderfull,</hi> Ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuell. <hi>I. H:</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>