<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface containing the occasions of the Dispute following.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119134_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14408</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24727</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119134</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface containing the occasions of the Dispute following.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Acts of the dispute and conference holden at Paris, in the moneths of Iuly and August. 1566. Betweene two doctors of Sorbon, and two ministers of the Reformed Church : A most excellent tract, wherein the learned may take pleasure, and the ignorant reape knowledge. Translate out of French by Iohn Golburne, and diuided according to the daies</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 263, 5 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="1" facs="4"/>
   <head>The Preface containing the occasions <hi>of the Dispute following.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or that I doubt not, but many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons (filled with the commō brute of the conference should bee made at the house of my Lord the Duke <hi>de Montpensier,</hi> betweene the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the one part, and the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of the other, appointed for that purpose) desire to know the truth: and that others speake thereof diuersly, according to the reports thereof made vnto them, or their conceiued imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations concerning the same: Me seemeth, that to satisfie the one, and take from the other all occasion of lying or giuing credit to lies: it should bee good to put briefly in writing all the matter as it passed: and likewise to declare, what was the motiue, &amp; first occasion of the same.</p>
   <p>My Lord the Duke of <hi>Montpensier,</hi> who (as each one knoweth) is very zealous of his Religion, and dearely loueth his children; seeing that his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Duchesse of <hi>Buillon</hi> was departed from the Komish Religion, thenceforth to follow that of Iesus Christ: and that without chilling, shee still perseue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and more and more increased in the knowledge and feare of God: in zeale, godlinesse, and all other
<pb n="2" facs="5"/>
good and commendable vertues; (his speech he had in the beginning with her, and other meanes he had since assaied, to reduce and call her backe from the way wherein shee was, nought preuailing): willed for a last remedie, to attempt if he could, to winne her by the meanes and remonstrance of a Doctor named <hi>Vigor,</hi> whom he much esteemed. And to the end that the said Lady should remaine more satisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, hauing called my Lord of <hi>Buillon</hi> her husband, hee declared vnto him his minde, and said; hee was contented that the said remonstrance should bee made to his daughter, in the presence of some Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters; as namely of <hi>Spina,</hi> &amp; such others as she should please to choose: to the ende that had they any thing to say against the doctrine of the saide <hi>Vigor,</hi> they should alleadge it; And if after they had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred together, they were not confuted by him, and wholly vanquished, that his daughter should then abide in her opinion; without that hee, or some others of his side would euer assay ought to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert her.</p>
   <p>My Lord <hi>de Buillon</hi> promised to accomplish his commaund therein: and to shewe his obedience to him. Shortly after hee imparted the same to my Lord the Admirall; by whose aduice, and other Lords which hee spake too, <hi>De Spina</hi> was suddenly sent for; who beeing come vnto them, and hauing vnderstood all that aforesaid, said; that hee hoped for little fruite of all this Conference; considering the qualitie and humour of the man with whom hee was to deale: because hee is much more partiall
<pb n="3" facs="5"/>
for the Pope and his traditions, then zealous for the word of God, and truth of Iesus Christ. Which thing, those that were present did well approoue. Neuerthelesse, hee was purposed for two considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to present himselfe at the said Conference: the one, to support and stablish my said Lady <hi>de Buillon,</hi> against the Sophismes, and cauillations of the said <hi>Vigor:</hi> the other, to take from him the occasion to boast (as his custome is) that the Ministers durst not appeare before him.</p>
   <p>And then was the proceeding and order aduised of, which they should hold in the said Conference. And that the said <hi>De Spina</hi> should first require, that it might be authorized by the Kings permission: Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, that to auoyd all confusion, it should bee made in the presence of a fewe persons; Thirdly, that there should bee some certaine theame and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect proposed, wherof they should conferre: Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that there should be two Moderators of the whole Action, and two others deputed, faithfully to collect all the reasons and arguments which should bee brought forth by the parties.</p>
   <p>All which things hauing beene proposed to my Lord the Duke of <hi>Buillon,</hi> as well by <hi>Monsieur</hi> the Admirall: as by the said <hi>De Spina,</hi> hee found them very reasonable, and promised to giue the best order he could to all the businesse: admonishing <hi>De Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> to be readie the first day of Iuly, 1566. for after dinner hee should make the said Conference. By meanes whereof, the same <hi>De Spina</hi> to prepare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, went to finde out <hi>Monsieur Barbaste,</hi> Minister
<pb n="4" facs="6"/>
to the Queene of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> whom hee prayed to vouchsafe to accompany, and second him in the said conference. Which he graunting, both two, together with three other Gentlemen, left by my said Lord <hi>de Buillon</hi> to conduct them; went after dinner, the day and yeare aboue said, to the house of my Lord the Duke <hi>de Montpensier;</hi> where when they were ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued, the Duke <hi>de Buillon</hi> aduertised thereof by one of the said Gentlemen, came vnto them in the Hall where they were. And speaking to <hi>De Spina,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded of him (induced as is likely by the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, assembled in the chamber whence hee came) if he were purposed and resolued to pray, after the custome of the reformed Churches, before they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan the said conference. He answered yea: and that neither he, nor his companion, could not, nor ought to attempt a thing of such importance, as to handle the Mysteries of Christian Religion; without first be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prepared therevnto by the inuocation of Gods name. That heard, hee entred the chamber where the Doctors were assembled: and hauing commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to them the answere of the said Ministers, they appointed Doctor <hi>Ruze,</hi> to declare vnto them, that they would not be present at their prayers, and that no more reasonable it was, that they should bee there, then they at their Masse. The Ministers answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: that they could not with good conscience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the conference, before they had prayed vnto God: and that it was in the Doctors choise &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to be present, or absent at their praiers; And they for their part would content themselues to pray in the place &amp; assembly, wherin the conference should
<pb n="5" facs="6"/>
be made. But neuerthelesse, that their prayers, which are (as they themselues confesse) conformable to the pure word of God; and their Masse, wherin are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things contrary therevnto, (as they may easily know and iudge that will trie and examine it by the rule of the scripture) were not like things; And so, by meanes of the impietie and Idolatrie which is in their Masse, they could not any way communicate thereat, without offence to God, and making them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues highly culpable before him: but that he, and the other Doctors his companions could not be let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by any such difficulties to be present at their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: For as much as there was no article which (by their owne confession) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> not holy, and according to God. Herevpon replied Doctor <hi>Ruze,</hi> that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters staied on a thing of small moment. And they answered, that the principall exercise of Christian Religion, was prayer: and that it is a necessarie mean to obtaine the fauour and grace of God; without which, men cannot attaine successe, nor any good speed in all their workes: and that therfore the omis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion thereof was verie pernitious. And that they for their part were abashed, that he, which called him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe a Doctor, and Diuine, should make so litle ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of praier; which is the true practise, fruite, and vse, of all the knowledge which can be had of God, and his word: and that therein one may know what was the iudgement of them, which measure diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie by Idle and vaine speculations. Then said he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>them: that the Duke <hi>de Montpensier,</hi> would neuer suffer, he should so be braued in his owne house: nor that it should bee said, that the Ministers had made
<pb n="6" facs="7"/>
their prayers. Wherevnto answered the Ministers, that to braue, was a thing contrarie to their professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And that so farre off were they from brauing of Princes, (to whom they owed all honour, feare, and obedience) that they would condemne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues if so be they had vsed it, to a man of the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest qualitie in the world. And added moreouer, that the Doctors, and such others, which charged them with such slaunders towards Princes, to stirre vp, and moue them against them, should be assured they should once answere before God for the same. Herevpon spake Doctor <hi>Ruze,</hi> and demaunded of the Ministers, why they stood so stifly vppon that point of prayer. They f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> answere proposed vnto him; first, that the end of the Conference, was to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest the true meaning of the scripture, and make the hearers vnderstand it: which thing could not be done, without the spirit of God; who enlightneth the minde and vnderstanding to comprehend it; and openeth the mouthes to expresse the same: And therefore it behoueth to implore and obtaine his grace by prayers. Afterwards, that God commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all those that want wisedome, to aske it of him; and to seeke what they would finde; and to knocke, if they would haue him to open vnto them. All which things cannot otherwise bee obtained, then by prayers. And therefore concluded, that for this cause they were necessary. They alledged further, that all things ought to be reduced to the glory of God: and that inuocation was therefore requisite in the beginning, and thankesgiuing at the ending and consummation of all our workes, nor more, nor lesse,
<pb n="7" facs="7"/>
then wee beginne and finish our repast, in blessing and praising the name of God.</p>
   <p>Then said Doctor <hi>Ruze</hi> vnto them, that they would not hinder them to pray vnto God: but that they should do it in their hearts. And they answered: that it was not sufficient; but that it behoued to pray also with the mouth, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> commandeth: withdraw your selues then into some place apart (said hee) and make your praiers all alone. They answered: that in such an act, it ought not so to be done: and that they were bound by the cōmandement of God, to make their light to shine before men, to the end, that seeing their good works, they might haue means to glorifie God, and to be therby edified. Also that in so doing, they might giue occasion of scandall to their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, confirming the euil opiniō imprinted by their aduersaries in some of their doctrine and exercises: to wit: that by reason of the errors and blasphemies which were therein; they dared not to publish the same: and that to quite them of this slaunder, meet it was, that as they spake in publike, their praiers should be also in publike. To be briefe, that they ought not, neither could they with reason refuse that which the King had graunted vnto them in the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of <hi>Poissy:</hi> where, in all the assemblies there made, they were alwayes permitted to pray to GOD publikely, before they spake of any matter. And added for their last reason, that it was verie needefull to comprehend in theyr prayers them, and all those that should be present at the said confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: to the end, that God might grant grace both to them and others, to dispoile them wholly of all
<pb n="8" facs="8"/>
their passions: and that there should bee nothing which might hinder them, to iudge rightly of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer should be proposed on the one side, &amp; on the other: And that he would also make the hearers do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible and attentiue to gather to themselues some pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit thereof. I shame here to recite one word which scaped from Doctor <hi>Ruze</hi> in this behalfe: who in contempt of God, and his seruice, said: that if the Ministers would goe pray, he would go pisse during the time of prayer. Wherevpon the Ministers cryed out, saying: What resolution? what counsell? what good word can be hoped for, of a heart filled with so an apparant contempt of God?</p>
   <p>My Lord the Duke of <hi>Buillon,</hi> and the said Doctor <hi>Ruze,</hi> seeing the Ministers setled, and firme in this, not to enter into any conference before prayers were made, in the presence of the assembly, where the same should be made: after they had reported the same to my Lord <hi>de Montpensier,</hi> and the Doctors which were with him; they purposed to send them backe; and that on this condition they should not conferre with them.</p>
   <p>Herevpon they departed: and as they were now arriued at the little Bridge of our Lady, they called them backe, and they forth with returned; supposing they would graunt them what they requested. But herein were they deceiued. For Doctor <hi>Ruze</hi> came towards them to the gate, and for a finall resolution, said vnto them: that if they would pray, they would giue them a house neare at hand: but that my Lord <hi>de Montpensier</hi> would not permit, they should make them in his house; nor that any of his family should
<pb n="9" facs="8"/>
be present thereat. Wherevnto they answered, that they now yeelded lesse vnto them, then in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning they had done: and therefore they could not answere otherwise then they had answered.</p>
   <p>Thē Doctor <hi>Ruze</hi> addressed particularly his speech to the Minister <hi>De Spina;</hi> to whom in scoffing maner, he said two things: that he well saw, he had no great desire to enter disputations: and that in times past he had bene of their company; but that he was now cut off from them. Wherevnto answered <hi>De Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> that had he fled the conference, he would not in that great heate, haue come eight long miles, nor left his Church, which was to him more deare and acceptable then any other thing, to finde them in their owne houses. And as touching his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from them, that hee thanked God hee had withdrawne himselfe from them: and that it was the greatest good, that euer happened to him. And to the end that hee and his companions should no way doubt but that hee was readie to conferre with them, he shewed them a way, by which both parties might be satisfied: to wit; that they should confer to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by writing: shewing, that it should be much more profitable; for as much as by that meane, they should withstand all contentions: that the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and answeres should better be meditated and digested: that many should thereby be edified, and in so dooing, there should be no daunger, that by adding or diminishing, they should bee any way altered.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Ruze</hi> answered, that they could write nothing which hath not beene written. And <hi>De Spina</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>
replied; that they could not also speake ought, which hath not bene spoken. This was the end and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of al their speeches. Wherby may be seene, what will the Doctors had to conferre with the Ministers: to whom, at their arriuall (to stop their passage) they proposed such a condition, as they were well assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, should neuer be accepted of them: namely to enter into publike conference of the scripture, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had publikely prayed to God in the place and assembly where it should be made.</p>
   <p>Moreouer one may also iudge, what was their intention, by the order they had giuen, to direct their conference. For in stead of procuring some place and rest to the said Ministers, which were come vnto them; there were at the least, a hundred persons of all qualities about the Ministers, to astonish them: some by scoffes: others by iniuries: others by threats: So that, had it not bene the care which the three gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of the Duke of <hi>Buillon</hi> had of them, and to driue them often back, which approached too neare them; they had bene in danger to haue suffered out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage. One may also imagine, how the Doctors do endeuour to serue God, and pray vnto him: seeing they cannot endure him to be prayed vnto in their presence. And for conclusion, what vnderstanding can they haue of the scripture? with what faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse can they handle it? And what dexteritie and facultie can they haue to preach it, considering they disdaine, and thinke it straunge, that for the obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of all these things, God should be prayed vnto in their presence? As though their sufficiencie were in themselues, and that it came not from him who is
<pb facs="9"/>
the wel-spring and author of all light.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>It followeth: of the occasions declared in the precedent Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, and first of the Dispute on Wednesday the ninth of Iuly, 1566.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Albeit the Doctors by the meanes heere before declared, had sought occasion to hinder the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence which was to be made betweene them and the Ministers, in the house of my Lord <hi>De Montpensier:</hi> Neuerthelesse, to auoyd the euil opinion that might be conceiued of them, by reason of their refusall, to enter into the said conference, they raised a rumour, that the Ministers, perceiuing themselues weake, and that their doctrine was vncertaine, had fled the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat. Which thing beeing come to the eares of the King and Queene, <hi>Mounsieur</hi> the Admirall, seeing it might bring some scandall and damage to the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches, if it were not presently met with: knowing also, that it was a false reproach which they had put vpon the Ministers, began to excuse them: assuring the King and the Queene, that the Ministers would alwaies be readie to conferre with the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and to defend by the scripture, the confession of their Churches, in what place soeuer, and before such persons, as they would it should bee. So that they were permitted to pray vnto God (as they had required) in the beginning of their conference, and that they should there obserue the order and meanes which they had proposed, or other better, as they should thinke good: to the end to auoyd all wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and the confusion of voyce and cries, as is ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily
<pb n="12" facs="10"/>
seene in schooles, and disputes of Sophisters, and contentious persons.</p>
   <p>My Lord of <hi>Neuers</hi> hauing vnderstood these words of my Lord the Admirall, found them verie reasonable; and perswaded (as it is certaine) first by the spirit of God, and afterwards by a haughtinesse and generositie of heart; which thrust him forward, with a will to vnderstand the truth of each thing, sollicited the King and Queene, that by theyr com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, and vnder their authoritie, the said Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence might bee established: And so wrought he, that hee obtained of their Maiesties what hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded. By meanes whereof, hauing aduerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed my Lord the Admirall of theyr pleasures, they consulted together, of the order should bee held in the same conference. And resolued in the end, that my Lord <hi>De Neuers,</hi> and my Lord the Duke of <hi>Buillon,</hi> should bee the chiefe Iudges therein; and that of the one side, and the other, should some Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen be present, to bee witnesses and beholders, of whatsoeuer should bee done in the same. And further, that there should be two Notaries of both sides, of the litle fort at <hi>Paris,</hi> which should put in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and signe whatsoeuer should be alleadged, and proposed by the parties.</p>
   <p>These conditions thus conceiued, and agreed of among the said Lords; were also accepted by the Doctors, <hi>Vigor</hi> and <hi>De Sanctes</hi> of the one partie, and by the Ministers <hi>De Spina, &amp; Sureau,</hi> of the other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: Who began to assemble themselues together on Tuesday the ninth of Iuly, 1566. in the house of my said Lord of <hi>Neuers:</hi> where in his presence, and of
<pb n="13" facs="10"/>
other Lords which were with him, (after prayers made by the Ministers, in the absence of the Doctors, who because they would not be present, had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn themselues apart) Doctor <hi>Vigor</hi> spake, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan by protestation: That the cause why hee and his companion were entred into Conference with the Ministers, was not to be instructed in any point of Religion: nor any way to withstand the Constituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Councels, and chiefly that of <hi>Trent,</hi> by which they are forbidden to dispute with heretikes: And that they for their part, were wholly resolued to abide in the faith of the Romish Church: but that at the request and pursuite of the Lord <hi>de Montpensier,</hi> (who for the reducing of his daughter Madame <hi>de Buillon,</hi> had required the said Conference) they were come thither to the end, to satisfie him, &amp; declare the holy zeale they haue to seeke and bring backe to the flocke, those which are thence departed.</p>
   <p>Wherevpon (their speeches ended) the Ministers speaking, protested likewise, that, that which had led thē to conference with the Doctors, was not, because they doubted of any article conteined in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, which they knew to bee drawne frō the pure word of God: but that it was to maintaine the same, against the Sophistries and cauillations of thē which would impugne it, and to retaine Madame <hi>de Buillon,</hi> in the good and holy institution, which shee had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by the grace which God had giuen her.</p>
   <p>Thus the protestations on both sides made, the Ministers supposed that the Doctors (thē following the intention of my Lord <hi>de Montpensier,</hi> and the desire of Madame <hi>de Buillon)</hi> should haue begunne
<pb n="14" facs="11"/>
the Conference by the Dispute of two points, the Supper, and the Masse. But as they that will besiege and batter a Towne, begin a farre off to make their Trenches, and approaches: to prepare themselues to the deciding and conference of the said two points, they began to lay their foundation, by the authoritie of the Church: wherevpon they would establish the certaintie of the Articles of faith, and generally of all the holy Scripture. And therefore the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds and objections were proposed by the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. And the answeres giuen by the Ministers; <hi>De Sainctes</hi> beginning, and <hi>De Spina</hi> answering; as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>