<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119234_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03512</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13634</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119234</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Iliads of Homer prince of poets· : Neuer before in any languag truely translated. With a co [m] ment vppon some of his chiefe places; donne according to the Greeke by Geo: Chapman</title>
                 <author>Homer</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 341, 11 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F all bookes extant in all kinds, <hi>Homer</hi> is the first and best. No one<note place="margin">All bookes of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane wisedome.</note> before his (<hi>Iosephus</hi> affirmes,) nor before him (saith <hi>Velleius Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus</hi>) was there any whom he imitated: nor after him, any that could imitate him. And that Poesie may be no ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>se of detraction from al the eminence we giue him; <hi>Spondanus</hi> (preferring it to all Arts and sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences) vnanswerably argues and proues. For to the glory of God, and the singing of his glories, (no man dares deny) man was chiefly made. And what art performes this chiefe end of man, with so much excitation, and expression as Poesie? <hi>Moses, Dauid, Salomon, Iob, Esay, Ieremy, &amp;c.</hi> chiefly vsing that to the end abouesaid. And since the excellence of it cannot be obtained by the labor and art of man (as all easily confesse it,) it must needs be acknowledged, a diuine infusion. To proue which in a word, this distich, (in my estimation) serues something nearely:</p>
   <lg>
      <l>Great Poesie, blind Homer, makes all see</l>
      <l>Thee capable of all Arts, none of thee.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>For out of him (according to our most graue and iudicial <hi>Plutarch</hi>) are all Arts dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, confirmed, or illustrated. It is not therfore the worlds vilifying of it, that can make it vile: for so we might argue, &amp; blaspheme the most incomparably sacred. It is not of the world indeed: but (like <hi>Truth</hi>) hides it selfe frōit. Nor is there any such reality of wisdomes truth in all humane excellence, as in Poets fictions. That most vulgar &amp; foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish receipt of Poeticall licence, being of all knowing men to be exploded; (accepting it, as if Poets had a tale-telling priuiledge aboue others,) no Artist being so strictly, and inextricably confined to all the lawes of learning, wisedome, and truth, as a Poet. For were not his fictions composed of the sinewes and soules of all those; how could they differ farre from, and be combined with eternitie? To all sciences therefore, I must still (with our learned and ingenious <hi>Spondanus</hi>) preferre it; as hauing a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall commerce with the diuine Maiesty; embracing and illustrating al his most holy precepts; and enioying continuall discourse with his thrice perfect, and most comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble spirit. And as the contemplatiue life is most worthily &amp; diuinely preferred by <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> to the actiue; as much as the head to the foote; the eye to the hand; reason to sence; the soule to the bodie: the end it selfe, to all things directed to the end: quiet to motion; and Eternitie to Time; so much preferre I diuine Poesie to all worldly wisedome. To the onely shadow of whose worth yet, I entitle n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>t the bold rimes of euerie Apish and impudent Braggart, (though he dares assume any thing) such I turne ouer to the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of Cobwebs; and shall but chatter on molehels (farre vnder the hill of the Muses) when their fortunat'st selfloue and ambition hath aduanced them highest. Poesie is the flower of the Sunne, &amp; disdains to open to the eye of a candle. So kings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ide their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, &amp; counsels frō the vulgar; <hi>ne euilescant</hi> (saith our <hi>Spond.</hi>) we haue example sacred enough; that true Poesies humility, pouerty &amp; contempt, are badges of diuinity; not vanity. Bray then, and barke against it ye Wolf-fac't worldlings; that nothing but
<pb facs="10"/>
honours, riches, and magistracie, <hi>nescio quos, turgidè spiratis</hi> (that I may vse the words of our friend still,) <hi>Qui solas leges</hi> Iustinianas <hi>crepatis; paragraphum vnum aut alterum, pluris quàm vos ipsos facitis,</hi> &amp;c. I (for my part) shall euer esteeme it much more manly and sacred, in this harmelesse and pious stu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e, to sit till I sinke into my graue, then shine in your vainglorious bubbles, and impieties; al your poore policies, wisedomes, and their trappings, at no more valuing then a musty Nut. And much lesse I wey the frontlesse detractions of some stupide ignorants; that no more knowing me, then their owne beastly ends; and I, euer (to my knowledge) blest from their sight; whisper behind me vilifyings of my translation: out of the <hi>French</hi> affirming them; when both in <hi>French,</hi> and all other languages but his owne, our withall-skill enriched Poet, is so poore and vnpleasing, that no man can discerue from whence flowed his so generally giuen eminence, and admiration. And therfore (by any reasonable creatures conference, of my sleight comment, and conuersion) it will easily appeare how I shunne them: and whether the originall be my rule or not. In which, he shall easily see, I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand the vnderstandings of all other interpreters, and commenters in places of his most depth, importance, and rapture. In whose exposition and illustration, if I abhorre from the sence that others wrest, and racke out of him; let my best detractor examine how the Greeke word warrants me. For my other fresh fry, let them fry in their foolish gals; nothing so much weighed as the barkings of puppies, or foistinghounds; too vile to thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ke of our sacred <hi>Homer,</hi> or set their prophane feete within their liues lengths of his thresholds. If I faile in something, let my full performance in other some restore me; haste spurring me on with other necessities. For as at my conclusion I protest, so here at my entrance, lesse then fifteene weekes was the time, in which all the last twelue books were entirely new translated. No cōference had with any one liuing in al the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelties I presume I haue found. Only some one or two places I haue shewed to my worthy and most learned friend, <hi>M. Harriots,</hi> for his censure how much mine owne weighed: whose iudgement and knowledge in all kinds, I know to be incomparable, and bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse: yea, to be admired as much, as his most blameles life, and the right sacred expence of his time, is to be honoured and reuerenced. Which affirmation of his cleare vnmat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chednesse in all manner of learning; I make in contempt of that nastie obiection often thrust vpon me; that he that will iudge, must know more then he of whom he iudgeth; for so a man should know neither God nor himself. Another right learned, honest, and entirely loued friend of mine, <hi>M. Robert Hews,</hi> I must needs put into my confest con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference touching <hi>Homer,</hi> though very little more then that I had with <hi>M. Harriots.</hi> Which two, I protest, are all, and preferred to all. Nor charge I their authorities with any allowance of my generall labour; but onely of those one or two places, which for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of my innouation, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ow it shewed to them, I imparted. If any taxe me for too much periphrasis or circumlocution in some places, let them reade <hi>Laurentius Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> and <hi>Eobanus Hessus,</hi> who either vse such shortnesse as cometh nothing home to <hi>Homer;</hi> or where they shun that fault, are ten parts more paraphrastical then I. As for example; one place I will trouble you (if you please) to conferre with the originall, and one interpreter for all. It is in the end of the third booke; and is <hi>Hellens</hi> speech to <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> fetching her to <hi>Paris,</hi> from seeing his cowardly combat with <hi>Menelaus:</hi> part of which speech I will here cite:</p>
   <q>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
   </q>
   <p>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> &amp;c. For auoiding the common readers trouble here, I must referre the more <hi>Greekish</hi> to the rest of the speech in <hi>Homer,</hi> whose translation <hi>ad verbum</hi> by <hi>Spondanus,</hi> I will here cite; and then pray you to conferre it with that
<pb facs="10"/>
which followeth of <hi>Valla.</hi>
   </p>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>Quoniam verò nunc</hi> Alexandrum, Menelaus</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Postquam vicit; vult odiosam me domum abducere;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Propterea verò nunc dolum (ceu dolos) cogitans aduenisti?</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Sede apud ipsum vadens, deorum abnega vias,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Neque vnquam tuis pedibus reuertaris in coelum,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Sed semper circa <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>um aerumnas perfer, &amp; ipsum serua</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Donec te vel vxorem faciat, vel hic seruam, &amp;c.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <p>
      <hi>Valla</hi> thus:</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Quoniam victo</hi> Paride, Menelaus, <hi>me miseram, est reportaturus ad lares, ideo tu, ideo falsa sub imagine venisti, vt me deciperes ob tuam nimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am in</hi> Paridem <hi>beneuolentiā: eò dum illi ades, dum illi studes, dum pro illo satagis, dum illum obseruas atque custodis, deorum commercium reliquisti, nec ad eos reuersura es ampliùs; adeò (quantum suspicor) aut vxor eius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>fficieris, aut ancilla, &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Wherein note if there be any such thing as most of this in <hi>Homer;</hi> yet only to expresse (as he th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>nkes) <hi>Homers</hi> conceipt, for the more pleasure of the reader, he vseth this ouerplus <hi>dum illi ades, dum illi studes, dum pro illo satagis, dum illum obseruas, atque custodis, deorum commercium reliquisti.</hi> Which (besides his superfluitie) is vtterly false. For where he saith, <hi>reliquisti deorum commercium, Hellen</hi> saith, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>deorum autem abnega,</hi> or <hi>abnue vias,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, (<hi>vel</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> as it is vsed poetically) signifying <hi>denegare,</hi> or <hi>abnuere;</hi> &amp; <hi>Hellen</hi> (in contempt of her too much obseruing men) bids her renounce heauen, and come liue with <hi>Paris</hi> till he make her his wife or seruant; scoptically or scornefully speaking it: which both <hi>Valla, Eobanus,</hi> and all other interpreters (but these <hi>ad verbum</hi>) haue vtterly mist. And this one example I thought necessarie to insert here, to shew my detractors that they haue no reason to vilifie my circumlocution sometimes, when their most ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued <hi>Grecians, Homers</hi> interpreters, generally hold him fit to be so conuerted. Yet how much I differ, and with what authoritie, let my impartiall, and iudiciall reader iudge. Alwaies conceiuing how pedanticall and absurd an affectation it is, in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of any Author (much more of <hi>Homer</hi>) to turn him word for word; whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> (according to <hi>Horace</hi> and other best lawgiuers to translators) it is the part of euery knowing and iudiciall interpreter, not to follow the number and order of words, but the materiall things themselues, and sentences to weigh diligently; and to clothe and adorne them with words, and such a stile and forme of Oration, as are most apt for the language into which they are conuerted. If I haue not turned him in any place fals<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (as all other his interpreters haue in many, and most of his chiefe places;) if I haue not left behind me any of his sentence, elegancie, height, intention, and inuention: if in some few places (especially in my first edition, being done so long since, &amp; following the cōmon tract) I be somthing paraphrasticall &amp; faulty; is it iustice in that poore fault (if they will needs haue it so) to drowne all the rest of my labour? But there is a certaine enuious Windfucker, that houers vp and downe, laboriously engrossing al the aire with his luxurious ambition; and buzzing into euery eare my detraction; affirming I turne <hi>Homer</hi> out of the Latine onely, &amp;c. that sets all his associates, and the whole rabble of my maligners on their wings with him, to beare about my empaire, and poyson my reputation. One that, as he thinkes, whatsoeuer he giues to others, he takes from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe; so whatsoeuer he takes from others, he addes to himselfe. One that in this kinde of robberie, doth like <hi>Mercurie,</hi> that stole good, and supplied it with counterfeit bad
<pb facs="11"/>
still. One like the two gluttons, <hi>Phyloxenus</hi> and <hi>Gnatho,</hi> that would still emptie their noses in the dishes they loued, that no man might eate but themselues. For so this <hi>Castrill,</hi> with too hote a liuer, and lust after his owne glorie, and to de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>oure all himselfe, discourageth all appetites to the fame of another. I haue striken, single him as you can. Nor note I this, to cast any rubbes, or plasters out of the particular way of mine owne estimation with the world; for I resolue this with the wilfully obscure:</p>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>Sine honore viuam, nullo{que} numero ero.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Without mens honors I will liue, and make</l>
      <l>No number, in the manlesse course they take.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>But to discourage (if it might be) the generall detraction of industrious, and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaning vertue. I know I cannot too much diminish, and deiect my selfe; yet that passing little that I am, God onely knowes; to whose euer-implored respect, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, I onely submit me. If any further edition of these my sillie endeuors shall chance, I will mend what is amisse (God assisting me) and amplifie my harsh Comment to <hi>Homers</hi> farre more right, and mine owne earnest, and ingenious loue of him. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding, I know, the curious, and e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>uious, will neuer sit downe satisfied. A man may go ouer and ouer, till he come ouer and ouer; and his paines be onely his recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence: euery man is so loded with his particular head; and nothing in all respects per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, but what is perceiued by few. <hi>Homer</hi> himselfe hath met with my fortune, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny maligners; and therefore may my poore-selfe, put vp with motion. And so little I will respect malignitie; and so much encourage my selfe with mine owne knowne strength, and what I finde within me, of comfort, and confirmance; (examining my selfe throughout, with a farre more iealous and seuere eye, then my greatest enemie; i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitating this:<q>Iudex ipse sui totum se explorat ad vnguem, &amp;c.)</q>That after these <hi>Iliads,</hi> I will (God lending me life and any meanest meanes) with more labour then I haue lost here, and all vncheckt alacritie, diue through his <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dysses.</hi> Nor can I forget here (but with all heartie gratitude remember) my most ancient, learned, and right noble friend <hi>M. Richard Stapilton,</hi> first most des<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rtfull mouer in the frame of our <hi>Homer.</hi> For which (and much other most ingen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ous and vtterly vndeserued desert) God make me amply his requiter; and be his honorable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies speedy and full restorer. In the meane space, I intreate my impartiall, and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall Reader; that all things to the quicke he will not pare; but humanely and nobly pardon defects; and if he find any thing perfect, receiue it vnenuied.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Of Homer.</head>
      <p>OF his countrey, and time, the difference is so infinite amongst all writers, that there is no question (in my coniecture) of his antiquitie beyond all. To which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, the nearest I will cite; <hi>Adam Cedrenus</hi> placeth him vnder <hi>Dauids</hi> &amp; <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> rule; &amp; the destruction of <hi>Troy</hi> vnder <hi>Sauls.</hi> And of one age with <hi>Solomon, Michael Glycas Siculus</hi> affirmeth him. <hi>Aristotle (in tertio de Poetica)</hi> affirmes he was borne in the Ile of <hi>Io,</hi> begot of a <hi>Genius,</hi> one of them that vsed to dance with the <hi>Muses,</hi> and a virgine of that Ile, comprest by that <hi>Genius,</hi> who being quicke with child (for shame of the deed) came into a place called <hi>Aegina,</hi> and there was taken of theeues, and brought to <hi>Smyrna,</hi> to <hi>Moeon</hi> king of the <hi>Lydians,</hi> who for her beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie maried her. After which, she walking neare the flood <hi>Meletes;</hi> on that shore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouertaken with the throwes of her deliuerie, she brought foorth <hi>Homer,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly
<pb facs="11"/>
died. The infant was receiued by <hi>Moeon,</hi> and brought vp as his owne till his death; which was not long after. And according to this, when the <hi>Lydians</hi> in <hi>Smyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> were afflicted by the <hi>Aeolians,</hi> and thought fit to leaue the citie, the Captaines by a Herald willing all to go out that would, and follow them; <hi>Homer</hi> (being a little child) said he would also <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> (that is, <hi>sequi.</hi>) And of that, (for <hi>Melesigenes,</hi> which was his first name) he was called <hi>Homer.</hi> These <hi>Plutarch.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>The varieties of other reports touching this, I omit for length: and in place thereof, thinke it not vnfit to insert something of his praise, and honour amongst the greatest of all Ages; not that our most absolute of himselfe, needs it; but that such autenticall testimonies of his splendor and excellence, may the better conuince the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of his maligners.</p>
      <p>First, what kind of person <hi>Homer</hi> was, (saith <hi>Spondanus</hi>) his statue teacheth; which <hi>Cedrenus</hi> describeth. The whole place we will describe, that our relation may hold the better coherence; as <hi>Nylander</hi> conuerts it. Then was the <hi>Octagonon</hi> at <hi>Constantinople</hi> consumed with fire; and the Bath of <hi>Seuerus,</hi> that bore the name of <hi>Ze<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>xippus:</hi> in which there was much varietie of spectacle, and splendor of Arts; the workes of all Ages being conferred, and preserued there, of <hi>Marble, Rockes, Stones,</hi> and <hi>Images</hi> of Brasse; to which, this onely wanted; that the soules of the persons they presented, were not in them. Amongst these master peeces, and all-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exceeding workmanships, stood <hi>Homer,</hi> as he was in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>is age; thoughtfull, and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing: his hands folded beneath his bosome; his beard vntrimmed, and hanging downe; the haire of his head in like sort thinne on both sides before; his face with age and cares of the world (as these imagine) wrinkled and austere; his nose proportioned to his other parts; his eyes fixt or turned vp to his eye browes, like one blind (as it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported he was) not born blind (saith <hi>Vell. Paterculus</hi>) which he that imagins (saith he) is blind of all senses. Vpon his vnder coate he was attired with a loose robe; and at the base beneath his feet, a brazen chaine hung. This was the statue of <hi>Homer,</hi> which in that conflagration perished. Another renowned statue of his (saith <hi>Lucian</hi> in his <hi>Encomion</hi> of <hi>Demosthenes</hi>) stood in the temple of <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> on the vpper hand of his own statue. <hi>Cedrenus</hi> likewise remembreth a Library in the Pallace of the king, at <hi>Constantinople,</hi> that contained a thousand a hundred and twentie bookes: amongst which there was the gut of a Dragon, of an hundred and twentie foote long; in which, in letters of gold; the <hi>Iliads,</hi> and <hi>Odysses</hi> of <hi>Homer</hi> were inscribed: which miracle (in <hi>Basiliscus</hi> the Emperours time) was consumed with fire.</p>
      <p>For his respect amongst the most learned; <hi>Plato</hi> in <hi>Ione</hi> calleth him, <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, <hi>Poetarum omnium, &amp; praestantissimum, &amp; diuinissimum.</hi> In <hi>Phaedone,</hi>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, <hi>diuinum Poetam,</hi> and in <hi>Theaetetus, Socrates</hi> citing diuerse of the most wise and learned for confirmation of his there held opinion, (as <hi>Protagoras, Heraclitus, Empedocles, Epicharmus,</hi> and <hi>Homer</hi>) who (saith <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi>) against such an armie, being all led by such a Captaine as <hi>Homer,</hi> dares fight or resist, but he will be held ridiculous? This for <hi>Scaliger,</hi> and all <hi>Homers</hi> enuious and ignorant detractors. Why therefore, <hi>Plato</hi> in another place banisheth him with all other Poets out of his <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> dealing with them like a Politician in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; vse men, and then cast them off, (though <hi>Homer</hi> he thinks fit to send out crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and annointed;) I see not, since he maketh still such honorable mention of him; and with his verses, (as with precious Iemmes▪) euerie where enchaceth his writings. So <hi>Aristotle,</hi> continually celebrateth him. Nay euen amongst the Barbarous, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Homers</hi> name, but his Poems haue bene recorded and reuerenced. The <hi>Indians</hi>
         <pb facs="12"/>
(saith <hi>Aelianus var. hist. lib. 12. cap. 48.</hi>) in their owne tongue had <hi>Homers</hi> Poems translated and sung. Nor those <hi>Indians</hi> alone, but the kings of <hi>Persia.</hi> And amongst the <hi>Indians</hi> (of all the <hi>Greek</hi> Poets, <hi>Homer</hi> being euer first in estimatiō;) whensoeuer they vsed any diuine duties according to the custome of their housholds and hospitali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ies, they inuited euer, <hi>Apollo,</hi> and <hi>Homer. Lucian</hi> in his <hi>Encomion</hi> of <hi>Demosth.</hi> affirmeth all Poets celebrated <hi>Homers</hi> birth day; &amp; sacrificed to him the first fruites of their verses. So <hi>Thersagoras</hi> answereth <hi>Lucian,</hi> he vsed to do himselfe. <hi>Alex. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phius</hi> (saith <hi>Eustathius</hi>) deliuers <hi>Homer,</hi> as borne of <hi>Egyptian</hi> Parents; <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>asa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi> being his father, and <hi>Aethra</hi> his mother; his nurse being a certaine Prophetesse, and the daughter of <hi>Oris, Isis</hi> Priest; from whose breasts, oftentimes, honey flowed in the mouth of the infant. After which, in the night, he vttered nine seuerall notes or voices of fowles, <hi>viz.</hi> of a Swallow, a Peacocke, a Doue, a Crow, a Partrich, a red-Shank, a Stare, a Blackebird, and a Nightingale: and being a little boy, was found playing in his bed with nine Doues. <hi>Sibylla</hi> being at a feast of his Parents, was taken with so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine furie; and sung verses, whose beginning was <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>polynice,</hi> sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying much victorie; in which song also she called him <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> great in glorie; and <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, signifying gyrlond-seller; and commanded him to build a temple to the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gridarij,</hi> that is, to the Muses. <hi>Herodotus</hi> affirmes, that <hi>Phaemius</hi> (teaching a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke schoole at <hi>Smyrna</hi>) was his maister; and <hi>Dionysius</hi> in in 56. oration saith, <hi>Socrates</hi> was <hi>Homers</hi> scholler. In short; what he was, his workes shew most truly; to which (if you please) go on and examine him.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>