<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the noble Knight, Sr HORRACE VERE, Generall of the English-forces in the Low-countries. AND To the most worthy Lady, the Lady MARY VERE his Wife, my most respected and religious Parishioners.</title>
           <author>Byfield, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119554_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17387</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4214</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119554</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the noble Knight, Sr HORRACE VERE, Generall of the English-forces in the Low-countries. AND To the most worthy Lady, the Lady MARY VERE his Wife, my most respected and religious Parishioners.</title>
                 <author>Byfield, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Directions for the priuate reading of the Scriptures : wherein besides the number of chapters assigned to euery day, the order and drift of the whole Scriptures is methodically set downe: and choice rules (that shew how to read with profit) are likewise giuen: the vse whereof is shewed in the preface. By Nicolas Bifeild preacher of Gods word at Isleworth in Middlesex</title>
                 <author>Byfield, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 117, 3 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the noble Knight,</hi> S<seg rend="sup">r</seg> HORRACE VERE, Generall of the English-forces in the <hi>Low-countries.</hi> AND <hi>To the most worthy</hi> Lady, the Lady MARY VERE his <hi>Wife, my most respected and religious Parishioners.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are three things incite me, to Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle direction to your Lordship and my Lady:
<pb facs="3"/>
The first is to testifi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> hereby vnto the world my vnfained estimation of those sauing grace and the true religion that dwels in you both The second is, to ex presse hereby my great desire to shew my thankefulnesse, for the many fauours I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, but especially for all the incouragements wherewith I haue beene refreshed in obseruing your loue to my Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie,
<pb facs="3"/>
aad care in your selues and your familie to shew the profit of it. The third is, because it pleased your Lordship and my Lady hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to desire and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept directions of this kinde from me, in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
   <p>I haue beene the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linger to suffer this copy to come into publike view, because I haue beene vrged by many friends from diuers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="4"/>
of late, to giue them Directions of this kind: and I haue long obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that in the most places the godly that are vnlearned, are at a great want of a setled course herein. If it may please your Lordshippe and my Lady to afford this little worke, your acceptation and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, I shall be richly satisfied. My hope is that the Lord that hath as it were called for it by
<pb facs="4"/>
the request of many well disposed, will bee pleased to giue a bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to it: if any thing be now wanting, by the intimation of my friends, I may make fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther supply in after Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, if God will.</p>
   <p>The Lord multiplie grace &amp; ioy with righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse and peace in both your hearts and liues, and prolong with increase your Lordships honour and good suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse
<pb facs="5"/>
in your militarie calling, in which you haue beene hitherto a speciall ornament to this Nation. I end and rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the seruice of my ministery to be commanded,
N: BIFEILD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>