<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN Reader, an admonition touching reading.</title>
           <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119631_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14450</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24768</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119631</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN Reader, an admonition touching reading.</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A learned and excellent treatise containing all the principall grounds of Christian religion : Set downe by way of conference in a most plaine and familiar manner. Written first in French by maister Mathew Virell, after translated into Latine: and now turned into English for the vse of our countrey-men</title>
                 <author>Virel, Matthieu</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 <publisher>Dexter, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 280 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN Reader, an admonition touching reading.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T falleth out in matter of learning as it doeth in matter of meats. For as in meates, one, &amp; the selfe same dish is diuersly set forth, according to the inuention of the dresser, and appetite of the eater: so in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, one, and the selfe same point is diuersly handled, according to the discretion of the writer, and capacitie of the Reader. Hence it commeth that in humane learning, euery writer (almost) hath his Grammer, his Rhetoricke, his Logicke, his Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophy; and in diuine knowledge, his Catechisme, his Common places, his Commentaries. Many complaine of this, as a thing which distracteth the mind, cōfoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the memorie, and hindereth the iudgement. And not without cause. For as varietie of meates do cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt in the stomacke, and breede sickenesse, rather then preserue health: so variety of treatises, vppon one and the selfe same thing, doth hinder the growth and profiting of diuerse, in soundnesse of iudgement and godly life. But the reformation hereof, is a worke worthy of all the Churches, Princes, and states in chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendome; for the beginning and perfecting where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, priuate men can but pray and wish well; and euery man carefully look to the warrant of his own worke. In the mean time let no man condemne, the variety and choise of Gods manifold gifts, which both in bodily and spirituall thinges, set foorth the riches of his wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and goodnesse. What then? Surely the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and vanity of men, who, doe eyther not vse at all, or else greatly abuse the gifts and blessings of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed vpon them. This vanity appeareth partly in the foode of the body, but more specially in the food of the soule. <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 28. 23.</note> For no man will refuse his meate except it be in some extreame passion. Besides, how carefull are the most part in making their prouision? how curious in as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="3"/> what is wholesome or hurtfull for thē? how precise and constant in keeping their hours for dinner &amp; sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per? how willing to keep themselues to some few kinds of meat, though they haue often tasted &amp; fed on them before? But touching the food of the soule (which cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth chiefly in the pure vse of Gods publick worship, and partly in holy praiers, meditations, and readings in priuat) how many do refuse it as a fruitlesse &amp; vnsauory thing? And though the most part be content, for some carnall respect, to shew themselues in the publicke as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblies: yet who shall find a faithfull Christian, that is carefull to redeeme the time, and to make himselfe, by priuate reading and meditation, more fit to reape fruit by the publicke ministery of the word and sacraments? But know thou (beloued) that as they, who, through er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, preiudice, or self loue, are so addicted to their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uat studies that they despise or neglect the publick mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery, shall (without speedy mercy from God, fal into diuerse fond opinions, and dangerous errors, and pine away in their ignorāce &amp; sins: so to little purpose is out hearing of sermons abroad, if there be not a setled and constant course of priuat prayer, reading, meditation, and conference at home. But because my purpose is now to speak only of reading, and that very briefly (for the argument is infinit, and I haue somewhat touched it else where,) <note place="margin">Preface to master Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers Sermōs</note> I would entreat thee Christian reader, and in the Lord Iesus beseech thee (if my request may seeme reasonable) that thou wouldst be as wise for thy soule as thou art for thy body; as mindfull of the life to come, as thou art of this present life; <note place="margin">Four things to be obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</note> and that for this end thou wouldest obserue these foure things, as well for the one as for the other. <note place="margin">1 Prouide the best bookes.</note> First therefore make thy prouision of good books, especially of the booke of all books, I meane the holy Canonicall Scriptures, in that respect called the Bible: &amp; then of some other, such as are most fit for thy calling and capacitiy. And because thou shalt want either money to buy, leysure to reade, iudgement to vnderstand, or memory to bear away the substance of al good books, prouide the best. Many wil
<pb facs="3"/> say, they find by experience that in meate and apparel the best is best cheape: and thou shalt bee sure to find, that among bookes the best will yeeld most fruit to thy soule. <note place="margin">2 In chus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ng vse the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise of the godly lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> Secondly, because the most part are babes in iudgement and discerning of spirituall things (though euery foole be wise in his own eyes) not knowing what is fit &amp; profitable, or what is hurtfull and inconueniēt: let me intreat thee to aske counsell and aduise of the godly learned, especially of thine owne pastor (if God haue blessed thee with an able &amp; faithful mā) <note place="margin">
         <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 14.</note> or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise of him whose publicke ministerie may giue thee hope that his senses are exercised in the discerning of good and euill. No wise man will receaue a writing for the least plot of ground without the counsaile of some learned Lawyer, nor a medicine for his body, without the aduise of some learned Phisitiō: and wilt thou ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vpō a booke, wherein may be some dānable error, which may cōuay frō thee thy heauēly inheritance; or some deadly poison, which may kill the soule, without the direction of some godly diuine? do it not. <note place="margin">3 Be constant in keeping of houres.</note> Thirdly, remember that nothing is more hard, then to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stāt in holy exercises. For herein the subtiltie and rage of our inuisible enemie Sathan doth most notably ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, herein the frailtie &amp; corruption of flesh &amp; bloud will bewray it selfe. Here profit &amp; pleasure, businesse, &amp; idlenesse, matters at home &amp; matters abroad, cōpany, &amp; a thousand occasions will lye in our way as so many Lions to let &amp; hinder vs. Therefore herein gird vp the loynes of thy mind, put vpon thee the whole armour of God, &amp; dayly renue thy couenāt of redeeming the time made with God and thy owne conscience. Thou seest that men who are most greedy of the world, will not misse (scarce once in a yeare) their ordinary hours of eating and drinking. Why then shouldest thou be so sickle &amp; vnfaithfull in forgetting &amp; omitting the times of reading and praying vnto God. <note place="margin">4 Read a good booke through, and read it often ouer.</note> Fourthly, whē thou hast begun a good booke, giue not ouer till thou haue ended it, &amp; when thou hast read it ouer once, let it not be tedious vnto thee to read it ouer again &amp; again, for
<pb facs="4"/> thou shalt finde the second reading more fruitfull thē the first, &amp; the third more fruitfull then the second, &amp; so the oftener the better This is a great vanitie &amp; an euill sicknesse among mē, that if they haue once seene the title of a booke, and the authors name, &amp; read two or three leaues, it is cast at their heeles for euer after, as if they had attained all that could be learned by it, when they can name the title &amp; author of it. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for this point marke the course &amp; manner of mē in the keeping and encreasing of their bodily strēgth though they eate their fill of this kinde of meate to day, yet they come with great desire and fresh appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite to the same againe within a day or two, yea of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes the same day: otherwise it argueth either an extreme weakenesse or an intollerable daintinesse of the stomacke. Here perhaps thou wilt aske what bookes, beside the holy Bible I would commend vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee: Wherein though I see some difficultie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it cannot be done without cōparisons which are coūted odious: yet for thy good I wil not spare to shew my poore opiniō: <note place="margin">No one book of the like volume more fruite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full then Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell.</note> which is that no one mā (that I haue seen) hath set down the summe &amp; grounds of Christiā Religion more holily &amp; happily, for the capacitie and edifying of all sortes, thē this present author. For this cause I specially recōmend him to thee, as one by whō thou mayst specially profit if thou call vpō the name of God through Iesus Christ, &amp; bind thy selfe to diligēce &amp; constancie: remembring that as one dish of meate, well chewed &amp; digested, will cōfort nature more then diuers delicates, that lye raw &amp; vndigested in the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, so one booke often &amp; throughly read wil do thy soule more good, then the superficiall fight and tast of a thousand. And so I commend thee to the Lord, who vouchsafe to giue thee wisedome in all thinges, for his mercies sake. Blacke Friers the 23. of Iuly. Thine in the Lord Iesus.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>STEPH. EGERTON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>