<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORY, To the Right Reuerend Lords, the LL. Arch∣bishops of England: And to the right Wor∣shipfull, the Heads, and Maisters of the Col∣ledges of both Vniuersities.</title>
           <author>N., O.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119849_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07966</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18333</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119849</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORY, To the Right Reuerend Lords, the LL. Arch∣bishops of England: And to the right Wor∣shipfull, the Heads, and Maisters of the Col∣ledges of both Vniuersities.</title>
                 <author>N., O.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An apology of English Arminianisme or A dialogue : betweene Iacobus Arminius, professour in the Vniuersity of Leyden in Holland; and Enthusiastus an English Doctour of Diuinity and a great precisian. Wherein are defended the doctrines of Arminius touching freewill, predestination, and reprobation: the said doctrines being mantained &amp; taught by many of the most learned Protestants of England, at this present time. Written by O.N. heertofore of the Vniuersity of Oxford</title>
                 <author>O. N.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 200 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>
      <hi>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORY,</hi> To the Right Reuerend Lords, the LL. Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishops of England: And to the right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull, the Heads, and Maisters of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of both Vniuersities.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST Reuerend Lords,</hi> and you other <hi>Learned men of our Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersities</hi> (vvhose due <hi>Panegyricks,</hi> and <hi>Lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues</hi> deserue to proceed from a more skillfull Penne, then mine:) you are not to thinke strange, that I make bould to dedicate this my small <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise</hi> to your selues. The reason is manifest, and it is this.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>Common Report (and you knovv the vulgar saying, <hi>Ʋox populi, vox Dei</hi>) though it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten erre in its ovvne agitation, hath neuerthelesse voyced it much throghout this Realme, that diuers of You do entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne in your iudgments, certai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne <hi>Positions</hi> in doctrine, not long since reuiued by <hi>Iacobus Arminius,</hi> heertofore the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike <hi>Poofessour</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> in <hi>Holland:</hi> To vvit; 1. <hi>Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching mans hauing Freevvill. 2. That no man is infallibly assu- of his Saluation. 3. That iustify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fayth may be lost. 4. And finally, that God doth not repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate any man to damnation, vvithout preuision, or reference
<pb facs="4"/>
to his bad and vvicked vvorkes.</hi> Yea some of you haue in your publike Sermōs learnedly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fēded certaine of these Points. And of my ovvne knovvledge there are diuers in the <hi>Ʋniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities,</hi> most strong in the sayd doctrines.</p>
   <p>The truth of this then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so fully acknovvledged, I (vvho do runne one, and the same line of doctrine vvith you heerin) haue vndertaken to vvarrant and make good in these ensuing leaues, the most Ancient, &amp; <hi>Orthodoxall</hi> Verity of the said Points: &amp; therfore in regard of this assumed At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, my <hi>Ambition</hi> hath em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouldned this my <hi>Dedication.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="5"/>I presume, that most of you, vvho are Patrones of these▪ <hi>Theorems,</hi> haue already forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed your Iudgments (throgh your ovvne▪ Reading) vvith most of the Arguments, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in this <hi>Treatise;</hi> &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this respect, to You it vvill proue lesse necessary, or profitable▪ Neuerthelesse, that▪ those, vvho are <hi>Anomalous,</hi> and irregular Professours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you (as I may terme them,) and vvho through the crookednes of their ovvn paths, do tread different steps from You therein, may see, vpon vvhat grounds (both <hi>Diuine</hi> and <hi>Humane</hi>) the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Articles are seated, and▪
<pb facs="5"/>
consequently hovv incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible the contrary <hi>Tenets</hi> are vvith the holy Scriptures; I haue to that end vndertaken this <hi>Prouince.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The matter is heer deliuered in the forme of a <hi>Dialogue,</hi> as best comporting vvith the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stidious humour of the present times The Interlocutours are, <hi>Arminius</hi> himselfe (vvhome I suppose to be novv liuing) &amp; one <hi>Enthusiastus</hi> an <hi>Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> English Doctor of <hi>Diuinity;</hi> a man, sufficiētly learned, but a great <hi>Precisian,</hi> &amp; a resolute Enemy to the former Positiōs of <hi>Arminius.</hi> What othervvise this aēry <hi>Doctour</hi> is, You may casely coniecture; since to you
<pb facs="6"/>
vvho are learned, his name (as comming from the Greeke Verbe <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>) is his <hi>Character.</hi> Novv touching the further fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of this <hi>Dialogue,</hi> I refer you to the <hi>Argument</hi> thereof prefixed before.</p>
   <p>If this my labour may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come seruiceable to any▪ I shal hould my selfe sufficiently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compensed: but hovvsoeuer, my cōfort is, that the <hi>Highest</hi> euer setteth a poise more vpon the intention of the Worker, then vpon the vvorke it selfe: &amp; vvell I am assured, that my▪ intention heerin is <hi>Azimous,</hi> and pure, as leuelling only at the spirituall good of others.</p>
   <p>That I partly become <hi>Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymous,</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
or rather (in outvvard shevv) <hi>Fatherlesse</hi> to this my ovvne <hi>Issue,</hi> contēting my self only (as it vvere) to <hi>Anagrā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matize</hi> my name vnder tvvo letters, your Ingenuity &amp; Cā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour (I hope) vvill pardō. The maine reason of thus masking my self, is this follovving: ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting once the <hi>Author</hi> heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to be certainley knovvne, vvhat sallies, and incursions (more against my <hi>Person,</hi> then against my <hi>Treatise</hi>) vould the▪ maintainers of the contrary doctrines make vvith their Pens? And hovv vvould they, and their follovvers (being so infinite in number, and vvarranted vvith the streame
<pb facs="7"/>
&amp; current of the tymes) euen shovvre dovvn vvords (of Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, &amp; Cōtumely vpon me▪ So loath I am to stand vvithin the breath of such men.</p>
   <p>But novv, <hi>Reuerend men,</hi> I vvill exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tiate no further; noi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther vvill I distune your eares vvith any longer difcourse; as being more vvilling to spread my selfe in <hi>Matter,</hi> then in <hi>VVords▪</hi> Therefore referring this small vvorke (I could vvish to your <hi>Patronage</hi>) I hope, to your <hi>perusall,</hi> I commit You to the Protection of him, vvho is the Protectour of <hi>Israel,</hi> and do rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in all dutifull Obseruancy, O. N.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>