<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honorable Sir Thomas Egerton Knight: Lord Keeper of the great Seale of England: Cham∣berlaine of the Countie Palatine of Chester: and of her Maiesties most Honorable priuie Counsaile.</title>
           <author>Golburne, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119134_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14408</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24727</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119134</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honorable Sir Thomas Egerton Knight: Lord Keeper of the great Seale of England: Cham∣berlaine of the Countie Palatine of Chester: and of her Maiesties most Honorable priuie Counsaile.</title>
                 <author>Golburne, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Acts of the dispute and conference holden at Paris, in the moneths of Iuly and August. 1566. Betweene two doctors of Sorbon, and two ministers of the Reformed Church : A most excellent tract, wherein the learned may take pleasure, and the ignorant reape knowledge. Translate out of French by Iohn Golburne, and diuided according to the daies</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 263, 5 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Honorable Sir <hi>Thomas Egerton</hi> Knight: Lord Keeper of the great Seale of England: Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine of the Countie <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Chester:</hi> and of <hi>her Maiesties most Honorable priuie Counsaile.</hi>
   </head>
   <head type="sub">
      <hi>I. G.</hi> wisheth all health, honour, and euerlasting happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, my good Lorde: If affectionate dutie shall be held presumption, or any taxe me of rashnesse, for still troubling your Lordship with my rude labors; I plead mine excuse, with the Poet <hi>Affranius:</hi> who (blamed for guilt of like crime to <hi>Traian)</hi> yet dared to present him, with homely Poems: excusing himselfe still, with the curtesie of the Emperour, which as Princely accepted, as the other poorely offered: And so shrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the shelter of your honorable cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesie, I shall be shielded from the stormes of
<pb facs="3"/>
idle imputations, stop (as did <hi>Affranius)</hi> the mouthes of my Taxors▪ and aduenture once more to present vnto your Lordship, my pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son-night-watches, as a simple token of my thankfulnesse, and pledge of further dutie: then deeming my selfe happie, when I may acknowledge your honourable goodnesse, with any performance of dutie, or accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble seruice to your Lordship, to whom, both my self, and poore endeuours, are wholy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoted. The worthy and necessary vse of this <hi>Treatise,</hi> I leaue to the graue iudgment of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Censors:</hi> and in all dutie and zeale, do of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it to your Lordships Patronage, &amp; assure me of your like good (as former) acceptance. For a good vine yeeldes grapes, still answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to it nature▪ and an honourable mind, the fruits of an honorable disposition. Long liue, and prosper (ho. Lord). <hi>Pater sis Patriae, &amp; Ecclesiae, &amp; Reipublicae charus.</hi> So in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, I take leaue. Fleete this 25. of March. 1602.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships most bounden<lb/>
in all dutifull affection;<lb/>
         <hi>Iohn Golburne.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>