<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119173_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20757</idno>
           <idno type="STC">714</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119173</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe discourse of the most haynous and traytorlike fact of Thomas Appeltree : for which hee shoulde haue suffred death on Tuisday the one and twentith of Iulie last: wherin is set downe his confession. Whereunto is annexed, the report of the message sent to the place of execution from hir most excellent Maiestie, by the right honourable Sir Christopher Hatton Knight, vizchaberlain to hir highnesse</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as much as the nature of man is affected to listen after newes, by the report whereof ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the minde is delighted, or else stricken with fear, I haue thought it conuenient to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish vnto all the worlde, and namely to all good and godly subiects, a thing of no small importaunce, verie straunge, and not so strange, as most certaine true. May it therfore please thee to peruse this little booke, wherin as in a loking glasse, thou shale beholde to thy great comfort, the verie effectes of iustice, iustlie executed against an offender, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thilie condemned to death: and further, thou shalt to thy ioye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the rare and singular mercies offered vnto him, that had most grieuouslie trespassed against the royal estate of this noble realme of England, euen by the Queenes most excellent maiestie, for whose prosperitie all faithful heartes are bound continuallie to praie to the Almightie, who guide and gouerne hir, high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse with his holie spirite, poure vpon hir the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting deawes of his heauenlie grace, prosper hir in all hir affaires, graunt hir long life, health, peace, and quietnesse of bodie and minde, where vnto all true harted subiectes vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe with me to say. <hi>AMEN.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>