<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The coppie of a Letter written
by a Gentleman of account, sent to a Ladie
in England, concerning the present state
of the Lowe Countries.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119062_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14338</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24652</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119062</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The coppie of a Letter written
by a Gentleman of account, sent to a Ladie
in England, concerning the present state
of the Lowe Countries.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>True nevves from one of Sir Fraunces Veres companie : Concerning Delftes-Isle, and sundry other townes in the Lowe Countries, yeelded to the generall since May last. Of the great armie, nowe comminge out of Germanie for the aide of the French King, and their hope for the speedye winninge of Antwerpe. VVith the bloody persecution and marterdome which sundry cheefe persons of account did lately suffer in Spaine for the profession of Christ Iesus. Translated out of Dutch. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Nelson, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The coppie of a Letter written
by a Gentleman of account, sent to a Ladie
in England, concerning the present state
of the Lowe Countries.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable Ladye
to whom I am in all duety
bound: the dispatch of my
last letter sent away with
such great speede concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
the yeelding vp of the
Sconce and towne of <hi>Zut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen,</hi>
made me ouerslip to acquainte your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diship
with one peece of seruice don at that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant
by a straunger in our Campe, a thinge
worthy to bee remembred, which was as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.
After we had obtained the Sconce of
<hi>Zutphen,</hi> we set forward towardes the town,
against which hauing placed our ordenaunce,
with full resolution by force to enter it: there
issued foorth of the said towne of <hi>Zutphen</hi> an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talian
hauing so sterne a countenaunce, and
beeing so mighty a man of person, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he seemed
more like a monster then a man: this Italian
carryinge a countenaunce as it had beene a
young Giant, vaunted him selfe, and made a
<pb facs="3"/>
proud challenge before our General the <hi>Graue
van Maurice,</hi> offering to combate hand to hand
with any Gentleman hee had in all his armie,
for the estate of the whole towne. But the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
made slight accounte of his challenge,
and was very vnwilling that any one shoulde
fight with him, the rather for that he seemed to
bee so mightie a man at armes.</p>
   <p>Hereupon a young youth (borne in the Low
Countries) stepte before the Generall beeing
scarce 19. yeeres of age hauing no haire on his
face, and vpon his knee besought the General
that hee might be permitted to Combate and
fight with this mightie Champion, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the Generall woulde hardlye condecend
by reason of the youngnes of his yeares, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthelesse
at the importunate sute of the
young man whose name was <hi>Rihouen,</hi> the
Generall gaue his consent, commaundinge
him to be mounted vpon a great horse who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
well armed and prouided for that purpose,
set vpon this challenger, they beeing bothe
singled foorth in the plaine fielde, began to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sault
and run at eache other with their Laun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
which beeing broken, <hi>Rihouen</hi> suddainly
began to drawe foorth his Cutlace wherwith
he entending to haue smitten the Italian (from
whom he also looked to receiue the like curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie)
suddainely espied this challenger to haue a
dagge charged which he was discharging at
<hi>Rihouen,</hi> wherupon <hi>Riechouen</hi> fiercely stroke
a him and at the first blowe cut of his right
arme, so that the arme, dagge and all fell to the
<pb facs="3"/>
ground. Whereupon <hi>Riehouen</hi> tooke him pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soner
and brought him before the Generall,
who not onely commended him but bountiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
rewarded him for his honourable seruice.</p>
   <p>Thus much I thought good to certifie vnto
your good Ladiship the thing beeing trueth, &amp;
besides here withall to signify vnto you, our
good successe and affaires happened since that
time. May it therefore please your Ladiship
to vnderstand, that so soone as wee had obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<hi>Zutphen,</hi> wee marched with our forces to
<hi>Deuenter,</hi> wher hauing planted our ordinance
before the weakest part of the towne, we pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ied
vpon it with the Cannon, so y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> on the first
night, our Souldiers were lodged vnder the
walles thereof.</p>
   <p>On the next morning early, the enemy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing
our great preparation and whot as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sault,
and that we were resolued to enter the
towne by force, craued a parley being no way
able to withstand vs, whereupon the Lord of
<hi>Fama</hi> being General of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ordinance with some
of the cheefe commanders of our army, asked
them if their demaund were in good earnest or
not, which they affirmed by a great oath to be
don in earnest.</p>
   <p>Wherupon we presently appointed two cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines
the one called <hi>Vandernots,</hi> and the other
<hi>Lennits,</hi> these two we appointed to go into the
Citty accompanied with some few souldiers.
On the Enemies side, two of their Captaines
came into our campe as pledges the one being
a Spaniard, the other a Wallonne, with whō
<pb facs="4"/>
when his excellency had cōferred, he granted
vnto them after a ripe deliberation with his
councell at war, the same conditions that he
had graunted before vnto the towne of <hi>Zut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen,</hi>
the coppie wherof was as followeth.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>The agreement of his excellencie with those
of Deuenter.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>MAurice</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> Earle of <hi>Nassawe
Catzelenboghen, Vianden, dieth</hi> &amp;c. Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
and Captaine Generall of the dukedome
of <hi>Gelderland</hi> and the counties of <hi>Holland, Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
West-frieseland, Zutphen, Virich</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerrisell,</hi>
Admirall Generall, &amp;c. Promise by
these presentes and vpon our honour to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour,
Captaines, officers and souldiers, as
also to the Cittizens and inhabitantes of the
Citty of <hi>Deuenter,</hi> of what quallitie or conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
soeuer, that they maye with their wiues,
Children, mooueables, furniture, and withall
other appurtenances, freely departe out of
the said citty either to <hi>Nimweghen,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
place wheresoeuer it shall please them.</p>
      <p>And if it happen that some of the said Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,
Officers, and soldiers spirituall or tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall
or any of the cittizens be not able to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch
their affaires so soone, we then graunt
vnto them moreouer the space of three daies
free, wherein to dispatch all their busines: and
that it shall be lawful for them to depart when
so euer they please. And those that shall bee
willing to remaine where they are, whether
they are spirituall or temporall shal be vsed as
the other inhabitants of the vnited prouinces.</p>
      <p>
         <pb facs="4"/>
And to the ende that they may bee the more
assured hereof, we graunt vnto them a certain
Conuoy and sixe horses, vpon condition not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding:
that their Liefetenant Collonel
shall promise and binde him selfe to see them
safely deliuered againe in <hi>Deuenter,</hi> so soone as
they shall be arriued at the place appointed.</p>
      <p>These conditions beeing ratified and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
vnder the hande and seale of his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie,
on the tenth day of Iune, the said towne
was immediatelye yeelded vp vnto the sayde
Lord Generall to the vse of the States.</p>
      <p>After wee had thus obtained the towne of
<hi>Deuenter,</hi> we gaue some small assault against
the towne of <hi>Nimmingham</hi> where we made
no tariaunce. Then we passed toward <hi>Grun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningen,</hi>
and in our way we assaulted a town of
great strength called <hi>Delits Ile:</hi> beeinge eight
English mile from <hi>Giunningen,</hi> which towne
was strongly fortified and entrenched: neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse
wee had not lien before it aboue two
daies, but the towne was constrained by force
to yeelde vnto vs, for wee entered the Sconce,
where we had a fierce battaile: but in the end
wee put many of the Enemies to
the sword, without the
losse of any store of
men.</p>
      <p>
         <pb facs="5"/>
THe towne of <hi>Delftes Isle,</hi> (after we had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
it,) wee fortified it and sent our army
immediatly towards <hi>Stenwick,</hi> before which
town we nowlie, hauing daily some small skir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mishes: In this towne it is supposed that the
Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> abideth, whose strongest
power at this present is not aboue three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand.
We receiued certaine newes from <hi>Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi>
that the Lord Uiconte of <hi>Turyn,</hi> accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied
with some of the nobilitie of <hi>Germany,</hi> is
comminge downe into the Lowe Countries
with thirty thousand footemen, and ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand
horse-men, these purpose to haue passage
into <hi>Fraunce</hi> for thereleefe &amp; aide of the french
King, and our general meeteth them the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
of this month to welcome them into the
countrie: they are very valiant soldiours and
wonderfully well prouided both for horse and
foote, I trust verye shortly to aduertise you of
some attempte to bee perfourmed against <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twerpe:</hi>
which forthwith we meane to put in
practise, for hauing gotten the Castell of <hi>Tuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nout</hi>
which we now enioy, wee may plainlye
come to the walles of the Cittye: Wee heere
good newes God be thanked out of all partes
especiallye out of <hi>Brittany,</hi> where a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
of Captaine <hi>Salamon Wolfes</hi> companye
writeth that he is in good hope, very shortly to
send word of one of the most brauest and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendablest
battels that euer was fought this
hundreth yeere, well God and S. George for
England, God blesse them and our Generall
with S. <hi>Frauncis Vere</hi> vnder whose comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement
<pb facs="5"/>
I still abide, our Generall deserueth
great honour for his skill and curradge, and so
dooth S. <hi>Frauncis</hi> who is in good health, hee
sheweth that he is decended of an honourable
house: yea his very name is feared in all the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
forces. The thundring shot of the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non
calleth me to my place, and therefore am
constrained to cut short, leauing your good La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieship
to the consideration of all heerein ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed
which is no more but what I
my selfe haue seene and
know for truth.</p>
      <p>The towne of <hi>Groninghen</hi> is somewhat dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tressed,
by reason the passage is hindered tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough
the taking of <hi>Delftes Isle.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>The towne of <hi>Huelft</hi> in the land of wast is
lately yeelded.</p>
      <p>And the greatest part of <hi>Artoyes</hi> is now in
yeelding.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>