<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Criticke-seeming Censurer.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119941_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09036</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19328</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119941</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Criticke-seeming Censurer.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cures for the itch : Characters. Epigrams. Epitaphs. By H.P</title>
                 <author>Parrot, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jones, Thomas 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_critic">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Criticke-seeming Censurer.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou maist be curteous for ought I know, without the least of carping or deprauing, let thy wits excellence or worths best estimate be what it will: Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sir, then might it be askt me why I should thou thee, or any Gentleman of those in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments, My answer briefly (though not worth the answering) is, that thy betters haue much more endured, and daily doe accept without exceptions. But to the businesse, Here's a new Booke, or rather new Brood (as a man may call it) of some vnusuall odde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, hastily hatcht without obseruance of time, rule, or reckoning, and therfore little know I yet what may become of them; nor dare I promise more on their behalfes, then that they either may starue through pouerty, or desperately lye vpon the parish for want
<pb facs="4"/>
of shelter, so farre vnlikely will it be (I know) to finde the owners or fathers out, who que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stionlesse will quite disclaim them to be their Bastards though nere so iumpe a like in qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities as can or may be possibly required. But to leaue Metaphors, I know I shall bee fowly censured, and that by none so much, as those, that are or haue beene of mine own acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, I mean not such as are iudicious (whom I loue and reuerence) but other sort of prou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vpstarts that would bee wiser then their ancestors, because a little bolstered vp since their forgetfull base beginnings. I should but vex my selfe, and ill detaine you with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of things so friuolous, which ceasing so much as but to thinke vpon, If any man shall question me; <hi>Quorsum haec inania scripsi,</hi> tis ten to one I answer not directy, more then thus, that whats done and past cannot bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cald: Therefore in briefe, without least complements (as I said before) whatsoeuer to others may proue distastfull, shall vnto me be twice as odious, and there's an end.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>