<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>William Bulleyne</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1572</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119043_Fr1_9</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14315</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24631</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119043</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>William Bulleyne</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The foure bookes of Flauius Vegetius Renatus : briefelye contayninge a plaine forme, and perfect knowledge of martiall policye, feates of chiualrie, and vvhatsoeuer pertayneth to warre. Translated out af [sic] lattine, into Englishe, by Iohn Sadler. Anno. 1572. Seene and allovved, accordinge to the order appointed</title>
                 <author>Vegetius Renatus, Flavius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1572</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 66, 8 leaves, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>William Bulleyne</head>
   <lg>
      <l>THe fruites of fearefull warre, eche wight maye plainly knowe:</l>
      <l>It is the rodde from God aboue, to vs that dwell belowe.</l>
      <l>A blessing rich it is in deede, where God doth winne the fielde:</l>
      <l>Or els a triple plague (God wotte) to vse the sword or shielde.</l>
      <l>By warre most lands &amp; Cittyes great were wonne and still do stand:</l>
      <l>By warre Nauyes and gallyes swift haue gayned many a lande.</l>
      <l>Euen so great fortes and walled townes by warres ouerthrowne:</l>
      <l>Sometime (agayne) the Nauyes great in stormes are ouerblowne.</l>
      <l>And captiues great in bondage ledde, which neuer backe returnes</l>
      <l>And bloudye corpes in streete lye dead: the fyer consumes &amp; burnes.</l>
      <l>The buildinges fayre, and antiques olde: in bedde the child is slaine:</l>
      <l>The Temples huge are cast a downe: nothinge doth els remayne,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="10"/>But hunger plague, &amp; bloudy woundes, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mother her child doth ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e:</l>
      <l>Dunge is daintye to hungrye slaues, when they do dye for meate.</l>
      <l>Why then feare God, loue wel your Prince, esteeme y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> man of warre:</l>
      <l>For they do garde eche common wealth, &amp; chase thine ennemye farre.</l>
      <l>Geue peace good God in these our dayes, for thou dost for vs fight</l>
      <l>Preserue the Church, defende y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Queene, and people daye and nighte.</l>
      <l>And Sadler then for his rewarde d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e prayses let him haue:</l>
      <l>Take in good part his diligence, els nothing doth he craue,</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The Prince to chiefe rule,</l>
      <l>The Preacher to the worde:</l>
      <l>The Lawyer to the skroule,</l>
      <l>The Souldiour to the sword.</l>
      <l>The Marchant to the purse,</l>
      <l>The thrasher to the flayle,</l>
      <l>The sheapehearde to the flocke:</l>
      <l>The mariner to the sayle.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>