<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>W., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119589_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14783</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25082a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119589</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>W., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Albions England : a continued historie of the same kingdome, from the originals of the first inhabitants thereof: and most the chiefe alterations and accidents there hapning: vnto, and in, the happie raigne of our now most gracious soueraigne Queene Elizabeth. VVith varieti of inuentiue and historicall intermixtures. First penned and published by VVilliam VVarner: and now reuised, and newly inlarged by the same author</title>
                 <author>Warner, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Joan</publisher>
                    <distributor>Broome (Brome), Joan</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 336 pages, folded plates, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>El know I, that Pearls low-pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in <hi>India</hi> are precious in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that euen <hi>Homer</hi> was slightly authorised in <hi>Greece,</hi> but singularly admired elswhere, and that for the most part, the best Authors find at home their worst Auditors: howbeit, whatsoeuer VVriter is most famous, the same is therefore indebted to his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Language: Neither preferre I aboue three spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches before ours, for more sententious.</p>
   <p>VVritten haue I alreadie in Proese, allowed of some: and now (friendly Reader) offer I Uerse, atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thine indifferent (ensure. In which, if grosely I faile (as not greatly I so feare) in Ueritie, Breuitie, Inuention, and Uarietie, profitable, patheticall, pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, and pleasant, so farre off shall I be from being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinionate of mine owne Labours, that my selfe will also subscribe to prescribe the same for absurd and
<pb facs="4"/>
erronious. But in Uaine is it either to intreat or feare the Courteous or Captious: the one will not cauill, nor the other be reconciled.</p>
   <p>My labour is past, and your liking to come: and things hardly founded, may easily be confounded; Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancie is <hi>Linx-</hi>eyed into aduantages: Enuie and selfe-conceited Readers capable of the least errour. But such are good Mindes, and the Contraries of these Men in reading of Books, as were the Paganes in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerencing their Gods, sacrificing as deuoutly to a woodden <hi>Iupiter,</hi> as to a golden <hi>Iupiter:</hi> to an Oxe, a (at, or vnreuerent <hi>Priapus,</hi> as to the Sunne, the Starres, or amiable <hi>Venus:</hi> deuotion and discretion being euermore senceles in detraction. Of the latter sorte therefore I craue pardon, presupposing their patience; to the former, presupposing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience, I offer pardon: resting to either, and to you all, in good will such as I should.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours.
W. W.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>