<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER</title>
           <author>J., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119449_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04613</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14732</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119449</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER</title>
                 <author>J., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first booke of songes or ayres of foure parts with tableture for the lute : So made that all the parts together, or either of them seuerally may be song to the lute, orpherian or viol de gambo. Composed by Robert Iones</title>
                 <author>Jones, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Morley, Thomas, Assignee (with assent, etc.) of.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Short, Peter</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, music, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>
      <add>TO THE READER</add>
   </head>
   <p>
      <add>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLEMEN, since my desire is your eares shoulde be my indifferent iudges, I cannot thinke it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to make my trauels, or my bringing vp arguments to perswade you that I haue a good opinion of my selfe, only thus much will I saie: That I may preuent the rash iudgments of such as know me not. Euer since I practised spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, I haue practised singing; hauing had noe other qualitie to hinder me from the perfect knowledge of this faculty, I haue been incouraged by the warrant of diuers good iudgments, that my paines herein shall at the least procure good liking, if not delight, which yet for mine owne part I must needes feare as much as I desire, especially when I consider the ripenes of this industrious age, wherein all men ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to knowe all thinges, I confesse I was not vnwilling to embrace the conceits of such gentlemen as were earnest to haue me apparel these dit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for them; which though they intended for their priuate recreation, neuer meaning they should come into the light, were yet content vpon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty to make the incouragements of this my first adventure, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon I was almost glad to make my small skill knowne to the world: presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that if my cunning failed me in the Musicke: yet the words might speake for themselues, howsoeuer it pleaseth them to account better of that, then of those. Of purpose (as it should seeme) to make me belieue I can do something; my only hope is, that seeing neither my cold ayres, not their idle ditties (as they will needes haue me call them) have hitherto beene sounded in the eares of manie: they maie chance to finde such en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, as commonlie newes doth in the world: which if I may be so happie to beare, I will not saie my next shall be better, but I will promise to take more paines to shew more points of musicke, which now I could not do, because my chiefest care was to fit the Note to the Word, till when, I must be as well content with each mans lawfull censure, as I shall be glad of some mens vndeserued favours.</add>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <add>R. J.</add>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>