<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONOURABLE AND VERTV∣OVS GENTLEMAN SIR ROBERT SIDNEY, KNIGHT GOUERNOUR VNDER HER MAIESTIE OF THE TOWNE OF VLUSHING, AND THE CASTLE OF THE Ramekins IN THE LOW COUNTRIES, AND OF the forts of the same appendant, with the garrison there∣in placed as well of horse as foote.</title>
           <author>Jones, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119449_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04613</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14732</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119449</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONOURABLE AND VERTV∣OVS GENTLEMAN SIR ROBERT SIDNEY, KNIGHT GOUERNOUR VNDER HER MAIESTIE OF THE TOWNE OF VLUSHING, AND THE CASTLE OF THE Ramekins IN THE LOW COUNTRIES, AND OF the forts of the same appendant, with the garrison there∣in placed as well of horse as foote.</title>
                 <author>Jones, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first booke of songes or ayres of foure parts with tableture for the lute : So made that all the parts together, or either of them seuerally may be song to the lute, orpherian or viol de gambo. Composed by Robert Iones</title>
                 <author>Jones, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Morley, Thomas, Assignee (with assent, etc.) of.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Short, Peter</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, music, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>
      <add>TO THE HONOURABLE AND VERTV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OVS GENTLEMAN SIR ROBERT SIDNEY, KNIGHT GOUERNOUR VNDER HER MAIESTIE OF THE TOWNE OF VLUSHING, AND THE CASTLE OF THE <hi>Ramekins</hi> IN THE LOW COUNTRIES, AND OF the forts of the same appendant, with the garrison there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in placed as well of horse as foote.</add>
   </head>
   <p>
      <add>
         <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OUR great loue and fauour Honorable Syr, euer manifested to all worthy Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, hath imboldened me to offer vppe at your Lordships Shryne, these the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie labours of my musicall trauels. And though in respect of their weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, they may perhaps seeme vntimely brought forth, and therefore the vnlikeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to prosper; yet doubt I not but if tenderd by you, they shall happelie find gentle cherishing, which may be a meane to make them more stronger, or else miscarrying, to encourage my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours to beget a better: for as no arts wincks at fewer errors than musicke: so none greater enimies to their owne profession then musicians; who whilst in their own singularitie, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne euery mans workes, as some waie faulty, they are the cause, the art is the lesse esteemed, and they themselues reputed as selfe-commenders, and men most fantasticall. Wherefore if this one censuring infirmitie were remoued, these my ayres (free I dare say from grosse errours) would finde euery where more gratious entertainement. But since euen those, who are best seene in this art, cannot vaunt themselues free from such detractours, I the lesse regard it being so well accompanied. Howsoeuer if herein I may gaine your Honors good allowance, I shall thinke I have attained to the better ende of my labours (which with my self, and the best of my seruice) restes euer more at your Lordships imploiment.</add>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <add>Your Lordships deuoted in all dutifull seruice. ROBERT IONES.</add>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>