<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Of his friend M. Iames Wadsworth
and his Booke.</title>
           <author>G., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119406_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14618</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24928</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119406</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Of his friend M. Iames Wadsworth
and his Booke.</title>
                 <author>G., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Further obseruations of the English Spanish pilgrime, concerning Spaine : being a second part of his former booke, and containing these particulars: the description of a famous monastery, or house of the King of Spaines, called the Escuriall, not the like in the Christian world: a briefe relation of certaine dæmonicall stratagems of the Spanish Inquisition exercised on diuers English men of note of late times, and now liuing in England. A relation of the founding of a military order in Rome, to wit, of the immaculate Conception of our Lady, the blessed Virgin. Composed by Iames Wadsworth, Gentleman, lately conuerted into his true mothers bosome, the Church of England, and heretofore pentioner to the King of Spaine</title>
                 <author>Wadsworth, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Allott, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Butter, Nathaniel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 35, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>Of his friend M. Iames Wadsworth
and his Booke.</head>
   <l>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>An's borne to Griefe; without their mothers groane</l>
   <l>None are brought forth; none liue without their owne:</l>
   <l>We need no proofs; but stand amazd to see</l>
   <l>In one mans sorrowes short Epitome▪</l>
   <l>Well his vnhappy trauailes witnesse may,</l>
   <l>That true Religion hath a thorny way,</l>
   <l>He was on Sea by the windes billowes shaken,</l>
   <l>By theeues was rob'd, and by the Pyrate taken;</l>
   <l>He was endungeond by the Iesuite,</l>
   <l>That hopt with him to keepe his faults from light:</l>
   <l>But he was now freed, the Papists naked showes,</l>
   <l>Well fitted to receiue the scourges blowes,</l>
   <l>They with their disciplines haue rac'd his skinne,</l>
   <l>And he's become the Trumpet of their sinne;</l>
   <l>Yet wrongs not charity, since 'tis his care</l>
   <l>To shame the bad, and bid the good beware.</l>
   <l>Now may he sleepe not fearing <hi>Thunders</hi> noise,</l>
   <l>And make post miseries sweeten future ioyes.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>I. G.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>