<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Mason, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119107_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07223</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17620</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119107</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Mason, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A mirrour for merchants : With an exact table to discouer the excessiue taking of vsurie, against the lawes manifested in this treatise of Reasons academy. Set forth by R. Mason of Lincolnes Inne gent</title>
                 <author>Mason, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Browne, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 104 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nderstand mee lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Reader, as well for my purpose, as my paines. In the one, I meane not to confront great Schoole men, but leaue both them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, and their worthy Sciences, to happy successe; and the other I freely bestow on such, as shall bee content to giue the same perusall. As in the whole, I presume there is nothing hurtfull; so in some parts I hope there may be some thing auaileable. Herein one principal Marke I ayme at, is, to discouer the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buse of Vse, or rather the abused vse of Vsurie, so entertained in this Kingdom, that according to <hi>Seneca</hi> his speech, <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit licitum esse, quia publicum est.</hi> In late a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Diuines haue defied it, vnmasked her foule visage, and brought her to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignement
<pb facs="3"/>
and conuiction, for her vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, vnhallowed and vnlawfull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts, the Lawes of this Kingdome, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer este<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>med and adiudged it damnable; and the holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ooke of God, set an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Curse there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n. The Iewes in this Kingdome, caried then markes of sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, from ciuill, and honest compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and the Vsurers generall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> forbidden Christian Buriall; and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sabled▪ to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose by their Wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, of thing so wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gotten. <hi>Sed tempore mutantur,</hi> but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve the mutation of time. In this our Age (when God is most taught, and should be most obeyed) the old Serpent hath not onely perswaded the tasting, but surfetting on this forbidden fruit: The Takers haue lost their estates, and broken their hearts with penurie; and the Lenders filled their bagges, and through cruelty brought their soules to perdition: This viperous poyson hath infected the Court, and the Country, the Laity and Ciuilians, the Church and the Chancell, the Priests and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in so much, that Vsurie is set vp as an vniuersall Trade▪ This is the cause,
<pb facs="3"/>
that Charitie groweth cold louing affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction betweene friends and alies, turned into hatred, hospitalitie decayed, and the seruice of God despised: <hi>Hinc illae la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrymae</hi>; This is the cause, that the almes to the poore are neglected, the dish of neighbourly hospitalitie not prouided, the ordinary and necessary seruants tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned off, and the gate of pitie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion fast locked and sealed vp.</p>
   <p>One thing I must explaine in this place concerning the foure first Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons▪ and the Table herein placed.</p>
   <p>The Sections I haue wri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ten, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse the care power, and prouidence of God, who hath left nothing vnmade needfull for the vse of man, and for the preseruation and increase of all things, hath ordained and appointed a certaine number of things to bee ingendered: a time when, and a place where, they should be produced, and hath limitted each of these to their certaine bounds, <hi>quas vltra, citra{que} nequit consist<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>re rectum</hi>: but the policie of man hath past the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of them all, by inuenting a new kind of production, that money, being
<pb facs="4"/>
taken out of the bowels of the earth her natural place, in a certaine time limitted at their pleasure, should produce the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of money, by deliuering the same vpon Vsurie, and so abuse both number, time, and place, against the Law of God, Nature, and Nations.</p>
   <p>The Table discouereth, that the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall taking of money, being for lesse time then a whole yeere, is within the compasse, both of the prohibiting, and Penall law of this Kingdom, because it exceedeth the rate often for an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth, for one whole yeere: and for the vnderstanding thereof, I haue explay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in what sort the ignorant Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticians haue abused their Art, by mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Divident and Diuisor. Vse ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken according to the rate of the first Table, is subiect to the penall Law: Vse taken according to the second Table, is free from such punishment, though the taking it selfe bee not approued by any Law of God, or man. All which I leaue to thy considerate perusall, and thy selfe to the fauour of God.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Robert Mason.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>