<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO The READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119764_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19170</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5581.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119764</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO The READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The life and death of Hector : One, and the first of the most puissant, valiant, and renowned monarches of the world, called the nyne worthies. Shewing his jnvincible force, together with the marvailous, and most famous acts by him atchieved and done in the great, long, and terrible siege, which the princes of Greece held about the towne of Troy, for the space of tenne yeares. And finally his vnfortunate death after hee had fought a hundred mayne battailes in open field against the Grecians: the which heerein are all at large described. Wherein there were slaine on both sides fourteene hundred, and sixe thowsand, fourscore, and sixe men. VVritten by Iohn Lidgate monke of Berry, and by him dedicated to the high and mighty prince Henrie the fift, King of England</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 131, 126-318, 2 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO The READER.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Muses subiect</l>
      <l>tending to intreate</l>
      <l>Of ancient warres,</l>
      <l>and acts of Chivalrie,</l>
      <l>Whereby renowned Knights</l>
      <l>much honour get:</l>
      <l>And with Eternall parises deifie</l>
      <l>(Their names and fames,) is forced to require</l>
      <l>Thee mighty <hi>Mars</hi> with Art him to inspire.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Whose fiery nature bent to wrath and thrall,</l>
      <l>(As being of complexion hot and drie,</l>
      <l>Melancholicke, and furious withall,</l>
      <l>For in thy bowels chollor hid doth lie)</l>
      <l>Doth rightly cause all Poets sound thy fame,</l>
      <l>And thee the God of warres in stories name.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Sith then thou art of warlike influence,</l>
      <l>And that my stile of battailes must indite:</l>
      <l>Assist me with some Marshall Eloquence,</l>
      <l>That I may frame my hand and pen aright,</l>
      <l>With words of Art and arteficiall phrase,</l>
      <l>Of valiant Knights to sing th'eternall praise.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And if at my request thou dainst to list,</l>
      <l>Or graunt the thing which I of thee do craue,</l>
      <l>Yet for her sake that lovingly thee kist,</l>
      <l>(Blacke <hi>Vulcans</hi> wife) and further fauour gaue;</l>
      <l>Vouchsafe thy ayd my verse so to infuse,</l>
      <l>That I therein fit tearmes and phrase may vse.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Els truth to say, so barren is my wit,</l>
      <l>And void of <hi>Aureat</hi> liquord Eloquence,</l>
      <l>That I confesse my selfe to be vnfit,</l>
      <l>Or able to accomplish my pretence.</l>
      <l>Helpe then God <hi>Mars</hi> for faire <hi>Bellonaes</hi> sake,</l>
      <l>And of my worke vouchsafe protection take.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And thou sweet <hi>Clio</hi> with thy sisters deare,</l>
      <l>Whose chiefe aboad is on <hi>Pernassus</hi> hill</l>
      <l>By <hi>Helicon,</hi> the fountaine faire and cleare,</l>
      <l>Lend me thine ayd, and giue to me some skill,</l>
      <l>That loftie verse by stately tearmes may yeild</l>
      <l>To valiant Knights their honour due in field.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Assist herein likewise, ift be thy will</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Calliope,</hi> (to <hi>Orpheus</hi> mother deare,</l>
      <l>Who insweet musicke so exceld for skill,</l>
      <l>That with the sound of harpe as doth appeare,</l>
      <l>He pleasd the monster <hi>Cerberus</hi> so well,</l>
      <l>That he had leaue to enter into hell,</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>To fetch his loue out of th'infernall lake,</l>
      <l>Where <hi>Pluto</hi> held her for his owne sweet-hart,</l>
      <l>But with the musicke he to them did make,</l>
      <l>He graunted she with him should thence depart.)</l>
      <l>And with the dew of thy sweet liquor wet</l>
      <l>My tongue so harsh, and in right tune it set.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For thou art sayd of Rethoricke to beare</l>
      <l>The onely praise, and patronesse for skill,</l>
      <l>And eke of musicke pleasant to the eare,</l>
      <l>Thou canst direct each instrument at will:</l>
      <l>Deny not then (sweet Muse) thy ayd to mee,</l>
      <l>And I shall rest beholding vnto thee.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Els will the clowds of ignorance enclose</l>
      <l>And round incampe my wits that are so bare,</l>
      <l>And cause the rude (to Poets vtter foes)</l>
      <l>To laugh at me: But such as learned are</l>
      <l>I will intreat what faults soere they find</l>
      <l>To winke thereat, and keepe them in their mind.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And if that in my verses I haue err'd,</l>
      <l>(As no man but may erre what ere he be)</l>
      <l>I must confesse I never yet deseru'd</l>
      <l>To haue the praise for excellent Poetrie.</l>
      <l>For God he knowes when I this worke began,</l>
      <l>I did it not for praise of any man.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <l>But for to please the humor and the hest</l>
      <l>Of my good Lord and Princely Patron,</l>
      <l>Who dained not to me to make request</l>
      <l>To write the same, least that obliuson</l>
      <l>By tract of time, and times swift passing by,</l>
      <l>Such valiant acts should cause obscur'd to lie.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>As also cause his Princely high degree,</l>
      <l>Provokes him study ancient Histories,</l>
      <l>Whereas in Myrrour be may plainely see</l>
      <l>How valiant Knights haue won the masteries</l>
      <l>In battailes fierce, by prowesse and by might,</l>
      <l>To run like race, and proue a worthy knight.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And as they sought to clime to honors seat,</l>
      <l>So doth my Lord seeke therein to excell,</l>
      <l>That as his name, so may his fame be great,</l>
      <l>And thereby likewise Idlenesse expell.</l>
      <l>For so he doth to vertue bend his mind,</l>
      <l>That hard it is his equall now to find.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>To write his Princely vertues, and declare</l>
      <l>His valor, high renowne, and Maiestie,</l>
      <l>His braue exploits, &amp; Marshall acts that are</l>
      <l>Most rare, and worthy his great dignitie,</l>
      <l>My barren head cannot devise by wit</l>
      <l>T'extoll his fame with words &amp; phrases fit.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>This mighty Prince whom I so much cōmend,</l>
      <l>(Yet not so much as well deserues his fame.)</l>
      <l>By royall blood doth li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ally descend</l>
      <l>From <hi>Henrie</hi> king of <hi>Englād</hi> forth by name</l>
      <l>His eldest Son, &amp; heire vnto the Crowne,</l>
      <l>And by his vertues Prince of high renowne.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>(For by the graft the fruit men easly know)</l>
      <l>Excreasing th'honour of his pedigree:</l>
      <l>His name Lord <hi>Henrie</hi> as our stories show,</l>
      <l>And by his title Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> is hee:</l>
      <l>Who with good right, his father being dead,</l>
      <l>Shal weare the Crown of <hi>Brittain</hi> on his head.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>This mighty Prince hath made me vndertake</l>
      <l>To write the siege of <hi>Troy</hi> the ancient towne,</l>
      <l>And of their warres a true discourse to make</l>
      <l>From point to point, as <hi>Guydo</hi> sets it down:</l>
      <l>Who long since wrot the same in latin verse,</l>
      <l>Which in the English now I will rehearse.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The time when first I tooke the same in hand,</l>
      <l>To say the truth was in the fourteenth yeare</l>
      <l>Of famous <hi>Henrie</hi> King of <hi>England</hi>
      </l>
      <l>The Fourth by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ne, my Princes Father deare.</l>
      <l>When <hi>Phoebus</hi> shew'd in altitude to be,</l>
      <l>Fine three times told, and foure and one degree.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>When he did in his Chariot downe descend</l>
      <l>With golden streames into the Ocean strand</l>
      <l>To bath his steeds, and light to others l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nd,</l>
      <l>That farre remote inhabite th'Indian land▪</l>
      <l>Where when our Summer is clean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> past and gon,</l>
      <l>Their spring beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>s but newly to come on.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And when <hi>Lucina</hi> faire with paler light</l>
      <l>Began in cold October to arise.</l>
      <l>(T'enhase the darkenes of the winters night,</l>
      <l>And glistring starres appeard in christall skies:)</l>
      <l>And then was in the signe of <hi>Scorpion,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>And <hi>Hesperus</hi> then westward running downe,</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>His course to hasten gainst tomorrow bright,</l>
      <l>As <hi>Lucifer,</hi> that driues darke clouds away,</l>
      <l>Is sayd to bee the messenger of light,</l>
      <l>And shineth at the dawning of the day:</l>
      <l>When <hi>Phoebus</hi> early shoes his glistring face,</l>
      <l>Ascending from <hi>Proserpins</hi> obscure place,</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Where <hi>Pluto</hi> sits environed about</l>
      <l>With furies of the fowle infernall Lake.</l>
      <l>In this yeare, moneth, and time as it fell out,</l>
      <l>This Historie I first in hand did take.</l>
      <l>And of the <hi>Troyan</hi> wars the truth vntwind,</l>
      <l>As in my ancient Author I it find.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For if no Authors had the truth set downe</l>
      <l>In written Bookes, of things that are forepast,</l>
      <l>Forget fulnes would soone haue trodden downe</l>
      <l>Each worthy act, and cleane extinct at last.</l>
      <l>Which Serpent never ceaseth to assaile</l>
      <l>The world, to cause all truth on earth to faile.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And had no ancient Histories been found,</l>
      <l>But all things vnto memorie were left;</l>
      <l>Truth surely then would soone be layd in ground,</l>
      <l>And men of knowledge vtterly bereft.</l>
      <l>But God intending Sathan to prevent,</l>
      <l>That hath foreseene, and writers alwaies sent</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>From age to age, still to renew the same,</l>
      <l>That truth might alwaies spring and come to light,</l>
      <l>And thereby win an everlasting name,</l>
      <l>Against the which sowle envy still doth fight.</l>
      <l>But famous Clarkes not ceasing truth to show,</l>
      <l>By writing leaue the same to vs to know.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Els time with syth, would soone cut downe the grasse,</l>
      <l>And re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ening death extirpe the root and all,</l>
      <l>And nothing whatsoere on earth did passe</l>
      <l>Should haue record, the same to mind to call.</l>
      <l>Nor honor due to valiant Knights be read,</l>
      <l>But it with them should rest, and lie as dead.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <l>And so not onely name, but fame would die,</l>
      <l>And wholy be defaced out of mind.</l>
      <l>But Histories explain the same to th'eie,</l>
      <l>As daylie by experience we may find.</l>
      <l>Nere ceasing spight of envy to vnfold</l>
      <l>The truth of all which may not be controld.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Therein we see of high and low estate,</l>
      <l>The life and acts as it were on a stage,</l>
      <l>For writers that are wise in heart do hate</l>
      <l>To speake vntruth, or flatter any age.</l>
      <l>For tyrauts being dead they will not feare</l>
      <l>To write and shew their follies as they were.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And t'yeild each man as he shall well deserue</l>
      <l>Be't good or bad, and therefore it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> best,</l>
      <l>For every one that credit will preserue,</l>
      <l>In life to vertue cleaue, and vice detest:</l>
      <l>For after death know this and marke it well,</l>
      <l>Clarkes will not spare the truth of them to tell.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For such vnpartiall dealing in their daies,</l>
      <l>Great Princes in them tooke no small delight</l>
      <l>For truely blasing forth their laud &amp; praise,</l>
      <l>Their high renown, their power &amp; their might</l>
      <l>Their knightly acts, their victories, &amp; fame,</l>
      <l>Eternally with glory of their name.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For they still sought to shun the sisters three,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Fraud, Negligence,</hi> and <hi>Sloth,</hi> that none might doubt</l>
      <l>Ought was forgot, or more p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t in to bee,</l>
      <l>Then truth requird, and as the truth fell out.</l>
      <l>Els worthy acts were wholy done in vaine,</l>
      <l>And those that honour sought had lost their paine.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And time by length of yeares and ages past,</l>
      <l>Would haue defaced name and honor cleane</l>
      <l>Of Conquerors, (for what can ever last)</l>
      <l>Vnlesse record thereof were to be seene:</l>
      <l>Which Clarkes (for which they merit and deserue</l>
      <l>Continuall praise,) haue sought still to preserue.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For Histories and Bookes are sayd to bee</l>
      <l>The keyes of learning, memory, and skill,</l>
      <l>In them, and by them all men plainely see,</l>
      <l>What, hath forepast, and what is good, or ill:</l>
      <l>Witnesse the fall of <hi>Thebes</hi> the ancient Towne,</l>
      <l>In <hi>Stacies</hi> Booke for truth at large set downe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Where you may read and see how <hi>Polinece</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Was nere content with <hi>Etocles</hi> a day,</l>
      <l>Nor would like louing Brother liue in peace,</l>
      <l>Till <hi>Thebes</hi> Towne was brought vnto decay.</l>
      <l>And h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>w <hi>Tedeus</hi> through that mortall ctrife,</l>
      <l>And by dissention was bereft of life▪</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>How <hi>Oedipus</hi> with sorrow, griefe, and woe,</l>
      <l>Did loose his eies so bitterly he wept,</l>
      <l>And how the Smo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>kes devided were i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> two,</l>
      <l>Of fiers made, when funerall feasts was kept,</l>
      <l>Which fier brothers hatred did engender,</l>
      <l>And death to both for iust reward did render.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Mine author <hi>Guydo</hi> in like sort doth show</l>
      <l>(As by his Booke most plainely it appeares)</l>
      <l>Of all the <hi>Troian</hi> Princes overthrow,</l>
      <l>While <hi>Greeks</hi> besieg'd the towne so many yeares:</l>
      <l>In very truth, and though tis long since past,</l>
      <l>No time, nor age, the storie hath defast.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For maugre them, you may it still behold</l>
      <l>In Bookes set downe most plainely to mens eies,</l>
      <l>For truth by lying will not be controld,</l>
      <l>Though enviously some seeke it to disguise:</l>
      <l>Transforming all the substance of the matter</l>
      <l>By fayned tales, dissembling to flatter</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>As <hi>Homer</hi> did, who truth would seeme to show,</l>
      <l>Yet covertly did seeke the same to hide,</l>
      <l>And by vntruth which he full well did know,</l>
      <l>With Artificiall words doth truth deride:</l>
      <l>Who seeming <hi>Greecians</hi> honour to defend,</l>
      <l>Doth faine the Gods from heaven to descend</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>In shape of men, and openly were knowne</l>
      <l>To helpe the <hi>Greeks</hi> against the <hi>Troians</hi> fight,</l>
      <l>And many such vntruths by him are showne</l>
      <l>In sugred words, and phrases for delight:</l>
      <l>Pretending so his malice for to hide,</l>
      <l>For falsehood seekes in darkenes to abide.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The cause why he the <hi>Greeks</hi> so smothly prais'd,</l>
      <l>Was for that he vnto them was allide,</l>
      <l>And therefore sought their glory to haue rais'd.</l>
      <l>But such as loue the truth cannot abide</l>
      <l>Gainst conscience for to praise or discommend,</l>
      <l>Where no desert their action may defind.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But <hi>Cupid</hi> (as the Poets faine) is blind,</l>
      <l>And giues his doome more after lust, then law:</l>
      <l>So Sicophants as we by proofe doe find</l>
      <l>Commend and praise the men they never saw,</l>
      <l>By false report extolling them to skie,</l>
      <l>Of whom in heart they know full well they lie:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Whereby such men as never merit fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e</l>
      <l>But iust disgrace, are highly magnified:</l>
      <l>And they contrary that deserue good name,</l>
      <l>Are either not remembred or beli'd:</l>
      <l>For favor now doth beare so great a s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ay,</l>
      <l>That true desert is driven cleane away.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <l>
         <hi>Ovidius Naso</hi> likewise hath devis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </l>
      <l>A Booke in verse, of <hi>Troian</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>s to show,</l>
      <l>Part true, part false, but in such sort disguisd,</l>
      <l>That who so reads it, can by no meanes know</l>
      <l>Which way to sound the deapth of his intent,</l>
      <l>His phraise therein's so mis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ically bent.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Like story also <hi>Virgill</hi> doth declare,</l>
      <l>When of <hi>Aeneas</hi> tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>les he doth write,</l>
      <l>Where truth to tell in part he doth not spare,</l>
      <l>Although s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap> time he seemth to delight</l>
      <l>In <hi>Homers</hi> course, with Rethoricke to glose,</l>
      <l>And truth with falsehood often to compose.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>Dares</hi> an ancient Author first was found,</l>
      <l>And <hi>Ditus</hi> eke of <hi>Troian</hi> warres to write,</l>
      <l>Who both set down the truth &amp; perfect groūd,</l>
      <l>As being there, and did behold the fight.</l>
      <l>And thogh their books in seuerall language be,</l>
      <l>Yet they are knowen in all things to agree.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The Books in time to <hi>Athens</hi> being brought,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Salustius</hi> cousen, one <hi>Cornelius,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>By diligent enquirie out them sought;</l>
      <l>And being of a mind industrious,</l>
      <l>Translated them with great &amp; earnest care</l>
      <l>In each respect, as th' Authors doth declare.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>His only fault was, that he did not write</l>
      <l>The story full at large as he it found,</l>
      <l>But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ure he did in breuity delight;</l>
      <l>Els would he not haue spar'd to shew the groūd</l>
      <l>And first beginning of that mortall strife,</l>
      <l>Which cost so many thousand men their life.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And how the <hi>Greeks</hi> came both by sea &amp; lād</l>
      <l>The nūber of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>en, and of their ships,</l>
      <l>The manner how they first did take in hand</l>
      <l>To plant their siege, (all this he ouerskips.)</l>
      <l>How envy was the root and cause of all</l>
      <l>The mischiefe that on <hi>Troy</hi> at last did fall.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>How many Kings and Princes thither went</l>
      <l>In warlike wise to win them high renowne,</l>
      <l>How they agreed all with one conscent</l>
      <l>To see the full sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap> of the Towne:</l>
      <l>What armes they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>are, what men they did retaine,</l>
      <l>Who in the siege did longest there remaine.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>How one the other Knightly did assaile,</l>
      <l>How many valiant Princes lost their life:</l>
      <l>How of t they met in field to giue battaile:</l>
      <l>How hatred still increast and bred new strife:</l>
      <l>Nor of their deaths <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>iteth not the yeare:</l>
      <l>Thus much he leaueth out as doth appeare.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Which lately causd an Author to arise,</l>
      <l>Whose truth in writing is not to be bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>'d,</l>
      <l>That tooke in hand this st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> such wise,</l>
      <l>As that of <hi>Ditus</hi> and of <hi>Dares</hi> nam'd:</l>
      <l>He hath not sought one sentence to neglect,</l>
      <l>Nor yet in ought the meaning to reiect.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>This Clarkethat wrote so true, so iust, so well,</l>
      <l>Was <hi>Guydo</hi> of <hi>Columpna</hi> by his name,</l>
      <l>Who in sweet Rethoricke did so much excell,</l>
      <l>That he enricht his storie with the same:</l>
      <l>So Eloquently hath he set it downe,</l>
      <l>That he deserueth praise and high renowne.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For which in heart and voice I will not stay,</l>
      <l>To giue him praise and commendation due,</l>
      <l>And with applause in truth, and rightly say,</l>
      <l>He was the flower most certainely and true,</l>
      <l>Of all that sought this storie to compile,</l>
      <l>For wit, and soveraignty of stile.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Whose treces as I can I will obserue,</l>
      <l>If God vouchsafe me time and grace to do't,</l>
      <l>And graunt my labour may of him deserue</l>
      <l>The Princely praise that first provokt me to't:</l>
      <l>Beseeching all that see't, with heart &amp; mind</l>
      <l>Not spare to speake, if any fault they find.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And with good will I shall amend the same,</l>
      <l>(For many eies may see much more then one.)</l>
      <l>Correct then freely where you find the blame,</l>
      <l>But find not fault whereas deserueth none.</l>
      <l>And so in hope I shall your favours win,</l>
      <l>With your support this storie ile begin.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>