<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE ARGVMENTES of the twelue bookes of Aeneidos, expressed in twelue verses.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1573</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119243_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14480</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24801</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119243</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE ARGVMENTES of the twelue bookes of Aeneidos, expressed in twelue verses.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The whole .xii. bookes of the Æneidos of Virgill. Whereof the first .ix. and part of the tenth, were conuerted into English meeter by Thomas Phaër Esquire, and the residue supplied, and the whole worke together newly set forth, by Thomas Twyne Gentleman. There is added moreouer to this edition, Virgils life out of Donatus, and the argument before euery booke. There is added moreouer to this edition, Virgils life out of Donatus, and the argument before euery booke</title>
                 <author>Virgil</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1573</date>
                 <publisher>How (Howe, Haw), William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Veale (Vele), Abraham</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>316 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="verse_summary">
   <head>THE ARGVMENTES of the twelue bookes of Aeneidos, expressed in twelue verses.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>Aeneas,</hi> in the first, to <hi>Liby</hi> land arriueth well.</l>
      <l>The fall of <hi>Troy,</hi> and wofull dole, the second booke doth tell.</l>
      <l>The thyrd of wandringes speakes, and father dead, and layd full low.</l>
      <l>In fourth Queene <hi>Dido</hi> burnes, and flames of raginge loue doth show.</l>
      <l>The fift declareth plaies, and how the fleet with fier was cought.</l>
      <l>The sixt doth speake of ghosts, and how deep
<hi>Plutoes</hi> reygne was sought.</l>
      <l>The seuenth booke, <hi>A eneas</hi> bringes vnto his fatal land.</l>
      <l>The eight-prepareth war, and power how foes for to witstand.</l>
      <l>The ninth of battels telles, and yet the captaine is a waye.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Aeneas</hi> greeuous wrath <hi>Mezentius,</hi> in the tenth, doth slaye.</l>
      <l>The eleuenth in vnequall fight <hi>Camilla</hi> castes to ground.</l>
      <l>The twelfth with heauenly weapons gyues to <hi>Turnus</hi> mortall wound.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>