<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY HONOV∣RABLE FRIEND, Sir EDWARD DIMMOCK Knight, the most worthy and generous Champion vnto the Sacred Maiestie of Great BRITAINE, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>T., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119026_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14277</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24593</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119026</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY HONOV∣RABLE FRIEND, Sir EDWARD DIMMOCK Knight, the most worthy and generous Champion vnto the Sacred Maiestie of Great BRITAINE, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>T., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The blazon of iealousie· : A subiect not written of by any heretofore· First written in Italian, by that learned gentleman Benedetto Varchi, sometimes Lord Chauncelor vnto the Signorie of Venice: and translated into English, with speciall notes vpon the same; by R.T. Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Varchi, Benedetto</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Busby, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 87, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO MY HONOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE FRIEND, Sir EDWARD DIMMOCK Knight, the most worthy and generous Champion vnto the Sacred Maiestie of Great BRITAINE, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, I present vnto your iudicious view, the Plague of Men, and the auncient Disease of Women: a Subiect knowne, but too-too well, to many, and yet not written of by any heretofore, as farre as I can finde. <hi>Tasso</hi> toucheth it (here and there) in his Workes: and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riosto</hi> glanceth at it (a little) in his ORLANDO FV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIOSO; onely this graue Author BENEDETTO VARCHI, hath discoursed of it at large. The draught is both Philosophicall and pleasant; If it like you I esteeme the lesse what Others distaste therein. The auncient Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes vsed to set forth the portratures of their best Friends in the formost front of their Pallaces; and so I hope you will vouchsafe that I may blaze your name, in the frontispice of my Booke. Neyther doubt I but that
<pb facs="3"/>
you will as kindly entertayne it, as it is heartily recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended vnto you, considering my meaning, and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Martials,</hi> is all one in this point:
<q>
         <lg>
            <l>Quod non argentum, quod non tibi misimus aurum,</l>
            <l>Hoc faecimus causa (Stella diserte) tua</l>
            <l>Quisquis magra dedit, voluit sibi magna remitti,</l>
            <l>Fictilibus nostris exoner atus eris.</l>
         </lg>
         <lg>
            <l>That we no Gold nor Siluer doe thee send,</l>
            <l>Twas for thy sake (kinde <hi>Stella)</hi> courteous Friend.</l>
            <l>Who great things giue, doe looke for great againe,</l>
            <l>Our trifting toyes shall ease thee of that paine.</l>
         </lg>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>This Worke then being but a trifle, my labour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in cannot be much, which, neuerthelesse, if it be any, is onely due to your true, courteous, and bountifull Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; to which not my selfe alone, but diuers other Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, as well English as Strangers, were beholding for the kinde Entertainment you gaue vs at our being in Italy together. Accept then, this small Mite in part of a greater amends. It is some comfort to an honest minde, to render what (to his power) he can, although not what he should; and better to repay a small Interest, then keepe backe Principall and All, as many Bancke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts (of good Manners) vse now a dayes to doe. And thus with my best wishes for the good of your Worthy selfe, and of your vertuous Lady, the true Paralell of all Courtly Perfection, I end,</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From my Lodging in</hi> Holborne, <date>
            <hi>this</hi> 7. <hi>of</hi> Nouember, 1614.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>
         <hi>Ingeniously deuoted to your Worship,</hi> R. T.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>