<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Courteous Reader.</title>
           <author>Chibald, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119281_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18602</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5130</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119281</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Courteous Reader.</title>
                 <author>Chibald, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An apology for the treatise, called A triall of faith. Concerning the precedency of repentance for sinne, before faith in Christ for pardon</title>
                 <author>Chibald, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Samuel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 177, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Courteous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N a Defence of one point of my Triall of faith opposed by some, I tooke occasion to write a briefe explication of a second contradicted by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
   <p>In the conclusion of that explication, I prayed the Reader to be content, that of the later point, <hi>as yet I sayd no more, because as yet I saw no more.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>By Gods prouidence I haue seene more since that time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>th the spectacles of some which oppose that Doctrine.</p>
   <p>It remaines (because those words im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied a promise) that now I write more of that matter because I vnderstand more, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> I say more because I see more.</p>
   <p>But first when I say that <hi>now I see more,</hi> my meaning is not, that I am s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered in my iudgement, by somewhat la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>y seene &amp; that therfore now I vnderstanding question otherwise then I did at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> but that now I know more of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="3"/> that oppose it, then I did before, and know better how to confirme mine owne opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
   <p>That this may appeare I pray the Christian Reader to remember the state of the question set downe in my Treatise in these wordes, <hi>Repentance is begunne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore faith in Christ,</hi> and therein to consider two things; first of whom I speake in this question, secondly of what.</p>
   <p>They of whom I speake, are the Elect onely, who onely are <hi>ordained by God to eternall life,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>cts 23.48.</note> and who for that purpose are appointed also to all the meanes effectually conducing thereunto, from the beginning to the end, in all the parts and degrees of the same. For because this faith is onely wrought in them, therefore is it called the faith <hi>of the elect;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Tit. 1.1.</note> and because these only are in the euent saued by it, therefore do <hi>they receiue the end of their faith,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Peter 1.9.</note>
      <hi>which is the saluation of their soules.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>That whereof I speake is contained in the wordes of the Question before recited. Wherein I pray further that two things may be considered. First, the Antecedent, subiect matter of the question, or the thing that is spoken of, in this word <hi>Repentance.</hi> Secondly, the consequent, predicat or say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that is affirmed of this Repentance, in
<pb facs="3"/> the rest of the words, <hi>is begunne before faith in Christ,</hi> for these termes must be rightly vnderstood.</p>
   <p>First, the subiect matter or thing spoken in that Question, is <hi>Repentance,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Repentance.</note> and by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance I meane not the practicall repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the conuersation or practise of the purpose of amendment of life, in a constant, conscionable and cheerefull course of new obedience, but onely the repentance of the heart: and by the repentance of the heart I do not vnderstand <hi>newnesse of heart or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitude</hi> of Spirit, or mortification,<note place="margin">Psalme 51.10</note> and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uification, or habituall conuersion to God with the whole soule in all the powers and faculties of it, ioyned with a good conscience which all are fruites and effects of faith in nature following it: But by <hi>Repentance</hi> I meane onely hearty sorrow for past sinnes already committed, and purpose first not to commit the very same sinnes, if they were not already done, but were againe to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and then consequently a purpose not to commit the like sinnes in kinde for time to come, namely a purpose in truth without hypocrisy and dissimulation.</p>
   <p>Repentance from dead workes being a qualification to fit men for beleefe in Christ, beleeuing in Christ a qualification to fit them to receiue benefit by the promise
<pb facs="4"/> of the Gospell vnto iustification, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of life or new obedience being a qualification to fit them to the further assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their iustification and of eternall life.</p>
   <p>Secondly, in the predicate or saying that is affirmed of this repentance three things are to be obserued. <hi>1.</hi> What is meant by <hi>being begunne. 2.</hi> By <hi>Before. 3.</hi> By <hi>Faith in Christ.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">1 Is begunne.</note>First by <hi>being begunne,</hi> I doe not meane a being of repentance in the heart suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to saluation: but onely a beginning of it in all the preparations thereunto, as also a beginning of the habit it selfe, so farre as concernes sorrow and purpose, namely a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof in some measure without dissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation; and (if it may be proued suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently) that amendment of life is a part of repentance, then I say, repentance is begun in some part, <hi>viz.</hi> in sorrow and purpose touching past sinnes before faith in Christ, and finished in another, <hi>viz.</hi> amendment of life after faith.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">2 Before.</note>Secondly, by <hi>(Before)</hi> I doe not meane a precedency some space of time: but in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture onely and in the order of causes.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, by <hi>faith in Christ</hi> I doe not meane a beleefe of the word and Gospell,<note place="margin">Faith in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>st.</note> for this of necessity must goe before repentance,
<pb facs="4"/> in as much as it is the meanes to driue and to draw thereunto:<note place="margin">Acts 2.32. Math. 11.68. Hebr. 11.6.</note> but I vnderstand there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a resting and relying vpon Christ with our whole hearts, or a trusting to and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting confidence in the merits of the death and righteousnesse of Iesus Christ for and vnto saluation.</p>
   <p>In the second place in that <hi>now I say more,</hi> It is not because (I thinke) I haue not sayd enough all ready to the point it selfe for the prouing of it: but because I haue not sayd enough to some for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swading of them. Nor yet because I haue not sufficiently answered the obiections which I knew: but because I knew them not all then, to the end I might haue answered them at the first: for now I stoppe three or foure gapps with one bush, and answere the Exceptions of more then one man.</p>
   <p>As in these regards, this further la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour by way of Apology hath beene vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken not without some cause: so in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther respects it ought to be well construed, accepted and vsed, namely because (the Lord knows) my purpose herein is not, to maintain my credit, but the cause of God and the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nor to striue for Triumph and Victory, but for Truth and verity: muchlesse wilfully to oppose any that hold the contrary. Least of
<pb facs="5"/> all to detract from <hi>pretious faith,</hi> or our <hi>blessed</hi> Sauiour in any the least measure or meaning.<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Pet. 1.1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uke 1 42. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>om. 9.5.</note>
   </p>
   <p>Of my sincerity herein the Christian Reader may the rather be perswaded by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering these particulars.</p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1.</hi> I labour not to darken my opposite with disgrace, (except it bee by clouding their names with silence) but onely to cleare the point in question with a larger explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and confirmation.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2.</hi> I seeke not to shift of the force of an argument by evasions: but answer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto with direct solutions, to my best vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3.</hi> I study not to iustifie any thing that cannot be defended with truth and plainnes: for I freely confesse the weakenesse of my disputation where such weakenesse is dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <hi>4.</hi> I spend not my spirit to requite in kinde, many vnkinde and some insolent termes in their Exceptions: but onely trie my strength to vntie the knots of their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections, (I meane) not euery idle cavill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout words, or matter impertinent to the clearing of the maine question, but to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere such reasons onely as make directest and strongest opposition to my Doctrine.</p>
   <p>The maine purpose being good, and the
<pb facs="5"/> meane proceeding faire, it remaines, that I humbly pray the Reader to peruse my Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy with patience and without preiudice to compare reason with reason, with prudence and without partiality, and to iudge of truth by reason, rather then by humaine autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
   <p>This if they shall doe (it is reasonable to request it, it is equall to grant it) It may come to passe (through Gods blessing) that hotte and confident opposers may bee cooled and conuinced, that moderate and vnresol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Christians may be perswaded and satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. That errour may be discerned confuted and auoided, and the truth more cleared and confirmed: which God the Father grant for his Sonne Iesus sake, by the grace and wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Holy Spirit, to his owne glory and his Churches good, <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours in the seruice of your Faith,</hi> William Chibald.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>