<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THOSE WOR∣THY HERO'S OF OVR Age, whose noble Breasts are wet and watred with the deaw of Helicon, N. W. wisheth ever-flourishing Laurels.</title>
           <author>W., N.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119865_Bo1_11</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15139</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25437</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119865</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THOSE WOR∣THY HERO'S OF OVR Age, whose noble Breasts are wet and watred with the deaw of Helicon, N. W. wisheth ever-flourishing Laurels.</title>
                 <author>W., N.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The most pleasante historie, of Albino and Bellama : A poeme. To which is annexed the vindication of poesie. by N.W</title>
                 <author>Whiting, Nathaneel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Fussell, Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 143, 25 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_poets">
   <pb facs="84"/>
   <pb facs="84"/>
   <head>TO THOSE WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THY HERO'S OF OVR Age, whose noble Breasts are wet and watred with the deaw of Helicon, <hi>N. W.</hi> wisheth ever-<hi>flourishing Laurels.</hi>
   </head>
   <lg>
      <l>YOu noble Laureats, whose able Quills</l>
      <l>In framing Odes, do drean the sacredrills</l>
      <l>Of <hi>Aganippe</hi> dry, within whose brests</l>
      <l>The Syre of <hi>Aesculapius</hi> safely rests;</l>
      <l>And all the Muses Temple, daigne your rayes</l>
      <l>To cheare the measures of an infant Bayes,</l>
      <l>Spread forth the Banners of your worths to sheild</l>
      <l>His yonger Muse, unable yet to weild</l>
      <l>Armes, 'gainst the Monsters of this Critick age,</l>
      <l>Envie, detraction, and Saturnine rage.</l>
      <l>I to my selfe assume not double worth,</l>
      <l>Or that my teeming phansie can bring forth</l>
      <l>Words to make wonder stand amaz'd, doe trye</l>
      <l>To vindicate the breath of Poesie.</l>
      <l>In such a thought I'me silent, but because</l>
      <l>I've heard invectives belched from the jawes</l>
      <pb facs="85"/>
      <l>Of <hi>Nil-scientes,</hi> whose audacious bragges</l>
      <l>Have rays'd a thunder like a shoale of dagges</l>
      <l>T'affright endevours:</l>
      <l>In writing which, if my weake studies hit</l>
      <l>Of any fansie speaking worth or wit,</l>
      <l>If I have snatched any fainting Muse</l>
      <l>From the black jawes of envie and abuse,</l>
      <l>Shooting a soule into her, and new breath,</l>
      <l>Maugre those tongues that doomed her to death.</l>
      <l>Eccho forth thankes unto coy <hi>Daphnes</hi> lover</l>
      <l>(About whose Fane the sacred Nine doe hover)</l>
      <l>Whose kindnesse smild on my uncrusht designes,</l>
      <l>And lockt a Muse in my unworthy lines</l>
      <l>Able to blunt the darts of envie, pare</l>
      <l>The sharpest hoofed Satyr, and with ayre</l>
      <l>Shrill as the voyce of thunder, chide those gaules,</l>
      <l>That belch forth scandals and invective bawles:</l>
      <l>Nay, he, befriending me above my merit,</l>
      <l>Vnseen of any, heav'd my winged spirit</l>
      <l>T'a higher court than the Star-chamber is,</l>
      <l>Where soules may surfet with immortall blisse.</l>
      <l>And taught my phansie in those quiet slumbers,</l>
      <l>What, waking, I have folded up in numbers,</l>
      <l>To tell the brood of Critickes, that there are</l>
      <l>Some few, or if not some, yet one, that dare</l>
      <l>(Backed by your thrice-sacred worths) expose</l>
      <l>These lines and letters to the ken of prose.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>The humble admirer of your Nuses</hi> N. W.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>