<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Summary Of Part Two (Forthcoming)]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119302_Ba1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16892</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3788</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119302</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Summary Of Part Two (Forthcoming)]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fourth part of the true watch : containing prayers and teares for the churches. Or A helpe to hold up the hearts and hands of the poorest servants of God, untill our Lord Iesus Christ shall have rescued his glorie, kingdome, and people in all the world, and fully prepared the way to his most glorious appearing</title>
                 <author>Brinsley, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, Isaac</publisher>
                    <distributor>Pavier, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>108, 273, 278-420, 38 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary_of_part_two__forthcoming">
   <pb facs="278"/>
   <p>The Second Part, to suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede in the next place; containeth Prayers like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise for all the Churches and people of God, scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered thorough the whole world: that wee may all seeke to pacifie the Lord, by giving him his glorie, in returning and submit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our selves wholly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Covenant; and that we may obtaine by our instant prayers, that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e may ioyntly honour him; so walking and beleeving as his heavenly wisedome hath appoynted. For this is a thing notoriously ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served and acknowledged by all, who rightly under stand the state of forraigne parts; that as it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> amongst
<pb facs="278"/>
us▪ for the most part; so it hath beene very generally amongst them in all the Churches, that they have had onely a bare forme of godlinesse, a naked out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profession of the Gospell in word, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most without any power or life thereof, more then for a fashion. And that this hath not onely thus fleshed our Adversaries to the destruction of the whole Church (as dooing a thing meritorious unto God heerein▪ for that they conceyve us to bee but a company of Heretiques in professi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>n, very Atheistes in our lives) but also pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked our blessed God, so farre aire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>die to leave so
<pb facs="279"/>
many of the Churches in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their hands, and thus to threaten all the rest, even us our selves, seeing his kingdome is not in word, but in power. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, so many of us as have made such a carnall profession, have not onely shewed foorth a manifest contempt of his heavenly Maiesty, and his holy Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; but put a Scepter of Reede into the hand of our Lord Iesus Christ; smitten him uppon the face, and trampled his Crowne under our feete, and indeede made his and our enemies to blaspheme and thus farre to prevayle and insult over us.</p>
   <p>Whereupon, hee hath iustly begunne, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="279"/>
us all, to take his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from us, to give it to another people, which would bring foorth the fruite of it; and to leave us all to bee trampled un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foote by these our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemyes, untill we know by wanting, the blessinges which wee have formerly inioyed, and the difference betweene his service, and the slaverie of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes.</p>
   <p>As these prayers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, according to our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours direction, may serve to prepare the way for all other our prayers, and our right accesse unto his glorious Maiestie, to come with confident assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and do proceed un
<pb facs="280"/>
to the first petition of the Lords Prayer, and the end of the first Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that we may all give him his due glory, perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming unto him his inward worshippe, which is the fountaine of all true obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; so those that are to follow in the second part (the Lord assisting) are to go according to the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the same heavenly rule of our Saviour; tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the whole Covenant made with our God, both for all his Law and Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, beginning at the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Commandement, &amp; so thorow the Law, and thorow all the Articles of faith, with the doctrine of the Sacraments, and other
<pb facs="280"/>
things belonging thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. That thus all, even the poorest servants of God, may have matter enough of prayer to be exercised in continually, and all to this very end for appeasing the Lordes wrath, and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciling him to all his Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Children againe. First, every one for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, and his owne parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, to be assured of his own reconciliation to the Lord by the blood of his Son, when he can so pray and obey in truth. And se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that every one ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving attained to this assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and favour with the Lord, may bee exercised dayly, as those worthy ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God, <hi>Nehemiah,</hi>
      <pb facs="281"/>
      <hi>Ezra,</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing their owne sinnes, and the sinnes of all the Churches and people of the Lord, and in so crying unto him, and importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him▪ untill wee shall see the ful deliverance and restoring of the Churches in Bohemia, Palatinate, &amp; the rest: yea the enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them, by the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering in of the Iew, and the remainder of his Israel from the uttermost partes of the earth, with the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter razing of Babel: and untill we obtaine whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver else the Lord hath ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther promised to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or denounced against his enemies. And finally, untill we shall everie one
<pb facs="281"/>
see the heavenly Ierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, and the eternall glory of his Sion. The third &amp; last part, is (God willing) to containe principally Prayers for this our sinfull Nation, that we may first all see, and lively appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the danger wherein wee stand every moment, of drinking at the Lords hand, after those other Churches, which have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted so deepely of the cup of his displeasure, seeing our sinnes are no lesse, but farre greater then theyrs; and that specially sith their ensample hath no more prevayled with us. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that we may all in time wisely understand the meanes which in his wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="282"/>
and mercie hee hath yet left unto us to prevent the execution ready to come forth against us. And thirdly, that we may euery one use all the meanes thereto, each according to our place and calling, by turning unfeignedly to the Covenant of our God, not onely to prevent, and for ever to turne away all the calamities deuised against us by our deadly &amp; bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy enemyes; but also so to reconcile the Lord unto us, that insteede of those miseries which our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies so long for, to rush upon us, hee may make us the happiest and blessedst Nation that ever was, in this last Age of the world▪
<pb facs="282"/>
so to remaine to his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall glory, the comfort &amp; example of all the other Churches for evermore.</p>
   <p>To these are also to bee added some speciall Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for our particular purposes and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>