<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE RICHARD, EARLE OF CARBERY.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119035_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14290</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24606</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119035</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE RICHARD, EARLE OF CARBERY.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Church militant : historically continued from the yeare of our Saviours Incarnation 33. untill this present, 1640. By William Vaughan, Knight</title>
                 <author>Vaughan, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Paine (Payne), Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Blunden, Humphrey</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 345, that is 355, 3 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE <hi>RICHARD,</hi> EARLE OF CARBERY.</head>
   <argument>
      <head>The Argument.</head>
      <l>The <hi>Authour</hi> here my <hi>Noble Lord</hi> acquaints</l>
      <l>What <hi>Paths</hi> they tread who lead the lives of <hi>Saints,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>What <hi>Comforts</hi> he shall finde, what good successe,</l>
      <l>While he walks in the <hi>New-mans</hi> Diocesse.</l>
   </argument>
   <lg>
      <l>I <hi>Sound not forth</hi> Old Souldours <hi>turn'd to Swine</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>By</hi> Harlots <hi>Charmes, by fulsome Cheere or Wine;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>But the</hi> New-borne <hi>(a Theame to Worldlings strange)</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> sing the</hi> Minds <hi>more then the</hi> Bodies <hi>Change;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="3"/>
         <hi>I sing the</hi> Churches Change, Eclipse, Decrease,</l>
      <l>Her East, and West, with her Full Moones Encrease.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Such</hi> Newes <hi>I blaze, which no good</hi> Protestant</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Shall justly taxe for</hi> Sparkes <hi>exorbitant,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Like to those</hi> Brats <hi>expos'd to</hi> Brambles Flame</l>
      <l>
         <hi>By</hi> Midwives <hi>Doome to hide the</hi> Parents <hi>shame,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Or those, for which of late our</hi> Pauls Church-yard</l>
      <l>
         <hi>And</hi> Smith-field <hi>in the Spoiles with</hi> Vulcan <hi>shar'd.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Truth <hi>smites the</hi> Chast: <hi>while</hi> Wantons <hi>long to heare</hi>
      </l>
      <l>False Tales, <hi>at which they Nod, or fondly Ieere,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Fooling away the Time, their pretious Time,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Lent them for better use in</hi> Prose <hi>or</hi> Rime,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>To win some</hi> Strayes <hi>by meanes of</hi> Vertuous Books,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Not</hi> Soules <hi>to tempt with</hi> Fornications <hi>Hookes.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>There, with much Gall</hi> Gulls <hi>one another flout:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Hoere for Mistakes, the Lie, or Toyes they pout,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Forgetting</hi> Satans <hi>Ambush for Good Wits,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Tongues trip, Pens blur, None free from</hi> Passions Fits,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="3"/>
         <hi>And yet for</hi> Words <hi>and</hi> Names, <hi>Externall things,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>They persecute their</hi> Christian Mates <hi>with stings,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ill tir'd at last with Conscience-griping Cares,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Both Parties howle within the</hi> Divels <hi>Snares.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Others by</hi> Lines <hi>and</hi> Cubes <hi>aspire to know</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>The</hi> Higher Orbes, <hi>or in the</hi> Globe <hi>below</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>They levell</hi> Spires, <hi>the</hi> Climates, <hi>or the</hi> Lawes,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>nto whose Depth they pry no more then</hi> Dawes;</l>
      <l>
         <hi>And yet to gaine applause, or</hi> Golden Fees,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>They hope for</hi> Swans <hi>to chop their gaggling</hi> Geese.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Some Court</hi> Faire Dames <hi>with</hi> Fancies Madrigalls,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Chaulking the way to</hi> Paphian Lupercalls,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Which they frequent with uncontrouled Lust</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Till Honour, Wealth, and Health lye in the Dust.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Sometimes Pelagian-wise they ruminate</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>On</hi> Mans Free-will, <hi>and the</hi> Predestinate,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Till they from</hi> Grace <hi>quite excommunicate</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Doe pitch on</hi> Hell, <hi>and on the</hi> Reprobate.</l>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <l>
         <pb facs="5"/>
         <hi>Now, of</hi> long-handed Kings <hi>the mounted state,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Anon, their slips or Fall they personate</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>With</hi> Satyres <hi>sting, untill themselves are stung;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Or else they sooth</hi> Great men <hi>with glozing Tongue,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Untill they feele worse Racks with Conscience sear'd,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Then</hi> Poets <hi>faign'd for stroaking of</hi> Joves Beard.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Some other whiles they dare more Curious peepe</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Into the Concaves of th' Infernall Deepe,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Of</hi> Limboes Vault, <hi>or</hi> Purgatories <hi>Paine</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Redeem'd for</hi> Gold <hi>the</hi> long-white Robe <hi>to staine.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>With such</hi> Bald Stuffe <hi>most</hi> Writers <hi>doe oppresse,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>In hope to purchase Fame, the</hi> Printers Presse.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Which shewes, that</hi> Soules, <hi>like</hi> Seas <hi>tost with unrest,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Wave, till they set into</hi> Gods <hi>Port of Rest;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Or else that they, like</hi> Swine, <hi>fall to worse</hi> Seas</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Then</hi> Gaderens <hi>for their prodigious Pleas,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Remonstrances, <hi>and</hi> Problems, <hi>which they pend,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Of Rampant Zeale the</hi> Churches Peace <hi>to rend▪</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <l>
         <hi>SO busie is</hi> Mans Braine: <hi>It alwayes workes</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And seekes to know what from the</hi> Sences <hi>lurkes,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Abstruse and hid, like</hi> Planets <hi>moving still;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>But in default of Objects good or ill,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Because it findes no businesse from without,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Turnes</hi> Monke <hi>within, an</hi> Ideot, <hi>or a</hi> Lout;</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Or on it selfe with</hi> Atomes <hi>and</hi> Chymeres</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Playes</hi> Whirligig, <hi>untill it ends in Feares,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Distractions, Lies, and</hi> Schismes, <hi>just Penalties</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Due for the Search of</hi> Knotty Novelties.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>For want of</hi> Grace, <hi>and of</hi> Celestiall <hi>Armes,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Sighes, Teares, &amp; Vowes, <hi>thus by the</hi> Serpents <hi>charmes</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Are Men seduc'd</hi> Old Adams Tree <hi>to tast,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And with vaine</hi> Fruit <hi>to break their needlesse Fast.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Because</hi> Gods Word, <hi>whereby they might be sav'd,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>They slighted, 'tis no marvell though they rav'd.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="6"/>
         <hi>But our</hi> New man <hi>wean'd from the</hi> Carnall Teat</l>
      <l>
         <hi>By</hi> Truths <hi>calme Breath, the</hi> Flaming Paraclete,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>With Drier Braine holds a Cleere</hi> Intellect,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>So solid, that he others can direct</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>A safer Course of knowledge to affect</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Then what the</hi> Wind-mill <hi>grinds of</hi> Satans Sect.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Though</hi> Natures sting <hi>in our</hi> Originall</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Hath made us prone into the Snare to fall:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Yet we</hi> New-borne <hi>fight with the</hi> Spirits Sword,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>And triumph by the</hi> Second Adams Word</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Over the</hi> Dragons <hi>false enchanting Arts,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>With constant</hi> Faith <hi>repelling all his</hi> Darts,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Those</hi> sober Cates <hi>contenting our repast,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Which lawfull are for tender Soules to tast.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>We would seeme</hi> Inward <hi>more then</hi> Outward <hi>wise,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Yet Both addresse with</hi> Saints <hi>to sympathize.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>For</hi> carnall Samians transubstantiate Change,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>(The</hi> Old Mans Quirk) <hi>the</hi> New man <hi>we exchange.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="6"/>
         <hi>Instead of</hi> Lethes Lake, <hi>or</hi> Phlegeton,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e</hi> Tophets Paine <hi>sing due to</hi> Babylon.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>For</hi> Limbus Patrum, <hi>or th'</hi> Elizian Camp.</l>
      <l>Gods Paradise <hi>for</hi> Saints <hi>renewes our Lamp.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>A</hi> Dolphin <hi>bore</hi> Arion <hi>from the Seas;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mphions Harp, <hi>they say, did</hi> Thebes <hi>appease:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>But</hi> Jesus Christ <hi>the Third day to have rose</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>From</hi> Josephs Tombe, <hi>we really disclose,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Or by a</hi> Whale <hi>we</hi> Jonas <hi>bring to Land,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Who</hi> Niniveh <hi>converted out of hand.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>For</hi> Cerberus, <hi>we blaze proud</hi> Satans Losse;</l>
      <l>
         <hi>For</hi> Hercules <hi>his</hi> Club, <hi>our</hi> Saviours Crosse.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>For</hi> Triviall Tales, <hi>and sence-alluring Toyes,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>We read on</hi> Bookes <hi>Soule-ravishing to joyes.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>For</hi> Thalmuds <hi>we the</hi> Scriptures <hi>native sence;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And for Nice</hi> Schoole-mens <hi>Glosse, in our Defence,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>We can produce by</hi> Truths <hi>Prerogative</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>The Chiefest</hi> Starres <hi>of the</hi> Church Primitive,</l>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <l>
         <pb facs="8"/>
         <hi>Or those, who in the Last and Present Age</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>With</hi> Volumes <hi>rare repair'd our</hi> New mans <hi>Stage.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>To banish</hi> Humane Lies, <hi>and Brain-sick Dreames,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>What</hi> Tree <hi>more full? what</hi> Field <hi>yeelds riper Theames</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Then</hi> Christ his Life, <hi>and the</hi> New Testament?</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Or in her</hi> Swathes <hi>the</hi> Churches <hi>fragrant scent?</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>This</hi> Lady <hi>here my</hi> New man <hi>warbles forth,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Though fully not according to her worth,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Yet so,</hi> My Lord, <hi>that you may cleerely see:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Though she was long obscur'd, she now raignes free,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Cloath'd with the</hi> Sunne, <hi>Crown'd with a dozen</hi> Starres,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>And no</hi> Eclipse <hi>you from her Influence barres.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>But out alasse! how many boast of</hi> Faith?</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Who never markt what</hi> Christian Scripture <hi>saith:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>For what is</hi> Faith <hi>without</hi> Good works, <hi>or Fruit,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>But a dead Stock? not worth a</hi> Moores <hi>pursuit?</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="8"/>
         <hi>Unlesse he dreames of</hi> Mechaes <hi>fond Delights?</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Or</hi> Millenairs <hi>to snare</hi> Voluptuous Wights?</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Or of vaine</hi> works <hi>of</hi> Supererogation,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Soules to bewitch with</hi> Babels Fornication?</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Our</hi> Saint <hi>is not with such Conceits defil'd,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Nor turnes with such Extravagances wild,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>For he well knowes, that as good Trees will bud,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And beare good Fruit, so</hi> Saints <hi>doe alwayes Good,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And never scorne to greet the Simplest Man;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>To call home Strayes they labour what they c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Such is our</hi> Saint <hi>the Naked he actires,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And helps to warme their Soules with zealous Fires.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>According to his Power great or small,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>He saves distressed Saints from</hi> Tyrants Thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>He sues for Peaoe, and grieves to see debate.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And daily prayes</hi> Lawes Rigour <hi>to abate.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>If he be forc't to</hi> Law <hi>in his defence.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>He doth it without spl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>n, or</hi> Saints <hi>offence.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="9"/>
         <hi>And if his</hi> Clapper <hi>hap to clatter wild,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Before</hi> Sun-set <hi>he growes more Calme and mild;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Or if that</hi> Filmy Piece <hi>in others blabbs</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>His shame, he counts it like the Noise of</hi> Drabbs.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>He sets not out his Lipps to Farme, nor slander,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Nor lets his</hi> Tongue <hi>before his</hi> Wits <hi>to wander.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>He holds his</hi> Word <hi>as pretious as his</hi> Seale,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>And scornes</hi> False Cards <hi>unto the Least to deale.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>He dares not plot Revenge, nor scoffe, nor raile,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>But beares with Knaves and Fooles for</hi> Saints <hi>availe.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>He covets no mans Goods, but if at</hi> Play</l>
      <l>
         <hi>He winnes, He gives it to the</hi> Poore <hi>away.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>He spends his vacant Howres in thrifty Course,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Lest</hi> Idlenesse <hi>corrupt him worse and worse.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>He prizeth</hi> Coine <hi>but excrementall Drosse,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And toiles for Others Good, though with his Losse.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>He doth his Best to curbe Promooting</hi> Scribes,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Lest</hi> God <hi>require of him their winkt-at Bribes.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="9"/>
         <hi>At Night he scores the Deedes he did that Day,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And the next Morning scowres their rust away.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>The</hi> Sabbath, <hi>like the</hi> Puritan, <hi>he waighes,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And, like the</hi> Papist, <hi>keepes the</hi> Fasting dayes:</l>
      <l>
         <hi>The</hi> Former <hi>mindes him of the</hi> Spirits <hi>Mart,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>The</hi> Latter <hi>helpes to stint the Sensuall Part.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>He daily strives so to compose his Minde,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>That seldome him doe</hi> Idoll-passions <hi>blinde,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Nor cause him long to doat on</hi> Pleasures <hi>shape,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Be it a</hi> Horse, <hi>or</hi> Hawke, <hi>a</hi> Dog, <hi>or</hi> Ape,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>He kindly speakes, meanes well, doth good to all,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>But most to</hi> Saints, <hi>and helpes up them that fall.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>God <hi>root these</hi> Works <hi>in me, lest whilst his Way</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>I others teach, my selfe a</hi> Cast-a-way</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Become, like him, anothers Floore that sweepes,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And yet his owne New house most nasty keepes.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <l>
         <hi>THe</hi> Heart <hi>still moves: It</hi> Loves <hi>and spreads with</hi> Joy</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Or wrung with</hi> Gall <hi>and</hi> Griefe <hi>it feeles Annoy.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>The</hi> Former <hi>flow, because</hi> Gods Flames <hi>inspire it,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>The</hi> Latter <hi>chance in absence of his</hi> Spirit.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Of these</hi> Affects <hi>our</hi> Inward Man <hi>partakes,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Amidst his</hi> Joyes <hi>sometimes his</hi> Spirit <hi>akes:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Yet his</hi> Griefes <hi>smart spring not for worldly Cause,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>But for mens Breach of the</hi> Creators Lawes,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>For the Encrease of</hi> Idols, Avarice,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Of</hi> Drunken Healths, <hi>or the like Heath'nish vice,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>For Concords Breach, for</hi> Christian Blouds <hi>effusion,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>For losse of</hi> Time, <hi>our</hi> Talents <hi>vaine profusion;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Or else because he sees the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> Christ</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Opprest by</hi> Fiends, <hi>and</hi> Saints <hi>by</hi> Antichrist.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Sometimes he feeles strange</hi> Qualmes, <hi>neer destitute</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Of zeale-bred heat, till entring to dispute</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="10"/>
         <hi>With his Proud</hi> Foe, <hi>he like One cheer'd with Wine,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Threats him with Thumps, to make his Pride decline:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>He calls him</hi> Monster, Belly god, <hi>and</hi> Slave,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>And vowes his Fare to shorten, if be ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>With</hi> Davids Sling <hi>he knocks</hi> Gollahs <hi>down<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>For standing out against his</hi> Masters Crowne.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Though he enjoyes an outward faire Estate,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And seemes to some to be most fortunate;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>et in his Mind he waighes the Cause, th'Event,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Mens Frailty, and his owne coincident,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Whereat he Lion-like for braver Prey</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>His Courage lifts at full, not giving way</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>To poore Conceits, but to the Noblest End▪</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>His Cares, his Thoughts, and his designements bonds;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Which he Effects by a</hi> New Sacrifice</l>
      <l>
         <hi>To</hi> God, <hi>who gave those undeserv'd Supplies</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>With knowledge of his</hi> Mysteries Divine,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>And</hi> Prudent Rules <hi>Old Passions to confine,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="11"/>
         <hi>When Thousands of his Brethren want that store,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Who would perhaps have glorifi'd him more,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And never ceas'd, like</hi> Angels <hi>here on Earth,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>To praise those helpes, since Others dye of Dearth.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>His</hi> Spirit <hi>scornes that which the</hi> Body <hi>joyes;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And checks that</hi> Lump, <hi>because it did rejoyce</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>In</hi> Aiery Toyes, <hi>in things meere transitory,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Which draw the</hi> Sence <hi>from the bright</hi> Sun of Glory,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>And like to</hi> Golden Clouds <hi>may passe away</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>By</hi> Humane Plots, <hi>or by</hi> Death <hi>in a day.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>HE reapes Content to see his</hi> Neighbours <hi>thrive,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And their</hi> Amendment <hi>doth his Soule revive,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>For he the Poorest</hi> Saint <hi>in</hi> Christ <hi>preferre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Before the Greatest</hi> Potentate <hi>that erres.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>He Ioyes, that he breathes of the Common Aire;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Which is allotted for the</hi> Saints <hi>repaire,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="11"/>
         <hi>With whom he sings, grieves, and Communicates,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Swell for</hi> Sacred Rites, <hi>as</hi> Needfull Rates.</l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Joyes, <hi>that he had learned from his</hi> Youth,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>ke</hi> Timothy, <hi>the</hi> Word of Sacred Truth,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>at taught to serve</hi> One God, One Advocate,</l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>could not brooke of</hi> Balaams Snares <hi>to prate.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Joyes, <hi>that he no raking Money owes,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>en what to pay he on short warning knowes,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Without grim</hi> Sergeants <hi>Threats, or</hi> Suerties <hi>Thrall,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>without</hi> Robbing Peter to pay Paul.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> glories more of</hi> Soules <hi>and</hi> Bodies Health,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>en in the Blaze of</hi> Honour, Fame, <hi>or</hi> Wealth.</l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>cheere his</hi> Noblest Part <hi>he soares aloft,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And viewes the</hi> Starres <hi>of</hi> Holy Stories <hi>oft;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>He Courts the</hi> Of-Spring of faire Memory,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Aswell</hi> Divine <hi>as</hi> Humane History;</l>
      <l>
         <hi>By which true Glasse he findes how short and vaine</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Those Pleasures are, which</hi> Worldlings <hi>hold for Gaine,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="12"/>
         <hi>Though Cause of Paine eternall after Deuth;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>If not before of Dolour-racking Breath.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Another while</hi> Wraths Cornet <hi>to prevent,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Which he observes with burning</hi> Arrowes <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
               <desc>•••</desc>
            </gap>t</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>To aime at</hi> change, <hi>by</hi> Learned Art <hi>he strives</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>To blunt their Shafts, and into</hi> Physick <hi>dives</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Aswell by</hi> Prayer <hi>as by</hi> Galens Quill,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>With Zealous Heart, as by</hi> Arabian Skill,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Like Good</hi> Saint Luke, <hi>for the</hi> Foure Humours <hi>foule</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>He studies Cure, as Solace for the Soule.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>For which I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="4 letters">
               <desc>••••</desc>
            </gap>t, and the</hi> Complexions <hi>Good</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>He for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>d, which might insta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap> the Bloud:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>For what exceedes the</hi> Temper Oily warme,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Or</hi> Mayes mild Heat <hi>he knowes breeds after-harme.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Lest</hi> Nature <hi>dro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>, he breathes his Park-horse oft,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Not on the</hi> Rheumy Vale, <hi>or</hi> Marish <hi>soft,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>But on dry</hi> Hills <hi>to suck most wholesome Aire,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>There, with Pure Gales the</hi> Spirits <hi>to repaire.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="12"/>
         <hi>While</hi> Gulls <hi>fly out with</hi> Golden Wings <hi>excesse,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>lives at home content with Fortunes lesse,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>t daring by Anothers Idoll-store</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>mete his wants, where</hi> Saints <hi>do languish more:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>d if he should lash out in Pompe like those,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> Pompe and Store would cause him after-woes,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>en the Great</hi> Judge <hi>requires his</hi> Talents <hi>use,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>th strict Account of Stocks and Times abuse.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Drinks <hi>no more then doth a</hi> Saint <hi>befit,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>d ever riseth with an Appetite,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>r, as a Type of Blessed</hi> Abstimence,</l>
      <l>Joyes <hi>to sing of</hi> Diets Excellence▪</l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>d to relate, when</hi> Girald <hi>liv'd, that they</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>f</hi> Cambriaes Soile <hi>did feed but once a day;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>s how the</hi> Greekes <hi>thought</hi> Platoes Tale <hi>a Lye,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>That twice a day they meal'd in</hi> Sicily.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>No</hi> Beauty, Wine, <hi>nor</hi> Musicks <hi>Harmony</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ontents our</hi> Saint <hi>more then Good Company,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="13"/>
         <hi>Knowing their</hi> Vowes, <hi>and mutuall Hearts Consent</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Availe him more then</hi> Worldlings <hi>Blandishment.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>To end his</hi> Joyes, <hi>on this he sets his Rest:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>That a Good Conscience is his daily Feast.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>THese</hi> harmelesse steps <hi>a</hi> Christian <hi>ought to tread</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And the same Life I strive and hope to lead.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And if these Rules</hi> My hopefull Nephew <hi>scan,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>He then shall passe for a Right</hi> Noble Man,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Excelling vulgar Wits as</hi> Porcellan,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Course vessels, as the</hi> New <hi>the</hi> Outward Man,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>By</hi> Vertue <hi>rankt within</hi> True Honours <hi>File</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Among the brave</hi> Heroes <hi>of this</hi> Ile,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Crown'd with a faire and brighter</hi> Coronet,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Then One with</hi> Gold <hi>and</hi> Pretious Stones <hi>beset,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And be so skill'd in Both the</hi> Fortunes Cures,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>That</hi> Poore mens Cries <hi>tend not to</hi> You <hi>nor</hi> Yours.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="13"/>
         <hi>While</hi> Vengeance <hi>strikes a</hi> Nembrodizing Lord.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>And his</hi> Proud Race <hi>with</hi> Fates two-edged Sword,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ke</hi> Mordecai, <hi>unwearied in your wayes,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>u shall we are out on Earth most happy Dayes;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>And after Death when they feele endlesse Paine,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>u shall with</hi> Christ <hi>in</hi> Peace <hi>for ever Raigne.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>ch blisse pursues a Pious-minded</hi> Peere,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>And such I hope attends you there and heere,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Which to seale up, and to set forth Your Traine,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>eere take your Choise of</hi> Posies <hi>various Straine:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>Without the</hi> New-mans Robes <hi>none are indeed</hi>
      </l>
      <l>True Noble-men, <hi>but borne of</hi> Mongrell Seed.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>To be borne</hi> Great, <hi>great</hi> Honour <hi>some esteeme it:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>But to doe Good I greater</hi> Honour <hi>deeme it.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Vertue <hi>so farre excells</hi> Sires Heraldry,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>As doth</hi> Day-light <hi>the Darke, the Sap the Dry.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>A</hi> Noble Minde <hi>surmounts a</hi> Noble Birth;</l>
      <l>
         <hi>But who hath Both-shines like</hi> Sunne <hi>on Earth.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="14"/>
Magnus honor nasci praelustri stemmate, Major Stemma <hi>Piis Factis</hi> nobilitare suum.</l>
      <l>"Quantò <hi>Lux</hi> Tenebras, Siccum vel <hi>Succidus Hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> Tanto depictos <hi>Mens Pia</hi> vincit Avos.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>"Virtus</hi> Naturam superat, sed amictus utrisque Dotibus ut <hi>Lumen Solis</hi> in orbe nitet.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>