<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Translator to the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>G., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119134_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14408</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24727</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119134</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Translator to the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>G., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Acts of the dispute and conference holden at Paris, in the moneths of Iuly and August. 1566. Betweene two doctors of Sorbon, and two ministers of the Reformed Church : A most excellent tract, wherein the learned may take pleasure, and the ignorant reape knowledge. Translate out of French by Iohn Golburne, and diuided according to the daies</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 263, 5 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Translator to the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongst all the meanes, prescribed by wisedome, to attaine the perfection of true knowledge, there is none (good Reader) in my poore conceit, more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie for the ignorant, next to the fountaine of life, the word of God, then the reading of Controuersies; wherein the truth is debated, the reasons on both sides deduced, and laid open to the view, and Readers iudgement. For, as by striking together of the steele &amp; flint, the fire is out forced: euen so by disputation and conference, the truth is boulted out, and decyded. But because it is hard for a blinde man to iudge of colours, and we being all blinde by nature, and ignorant of God and goodnesse, are of our selues vncapable of right iudgement in matters of faith: for flesh and bloud cannot attaine vnto it; neither can the naturall man dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the things of God: we must therefore vse the appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted meanes of our saluation; namely, hearing, reading, and meditating of Gods sacred word: which is onely able to make vs wise vnto saluation, and to enlighten the eyes of the simple. So that by this touchstone, and faithfull inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of God, in the name and sole mediation of Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, for the direction of his holy spirit; wee shalbe enabled to know all things, and to trye the true and pure Gold from the false and counterfeit: and then (comparing the sayings
<pb facs="4"/>
and assertions of both sides, with the sincere &amp; vndeceiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able milke of Gods word) we shalbe likewise able to discerne the spirit of God, from the spirit of Error: and discerning, shall perceiue the incomparable beautie of the one, and the vgly deformitie of the other. Which thing waighing with my selfe, and finding in this Treatise, both the deepnesse of Sathan, and the inuincible force of truth, which is the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God vnto saluation of all true beleeuers, I resolued at the speciall instance of a religious friend, who had begun the Translation, to attempt, effect, and finish the same: which by diuine assistance, I haue faithfully performed, and here present it to thy view. Read it with consideration, consider thereof with iudgement, and iudge with discreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; so shalt thou finde not onely pleasure, but much profit, in matters discussed of greatest moment. For which, and all things else, giue God the glory, make vse for thine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, and accept my poore endeuour; whose desire was to do thee good. Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord,<lb/>
         <hi>I. G.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>