<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, THOMAS Lord Coventry, Baron of Aylesborough, Lord Keeper of the Great Seale of England, one of his Majesties most Honourable Privie Councell, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Wigmore, Michael</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119961_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15330</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25617</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119961</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, THOMAS Lord Coventry, Baron of Aylesborough, Lord Keeper of the Great Seale of England, one of his Majesties most Honourable Privie Councell, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Wigmore, Michael</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The meteors : A sermon preached at a visitation. By Michael VVigmore, Rector of Thorseway in Lincolneshire, and sometimes Fellow of Oriel Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Wigmore, Michael</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 <publisher>Butter, Nathaniel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 15, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, THOMAS Lord <hi>Coventry,</hi> Baron of <hi>Aylesborough,</hi> Lord Keeper of the Great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> one of his Majesties most Honourable Privie Councell, &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vch is the <hi>Leprosie</hi> of <hi>Ingratitude,</hi> that scarce <note place="margin">Luke 17.</note> one in ten comes backe to be thankfull: and God seemes to give a checke to mans nature, in placing <hi>Memory</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind in the head, as being an <hi>Embleme</hi> of our dulnesse, in rendring the <hi>Offices</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>of Gratitude.</hi> I must, and ever will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to Gods glory, and your Honour, that as I had my <hi>being</hi> from above, so have I my <hi>bene esse</hi> from your <hi>bounty,</hi> in so much that (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Philemon) I owe unto you even mine</hi>
      <note place="margin">Philem. 19.</note>
      <hi>owne selfe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>With that <hi>Samaritan</hi> in the Gospell, <note place="margin">Luc. 17. 15. 16.</note> I am at length <hi>come backe againe to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,</hi> and to present you with these <hi>false fires,</hi> to make my <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Affection</hi> le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible; <hi>ut Dei, ita est eorum qui Dei in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rex Platon.</note>
      <hi>vices obeunt, pro sua immensitate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficia largiri, sed hominum gratitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, ex eorum modulo aestimare.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Long hath <hi>mine heart burnt within me,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 39. 3.</note> with an earnest, <hi>Quid retribuam?</hi> In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard <note place="margin">Psal. 116. 12.</note> of those gratious encouragements, by your <hi>Honour</hi> conferd upon me. Nor have I slept in the <hi>Land of forgetfulnesse,</hi> but waited <hi>opportunity</hi> to vent my selfe;
<pb facs="3"/> and now I have borrowed so much <hi>strength</hi> of <hi>boldnesse,</hi> as to lift up the <hi>eyes of Hope,</hi> presuming to prefer these <hi>flashes</hi> to your view; in the which as the <hi>bad-borrowers</hi> of these dayes, I doe pay my <hi>great debts</hi> by <hi>small Pensions.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If this mine Adventure shall finde such admittance, as to give the least life to my riper studies, I shall not suffer my <hi>Temples to rest,</hi> till I be delivered of a <note place="margin">Psal. 132. 4.</note> stronger birth.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Coelum quietem sortitur in motu,</hi> I shal ever account it my heaven upon earth, to labour to shew forth my thankfulnes, and to pray with a <hi>flaming heart, that</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gen. 49. 22. 26.</note>
      <hi>the blessing of Ioseph</hi> light upon you.</p>
   <closer>
      <date>
         <hi>Decem.</hi> 15. 1632.</date>
      <signed>Your Honours humble <hi>Eleemosynarie,</hi> MICHAEL WIGMORE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>