<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT
HONOVRABLE HENRY LORD
CARY, Viscount of Faulkland, Controller of
his Maiesties household, and one of his Ma∣iesties
most Honourable priuie
Councell.</title>
           <author>Whitbourne, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119923_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15072</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25375</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119923</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT
HONOVRABLE HENRY LORD
CARY, Viscount of Faulkland, Controller of
his Maiesties household, and one of his Ma∣iesties
most Honourable priuie
Councell.</title>
                 <author>Whitbourne, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discourse containing a louing inuitation both honourable, and profitable to all such as shall be aduenturers, either in person, or purse, for the aduancement of his Maiesties most hopefull plantation in the Nevv-found-land, lately vndertaken. Written by Captaine Richard Whitbourne of Exmouth, in the county of Deuon</title>
                 <author>Whitbourne, Richard, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 46, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT
HONOVRABLE HENRY LORD
CARY, Viscount of Faulkland, Controller of
his Maiesties household, and one of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties
most Honourable priuie
Councell.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Plantation of <hi>New-found-land,</hi>
to which my former Discourse,
(not vnknown to your Lordship)
as a Harbinger hath in part alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
chalked out the way, and so
farre preuailed with the cleere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
and solidity of your iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
that lying on the naturall truth of my reasons, I
am confident there need no second motiues to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme
your <hi>Honours</hi> approbation of my first; seeing the
same hath been approued by the Lords of his Maiesties
most Honourable priuie Councell, as a Worke both
profitable and necessary for his Maiesties Kingdomes
in generall: But because the affections and resolutions
of men doe sometimes freeze, in stead of heating, and
most decline, when, to the eye of the world, they seeme
most to aduance; I haue therefore aduentured to forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
and assist my former printed discourse, with this se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond;
<pb facs="3"/>
and by vnfolding other reasons vnto all such as
are willing to be Aduenturers in your pretended pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose,
whereby to make it apparent that the said Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
beares its perswasion with it: yea, that it hath all
the grounds, and runnes on all the feet of good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilities,
as <hi>Religion, Honour, Empire,</hi> and <hi>Profit.</hi> For it
wil propagate <hi>Christians,</hi> where there are as yet but few.
It wil adorne the Crown of our Soueraigne with a spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
Continent: yea, it will empty England of many
people, which may so well be spared, and yeerely reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish
it with abundance of treasure, which it so much
wanteth. And although my insuing Discourse be plain,
yet I affirmatiuely auerre, it is true: for as I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted
in the latitude of matter, and not in the altitude
of words; so I haue written it out of my certaine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience
and knowledge, and not out of any borrowed
speculation; as hauing many yeeres, with much labour,
industry and cost, played the practicke part in that
Countrey, as well as the theoricke: and therfore know
well how to reduce my former contemplation, into fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
action, as it may partly appeare by representing
your Lordships seuerall Circuits of land in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey
(to the open view) in her natiue and naturall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours,
and by proposing and discouering the meanes
how, and where the Plantation may bee made firme,
flourishing, and profitable, to all such as will aduenture
therein. Now as you haue vndertaken it with much
zeale and iudgement, so I no wayes doubt, but you will
be the meanes to establish and settle it with renowne
and profit. And euen as little Pinnaces doe often looke
when the greater Ships will weigh Anchor, whereby
they may passe with the more safety vnder their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct,
vnto their wished Port: So the eyes of many sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects
<pb facs="3"/>
doe reioyce, that your Honour giues spirit and life
to this Plantation, whereby they may bee imployed
therein. For mine owne part, I haue receiued many
testimonies of fauour from your hands, during my long
attendance at Court herein: although, as yet, the
Subiects are not possest with my bookes, whereby they
may bee informed of the validity of the reasons they
containe for the establishing of this Plantation. And
thus I humbly present these my endeuours, as a thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
expression and acknowledgement in part of such
great fauours, as I haue already receiued from your
hands, vntill the prouidence of God, and the pleasure
of his Maiesty command mee to make tryall of what
my two discoueries and narrations haue proposed and
promised. Thus with hearty desire vnto the Almighty
for your long life, with increase of great honour, and
happinesse, I will euer remaine.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships, in all duty and
humblenesse to be commanded,
RICHARD WHITBOVRNE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>