<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>T.S. to faithfull Christi∣an Reader greeting.</title>
           <author>S., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119680_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06881</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17313</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119680</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>T.S. to faithfull Christi∣an Reader greeting.</title>
                 <author>S., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of the good and euell tounge : With the vnstablenesse of the same, and also with the abuses thereof. With a discourse of the punishment which the Lord hath shewed on al those which through swearing and periuring themselues, haue broken Gods commandements: as by this treatise most plainely appeareth. Made by Iohn of Marconuille gentleman</title>
                 <author>Marconville, Jean de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Perrin (Perin), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>58 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>T.S.</hi> to faithfull Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>Reader greeting.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eeing entreated by a freend of mine (<hi>Gentle Reader</hi>) to peruse this pamflet, and write some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in the behalfe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: I was contented, after the reading ouer of the same, to satisfie that his honest request, because in my poore opinion, it is well worthie the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing, and neuer more neede full (it at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time the like treatise was needeful) thē now in this our so corrupt age, after so long sincere preaching (the Lord be high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly praysed therefore) of the most holy &amp; glorious Gospel of our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ. The matter conteined herein setteth forth vnto thee, how and in what maner thou shouldest vse and rule they tongue, the good which commeth by the modest and holy vsage thereof, &amp; the euill and great danger which ariseth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by in the abuse of the same both to body and soule. It were superfluous for me to set downe here the infinite number of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of mischiefe, which an euil tongue hath wrought, &amp; what good otherwise be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing vsed in the feare of god it hath broght
<pb facs="3"/>and wil alwaies bring, because thou shalt find them in the reading hereof sufficiētly mētioned, both by the autority of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly scripturs, and also of other prophane au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, although in very deede the first au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie is most sufficient.: &amp; therfore sith the heathen who neuer knew god aright, (bicause they knew not his Christ, the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour &amp; redeemer of al such as faithfullye beleeue in him, and vnfainedly beleue his holy gospell, &amp; practize the same in their liues &amp; conuersation all the daies of their life) made such lawes and ordinances for the punishing of vnruly &amp; blasphemous tongues, some with marking in the face with hoat burning irōs, some by the purse and some by death, which is the iust lawe of the most high. Let vs christians, or at the least which beare the name of Christ, and would gladly so be called, take hede how we abuse our tongues, either with blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, periuries, flatteries, filthie &amp; ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable speeches, cursings, raylings &amp; backbitinges, least we fall into the hands of the most seuere &amp; iust iudge, who iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth both iustly and rightly, either to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting saluation, or els to perpetuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction both of body and soule for euer. Wherfore I exhort and besech al the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders hereof, of what estate or condition so
<pb facs="3"/>euer he or she be, in the name of God the father &amp; of his son Iesus Christ, to bring with them circumcised eares and hartes, and perfect &amp; sound iudgement, so that the things which they shal read herin, may take deepe roote in their hartes &amp; consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, as seats ready prepared for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering &amp; amending of them selues in the reasonable and holy vse of their tongues, as may be to the glory of God, their euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting comfort in Christ Iesus, &amp; the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of others with whom they shall be conuersant. For the Lord God created all things in the world for the vse and seruice of man, and man, to serue him alone, all the daies of his life in holines and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnes, which seruice of his resteth in the hart and tongue, for it is written, with the hart we beleeue vnto righteousnes, and with the tongue we confesse vnto saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And againe let your talke &amp; commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication be such as may bring grace to the hearers: and againe, if any man speake, let him speake as the wordes of God, that is, let his communication be holy that it may edify those which heare it, so that therby your heauenly father may be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified: again be ye holy, bicause I your god am holy. But we for the most part are thankeful vnto his maiestie neither in
<pb facs="4"/>hart nor tongue, for his benefites recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, &amp; especially when he feedeth vs, for euen then when we should be most thāk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for our meates and drinkes, we poure out all the repast whole: most filthie, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable, beastly, &amp; blasphemous talke, and he is no good companion forsooth, that cannot &amp; wil not do so, and by that mean in stead of glorifying his holy name we altogither blaspheme it with our hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houndish tongues, &amp; yet we thinke they do vs great wrong, who wil not thinke &amp; account vs to be good Christians, But if this be, to be a good christians, then al the deuils in hell are such christians. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, if anie man shal admonish those that thus shal abuse their tongues, they aske what hast thou to do with my speeches, &amp; as the prophet Dauid complained of the corruptiō of the people in his daies, Psal. 12. they say, our tongues are ours, wee ought to speake, what Lord shall vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trole? Furthermore, the tongue is the messenger of the hart, and whatsoeuer the hart imagineth the tongue vtte reth, so that by the talke of a man, is known what an hart he beareth, for it is said, out of the aboundance of the hart, the tongue spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, wherefore (Christian Reader) let vs so vse our tongues as that God may
<pb facs="4"/>be honored and serued by them: And marke I beseech you, what commoditie ariseth by the seruing of his maiestie tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and duelie. First this we knowe, that what soeuer paine an earthlie seruaunt taketh about the seruice of his maister, that, that his painefull seruice, turneth to the benefite of the maister: But he that serueth God, the more duetifullie and painefully he serueth him, the same his paineful &amp; diligent seruice turneth whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to his owne benefite: yea euen to the enheritaunce of the kingdome of heauen, through Iesus Christ our Lord: one chiefe and speciall point of which seruice consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth in the tongue. And thus much according to my simple skil, and not like any great clarke, haue I as briefe▪ l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e as I might, giuen thee to vnderstand how thou oughtest to come prepared to the reading of this treatise, not superfici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie &amp; without some fruit, but with iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment and vnderstanding. Wherefore I beseech thee thanke God, for the author hereof who hath offered this his trauell for thy benefite, that hee finding by his paynes taken, some good to haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued thereby, it may the rather encourage him and others which trauell in the like cases, to go forward in such measures as
<pb facs="5"/>the Lord God shall bestowe on them in their well doing, to the glory of his most holy name, and benefite of his Church, And so for this time I leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord. T.S.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>