<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Freendly Reader, Ulpian FullWell.</title>
           <author>Fulwell, Ulpian</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119694_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01351</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11472</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119694</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Freendly Reader, Ulpian FullWell.</title>
                 <author>Fulwell, Ulpian</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first parte, of the eyghth liberall science: entituled, Ars adulandi, the arte of flatterie : with the confutation therof, both very pleasaunt and profitable, deuised and compiled, by Vlpian Fulwell</title>
                 <author>Fulwell, Ulpian</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>How (Howe, Haw), William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>76 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Freendly Reader, <hi>Ulpian FullWell.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doubt not at al (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) but that I, for my indus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try in detecting this eyghth li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall Science, shall bee repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with many <hi>sapientum octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uus,</hi> the eyghth wise man: that is as wise as Will Sommer, but I shall contente my selfe with such reputacion, rather chosing to be truthes drudge, then Fortunes flattering dearling. And I can not but greatly lamente, that so many in these dayes doo so adict themselues to the filthy trade of flattery, whereby both Noble men, Gentlemen, and good natured men are abused: &amp; fooles flatterers, dissemblers and gesters, noseled in impudency, and nourished by petty theeuery, like the waspe that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vpon the labour of the paynefull Bee. And although such Waspes will for this my labour doo their endeuour to stinge mee for my paine: yet I will bee so bold with them as to tell thee (gentle Reader) what they are. Such they are as lye at receite for the fruites of other mens desertes. They catche the birdes, for the which other men beate the bush, and such they are, as with their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testable practice of flattery, withdrawe men from the study of vertue.</p>
   <p>And this their execrable science hath so peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of many in this age, and hath taken
<pb facs="5"/>
such habit in mans affections: that it is in moste men <hi>altera natura,</hi> and very difficile to bee expelled: yea, the very sucking babes hath a kinde of adula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion towardes their Nurses for the dugge, which (in my iudgement) commeth vnto them by corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of nature: and as they grow in reason, so they increase therin, vntill in time it is turned frō greene and tender addulation, to ripe and perfect dissimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, except by good education the same bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented. If I should generally condemne all men of this foule crime, I might iustly be blamed, yet may I bouldly say, that in comparison of the multitude, very few there are, whose hartes and tongues are not stayned with the blemish of flattery and the brāches therof: namely dissimulatiō, deceit, wicked perswations, with such other like sinisters practis. How common a thing is it, to see one man embrace another with such freendly salutacions, as though they were knit in the insoluble knot of perfect frend ship, and yet a man may buy as much loue at Byl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingsgate for a boxe on the eare.</p>
   <p>How shifte some men with goulden wordes to promisse, and how slacke to performe: how easie to haue a freend in wordes, and how hard to finde one in deedes: And certes, if I should particulerly descend to the very Begger, I should both bee too tedious in this Epistle, and also publish the effecte of my seconde parte of this matter, (as yet to come.) Desiringe thee not to wreste my woordes
<pb facs="5"/>
vnto a worse sence, then my playne meaninge hath pretended: and where thou findest this name <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,</hi> my meaning is the selfesame blinde Māmon, that the Poets speake of, vnder whose name and person, they comprehend earthly prosperitie, which wee daily see to bee vnegally, and vndiscretly distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted: and her stately pallace, is the wide worlde, wherunto all men haue ingresse and egresse: and thus dooing, thou shalt both gratify my desire, and hasten mee forth vnto my second part: Until which time (gentle Reader,) I pray thee let not this my beginninge offend thee, except thou be one of them that is here rubbed on the gall: but trustinge that thou art one of <hi>Lady Truethes</hi> retinue, I submit my labour vnto thy censure, wishing thee thy harts desire in God. <hi>Vale.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Vlpian Fulwell</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>