<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A BRIEFE SVMMARIE of what is contai∣ned in this TREA∣TISE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119291_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03941</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14049</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119291</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A BRIEFE SVMMARIE of what is contai∣ned in this TREA∣TISE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A Nevv-Yeares gift for English Catholikes, or A briefe and cleare explication of the new Oath of Allegiance : By E.I. student in Diuinitie; for a more full instruction, and appeasement of the consciences of English Catholikes, concerning the said Oath, then hath beene giuen them by I.E. student in Diuinitie, who compiled the treatise of the prelate and the prince</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 208, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>A BRIEFE SVMMARIE of what is contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this TREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TISE.</head>
   <p n="1">1. <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irst,</hi> An <hi>Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition</hi> to Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Catholiks, to examin their cōsciences ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this <hi>New Oath</hi> of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: for that by refusing the same if it bee lawfull and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred
<pb facs="3"/>by good and full authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, (as this Treatise conuinceth it to bee) they hazard not only their temporall estates, but also their eternall saluation, by diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying and resisting lawfull au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and the ordinance of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God.</p>
   <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> are set downe a <hi>Copie</hi> of the new <hi>Oath</hi> of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, <hi>The</hi> 13. Priests
<hi>Protestation;</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Iohn Colletons Petition</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee confirmeth his former <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation:</hi> and the
<hi>Acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Thomas Greene,</hi> (a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Priest of the order of Saint <hi>Benedict,</hi> and <hi>Professour</hi> of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie) concerning his opinion of the said <hi>Oath</hi> of Allegiance, with certaine notes and Obseruations added by the
<hi>Authour</hi> to the said <hi>Protestation,</hi> &amp;
<hi>Acknowledgement.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="3">3. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Certaine generall
<hi>Obseruations</hi> are set downe, to
<pb facs="3"/>know <hi>first,</hi> the nature and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of euery lawfull Oath. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> what rules are to be obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for the vnderstanding and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting of the true sense and meaning of any ambiguous word or sentence contained in any Law, and consequently in this
<hi>Oath</hi> of Allegiance established by a <hi>Parliamentall</hi> Law.
<hi>Thirdly,</hi> what was the intent and meaning of his <hi>Maiestie</hi> and the <hi>Parliament,</hi> in framing and proposing this new and vnwonted
<hi>Oath</hi> of Allegiance, deuised vpon occasion of that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wonted Barbarous and Deuillish Conspiracie of the <hi>Powder-Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours;</hi> to wit, not to make a distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, betwixt <hi>Protestants</hi> &amp;
<hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes,</hi> but between <hi>Catholikes</hi> &amp;
<hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes,</hi> in point of their loyaltie and ciuill obedience, especially concerning the <hi>Popes</hi> authority to practise the deposition of <hi>Princes,</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>which was the ground of that dānable
<hi>Powder-Treason. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> to know vpon what assured grounds the
<hi>Popes</hi> authoritie to <hi>depose</hi> Princes, or to
<hi>practise</hi> their deposition, may not only be bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denyed, but also abiured as <hi>damnable; impious,</hi> and <hi>hereticall:</hi> to wit, for that it is a controuersie among learned Catholikes, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the
<hi>Pope</hi> hath authoritie to depriue Princes or no: and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that it is open iniustice in the <hi>Pope;</hi> and manifest Treason in the Subiect to attempt the dispos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessing of any Soueraigne
<hi>Prince,</hi> by vertue of this pretended au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie and clayme, so long as this Controuersie remayneth a foot, and is not decided by a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Iudge, and who without all doubt and Controuersie is known so to bee.
<hi>Fiftly, page</hi> 64. it is shewed, that the <hi>Pope</hi> is no lawfull
<pb facs="4"/>Iudge to end and decide this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie concerning his own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tēded authoritie to depriue Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne <hi>Princes;</hi> for that it is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie among Learned Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, and approued by very many famous <hi>Prelates, Cardinals,</hi> and <hi>Doctours</hi> cited by the
<hi>Authour,</hi> that the <hi>Pope,</hi> without the consent and approbation of a lawfull and vndoubted generall <hi>Councell,</hi> hath not authoritie to decide, deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, or define any doctrinal que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion at all, and much lesse in his owne particular cause, as is this Controuersie betwixt Him and Christian <hi>Princes:</hi> and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore although hee should take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him to decide this question, yet the Controuersie would still re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne a foote, and bee vndecided as it was before.</p>
   <p n="4">4. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> In the <hi>first</hi> eight Chapters it is cleerly shewed, that
<pb facs="5"/>there is not any one Clause of the <hi>Oath,</hi> which wanteth either <hi>Veritie, Iustice,</hi> or Iudgement: and that therefore English Catholikes not only may lawfully, but also are bound in conscience to take it, when they are vrged thereunto by the
<hi>Magistrate,</hi> whom the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>State</hi> hath appointed to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the same: otherwise they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist lawfull authoritie, and the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God, which <hi>whosoeuer resist purchase to themselues dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Rom.</hi> 13.</p>
   <p n="5">5. <hi>Fiftly,</hi> In the <hi>ninth</hi> and last Chapter are cleerly answered the <hi>Popes</hi> declaratiue <hi>Breues,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding English Catholikes to take the <hi>Oath, for that it contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth many things, which are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festly repugnant to faith and salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> which <hi>Breues</hi> therefore doe not make, but only suppose the
<hi>Oath</hi> to bee vnlawfull, as contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in it some manifest falshood
<pb facs="5"/>or iniustice: and therefore, abstra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cting from the
<hi>Popes Breues,</hi> some particular clause of the <hi>Oath</hi> must be proued to be vnlawfull, which this <hi>Treatise</hi> doth euidently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince to bee vntrue. And <hi>first</hi> in this Chapter it is shewed, that it is no disobedience or irreuerence, not to obey. such
<hi>declaratiue Breues,</hi> seeing that they are groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon one of these <hi>two</hi> (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon both) false suppositions: to wit, that either the doctrine for the <hi>Popes</hi> power to depriue
<hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> is certaine, of Faith, and out of all Controuersie, and the contrarie not approued by learned Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, which <hi>supposition</hi> is manifest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly false: or else that the <hi>Popes</hi> power to
<hi>excommunicate,</hi> to bind and loose, and to absolue from Oaths in general, and consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his Spirituall authoritie is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed in the Oath, which also is no
<pb facs="6"/>lesse vntrue: and that therefore English Catholikes not only may lawfully and without any disobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience or irreuerence, but also are bound in conscience not to obey them, considering that they are so preiudiciall to themselues, so scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous to the <hi>Catholike Roman Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> which they professe, and so iniurious to their <hi>Soueraign Prince,</hi> who, being in reall possession of his Kingdome, cannot vpon any controuersed Title or Power with out open iniustice bee dispossessed thereof.
<hi>Secondly,</hi> it is shewed, that albeit diuers <hi>Popes</hi> haue since the time of Pope <hi>Gregorie</hi> the VII. challenged to themselues authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to depriue <hi>Soueraigne Princes,</hi> yet they cannot bee truly said, to haue beene for any little time in possession of this their pretended authoritie, right and clayme: for that they haue euer beene resisted
<pb facs="6"/>and contradicted by Christian <hi>Princes</hi> and
<hi>Subiects</hi> in this their pretended right and clayme, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, to possesse authoritie, right, or clayme to any thing, it is necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, according to the approued do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Molina,</hi> and
<hi>Lessius</hi> both Iesuites, and of all Diuines and Lawyers, that it bee without resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance and contradiction of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse part: but one may truly and really possesse corporall things, as Lands, Houses, Kingdomes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though hee, that pretendeth to haue right to the same, yea and perchance hath true right there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, contradict and resist neuer so much. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> it is shewed, that howsoeuer any man may vnder pretence of following a <hi>probable</hi> opinion, thinke himselfe excused in conscience and in the sight of God (wherewith <hi>Princes</hi> in their Tribunals doe not meddle, but
<pb facs="7"/>leaue mens consciences to the iudgement of God, the only sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of all mens hearts) by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring with the <hi>Pope</hi> to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing and dispossessing of his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne <hi>Prince;</hi> yet considering that it is not only <hi>probable,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so most
<hi>certaine,</hi> that hee is excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in conscience and in the sight of God, by defending his <hi>Prince</hi> against such damnable, and tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous practises, which are groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>at the most</hi> vpon a
<hi>probable</hi> power, title, and clayme, and also that hee cannot bee excused from formall Treason in the externall Court, both Ecclesiasticall and Secular of his <hi>Soueraigne Prince,</hi> who is in actuall possession of his Kingdome, &amp; cānot without open iniustice be dispossessed vpon any vncertayne and controuersed power, clayme, or title though it were neuer so probable; it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
<pb facs="7"/>that those Subiects might iustly bee accounted worse then mad, that would in such damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and trayterous practises con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre with the <hi>Pope</hi> to the dispos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessing of their
<hi>Soueraigne Prince,</hi> vnder pretence of a power, or ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, which, euen in speculation, and abstracting from practise, can be at the most but probable.</p>
   <p n="6">6. <hi>Lastly,</hi> are set downe, <hi>First,</hi> the
<hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> or the <hi>first Article</hi> of the lower House of <hi>Parliament,</hi> wherein of two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Deputies</hi> for the third Estates were but six <hi>Protestants: Secondly,</hi> two
<hi>Arrests</hi> or <hi>Decrees</hi> of the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> of
<hi>Paris,</hi> forbidding vnder paine of Treason Cardinall
<hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines</hi> Booke against <hi>Barckley,</hi> and <hi>Suarez</hi> Booke against our Kings <hi>Maiesties</hi> Premonition, and
<hi>third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> another <hi>Decree</hi> of the said <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> ordayning likewise that
<pb facs="8"/>no person of what qualitie or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition soeuer doe teach the said doctrine of <hi>deposing</hi> Princes as
<hi>problematicall</hi> or probable. All which <hi>Decrees</hi> are proued to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to truth and iustice, and that <hi>Christian Princes,</hi> by vertue of their temporall power, haue good and full authoritie, both to forbid the teaching, maintayning, and publishing of all vnnecessarie doctrines &amp; positions, be they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer so probable, as the teaching and publishing of the same ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the subuersion of States-and to the disturbance of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like peace in the Ciuill Common, wealth, and is dangerous to the Crownes and liues of temporall Princes; and also to punish with temporall punishments the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, maintayners, and publishers of the same.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>