<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           <author>B., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119545_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17299</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4140</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119545</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>B., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christians bulvvarke, against Satans battery. Or, The doctrine of iustification : so plainely and pithily layd out in the severall maine branches of it as the fruits thereof may be to the faithfull, as so many preservatives against the poysonous heresies and prevailin iniquities of these last times. By H.B. pastor of S. Mathevvs Friday-street</title>
                 <author>Burton, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 <publisher>Taunton (Tanton), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Young (Junius), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 373, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, loe here the two great mysteries laid open; the one of Godlinesse, the summe whereof is Christ, beleeued on in the World: the other of Iniquity, the head whereof is Antichrist, beleeued on of the World. Two Mysteries in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible, as light and darknesse. They are the two bounders, dister<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating Ierusalem from Babylon. This Mysterie of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, I meane, the Romish doctrine of Iustification, is the head-doctrine, or source, whence all their meritorious sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions doe flow. And <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> with other Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,<note place="margin">Bellarmin. de Iustif. l. 1. c. 4.</note> confesseth, Iustification to bee the maine <hi>Cardo</hi> or hinge, whereon hangeth the whole body of controuersies betweene them and the Pretestants. Nor was it for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that the Councell of Trent so improued all their skill and strength, to oppose and oppresse the true Catholicke do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Iustification, as whereby the Papall magnificence and the gaine of the Romish Craftsmen for their <hi>Diana,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Act. 19.</note> was endangered. So that this their Abortiue was a hatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for seuen moneths; so long was this Babylonish Ramme, wherewith they would force heauen gates, a hammering in the Trent-forge: so as the History noteth, that the most<note place="margin">Hist. Concil. Trid. lib. 2.</note> expert in the Church affirmed, That if all the Councels,
<pb facs="6"/>
assembled from the Apostles times to that, were sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vp together, they could not make vp so many Articles as the Trent-Fathers had amassed together, in this one sixt Session of that Synod, the best part whereof also they were beholden to <hi>Aristotle</hi> for. And no maruaile they were so puzzled, for they were to encounter sundry diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties: as first, the euidence of Scriptures: secondly, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent of ancient Fathers: thirdly, the powerfull preaching and writings of <hi>Luther.</hi> fourthly, the dissent of their Schoolemen; and fiftly, the diuision of the Councell it selfe, some being Thomists, some Scotists, some Dominicans, some Franciscans. To satisfie and reconcile all which, was more than an Herculean labour. But what could be difficult to the Papall Omnipotencie; who could send his holy Ghost post from Rome to Trent in a Cloake-bagge, which loosed all knots, and decided all doubts? Nor had the Pope wanting in that Councell the most pregnant wits in the Pontifician world, besides a numerous multitude of new titular Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops (as titular for learning as liuing) to lay on load of down right voyces, to conclude and ratifie whatsoeuer the Pope with his Cardinals in their Conclaue at Rome, and his dextrous instruments in the Councell, had with no lesse sweat than artifice, contriued. For the first maine obstacle, the euidence of Scripture, they are faine to collogue, and speake it faire, and borrow from it certaine broad Phylac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, wouen with Scripture phrases, wherewith the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonish Whore partly decks her shamelesse forehead, and partly adornes the cobwebbe Robe of her counterfeit selfe-Iustification: as <hi>Coelestis Pater: Iesus Christ, the Sun</hi>
      <note place="margin">Concil. Trid. Sess. 6. Proem. cap. 2. 5. 7.</note>
      <hi>of righteousnesse, the author and finisher of our faith: The Father of mercies, and God of all consolation, sent his sonne to redeeme Iewes and Gentiles, and that</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>all might receiue adoption of sonnes: Him hath God sent forth to be a propitiation for our sinnes in his bloud: for this Redemption we ought to giue thanks.</hi> And ch. 7. <hi>The Meritorious cause of our Iustification is our Lord Iesus Christ &amp;c.</hi> O holy Councell! Will any suspect the Serpent to lurke vnder such flowers of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise? Or that they goe about to betray Christ with Hayle Master? But in this their profound hypocrisie lyeth the whole Mysterie of Iniquity; <hi>Si tamen hypocrisis dici de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, quae iam latere prae abundantia non valet, &amp; prae</hi>
      <note place="margin">Bern. Serm. ad Clerum. Et super Cant. Serm. 33.</note>
      <hi>impudentiâ non quaerit;</hi> as <hi>Bernard</hi> saith of Romes Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy in his time. <hi>If that may be called hypocrisie, which neither for the abundancy of it can, nor for the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie of it cares to conceale it selfe.</hi> Thus by egregious hypocrisie <hi>Arrius</hi> deluded the Councell of Nice, confessing Christ to be <hi>God of God,</hi> yet denyed his consubstantiality with the Father. Thus the second Councell of Nice, sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned to decree the erection and veneration of Images, makes a goodly Preface, giuing thankes to God that they were deliuered from Idols. Thus <hi>Augustine</hi> confesseth how he was seduced by the Manichaean hypocrisie. Thus dealeth the Trent Councell. And besides her hypocrisie, her impudencie displayes it selfe, while in this Councell, Rome alters the Rule of Faith, addes her Traditions, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretals and Canons, as a party and equall rule with Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, guelds the Scriptures of their masculine authoritie<note place="margin">See Bulla Pii 4 super confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matione Conc. Trid. &amp; super Forma iura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis fidei.</note> and genuine sense, closing vp all in the Cabinet of the Popes breast, where lodgeth his <hi>Infallibilitie.</hi> And thus the sacred Scriptures, which, till that Idolatrous Councell of Trent, were held the sole and entire Catholicke Canon and rule of Faith, must now draw in the Popes yoake with his sophisticate Traditions.
<pb facs="7"/>
Now, the pure gold and siluer of Gods word must goe no longer for currant, vnlesse it be stamped in the Popes owne Mynt, and subiect also to be abased or inhansed at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure. Now, the waters of life are of no force, vnlesse distil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led through the Popes Limbeck; nor those riuers of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise medicinable, if they flow not from the sacred Minerals of the Romish Mountaines. Thus in effect the Romish A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazon cuts off the right pap of Scripture, which yeelds the sincere milke, reseruing only the left to suckle her Paplings withall, as that <hi>Lupa</hi> did Romes founder <hi>Romulus;</hi> or, at least, the right Pap is so patched to that stepmothers breast, as it yeelds no other milke, but such as relisheth of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt complexion of the Popes infallibility. Thus the first Rubbe is remoued, the Scriptures, which are made cock-sure for the Pope.</p>
   <p>2 For <hi>Luther,</hi> they could easily hisse him out for an arch heretick, and blast and brand with Anathema those euident truths by him deliuered. So that hard it was to iudge, whether fared worse, <hi>Luther</hi> for the truths sake, or the truth for <hi>Luthers.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>3 For the consent of ancient Fathers, the most they stand vpon is S. <hi>Augustine,</hi> who indeed writ more of this diuine mysterie, than all the rest put together. But the Councell could easily euade him, saying (as <hi>Catarinus</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Predestination) <hi>that</hi> S. Aug. <hi>his opinion therin was nouel, neuer heard of before his time:</hi> or, <hi>that S.</hi> Aug. <hi>was drawn to speake many things awry, through heat of disputation against the Pelagians:</hi> or (as <hi>Vega) Non necesse est &amp;c, It is not necessary to beleeue all S.</hi> Aug. <hi>his arguments to be demonstratiue, or altogether to stand in force.</hi> Thus all the Fathers corne, though grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the field of Scriptures, proues but chaffe, comming
<pb facs="7"/>
once to be sifted in the mysticall, if not <note n="a" place="margin">Luke 22. 31.</note> Satanicall fanne of this actiue Councell.</p>
   <p>4. &amp; 5. For the dissenting Schoolemen, and those Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicans and Franciscans in this Councell, whereof <hi>Vega</hi> and <hi>Soto</hi> were the two Standard-bearers, and bore a great sway therein, it behooued the Councell to keepe good quarter with them, and to vse all their witts, eyther to reconcile them, or with some pretty equiuocations to please all parties. For this purpose, <hi>Marcellus,</hi> Priest, intituled of the holy Crosse, President of the Councell, Cardinall and Apostolicall Legate <hi>à latere,</hi> whose wits were as ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satilous, as his titles magnificent and various: after much sweat spent in chopping and changing, peecing and pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, after an hundred Congregations, wherein these matters were canuased <hi>Pro &amp; Con:</hi> at length licked the <hi>Decrees and Canons</hi> to that forme, that each side was pleased, and <hi>Marcellus</hi> applauded on all hands; when each Sect might from the same Delphick Oracle pick out his owne meaning. Thus came these Trent Decrees to be like a curious Picture, which euery one in the Roome imagineth to looke directly vpon him. Or like an indented Table-Picture vpon a Wall, wherein the one side of the Roome may behold the face of a man, the other, of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and they in the midst, of an Owle. Thus <hi>Soto</hi> and <hi>Vega,</hi> who in the time of this Session, writ each a Volume of this Subiect, though in some smaller points different in their opinions, which they grounded vpon the Decrees, and dedicated to the Councell, were both well pleased; yet no otherwise reconciled, but, as <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> Brethren in euill, to crucifie Christ. The writing of which two Champions of Trent I haue mostly all along this Treatise, confuted.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="8"/>Thus, as S. <hi>Ambrose</hi> saith, <hi>Fucum faciunt, qui non</hi>
      <note place="margin">Amb. de fide l. 1. c. 8.</note>
      <hi>audent explicare, quod sentiunt censoriè, They do but iuggle, that dare not set downe in plaine termes, what they captiously conceiue.</hi> And as <hi>Hierome</hi> against the Pelagian Hereticks: <hi>Sola haec haeresis, quae publicè eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bescit</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hier. ad Cte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siph. de libero arbitr. contra Pelag. Ep. 3.</note>
      <hi>loqui, quod scripto docere non metuit: This only is heresie, which blusheth to speake that publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it feares not to teach secretly.</hi> But, as there hee saith, <hi>Ecclesiae victoria est, vos apertè dicere, quod sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titis; sententias vestras prodidisse, superasse est: It is the Churches victory for you to speake plainly, as you think; to detect your opinions, is to confute them.</hi> But we haue assayed to pull off Romes vizard, and to make the Whore naked. Her figge-leaue-righteousnesse will not salue her sinne, or hide her shame. Only I cannot but lament, to see many of my brethren, the sonnes of my mother in show, to stand vp to plead for Baal. Is it the symptome of this our age, wherein there is so much learning and so little sound knowledge in the Mysterie of Christ, or wherein the Spirit of the world is so predominant, that men are so tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sported with an vnnaturall zeale and loue to Babylon? <hi>But Wisedome is iustified of her children.</hi> And now I begin to conceiue the reason, why the Iesuites pennes are of late so silent: surely because they see ours so poynant in one anothers sides, while our Mother-Church bleeds for it. But those that be the true Ministers of Christ, will say with S. <hi>Paul, Wee cannot speake any thing against the truth, but for the truth.</hi> Now I could heartily wish, that my brethren of the Ministry would imploy the greater part of their paines in preaching and pressing this maine Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Iustification:</hi> It would be a maine Bulwarke to batter Babels Tower, whereby she would scale heauen with
<pb facs="8"/>
her merits. And for Antichrist, I wonder to see such a deepe silence of him. Doth the Councell of Laterans De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree dare vs, not to mention Antichrists comming? O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise to presse Iesuites with the point of Antichrist, would easily stop their mouthes, while they would put vs to show the vninterrupted lineall pedigree of the Professors of our Religion from the Apostles, all along downeward to <hi>Luther.</hi> Alas, this is but a poore shift to gaine time, and to cause vs to put vp our weapons against them. We can easily descry the pearles of our Religion, strawed all along in the bottome of those muddy streames of Popery. We can disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the starres, which haue giuen light in all ages of the Church, notwithstanding all Romes mysts, labouring to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipse them. And although iniury of time had consumed with fire our particular euidences, yet we finde them regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred in the Court-rowles of Scripture, which no fire, nor moth shall consume.</p>
   <p>But not to detaine you too long in the Porch of this lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger edifice; know Christian Reader, that this poore Worke hath lien by me licensed for the Presse a pretty space. It was borrowed from the interrupted succisiue houres of my Court-attendance. If it displease many, I passe not so much, if it may profite some; and therein shall I prayse God. This is the fruit of all my labour: I seeke no reward, so I may shun reproofe. What can be said in opposition to this truth, or any other by me deliuered, in speciall against the Synagogue of Rome; I shall be ready to maintaine if oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion require, in ampler maner, if I may haue alike liberty with my Antagonists. I say no more for the present, but commend you to God, and to the word of his grace, which is able to build you vp, and to giue you an inheritance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all them which are sanctified.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ, <hi>H. B.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>