<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PRINTER TO
THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119828_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03141</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13270.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119828</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PRINTER TO
THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A coale from the altar. Or, An ansvver to a letter not long since written to the Vicar of Gr : against the placing of the Communion table at the east end of the chancell; and now of late dispersed abroad to the disturbance of the Church. First sent by a iudicious and learned divine for the satisfaction of his private friend; and by him commended to the presse, for the benefit of others</title>
                 <author>Heylyn, Peter</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 78 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PRINTER TO
THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am to advertise thee, good
Reader, of some certaine
things, for thy better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding
of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise.
First, that whereas
thou shalt find here three
severall Characters, Thou wouldst take notice
that the <hi>Roman</hi> is the words of the Author;
the <hi>Itali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>k,</hi> matter of Distinction, partly, but
principally of Quotation by him used; and that
the <hi>English</hi> letter doth exhibit to thee, the
words and periods of the Epistle, or Discourse
which is here confuted. Secondly, that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever
the Letter by him here replyed unto, be
scattered up and downe, and in divers hands;
Yet because possiblie, the Copie of the same hath
<pb facs="3"/>
not hitherto been seene of all, who may chance
cast their eyes upon this Treatise; and partly,
that the world may see, that hee hath dealt tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
with the <hi>Epistoler,</hi> and not omitted any Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument
or Autority by him produced; The
very Letter it selfe is herewith Printed, and
bound together with it, though it bee <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crypha.</hi>
Last of all, I must let thee know, that
whereas the <hi>Acts and Monuments,</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
called the <hi>Booke of Martyrs,</hi> being a
Booke which the <hi>Epistoler</hi> makes much use of,
is of a different Edition in the reply, from that
which is so often cited in the Letter; and that
there have beene many Editions of the same:
That which the Author deales in, is the last
Edition, Printed at <hi>LONDON</hi> in three
volumes, <hi>Anno</hi> 1631. I have no more to
say unto thee, but wish thee good luck in the
name of the Lord; And so adieu.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>