<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the friendly Readers, both Gen∣tlemen and Gentlewomen, Wealth and Welfare.</title>
           <author>W., G.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119821_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15035</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25338</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119821</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the friendly Readers, both Gen∣tlemen and Gentlewomen, Wealth and Welfare.</title>
                 <author>W., G.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Aurelia. The paragon of pleasure and princely delights : contayning the seuen dayes solace (in Christmas holy-dayes) of Madona Aurelia, Queene of the Christmas pastimes, &amp; sundry other well-courted gentlemen, and gentlewomen, in a noble gentlemans pallace. A worke most sweetely intercoursed (in ciuill and friendly disputations) with many amorous and pleasant discourses, to delight the reader: and plentifully garnished with morall notes, to make it profitable to the regarder. By G.W. Gent</title>
                 <author>Whetstone, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>168 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_readers">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the friendly Readers, both Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and Gentlewomen, Wealth and Welfare.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entlemen &amp; Gentlewomē, I present you here (as I think) a profitable vnpolished labor: For, he that is the <hi>Trouchman</hi> of a strangers toung, may wel declare his meaning, but yet shall marre the grace of his Tale: And therefore, <hi>Themistocles</hi> the noble Captayne and Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sopher of <hi>Athens,</hi> compareth such forced speeches, to Tapistrie Hangings rowled vp: which being open, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare beatifull: and foulded, reserue their Vertue, but lose their shew: But I expect (somwhat) a better euent, then may an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter, that is bound to a present Reporte: for my Respit hath been sufficient to consider of <hi>Segnior Philoxenus,</hi> and his honourable companies vertues: and (least by rash acquital of their fauours, I should doe iniurie to their reputation) I haue with well aduised Iudgement, bethought me of such memorable Questions and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices, as I heard and saw presented, in this most noble Italian Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemans Pallace, the Christmas past: and answerable to my weake capacitie, haue exposed the same, in such sorte, as if you be not too curious, may delight and content you: and if not too carelesse, may direct and benefite you: And to satisfie you herein, I giue you friendly knowlehge, that <hi>Segnior Philoxenus</hi> reuerent regarde of the Queenes Maiesties high vertues, is a president for you; with a dutiful, and vnfayned heart, to loue, feare, and obey her Highnesse, from whom, next vnder God, you receiue such blessings, as throgh the whole world her excellencie is renowmed, and your prosperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie enuied. By this noble Gentlemans ciuill entertainement of straungers, you may perceiue with what Garland, Courtesie is principall, crowned: By the ciuill behauiours of <hi>Soranso, Dondolo, Bargetto,</hi> and other Gentlemen herein named, you haue a Presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of gouernment, which will commend you: and by well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding their speeches, you shal finde a discreet methode of talke, meete for you Gentlemen. The like benefite, shall Gentlewomen receiue in imitating of <hi>Madona Aurelia,</hi> (Queene of the Christ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas pleasures) <hi>Maria Beloch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, Lucia Bella, Franceschina Sancta,</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>and the rest of the well qualited Gentlewomen. Besides, a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of other Moral documents, needful reprehensions, and wittie sayings, to perfect the commendation both of a Gentleman and Gentlewoman. (Courteous Gentlemen and Gentlewomen) you haue here the honorable institution of Mariage, so perfectly Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomed, as a very weake iudgement may see the causes, which make housholde quarrels to resemble Hell. Agayne, the man which is willing to liue happily, may here learne such directions and lawes, as will change his priuate house into a Paradise on earth. If ciuil &amp; Moral pleasures, with al these benefites, may make you entertayne this booke, and report wel of the Author, I assure you, you shalbe pleased, and I satisfied. But if you make your tongue enemie to your owne reputation, you may detract, but not reproch the work: Iniure, but not hurt the writer, for both will liue, and laugh such Calumniators to scorne, when either are ready to doe the discreete Reader seruice.</p>
   <p>Some wil (perchance more of enuy to heare a stranger com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, then of pitie to bemone my hard fortune, or fowle vsage) say, I haue as iust cause to complaine of iniuries receiued at <hi>Roane, Rome,</hi> and <hi>Naples,</hi> as to commend the vertues and good entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt of <hi>Segnior Philoxenus:</hi> But to giue such suggestioners a double good example, both of patience and thankfulnesse: I here protest, that as these iniuries begunne, with my hard fortune, so they ended no wayes in my discredite: And as I forgiue the causes of my mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, so scorne I to recount them, to receiue amends, in a little pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. But for that they, and all such as view my reporte, may learne of me to be gratefull for receiued benefites: I make it knowen, that this trauel is <hi>Segnior Philoxenus</hi> due: And I still his debtor, and so shall remayne during my life: reseruing a good affection, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow on such as receiue his Vertues: and my paynes to profite and commend themselues. And in my opinion, it is iust they doe so: Wherefore, to giue a disgrace to ceremonies, Gentlemen and Gentlewomen, I end: as I hope to finde you friendly.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your assured friend, G. W.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>