<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Lee, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119736_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15011</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25315</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119736</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Lee, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A pithie, short, and methodicall opening of the Ten commandements. By Master William Whately, preacher of the word of God at Banburie in Oxford-shire</title>
                 <author>Whately, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Greene, Leonard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Pavier, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 256 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere is for thee (Christian friend) Gods sacred and pure Law, perspicuously and orderly vnfolded, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of those glorious beams more now then euer enlarged, though we haue many that haue done excellently. For in this short and pithie Treatise, if thou pleasest seriously to be acquainted with it, as also make an holy vse of it, there will issue three blessed benefits of speciall and weighty importance.</p>
   <p>First, hereby thou maist more clearely know thy selfe, and discouer thy cold faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, thy leane and idle seruices, and croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb facs="3"/>
disposition, and that snakie brood of sinne that lurketh in thy euer-vitious na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: for it is the Lawes office to detect sin, as a looking glasse to bewray spots, and as the Sunne to discouer euen little motes. Whence is it men see not their misled liues, but because they are vndisciplin'd in the Lords walkes? Can there be a worke of greater consequence then a large opening of these holy rules, which although the full splendor thereof is reserued for the glory aboue, yet open thine eyes to the blessed brightnesse which shines out of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, to discouer thy darke ignorance, thy infidelitie and stubborne pride, how rich thou art in follie, how poore in grace, and how conscience hitherto hath beene sealed with a cursed brand: here wee may be sad spectators of our froward way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnesse, our wandring and groueling thoughts, our barren memories, our raging discontented passions, and dull edg'd lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den affections, yea the disorder of the whole man, turning face to Satan and backe to God.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>Secondly, it lends powerfull aide in the seruices and worships of God. This will bring thee with a hunger-bitten soule and heauy heart to behold the Lords shining face in the preaching of the word, and bends thy will to it with absolute yeelding. This is a notable touch-stone to try thy selfe to the heart root when thou art to receiue that sacramentall meat, and will furnish thee with much store and varietie for prayer. Wouldst thou confesse against thy selfe? behold here a large field: Or wouldst begge graces of God? see here a sampler: here is matter for meditation, for Christian parlees; this will enable thee to catechize and instruct thy familie, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightens thy vnderstanding in reading the Scriptures, and for dayes of humiliation, times of pretious worth with Gods people; this worke thorowly lookt into, shall cause thee to fall out with thy selfe, and shall send thee with penitent eyes to bewaile thy wretched estate, and powre out thy soule into the bosome of Christ, and will put such marrow and strength into thee, that
<pb facs="4"/>
humbly and hotly thou maist wrastle with God.</p>
   <p>Lastly, this shall direct all thy paths, and wisely conduct thee through this thornie life; it will cause thee thinke well, speake well, and liue well, and furnisheth thee with knowledge, faith in God, humble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectednesse, spirituall wisdome, a well tuned conscience, a stooping will, heauenly thoughts, a right fraught memorie, and ranks in order thy loue, feare, ioy, confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and all the rest of those subordinate faculties of the soule, bending them to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue what is good, and stand stifly armed against euery euill. And as for being vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spotted of the world, and to liue vnblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, wronging neither thy selfe, nor any man, in soule, bodie, estate, name, or place, take this booke for thy counsellor. Feast thine eyes then with a subiect necessarily vsefull, and so exactly compiled, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but winne esteeme with euery knowing man and gratious heart. For I must tell thee, diuers friends of exquisite iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hearing that this worke was in my
<pb facs="4"/>
hand, did earnestly sollicite me to turne it to common good. Amongst the rest, a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned worthy vnderstanding Diuine, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster R. Bolton,</hi> hauing perused it, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended it vnto mee in these termes: <hi>Me thinkes, in short and little roome, it opens &amp; represents the marrow and mysteries of that adored depth, the banks and bottome whereof, no wit of man shall euer be able fully to fathom and comprehend, while the world lasts, with more cleare, exact, and compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dexteritie, then I haue discouered in others, though they haue also done ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently.</hi> And he perswaded with the Author, and since also with me, to let it passe abroad more publikely. Let then the more then ordinarie parts of the workman, and of such as haue commended it, as also the great paines of our pen-man, who hath told me, he had a long haruest for this hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of corne, together with the pretiousnes of the subiect, and the goodly meeds thou maist gaine by it, let these perswade thee to read it, and that vnpartially: In the meane
<pb facs="5"/>
time, my prayer and hearty desire is, that thou maist right plentifully prosper by it, and so I rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From</hi> Blaston
<date>
            <hi>4. of</hi> Septemb.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord Iesus, RICHARD LEE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>