<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all the wanton youths of England: Robert Greene wisheth refor∣mation of wilfulnes.</title>
           <author>G., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119749_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02166</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12306</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119749</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all the wanton youths of England: Robert Greene wisheth refor∣mation of wilfulnes.</title>
                 <author>G., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The repentance of Robert Greene Maister of Artes. Wherein by himselfe is laid open his loose life, with the manner of his death</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Danter, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Burby, Cuthbert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To all the wanton youths of England: <hi>Robert Greene</hi> wisheth refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of wilfulnes.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I consider (kinde Cuntrimen) that youth is like to the spring time of mans age readie in the bloome to be nipped with eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie misfortune, and that a yong man is like to a tender plant, apt to be wrested by nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture either to good or euill, as his friendes like good Gardeners shall with care indeuour his education, seeing in the prime of our yeares vice is most ready to creepe in, and that want of experience committeth sundrie wanton desires, I thoght good to lay before you a president of such preiudiciall inconueniences, which at the first seeming sweete vnto youth, at the last growe into fruits of bitter repentance: For a yong man led on by selfe will (hauing the raines of libertie in his owne hand) foreseeth not the ruth of follie, but aimeth at present pleasures, for he giues himselfe vp to delight, and thinketh euerie thing good, honest; lawfull and vertuous, that fitteth for the content of his lasciuious humour: hee foreseeth not that such as clime hastely, fall sodainely: that Bees haue stings as well as honie: that vices haue ill endes as well as sweete beginnings: and whereof growes this heedles life, but of
<pb facs="4"/>
selfe conceit, thinking the good counsell of age is dotage: that the aduice of friends proceeds of enuie, and not of loue: that when their fathers correct them for their faults, they hate them: whereas when the blacke Oxe hath trod on their feete, and the Crowes foote is seene in their eies, then toucht with the feeling of their owne follie, they sigh out had I wist, when repentance commeth too late. Or like as waxe is ready to receiue euerie newe fourme, that is stamped into it, so is youth apt to admit of euery vice that is obiected vnto it, and in young yeares wanton desires is cheefely predominate especiallie the two Ringleaders of all other mischiefes, namely pride and whoredome, these are the Syrens that with their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanting melodies, drawe them on to vtter confusion, for after a young man hath suckt in that sinne of pride, hee groweth into contempt, and as he increaseth prowde in his attyre, so he is scornfull in his lookes, and disdaines the wholsome admonition of his honest freends, whose aduice he supposeth to be doone of malice, and therefore estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth his owne waies best, and had rather hazard his life, than to loose an intch of his credit. Pride is like to fier, that will die and goe out if it bee not maintained with fewell, and yet lay on neuer so bigge logges, it consumes them all to ashes, so pride craues maintenance, or els it will fade: and had a young man neuer so great reuenues, pride at last will reduce it to begger you, for it is such a sinne, as once got into the boane it will step into the flesh, he that once ietteth in his brauerie: if he haue no meanes to maintaine it, it will leaue no bad course of life vnat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, but hee will haue corners to vphold his follie. Heereof growes coossenages, thefts, murthers, and a thousand other pettie mischiefes, and causes many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb facs="4"/>
persons to bee trust vp at the gallowes, purchasing thereby infamy to themselues, and hart breaking sorrow to their friends and parents for euer.</p>
   <p>Companion to this vice, is lust and lecherie, which is the viper, whose venome is incurable, and the onely sinne that in this life leadeth vnto shame, and after death vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell fire: for he that giueth himselfe ouer to harlots, selleth his soule to destruction, and maketh his bodie sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to all incurable diseases. These two vices do not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie waste a mans substance, but also consumeth his bodie and soule, and maketh him attempt to do any mischiefe for his maintenance therein. If happely the young man hath any grace, and is loth to take any vnlawfull wayes, the ordinary course of his copesmates, is straight to call him coward, and cast him out of their fauour, or els by svveete persvvasions and flattering vvordes, make him forsake God and all good meanes of life vvhatsoeuer: this is the manner, life, and course of such as vvill not listen to the graue aduice of their parents, but seeke ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to bring their graie haires vvith greefe vnto theyr graues.</p>
   <p>This ensuing discourse, gentle Reader, dooth lay open the graceles endeuours of my selfe, vvho although I vvere for a long time giuen ouer to the lust of my ovvn hart, yet in the end, Gods grace did so fauourablie worke in me, that I trust heerein thou shalt perceiue my true and vnfained repentance. Accept it in good part, and if it may profit anie I haue my desire.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Farewell,</hi>
R. G.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>