<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE GODLY READER, GRACE, MERCY, and Peace from God the Father, &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119158_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01737</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1187</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119158</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE GODLY READER, GRACE, MERCY, and Peace from God the Father, &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The stewards last account : Deliuered in fiue sermons vpon the sixteenth chapter of the gospell by Saint Luke, the first and second verses. By Robert Bagnall, Minister of the Word of God, at Hutton in Somersetshire</title>
                 <author>Bagnall, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Clarke, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 86, 79-99, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE GODLY READER, GRACE, MERCY, and Peace from God the Father, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in the contriuing, managing, and bringing to good effect worldly busines<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses that tend to the maintenance of the body in this present life, we account op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie of time, and fit occasions, the greatest furtherers; and losse of time, the greatest hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers: and therefore in euery thing, wee take the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test time; as in planting, sowing, gathering in the fruits of the earth, and all other affaires: So nothing doth more helpe in the course of Piety, and further our iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to eternall life, then to be vigilant and carefull, to take all times and occasions to serue God, and to let no time passe away vnprofitable. For time hasteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and tarrieth for no man, and foolishly spent, cannot be recalled: And therefore the Heathens painted out Time with wings at her hands, and also at her feet, with a locke of haire before, but bald behinde. This velocitie of time, and irrecuperablenesse of her being carelessely and idly let slip, <hi>Bernard</hi> laid downe to his Schollers,
<pb facs="5"/> when hee said:<note place="margin">Bern. ad Scho.</note>
      <hi>Volat tempus irreuocabile, volat tempus irremeabile, nec aduertit insipiens quid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittat, &amp;c.</hi> that is, Time flyeth away, that cannot bee recalled; Time flyeth away, that cannot come againe, and foolish man doth not consider what he loseth: and yet (alas) hee loseth all the good vse of time, and all the benefit that hee might make of the same, when it offereth it selfe.<note place="margin">Basil.</note> And therefore <hi>Basil</hi> well said: <hi>Nemo vsum temporis habere queat, nisi quis cum se of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert, arripiat:</hi> that is, no man can receiue any profit of Time, but he that speedily layeth hold on it, when it offereth it selfe. Let the parabolicall example of the ten Virgins teach and admonish vs herein, and make vs take <hi>Bildad</hi> the Shuhites counsell: Early to seeke the Lord, and seeke him while he may be found, and speedily to goe about the Lords businesse,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.</note> as the Cherubims did, and therefore were pourtraied with wings before the place where the Israelites prayed. O good Christian Reader, consider, I beseech thee, what a foolish thing it is for thee, to let time passe away securely, to let thy rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>konings runne so long without any examination of thy life, and doings, and without calling thy wayes to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, that thou shouldest be growne obdurate, past sense and feeling, yea, and so forgetfull of thy dealings, that thou canst not bring in a true reckoning.</p>
   <p>Consider this in time, and call thine owne wayes to remembrance, sleepe no longer in securitie; but be sober and watch, that thou maist not bee called to account when thou thinkest not thereof, and be found false there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and so he proued and conuicted a false Steward. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie will bring thee to extremities, and to all these
<pb facs="5"/> distresses, as it did the people in <hi>Noah</hi> his time, in <hi>Lots</hi> time, and many other people in all ages, and so it will doe many at the last audit. Therefore let me beseech thee; yea, and perswade thee by the tender mercies of God, to suffer mee to pull thee backe by the sleeue from running into the pit of perdition, haue thy bookes of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in a readinesse, be a vigilant and watchfull Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, that at the last Day it may be said vnto thee, <hi>O well done, thou good and faithfull Seruant, thou hast been faithfull ouer few things, I will make thee Ruler ouer many things: enter thou into the ioy of thy Lord.</hi> I haue (good Christian Reader) bestowed my small skill and labour in this Treatise, to make thee a good Steward and accountant at the last audit and Generall Assize. I pray thee reade the same, not with a preiudicate opinion, but with a yeelding resolution to the truth, as thou shalt finde it, and perswade thy selfe that this is written (howsoeuer it may crosse thy humours in taking thy fleshly pleasures) yet for thy learning, and to doe thee good, and to set thee in the way to Heauen, in the which way God speed thee with faithfulnesse and constancie to the end, and then thou shalt be sure of thy wished desire, a crowne of incorruptible glory: Which God of his infinite goodnesse and mercy grant mee, and thee, and the whole Church quickly. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>