<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE
to the Catholike Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119803_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09105</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19411</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119803</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE
to the Catholike Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A manifestation of the great folly and bad spirit of certayne in England calling themselues secular priestes : VVho set forth dayly most infamous and contumelious libels against worthy men of their owne religion, and diuers of them their lawful superiors, of which libels sundry are heer examined and refuted. By priestes lyuing in obedience</title>
                 <author>Parsons, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Conincx, Arnout</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 114 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE
to the Catholike Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>VCH against our wils were we forced these dayes
past (deare Catholike reader) to interrupt the
course of our peaceable priestly labors, and to enter
into a certayne contention and warre of wryting,
not so much against the comon enemy of our reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
(for that had byn comfortable) as against our
owne tumultuous brethren, in defence of order,
iustice, and innocency, and of the lawful authority of our Superiors
intemperatly impugned by them, which defence we called, <hi>an Apologie
of the English Catholike Ecclesiastical Hierarchy, &amp;c.</hi> endeauoring therin so to
temper the style of our wryting, as migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> be somewhat answerable to
the grauity of the subiect, &amp; yet exasperate no further the impugner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
then the necessary opening of the truth of matters should meerly
force vs vnto; and this we hope that euery indifferent Reader wil haue
considered, and be ready to beare vs witnesse.</p>
   <p>And this office being once performed for the true information of
those that desyre to knowe how matters had passed, our meaning was
to go no further in this contention but to returne to our reposed lyfe
againe, and so our hope was, that we might, but alas we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> prooue
the contrary,<note place="margin">Plut. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Sy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos.</note> and that as a graue author saith: <hi>facilior est ortus, quam exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus
rix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rum,</hi> the beginning of braulings is easyer then the ending,
especially when the passions wheron they are grounded, be inward
and permanent, as in our case it seemeth to stand, the ground of al
these contentions appearing euidently, to be enuy and emulation,
fostered by ambition, anger, reuenge and other such Assistants, which
how perilous and pernicious counselors they be to continue debate,
rancor, and malice, and to bring all to perdition that harken vnto
them, were ouerlong to recyte out of holy mens wrytings, yet can I
not omit the saying of an old Saint, <hi>Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mmo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> the Anachorite recoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
by <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Cassia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>us</hi> almost twelue hundred yeares pas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>; his speech
is this:</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Sciendum sanè est i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>idiae morbu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> difficilius ad medel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>tera vitia per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duci,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cassian. col. 18 Cap. 17.</note>
      <hi>nam eum, quem semel veneni sui peste corruperit, penè dixerim carere reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio:
ipsa nam{que} est lues de qua figuraliter dicitur per prophetam: Ecce ego mittam
vobis serpentes regulos quibus non est incantatio, &amp; mordeb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nt vos, &amp;c.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hier. 2.</note>
      <q>Yow must know that the sicknesse of enuy is cured more hardly then other vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
in so much that when any man is infected with this venome, I
may almost say, that he is irremediable, seing this infectiō is that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
God speaketh of by <hi>Hieromie</hi> the prophet figuratiuely: <hi>Behould I vvil
send vpon yovv deadly serpents, against vvhome no inchauntment shal preuayle, &amp;
they shal byte yovv, &amp;c.</hi>
      </q> Thus beginneth he his treatese of this matter,
wherin for that diuers things are most excellently spoken by him fit
to our purpose, and easy to be applyed to the present state of our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayers,
we think it not amisse to recyte some part therof more at
large: heare then his discourse:</p>
   <q>
      <p>Rightly (saith he) is the byting of enuy compared by the prophet
to the venemous stinging of a deadly basiliske serpent, wherby the
first poysoned serpent of all others, yea the author and inuentor of all
poyson (the diuel) was both slayne and slue. For first by enuy he slue
himself, &amp; afterward him whome he enuyed, to wit our first parent,<note place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. 2.</note>
according to the saying of the scripture: <hi>By enuy of the diuel death entred
into the vvorld, &amp;c.</hi> And as he being once deadly infected with this poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
of enuy could neuer after be cured, eyther by the holsome medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine
of pennance or otherwise, but perished eternally: so men that
suffer themselues to be corrupted with the same poyson, and bytings
of enuy; do become incurable, excluding all helpes of holsome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntements
of the holy Ghost against the same.</p>
      <p>The reason wherof is, for that the enuious are not styrred vp to
hate others for any true fault, which they see in them, but rather for
their good parts, vertues and gifts of God, and so being ashamed to
vtter the true causes in deed of their auersion, they pretend other idle
&amp; superfluous external reasons, which being no true causes indeed,
but only fayned, it is but tyme lost to go about to remoue them:
the true causes indeed lying hidden in the bottome of their entral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,
&amp;c. Nay further this pestilence of enuy when it once entreth mās
hart it becometh so incurable, as it is exasperated by faire speech, puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed
vp by humble offices, and styrred to wrath by gyfts &amp; good tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes;<note place="margin">Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. 22. Secundum 70. Into.</note> in so much as <hi>Salomon</hi> saith, <hi>nihil sustinet zelus,</hi> nothing can content
or satisfie emulation; for by how much the party enuyed is eminent
eyther in humility, patience, munificence, or other vertues; the more
potent prickes of enuy hath the enuyer to be styrred vp against
<pb facs="3"/>
him, nor is he satisfied with any thing but with his death or ruine, &amp;c.</p>
      <p>Wherfore so much the more pernicious and incureable is enuy
aboue all other vices, by how much more it is encreased, &amp; nourished
by those very remedyes wherby other synnes are cured and extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished;
as for example: he that is angry with yow for some hurt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued,
if yow recompence him liberally he is content and satisfied:
He that complayneth of an iniury receaued, if yow giue him humble
satisfaction he is pleased againe: But what wil yow do to him who
the more humble and benigne he seeth yow, the more is he offended
to see those vertues in yow? And what seruant of God to satisfie an
enuious man wil leaue of vertue and other good things, wherwith
God hath endewed him? &amp;c.</p>
   </q>
   <p>Thus wryteth that blessed man, and how fully this falleth out in
our affayre, where Gods holy gyfts and vertues themselues are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyed
at, by them that wil not immitate the same, is easy to discerne.
And if no other proof were extant, yet their owne books set forth in
such number and with such passion to discredit their aduersaryes are
sufficient witnesses, wherin they set downe so many high prayses gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
by other men to their said aduersaryes, as albeit the partyes thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues,
do nether chalēge nor acknowledge them, yet is it euidēt, that
the enuy of these and other like prayses hath put these mens mynds
quite out of ioynt. Neyther remayneth there any way (as it seemeth)
for the enuyed in this case to discharge them̄selues of this raging tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest
raysed against them, but eyther to chaunge their laudable course
of lyfe, wherby they haue gotten that esteeme which these men enuy
at: (&amp; this is not tolerable) or for these men to alter their iudgmēts,
and se their owne follyes and passiōs herin, which we shal endeauour
to lay before them in this our treatese, and that out of their owne
bookes and wrytings.</p>
   <p>And albeit we had fully purposed (as before is sayd) to wryte no
more about this argumēt, yer seing so many libels to come our daylie
so false and slaunderous, &amp; so pernicious, not only to Christian vnity
but also to the integrity of Catholike faith &amp; verity, and those vnder
the names of priests, the very honor of priesthood it selfe hath forced
vs to take pen in hand againe (contrary to our former determinatiō)
therby to wipe away (if it be possible) some part of that notorious
discredit, and slaunder which iustly otherwise may fal vpon our whole
order if such intemperate proceedings published in priests names,
should passe vncontrouled by all kynd of priests.</p>
   <p>Wherfore, our entent in this treatese is, to shew that eyther these
<pb facs="4"/>
infamous libels set forth in priests names are not indeed of priests, but
of some other that play their parts, or if they come from priests in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
then must we needs runne, in this matter, to the words of our
Sauiour touching <hi>sal infatuatum</hi> infatuated priests,<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> such as haue lost not
only all sauour of priestly wisdome,<note place="margin">Luc. 14.</note> and shining light of true vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing,
but all true spirit also of Christian priests and priesthood,
which we shal declare by diuers proofes and considerations, takē out
of their owne books, for which cause we haue intituled this treatese.
<hi>A manifestation of the great folly and bad spirit of some in England that call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
secular priestes.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luc. 11.</note> Wherunto we were induced the rather as wel by
those words of S. Paul. alleadged in our first page, <hi>insipientia corum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifesta
erit omnibus:</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.</note> their folly shalbe made manifest to all (speaking of
such as made diuision) as also by that dreadful parable of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour,
concerning the wicked vncleane spirit, that leauing men for a
tyme, and finding no rest abroad returned, and perceauing the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
left by him to be wel cleansed, but not wel fenced, entred
againe with seauen worse spirits then himself, and so made the
ending of those men worse then their beginning.</p>
   <p>It were ouer long, and exceeding the measure of a preface, to set
downe heer, the interpretations and godly considerations of old
ancient Saints about this parable of our Sauiour, especially seing that
for so much as appertayneth to this our affayre, it is not hard for any
man to see the coherence and application therof for that when these
libellers were first made priests (if they be priests) and took that
most sacred order of cleargy vpon them, wherby they weare adopted
into the peculiar choise and seuered portion of almighty God (for so
much importeth Cleargie) they did not only renounce the spirit of
Sathan in general, as men do in baptisme by those words: <hi>ab renuncio
diabolo &amp; omnibus operibus eius, &amp;c.</hi> but particularly also the prophane &amp;
secular spirit of the world, and all corruption and vncleanesse therof
appertayning to libetty of the flesh, by their strait obligation of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stity
deuotion &amp; piety annexed to that holy calling aboue other men,
which prophane and vncleane spirit being once excluded, by the
holy character and vnction of priesthood, and the house made cleane
by the broome of holy pennance, adorned also with graces and gyfts
of the holy Ghost, if after the same spirit returne agayne, and fynd
the guard and defence therof weake by negligence of the keeper, or
the dores broken open by the violence of passions (as in our case,
alas, it seemeth to stand) he presumeth (saith our Sauiour) not only to
enter agayne himself, but to take bad company also with him, to wit
<pb facs="4"/>
seauen other spirits <hi>nequiores se,</hi> more wicked then himself, that is to
say more spiritual malitious, more couert and hidden, more obstinate
and self willed, more opposite to charity, and more like to the diuel
himself, that is a meer spirit, and the head patron and fountayne of
all wicked wilful spirits.</p>
   <p>For albeit the grosse spirit of wordly sensualitie be a foule and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane
spirit (especially in a priest) and be also from the diuel, yet as
<hi>Cassianus</hi> in the former place doth note, and all other Fathers do ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue
in like manner, it is no way so dangerous or wicked as are the
spirits of more spiritual sinnes, to witt enuy, pride, ambition, hatred,
reuenge &amp; other like, which are so counterset and couered poysons,
as often tymes they are not knowne nor held for vices, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
neyther cured nor cared for; nay they passe for vertues, &amp; so
are often tymes taken by the possessors themselues, as for example;
enuy for zeale in Gods cause, pride for corage, ambition for desyre
of ability to do much good, and so in the rest; wherby it cometh to
passe that he whose house is possessed with these most pernicious
guests doth think himself wel furnished, and in good case, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently
neyther endeauoreth to expel them out, nor confesseth his
fault or negligence therin, nor seeketh remedy by the holy refuge of
pennance, good counsel or other spiritual helpes, and herby cometh
it to passe that which our Sauiour saith: <hi>fiunt nouissim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> hominis istiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,
peioraprioribus,</hi> the ending of this man is worse then his begynning.
VVherunto that dreadful commination of the holy Apostle S. Paul.
doth wel agree also, who sayth: (wryting to the Hebrues) <hi>Impossible est
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>os, qui semel sunt illuminati, &amp;c. &amp; prolapsi, rursus renouari ad poenitentiam.</hi>
It is vnpossible for them that are once lightened by Gods grace, and
fal back agayne, to be renewed by pennance.</p>
   <p>Which words howsoeuer we vnderstand them, eyther that the
grace of baptisme is here meant, or the word <hi>impossible,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hebr.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> taken for hard
and rare, euery way, and in all senses, it is a most terrible sentence, &amp;
ought to mooue men greatly, that do see themselues fallen from a
better state to a worse, and from a quiet, calme, sweet, humble &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest
spirit, to a proud, turbulent, ireful, impudent or contemptuous
behauiour towards their brethren or equals, and much more to their
betters and superiors. And this shalbe sufficient by way of Preface.
The rest yow shal discerne by that which is treated in the Chapters
following.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>