<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Master Iones his Prayer before his Sermon.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119135_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04605</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14722</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119135</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Master Iones his Prayer before his Sermon.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Londons looking backe to Ierusalem, or, Gods iudgements vpon others, are to be obserued by vs</title>
                 <author>Jones, John, minister at St. Michael Basenshaw, London</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>7, 5, 50, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prayers</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prayer">
   <pb n="1" facs="4"/>
   <head>Master Iones his Prayer before his Sermon.</head>
   <p>MOst great and glorious Lord God, who by thy Almighty power hast created the Heaven and the Earth, and by thy unsearchable wisdome gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest and guidest the same: we vile and base wretches, that have defiled the Heavens by our sinnes, and cursed the earth by our transgressions, doe prostrate our selves in all humility before the throne of thy Divine Majesty: beseeching thee to looke upon us not in justice, but in mercy; not as we are in our selves, but in the face and coūtenance of thy Sonne Iesus Christ. In our selves we are altogether unworthy to come into thy holy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, to tread upon holy ground, or to meddle with holy things. This day is holy, set apart by thine owne selfe for thine owne holy worship: this place is holy, it is thy owne sanctuary, thy ordinances are holy, &amp; the service in which we are imployed, is a holy service. But we are most vnholy, impure in our very beginnings, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure in our proceedings; all over polluted with sinne: in all the faculties of our soules, in all the members of our bodies: in the notions &amp; imaginations of our minds, in the motions &amp; inclinations of our wils, in the affectiōs and desires of our hearts, in the words of our mouthes, in the workes of our handes: wee are poore, and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and blinde, and naked, high-minded, vaine-min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, worldly-minded, false-hearted, full of hypocrisie, full of security, full of infidelity, wanting in charity, wanting in knowledge, in zeale, intemperance, in patience; deficient in all grace, abundant in all sinne, wee have sinned against all the meanes of grace: thy word, thy Sacraments, thy Sabbaths, thy Christ, thy Spirit; we have sinned against all the times of grace: we have sinned in the times of our childhood, in the times of
<pb facs="5"/>
our youth, and our riper yeares not onely in the times of ignorance, but since wee have knowne thy will: not onely through infirmity, but presumptuously: we have sinned against all thy attributes, we have abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed thy patience, provoked thy anger: we have sinned against thy Iudgements, which should have enforced us to obedience; against thy mercies, which should haue allured us and led us to repentance: wee haue sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned against all thy creatures, against heaven, and against earth: against all thy workes; against the worke of creation, by defacing thy Image; against the worke of thy preseruation, by distrusting thy prouidence: against the worke of redemption, by our infidelity; against thy law, which is the rule of righteousnes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Gospell of grace and saluation; against our vow made unto thee in our baptisme: we haue broken the first vow that ever we made, and never since haue beene faithfull in our promises unto thee: against our owne purposes and promises made unto thee in our prayers, and that before our calling, and since our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: in our generall calling, and in our particuler cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings: we haue failed and sinned since it hath pleased thee of thy free mercy to translate us out of the powers of darknesse into the kingdom of thy deare Sonne. What shall wee doe that haue thus sinned against thee, ô thou preseruer of men? whither shall we goe from thy spirit, or whither shall we sly from thy presence? If we ascend up into heaven, thou art there: if we make our bed in the deepe, thou art there: if wee take the wings of the morning, and dwell in the uttermost parts of the sea, even there shall thy hand finde us. No darkenesse can cover us from thy all-seeing eye, no place can shelter us from thy almighty hand: thy judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments can follow us, and thy vengeance take hold on us whithersoever we goe. What then shall we doe in this perplexity? In all humility wee cast downe our selves before the throne of thy mercy, bewailing our
<pb facs="5"/>
misery, with bleeding hearts and throbbing soules de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring our misery, imploring thy mercy, condemning our selues, confessing our sins; promising, purposing and resoluing with all our hearts to forsake our sinnes. Though we are out of measure sinfull, yet thou art out of measure mercifull: thou art infinite in mercy, and with thee is plenteous redemption. The greater our sins are, the greater shall be the glory of thy mercy, and of thy Sons merits, in forgiving our sinnes, which are so many and so great. Pardon therefore, we pray thee, all our sins past: wash us from them in the pure la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of thy Sons blood. It is not the river <hi>Iordan,</hi> nor all the rivers of <hi>Damascus,</hi> that can cleanse us from our spirituall leprosie: onely thy Son, thine onely Sonne, and that pure fountaine of thy Sonnes blood, which thou hast opened to the house of <hi>David,</hi> and to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Ierusalem</hi> for sin, and for uncleannesse. In that blood we beseech thee to wash us from our sins, from the guilt of sin, from the punishment of sin, from the power of sin, with that blood purge our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences from dead workes, and quicken us by thy Spirit unto a new life, that we may serve thee the true and ever-living God, zealously without feare, univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sally without partiality, sincerely without hypocrisie, constantly without apostacy, in all righteousnesse and true holinesse all the dayes of our liues: that the end of our life may be the end of our faith, which is the salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our soules. And although we are unworthy to pray for our selues, yet in the name of thy Sonne we are bold to enlarge our prayers for thy whole Church, howsoeuer distressed or whersoever dispersed through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the parts of the whole earth. Give thy Gospell a free passage, repaire the ruines of <hi>Sion,</hi> build up the broken walles of <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> and with the breath of thy nostrills blow downe the walls of Iericho. In thy due time put an end to the troubles of the Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. Why withdrawest thou thy hand, even thy
<pb facs="6"/>
right hand; and doest not plucke it out of thy bosome? how long oh Lord, how long wilt thou suffer the blood of thy seruants to be spilt upon the ground? Thou that didst once heare and regard the blood of <hi>Abel,</hi> one man crying for vengeance; wilt thou not heare the blood of many thousands? What advantage canst thou have in giving over thy owne children to the fury of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies? shall thy enemies triumph, and thy children pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish? shall thy enimies reioyce &amp; thy children mourne? shall the light of thy Gospell be eclipsed, the splendour of thy glory obscured, thy temple defiled, thy name dishonoured, thy truth slandered? Are they of Babilon better than they of Sion? or is there any other people that knoweth thee besides Israel? or what generation hath so beleeued thy couenant as <hi>Iacob?</hi> Arise then oh Lord, arise, plead thy owne cause, honour thy owne name, defend thy owne altar, fight thy owne battaile, protect thy owne people: behold the pride of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and send thy wrath upon their heads: throw downe the forces of all them that haue purposed cruel things against thy Sanctuary, against the top of Sion, thy hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed house, the place where thine honour dwelleth. Make every nation to acknowledge that thou art the God of all power, that there is none other that protects thy Church and truth but thou onely. Protect thy Church and truth among us, and all that thou hast pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in authority over us; especially his sacred Maiesty, <hi>Charles,</hi> by thy gracious providence King of great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, France and Ireland defender of the true, ancient, Catholick Apostolick faith, and in all causes, and over all persons, as well Ecclesiasticall as civill, next under thee and thy Sonne Christ, supreme governour. Blesse we beseech thee his royall consort Queene <hi>Mary:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeching thee that with Mary shee may chuse the better thing that cannot be taken from her. Blesse the present pledges of our succeeeding hopes, Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> with lady <hi>Mary</hi> his sister. O Lord grant that as they grow in
<pb facs="6"/>
yeares, so they may grow in grace and favour with thee and with men. Blesse the rest of the Royall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genie beyond the scaes, the Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> with her princely issue, when thou seemest best, settle them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, in their former inheritance, that they may be nursing Fathers and mothers unto thy Church. Blesse the Right Honorable the privie Councel, the true hearted Nobility and Gentrie of our Land, the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Iudges, all vnto whom thou hast committed the sword of iustice, all Ministers vnto whom thou hast committed the sword of the spirit, what names or titles soever distinguished; whether Archbishops Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, or inferiour Pastors. And that there may be a continuall supply of able men to governe both in Church and common wealth, blesse all nurseries of good learning, especially the two famous Vniversi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of this Land, Cambridge and Oxford, water the young plants that are in both of them, with the dew of thy grace that they may grow vp as Cedars in Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banon for the building of Sion. And comfort all that are comfortlesse oh thou Father of comfort, and God of all consolation, visite the sicke, strengthen the weake, heale the wounded, bind vp the broken hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, gather the dispersed redeeme them that are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thralled, releeue them that are impoverished, succour them that are tempted, restore them that are fallen by infirmitie, and establish them that stand by thy free spirit. Finally, giue a blessing we pray thee, to this our meeting, in this thy house vpon this thy day: to speake and to heare thy holy word, O Lord God I am a child, and cannot speake, I am of polluted lipes, and slow of speech, but thou art he that canst giue sight to the blind, and speech to the dumbe, therefore untie the strings of my stamering tongue, and touch it with a coale from thine alter, my doctrine shall drop as doth the raine and as the dew vpon the grasse. And for this thy people, touch their eares and their hearts
<pb facs="7"/>
with the finger of thy blessed spirit that they may heare thy word attentiuely, conceiue it rightly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it readily, apply it wisely; treasure it upon their memories, faithfully practise it, in their life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versations conscionably so all our vnderstandings may be enlightned, our hearts purified, our conscience spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, our sinfull liues reformed and our soules saved yea, the whole man at length glorified in the land of the living. And that in and through thy deare soone, our onely Saviour Iesus Christ, in whose name and words, we pray: Our Father &amp;c.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>