<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN EXAMINATION OF Censures contained in two Tables sett before booke entituled The Defence of, &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119896_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15134</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25433</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119896</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN EXAMINATION OF Censures contained in two Tables sett before booke entituled The Defence of, &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An examination of M. Doctor VVhytgiftes censures, contained in tvvo tables, sett before his booke, entituled The defence of the aunswer to the admonition, &amp;c</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>—Puritan</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>53, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="examination">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>AN EXAMINATION OF Censures contained in two Tables sett before booke entituled The Defence of, &amp;c.</head>
   <head type="sub">THE EXAMINER TO HIS FREIND IN CHRIST IESVS.</head>
   <p>YOVR importunitie rather then any other Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hathe moued me to yelde vnto your request. For what am I, that I should take vpon me to be an Arbiter betwen two so renoumned Clarkes? You knowe a great nomber I am suer, bothe wyse and learned, whiche fauor the cause of reformation, that might better satisfie you with ther learned iudgment, then I can pleas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> you with my simple opinion. Beside this, it is not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyse lyklie, but that T. C. (if God spare hym lyfe) will make answer in his owne defence, as one that knoweth his owne mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge best As for me, I can but coniecture, howe an indifferent man without affection vnto ether partie, or desire of cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>tion mighte reasonablie and charitablie Iudge of those matters, sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed by M Doctor Whytgifte to be daungerous pilates of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, or falsifications and vntruthes Howe be yt in one thinge, I can not but thinke as you doe, that M W. in premisinge these-two tables in the first face of his treatise, and after placing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> them in the beginninge of his booke, hathe vsed a very preiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall pollicie. For his volume beinge so large, his style so vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasant, and his matter for the most<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> part suche, as no man without greate pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ience, can abide to reade him ouer, although he fauour his cause neuer so muche: he might well thinke, that as he sholde haue many curious vewers of the first leafe: so he sholde haue fewe diligent readers vnto the last ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> this polycye were commendable, but that diuine matters require to be handeled rather with sinceritie, then with sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>litie, For suche defacinge of the aduersarie maye perhaps procure a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lamation, but a stronge defence of the cause obtaineth a suer victorie. And therefore M. W. (in myne opinion) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> haue done better, to the furderiage of his purpose, yf on s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>de of these two Tables of Daungerous poyntes, and vntruthes, that tende to none other ende, but to deface his aduersarie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>: he had made one Table of short and sounde arguments whereby ether his cause wer confyrmed, or the contrary confuted. For in so doinge, aswell his plaine dealinge, as the strength of his cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>, shoulde haue clearly appeared to all men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. But as he hath omitted, that so I will let it passe, and shew you what I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of euery one of his Censures seuerallie.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>