<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PREFACE, DE∣CLARING ALL SVCH MATTERS AS ARE TO BE handled and treated of, within this present hooke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119146_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14460</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24775</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119146</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PREFACE, DE∣CLARING ALL SVCH MATTERS AS ARE TO BE handled and treated of, within this present hooke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The cauteles, canon, and ceremonies, of the most blasphemous, abhominable, and monstrous popish Masse : Togither, the Masse intituled of the body of Iesus Christ. Fully and wholy set downe, both in Latine and Englishe, the Latine faithfully taken out of the Masse booke after the romishe vse. Imprinted at Lyons by Iohn Cambray, in the yeare a thowsand fiue hu [n] dred and twenty, the title whereof hereafter ensueth on the next page. With certaine annotations for the vnderstanding of the text, set forth by that godly and learned minister in the Church of God Peter Viret, and translated out of French into English by Tho. Sto. Gent</title>
                 <author>Viret, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 <publisher>Maunsell (Mansell), Andrew 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Vautrollier, Thomas 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 156, that is 256 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>A PREFACE, DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CLARING ALL SVCH MATTERS AS ARE TO BE <hi>handled and treated of, within this present hooke.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>ITH we are now growne to an end of that Cronicle which wee were determined to make, concerning the Actes and deeds of Popes, whereby their holinesse, &amp; the rest of their ordinances, may the better be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned and iudged: I haue not thought it amisse to make some discourse of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons and decrees made and established in the Councelles which haue bene solemnelie helde from the Apostles time, euen vnto this present. I meane of the Canons &amp; decrees, which touch those matters that we nowe intend to treat of. Howbeit there are manie causes which giue me occasion, at this time not to deal with thē. The first is, for that I fear the book will grow to be ouer great, as I see it fal out by another booke of mine, which I tooke in hand intituled, <hi>Of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and conference of the Supper of the Lorde, and the Masse:</hi> Albeit I did at that time cut of manie thinges, which might verie well haue bene set foorth. The other is, That a great part of the Decrees and Canons of the Councelles appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to that matter which we presentlie are to treate of, are attributed to the Romish Bishops, &amp; especiallie to those who at that time enioyed that sea, wherein, those Councels were solemnized. And therefore the greater part of them hath alreadie bene published and set abrode. Moreouer I do also consider, that these Canons and decrees which are as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed vnto the ancient Councelles, are often alotted vnto them vnder a false title, as manie other ordinances also are attributed to manie auncient Romish Bishops, who neuer
<pb facs="4"/>once thought of them: and were falslie collected euen by the very selfe same men which vpheld the Popish sea, &amp; all the abuses and superstitions that euer were brought into Christendome. Wherefore, it is most necessarie, that when anie Councelles are spoken of, that they which reade thē call to mind that, which we haue spoken of, in our other booke, concerning the witnesses by vs produced, for the setting downe of those ordinances attributed to Popes, of whom we haue made mention. For therein is likewise com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted great leasings, by the reason of the knowledge and practise of a great number of false witnesses by whom Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ hath serued his owne turne, that by them he might obtaine a glorious glittering shewe vnto his false religion &amp; tyrannie, and chieflie vnder the title of antiquitie and aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Councelles: vnder which colour, the Suppostes of the Romish Church labour with tooth and naile, to quench the truth and word of the Lord. And therefore it is verie requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site that the matter be well looked vnto. For, as wee must not lightly contemne the authoritie of the lawfull &amp; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Councelles: euen so likewise we must be well aduised how we allow vnlawfull Councelles, for lawfull, and that er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, superstitions, and heresies, be not allowed &amp; receaued vnder the colour of Christian Councelles. And besides, we must also vnderstand thus much, That there was neuer any Councell so pure &amp; Christian like sithens the Apostles time wherein som chaffe hath not bene mixed with the Corne, yea, &amp; some notable beginning of superstition also: by which meane Antichrist soone after, hath not gotten some mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to build an house for his raigne, and to work his secrete iniquitie withall. Wherefore, we are with very sound iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to reade, whatsoeuer is set downe vnto vs vnder the name of Councelles and auncient Fathers, and not lightlie approue any thing, vntill such time as we haue thoroughly examined the cause by the prescript rule of Gods word. For which causes I haue purposlie set downe this aduertisement, as well by reason of the Cannons and decrees which haue hertofore sometimes bene alleaged, vnder the name of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Councelles, as also (if neede were) for those, which hereafter might be alleaged for the declaration, and anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations
<pb facs="4"/>which we haue yet to make, as well vpon the Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telles or instructions, as vpon the forme and manner of the Masse, which we are now in hand to go on withall. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we wold be glad to obserue the best order that might be, we will beginne at the Instruction which the Priestes in their Masse bookes call, <hi>The Cautelles of the Masse:</hi> Because they are taught by them, those things which he is to obserue that meaneth to say Masse, and of the dangers which therin might fall out: as may very well be discerned by the reading of them. And therefore by a barbarous word they call them <hi>Cautelles,</hi> chieslie by reason of the sense, which they meane to take at it, signifying thereby, that euerie Priest must take good heede vnto that which is set downe in them: although in verie deede this word <hi>Cautell,</hi> properly signifieth nothing else, but falshood and deceipt. Wherefore, they them selues speake more likely and truly in this behalfe then they think: considering, that whatsoeuer is in their Masse, is nothing else but mere trumperie and deceipt, and a common sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of all Christian people. And in verie deede, I haue set them foorth after the selfe same maner and forme, as they are set downe in their Popish Masse booke, which title is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie in the beginning of this booke proposed and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie translated: to the end that euery man might the better vnderstand, the notable follies and horrible abhominations which are in the Masse, and in all those which celebrate the same, and are at it. And for the better helping of the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing of the Readers, I haue added thereto certaine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions &amp; annotations, to make the matters more plaine. Howbeit, I am to beseech the Readers, not to be lightly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at them, although they seeme very grosse &amp; strange Because I am to make them agree with the text, which is to be declared: and is in verie trueth worthy the glose which shall be giuen thereto: which shal not be a glose of Orleāce, contrarie to the text, but neat and pure, and of it selfe. And to the end that euery iot therof might be the better vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood, I haue deuided the matters into Chapters: &amp; besides, haue set downe the annotations of euerie of them in order, one after another: and marked by the Alphabet and cifers
<pb facs="5"/>euerie annotation, according as the letters are marked in the text, to the end it might be the better vnderstood, vnto what place euerie of them is to be referred.</p>
   <p>
      <figure>
         <figDesc>decorative device featuring initials of printer, T.V.</figDesc>
         <p>T V</p>
      </figure>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>