<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE GODLY READER, WHETHER MINISTER, OR PRI∣VATE CHRISTIAN.</title>
           <author>C., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119430_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03342</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13462</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119430</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE GODLY READER, WHETHER MINISTER, OR PRI∣VATE CHRISTIAN.</title>
                 <author>C., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>CVIII lectures vpon the fourth of Iohn : Preached at Ashby-Delazouch in Leicester-shire. By that late faithfull and worthy minister of Iesus Christ. Arthur Hildersam</title>
                 <author>Hildersam, Arthur</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Brewster (Bruster), Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 52, 51-351, 358-500 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE GODLY READER, WHETHER <hi>MINISTER,</hi> OR PRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VATE CHRISTIAN.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Booke which now at the length, the good hand of God hath put into thy hand to reade, deserueth a name in this kinde of writing (to speake freely and at once, what I truly iudge) like one of the chiefe of <hi>Dauids</hi> Worthies, <hi>not amongst the thirty, but amongst the first three.</hi> In reading most of the best Bookes extant, the studious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is wont to select and transcribe the pith of such Notes, as stand like Lights, or Goades, or Nailes, in the body of the discourse, and in the Spirit of the Writer: But in this Booke (to tell you what I find) I find such variety of choice matter running throughout euery Veine of each discourse herein handled, and carried along with such strength of sound and deepe Iudgement, and with such Life and Power of an heauenly Spirit, and withall expressed in such pithy and pregnant words of wisdome, that I knew not what to select, and what to omit, vnlesse I should haue transcribed the whole Booke.</p>
   <p>In the Authors manner of handling this Scripture, Ministers shall obserue a double excellency: <hi>i. e.</hi> An exemplary Patterne of Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching in the euidence of the Spirit. The euidence of the Spirit is shewen in discouering the hidden Treasures of the Graces of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, partly breathing in the Scriptures (which he either handleth of purpose, or alledgeth occasionally; partly flowing out of the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the good treasure of his owne heart. Both which manifested to the conscience of the Hearer, do shine like a light in a darke place, and do discouer both God to the Soule, and the Soule (in his owne feeling) vnto God, so that the Soule discerning the presence and Power of God, is ready to cry out (like <hi>Iacob) Doubtlesse God is in this place;</hi> this is no other but the Word of Life, this is the gate of heauen.</p>
   <p>Againe Ministers may further obserue in this Treatise, an exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary Patterne of reading and studying the Scriptures, so as thereby to make a man of God perfect to euery worke of his Ministry. For this Treatise euidenceth, that this Author in reading the Scriptures, hath so diligently pondered, and searched out the true sence of the Holy Ghost, and hath so wisely digested the knowledge and wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Scriptures to the clearing of euery Common-place, and
<pb facs="4"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="5"/>
Doctrine of Religion, that whether he speake to Explication, or Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of any Text, He fitly and fully amplifieth and presseth all, from Scripture-grounds: that you may at once both adore the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of God in the Scriptures, making the Man of God perfect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euery good work: and may also admire the dexterity, and skill of a Scribe taught vnto the kingdome of God, and bringing out of his treasure things both new and old.</p>
   <p>When Schollers furnish themselues with store of other writers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the Scriptures, and being little conuersant in the Scriptures doe draw the Scriptures to the Authors, whom they most affect, and not their A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>thors to the Scriptures, their Diuinity prooueth but Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and their Ministry speaketh to the braine, but not to the consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Hearer. But he that diggeth all the Treasures of his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and the grounds of Religion out of the Scriptures, and maketh vse of other authors, not for ostentatiō of himself, nor for the ground of his faith, nor for the principall ornament of his Ministry, but for the better searching out of the deepe wisedome of the Scriptures, such an one belieueth what he teacheth, not by an humane Credulity from his Author, but by a diuine faith from the Word: and <hi>because he belieueth, he therefore speaketh:</hi> and speaking from faith in his owne heart, he speaketh much more powerfully vnto the begetting and strengthening of faith in the Hearer.</p>
   <p>The priuate Christian in the diligent suruey of this Treatise, shall obserue liuely decyphered, the scornefull vanity of corrupt Nature, the lothsomenesse and desperate danger of sin, the wonderfull power of Gods Grace in the conuersion of a sinner, the tryall of a mans own deceitfull heart, the amiable life of Gods grace in the regenerate, the comfortable benefit of afflictions, sundry sweet consolations of a troubled spirit, the vanity of Popery, the necessity of a faithfull Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry, the beauty of Gods Ordinances holily administred, and the resolution of sundry cases of conscience fitting these times: and all deliuered with such euidence of Scripture-light, and Christian expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that the hearts of the godly Readers, will at once blesse God, who hath giuen such gifts to men: and blesse the Writer, who hauing spent the strength of his yeares in a faithfull and fruitfull Ministry (to the great comfort and succour of many Ministers, and people, far and neare, round about him) doth now at last adorne his hoarie head with this Crowne of glory, to bring forth his workes to more publike Light, now more at the last, then at the first.</p>
   <p>My hearts desire is, that God would adde yet many daies more to the Authors life, and support him still both in body and spirit, to bring to light many other such monuments of his fruitfull labours: not only that elaborate Commentary vpon the 51. Psalme, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise such Sermons or Treatises, or Letters touching cases of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, as haply haue lyenby him, these many yeares. Why should any Talent lye buried in a Napkin, or candle lye hid vnder a bushell, which being set on a candlesticke, might giue light to all that are in
<pb facs="5"/>
the house? Such <hi>(Opuscula)</hi> little Treatises, as himselfe would hardly acknowledge vnder his owne Name, might be of speciall vse, and much esteeme, with others. Witnesse those questions and Answers, wherein he hath comprized the doctrine of the Lords Supper: which though without his Name, they be annexed to a little Treatise of the like Argument, set forth by a godly learned Diuine, <hi>M. William Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shaw:</hi> yet haue they beene of singular good vse to many poore soules, for their worthy preparation to that Ordinance. And in very deed they do more fully furnish a Christian to that whole spirituall Duty, then any other, in any language (that I know) in so small a compasse: yea, and that one Letter of his to a Gentlewoman against the separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which without his consent, a separatist printed and refuted, hath so strongly and clearely conuinced the iniquity of that way, that I could not but acknowledge in it both the wisedome of God, and the weakenesse of the separatist. His wisdome, in bringing to light such a beame of the Light of his truth by the hand of an aduersary, against the Authors mind: and the weakenesse of the other, to aduance the hand of his aduersary to giue himselfe, and his cause such a deadly wound in open view, as neither himselfe nor all his associates can be able to heale. In which respect, I conceiue it was, that the industri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Doctor <hi>Willet</hi> (in his Dedicatory Epistle to CHRISTS Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, before his harmony vpon the first of <hi>Samuel)</hi> stileth this our Author, <hi>Schismaticorum (quivulgò Brownistae) Malleum,</hi> the Hammer of Schismatiques, whom they commonly call Brownists.</p>
   <p>Now the God of all grace, prosper the workes of his seruants, to those good ends himselfe hath appointed, and they haue aimedat, the glory of his owne great Name, in the edification and saluation of his people in Christ.</p>
   <p>So I take leaue, and rest, desirous to prouoke my selfe and thee to a thankfull, and fruitfull vse of such mercies.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>The vnworthiest of the least of Gods Mercies, and Seruants: I. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>