<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his Friend the Author.</title>
           <author>C., C.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119406_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14618</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24928</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119406</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his Friend the Author.</title>
                 <author>C., C.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Further obseruations of the English Spanish pilgrime, concerning Spaine : being a second part of his former booke, and containing these particulars: the description of a famous monastery, or house of the King of Spaines, called the Escuriall, not the like in the Christian world: a briefe relation of certaine dæmonicall stratagems of the Spanish Inquisition exercised on diuers English men of note of late times, and now liuing in England. A relation of the founding of a military order in Rome, to wit, of the immaculate Conception of our Lady, the blessed Virgin. Composed by Iames Wadsworth, Gentleman, lately conuerted into his true mothers bosome, the Church of England, and heretofore pentioner to the King of Spaine</title>
                 <author>Wadsworth, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Allott, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Butter, Nathaniel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 35, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To his Friend the Author.</head>
   <l>I That once fear'd the Circe's cup of <hi>Rhemes,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>But now doe drinke <hi>Thalia's</hi> clearest streames:</l>
   <l>Vieuing thy Shipwrack't danger thou hast past,</l>
   <l>To <hi>Neptune,</hi> a votiue Table, owe to cast.</l>
   <l>Where an <hi>Apelles</hi> Art may seeme the more,</l>
   <l>If that it paint the Babalonish whore.</l>
   <l>Whose coate became thy cloake for each deceite,</l>
   <l>That so the whore might haue her Pander straite:</l>
   <l>Her Rags, thy Veluets were; her triple Crowne,</l>
   <l>Thy Beauer; Princes with a pinching frowne</l>
   <l>T' out baffle, or from their Kingdomes depose:</l>
   <l>If, by them, the <hi>Catholike cause</hi> did lose.</l>
   <l>Her Siren tones would make thee soone awake:</l>
   <l>If not: a clap of Thunder would thee shake.</l>
   <l>The Holy Crosse to beare, was no labour,</l>
   <l>And crosse thy selfe, to crosse thy Sauiour.</l>
   <l>Such was thy hungry zeale the old Saints bones</l>
   <l>T' adore, thou made no bones of't carued stones</l>
   <l>Would turne thy bead-deuotion into gold;</l>
   <l>Which to a made-god (wise man like) thou tould.</l>
   <l>Thou knew neuer cake could make its baker</l>
   <l>Yet often the Priests saw cake their maker,</l>
   <l>Which did vnseale thy eyes cleerely to see</l>
   <l>All their Religion was but trumperie.</l>
   <l>They had told thee of a Purgatory:</l>
   <l>In <hi>Spaine</hi> thou found'st it thy Book's the Story.</l>
   <l>Saint <hi>Omers,</hi> was thy limbus Puerorum,</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Callis</hi> Dungeon, thy limbus Patrum.</l>
   <l>If one should aske where Hell on earth should be</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="6"/>
Thou think'st in <hi>Spaine,</hi> or <hi>Roome,</hi> he may it see,</l>
   <l>What Iesuites are I know thou know'st full well;</l>
   <l>They were the cause that others did thee sell.</l>
   <l>Such Locusts, our Land to eate vp still striue,</l>
   <l>May our Kings Northwinde to <hi>Romes</hi> sea them driue.</l>
   <l>For, I dare boldly say, tis <hi>Englands</hi> doome,</l>
   <l>That they should liue with vs, who sweare for <hi>Roome.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>We haue their heads, but Serpentine, to bite</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Rome,</hi> has their hearts, and their allegeance quite</l>
   <l>A Climactericke yeere hang'd<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Barlow</hi> hang'd, draw'd, and quarter'd at Lancaster Anno 1623.</note> one of late,</l>
   <l>Who sware for Pope against our King and State,</l>
   <l>His dissect parts might teach them to espie</l>
   <l>Those parts that liu'd against should by vs die.</l>
   <l>He many from receiued Truth seduc'd,</l>
   <l>Who to frequent our Church affore time vs'd.</l>
   <l>T'was iust then, to hang the body of him,</l>
   <l>Who t' hang mens soules great merit would it deeme.</l>
   <l>Now may his holinesse him canonize</l>
   <l>As good as <hi>Becket</hi> for Treasons, and lies.</l>
   <l>He with his associates often went</l>
   <l>To a wench, which was to confession bent:</l>
   <l>T'was knowne she was a whore, then well she might</l>
   <l>Make her confession to a Iesuite.</l>
   <l>They kept their<note n="*" place="margin">Si non caste, tamen cautè.</note> Rule and might then shew their skill,</l>
   <l>Liue chaste, thou canst not keep a close whore stil.</l>
   <l>Such hellish firebrands Papists did incense</l>
   <l>Against<note n="*" place="margin">See the life &amp; death of Mistris <hi>Brettergh</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> by <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Harri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> Preacher of Hyton in Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire.</note> one, who liued the Truths defence,</l>
   <l>Whose pretious life because they could not waste,</l>
   <l>The dumbe cattell their cruelty must taste.</l>
   <l>And sith they could not take off that one heade,</l>
   <l>These tales must all off: where a man might reade</l>
   <l>Their rubrick cruelty on th't earth, and heare</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="7"/>
Those dumbe beasts bespeake vengeance in Gods eare.</l>
   <l>I sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ake all this for to congratulate</l>
   <l>Thy ransom'd glory, and most happy fate.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>s</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oote alone scaped out of their snare,</l>
   <l>Thy body also, and thy soule most rare.</l>
   <l>Which soaring vp toward God is fixt aboue</l>
   <l>Nor Pope nor Spainiard can it moue.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Vlisses</hi> valour thou dost farre excell,</l>
   <l>The towring Son of <hi>Thetis</hi> fame dost quell,</l>
   <l>They had their Homers to relate their fame:</l>
   <l>Thou need'st them not: thy workes, can write thy name.</l>
   <l>Iliads of euill could them outweare</l>
   <l>Braue Spirit! a world of euills thou didst beare:</l>
   <l>Nor, beare alone, but breake them through, and showes</l>
   <l>The Trophees of thy glory from thy foes</l>
   <l>To be a true Conuert thou art spoken</l>
   <l>
      <hi>English, Spanish, Pilgrime,</hi> is thy token.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>T. H. A. B.
<hi>C. C. C.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>