<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Honourable Edward Earle of Worcester, Lord of Chepstoll, Ragland, and Gower, Knight of the most Noble order of the Gar∣ter, Mayster of the Horse, and one of the Kinges most Honourable Priuy Councell.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119729_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03250</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13366</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119729</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Honourable Edward Earle of Worcester, Lord of Chepstoll, Ragland, and Gower, Knight of the most Noble order of the Gar∣ter, Mayster of the Horse, and one of the Kinges most Honourable Priuy Councell.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Troia Britanica: or, Great Britaines Troy : A poem deuided into XVII. seuerall cantons, intermixed with many pleasant poeticall tales. Concluding with an vniuersall chronicle from the Creation, vntill these present times. Written by Tho: Heywood</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 128, 109-124, 123-265, pages 254, 301-466, 465-466 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Honourable Edward Earle of <hi>Worcester, Lord of Chepstoll, Ragland, and</hi> Gower, Knight of the most Noble order of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Mayster of the Horse, and one of the Kinges most Honourable Priuy Councell.</hi>
   </head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O you, whose Fauour gaue my Muse first breath,</l>
      <l>To try in th' Ayre her weake vnable wing,</l>
      <l>And soare this pitch, who else had tasted death</l>
      <l>Euen in her byrth, from the Castalian spring</l>
      <l>She dedicates her labours (as they are)</l>
      <l>Though as you see, poore, featherlesse, and bare.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Your Noble hand, to her, supportance gaue,</l>
      <l>Euen in her Pen-lesse Age about to fall,</l>
      <l>Her Cradle then had beene her Infant graue,</l>
      <l>Had not your power and Grace kept her from thrall:</l>
      <l>Then by the Muse, by your hie bounty raisde,</l>
      <l>Y'are by your Merit and my duty praisde.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Her power (though weake) yet to her sickly strength</l>
      <l>Is willing, your past Graces to record,</l>
      <l>Though smothered long, yet she findes time at length</l>
      <l>To shew her office to her Patron-Lord,</l>
      <l>Wishing (for your sake) that vpholds her still,</l>
      <l>Her worth, had correspondence to her will.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Then had her Theame, that treats of forren deeds,</l>
      <l>Beene only tunde to your desert and Merit,</l>
      <l>And you, from whom her nonage Art proceeds,</l>
      <l>Should by her Pen, Eternity inherit:</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="3"/>
But since (great Lord) her best fruites are but words,</l>
      <l>Prise what her hart, not what her Art affoords.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Tis fit those Lordes which we from Troy deriue,</l>
      <l>Should in the Fate of Troy remembred be,</l>
      <l>For since their Graund-sire vertues now suruiue,</l>
      <l>And with the Spirits of this Age agree,</l>
      <l>It makes vs fill our Cantons with such men,</l>
      <l>As liumg now, equaldtheyr vertues then.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Homer (long since) a Chronicler Diuine,</l>
      <l>And Virgill, haue redeemd olde Troy from fire,</l>
      <l>Whose memory had with her buildings line</l>
      <l>In desolate ruyne, had not theyr desire</l>
      <l>Snatcht her fayre Tytle from the burning flame,</l>
      <l>Which with the Towhe had else consumde her name.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Had they surviude in these our flourishing daies,</l>
      <l>Your vertues from the auncient Heroes drawne,</l>
      <l>In spight of death or blacke obliuions rage,</l>
      <l>Should liue for euer in Fames glorious fawne,</l>
      <l>Rankt next to Troy, our Troy-novant should be,</l>
      <l>And next the Troyan Peeres, your places free.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Nor let your Honour my weake stile despise,</l>
      <l>That striues to Register your names with theirs;</l>
      <l>For could my numbers like blinde Homersrise,</l>
      <l>I would create you, Fames eternall heyres:</l>
      <l>Accept my strength, (my weaknesse I bewray)</l>
      <l>Had I like Art, I would as much as they.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>Your Honours euer faithfully deuoted,</p>
   <p>Tho: Heywood.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>