<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Kemps humble request to the impudent generation of Ballad-makers and their cohe∣rents; that it would please their rascalities to pitty his paines in the great iourney he pretends, and not fill the country with lyes of his neuer done actes as they did in his late Morrice to Norwich.</title>
           <author>Kemp, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119460_Bo1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14326</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14923</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119460</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Kemps humble request to the impudent generation of Ballad-makers and their cohe∣rents; that it would please their rascalities to pitty his paines in the great iourney he pretends, and not fill the country with lyes of his neuer done actes as they did in his late Morrice to Norwich.</title>
                 <author>Kemp, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Kemps nine daies vvonder : Performed in a daunce from London to Norwich. Containing the pleasure, paines and kinde entertainment of William Kemp betweene London and that citty in his late morrice. Wherein is somewhat set downe worth note; to reprooue the slaunders spred of him: many things merry, nothing hurtfull. Written by himselfe to satisfie his friends</title>
                 <author>Kemp, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Ling (Lyng), Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>X to the Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Games and recreations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_ballad_makers">
   <pb facs="15"/>
   <head>
      <hi>Kemps humble request to the impudent</hi> generation of Ballad-makers and their cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; that it would please their rascalities to pitty his paines in the great iourney he pretends, and not fill the country with lyes of his neuer done actes as they did in his late Morrice to Norwich.</head>
   <opener>To the tune of <hi>Thomas Delonies</hi> Epitaph.</opener>
   <p>MY notable Shabetags, the effect of my sure is discouered in the Title of my supplication. But for your better vnderstandings: for that I know you to be a sort of witles beetle hends, that can vnderstand nothing, but what is knocke into your scalpes. These are by these presentes to certifie vnto your block headships, that I William Kemp, whom you had neer hand rent in sunder with your vnreasonable times, am shortly God willing to set forward as merily as I may; whether I my selfe know not Wherefore by the way I would wish ye, imploy not your little wits in certifying the world that I am gone to Rome, Ierusalem, Venice, or any other place at your idle appoint. I knowe the best of ye by the lyes ye writ of me, got not the price of a good hat to couer your brainles heads: If any of ye had come to me, my bounty should haue exceeded the best of your good masters the Ballad-buiers, I wold haue apparrelled your dry pates in party coloured bonnets, &amp; bestowd a leash of my cast belles to haue crown'd ye with cox-combs. I haue made a priuie search, what priuate Iigmonger of your iolly num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb facs="16"/> hath been the Author of these abhominable bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets written of me: I was told it was the great bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let-maker <hi>T.D. alias Tho. Deloney,</hi> Chronicler of the memorable liues of the <hi>6.</hi> yeomen of the west, Iack of Newbery, the Gentle-craft, &amp; such like honest mē: omitted by Stow, Hollinshead, Graftō, Hal, froysart, &amp; the rest of those wel deseruing writers: but I was giuen since to vnderstand, your late generall Tho. dyed poorely, as ye all must do, and was honestly bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried: which is much to bee doubted of some of you. The quest of inquiry finding him by death acquited of the Inditement, I was let to wit, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> another Lord of litle wit, one whose imployment for the Pageant, was vtterly spent, he being knowne to be Eldertons immediate heyre, was vehemently suspected but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter due inquisition was made, he was at that time knowne to liue like a man in a mist, hauing quite gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ouer the mistery. Still the search continuing, I met a proper vpright youth, onely for a little stooping in the shoulders: all hart to the heele, a penny Poet whose first making was the miserable stolne story of Macdoel, or Macdobeth, or Macsomewhat: for I am sure a Mac it was, though I neuer had the maw to see it: &amp; hee tolde me there was a fat filthy ballet-maker, that should haue once been his Iourneyman to the trade: who liu'd about the towne: and ten to one, but he had thus terribly abused me &amp; my Tabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer: for that he was able to do such a thing in print. A shrewd presumption: I found him about the bankside, sitting at a play, I desired to speake with him,
<pb facs="16"/> had him to a Tauerne, charg'd a pipe with Tobacco, and then laid this terrible accusation to his charge. He swels presently like one of the foure windes, the violence of his breath, blew the Tobacco out of the pipe, &amp; the heate of his wrath drunke dry two bowle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of Rhenish wine. At length hauing power to speake. Name my accuser saith he, or I defye thee Kemp at the quart staffe. I told him, &amp; all his anger turned to laughter: swearing it did him good to haue ill words of a hoddy doddy, a habber de hoy, a chicken, a squib, a squall: One that hath not wit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make a ballet, that by <hi>Pol</hi> and <hi>Aedipol,</hi> would Pol his father, Derick his dad: doe anie thing how ill soeuer, to please his apish humor. I hardly beleeued, this youth that I tooke to be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, had bin so graceles: but I heard afterwards his mother in law was eye and eare witnes of his fathers abuse by this blessed childe on a publique stage, in a merry Hoast of an Innes part. Yet all this while could not I finde out the true bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let-maker. Till by chaunce a friend of mine puld out of his pocket a booke in Latine called <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Furiosus:</hi> printed at <hi>Cullen,</hi> written by one of the vildest and arrantest lying Cullians that euer writ booke, his name Iansonius, who ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vpon him to write an abstract of all the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent actions that had beene lately attempted or performed in Christendome, like an vnchristian wretch, writes onely by report, partially, and
<pb facs="17"/> scoffingly, of such whose pages shooes hee was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to wipe, for indeed he is now dead: farewell he, euery dog must haue a day. But see the luck on't: this beggerly lying busie-bodies name, brought out the Ballad-maker: and it was generally confirmd, it was his kinsman: he confesses himselfe guilty, let any man looke on his face: if there be not so redde a colour that all the sope in the towne will not washe white, let me be turned to a Whiting as I passe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Douer and Callis. Well, God forgiue thee honest fellow, I see thou hast grace in thee: I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thee do so no more, leaue writing these beastly bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, make not good wenches Prophetesses, for litle or no profit, nor for a sixe-penny matter, reuiue not a poore fellowes fault thats hanged for his offence: it may be thy owne destiny one day, prethee be good to them. Call vp thy olde Melpomene, whose straube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry quill may write the bloody lines of the blew La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and the Prince of the burning crowne: a better subiect I can tell ye: than your Knight of the Red Crosse. So farewel, and crosse me no more I prethee with thy rabble of bald rimes, least at my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne I set a crosse on thy forehead, that all men may know thee for a foole.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>VVilliam Kemp.</signed>
   </closer>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   <pb facs="17"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>