<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the proficient Scholler or louer of the Cittharn.</title>
           <author>Holborne, Anthony</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119009_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03441</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13562</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119009</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the proficient Scholler or louer of the Cittharn.</title>
                 <author>Holborne, Anthony</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The cittharn schoole, by Antony Holborne gentleman, and seruant to her most excellent Maiestie. Hereunto are added sixe short aers Neopolitan like to three voyces, without the instrument: done by his brother William Holborne</title>
                 <author>Holborne, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Short, Peter</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>136 pages, music, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the proficient Scholler or <hi>louer of the Cittharn.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ar be it from me (gentle friend) in the humor of vaineglorie to recommend these my silly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to the presse, and by the presse to thee, vnder a further hope of thy better censure then of their little-worth: for hitherto could I neuer stande so well conceipted of my selfe in selfe-opinion, nor by perswasion of others, to enwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy them of thee in this publike forme. But the time nowe presenting occasion by a wrong proffered from a meere stranger vnto me, who (without my knowledge of either man or meane) hath deliuered in common to the worlds view cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiane corrupt coppies of my Idles, (the vntimely fruits of my youth, begotten in the cradle and infancy of my slender skill) I am ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with a more easie reason led to call home mine own mangled children to the originall place of their natiuity: both in respect of their immaturitie, and the disguised countenance wherin they liue abroad. And to purchase thy better conceipt, with a more pleasing rellish to thy chast eares then their <hi>bastarde barbarisme</hi> since their first escape from me could promise, I haue indeuored my selfe in a carefull reuisitation, to regenerate and newly replant them, by pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them of those vnsauory corruptions, which I know could not choose but giue offence to thee as well as to my selfe. Such there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as they nowe are, with a liberall consent I do freely commend them to thy handes and good vsage, as the true images of their father; whome I haue appointed to attend thee in all their best ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices. And in their deseruings if they haue any, giue them leaue I pray thee, (as well for their dutie towardes me as their willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb facs="4"/> to serue thee) meekely in my name to craue but good accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Thou shalt find them of seuerall natures and offices: which I haue accordingly marshalled in such methode and forme, as to my iudgement may best beseeme thee in degrees of thine habilitie to entertaine them. For in the front of the booke (as the first step or key to open a way to thy beginnings) I haue prefixed some fewe tastes, which by another name I call <hi>Praeludia:</hi> things short and not hard: deliuered vnto thee of purpose to guide thy hand to some proper vse of plaie, and withall to search and feele if thy <hi>Cytharn</hi> be well in tune: thinges verie well also becomming any man as a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face before he shall proceede to do any determinate matter. Next vnto them as in an orderly consequence I haue conioyned the most vsuall and familiar grounds of these our times, for consort or thine owne priuate selfe: together with some such other light fansies of vulgar tunes for variety as I could best call to memory: wherein happilie some men in the condition of their own nature may hould themselues better pleased then in things of more worth. All which I haue layde downe with as much facilitie and ease for a schollers encouragement as my poore wits could fashion, obseruing such formality as may wel stand with a tollerable allowance in the nature of the Instrument. To these as thy increase of performance ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth, haue I annexed some of the same groundes in variable diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion: done after a more quicke and hard maner of plaie: thereby to teach thee the neerest course to shift thy hand from string to string. Lastly, (as a complet summary of this little worke) <hi>I</hi> conclude with thinges graue and more iudicious then the rest with their Bases in prickesong notes, which <hi>I</hi> haue set downe on euery Page oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site to the same lesson. These thinges being of another stampe, doe carry their naturall partes tyed together in a different nature, with some reasonable good cordes and bindinges after a more heedfull manner of composition, which in the first obiect to thine eye and finger by a superficiall passage, may amate and withhould thy forwardnesse, because they will appeare more seuere and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full then do lie in common custome. Howbeit <hi>I</hi> wish thee not to desist, but rather aduance thy best conceiptes with a resolution, for I haue prepared nothing which hath not beene, is not, and may bee commanded by the hand: for all are comprehended within the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits
<pb facs="4"/> of hand-reach. And therefore (good friend if thou do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectiuely performe them in a true obseruation and orderlie rule of plaie, they shal leaue in thee a better impression of their worth then the other first sortes, and feede thee (no doubt) with a pleasing hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor of passion and sweet melancholy. Mine they were once, now are they euer thine, begotten, bred, and borne to doe thee seruice. Vse them therefore: and m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, (if thou please) as but in common cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesie I hope thou wilt. And if the liberty of hereafter-times shall occasion me in this kind to enlarge my further paines, I will sende some others of my children in the quest of their brethren: which proouing better schollers shall also teach thee to handle sixe strings, where now thou hast but foure. In the meane time <hi>I</hi> wish to please thee, and thee to please thy selfe in a liberall saciety if it bee heere. And if happily (euen in a narrow search) thou do but meet with any one digestiue portion of contentment from among these my little ones, I shall hould my selfe bound in euer-redou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling thanks for thy fauorable acceptation, and rest thine in all loue, and my best means to pleasure thee.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Ant: Holborne.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>