<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Whitbourne, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119923_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15072</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25375</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119923</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Whitbourne, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discourse containing a louing inuitation both honourable, and profitable to all such as shall be aduenturers, either in person, or purse, for the aduancement of his Maiesties most hopefull plantation in the Nevv-found-land, lately vndertaken. Written by Captaine Richard Whitbourne of Exmouth, in the county of Deuon</title>
                 <author>Whitbourne, Richard, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 46, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Reader, I haue, in my former printed Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course,
laid open a discouery of the <hi>New-found-land,</hi>
and purpose (in this my second
labours, to acquaint all Vndertakers of that
Plantation, what particular profit may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>downd
to themselues and posterities, and what honours
(through their industry) will accrew to the English Nation;
Beare therefore, I beseech thee, with my rough stile, and plain
meaning, in which I striue rather to shew truth in her owne
brightnesse, then to heape applause or glory to my selfe. To
crowne that Countrey of <hi>New-found-land</hi> with due praises,
that she may (by the approbation and fauour of his Maiesty)
be iustly called a Sister-land to this great Iland of <hi>Britannia,
Ireland, Virginia, New-England,</hi> and <hi>Noua-Scotia:</hi>
And that she may claime her selfe this bold and honourable
Title, the world, I thinke, will bee on her side, especially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
she, from her owne mouth, doth shew what infinite and
vnspeakable benefits for many yeeres together, the negotiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of our Kingdome with her, hath brought to all our people,
not onely by the increrse of Mariners and shipping, but by
inriching of many a subiect, and so consequently by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieuing
of many thousands of families, which else had liued
in miserable wants for lacke of honest imployments; Our
English Nation, hauing more then fourescore yeeres together,
made thriuing and profitable Voyages to that Countrey, the
possession whereof began in our late Soueraigne of happy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory,
Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and so continues more strongly
<pb facs="4"/>
now in his Maiesty, without the claime, interest, or authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of any other Prince.</p>
   <p>Touching the Iland it selfe: It lyeth a great part thereof
more to the South then 47. degrees of North-latitude, which
is fiue degrees neerer the Equinoctiall line, then the City of
London: the distance of it on this side from the Continent of
America, bearing the same proportion that England doth
to the neerest part of France, and lyeth neere the course, and
halfe the way betweene Ireland and Virginia.</p>
   <p>This proper and commodious situation of the place, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
with the correspondency of benefits, which not only Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
but Scotland, and Ireland may, and doe receiue from
the same, filles me more with an ardent desire, so to haue her
stiled, a Sister-land. And worthily may that Royalty be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed
vpon her: For as great Brittaine hath euer been a
cherishing nurse and mother to other forraigne sonnes and
daughters, feeding them with the milke of her plenty, and
fatting them at her brests, when they haue been euen starued
at their owne: Euen so hath this worthy Countrey of <hi>New-found-land</hi>
from time to time giuen free and liberall enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment
to all that desired her blessings: and chiefly (aboue
all other Nations) to the English. What receiue wee from the
hands of our owne Countrey, which in most bountious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
we haue not had, or may haue at hers? Nay, what can
the world yeeld, to the sustentation of man, which is not in her
to be gotten? Desire you wholesome ayre (the very food of
life?) It is there: shall any Land powre in abundant heapes of
nourishments &amp; necessaries before you? There you haue them:
What seas so abounding in fish, what shores so replenished with
fresh and sweet waters? The wants of other Kingdomes are
not felt heere, and those prouisions which many Countryes
want, are from thence supplied. How much is Spaine, France,
Portugall, Italy, and other places beholding to this noble part
<pb facs="5"/>
of the world for fish and other commodities, it is to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.
Let the Dutch report what sweetnesse they haue suckt
from her by trade thither, in buying of fish from our Nation.
And (albeit all the rest should be dumbe) the voyces of them
are as Trumpets lowd enough, to make England fall more and
more in loue with such a sister-land. I will not wearie thee
(good Reader) with leading thee to those famous, faire, and
profitable riuers, nor to those delightfull, large and inestima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
woods, neither ouer all those fruitfull and inticing hils,
and delightfull vallies, there to hawke and hunt, where there
is neither Clowne, nor sauage people to hinder thy sports.
They are such, that in so small a piece of paper, as now my loue
salutes thee with, I cannot fully set them downe as they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue:
and therefore intreat thee, with iudgement, with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
and with desire, for the benefit of they Countrey, to reade
ouer this Discourse, which I trust may incourage thee to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
so hopefull a Plantation, as it appeareth to bee, and also
giue thee ample satisfaction, and iust cause to answere op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posers,
if any out of ignorance, or other sinister respect, shall
seeke to hinder so honourable and worthy designes. So wishing
thee all happinesse, I rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Euer thine, for my Countries good,
RICHARD WHITBOVRNE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>