<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Grimeston, Harb.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119467_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14727</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25030</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119467</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Grimeston, Harb.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvonders of the load-stone. Or, The load-stone newly reduc't into a divine and morall vse. By Samuel Ward, of Ipswich. B.D</title>
                 <author>Ward, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Cole, Peter.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, Elizabeth</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 96, 111-142, 151-181, that is 281, 1 page, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations (metal cut), 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Christian Reader</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>THe Scripture discommends that ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant who hid his Talent and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised it not, aend indeed our time being but short, yet precious, must not be negligently let slip, we are not onely borne for our selves, every man must labour to doe some good to the Country and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth wherein he lives, We must be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptable for our times of leasure when we are freed from other more serious affaires, <hi>Tam otii quam negotii ratio habenda est,</hi> Therefore in the late long vacation I was willing to imploy my selfe about the translation of this following Discourse, which I thought fit and worthy to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to the vi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>wes of our English subjects, having already received a gracious appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation from his Royall Majestie. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="11"/>
I was induc't to undertake this worke that the divine ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lications cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ined there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in might be known to all, as well as to Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, the meaner sort having more need of sensible <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eroglyphiks,</hi> and exemplary helps, to accomplish their salvations, then the wise and great <hi>Rabbies,</hi> againe, I had an ayme herein, that ignorant Mariners who have onely gained a piece of the use of the <hi>Loadstone</hi> by a practicall observation, that they might s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yle in safety, might now by the knowledg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of this booke, when they looke on their Compasse, find out a way by applying to their owne hearts, the admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble contemplations contained therein, to steere t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eir owne soules to the haven of heaven, as well as their shippes to the harbour. Besides the Authour, whom I doe highly honour for his integrity of life, and eminency of learning, of whom I would speake more, but that I will not offend his humility and modesty, I say the Authour himselfe, who hath a commanding power in me, did request me to undertake this taske, and I am glad, if my Pensill hath in some measure, taken out to the life so curious a <hi>Proto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>type,</hi>
      <pb facs="12"/>
howsoever (Courtious and Christian Reader) I have resolved to venture upon thy favourable acceptance, and to desire thee to interpret this interpretation to the best, in hope of which I remaine,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine to my power,</hi> Harb. Grimeston.</signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="12"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>