<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Preface to the Reader, wherein is contained the Scope and Argument of the following Treatise.</title>
           <author>W., S.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119467_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14727</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25030</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119467</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Preface to the Reader, wherein is contained the Scope and Argument of the following Treatise.</title>
                 <author>W., S.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvonders of the load-stone. Or, The load-stone newly reduc't into a divine and morall vse. By Samuel Ward, of Ipswich. B.D</title>
                 <author>Ward, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Cole, Peter.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, Elizabeth</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 96, 111-142, 151-181, that is 281, 1 page, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations (metal cut), 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>A Preface to the Reader, wherein is contained the Scope and Argument of the following Treatise.</head>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Crollius, p.</hi> 77 Plane▪ tis.</note>THe <hi>Chymists</hi> doe make equall in number, and assigne those seaven Mettals that are in the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of the earth,<note place="margin">
         <hi>1 Lead to Saturne,</hi> ♄</note> to so many <hi>Planets</hi> that are in the <hi>Orbes</hi> of heaven;<note place="margin">
         <hi>2 Tin to Iupiter,</hi> ♃</note> the <hi>Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone</hi> not regarding the most excellent of these,<note place="margin">
         <hi>3 Iron to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>punc; Mars,</hi> ♂ <hi>4 Gold to the Sun,</hi> ☉</note> and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versally neglecting other ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall substances,<note place="margin">
         <hi>5 Brasse to Venus,</hi> ♀</note> doth draw onely iron unto it, in whose friendship as it were, and
<pb facs="7"/>
serviceable company to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon it,<note place="margin">
         <hi>6 Quicke silver to Mercury,</hi> ☿</note> it doth much delight; such is the condition of Bookes,<note place="margin">
         <hi>7 Silver to the Moone,</hi> ☽</note> of which though there be an innumerable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany that abound everywhere, yet every one hath its <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neticke</hi> Genius,<note place="margin">Clemens Alex. p. 176. Edit Grotii.</note> fitted to the disposition of the Reader, whereby it doth allure unto it, the eyes and hearts of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and being allured, doth in a manner bewitch them, neither doth every ones affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or phantasie draw him with lesse force▪ then the <hi>Loadstone</hi> doth Iron. If thou beest a <hi>Philosopher,</hi> the wōders of the <hi>Loadstone</hi> then which there is nothing found more pleasant or excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in the whole <hi>Theater</hi> of nature, will draw thee hither.
<pb facs="8"/>
If thou beest a <hi>Christian,</hi> Christ will draw thee hither, as also his graces en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven in a lively manner upon the <hi>Loadstone</hi> by the finger of God, If thou beest a Divine, many places of Scripture seemingly repugnant, that are briefly illustrated, will draw thee hither, as also those knotty School doubts, which are resolved by the way. If thou beest a <hi>Poet,</hi> this whole Booke is a kind of <hi>Poem,</hi> If a <hi>Rhetorician,</hi> here thou hast a continued Allegorie, and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophy</hi> besides, wayting upon Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, yeelding light unto it; one while as it becommeth an humble hand-maid, another while as a modest Gentleman Vsher, in which particular I have fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>Dion,</hi> not the <hi>Historian,</hi> but that Orator which was most deare un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Trajan,</hi> and for his eloquence sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>Chrysostome,</hi> or golden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth, I have also imitated, the skill of Husbandmen, who graffe fruitfull
<pb facs="8"/>
branches of a good kind, upon wild plants, that of barren and bitter, they may become fruitfull and sweet; Here thou hast a <hi>Chria,</hi> or an exercise of <hi>Rhethoricke</hi> most effectuall to teach, move, and delight, which had his name imposed, from the use and profit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Now this <hi>Chria,</hi> as <hi>Vosius Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd others describe it) is not a painted or feigned, but a lively Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme, where either the person is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled to the thing, or somewhat is done and pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>'t before the eyes of the body, which may more speedily pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate the sharpe sight of the mind, more strongly move the affections, and more faithfully sticke to the memory, which kind of cunning, or artificiall skill, the Prophets both of the Old and New Testament have often used, whereby they might more deepely imprint, their Propecies in the eyes of their Auditors. So <hi>Agabus</hi> held it not sufficient to
<pb facs="9"/>
foretell the bonds of <hi>Paul,</hi> but he bound himselfe also with <hi>Pauls</hi> Girdle: nor did the Lord Iesus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>old it sufficient, to be the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>her and pattern of humility, but he plac't also a little Infant in the midst of the Apostles, in a most high place, whereby he mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t point out unto them, that he should be the greatest among them, which endeavoured to be the least; moreover at the last, hee himselfe also being clothed, af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er the fashion of a servant, did wash t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eir feet with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ater, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ped them with a linnen cloth that he might herby leave this vertue, which is necessary for all, though least acceptable, most chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to all his servants; for though the eares are rightly tearmed by <hi>Fabulists,</hi> the senses of <hi>Minerva,</hi> or of wisedome, or instruction, yet doe those things mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e slowly stirre up the mind, which come to be knowne by the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r windings and turnings, then those which
<pb facs="9"/>
doe presently incurre to it by the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of the eyes; where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ore in briefe, thou art to be intreated at the very first, to procure unto thy selfe a stone, which is of great vertue, or to goe unto some one that hath such a stone in his possession, whereby thou maiest be both a diligent spectator, and also a benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Reader. Vnlesse thou be both, both of us shall be frustrated of our ends, thou of thy profit and pleasure in reading, I of my scope and labour in writing; for here are divers experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, of which if thou beest not an Eye witnesse, they shall not loose onely all their grace, but also thy beliefe, and their end. But if thou professest thy selfe among <hi>Criticks,</hi> such as are cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious about matter, and manner of stile, I would have th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e consider, that one thing of <hi>Plinie,</hi> that it is not lawfull to ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nish a Diamond. The <hi>Loadstone</hi> is of the like condition,
<pb facs="10"/>
not onely for hardnesse, as very scarcely admitting a penne of steele, as also for the innate vertue, which refuseth and disdaines all borrowed ornaments. To conclude, whosoever thou art, whom either the noveltie or utility of the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, shall draw hither, if thou receive the least delight, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit this shall be to him a sufficient reward for his labour, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver presumed to expect for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, or his meditations, any better lot or lucke, then happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to the <hi>Loadstone,</hi> that it should be of great use, but of little esteeme and reputation with many, nor did he for any other respect, then somewhat to please thee, and much to profit thee, endeavour according to his abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, at spare houres, to mingle Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine things with <hi>Philosophicall,</hi>
      <pb facs="10"/>
Morall with Divine, and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with pleasant; <hi>And this he was desirous to let thee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand,</hi> Who is,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord Iesus, who is all Loadstone and the most excellent. S. W</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>