<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO EVERIE TRVE CHRISTIAN Soule, rightly taking to heart the estate of Christs poore Churches and disper∣sed Flocke.</title>
           <author>B., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119302_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16892</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3788</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119302</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO EVERIE TRVE CHRISTIAN Soule, rightly taking to heart the estate of Christs poore Churches and disper∣sed Flocke.</title>
                 <author>B., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fourth part of the true watch : containing prayers and teares for the churches. Or A helpe to hold up the hearts and hands of the poorest servants of God, untill our Lord Iesus Christ shall have rescued his glorie, kingdome, and people in all the world, and fully prepared the way to his most glorious appearing</title>
                 <author>Brinsley, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, Isaac</publisher>
                    <distributor>Pavier, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>108, 273, 278-420, 38 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_protestant_reader">
   <pb facs="45"/>
   <pb facs="45"/>
   <head>TO EVERIE TRVE CHRISTIAN Soule, rightly taking to heart the estate of Christs poore Churches and disper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Flocke.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, if thou take to heart the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honours done unto our most holy God, the trampling vnder foot the Gospell and Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of our Lord Iesus Christ in so many parts of his Church, the miserable estate of his people and servants professing his name, under the slaverie and tyrannie of Antichrist; or the wofull conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the remainder of Gods elect not yet cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led &amp; gathered forth, but remainining under the power of Satan; or if thou regard but the saving of thine owne soule, afford some assistance to him and his poore people, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially now that hee so graciously cals upon thee, and offers thee so much direction
<pb facs="46"/>
and helpe thereunto, even in these meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and prayers b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>sides many others.</p>
   <p>Consider of them well; and so farre as thou findest him calling on thee, to put them in practice, set thy selfe forthwith to helpe in this blessed worke. If any of them, either meditations or prayers, seeme unto thee weake, as they must needs be, having beene written for most part when many others slept; and that because of the industrie of Satan and his instruments, that they might not bee any hinderance unto my calling, yet are they such as thy Christ expects at thy hands, so far as they are soundly grounded upon his sacred truth, and agreeable to his heavenly will. Give him thy heart and best affections, and better the forme in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ne owne devotion, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring ever for whom they are chiefly intended, <hi>viz</hi> to helpe the weaker sort, which are not able to pray of themselves, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>se occasions.</p>
   <p>If they seeme over long for thy occasions, yet are they so divided, as thou mayest leave off and begin againe wheresoever thou pleasest, onely fitting some generall beginnings and ends of the prayers, according to the other, or according to thine owne holy meditation.</p>
   <p>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> this offend thee, that they are s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>t downe in a booke, remember the publique prayers, that in all ages have beene so in the Church, and yet most pleasing and available. Let the consideration of so many of thine owne nation, yea so many of the chiefe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb facs="46"/>
so fearefully seduced, and even bewit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by Iesuites, and other Seminarie Priests, and everie day more and more falling away, to the indangering not onely of themselves, but of the whole Land continually, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke thee to this dutie: and especially see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they professe themselves to have beene drawne to that Romish Religion hereby chiefly; <hi>That they in their Church have moe devotions, and spend more time therein, than we in ours.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Let this move thee to take some pitie of them, and to helpe by thy prayers, to pull them out of the fire of Gods vengeance, and likewise to keepe others from falling from him. Let their blinde zeale and superstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous devotions (which condemnes the coldnes and securitie of the greatest part of those, who professing Christs Gospell, yet pray so litt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e, and which is one principall cause of their stumbling, I speake upon certaine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, both concerning high and low, noble and mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>) let this, I say, provoke thee to more devotion in holy meditations and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant prayers, according to the word and will of thy God, and enforce thee hereunto, to spend daily some part of it, as God gives thee more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>it opportunitie; or as thou hast more neglected these. They (as is said) use some devotions daily to pull soules out of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie; be thou instant for them, to pull them from the power of Satan to Christ.</p>
   <p>Begin thus to redeeme thy time, so badly
<pb facs="47"/>
mis-spent, and that so long, untill thou shalt see Gods glory recovered, the scepter of his Christ set up againe in all places whence it is removed; with the deliverie of thy brethren in all forraine part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>; and the dangers past which are so threatned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all the Churches, and namely our ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest and faithfull neighbours, and even to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thy selfe. Suffer not these blinded soules to rise up in judgement against thee, that they have spent more time and paines in their devotion to serve Satan and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ, and to hold up his throne, to their endlesse perdition; than thou to serve our Lord Iesus, to the saving thine owne soule, and the lives of all his people.</p>
   <p>If thou wouldst be ready to spend thy goods, and to adventure thy life for the glory of thy God, for thy Christ, and his Church, at his command; yea if thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest bestow any labour or cost, to save thy native Countrey or Countreymen being in danger, and much more the Lords Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, with our Royall Prince, and that most illustrious Prince and Princesse Palatine, all of whom haue shewed so much love to Christs Gospell, and if thy heart be truly affected to that sweet and happy progen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>, then be ready to helpe them all by thy prayers: especially sith thou maiest doe this without any cost or losse, and hast helpe offered from his Majestie, and the same also, not onely put into thy hands, but, as
<pb facs="47"/>
it were, into thy mouth; and withall thy hands holden up by him to doe it. Doe it therefore as well as thou caust, if thou regard but thine owne case, either of soule or bodie, thy present or eternall estate.</p>
   <p>I have purposely in many of the praiers, followed the order in <hi>the first part of this Watch,</hi> which I have taken for a good di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, both for that it hath beene so oft tried by the learned to be according to the true <hi>Rule of Life,</hi> and for that the places for proofes are there quoted to auoid further labour: and that thou and all the weaker sort may learne together both to watch and pray for your selves and all the people of the Lord, and so be sure to prevaile with his heavenly Majestie.</p>
   <p>If thou shalt finde or suspect any errour, wherein thou darest not joyne, signifie it as in love and in the feare of the Lord; and I shall (as I have ever bound my selfe) be most ready either to give thee satisfaction, or to reforme it; and yet in the meane time proceed in the rest joyntly with thy brethren.</p>
   <p>Let us all joyne as being of one heart and soule, wherein we all agree, crying unto our heavenly Father, compassing him about at his feet for our selves and all his deare children, and he will surely heare our cries, and in his due time reveale every diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence unto us, and wherein the errour lieth.</p>
   <p>I tie thee not to daies nor houres, but as thou observest the Lord offering thee fittest
<pb facs="48"/>
opportunities, and as he shall move thee thereto: though because of Satans subtlety, and the falsenesse and corruption of our owne hearts, we shall finde by experience, that all the bonds whereby we can binde our selves to holy duties, especially of this nature and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, are farre too little, so we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> doe it in an holy wisdome and wise consideration, that we bring not a snare upon our selves.</p>
   <p>Wonder not that I so oft go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> over that heavenly prayer of our Saviours, and so strictly tie my selfe unto it, for that I finde it the wisdome of God, and the power of God, ministring still now and most heavenly matter even to this our present purpose; and also am fully assured that all the true Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches &amp; people of the Lord both do &amp; shall so finde it, and that more &amp; more, as we more labour according to it; having also such sure directions and such undoubted promises; every part and pecce of it containing promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses to the prayer of faith, and to every true beleeving soule. Whereby we may have a certaine assurance from our Lord Iesus Christ the author of it, that he will accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie it to every soule (that shall be so pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, and so use it as be hath directed) with the power of his owne spirit, and be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull in granting all things which we so beg according to his heavenly will, above all that any heart can conceive.</p>
   <p>Remember also for thy better incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, how every prayer herein tends to the
<pb facs="48"/>
appeasing of the Lords heavy indignation, which hath beene thus far declared against his people: and this by our joynt seeking to give him his glory in helping to reclaime and reduce us all to the obedience of his blessed Covenant of Grace, wherein is our life, and thereby to the deliver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e and saving of all the Churches, the eternall salvation of all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to that his election of grace, be they now Atheists, Papists, wicked, profane, or whatsoever, and so to prepare the way in the universall repentance of the Churches to the comming of the new Hierusalem, and the eternall glory of Sion. So that every one of us striving to pray faithfully and fervently, and to put in practise whatsoever we thus pray for; so farre as it concernes us, shall in every prayer and petition be true helpers unto our Lord Iesus and his poore Church; and for every such a service, even every houre so spent, receive our pay, and in the end for all a rich and most full reward.</p>
   <p>Let every prayer be a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> the Sunne, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at thy selfe in thy meditations, but dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusing and spreading the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ames into all the Churches, chiefly to those which stand in most need thereof, and to every one of Gods chosen in all the world, so far as he shall inable thee and it concerneth them, and from them ever reflecting to thy selfe againe.</p>
   <p>Thou hast heard the sound of the cruell warres abroad, the late prevailing of the enemie, the overthrow of the Churches, the
<pb facs="49"/>
new threatnings of those bloudy intendments against all the rest, and the increase of their rage daily. In these poore helps, and the like, the Lord offereth thee weapons, and directs thee so to use them, that thou maist helpe them in the remotest parts; calls upon thee loud to come and helpe them, assures thee of a blessed victorie in the end, that then thou and all the true Church and people of the Lord shall sing the songs of <hi>Miriam</hi> and <hi>Deborah,</hi> and of the 24. <hi>Elders,</hi> and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph with Christ eternally, when all who have refused to helpe, shall weepe and waile for evermore.</p>
   <p>Thus intreating that the Lord may at length awake thee and all his people, that we may each give up a happy account, and escape the dreadfull doome and sentence, for neglecting his glory, kingdome, and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and may hence forward carefully use all the meanes which his goodnesse af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords unto us for our present and eternall happinesse, I commend thee to his grace, and rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy fellow-souldier in Christ thus striving with and for thee, I. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>