<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119839_Fr1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14820</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18063</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119839</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The true crucifixe for true Catholickes or The way for true Catholickes to haue the true crucifixe. By Sr. William Moore, To: of Rovvallane Knight</title>
                 <author>Mure, William, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wreittoun (Scribonius), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 238, that is 239, 7 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <head>TO THE READER</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>CHRISTIAN READER</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>OOKE rather what is intended, than what I have attained. My principall aime and purpose is to show that who soever doth love to see the true purtrate of <hi>IESUS CHRIST</hi> our <hi>LORD,</hi> must verse Himselfe in holy <hi>Scripture,</hi> except Hee will chuise to ly open to delusion. If it please Thee to read and seriously perpend what is said to this purpose, I have eneugh for my paines. I haue contrivd it in a measured stile, that thou mayst read with lesser wearying. Looke not for elaborat words, for not only the weighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the subject made mee shunne what soe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver might breed obscuritie, but I ever held the whorish ornamnets of affected eloquence an vnsutable Ornament to garnish pure <hi>Truth.</hi> If it seeme to Thee I haue extended the worke to more than a competent length, some few moments shall serue Thee to runne thorow the margents, Howrs thou mayst reserue to what further it stall please to make search for in the work. If my stile seeme any where sharpe against the abuise and abuisers of the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall
<pb facs="2"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="2"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Crucifixe,</hi> weigh my reasons withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> prejudice, and I hope, I shall not neede to stan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in feare of thy condemning censure. If th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> maner of handling of this Subject seeme to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> more proper for a <hi>Preacher</hi> than a <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> of my place, refuse it not for this, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> worthy <hi>Preacher,</hi> of my neere and deare ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, out of His loue to <hi>CHRIST</hi> and thy <hi>Salvation,</hi> did not only stirre mee vp to buil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> this peece of worke, but both by <hi>Conference</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Counsell,</hi> (as my weaknesse stood in need<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of advise) did fordwardly concurre to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish helpe to the materials. Thou shall doe we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> therefore to passe by the insufficiencie of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Instrument;</hi> that, likeing the purpose neither the better nor the worse for this respect, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> looking (chiefly) to the <hi>Truth</hi> of that whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> is spoken, by occasion thereof Thou mayst be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> stirred vp to a further study of the knowledge of <hi>IESUS CHRIST,</hi> and Riches of <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>truth</hi> in Him, and so to a greater <hi>love</hi> of Him, and <hi>communion</hi> with Him, for which end I pray the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>IESUS</hi> be with Thee.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>