<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The argumēt of this booke: Wherein the Epistle or Letter mis∣siue of Maister Gentian Heruet, is deui∣ded into sixe partes, and the mea∣ning of the same brieslie de∣clared.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119818_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07026</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17445</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119818</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The argumēt of this booke: Wherein the Epistle or Letter mis∣siue of Maister Gentian Heruet, is deui∣ded into sixe partes, and the mea∣ning of the same brieslie de∣clared.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The bee hiue of the Romishe Church : a com [m] entarie vpon the sixe principall pointes of Master Gentian Heruet, a Romish Catholike his booke, which is deuided into sixe partes, as in the argument doth appeare. And an epistle made by the authour of this booke vnto Franciscus Sonnius, late Bishop of Antwerpe. Translated out of Dutch into English, by George Gylpen the elder</title>
                 <author>Marnix van St. Aldegonde, Philips van</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Schilders (Grapheus, Painter), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stell, Jan (Hans)</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>15, 346, 1 leave, 2 folded plates, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <head>The argumēt of this booke: Wherein the Epistle or Letter mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siue of Maister <hi>Gentian Heruet,</hi> is deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into sixe partes, and the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the same brieslie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</head>
   <p>THis deepe grounded and most lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Epistle of the right worshipfull Doctour, Maister <hi>Gentian Heruet,</hi> directed to those, that are declined &amp; fallen from the holie Romishe Catholike Church, is deuided into sixe speciall and principall partes: whereof the first is:</p>
   <p n="1">1 That the <hi>Heretikes</hi> and <hi>Huguenotes</hi> cannot repute them selues for faithfull peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, so farre forth as they do not beleeue all things, which our louing mother the holie Church beleeueth, without whom no salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can be obteined: &amp; especiallie, for that they will not beleeue the Transubstantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the breade into the verie bodie of Christ.</p>
   <p n="2">2 The second is knitte to the first: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie: They mainteine iniuriouslie, that wee ought to allowe nothing, but what is main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined by Scripture.</p>
   <p n="3">3 Thirdlie: They doe not beleeue nor
<pb facs="15"/>
allowe of seuen Sacramentes, especiallie▪ Auricular confession, the sacrament of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie, and the holie ointment of Vnc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
   <p n="4">4 Fourthlie: They doe the Catholikes great iniurie: insomuch as they repute them for idolaters and worshippers of idols.</p>
   <p n="5">5 Fifthlie: They seeke nothing else, but fleshlie libertie, and their owne appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites.</p>
   <p n="6">6 Sixthlie &amp; lastlie: Their Preachers are vnlearned Doultes, and leade a lewde, loathsome, and wicked life.</p>
   <p>In these sixe pointes is brieflie rehearsed the whole grounde and foundation of the holie Catholike doctrine, taught by the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mishe Church▪ and is so gallantlie establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed: yea, and all the Heretikes so finelie fetche ouer the coales, that there remaineth not a iotte to be spoken of anie further. Yet, seeing the ground and meaning of this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistles Authour, did stretch chieflie to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the Heretikes foorth into the fielde, and then Championlike, to combate with them: (like as hee sheweth that not long since the noble Knight, Maister <hi>Nicholas Villegaignon,</hi> who by his writing thought
<pb facs="15"/>
to egge foorth Maister <hi>Iohn Caluine,</hi> and by that meane to haue wonne a perpetuall fame, and euerlasting memorie.) It is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in like sorte fallen out with this good fellowe, as it did with the saide <hi>Villegaig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non.</hi> For his happe was, the better to fitte his purpose, to set downe (as hee before mencioned) manie doubtfull partes, verie darke and obscure reasons, yea, and some somewhat grose, supposing herewithall (as with a baight) to drawe the fishe into his net. Whereby (alas) it came to passe, that his good and godlie meaning was spelde and construed a wrong waie, and the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes did seeme to make a mocke of it, as though he were vnworthie to haue an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere to the same, considering that hee did shewe verie litle scripture or authoritie to affirme his matter: Euen in like manner as they had in times past iested with the foresaid <hi>Villegaignon.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Therefore it hath seemed both good and necessarie vnto vs, and for the preferre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the holie Romishe Church, most auaylable, that this present Epistle shoulde be at large declared: and verie strong and apte authorities to be brought in, for euerie part and parcell of the same, collected as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well
<pb facs="16"/>
out of the Scripture, as out of the bes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and fittest bookes of the auncient Fathers, Councels, and Decrees, wherewithall our louing mother the holie Churche is most supported: to the ende wee should the better conceiue the costlie hidden treasures, which are comprehended in this short Epistle: and that eache might vse the same to his most aduantage, and for a publike instruction, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping (thorough this holie and meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous worke) to purchase heauen, and withall to redeeme and set free two or three soules out of Purgatorie.</p>
   <pb n="1" facs="16"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="17"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>