<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Reuerend Father in God, IOHN by GODS Prouidence,
Lord Bishop of St. Asaph: Grace, Mercy, and Peace, be
Mul∣tiplied.</title>
           <author>Kingsmill, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119959_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04870</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15008</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119959</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Reuerend Father in God, IOHN by GODS Prouidence,
Lord Bishop of St. Asaph: Grace, Mercy, and Peace, be
Mul∣tiplied.</title>
                 <author>Kingsmill, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The drunkards vvarning : A sermon preached at Canterbury in the Cathedral Church of Christ. By Thomas Kingsmill Mr. of Arts, and preacher of the Word at Hyth, one of the Cinque-ports, in the county of Kent</title>
                 <author>Kingsmill, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 <publisher>Collins, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 40 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Reuerend Father in God, IOHN by GODS Prouidence,
Lord Bishop of St. <hi>Asaph:</hi> Grace, Mercy, and Peace, be
Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Charge that was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the Prophet <hi>Esay,</hi> by the
Lord himselfe, <hi>cry aloud, spare not, lift vp thy voice like a Trumpet,
and shewe my people their Transgressions, and the House of</hi> Iacob
<hi>their sinnes:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Esay 58.1</note>
      <hi>is also
imposed (Right Reuerend Father in God) on euery Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of the Word, in
these last<pb facs="3"/>daies and perilous times.</hi> For ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity
aboundeth now, as much as euer it did: <hi>there is no truth, nor mercy, nor
knowledge of God in the Land; by swearing, and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and killing, and
stealing, and committing adultery, men break out, and blood toucheth
blood.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hose. 4.1.2</note>
      <hi>They rise vp early in
the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that they may follow strong drinke, they continue vntill night,
till wine inflame them.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Esay 5.11.</note> Oh! now is
the time (if euer) for a Preacher to lift vp his voyce, and crye downe these
loud-crying sinnes.</p>
   <p>As for my selfe, I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready (by Gods assistance)
lifted vp my voyce in a Sermon, in a great Congregation, against the
beastly sinne of Drunkennes: but a man may crye louder with pen, then with
tongue: and bee heard further out of the Presse, then out<pb facs="3"/>of the
Pulpit. Therefore (sith there is no Labourer so simple, but may bring
somewhat to Gods buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding:) I haue incouraged my selfe, vpon assurance
of your Lordships pardon, humbly to commend this Sermon (as it was deliuered,
with out addition, or detraction) to the view of your Wisedome: and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
your protection, to the House<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde of Faith. Not doubting, but that which
hath passed the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable censure of so Reuerend, and so Learned an
assembly, as then were the Hearers: will now finde like acceptance with all
that be iudicious and indifferent Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
   <p>Many weighty reasons I could shew, that mooued me to Dedicate
these my slender labours vnto your Lordship: but I forbeare to
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse them, least I exceede an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle to so small a Booke;
and<pb facs="4"/>make the Wals as big, as the City. And thus hauing satisfied
my desire, by giuing some testimony of my duty to your Lordship:
fearing to hinder the course of your more serious cogitations, and actions;
I humbly take my leaue, and commend my selfe to your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and your
Lordship to the grace, and fauour of God in Christ.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From <hi>Hyth</hi> one of the Cinque-Ports in
<hi>Kent.</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>February</hi> 12. 1630</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships most obliged to all humble duty.
<hi>Thomas Kingsmill.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>