<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ A GENERAL SVM WHEREOF ALL THE XII. BOOKES OF AENEIDOS DO ENTREATE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1573</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119243_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14480</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24801</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119243</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ A GENERAL SVM WHEREOF ALL THE XII. BOOKES OF AENEIDOS DO ENTREATE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The whole .xii. bookes of the Æneidos of Virgill. Whereof the first .ix. and part of the tenth, were conuerted into English meeter by Thomas Phaër Esquire, and the residue supplied, and the whole worke together newly set forth, by Thomas Twyne Gentleman. There is added moreouer to this edition, Virgils life out of Donatus, and the argument before euery booke. There is added moreouer to this edition, Virgils life out of Donatus, and the argument before euery booke</title>
                 <author>Virgil</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1573</date>
                 <publisher>How (Howe, Haw), William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Veale (Vele), Abraham</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>316 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prose_summary">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>¶ A GENERAL SVM WHEREOF ALL THE XII. BOOKES OF AENEIDOS DO ENTREATE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN <hi>Troy</hi> was destroyed by the <hi>Greekes,</hi> and theyr most of Noblitie slayne, <hi>Aeneas</hi> beynge Sonne to prince
<hi>Anchises,</hi> and begotten of VENVS, a man of most valient courage and vertue (after great slaugh ter made on his enemies) was forced to flee his coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and takyng with him his Images and Goddes, whom he than worshipt for his auouries, withdrew himself to the sea, with his sunne
<hi>Ascanius,</hi> and his olde father <hi>Anchises</hi> and family to whom a great number of <hi>Troians,</hi> from euery quarter resorted, and ioynyng togethers vnder him, erected a Nauie of twenty ships and departed to seas, perswaded by their Goddes, that they should come to a land, where their kingdom should florish. First he arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in <hi>Thracia,</hi> and would haue remayned there, but vnderstanding that yonge <hi>Polydorus</hi> his cosin was murthered there by the kynge therof, for his Golde, he forsooke that coouetous land, and after he had builded a citie called of his name
<hi>Aeneas.</hi> From thence he sai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into <hi>Candy,</hi> where he was setled a whyle, but he felt his prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie wronge expounded, and was put from thence by a pestilence.</p>
   <p>Than remembryng that his auncient forefathers came out of
<hi>Italy</hi> and beynge better instructed by his Gods, that <hi>Italy</hi> should be his place and kyngdome appoynted: he cut another course to the land of <hi>Chaonia,</hi> where one <hi>Helenus</hi> raigned, beyng his kinsman a <hi>Troian,</hi> of whom he learned many thinges touching his Prophecie, and was newly refreshed with men, amour, and treasour. He passed from thence to the yle of <hi>scicil,</hi> and was there wel receiued of king <hi>Acestes</hi> his cosin, and there he buried his old father <hi>Anchises,</hi> by which time, vij. yeres wear almost expired. Than hauing but a short iourney to <hi>Italy,</hi> he went thitherwards out of <hi>Scicil,</hi> and by the way was taken with an horrible tempest, and driuen from <hi>Italy</hi> an extreme course, to the countrey of whyte
<hi>Moores</hi> in <hi>Affrike,</hi> and after extreme des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, was honourably there enterteyned of the Queene DIDO a widow, with whom he ioyned in loue, and remayned till his Gods
<gap reason="missing" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ pages">
         <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
      </gap>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>