<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Queenes most excellent Maiestie.</title>
           <author>Rowlands, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119192_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09758</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20025</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119192</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Queenes most excellent Maiestie.</title>
                 <author>Rowlands, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The power of praier : A sermon preached in the Cathedrall Church of Exeter in August. 1596. By Thomas Playfere Professour of Diuinitie for the Ladie Margaret in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Playfere, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waterson, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 44 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Queenes most excellent Maiestie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eligion,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gloriosa in deum pietas honoribus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giis immobile est fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. Cyrillus ad Theodos. de recta fide.</hi>
      </note> dread and deare Soueraigne, is an vnmoueable foū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of highest au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie and honour. O then howe blessed are all we? how sure and vnmooueable is our peace and ioy? God hauing blessed vs with a king, who in religion and learning excelleth all aliue, and his Maiestie with a Queene in due proportion answerable to himselfe. Wherefore as it is our dutie to ioyne both in our daily praiers: so neither would I separate you in my humble endeauours. For the present felicitie and glory of this realme resteth wholly in his Maiestie,
<pb facs="3"/>
but the future hope to haue these infinite blessings continued vpon vs and all our posteritie, euen vnto the worlds end, ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth from you both, in respect of that most happie royall issue you haue had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie, and which if it please God you may haue hereafter. Which as it will be our greatest securitie and comfort: so that it may be no danger to your Maiesties health, especially that which your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse now goeth withall, we shall continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and importunately pray and beseech at Gods hands. And what <hi>the power of praier</hi> is, this short sermō which I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume to offer vnto your sacred Maiestie, doeth in some sort shewe.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties most deuoted and obedient subiect, Thomas Playfere.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>