<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, RIGHT Worthy, and truely ennobled Hero, IOHN, Lord Loveliss, Baron of HURLEY, N. W. S. P. O.</title>
           <author>W., N.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119862_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15137</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25436</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119862</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, RIGHT Worthy, and truely ennobled Hero, IOHN, Lord Loveliss, Baron of HURLEY, N. W. S. P. O.</title>
                 <author>W., N.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Le hore di recreatione: or, The pleasant historie of Albino and Bellama : Discovering the severall changes of fortune, in Cupids journey to Hymens joyes. To which is annexed, il insonio insonadado, or a sleeping-waking dreame, vindicating the divine breath of poesie from the tongue-lashes of some cynical poet-quippers, and stoicall philo-prosers. By N.W. Master in Arts, of Queenes Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Whiting, Nathaneel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dawson, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Greene, Charles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Greene, Charles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Moseley, Humphrey</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 143, 25 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, RIGHT Worthy, and truely ennobled Hero, IOHN, Lord <hi>Loveliss,</hi> Baron of HURLEY, N. W. S. P. O.</head>
   <l>THE Law-enactors, whilst time fear'd the rod,</l>
   <l>Faign'd in their lawes, the presence of a god,</l>
   <l>Whose awful nod, &amp; wisedome grave shold b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
   </l>
   <l>As hand and signet unto their decree▪</l>
   <l>And such commanding aw that sacred name</l>
   <l>Struck in the vulgar breasts, it teen'd a flame</l>
   <l>Of Love and duty to their pious hefts.</l>
   <l>Thus <hi>Rhadamanthus</hi> in his lawes invests</l>
   <l>Him, whom prophaner times stil'd Heavens King▪</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Minos</hi> and others strike the selfe-same string.</l>
   <l>The Moral's mine: for in this quirking season</l>
   <l>When pride and envie steere the Helme of reason▪</l>
   <l>Itis, has with Presse-taskers been in use</l>
   <l>To presse the issue of their prose and Muse</l>
   <l>Vnder the Ensignes of some worthy Peere,</l>
   <l>Whose very name unsatyr can a jeere,</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="4"/>
And lock detraction up in beds of clay</l>
   <l>To sleepe their suns as Reare-mice doe the day.</l>
   <l>Then doe they bravely march with honour arm'd,</l>
   <l>Which, as the gods, the people, charmeth, charm'd,</l>
   <l>On this knowne priveledge feete I these lines,</l>
   <l>In which, though dimmer then your native, shines</l>
   <l>Your worth, en-fired by my kneed quill,</l>
   <l>Which claimes the scale not of desertes, but wil,</l>
   <l>In your acceptance and the worlds surmise</l>
   <l>Then Cynicks barke and Critekes beame your eyes.</l>
   <l>My quill's no pensill to emblason forth</l>
   <l>Your stainlesse honour and your matchlesse worth,</l>
   <l>As dust-borne flyes which 'bout the candle play</l>
   <l>Glide throughits arch, en-circle, fan, survay,</l>
   <l>Winke at the presence of dayes beamy blaze,</l>
   <l>Pur on the glasse, or on hearb-pillowes laze,</l>
   <l>Iust so my downy Muse in Distiques dare</l>
   <l>Feete the perfection of a silklesse faire</l>
   <l>Pumex each parr so trimly that her foe</l>
   <l>Sweares her cheekes roses and her bosome snow,</l>
   <l>Nay has strewd flowres of desertlesse prayse</l>
   <l>T' adorne the Tombe of good Sr worthy Crayse,</l>
   <l>Vnder this (ah mee) stone is laid (alas!)</l>
   <l>A man,—a knight—the best that ever was</l>
   <l>His prowesse war, his wisedome state did prove,</l>
   <l>His kindnesse kindred, and the world his love.</l>
   <l>But when shee should with her weake feathers soare</l>
   <l>To court a star, or with her feeble oare</l>
   <l>Strike such a sea of worth, ride honours ring.</l>
   <l>Shee dares not touch, or snaffle, saile or wing,</l>
   <l>Onely as he which limb'd those teares and sighs,</l>
   <l>Which <hi>Iphigenias</hi> death, from hearts and eyes</l>
   <l>Of kindred drew, but ore her father's brow</l>
   <l>(Telling the world hee mourud without an how,)</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="4"/>
Hee drew a vaile spake sorrow in excesse,</l>
   <l>So with a—must my muse expresse</l>
   <l>Your sacred worth, concluding it to bee</l>
   <l>Too high for any Bard, if not, for mee,</l>
   <l>Beside, the world of late has nicknam'd praise</l>
   <l>Calls it an elbow-claw and scraping bayes,</l>
   <l>Then pardon (Sir) this dearth, and iudge the why</l>
   <l>Is your worth soar'd above Parnasse's eye</l>
   <l>Let not your slights or <hi>nescio's</hi> (thogh most iust)</l>
   <l>Condemne my muse to bee en-seild with dust,</l>
   <l>Nor let presumption h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yste to your embrace</l>
   <l>But rather let your honour bate its place</l>
   <l>And stoope unto my measures, since the name</l>
   <l>Of Patrone awes oft times the breath of fame</l>
   <l>And by this honour shall you ere en-gage</l>
   <l>The knee, hand▪ duty, ayre and thriving age</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Of your honours ever humbly devoted, N. W.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>