<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Copie of the new Oath of Allegiance, deuided into eight Branches as it is in this Treatise explay∣ned.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119291_Fr1_4_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03941</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14049</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119291</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Copie of the new Oath of Allegiance, deuided into eight Branches as it is in this Treatise explay∣ned.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A Nevv-Yeares gift for English Catholikes, or A briefe and cleare explication of the new Oath of Allegiance : By E.I. student in Diuinitie; for a more full instruction, and appeasement of the consciences of English Catholikes, concerning the said Oath, then hath beene giuen them by I.E. student in Diuinitie, who compiled the treatise of the prelate and the prince</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 208, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="oath">
   <head>A Copie of the new <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> deuided into eight <hi>Branches</hi> as it is in this <hi>Treatise</hi> explay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</head>
   <p n="1">1. I A.B. doe truely and sincerely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, professe, testifie and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare in my conscience before God and the World, That our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord King <hi>Iames,</hi> is lawfull and rightfull King of this Realme, and of all other his Maiesties Dominions and Countries.</p>
   <p n="2">2. And that the Pope neither of himselfe, nor by any authoritie of the Church, or See of Rome, or by any other meanes which any other hath any Power or Authoritie to depose the King, or to dispose any of his Maiesties Kingdomes, or Dominions, or to authorize any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Prince to inuade or annoy Him or his Countries, or to discharge any of his Subiects of their Allegiance and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to his Maiestie, or to giue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cense or leaue to any of them to beare Armes, rayse Tumults, or to offer any
<pb n="2" facs="17"/>Violence, or hurt to his Maisties Royall Person, State, or Gouernment, or to any of his Maiesties Subiects within his Maiesties Dominions.</p>
   <p n="3">3. Also, I doe sweare from my heart, that notwithstanding any Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, or Sentence of Excommunication, or Depriuation made or granted, or to be made or granted by the Pope or his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessours, or by any Authoritie deriued or to be deriued from him, or his See against the said King, his Heires or Successours, or any absolution of the said Subiects from their Obedience, I will beare Faith and true Allegiance to his Maiestie, his Heires and Successours, and him and them will defend to the vttermost of my power, against all Conspiracies and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts whatsoeuer, which shall be made against His, or their Persons, their Crown and Dignitie, by reason or colour of any such Sentence or Declaration or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, and will doe my best endeuour to disclose and make knowne vnto his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, his Heires and Successours, all Treasons and Trayterous Conspiracies, which I shall know or heare of to bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him or any of them.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <pb n="3" facs="17"/>4. And I doe further sweare, That I doe from my heart abhorre, detest and abiure, as impious and hereticall, this damnable doctrine, and position, That Princes which bee excommunicated or depriued by the Pope may be deposed or murthered by their Subiects, or any other whatsoeuer.</p>
   <p n="5">5. And I doe beleeue, and in consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence am resolued, that neither the Pope, nor any person whatsoeuer hath power to absolue mee of this Oath, or any part thereof.</p>
   <p n="6">6. Which I acknowledge by good and full authoritie to bee lawfully ministred vnto me, and doe renounce all Pardons and Dispensations to the contrarie.</p>
   <p n="7">7. And all these things I doe plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and sincerely acknowledge and sweare, according to these expresse words by mee spoken, and according to the plaine and common sense and vnderstanding of the same words without any Equiuocation, or mentall euasion, or secret reseruation whatsoeuer.</p>
   <p n="8">8. And I doe make this recognition and acknowledgement heartily, willingly and truly vpon the true Faith of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian. So helpe me God.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>