<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣SHIPFƲLL AND MOST WOR∣THIE KNIGHT, HENRY VN∣TON, his most loving and munificent Pa∣tron, Grace, mercy, and peace in Christ bee multiplied.</title>
           <author>Lewes, R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119665_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05404</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15556</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119665</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣SHIPFƲLL AND MOST WOR∣THIE KNIGHT, HENRY VN∣TON, his most loving and munificent Pa∣tron, Grace, mercy, and peace in Christ bee multiplied.</title>
                 <author>Lewes, R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse : by R. Lewes, Baccheler of Divinitie, concerning Isaac his testament, disposed by the Lord to Iacobs comfort, though it were intended to Esau by his father; shewing, that the counsel of God shal stand, albeit the whole worlde withstande it</title>
                 <author>Lewes, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barnes, Joseph</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT</hi> WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFƲLL AND MOST <hi>WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THIE KNIGHT, HENRY VN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TON,</hi> his most loving and munificent Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, Grace, mercy, and peace in Christ bee multiplied.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE is no ende of making many bookes,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Eccle.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> and much reading is a wearinesse to the flesh: and in our carelesse daies, bookes may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther seeme to want rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, then readers to want bookes: whether men desire to tast, and see howe gratious the Lorde is, in learned and Godly discourses;<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 34.</note> or otherwise feede their own fancies on the chaffe and huskes of vnlearned and vnsavory pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets; fitter for children, then men, for infidels then Christians, for swine, then for the prodigal sonne. This consideration well digested,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Luke.</hi> 16.</note> had wel nigh induced mee to resolve with Licimus, that neither learned, nor vnlearned shoulde reade any of my doinges: not the one, because they are of that stupiditie, that they conceive not ones meaning; not the other, as beeing so wise, that I may dispare of satisfiyng their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act
<pb facs="3"/>
iudgementes. And doubtlesse, had not my good friend Master <hi>Wright,</hi> your Worships most diligent and learned Preacher, (at what time you most honourably managed your worthy embassage in <hi>Fraunce</hi> of late) had not that paineful member of the Church, and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, in peace and warre, devoted to <hi>Mars,</hi> as well as to <hi>Mercury</hi> when need required, &amp; Gods glory craved his service, had not that tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed souldier of Christ in the vniversity, citie, and country, yea and in the field among the pikes, having pervsed this sermon, greatly animated mee to publish it: I woulde never have brought stickes into the woode, and cast water into the sea, as I doe. Another speciall motive that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered my determination, was this, that I might some way testifie my most gratefull minde to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, &amp; my very singular good <hi>Lady,</hi> for your sundry, rare, &amp; vndeserved favours, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped &amp; multiplied vpō me. If any of Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters have iust cause, both to love, and honour their loving and liberal benefactors &amp; patrons: thē may that learned Preacher Master <hi>Iennings,</hi> that grave Devine, Master <hi>Sheward,</hi> that zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Trumpettor of Gods word, Master <hi>Wright,</hi> with others of good note in that famous vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versitie, but chiefly I, acknowledge your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship as a true patterne of all patrons. All men see your magnanimity, prudence, temperance,
<pb facs="3"/>
affability, constancy, and zeale to Gods glorie: but wee feede daily on your vertue, and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie God for such a stay at home, and such an ornament abroad, as is a spectacle of iustice, so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, and true Godlines. The Lorde alwaies blesse you with all his blessings, and blesse vs with you, to the vnspeakeable bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of Gods Church, for whose good, he hath raised you vp.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your worships most bounden, <hi>R. LEWES.</hi>
      </signed>
      <date>This xviij of <hi>Iune.</hi>
      </date>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>