<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honorable his singular good Lord, Sir William Spencer Knight, Baron Spencer of Wormeleighton, and to his Honorable Lady: Simon Wastell wisheth encrease of honour in this life, and e∣ternall happiness in the world to come.</title>
           <author>Wastell, Simon</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119488_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14801</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25102</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119488</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honorable his singular good Lord, Sir William Spencer Knight, Baron Spencer of Wormeleighton, and to his Honorable Lady: Simon Wastell wisheth encrease of honour in this life, and e∣ternall happiness in the world to come.</title>
                 <author>Wastell, Simon</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Microbiblion or The Bibles epitome: in verse : Digested according to the alphabet, that the Scriptures we reade may more happily be remembred, and things forgotten more easily recalled. By Simon Wastell somtimes of Queenes Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Wastell, Simon</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 506, 10 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Honorable his singular good Lord, Sir <hi>William Spencer</hi> Knight, Baron <hi>Spencer</hi> of <hi>Wormeleighton,</hi> and to his Honorable Lady: <hi>Simon Wastell</hi> wisheth encrease of honour in this life, and <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall happiness in the world to come.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable; Excellent is that sentence which <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gapetus</hi> wrote to <hi>Iustinian</hi> the Emperour long agoe, viz <hi>It is the crowne of Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ie which adornes a Potentate; for riches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> with vs, and glory vanisheth</hi> (saith hee) <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> that renowne, but that care of leading <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> liues according to Gods will, hath the promise of a Reward euerlastingly permanent, and of a Crowne immarcessible.</hi> And such hath
<pb facs="3"/> beene Gods mercy to your Honours, that he hath accumulated both internall and externall blessings vpon you, adding to your temporall greatness, spirituall graces, which make your Honors far more ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in Gods sight, then any terrene (though transcendent) felicitie can make you admired in the sight of men. The very Ethnicke could say, <hi>Nobilitas sola est at{que} vnica virtus.</hi> If the glimmering light of their purblind intellectualls, could ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate such like Panegy rickes, onely to their Morall and Socraticall vertues, how great are those prayses which are due to those Theologicall and heauenly gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which by a more diuine Spirit, are breathed into the soules of <hi>Dauids</hi> Saints on earth: Wherein though your Honors endowments haue not the meanest por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (they not being in you, meane, but euen Heroicall,) yet lest I should seeme (as the manner of some Dedicatory Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle is) to make my way to your Honour by a Parasiticall salutation of all your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>splendent vertues in my passage, and lest I do therein offend your right Noble and magnanimous disposition, whose property it is not to be very much affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="3"/> with those your deserued praises; and because also the action in mee would bee cozen-German to base flat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>erie: I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore passe them by in silence, whereat my mind shall neuer cease to afford the due tribute of perpetuall admiration. May it therefore please your Honor (as formerly it pleased your worthy Father my good Lord, now deceased) to patronize this little worke, which with all submission I present vnto your Honours. Sure I am, that those manifold fauours which I (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy I) from time to time haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from him and you, may challenge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall; which to be performed by mee is impossible, and to be testified by so small and slender a Dedication is in a manner indecent, as being in no waies proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to your large and copious demerits. But I am somewhat incouraged to make it trauell vnder your Honours Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage. I know that in all ingenuous and heauenly begotten soules, there is an affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in some sort analogical to God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, of accepting the desire for the deed▪ Receiue it therefore I beseech you, it is performed as I could, not as I would; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> your Honour looke to the matter of that
<pb facs="4"/> booke, it is an Epitome of Gods Oracles, and containes some of that <hi>aqua coelestis,</hi> or liuing waters of life and grace: If to the manner of handling the matter, it is briefe, and Alphabeticall, and metricall, for the better and surer memorie. Plaine also it is because the pure and spirituall word needs not the mixture of mans de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praued braine; and also because the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plest Christian may reape the greater be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, when all things are done to edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Thus presuming vpon your Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble protection, &amp; intreating the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that in blessing hee would blesse both your Honors, and honorable Progeny, I humbly take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors euer to be commanded, <hi>SIMON WASTALL</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>