<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Title and Summe of the fourth Dialogue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119210_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B16217</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24786.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119210</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Title and Summe of the fourth Dialogue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second part of the demoniacke vvorlde, or worlde possessed with diuels : conteining three dialogues: 1. Of familiar diuels. 2. Of lunaticke diuels. 3. Of the coniuring of diuels. Translated out of French into English by T.S. Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Viret, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Perrin (Perin), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Title and Summe of <hi>the fourth Dialogue.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His fourth Dialogue is intituled, Familiar Diuels, because it maketh menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the subtleties wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Sathan persecuteth the Gospel, vnder shewe of friendship and familiarity to the seruants of God. These Diuels are of the kind of those which before I called White Diuels, and therefore they may very well bee placed alike. And as for the matters here trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of in this Dialogue, there is mention made of the contradiction, that is in the Diuel, and the wicked: Of the commendation which they giue to the good to an euil end. And contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, how they discommend and dishonour al such as praise and honour Christ, his seruants, and Gospel.</p>
   <p>The manner howe the Papistes honour the Gospel, and of the true honour, or dishonour that may be done to the same.</p>
   <p>The honour that the enimies of Christian discipline doe to the Gospel, whiche they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse
<pb facs="4"/> only in the lippes.</p>
   <p>The Sorceresses diuel of Philippi.</p>
   <p>The praise and commendation which the Diuel giueth to the ministery and ministers of the Gospel.</p>
   <p>The meanes wherewith the Diuel vseth to fight against the Gospel.</p>
   <p>The Diuel transfigured into an Angell of light.</p>
   <p>Of the troth which the Diuel may speake, and how we ought to iudge of the troth.</p>
   <p>Of the feigned friendship that certeine shorne hypocritical Balamites shewe vnto the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel, that they might thereby hinder the course thereof.</p>
   <p>What fauourable accusations the enemies of the Gospel are woonted to vse against the true seruants of God.</p>
   <p>Of the diuers and sundry false shewes whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the Diuel maketh.</p>
   <p>What good affection the wicked beare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God and good men.</p>
   <p>Of the charitie of Iudas.</p>
   <p>With what colour the mainteiners of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ vse to colour their false religion.</p>
   <p>What iolly shiftes they haue, that glory of the profession of the Gospel, and yet followe
<pb facs="5"/> the old manner of Poperie.</p>
   <p>How they condemne the Gospel, before they know any cause why.</p>
   <p>The fayned friendship which the enemies of the truth vse towards Princes.</p>
   <p>What fauour the wicked find among magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates.</p>
   <p>What regard Magistrates ought to haue to Backbiters &amp; slaunderers.</p>
   <p>What greate mischiefe is ordinarily done vnto the seruantes of God.</p>
   <p>What the causes are why men cannot abide nor away with the seruantes of God.</p>
   <p>The iudgement of God for our vnthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of despising &amp; hating of the troth: &amp; of the power and force of illusion and errour.</p>
   <p>What the causes are, why we rather follow lyes then trueth.</p>
   <p>The lets that hinder vs from the knowledge of the truth.</p>
   <p>What kind of men they bee, vnto whom, Iesus Christ is a teacher and a Schoolemaister.</p>
   <p>The Preseruatiues against error and false doctrine.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>