<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the indifferent Readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119039_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14292</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24609</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119039</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the indifferent Readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The golden fleece : diuided into three parts, vnder which are discouered the errours of religion, the vices and decayes of the kingdome, and lastly the wayes to get wealth, and to restore trading so much complayned of. Transported from Cambrioll Colchos, out of the southermost part of the iland, commonly called the Newfoundland, by Orpheus Iunior, for the generall and perpetuall good of Great Britaine</title>
                 <author>Vaughan, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Williams, Francis</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 149, 1, 105, 1, 96 pages, 1 folded leaf of plates, map, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the indifferent Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Vdicious Readers,</hi> in this busie time I know you will won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, how I dare bring forth <hi>new Proiects</hi> shadowed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a glorious <hi>Title</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme <hi>Errours,</hi> and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store <hi>Trading,</hi> when men of farre greater vnderstanding doe find themselues puzled, grauelled, and almost at their wits end, accounting the taske to exceed all the labours of <hi>Hercules.</hi> The presumption, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, is great. Yet when I had called to mind that Action of <hi>Diogenes,</hi> how he tumbled vp and downe his <hi>Tub</hi> very laboriously at such time, when all his Neighbours prepared themselues for Armes, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solued likewise to do somewhat, and by toffing too and fro the barrell of my Conceits, albeit barren and inferiour vnto many thousands in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to encourage others to lend their hands vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Publicke prop,</hi> if not perpetually to secure it, yet for a time to stay it, vntill their wisdomes had concluded on stronger meanes. Among many <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies,</hi> which I haue heere produced, perhaps they may light on some not to bee contemned. At the least those which are <hi>Thriftie,</hi> will con mee thankes for reprehending of <hi>multiplicities of Law Suits and Prodigality:</hi> Both which do keep our <hi>State</hi> in an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ballance. The one vice disunites our hearts from
<pb facs="4"/>
the harmony of Concord; making vs vnworthy of the Communion of Saints, and consequently of the <hi>Lords Table,</hi> and the other disperseth our substance, that wee cannot yeeld sufficient supplies to saue the honour of our <hi>Countrey.</hi> What a masse of treasure doe we yeerely spend in forreigne Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities? What abundance of Silkes doe we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume on our backes? What a deale of Gold and Siluer lace? while the wary <hi>Spaniard,</hi> who hath the <hi>Indies</hi> in possession, contents himselfe with his owne Fashion and lesser moderation both in Apparell and Diet. The <hi>Dutch</hi> they follow no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trauagant Attires. Euery man is distinguished in his Ranke: some by wearing a Copper Chaine, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers a Siluer; and the Nobler of Gold. In <hi>France</hi> the meaner sort of women weare Hoods of Taffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, other of Satten, and the better of Veluet. No man intrudes into anothers vocation. But with vs, <hi>Ioane is as good as my Lady,</hi> Citizens Wiues are of late growne Gallants. The Yeoman doth gentilize it. The Gentleman scornes to be behind the Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Yea, many are not ashamed to goe as braue as the <hi>King.</hi> And if a Wiseman chance to taxe them for their prodigall humour: They will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere, that it is for the credit of the <hi>Kingdome;</hi> which indeed is a most weake excuse: for what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounds to the publike damage, and losse ought not to be termed honourable, as not safe nor wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy for a discreet Inhabitant to vaunt of. Such gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die sights neuer last aboue a nine dayes wonder, nay, sometimes one only day, like your Pageants,
<pb facs="5"/>
and then the memory becomes stale, their Silkes out of fashion. But the example, like a Leprosie, is transferred from the Court to the Citie, from the Citie to the Countrey. Of these and many other abuses, which our <hi>State</hi> had need to looke into, I purpose in this <hi>Treatise</hi> to discourse, submitting the necessitie of their Reformation to the <hi>Higher Powers</hi> consideration, as is meete and conuenient. In the first Part I will endeuour to remoue the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of <hi>Religion,</hi> in the Second the Diseases of the Common-wealth: And in the Third Part I will discouer the certainty of the <hi>Golden Fleece,</hi> which shall restore vs to all worldly Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>