<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Prologue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119919_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06480</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16949</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119919</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Prologue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A moral and pitieful comedie, intituled, All for money. Plainly representing the maners of men, and fashion of the world noweadayes. Compiled by T. Lupton</title>
                 <author>Lupton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 <publisher>Mundee (Munday), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ward, Roger</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Prologue.</head>
   <l>WHat good gift of God but may be misused?</l>
   <l>Nay what good thing newe but to euill is applye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
   </l>
   <l>Howe is the Scripture with many abused</l>
   <l>With mouth it is talked, but with liuing denyed</l>
   <l>What iewel it is the iust haue well tryed</l>
   <l>For if that be a Iewell that comfortes in care</l>
   <l>Than this is a iewell of other most rare.</l>
   <l>It is the consolacion of the repentant sinner</l>
   <l>It is the chiefe comfort of Christes persecuted</l>
   <l>The faithfull and wronged person haue therein pleasure</l>
   <l>The penitent which are with pouertie oppressed</l>
   <l>Thereby are made richer then the couetous and wicked</l>
   <l>For it is our Euidence of all our ioye and saluation</l>
   <l>Whereby we are certified that Christe hath payd our raunsome.</l>
   <l>Thereby many godly sciences needefull be studied</l>
   <l>Whereof the bodie hath onely the fruition</l>
   <l>As the Physicall arte whereby the sicke are cured.</l>
   <l>Musicke through whose harmonie the minde hath consolation.</l>
   <l>Cosmographi which describes the countrie, citie and Nacion.</l>
   <l>Geometri, through whose subtill arte and measuring</l>
   <l>At this day there is much costly and sumptuouse building.</l>
   <l>The pleasant science of Astrologie whereby Gods wonderfull workes</l>
   <l>Are rather to be marked then mused on, or meruayled:</l>
   <l>Which arte is not hidde from the Sarisons, Paganes and Turkes</l>
   <l>Whereby such starres and heauens they may knowe were not created</l>
   <l>But by a mightie God, whose name for euer be honoured.</l>
   <l>And the moouing of the Planetes to be learned very strange</l>
   <l>With the swifte course of the Moone who monethly keepes her change.</l>
   <l>Yet all other sciences with these before delated</l>
   <l>Shall vanishe as the smoke, and be nothing at length</l>
   <l>Yet heauenlie Theologie, Gods worde before declared</l>
   <l>Hath bene, is nowe, and euer of such force and strength</l>
   <l>That though heauen and earth perishe, as Christes woordes meaneth</l>
   <l>Yet his worde shall abyde and remayne for euer:</l>
   <l>The following whereof God graunt we endeuer.</l>
   <l>Notwithstanding Epicures and belly goddes so swarme</l>
   <l>Farced, and flowing with all kinde of euill</l>
   <l>That they feare not to doe any kinds of harme</l>
   <l>So much they fauour their father the deuill</l>
   <l>The Scripture is taken with them as no Iewell</l>
   <l>Their mindes are so much on their riches and goods</l>
   <l>That the learned they esteeme lesse then fooles that weare hoods.</l>
   <l>But if the learned be riche, then be they esteemed:</l>
   <l>Not for their learning but for their goodes sake.</l>
   <l>Such power haue riches and money obteyned</l>
   <l>That the riche are helde vppe, the poore fooles in the lakes</l>
   <l>God giue them grace not so much on goodes to make:</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Diues</hi> me thinkes might be to them a warning,</l>
   <l>For pleasure therein, lyeth nowe in hell burning.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="3"/>What mettayle is this money that makes men so mad?</l>
   <l>What mischiefe is it thereby is not wrought?</l>
   <l>What earthly thing is not therefore to be had?</l>
   <l>What hath bene so loued but money hath bought?</l>
   <l>What vertue or goodnes of vs so much sought,</l>
   <l>Who doth not wishe for money, and that euery day:</l>
   <l>I would I had thus much money eache one doth say.</l>
   <l>Howe many for money haue bene robbed and murthered?</l>
   <l>Howe many false witnes and for money periured?</l>
   <l>Howe many wyues from their husbands haue bene enticed?</l>
   <l>Howe many maydens to folly for money allured?</l>
   <l>Howe many for money haue spirites and deuilles coniured?</l>
   <l>Howe many friends for money haue bene mortall foes?</l>
   <l>Mo mischieues for money then I can disclose.</l>
   <l>Howe many Kings and Princes for money haue bene poysoned,</l>
   <l>Howe many betrayers of their countrey for money euery day,</l>
   <l>Howe many with money from true iudgement are led:</l>
   <l>Did not the prophete Balam curse gods people for money?</l>
   <l>Did not <hi>Iudas</hi> for money his master Christ betraye?</l>
   <l>Whereof he had no ioye, when he the same had done,</l>
   <l>But like a damned wretch honge him selfe full soone.</l>
   <l>One asked <hi>Diogenes</hi> why golde did looke so wan:</l>
   <l>No marueill said he it is though he so pale doe looke,</l>
   <l>For euery one layes wayte to catche him if they can.</l>
   <l>Fewe will take the paynes to catche holde on gods booke:</l>
   <l>Money ill vsed is the diuels snare and hooke.</l>
   <l>Whereby many are brought to endles damnation:</l>
   <l>But the godly doe bestowe it to their saluation.</l>
   <l>Fyer is the good gift and creature of God▪</l>
   <l>Whereby we may do good and also wickedly:</l>
   <l>We may warme the poore therewith as charitie hath vs bode,</l>
   <l>And also seeth the meate wherewith to feede the hungrie:</l>
   <l>We may keepe houses therewith, as many haue done truely:</l>
   <l>And we may cut our necessaries and meate with our knyfe</l>
   <l>Wherewith many haue cut their owne throtes &amp; bereued thē of their life.</l>
   <l>Thus the creature of God is not euill of him selfe,</l>
   <l>But through our misuse from good to euill conuerted:</l>
   <l>Euen so money ill vsed is a most wicked pelfe.</l>
   <l>And also as good where well it is, bestowed.</l>
   <l>Let all people take heede lest it of them be hoarded:</l>
   <l>For at the last day against them it will witnes,</l>
   <l>And then that they had not done it, to late for to wishe.</l>
   <l>And because that euery man of money is so greedie</l>
   <l>Our Authour a pleasant Tragedie with paynes hath now made,</l>
   <l>Whereby you may peceyue, All thing is for money:</l>
   <l>For <hi>Omnia pecunia effici possunt,</hi> as in <hi>Tullies</hi> sentence is said▪</l>
   <l>In hearing vs attentiuely we craue but your ayde,</l>
   <l>Beseeching God, the hearers that thereby shalbe touched,</l>
   <l>May rather amend their faultes, then therewith be grieued.</l>
   <trailer>The ende of the Prologue.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>