<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Honora∣ble, my very good Lord and Maister, Henrie Carey, Baron of Hunsdon, Knight of the most noble Order of the Garter: Lord Chamberlaine of her Maiesties most Honorable Houshold: Lord Gouernour of Barwick: Lord Warden of the East Marches for and anenst Scotland: Lord Lieftenant of Suffolke and Norfolke: Captaine of her Ma∣iesties Gentlemen Pencioners: and one of her High∣nes most Honorable Priuie Counsell.</title>
           <author>Baxter, Nathaniel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119589_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14783</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25082a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119589</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Honora∣ble, my very good Lord and Maister, Henrie Carey, Baron of Hunsdon, Knight of the most noble Order of the Garter: Lord Chamberlaine of her Maiesties most Honorable Houshold: Lord Gouernour of Barwick: Lord Warden of the East Marches for and anenst Scotland: Lord Lieftenant of Suffolke and Norfolke: Captaine of her Ma∣iesties Gentlemen Pencioners: and one of her High∣nes most Honorable Priuie Counsell.</title>
                 <author>Baxter, Nathaniel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Albions England : a continued historie of the same kingdome, from the originals of the first inhabitants thereof: and most the chiefe alterations and accidents there hapning: vnto, and in, the happie raigne of our now most gracious soueraigne Queene Elizabeth. VVith varieti of inuentiue and historicall intermixtures. First penned and published by VVilliam VVarner: and now reuised, and newly inlarged by the same author</title>
                 <author>Warner, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Joan</publisher>
                    <distributor>Broome (Brome), Joan</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 336 pages, folded plates, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, my very good Lord and Maister, <hi>Henrie Carey, Baron of Hunsdon, Knight of the</hi> most noble Order of the Garter: Lord Chamberlaine of her <hi>Maiesties most Honorable Houshold: Lord Gouernour of</hi> Barwick: Lord Warden of the East Marches for and anenst <hi>Scotland:</hi> Lord <hi>Lieftenant of</hi> Suffolke <hi>and</hi> Norfolke: <hi>Captaine of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties Gentlemen Pencioners: and one of her High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes most Honorable Priuie Counsell.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His our whole Iland, ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called <hi>Brutaine,</hi> but more aunciently <hi>Albion,</hi> presently containing two Kingdomes, <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> is cause (right Honorable) that to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish the former, whose only Occurrents I abridge, from the other, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from our Historie, I intitle this my Booke <hi>ALBIONS ENGLAND.</hi> A subiect, in troth, (without vaine-glory be it spokē) worthy your Honorable Patronage: had it passed frō the
<pb facs="3"/>
Pen of a more countenaunced Author. But for great Personages gratefully to entertaine the good wils of meane workemen, is answerable to themselues, and animating to feeble Artists. I therefore secure of your Honors Clemencie, &amp; herein not vnlike to <hi>Phaëton,</hi> who at the first did fearefully admire euē the Pallace of <hi>Phoebus,</hi> but anon feareles aduenture euen the presence of <hi>Phoebus,</hi> (hauing dedicated a former Booke to him that from your Honor deriueth his Birth) now also present the like to your Lordship, with so much the lesse doubt and so much the more duty, by how much the more I esteeme this my latter laboure of more Valew, &amp; I owe, &amp; your Lordship expecteth especiall dutie at the hands of your Seruant. And thus (right Honorable) hoping better than I may offend, desirous to please, desperate of praise, &amp; destitute of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Present, I make Tender onely of good will, more I haue not, for your Honors good word, lesse I hope not.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships most humble and dutifull Seruant,
W. Warner.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>