<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Authors Preface to the READER.</title>
           <author>Welles, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119607_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14923</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25231</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119607</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Authors Preface to the READER.</title>
                 <author>Welles, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The soules progresse to the celestiall Canaan, or heavenly Jerusalem : By way of godly meditation, and holy contemplation: accompanied with divers learned exhortations, and pithy perswasions, tending to Christianity and humanity. Divided into two parts. The first part treateth of the divine essence, quality and nature of God, and his holy attributs: and of the creation, fall, state, death, and misery of an unregenerated man, both in this life and in the world to come: put for the whole scope of the Old Testament. The second part is put for the summe and compendium of the Gospell, and treateth of the Incarnation, Nativity, words, works, and sufferings of Christ, and of the happinesse and blessednesse of a godly man in his state of renovation, being reconciled to God in Christ. Collected out of the Scriptures, and out of the writings of the ancient fathers of the primitive Church, and other orthodoxall divines: by John Welles, of Beccles in the County of Suffolk</title>
                 <author>Welles, John, of Beccles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Anne.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Griffin, Edward 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Shepherd (Sheppard), Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 304, 1, 308-372, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The Authors Preface to the READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Christian, friendly Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and loving country-man; about ten yeeres since past, at spare houres, as my daily em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments would give me leave, I first be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to collect and gather out of Scripture, and other godly and learned Authors, many prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall and speciall notes worthy observation and remembrance. When I first began, I had not thought to bring it forth to the worlds view, but onely for my owne private com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, to the comfort of my minde; the more I gathered, the more I was ravished, and being thus in holy contemplation, the matter being holy, excellent and heavenly, I was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited, and stirred up by godly motion, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake a worke so excellent, which through want of learning, I knew my selfe altogether
<pb facs="6"/> unable to performe what my heart desired; yet yeelding obedience to the holy motion, and humbly craving, and earnestly praying the power divine to assist mee with his holy Spirit, to accomplish that which I had a desire to finish,<note place="margin">Phil. 4.13.</note> and had already begun; knowing, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> saith, that <hi>I am able to doe all things,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Phil. 1.12.</note>
      <hi>through the helpe of him that strengtheneth mee.</hi> And praying for his blessing, to blesse my endeavours, and then in the name of God,<note place="margin">Prov. 16.3,</note> with cheerfulnesse of heart, I persevered in my purpose, committing the successe unto him,<note place="margin">Eccles. 8.</note> in whose power it is to blesse with his grace; whatsoever businesse is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to his glory: For fithence <hi>Salomon</hi> himselfe saith, that mans wisdome is unper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and his knowledge in each Science un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, therefore I being utterly destitute of that wisdome, and but of slender knowledge, neither may,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.5. 2 Cor. 4.5.</note> doe, nor will I presume to thinke that by any meanes I am able of my selfe, to perform my desired enterprize, as of my selfe, or bring to perfection so waighty a matter, and so intricate:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.4.</note> For though I may say with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> I know not what I have mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
<pb facs="6"/> or wherein I have erred; yet will I not dare to report, or be encouraged to affirme that my worke is perfect, or that I have fully performed my long-wished attempt; and for that cause, standing in doubt, whether I have concealed many truthes, or adventured to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port some errors, which by my weakenesse of judgement, or slacknesse of consideration, have happened in this Treatise, but through his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine assistance, have here accomplished what my soule desired to bring to passe, I meane, this poore Tractate, named <hi>the Soules Progresse to the celestiall Canaan;</hi> divided into two parts; the first part treateth of the divine Essence of God, and his holy attributes, and of the creation, state, death, and misery of man, put for the whole passage of the old Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the second part is put for the summe and compendium of the Gospel, and treateth of the words, workes and sufferings of Christ, and of the happinesse and blessednesse of a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man, in his state of renovation, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God in Christ: which poore mite I doe cast into the worlds treasury, knowing that the great learned orthodoxall Writers
<pb facs="7"/> out of their superfluous abundance, have cast in much, but like the poore widow in the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel;<note place="margin">Luke 21.4.</note> I out of my want, doe cast in, even all that I have, beseeching the Lord to give it a free passage in its progresse, and that it may take that good effect in mens hearts, as is by mee desired, to the glory of God; for whose sake, my soules comfort, and the good of my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and Christian brethren, I undertooke this worke; take it in good worth; if it be not as it should be, impute it to the want of learning, and not to the want of a loving heart to doe my country good: For the places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture cited in the margent are right, take them on my word; but howsoever it be, trouble not thy selfe, gentle Reader: For if it be good that is said, and agreeable to Scripture, make use of it, and be not solicitous to know from whose workes it is drawne. The manner is plaine and simple, and craveth pardon for what is amisse. Thus committing the worke it selfe to thy courteous acceptance, and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall reading, and both it and thee to the Lord, desiring him to honour thee with his grace, that you may so know him, as that you
<pb facs="7"/> may be knowne of him, what remaines, but that I pray unto God, that both you and I, and all them that shall reade this Booke, may profit by it, by the assistance of his holy Spirit, to the furthering of their salvation, to the glory of his Name, through Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus our Lord: in Christian love I take my leave,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>IOHN WELLES.</signed>
      <dateline>
         <date>
            <hi>October 22. 1638.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>