<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119050_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10148</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20403</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119050</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of the knovvledge and conducte of warres : two bookes, latelye wrytten and sett foorth, profitable for suche as delight in hystoryes, or martyall affayres, and necessarye for this present tyme</title>
                 <author>T. P.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Tottell (Tathyll, Tothill, Tottyl), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 48 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Climate, or Region of the firmament, vnder which euery Countrey is planted &amp; setled, hath great force and influence, for the temperature &amp; complexion of mens bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, whiche also worketh sundrie effectes &amp; motyons in the myndes &amp; disposityons of thē, as for profe: Experience sheweth, that the Italian and Frenchman comenlye, is more enclyned to be courtlyke, prompte, and quicke of spirite, then the Dutcheman or Flemyng, &amp; the Spaniard, the Moore or Libyen, more nimble, more politique, and more subiect to choler, enuie, and pryde thē the man of Sweden, or the Muscouyte being more of fleug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matike constitution of bodye. The Greekes also, for this purpose, haue bene noted of learned men, to be by disposition and motion of nature exquisite searchers of cunninge in manuel craftes, &amp; verie studious in the liberall Sciences. The Egiptians and Iewes (by obseruation of wise men) are founde more geuen to superstitions and idolatric, then other nations: The Scythien, the Turke, and Tartarian addicted to crueltie, and the Persian to delicate life. But to drawe nearer vnto our skope, and marke, The Englyshe man (for whom this trauaill is taken) liuinge in a fertile countrye, and vnder a temperate Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, and thereby indewed with the more excellent disposition of mynde and bodie, beinge by the great bountie and blessynge of God not vnfurnished of anie vertue, that other people haue: So is there principallye seene in him, that yet remaines of the right stampe or race vndegenerate, an honourable desire to the exercyse of armes, hauinge by the prycke of Magnanimitie, a victorious mynde, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectinge fame, soueraigntie, and honour aboue other nations. But least I flatter him whom I loue, and woulde to be warned, Two one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye poyntes of imperfection, thoughe not yet, nowe, notablie excea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to anie great vice, (how? be it some defectes) are noted to bee in a great parte of Englishe men, whiche maye well bee refourmed. The one is, negligence or securitie: The other is mutabilitie, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable chaunging of mynde, principallie shewed in delectable thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, not of the greatest importaunce, as in daintie fare of sundrye delicate meates, diuers curious buyldinges, and most of all in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye
<pb facs="4"/>
almost infynite guyses, sortes, and fashions of habyte, yea and diguysed attyre, whearein, oftentimes is planted and bestowed so muche care and studie, that, there is the lesse employed on vertuous and neadefull exercyses. Yea sometime, while tryfles are regarded, thinges most commendable &amp; requisite are neglected. I doe not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempne them, but commende ornamentes, they are to bee regarded in a sorte, and not to be reiected: but more worthye thinges to be pla ced before, and with greatest desire &amp; diligence endeuoured. Weare it not to be pytied, that the great helpe and benefite of nature geeuen to this nation, in highnesse of courage, and noble inclynation to prowesse, should be defaced &amp; obscured, that no light effecte, or ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue thereof shoulde appeare? yes, but there is an other thinge in it, besydes the pittye of the matter, which is the qualitie and necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this time, wherein wee liue, whiche if it be well considered, will sufficientlie perswade (where iudgement is, thoughe feawe wordes be vsed hearein) to stirre vp the sleapinge myndes from slewthe, to abandon tryfles, and fall to the commendable practises meete for men, and necessarie for the troublesome state of the worlde. For what is in want or lett that the Englisheman, hauinge a stronge bodie, good will enoughe, and a fertyle countrey, sufficient to supplye the prouysion and maintenance of a myghtie armye, shoulde not excell other nations in deades &amp; exployctes of Armes, and extende the victorious forces of this Realme, by renowmed conquestes farre? Surely the defectes are, lacke of endeuour, &amp; discipline. By these the Citie of Rome, from extreme pouertye (hauinge most bare &amp; slender <note place="margin">Practise &amp; skyll. Dido obtay ned somuch grounde, to buylde the Citie vpon, as might be compassed vvith an ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es hyde, and that she cut in thonges.</note> beginninges, their territoryes beinge as short, as the content or boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the smallest shyre within this lande) in shorte time, aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced her Empyre ouer the whole worlde, By these likewyse, the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaginoys, whose towne, countrey, &amp; dominion, weare first bounded by the circuyte and compassinge of an Oxes hyde: Soone after, they grewe in greatnes, to checke &amp; encoūter the mightie estate of Rome, &amp; once put the same in daunger of a mate, by this skill, the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of Macedone beynge not great, vnder the conducte of the most puissant Alexander, subdued the mightie Monarchye of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sians, with a great parte of the worlde besides, and in his mynde had the plott and conquest of the whole, yea &amp; of an other worlde, if it
<pb facs="4"/>
had bene to be founde, but GOD stayed his victories, (whiche men coulde not) by cuttinge of his life, about thyrtie yeares of his age. The mightie and victorious Alexander of Englande, whose most re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noumed battaile of Agincourte, and sudry triumphant conquestes in Fraunce, made the whole worlde to shake, was cut of in like youthe, <note place="margin">Henrye the fifthe.</note> from no lesse hope, then the other greate Alexander, after that hee had by most excellent disciplyne of warre, in shorte time obtayned many greate victories. By this arte and practise, of later time, an other Pirrhus, Prince of the little Countrey Epirus in Grecia, resisted the huge and grosse powers of the greate Turke: By this, the greate <note place="margin">G. Scander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beg. Baiazet.</note> Tamberlane conquered him, and made him his miserable vassall and captyue, in feawe yeares, arysinge from a poore Neteherde, to be Lorde ouer the most mightie Prince in the worlde. By this excercise partelie, thoughe principallye by the huge monstrous multitudes of barbarous Scithyens, the Turkes in no longe time, haue subdued so many kinges and countreyes, and extended their Empyre so farre, into all the three partes of the worlde, &amp; yet prosecuteth and thrus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the same further daylie. Now it is to be remēbred that the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and practyse of the actes and feates of armes, principallie and properlye are of the profession of noble menne, and gentlemen of greate reuenues. For and by whiche, they were firste ordayned and preferred into that place, to be a wall and defence for their countrye. For the poore man hath not, wheareof to lyue of his owne, if hee em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploye time, or expences hearein. And thearefore the other, ought to geue example, bothe by his owne industrye in such practises, and also maintayne the same in the meanor sorte. Securitye and longe peace breadeth idlenes, whiche sucketh the valure out of noble myndes. A plaine proofe wheareof, &amp; of the hurte that groweth theareby, ys <note place="margin">The arte of Nobilitie.</note> had by the Romaynes, whiche in xxiiij. yeares space, betwene the first and seconde warres of Carthage, weare so farre growen out of vse and good practyse of armes, that wheare as before, they weare euery wheare Conquerours. In the seconde warres, they went, alwaies to wracke, till their sundrye greate losses droue them vnto their olde course &amp; Bias againe. Thus seeynge the causes of these defectes in Englishe men discouered, the cure is the more plaine &amp; casie, &amp; the rather, if the remedie vnto the other impediment be applyed, that
<pb facs="5"/>
ys want of skill or discipline, which proceadinge &amp; growing partlie vpon the other cause, vz. lacke of practise, the reste, is also to bee sought for and supplyed. For as vse &amp; excercise, maketh prompt, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, &amp; skilfull in manye thinges: So by most iust &amp; sure argumēt, the contrarie, which is the priuation, or lacke theareof, worketh, &amp; causeth cōtrary effectes: And yet not alwayes in all thinges, doth ex cercise or labour bringe knowledge &amp; perfection, but theare must be skill with all, which in this matter, is for the more parte to be obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by collection &amp; iudgement of the reportes, historyes, &amp; Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles written of warres. For in matters of importāce, which haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Cauteles, difficultyes, &amp; obseruatiōs: yt is necessarie that a way be opened, &amp; a light geuen vnto him, which would be a passynger hearein, to directe &amp; encline his course vnto this knowledge: For o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise he shal trauail &amp; wāder in the darke trades, &amp; vnknowē pathes, like a blynde man, which goeth he woteth not whither. And proue, to that there be diuers groūdes, rules, stratagemes, &amp; enstruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiōs to be set downe, printed, &amp; obserued in the memory, of good soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, as a plot &amp; foūdation of their busines: The sūdrie bookes wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of these matters in the latine tongue, &amp; other lāguages, by great learned &amp; expert men, may be a sufficient argumēt hearein. Besides that, reason wil easelye discusse, that the knowledge of the aūcient orders &amp; gouernmēt of warre, with the sundrie sortes &amp; attyre of battail, vsed amonge sundry nations, their maners &amp; practises, the exāples of the antiquitie, the experiēce, pollicies, prudent coūsailes, most profitable and pitthye preceptes, and admonishmentes, moste excellent experimentes, instructyons, behauiour &amp; discipline of the greatest chyeftaines, &amp; most renoumed conquerours that euer weare, be requisite &amp; needefull vnto a good Captaine: for what is the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience or opynion of one man, to the practise &amp; iudgement of a great nūber of such, as haue conquered in all Countreys, vanquished great armyes, ouerthrowē many mightie battailes, &amp; honorablie passed al daūgers of warre? whose doinges be iudicially, &amp; perfectlie noted of most learned and wise men, in sundrie great volumes &amp; writinges, for example &amp; profite of the posteritie, which the vnlearned can not tast or attayne, without some preparatiue by plaine plott drawen, or introductiō in apt order made, to lead thē into the knowledge therof.
<pb facs="5"/>
For accomplishinge wheareof, thoughe, thoroughe the grossenes of my style, lacke of experience, and sundrye kindes of knowledge, wheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with a writer of so wayghtie a matter, ought to be furnished, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with my study of breuitie hearein, &amp; little leasure, which from myne other affaires I had, one time longe after an other, to accomplish this same, I shall not sufficientlye in all pointes, content the exquisite iudgementes whiche are to deame heareof: Yet for the necessitie and scarcitie of writing in this matter: (A willynge minde, and faithful affection to profite my Countreye, thrusting me foorth to beare a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thē to bigge for my shoulders:) This labour of myne, may be a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge to encourage sume other, of their greatest experience, to make larger addition, or supplie hearein. For yet nowe I finde Vegetius one lye, an auncient writer, &amp; Machiauell of these affayres, well trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated into Englishe, whiche aucthours being bothe expert in warres, and also verye learned, their industrie herein is of so much the more commendation, as those two qualityes are rare, and seldome mete to gether: For suche a one as hath knowledge, ioygned with courage &amp; experience, is a man worthe men, &amp; maye auayle more then a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: Yet for that the saide Machiauel is deamed sum what diffuse in his treatyse, his opinions also not altogether agreeinge with all mens iudgementes, nor reachinge to many matters mete for the state of our English warres: And Vegetius being a writter, when warres weare vsed in an other course, then they are nowe a dayes: Yt is therefore wished more to be done in this behalfe. And it is maruail to see, how the studies of many men haue ben addicted in this our time, hauing store of rype wittes, whiche can doe verye well: Yet amonge so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye bookes, as are written daylie, of dreames &amp; fantacies, introduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to pleasure, familier fruiteles talkinges, eloquent, formall or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, little material, of pleasant metinges &amp; fables amonge women, of Caunterbury, or courser tales, with diuers iestes, &amp; vaine deuises: in earnest, there is least labour layd on that arte, wheareby, kinges rule, &amp; are ruled and conquered, which erecteth, buyldeth establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth, encreaseth, beautifieth estates, the ende and fruites whereof, is honour most highe, euen aduaunced to the skyes, flowinge wealthe, fame neuer faylinge or forgotten, victorie and dominion withe out
<pb facs="6"/>
boundes: The contrarie and wante wheareof, is Captiuitye, Ruyne, Dishonour, and desolation. VVhearein to perswade by argument that, which euerye man doth plainelye see, yt weare waste of wordes and tyme. And, to styrre anye man to the studye of this knowledge, Sith the worthynes theareof allureth and draweth all right English men, (which by the pricke and inclinatyon of nature, doe with great desyre runne theare vnto.) I will thearefore omitte to spende further speache hearein, and drawe vnto the matter: whearein to make my course the plainer vnto the Reader, I deuide this worke into two bookes. Wheareof the first entreateth of the Captayne &amp; Souldiours. And the seconde of the disciplyne, obseruations, &amp; admonitions of warre: which two bookes, also for the better helpe of memorye, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointe and distribute into certaine Chapiters, braunches, or princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall pointes, touchinge the substaunce of this matter, as in my table appeareth, beginninge with the diffinition of warres. (Firste in the porche or entrye of this worke to be vnfoulded, before we enter into the particuler, &amp; inner partes theare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,) beinge the matter where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon this buyldinge is founded and framed.</p>
   <trailer>Vale.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>