<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE PHILIP Earle of Pembroke and Mountgomery: Baron Herbert of Caerdiff' and Sherland; Lord Parr and Ross' of Kendall; Lord Fitz-Hugh, Marmyon, and Saint Quin∣tin: Lord Chamberlain of his MA∣IESTIES most honourable Houshold, Lord Lieftenant of Kent, Wiltes, &amp;c. Lord Warden of the Stanneries in Corn-Wales and Devon: Knight of the most noble Order of the Garter: and one of his MAIESTIES most honourable Privie Councell.</title>
           <author>Herbert, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119691_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03066</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13191</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119691</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE PHILIP Earle of Pembroke and Mountgomery: Baron Herbert of Caerdiff' and Sherland; Lord Parr and Ross' of Kendall; Lord Fitz-Hugh, Marmyon, and Saint Quin∣tin: Lord Chamberlain of his MA∣IESTIES most honourable Houshold, Lord Lieftenant of Kent, Wiltes, &amp;c. Lord Warden of the Stanneries in Corn-Wales and Devon: Knight of the most noble Order of the Garter: and one of his MAIESTIES most honourable Privie Councell.</title>
                 <author>Herbert, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Some yeares travels into divers parts of Asia and Afrique : Describing especially the two famous empires, the Persian, and great Mogull: weaved with the history of these later times as also, many rich and spatious kingdomes in the orientall India, and other parts of Asia; together with the adjacent iles. Severally relating the religion, language, qualities, customes, habit, descent, fashions, and other observations touching them. With a revivall of the first discoverer of America. Revised and enlarged by the author</title>
                 <author>Herbert, Thomas, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bloome (Blome), Jacob</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 256, 259-364, 14 pages, illustrations, maps (metal cuts), 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE PHILIP Earle of <hi>Pembroke</hi> and <hi>Mountgomery:</hi> Baron <hi>Herbert</hi> of <hi>Caerdiff'</hi> and <hi>Sherland;</hi> Lord <hi>Parr</hi> and <hi>Ross'</hi> of <hi>Kendall;</hi> Lord <hi>Fitz-Hugh, Marmyon,</hi> and Saint <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin:</hi> Lord Chamberlain of his MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>IESTIES most honourable Houshold, Lord Lieftenant of <hi>Kent, Wiltes,</hi> &amp;c. Lord Warden of the <hi>Stanneries</hi> in <hi>Corn-Wales</hi> and <hi>Devon:</hi> Knight of the most noble Order of the Garter: and one of his MAIESTIES most honourable Privie Councell.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving past the Pikes, I take new courage to come on againe. One blow more and I have done. Ten to one it lights on my owne pate: but if my head stand free, my hand shall not bee guilty of more Intrusion: No more pressure to the Presse:
<pb facs="4"/>
the Crowd is too strong already: and I will get out by Head and Shoulders rather than faile.</p>
   <p>Your Lordships word may passe for me: and I dare not break it. Greatnesse hath a great stroak over Men, but Goodnesse a greater; Men choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to obey for Love, rather than Feare. In both, you have a strong Interest, and in both sorts of Men they have taken Possession, and like Twyns grow up together: <hi>Quam bene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniunt!</hi> And may their residence be as immova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as your Constancy to Good: yea may the Title of plain Dealing and honest Man bee the worst Reproach, Malice or double Dealing can fix upon your Name and Memory, who have gained much honour and ease too in Court and Country, by that excellent Dialect and generall Beliefe.</p>
   <p>The Dedication like a fayre Frontispice to a meane House, or a beautifull Signe to an ill Lodging, hath tempted Travellers to look in and make some stay: But I feare to have used my Readers, as my Host the Guests, that set a mark on the Doore, to passe by, and call in no more. Tis my feare only; which being begot of Modesty, may serve to invite the best and most ingenious Company.</p>
   <p>To please all is my Desire; but my Choice a few: taking the bigger Number to be the lesser in Vertue, and swollen only with a timpany of Wind and Water.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>The Boat is in your Lordships hand, which steares as you direct it. Yours is the greatest In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest: you are our Chiefe: yours is the leading Iudgement: do but approve, the Mark is hit, and you make many Followers; Which is the Request of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Lordships</hi> humblest Servant <hi>Tho. Herbert</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>