<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his friend Mr. Wadsworth the
Pilgrime.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119406_Fr1_11</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14618</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24928</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119406</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his friend Mr. Wadsworth the
Pilgrime.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Further obseruations of the English Spanish pilgrime, concerning Spaine : being a second part of his former booke, and containing these particulars: the description of a famous monastery, or house of the King of Spaines, called the Escuriall, not the like in the Christian world: a briefe relation of certaine dæmonicall stratagems of the Spanish Inquisition exercised on diuers English men of note of late times, and now liuing in England. A relation of the founding of a military order in Rome, to wit, of the immaculate Conception of our Lady, the blessed Virgin. Composed by Iames Wadsworth, Gentleman, lately conuerted into his true mothers bosome, the Church of England, and heretofore pentioner to the King of Spaine</title>
                 <author>Wadsworth, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Allott, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Butter, Nathaniel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 35, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>To his friend M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Wadsworth the
Pilgrime.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>FOrward, braue Pilgrime, let thy trauelling braine</l>
      <l>Giue birth to more Mineruaes; though to <hi>Spaine</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Imposture pawn'd thy Parents yet is that state</l>
      <l>Checkt by discouery of thy reaching pate.</l>
      <l>The speaking Crosse did steale thy Fathers heart,</l>
      <l>Thou speaking Crosse to his designes dost thwart</l>
      <l>Delusions credit, and impostures guile</l>
      <l>Beguilts its posture painting in thy stile.</l>
      <l>Did <hi>Callis</hi> dungeon thee obscurely keepe?</l>
      <l>We know that truth oft times lyes in the deepe;</l>
      <l>Did the darke dungeon thee bestride with night?</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Romes</hi> proiects and thy clearenesse came to light;</l>
      <l>Darknesse displai'd, and night being thrust away</l>
      <l>Thou clear'd, we must confesse th' hast wonne the day.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Mans life's a Pilgrimage, cease not to trauell</l>
      <l>From shore to Sea, from Sea to sand, to grauell</l>
      <l>Th' antagonists of truth: we know by common-sence,</l>
      <l>Trauels the high way to experience.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>E. R.</hi>
Mag. Coll. Cant.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>