<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO the two-fold Readers: the Courteous, and the Criticke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119729_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03250</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13366</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119729</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO the two-fold Readers: the Courteous, and the Criticke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Troia Britanica: or, Great Britaines Troy : A poem deuided into XVII. seuerall cantons, intermixed with many pleasant poeticall tales. Concluding with an vniuersall chronicle from the Creation, vntill these present times. Written by Tho: Heywood</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 128, 109-124, 123-265, pages 254, 301-466, 465-466 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO the two-fold Readers: <hi>the Courteous, and the Criticke.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He fauourable and gracious Reader, I salute, with a submisse <hi>Conge</hi> both of heart and knee: To the scornefull, I owe not so much as an hypocriticall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, or a dissembled curtesie. I am not so vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced in the enuy of this Age, but that I knowe I shall encounter most sharpe and seucre Censurers, such as continually carpe at other mens labours, and superficially pervsing them, with a kind of negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and skorne, quote them by the way, Thus: This is an Error, that was too much streacht, this too slightly neglected, heere many things might haue been added, there it might haue beene better followed: this superfluous, that radiculous. These indeed know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no other meanes to haue them selues opinioned in the ranke of vnderstanders, but by calumniating other mens industries. These <hi>Satyrists</hi> I meet thus: It were (in my opinion) more honor and honesty for them, to betake them seriously to the like studies, and the time they wast in detracting others, rather spend in instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themselues, and by some more excellent worke (moulded out of their owne braines) giue the foyle to others of lesse Fame and consequence: This were a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable and worthy detraction, sauouring of desert; the other, a meere ranco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous folly, grounded on nothing but malicious ignorance. For who more apt to call <hi>coward</hi> then the most tymerous, but he only merits a name among the vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunt, that hath actually and personally wonne his reputation by some deed of same and Honour. But since these <hi>Criticks</hi> are a generall Subiect in the front of subiect booke, I am content to neglect them, as those Ireguard not, and to the friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and best iudging Reader, thus turne my <hi>Apologie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I haue aduentured (right Courteous) to publish this <hi>Poem,</hi> and present it to thy generall acceptance; If it be gently receiued, and fauour ably ceusured, it may incourage me to proceed in some future labour; if any way distasted, I am so farre from troubling the world with more, that I shall hold this little, much too much. Yet if you vnderstandingly consider this proiect, you shall finde included herein a
<pb facs="4"/>
briefe memory or Epitome of Chronicle, euen from the first man, vnto vs, this se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time created <hi>Britons,</hi> with a faithfull Register, not onely of memorable thinges done in <hi>Troy</hi> and this Island, but of many, and the most famous accidents happening through the World, In who se raigne and what yeare of the world they chanced (with which we haue conferred the Histories of the Sacred Byble) &amp; the truth of the times so eeuen, that who so euer will daigne the perv sall of these, shall not onely perceiue such thinges were doone, but bee also-satisfied in whose Raigne (then successiuely gouerning in the kingdome of <hi>Britaine</hi>) they happened. In all which, I haue taskt my selfe to such succinctnesse and breuity, that in the iudisiall perusall of these few <hi>Cantons</hi> (with the <hi>Scolies</hi> Annexed) as little time shall bee hazzarded, as profite from them be any way expected.</p>
   <p>Accept then (I entreat you) this mingled Subject (as well home-borne as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine) and Censure it as fauourably, as I haue offred it freely. Though something may perhaps distast, something againe I presume will please the most curious Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late: Let that which pleaseth, mittig at the harshnes of the other. He that speaks much, may (excusably) speake somewhat Idely, and he that in vnknown Climats trauayles farre, may (by misaduenture) wander out of the way: but where the mayne intent and purpose is honest and good, it is pardonable to expect the best. And in that hope, I prostrate these my barraine industries to your kindest and gentle Constructions.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>