<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY CHRISTIAN Hearers, of the Pari∣shes of S. Nicholas and All-Saints, in New-Castle vpon Tine, especially to the yonger and ruder sort of them, R. I. wisheth a competent measure of the Spi∣rit of Wisedome and vnderstan∣ding, of the Spirit of Know∣ledge, and of the feare of the Lord.</title>
           <author>Jenison, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119429_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04377</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14490</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119429</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY CHRISTIAN Hearers, of the Pari∣shes of S. Nicholas and All-Saints, in New-Castle vpon Tine, especially to the yonger and ruder sort of them, R. I. wisheth a competent measure of the Spi∣rit of Wisedome and vnderstan∣ding, of the Spirit of Know∣ledge, and of the feare of the Lord.</title>
                 <author>Jenison, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Directions for the vvorthy receiuing of the Lords Supper : with some few questions to the same purpose. By Robert Iension, Batchelor in Diuinity, and Minister of Gods Word, at New-Castle vpon Tine</title>
                 <author>Jenison, Robert, 1584?-1652</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Harrigat, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>54 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO MY CHRISTIAN Hearers, of the Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes of S. <hi>Nicholas</hi> and <hi>All-Saints,</hi> in <hi>New-Castle</hi> vpon <hi>Tine,</hi> especially to the yonger and ruder sort of them, R. I. <hi>wisheth</hi> a competent measure of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Wisedome and vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, of the Spirit of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and of the feare of the Lord.</head>
   <p>WHat I now in heart, and euer in my hearty and dayly Prayers vnfay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly <hi>wish</hi> on your behalfe, right
<pb facs="3"/>
deare beloued Brethren, I am not (as you know) neither shall I euer, God assisting, be awan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to further by my dayly and best endeuours for you, whether it bee by my Preaching, or by my Pen: (though this latter finds enough to doe, to prepare matter for your eares, not eyes.) To which end, as also for the publike good of many others, I haue not beene vnwilling at the requests of some, that these few directions following (which, nigh seuen yeeres since, were, at the earnest intreaty of a neere friend, summed vp in haste) should, after they had also soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in your eares) see the light,
<pb facs="3"/>
and passe, euen rudely, as at first, (when there was no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of publishing them) they were written, without any al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration, vnder the publike censure of the world; hoping, yea earnestly desiring, men would bring rather humble and hungring hearts, than curious and catching heads to the reading of them; that so they may indeed truely profite by them. As I shall vnderstand these ruder, old<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and hastier Meditations are accepted of, I shall bee encouraged to greater, further, and fresher paines, in publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing soone after, what, I hope,
<pb facs="4"/>
will not bee vnprofitable to the Church of GOD, whose Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant I doe professe my selfe, as also,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours, in the Lord,</hi> Robert Ienison.</signed>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From my House, in</hi> New-Castle <hi>vpon</hi> Tine:
<date>Ian. 12. 1623.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>