<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PRINTER TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>B., F.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119531_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17049</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3922</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119531</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PRINTER TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>B., F.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The mysterie of the Lords Supper : Cleerely manifested in five sermons; two of preparation, and three of the Sacrament it selfe. By a reverend and faithfull preacher of Gods word</title>
                 <author>Bruce, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 149 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PRINTER TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> Present here vnto thy viewe (good reader) a learned and godly treatise, wherein the Doctrine of the Lords supper is both plainely and fully handled. A worke which heretofore hath beene in diuers mens hands, yet not without some inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience; for being at first borne in another soyle then our owne, it was written in a language (though but the same, with ours in substance) yet by reason of the peculiar dialect or propriety so often varying, and more then sufficient to make them that are not throughly acquainted with the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, to mistake euen things that to our vnderstanding are much more familiar then the holy mysteries of our saluation. The consideratiō of which incommodity did moue a worthy and truly religious Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man M. S. <hi>Michell,</hi> to take the paines to peruse and polishe so good a worke to the
<pb facs="3"/>end to publish it, that so it might be profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to all: But hauing scarse finished and prepared it for the presse, it pleased God to take him to himselfe, before he could see a finall end of this, and many other his religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and honest endeauors, yet least the Church should haue lost so precious a Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell (his zeale of good doing continuing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end) he committed the execution of this so godly a desire, to the speciall care of one of his good and trusty friends, who being faithfull in the trust committed vnto him is a principal meanes that now it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth safely to thy hands; receiue it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and esteeme it (as the most godly and iudicious haue euer done) the best and most profitable treatise that euer hath bin pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished of this subiect, and cease not to thanke God for raising vp so many meanes to procure thy good, whose sole end in all their labours is Gods glory, and the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of thy true happinesse. Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in Christ Iesus,</hi> F. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>