<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE To the Reader. By Question and Answer vpon the Title of the Booke, and the parts thereof.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119253_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08997</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1929</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119253</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE To the Reader. By Question and Answer vpon the Title of the Booke, and the parts thereof.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The common catechisme : with a commentary therevpon, by questions and answers, following the verie words, as they lie in their order without alteration. A profitable way, as also verie easie, and so likewise pleasant both to the teacher and learner, as by experience will be found true. By Richard Bernard, pastor at Batcomb</title>
                 <author>Bernard, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Samuel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE <hi>To the Reader.</hi> By Question and Answer vpon the <hi>Title of the Booke, and the parts thereof.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> HOw many things are you to obserue for entrance into this Booke?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> Two things.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> Which be they?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> The title and the book<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> it selfe.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> What is the title?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> A <hi>CATECHISME, <hi>that</hi>
      </hi> is An instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to be learned of euery Child, before he be brought to be confirmed by the Bishop.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q</hi> What things are you to consider in this title?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> These fiue circumstances. 1. The name of the Booke, a <hi>Catechisme.</hi> 2. The exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the name, an <hi>instruction.</hi> 3. Why it was set out, <hi>to be learned.</hi> 4. Of whom, <hi>of Children.</hi> 5. When and in what spare of time, <hi>before they come to be confirmed by the Bishop.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> Is there any difference betweene this Catechisme and other Catechisme?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> Not in substance, nor in manner of deliuery, but in other respects,</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> Which be they?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> 1. In respect of the <hi>Generalitie</hi> of it for all places. 2. Of the publike <hi>Athority</hi> commanding it.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> What is a Catechisme?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> It is an <hi>Instruction.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> Is euery instruction a Catechisme?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> No: but an instruction of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Religion, by the way of Question and, Answer.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> In how many things then doth a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techisme differ from other instructions?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> In two things. 1. In the matter, the principles of Religion. 2. In the manner, by question and answer,</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> Why is it set forth?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> That it may be both taught &amp; leraned.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> How is that?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> Two wayes; according to his Maiesties directions, set forth to this purpose.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> Which be those two waies?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> 1. By examination, in propounding the Questions and receiuing the Answers. 2. By exposition, in giuing the sense &amp; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the words, for further benefit to all the hearers.</p>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> Why is a Catechisme to be learne?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> For many reasons. 1. For better set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of mens iudgements in the truth, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well grounded in the principles of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. 2. To profit the more in reading holy Scriptures 3. To heare Sermons with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding and iudgement. 4. To discouer error. 5. To be able to examie our selues of our faith, of our duties to God and man, of our right deuotion in prayer, and of the holy vse of the blessed Sacrament, especially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we come to receiue. 6. To be able readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to giue an answer of our hope to any one. 7. To be able to teach and admonish others, especially such ouer whom we haue a speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all charge.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> Why is this Catechisme to bee taught and learned before all other Catechismes?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> 1. To shew obedience to authority, commanding this euery where to be taught. 2. For vniformity sake, that the same truths from on and the same Catechisme, may bée knowne to all in euery place. 3. For the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of such as remoue their dwellings from one Parish to another, that Children and Seruants may not be to spéee in their answers, when they come to be catechised, as it otherwise falleth out by variety of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techismes taught in seuerall parishes,</p>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> Who is to learne this Catechisme?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> Euery Childe comming to yeeres of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> How many wayes is the name <hi>Childe</hi> to be taken?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> Two waies, according to the Scrptures.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> Which be they?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> 1. For a Childe in yéeres, as it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly vnderstood. 2. For a Childe in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding as the scripture speaketh. 1. <hi>Cor. 3. 1. Heb.</hi> 5. 13.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> Whom comprehend you vnder the name of Children in yeeres?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> All Children, Apprentises and seruants, which haue not learned this Catechisme,</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> How must these be taught?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> By examination.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> Who are to be vnderstood by Children in vnderstanding?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> All ignorant of the grounds of Christian faith, though married and well strucken in yéeres, yea, the very eldest for age.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> How are these to be catechised?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> By their being present with attention, when others are examined, and by hearing their Teacher expound the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techisme.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> When and in what space is this to bee learned?</p>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> Before any either be admited to receiue the Lords Supper, or be brought vnto the Bishop to be confirmed.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> Why is it to be learned before any come to the Sacrament?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> Because by the knowledge hereof they may be the better prepared thereunto, without which preparation they are not counted sit to be communicants.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> Why is it to be learned before one bee brought to the Bishop?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> That hée may now in his owne person make profession of his faith, and with his owne mouth ratifie that which in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme was by his God-fathers and God-mothers promised in his name.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> But seeing our Church doth not allow Confirmation for a Sacrament, nor doth acknowledge that it addeth any thing vnto Baptisme, why are Children brought to bee confirmed?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> 1. To sée whether Children haue béen so religiously trained vp, as their God-fathers and God-mothers promised, and vowed at Baptisme for them. 2. Whether they be able to promise and professe so much now in their owne persons. 3. Hauing so done, that prayer may bee made vnto God, for his blessing and grace to strengthen them,
<pb facs="6"/> that they may continue and increase there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, vnto their liues end.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> HAuing gone through the <hi>Title</hi> now can you tell me how many parts the Booke consists of?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> Of these two. 1. Of the Preface. 2. Of the matter of the Booke.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the Preface?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> All that which goeth before the rehearsall of the Creede.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> What doth the Preface containe in it?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> The foure first questions, with the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers thereunto.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Q.</hi> What is the matter of the Booke, or Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chisme?</p>
   <p>
      <hi>A.</hi> It is the Créed, the tenne Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the Lords Prayer, &amp; the Doctrine of the Sacrments.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>