<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, and truely religious Lady, the Lady ANNE GLEMHAM, I. C. wisheth encrease of all godlinesse and vertue, with the fruition of eternall HAPPINESSE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119830_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08188</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18526.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119830</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, and truely religious Lady, the Lady ANNE GLEMHAM, I. C. wisheth encrease of all godlinesse and vertue, with the fruition of eternall HAPPINESSE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A day-starre for darke-wandring soules : shewing the light, by a Christian controuersie: or briefely and plainely setting forth the mysterie of our saluation. Diuided into principles, obiections, and answeres. By Richard Niccolls, th'elder, of the Inner Temple London, Gent. deceased. Published for the generall benefit of all those who heartily, and with a true faith, desire their owne saluation: by I.C</title>
                 <author>Niccols, Richard, of the Inner Temple</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Budge, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 73, that is 83, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, and truely religious Lady, the Lady ANNE GLEMHAM,</hi> I. C. <hi>wisheth encrease of all</hi> godlinesse and vertue, with <hi>the fruition of eternall HAPPINESSE.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>Right Honourable:</p>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S euery good Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist laboureth with much paines to rectifie and bring into due forme and order, the Art which hee himselfe professeth; and seeketh</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>all possible wayes and meanes to attaine to the perfection thereof; adding thereto his owne practice and experience, thereby to make it more facile and easie to be attained vnto by future Posterities; and vnto them conueying it, as it were a matter hereditarie, and which by succession they ought to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy. Euen so ought euery true Christian with his best endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, industrie and trauaile, labour to finde out the true Principles and Grounds of Christian Religion; and therein through his owne industry (di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by the Spirit of the Highest) daily seeke to attaine to the perfection of that blessed Truth which is the sole Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectresse to eternall Happinesse▪ and the profits of his Christian</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Labours to participate to all succeeding Ages. And as none can profit in any Science, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out first knowing the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Reasons and Grounds thereof; so it is impossible for any man to attaine to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Christian Religion, vnlesse hee be first instructed in the certaine and infallible Grounds and Principles of the same: with which this worthy and religious Author was well furnished, as by this ensuing discourse, or Treatise, made for the priuate vse of himselfe and his Wife, who being a godly and religious Gentlewoman, imparted the same to some few of her friends; amongst whom, my selfe (as vnworthiest of those few) had a written Copie, which (most Vertuous Lady)</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>remayning in my custody (and the Author being a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, vnder whom I had part of my Education, and fearing lest this Orphant (turned naked into the World, without a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector and Patron) might by sinister and fatall occasion hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen into the hands of some professed (though priuate) ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and there be smothered by those irremarkable persons mentioned in the</hi> Reuelation <hi>to haue receiued the marke of the Beast) depriuing the Author of his due and well deserued com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations, and the World of so honest and religious a worke, I could doe no lesse then cause it to be published, as well for the generall good of the well-affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and religious, as also for an Example and President vnto</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>all men to imploy their labours in godly exercise, for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of their Christian Brethren. And considering with my selfe where to bestow it, I was em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ed by the inducement of diuers reasons to select your Ladiship, as one most worthy to be the sole Patronesse and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector of this godly Treatise, knowing your Honourable Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and sinceritie of Religion to be such as are of force e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make that commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable which onely by your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours name is graced, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of which, and diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Honourable Curtesies, for which I am oblieged to your Ladiship, I most humbly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent vnto your fauourable view and Honourable protection, the zealous and truely religious la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>of this godly Gentleman, challenging nothing to my selfe but the imperfections in the harsh composure of the stile, which if your Honour vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe to receiue, it may be that although in the perusing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of your Ladiship shall not finde any matter which you are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of, yet may it confirme that which otherwise your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour may doubt in; or at least make it more euident by deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering the Circumstances in more particular termes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>And as in the Author it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serueth a generall and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall remembrance, so doth it argue in him a most godly and good minde, in labouring to finde out that which gaue a comfortable end to all his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, for the which doubtlesse</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>he now possesseth an vncorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible and immortall Crowne of Glory in the World which shall neuer end. To the which, after many, long, and happy yeeres, with much honor in this life, liued to the glory of God, and to the comfort and reliefe of his poore and afflicted Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, the Lord bring your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, with peace and quiet Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Your Honours</hi> solely deuoted <hi>in all seruiceable duty, and dutifull Affection,</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I. C.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>