<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE GENERAL ARGVMENTS OF THE ENSVINGE HISTORIE: SER∣VINGE ALSO FOR A PREFACE, to the Reader, to declare the scope of the Author, and contents of the worke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119562_Bo1_1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17015</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3895</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119562</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE GENERAL ARGVMENTS OF THE ENSVINGE HISTORIE: SER∣VINGE ALSO FOR A PREFACE, to the Reader, to declare the scope of the Author, and contents of the worke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ecclesiastical Protestant historie : of the high pastoral and fatherly chardge and care of the Popes of Rome, ouer the church of Britanie, from the first planting of the christia [n] faith there, by S. Peter the Apostle, and his disciples: continued in euery age, and hundred of yeares, by holy bishops, and cleargie men, sent hither and consecrated by them, his successors in the See Apostolicke. Euidently deduced and proued by historicall narration, from the published and priuiledged writings (to appeaseal protestants) of the most learned &amp; allowed English protestant pretended bishops, doctors, antiquaries, &amp; others of that religion</title>
                 <author>Broughton, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Boscard, Charles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>249, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>THE GENERAL ARGVMENTS OF THE ENSVINGE HISTORIE: SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VINGE ALSO FOR A PREFACE, to the Reader, to declare the scope of the Author, and contents of the worke.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Catholick Author well requainted with the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of Protestants, in these times, and the controuersies of them, to accept and allowe of nothing, but what is liked and allowed by them selues; and yet to make the world beleeue, they are Reuerencers of antiquitie, and would willingly embrace, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe that, which was our first faith in any question deliuered by the Apostles, &amp; thence continued from them: the greatest of all
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>
beeing that who planted here first the holy faith, and since had cheifest commanding power in such things: Hee setteth histori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally downe from the best Antiquaries, and learned protestant writers of this contry, &amp; other antiquities approued by them, the meanes and maner of our first conuersion vnto Christ, and by what spirituall cheife ruling authority this nation hath euer beene gouerned in such thinges, since then, vntill the conuersions of the Saxons by S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine, and his associats sent hither by Saint, and pope Gregory, the first, after which tyme now aboue 1000. yeares, our prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants put it out of Question, and agree, that the power of the popes of Rome abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely ruled here in such matters.</p>
   <p>Therfore this historie of the first sixe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares, is diuided into sixe Centuries or ages, euery one conteyninge one hundred yeares. In the first, hee sheweth from those protestant Authors, and Antiquaries, how S. Peter that greate Apostle of Christ, both immediately by himselfe, and mediately by his holy disciples, first preached here, foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded our church, consecrated for vs Bishops, preists, and other cleargie men, and ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="5" facs="3"/>
all thinges thereto belonging: and how from this first institution by him, we euer had a continued succession of such conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated parsons, vnto the more generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersion by pope Eleutherius in the daies of kinge Lucius after which time there can bee no question of such a succession of Bishops here. And how after the death of S. Peter vnto the end of the first hundred yeares, spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall matters were ordered here by autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and direction from the see of Rome, and successors of S. Peter there.</p>
   <p>In the second hundred of yeares, is proued by the same protestant authors, and their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquities, how from the beginninge of that age, to the end thereof, all spirituall things were likewise managed here, by that see Apostolicke, more or lesse, as the times then permitted. And in the generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersion of kinge Lucius, and his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, all ecclesiasticall businesses were done, and settled by iurisdiction of the popes of Rome, and their legats, directed hither by their authoritie, exercising here as ample iurisdiction spirituall, to the greate honor of this kingdome, as any pope of Rome may clayme.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="6" facs="4"/>Such was the estate of spirituall power, and proceedings here in the third, fourth, fift, and sixte age, or hundred of yeares also: in the later end whereof, S. Augustine was sent hither to conuert our auncestors the Saxons. In all which ages, and Centenaries of yeares, both the Kings, Archbishops, Bishops, and others, both Rulers, and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in this kingdome, gaue as much priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and prerogatiue to the popes of Rome, as Catholicks now may doe, by their catholick Roman Religion.</p>
   <p>In which tyme also, amonge all those christians which then liued here, those Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops of Scotland, and Walles, who, as our protestants tell vs, and commend them for it, did onely or most oppose against the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe, his legates, and authoritie here, were those alsoe, by the same protestants, which did much more intermeddle in princes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, then any popes, their legats, or such as were most obedient vnto, or Ruled by them. Which proceedings the Author doth in all places leaue to protestants relation, and medleth not with them otherwise at all. But soe much as with probabilitie in histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, hee may, mitigateth such matters, as
<pb n="7" facs="4"/>
some protestants, euen with publick allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the protestant state of Englād, haue boldly published to the world in that kinde: freely and before God protesting, as hee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hitherto had any intermedlinge with the temporall affaires of Princes, but euer to his vttermost, did yeeld and render all dutie vnto them, praying for the safety, honor and preseruation of his Soueraigne, and this kingdome, soe hee will euer continue the same moste humble and dutifull af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
   <p>Other particular Questions in Religion depend vppon this. Because whosoeuer in anie Religion hath the cheife chardge and cure, the particulars depend vpon his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, whether it bee Pope, Prince, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendents, Presbyteries, or whatsoeuer, and soe beeing proued that from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge of christianitie in this kingdome, the Pope of Rome euer had cheife cōmaund &amp; direction in Religious things. It must needs followe, that which protestants name pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistrie, euer raigned here. But I vnderstand there is a generall controuersiall historie to bee shortly published, of all such things in particular, from the first preaching of
<pb n="8" facs="5"/>
the Gospell in this kingdome, which will giue, full and ample satisfaction, in all such Questions.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>