<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119389_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19884</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6310</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119389</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An apologeticall reply to a booke called an ansvver to the unjust complaint of VV.B : Also an answer to Mr. I.D. touching his report of some passages. His allegation of Scriptures against the baptising of some kind of infants. His protestation about the publishing of his wrightings. By Iohn Davenporte BD</title>
                 <author>Davenport, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waesberghe, Isaac van</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Rotterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 326 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12.</note> Though the testimony of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, is of it selfe a suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cause of rejoycing in all the tribulations of this pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 23.1. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Act.</hi> 24.16.</note> and of confidence in our Apologies against fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se accusers, in which respect Blessed Paul, according to the wisdom given unto him, did <hi>herein excercise himselfe, to have alwayes a conscience voyd of offence toward God, and toward men: yet,</hi> next to a good conscience, every man is bound to provide for his <hi>good name,</hi> it being,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Eccles.</hi> 7.1</note> in Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons judgment, <hi>better then precious oyntment,</hi> which ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to cheare a mans owne spirits, and to make him ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to others, and as any man is of more publick use, so it is both more diffused, and more apt to be tainted by the shew of any infirmity: according to that holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Eccles.</hi> 10.1.</note>
      <hi>Dead flies cause the oyntment of the Apothecary to send forth a stincking savour; so doeth a litly folly him that is in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation for wisdom and honour.</hi> But the regard of our good name must be excercised upon higher, then selfe-respects, else it is but vaine glory, which flowing from pride falleth into unwarranted contention. Gods name must be more deare unto us then our owne, and our care must be, not so much to shun our owne, as his dishonour, our esteeme whereof ought, in some proportion, to answer to his dignity and eminency. We see that among men the same reproach which is but a slander of private persons, is <hi>scandalum magnatum,</hi> when it reflecteth disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb facs="3"/> upon peeres of a realme, and it is <hi>crimen lasae Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>statis,</hi> when it ascendeth to the soveraigne majesty. For which cause it is not to be wondred that God hath shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en himselfe so jealous of the honour of his owne name, not onely upon the sonnes of Aaron and Eli, and those wicked Preists in Israel,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.5.8.9.</note> but also upon Aaron and Eli themselves, and upon Moses, and David, in whom, though he pardoned their sinne, yet he passed not by this consequent of it, the dishonour of his name, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a temporall judgment.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iosu.</hi> 7.9. <hi>Psa.</hi> 8.1. <hi>Psal.</hi> 111.9. <hi>Mich:</hi> 5.4</note> For his name is <hi>a great, excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, holy,</hi> and <hi>reverent name,</hi> it is a name which hath <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty in it,</hi> and is as farr above all names, as his Majesty is above all creatures.</p>
   <p>Gods honour being principally intended, the good of men is not to be neglected, that they within the Church be not ashamed, or offended, nor they without, hindred, or hardned.<note place="margin">Luther on Gen. <hi>9.</hi> Gen. <hi>9.22</hi>
      </note> For such is the malignant <hi>genius</hi> of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents seed, that they delight in observing the slipps and falls of Gods servants, as swine doe to nuzzle in filth and excrements, vvhich evill inclination was so strong in Cham &amp; Canaan that it brake the bonds of nature, and therefore it is the lesse to be wondred at, if Sanballat and Tobiah,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Nehem.</hi> 6.13.</note> to hinder the worke of the Lord in the hands of his servants, did <hi>seeke matter of an evill report, that they might reproach them.</hi> And, as it would not satisfye Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans malice to lay hands upon Mordecai alone,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Hest.</hi> 3.6.</note> but he saught to destroy all the Iewes: so these are accustomed, for the miscarriage of any one, to misjudge the generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Gods children. Which David much feared, and earnestly deprecated,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 69 5.6.</note> saying. <hi>Let not them that wayte on thee O Lord God of Hoasts, be ashamed for my sake. Let not those that seeke thee, be confounded, for my sake, O God of Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/> And the laying of a stumbling block,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.13.</note> or an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of falling, in the way of weake Christians, by giving them offence, is of no lesse dangerous consequence to him by whom the offence cometh (for whom <hi>it had bene better that he had bene cast into the sea with a milstone about his neck</hi>) then it is to him who is scandalized,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.6.</note> who is <hi>wounded,</hi> and <hi>made weake,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.13.</note> and in danger of being <hi>destroyed</hi> thereby, which caused holy Paul to resolve rather to eate no flesh, whilest the world stādeth, then thereby to cause his brother to offend. And the same thing which maketh <hi>the hearts of the righteous sad,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ezeck.</hi> 13.22.</note> usually <hi>strengthneth the hands of the wicked,</hi> that he should not returne from his evill way. Thus it falleth out in scandalous reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches raysed against those that feare God by the worst of men, but much more when Israelites thrust their swords into their fellowes sides,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.22.27.</note> especially when those who are as <hi>women with child</hi> are spurned, hurt, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered, by reproaches, to miscarry, of some spirituall <hi>children, of whom</hi> they <hi>travayle in birth,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.19</note>
      <hi>till Christ may be formed in them.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>These considerations may serve to be an Apology to others for this my Reply, and for an admonition to my selfe, and direction about my wholl carriage in it.</p>
   <p>They, who have read the <hi>Answer,</hi> whereunto this Reply is made, will testifye, on my behalfe, that the honour of God, and the good of the Church, both for maintenance of truths opposed, and for vindicating myne owne name, and the names of others, far more worthy then I, from calumny, did necessitate the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing of this Apology. It had bene more to the Ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werers comfort, if he could have as truely pleaded the same necessity, as he readily pretended it. But, 1. how
<pb facs="4"/> easily might he have prevented it, in the cause: either by not making an unjust opposition, or by yeelding to such aequall meanes of accommodation as were propounded, or by propounding other wayes sufficient to salve the sore, or by referring the matter to the Church as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belonging to their cognition, or by fairely see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the advice of the Classis (seing he would bring it thither) without praepossessing the Dutch preachers with causelesse praejudices, and jealousies against men whom they knew not. 2. Seing due care was not taken to prevent the kindling of the fire: yet, how easily might it have bene quenched, when the smother of it began to breake forth apparently! at least, the fuell might have bene subtracted, and it suffered to have gone out, and to have dyed of it selfe, but, in stead, thereof, oyle is cast upon it to make it flame out, and the force and violence of it, is, by his booke (as by bellowes, or a strong wind) driven upon the faces of those, who have done, and suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered much that they might extinguish it. Alas! what benefit could redound to the Church by such personall vindications published to the world, seing a sufficient answer given in wrighting to their written complaints would have satisfyed their desire, and ended all diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence among them? And, what though these pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate wrightings were printed? yet, what necessity was there of printing any answer to them? seing the Answerer had many wayes to have suppressed them at the presse (being made privy to the printing of them, by the printer himselfe, which I was not) and seeing I protested, in print, against the first part, which concerned me, and the Complainants professed theire dislike of publishing the other part of it? How tender
<pb facs="4"/> I was of the Answerers reputation my <hi>Protestation</hi> shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, in part, and my labour to have the booke suppressed more fully manifesteth. For I procured that all the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies unsold might be bought up, so that (I am told) about foure hundred and fifty, of the five hundred, were stopped. How he hath requited me let his booke speake.</p>
   <p>And howsoever he pretendeth that the printing of that pamphlet compelled him to print, in his owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, yet it is evident, 1. that he declared his purpose of printing about these matters before any wrighting was made by me, in myne owne defence, or by them, in way of complaint of their greivances. 2. that his theatning to print an answer to their complaints, which then were onely written, and left in the Consistory privatly, and the report of one, who said that he had seene some of the sheets which the Answerer had prepared to print, were the causes moving W. B. to print that wrighting. 3. that himselfe declared in a letter, which the freind, to whom he sent it, shewed me, that he purposed to print an answer to that short wrighting which was left by me, when as nothing had bene printed by W.B. Which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth that the printed pamphlet was not the cause of his booke, but that he tooke occasion thereby to publish that which he had before purposed. 4. When he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted the ministers of the Classis with his purpose of printing an answer to that pamphlet, they disuaded him: yet he againe importuned them to consent to it, threatning to get it printed in England, if they opposed it here. To conclude. He so wearyed them with impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunityes, as if his life had layne in the doing of it, that they left him to himselfe (after they had advised him to
<pb facs="5"/> leave out some passages which they disliked in his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py) but still professed that, as they did not hinder him, so they would not counsail him to doe it. This some of those learned &amp; prudent men have affirmed to some of the members of that Church, whereby the Reader may see with how strong a bent of spirit he was carryed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, but upon what argument, or motives, I leave it to his owne consideration in the sight of God.</p>
   <p>Yet, if he would print, needlesly: ah, that he had not done it so reproachfully, sarcastically, bitterly! Not that I have cause to be troubled thereat, in respect of my selfe, who have, in some measure, learned to be content (if God will have it so) to be <hi>as a lampe despised in the thought of him that is at ease,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Iob.</hi> 12.5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.35.</note> and <hi>to be made a gazing stock, both by reproaches and afflications, &amp; by becoming a companion of them that were so used,</hi> but for the truthes sake, for the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es sake, for his owne sake, whom I doe unfeinedly reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and love in the Lord, though I am by him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to this unpleasing contest. I confesse, that when I read his booke, and considered how to answer it, upon a serious pondering of passages, I thought upon Herods short letter to Cassius (<gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>) and if I had so written to him,<note place="margin">Philostr. in vit. Herod.</note> though I should have censured my selfe, as not dealing according to the respect which I beare to his gravity, and long standing in the Church, &amp; ministeriall abilities &amp;c. Yet he could not answer as Paul did a like (though more unjust) chalenge, that he wrote <hi>the words of truth and sobernes.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 26.25.</note> For how untruely (though, I hope, but by ignorance, or forgetfullnes, or misapprehension, or inadvertency) passages are repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, I am compelled to declare in the severall answeres. How unsoberly let the Reader judge, without my raking into
<pb facs="5"/> that finck, which maketh the wholl booke the more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>savoury and uselesse. This also (remembring my prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent admonition) I would cover, for the better mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derating other mens censures, by imputing it to some aptnes in his naturall spirit to causelesse jealousies, or to the infirmity of his age, or to his melancholy temper, or to the instigation of others, or to the violence of temptation, or to a misguided Zeale, as our love causeth us to impute unbeseeming carriages of our freinds in violent feavers &amp;c. to the disease, not to the man.</p>
   <p>As for me; what reproaches soever I sustaine, I hope the <hi>spirit of understanding and counsaile, and the feare of the Lord</hi> will so guide me, that I shall not, by returning <hi>rebuke for rebuke,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>2.</hi> Pet. <hi>3.9</hi> Rom. <hi>12.21.</hi> Aug. ad Catech:</note> give just cause of suspicion that I am <hi>overcome of evill.</hi> But such a necessity is now layed upon me, that I may say, with Augustine, <hi>Cogimur non tacere, cum potius expediat flere quam aliquid dicere. I am constrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to wright, though</hi> (in some respects) <hi>it were more expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to weepe then to say any thing.</hi> My desire is to make a modest defence of the truth, and of mine owne innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, without injuring or irritating any body. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I purpose to propound to my selfe excelent patternes, whom I wish the Answerer also had imitated, such as Basil and Nazianzen,<note place="margin">Greg: Naz: Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod: in Laud: Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sil.</note> whose spirits were so sweetly composed in a difference betweene them, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing it, they gave due respect each to other, Basil calling Nazianzen. <hi>Vas electionis, puteum profundum, os Christi, An elect vessel, a deepe well, the mouth of Christ,</hi> and Nazianzen winding up his invention to the highest streine in Basils praise, as appeareth in an oration made by him for that purpose, though he noate an unkindnes
<pb facs="6"/> received from him, which he could not well digest. In like manner Augustine differed from Cyprian about re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptization, yet he doth not reproach him, but excuseth his errour rather,<note place="margin">Aug. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de bapt. contr. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat: Cap. <hi>7</hi>
      </note> saying, <hi>nondum erat diligenter ista baptis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi questio pertractata. That questiō about baptisme had not bene diligently discussed unto that time,</hi> and honoureth his name with excelent titles. <hi>Beatus Cyprianus, vigilantissimus Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copus, gloriosissimus Martyr. Blessed Cyprian, a most vigilant Bishop, a most glorious Martyr.</hi> And, comparing Cyprian, &amp; Stephanus,<note place="margin">Idem lib. de unico Bap. contr. Petil. cap. <hi>14.</hi>
      </note> &amp; Donatus together, in their different carria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge about that question, he did not reproach Cyprian as schysmatically affected, but shevved that both Cyprian and Stephanus and those that adhaered to them preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved unity each vvith other,<note place="margin">Idem contr Donat. lib. <hi>5.</hi> Cap. <hi>11.</hi>
      </note> and did not, as Donatus, seperate from the Church for that cause; and for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, he professed (hovvsoever he held as he did tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Baptisme of Iohn) <hi>se non acturum pugnaciter &amp;c.</hi> that he vvould not quarrrell those that held othervvise. In latter times Beza shevved the same spirit tovvards Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linger and Gualter;<note place="margin">Praef. in lib. de pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byt: et ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com. contr. Erast:</note> for though they seemed to incline more to Erastus his opinion then he could vvish, yet he speaketh honourably of them, calling them, after their deaths, <hi>non tantum Tigurinae, sed Christianae totius Ecclesiae lumina, lights not onely of the Tigurine, but also of the wholl Christian Church,</hi> and elsevvhere they are stiled by him, <hi>optimi illi beatissimae memoriae fratres, summâ tum pietate, tum eruditione praediti, his excelent brethren of very blessed memory, men of singular piety and learning,</hi> and he taketh occasion to excuse their difference from him in that point, not to brand them with any black noate for it. Thus in those men the spirit of love vvraught, as it had done before them in the Apostles of Christ: For, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever
<pb facs="6"/> Paul justly reproved Peter, as the case required,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.</note> yet Peter did not lye at the catch (as vve say) to recri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate him, but tooke occasion, from some passage in Pauls epistles, to make an honourable mention of him saying.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15.</note>
      <hi>Account that the long suffering of the Lord is salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as our beloved brother Paul, according to the wisdom gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto him, hath written unto you &amp;c.</hi> such a carriage of differences amongst Christians, specially Ministers of the Gospell, vvould much conduce to the advancement of the truth, and stopping of the mouthes of adversaries, vvhich are apt to be opened upon tvvo advantages. 1. The differences in judgment amongst professours. 2. The bitternes of spirit vvhich they discover in those differences. To prevent (as much as in me lyeth) any hurt that may come from these tvvo praejudices, I thinck it requisite that I add a word or two, upon occasion of this advantage, which some bitter passages in the Answer doe seeme to give all sorts of adversaryes to blaspheme the trueth.</p>
   <p n="1">1. All sorts of people are apt to object against the truth, that the professours of it doe not agree amongst themselves. This the ancient Philosophers objected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Christians in the first 300 yeares after Christ, whose mouthes the worthy lights in those times stop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, with the different sects among the Philosophers thēselves. In like manner I may tell the Papalls of the 26 Schysmes in the Romish Church, others of the troubles in Franckford raysed in Queene Maryes daies, about bringing in the English liturgy into that place, (for the effecting whereof they spared not to endanger the life of that famous Godly man Mr. Knocks who opposed it.) others, of Troubles about excommunications in
<pb facs="7"/> Amsterdam extant to the view of all men, and all men of differences about their severall wayes and projects.</p>
   <p n="2">2. Bellarmine, to prove that our Religion doeth not produce holynes in mens lives, instanceth in the violence of Luthers spirit, which appeared in much bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes even against those vvho agreed vvith him in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position to popery, because they differed from him in some particular tenets. That this is but a fallible signe, may appeare, not onely in this, that shevves of holynes may be vvhere holynes in trueth is not, as in that gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, constancy, and humility vvhich vvas observeable in that enimy of Gods grace Pelagius,<note place="margin">Aug. Epist. <hi>120.</hi> Mat. <hi>7.15.</hi>
      </note> according to our Saviours praediction, concerning Wolves in sheepes cloathing; but also in this, that distempered passions have bene found in eminent servants of God, as in the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betvveene Paul &amp; Barnabas, the onely vvise God, for his ovvne glory many vvayes, by some infirmityes stayning the glory of all flesh. Hovv hot vvas the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention betvveene Cyprian and Stephanus! vvhat vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and troublesome dissention vvas there betvveene Theophilus and Chrisostom! also betvveene Cyrill of Alexandria and Theodoret, boath Bishops, Catholicks, boath learned, boath godly, boath excelent pillars of the Church, and yet he that readeth both their vvrightings vvould thinck that boath vvere dangerous enimyes of the Church. The invectives of Ierom and Ruffinus one against another are extant, and Augustines Epistles, vvherein he bevvayled the same. Hovv many unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses passed betvveene Chrisostom and Epiphanius! Did not the one refuse to pray vvith the other? Did not the one chalēge the other for manyfold breaches of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons?
<pb facs="7"/> Did not the one professe that he hoped he should never dye a Bishop? and the other that he should never come alive into his country, boath vvhich things fell out according to their uncharitable vvishes, Epiphanius dying by the vvay as he vvas returning home, and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sostom being cast out of his Bishoprick, and dying in banishment? And these things came to passe, 1. partly, by the instigatiō of others. Thus Epiphanius vvas stirred up against Chrisostom by Theophilus. So that their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions arose from a versatilous wit accompanied vvith a malicious and vindictive spirit in Theophilus, &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudence accōpanied vvith too much credulity in Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius. 2. partly, by some stiffnes &amp; inflexibility of spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in some of them, accōpanied vvith much hardnes to be reconciled vvhen once offēded, to those vvith vvhom they vvere displeased, from vvhich blemish Chrisostom vvas not altogether free, and that caused him somevvhat the more trouble. 3. partly by mistakes, as in the differēce betvveene Theodoret and Cyrill, and in the division betvveene the Christians of the East, and those of the West, the one suspecting the other of haeresy, upon a mistake, For the Romans beleived three persons in the Trinity but vvould not beleive three <hi>hypostases,</hi> &amp; thence the Orientall Christians thought them Sabellians, vvho held that there is but one person in the Godhead called by three names. The Easterne Christians beleived three <hi>hypostases</hi> in the Godhead, but vvould not admit three persons, vvhence they of Rome thought them to be Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, vvho beleived that there are three distinct substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Godhead. Athanasius, perceiving that they differed not in judgment, brought them to accord, by shevving them that they meant one thing, though their
<pb facs="8"/> expressions vvere different, so that there vvas a difference arising from ill suspition which was grounded upon misunderstanding one another. Lastly, from an ill gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Zeale, whereby (beside the former) Luther and those that adhaered to him were carryed too far in opposition against Zwinglius, about the Sacrament, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Luther saw, and confessed to Melancthon, a litle before his death, that his wrightings, in that controversy had bene too bitter, &amp; professed his inclination to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish some thing for the qualifying of them, but that be feared the scandall that might grow upon such his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractation, as is to be seene in the <hi>Admonition of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of the County Palatine concerning the</hi> booke called <hi>liber concordiae.</hi> Thus a groundlesse jealousy sharpened Luthers spirit in that controversy, and a groundlesse jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousy hindred him from retracting what he had written. Had the same jealousy hindred Augustine, the wholl Christian world had bene loosers thereby, wanting that helpe by his booke of Retractations, which now they have. Which unproffitable jealousy, whereby men will make good what they have said or done, least they should seeme to have erred, Ambrose piously cast off, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed that his wrightings had need of a second review, <hi>et qnantumlibet quisque profecerit,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ambr: offic: lib. <hi>1.</hi> Cap. <hi>1.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>nemo est qui doceri non indigeat, dum vivit. How much soever any man hath profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, every man hath need to be taught whilest he liveth.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>These things being premised, for prevention of scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall, which may be taken at the Answer, whereunto the ensuing Reply is made, I will breifely conclude, after I have added one or two words for prevention of unae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall censures upon the Reply it selfe, with respect to the matter, and to the manner of my proceeding in it.</p>
   <p n="1">
      <pb facs="8"/>1. For the matter. I must intreat the wise hearted Reader to vouchsafe a benigne &amp; favourable construc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of things that may seeme lyable to some miscon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, and to consider that in all the passages of this discourse, I have a particular respect to the question be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene us, avoyding by-matters. As, for instance, when I speake of the summity of the power of particular Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <hi>in re propriâ, in such things as are properly their owne,</hi> &amp; doe instance in the choyse of their ministers, it may be, some captious polititian will thinck that I abridge the povver of the civill Magistrate, which is farr from my purpose (though I speake as I doe, limiting my selfe to the question betweene the Church and the Classis onely, which was the <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>) For I acknowledge, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that submission &amp; obedience is due, by the fifth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, both to the highest Governours in every common wealth, according to the severall lawes and customs thereof, as to Emperours, Kings, Consuls Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Dukes, States, and to other officers and ministers under them, as Senators, Counsailours, Iustices, Majors, Sheriffs, Balives, Constables, &amp;c. (these, and the like, being in respect of their severall kinds,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1</note> that <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>every ordinance of man,</hi> yet in respect of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon nature and power, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>are ordered or ordained of God</hi>) and that for conscience sake, in all their civill lawes and constitutions, but also in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ecclesiasticall &amp; spirituall, it belongeth to the cheife governour or governours to be <hi>nursing fathers</hi> of the Church, as well as of the Commonwealth,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Isa.</hi> 49.23.</note> to be <hi>Custodes et vindices utriusque tabulae,</hi> and that they may, and aught to establish, by their authority, the true Religion, &amp; pure worship of God, and to forbid and punish, not onely
<pb facs="9"/> civill persons for civill crimes: but even Churchmen al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, and boath sorts for crimes against Religion, as Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, Haeresy, Idolatry, Sacriledge, Schysme, &amp;c. and to take order (as occasion may require) that the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches make choyse of fit officers, and that Church offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers doe their duety in every kind, according to all Gods ordinances and institutions, and that the wholl worship of God, and all the parts of it, be administred in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations <hi>decently,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40.</note> without uncomelines, <hi>and orderly,</hi> without confusion, of which care they have excelent praecedents set before them for patternes in the Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, such as David, Salomon, Hezekiah, Iosiah. Nor are <hi>the matters of the Lord,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.11.</note>
      <hi>and the Kings matters</hi> of so different a nature, that the care of the things of God doeth not appertayne to the King, but onely to the high Preist, but they are distinguished in the manner of their perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming them, the Magistrates discharging their part, civil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; politically, &amp; the Church officers executing their<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ecclesiastically, and spiritually, that so piety and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, the Church and Common wealth, religion and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnes may dwell together, may kisse each other, and may flourish together, in the due subjection of all sorts of subjects to Princes and Magistrates, and of both prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and people to the scepter and government of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iames</hi> 4.12.</note>
      <hi>that one lawgiver, who is able to save and to destroy.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="2">2. For the manner. 1. I have endeavoured to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry my selfe inoffensively, in this wholl treatise, without wronging or provoking any, and for that purpose have concealed the name of the Answerer, wishing that it may not be remembred, upon this occasion, to blemish any of his well deservings, in any other service to God,
<pb facs="9"/> or to his Church. 2. I have laboured so to temper my stile that the truth may be manifested by his owne acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons sincerely related, rather then by my verball censures. 1. His owne words I have truely repeated and answered, and when I have bene compelled to contradict those things whereunto I could not consent, I have laboured to shew reason more then passion therein. If any thinck it might have bene done more smoothly, and plausibly, let him know there is a difference to be made betweene personall vindications, and doctrinall ventilations, there being not the same degrees of provocation to passion in the latter as in the former: and that some of the perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall aspersions, whereunto I am enforced to make reply, are such as whereunto a simple cold negation, without some vehemency, would seeme incongruous, as Ierom speakes of the suspicion of haeresy or schysme, wherein, he sayth, it becometh no man to be patient. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude; let the Christian reader, if he meete with any such passages, suspend his censure, till he have bene put upon the clearing of his innocency to the world, in answer to a printed booke made in so provoking a manner, by such a man, upon such an occasion, himselfe being excerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with the same tryalls &amp; difficulties wherewith I am excercised, in these tossings to and fro, yet with much quiet in my spirit, thorough inward supportments, wherein I may say, to the prayse of Gods grace, in my measure. <hi>As the sufferings of Christ abound in us,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5</note>
      <hi>so our consolation also aboundeth by Christ.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Lastly. If any man shall thinck that my Reply is too large, let him consider, 1. that the particular matters of fact, wherein myne innocency was necessarily to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended are many. 2. that I could not declare and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb facs="10"/> the truth which I hold in points of doctrine, and which is in word or actions opposed by the Answerer, in a breifer discourse. 3. that a necessity was layed upon me to wright somewhat on the behalfe of other Reverend ministers, some whereof are at rest, as Mr. Parker, Dr. Ames, Mr. Forbes, some are absent, as Mr. Hooker, Mr. Weld, Mr. Peter. 4. that he so interweaveth his discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents against the Elders, &amp; the complaints of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers with the passages which concerne me, that, in many things, I could not cleare my selfe without saying some thing also in their just defence, which I have done spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly, and but when it was made necessary by his joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning us together. 5. that he hath so frequently mentioned my name, almost in every passage, that I could not make a satisfying Reply, on myne owne behalfe, without exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining almost the wholl booke, which I was constray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to doe also more particularly (and according to the order of his Sections) then else I would, least it should be thought that I had bene unable to answer what I had praetermitted. Wherein what I have written the Reader seeth, but he knoweth not what I could have added, and therefore is to be intreated to suspend his censure concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning what I have said till he may understand the reasons whereby I am able to justifye such particulars, 6. that, for the helpe of the Reader in comparing the Reply with the Answer I have inserted his owne words every where. 7. that I thought it unaequall to cause the Reader to lay out his mony, and spend his precious houres upon a fruitlesse discourse of our personall concernments onely: and therefore have added many things, upon this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, for his intellectuall advantage, whereby the Reply
<pb facs="10"/> is made much larger then else it should have bene. The benefit whereof, will, I hope, with Gods bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, recompence his expence of mony or time upon it. Which I beseech the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of lights and of spirits to grant for the advancement of his truth in the hearts of many! Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>