<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119607_Fr1_8</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14923</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25231</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119607</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The soules progresse to the celestiall Canaan, or heavenly Jerusalem : By way of godly meditation, and holy contemplation: accompanied with divers learned exhortations, and pithy perswasions, tending to Christianity and humanity. Divided into two parts. The first part treateth of the divine essence, quality and nature of God, and his holy attributs: and of the creation, fall, state, death, and misery of an unregenerated man, both in this life and in the world to come: put for the whole scope of the Old Testament. The second part is put for the summe and compendium of the Gospell, and treateth of the Incarnation, Nativity, words, works, and sufferings of Christ, and of the happinesse and blessednesse of a godly man in his state of renovation, being reconciled to God in Christ. Collected out of the Scriptures, and out of the writings of the ancient fathers of the primitive Church, and other orthodoxall divines: by John Welles, of Beccles in the County of Suffolk</title>
                 <author>Welles, John, of Beccles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Anne.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Griffin, Edward 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Shepherd (Sheppard), Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 304, 1, 308-372, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>IF thou wouldst understand the Deity;</l>
      <l>Behold the mystery of the holy Trinity:</l>
      <l>An Essence divine, eternall, infinite is hee,</l>
      <l>Spirituall, and of wonderfull magnanimity,</l>
      <l>Of power, of might and majesty,</l>
      <l>Of goodnesse, greatnesse and excellency,</l>
      <l>Of glory, continuance and quality;</l>
      <l>And is perfectly good unchangeably,</l>
      <l>From everlasting and perpetually,</l>
      <l>And is every where present repletively,</l>
      <l>Essentially, potentially and vertually,</l>
      <l>Which is seene by his admirable works apparantly,</l>
      <l>With our eyes and minde continually,</l>
      <l>From age to age universally.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>This Almighty God incomprehensible,</l>
      <l>Omnipotent, invisible and incomparable,</l>
      <l>Immortall, incorruptible and unspeakeable,</l>
      <l>Dwelleth in light inaccessible;</l>
      <l>And is coequall, coessentiall and coeternall,</l>
      <l>Of one substance, immutable and unsearchable.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>This high blessed Heavens Creatour,</l>
      <l>Is the earths creatures Conserver,</l>
      <l>Increaser, nourisher, repairer and governour</l>
      <l>By his omnipresent power.</l>
      <pb facs="15"/>
      <l>Although he dwels in Heaven principally;</l>
      <l>Yet hee is, and dwels on earth effectually;</l>
      <l>In the faithfull his elect especially,</l>
      <l>In his wisedome, grace and mercy.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Therefore be praised evermore the Trinity,</l>
      <l>Father, Sonne and holy Ghost in unity;</l>
      <l>This to believe is godly charity,</l>
      <l>Saving faith and holy piety;</l>
      <l>For speaking of Gods simple verity,</l>
      <l>Nought more beseemes then true simplicity.</l>
      <l>If further thou wouldst understand his Majesty.</l>
      <l>Goe in, behold and see his excellency;</l>
      <l>For what I know of his all-knowing worth,</l>
      <l>With single heart I have simply here set forth;</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Thus wishing that my labours may,</l>
      <l>To heavens rest thy soule convey.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>No attributes can sufficiently expresse the essence of God, but the attributes which be given unto God, be taken out of the usage of mens speech, and so applyed unto the nature of God, to the end that those things which cannot be properly expressed by any toung nor language, may yet at the least wise be by the figures of mens speeches in some sort shadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; whatsoever therefore is spoken of God, is so in God, as it serveth to helpe our weake under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, to conceive in our reason, and to utter in our speech, the majesty of his divine nature, quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and essence; for of himselfe he is infinite and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effable, in his essence, might, power, and working.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>