<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE REVE∣REND FATHER IN God, William Lord Bishoppe of
Norwich, and to the rest of her Maiesties Officers for the execution of Iustice in that Dioces. T. N. wisheth grace and peace.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119504_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08430</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18748</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119504</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE REVE∣REND FATHER IN God, William Lord Bishoppe of
Norwich, and to the rest of her Maiesties Officers for the execution of Iustice in that Dioces. T. N. wisheth grace and peace.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A comfort against the Spaniard</title>
                 <author>Nun, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 <publisher>Oxenbridge, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>REND FATHER IN God, William Lord Bishoppe of
<hi>Norwich, and to the rest of her</hi> Maiesties Officers for the execution of Iustice in that Dioces. T. N. wisheth grace and peace.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>S it true that the Spanyardes will com this spring? And is it not as true that we are ready to receiue them? Hath this land at any time had, either better prouision, or more Souldiers: brauer Captaines to leade them, or sounder Diuines to encourage them?</p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>Yea, but what for Armour on our backes if feare bee in our hearts? can feare there remaine where our late victories are remēbered? Is not our enemie the same, our case, nay our God the same?</p>
   <p>But <hi>Pharao,</hi> and <hi>Sisera,</hi> their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow is now forgotten. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam</hi> may sing alone, and <hi>Barac</hi> and
<hi>Debora</hi> can get no hearers. O, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let this booke call to mind our dutie, for why should we depriue, either our GOD of his glorie, or our selues of such a comfort? Is it not an houres Sermon of that inuincible Nauie, and a briefe Apologie of the Portugale voiage? and doth it not set before our eyes how great thinges the Lord hath done for vs? To this ende I haue published it, &amp; to your Lordship, <pb facs="3"/>and worships, I doe Dedicate it. Beseeching God, so to blesse you in gouerning vs, that still the Gospell may haue free passage among vs. So shal we stil eate the fruite of our vines, in despite of <hi>Senacherib:</hi> and good
<hi>Ezechias</hi> shal not want <hi>Esaies</hi> to comfort her, whē
<hi>Rabsache</hi> shall be sent to rayle vpon her.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships, and worships in Christ Thomas Nun Minister of the word, at Weston.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>