<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶Vnto the Christian reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1546</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119176_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09505</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19786</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119176</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶Vnto the Christian reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Thre godly and notable sermons, of the moost honorable and blessed sacrament of the aulter. Preached in the Hospitall of S. Antony in London, by Wyllya [m] Peryn preest, bachelar of diuinite, [and] now set forth for the auaunceme [n] t of goddes honor: the truthe of his worde, and edification of good christen people</title>
                 <author>Peryn, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1546</date>
                 <publisher>Hill (Hyll, van den Berghe, Montanus), Nicholas (Niko—laos).</publisher>
                            <publisher>Toy (Toeus), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>224 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>¶Vnto the Christian reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prysed (mooste deare reader) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mōge the great riche mē (I mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of lernynge &amp; eloquēs) of this our tyme, to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer (wyth the poore wydow) thys my symple and rude myte into god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des cheste, towardes the repayrynge &amp; reedifyinge of Christes churche. Sygni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and declarynge herein, howe har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely I wyshe &amp; desyre, to haue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> church of Christe (that is to saye) the christen people repayred and reedifyed in the ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholyke and syncere fayth. Namelye suche, as of late are fallen into ruyne &amp; great decaye in matters of oure faythe, with the huge stormes and tempestes of heresyes, that the dyuell hath araysed, specially agaynst the blessed sacrament of thaulter, as well by the vehemēt stor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes of pestilent bokes, as also by the ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nemous wyndes and blastes of secrete deuelyshe doctrines. Wher <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e I shall mooste hartely desyre the christian rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="6"/>
(yf he be lerned) of hys moost gentle &amp; charitable censure &amp; iudgement. And yf eather letter, eather worde hath esca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped me or the printer (as there hath so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me) let the same with his penne gentlye correct it. Yf he be vnlerned, let hym take the frutes and commodities there of, gyuyng the prayse and thankes ther of to God, bycause I haue laboured it cheftly for him. And yf y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same shal fynd any worde or sentence here, that semeth vnto hym obscure or darke, let the same iuge that eather suche wordes hath esca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped me vnwarelye, eather that I could not openlye and conueniently set suche matter so breuely, in playner sentence.</p>
   <p>And for as muche as an order in thinges not onelye delyghteth the beholder (as the bewty therof) but also (makyng the matter more sensible and playne) it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth the reader to beare awaye and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne the better, that whyche he hathe redde, therfore haue I here, set forth bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uely, the order that I haue taken, in the proces of thys rude thynge. Where the cristiane reader shall vnderstande, that the former part of the fyrst Sermon, she wyth that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> admyrable workes of god, were wrought of God to manyfest the glorye of hys synguler power, and to buylde faythe in vs. And vppon thys grounde, I haue proued, the possibilitie
<pb facs="6"/>
of the myracles (wrought by God) in the blessed sacrament of the Aulter, by the other myraculous workes, that the scripture telleth vs, to haue ben wrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght, by the power of God. And bycause we beleue suche myracles and yet se thē not, we ought also (of lyke reason) to beleue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> myracles in the holy sacramēt, thoughe we se them not, bycause, that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> scripture affyrmeth them to be trewe, and sayth (in the voyce of Christ.) Thys is my bodye. For vppon the veritie of these wordes, dependeth the veritie, of all the other myracles, wroughte in the blessed sacrament. And fynally, I do applye the myracles of the blessed sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, vnto the other myracles of God, to shewe them to be of equal possibilitie and impossibilitie.</p>
   <p>✿ In the seconde Sermon I haue fyrste declared certayne fygures, of the olde lawe, to appertayne vnto the sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment. And then I haue brought in, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers places of scripture, to proue that thynge, to be so in dede, which I shewed (in the fyrste sermon possible.) For lyke as I shewed in the former sermon, the reall presens of Christes bodye in the sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crament (wyth al the myracles) possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by the other myraculous workes of God, so do I in this sermon proue it, by the scriptures, to be s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of a treuth.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>✿ In the thyrd, I haue set in place, fyrste the promyses, that Christe made vnto the Churche. Wherof I haue iust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye collected, that (standynge the veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of those promyses) that thyng muste nedes be of infallible truthe, the whych the churche hath beleued, and taught so many hundred yeres. In the seconde place, I haue brought in, the conselles, &amp; after them the testimonies of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient wryters, to proue that the churche hath, alwaye retayned, this same fayth of the sacrament, that we now do hold, syth the apostles tyme. Yet here I haue not recyted, al the wryters of al tymes, (for who can so do?) but I haue selected &amp; chosen onely such, as I haue thought, of moost antiquitie, and auctoritie, and that from .vii. or .viii. hundred yeares &amp; vpwarde, and haue not mencioned, nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alleged, any that writ within these vii. hūdred yeres, bycause, that they are in maner innumerable, and moost of thē so familiar, that theyr faythe in thys matter, is very manyfest, vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> meane learned. Thyrdlye, I haue answered, to the moost comē reasons (that semed vnto me mooste strongest) that are made for the contrarie. And where I haue not handeled, thys moost excellent mystery of our fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th, wyth so exquisite lerning, and exacte iugement, as a man of greate
<pb facs="7"/>
lytterature and learnynge wolde haue done, I shall moost humblye and herte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye desyre the christian reader, to esteme and waye, not howe homelye, base, and rude thynge is here cōpyled, but rather, to iuge, from howe syncere mynde, and good wyl it hath proceded, and to what ende, and intent, I thus enterprysed, to dyuulgate and set it forth. where in, I haue sought chefly, the settyng forth of the syncere and catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke faythe of the churche of Christe, and the spirituall lucre and gayne of my christiane brother to the honour of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghty god. Vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to whome be immortall glorye laude and prayse worlde with out ende. Amen.</p>
   <epigraph>
      <q>
         <bibl>ij. Petri vltimo.</bibl>
         <p>¶<hi>VOS <hi>fratres prescientes, custodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te: ne insipientium errore traducti, exidatis a propria firmitate.</hi>
            </hi>
         </p>
      </q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>