<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ Thomas Vycarie to his Brethren practising Chirurgerie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119628_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14394</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24713</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119628</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ Thomas Vycarie to his Brethren practising Chirurgerie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A profitable treatise of the anatomie of mans body: compyled by that excellent chirurgion, M. Thomas Vicary esquire, seriaunt chirurgion to king Henry the eyght, to king Edward the. vj. to Queene Mary, and to our most gracious Soueraigne Lady Queene Elizabeth, and also cheefe chirurgion of S. Bartholomewes Hospital. Which work is newly reuyued, corrected, and published by the chirurgions of the same hospital now beeing. An. 1577</title>
                 <author>Vicary, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bamford, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>120 pages, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>X to the Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_colleagues">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>¶ Thomas Vycarie to his Brethren practising Chirurgerie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>EEREAFTER foloweth a little trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise of the Anatomie of mans body, Made by Thomas Vycarie Citizen and Chirurgion of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, for all suche young Brethren of his Felowship practising Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgerie. Not for them that be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertly seene in the Anatomie: for to them Galen the Lanterne of all Chirurgions, hath set it foorth in his Canons, to the high glory of God, and too the erudition and knowledge of al those that be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertly seene and learned in the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Science of Chirurgerie. And because al the noble Philosophers wryting vppon Chirurgerie, doo
<pb facs="9"/>
condemne al suche persons as pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise in Chirurgerie not knowing the Anatomie. Therefore I haue drawen into certayne Lessons and smal Chapters, a parte of the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomie, but touching a part of euery member particulerly: Requiring euery man that shal reade this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Treatise, to correct and amend it where it shal be neede, and holde me excused for my bolde enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise, and accept my good wyl towards the same.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>