<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Gentlemen
Readers.</title>
           <author>L., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119669_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06173</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16665</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119669</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Gentlemen
Readers.</title>
                 <author>L., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Rosalynde. Euphues golden legacie : found after his death in his cell at Silexedra. Bequeathed to Philautus sonnes, noursed vp with their father in England. Fetcht from the Canaries by T.L. Gent</title>
                 <author>Lodge, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jeffes, Abel</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 <distributor>Busby, John 1</distributor>
                            <distributor>Gubbin (Gubbins), Thomas</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>120 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Gentlemen
Readers.</head>
   <p>GEntlemen, looke not heere to finde anie
sprigs of <hi>Pallas</hi> bay tree, nor to heare the
humour of any amorous Lawreat, nor the
pleasing vaine of any eloquent Orator:
<hi>Nolo altum sapere,</hi> they bee matters aboue
my capacitie: the Coblers checke shal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
light on my heade, <hi>Ne sutor vltra crepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi>
I vil go no further than the latchet, and then all is wel.
Heere you may perhaps finde some leaues of <hi>Venus</hi> mirtle,
but heven down by a souldier with his curtlaxe, not boght
with tle allurement of a filed tongue. To bee briefe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen,
roome for a souldier and a sailer, that giues you the
fruits of his labors that he wrote in the Ocean, when euerie
line was wet with a surge, &amp; euery humorous passion coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercheckt
with a storme. If you like it, so: and yet I will bee
yours in duetie, if you be mine in fauour. But if <hi>Momus</hi> or
any squinteied asse, that hath mighty eares to conceiue with
<hi>Midis,</hi> and yet little reason to iudge: if he come abord our
Barke to find fault with the tackling, when hee knowes not
the shrowds, Ile downe into the hold, and fetch out a rustie
pollax, that sawe no sunne this seauen yeare, and either well
bebast him, or heaue the cockescombe ouer boord to feed
cods. But curteous Gentlemen that fauour most, backbite
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, and pardon what is ouerslipt, let such come and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come,
Ile into the Stewards roome, and fetch them a kanne
of our best beuradge. Well Gentlemen, you haue <hi>Euphues
L<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>gacie.</hi> I fetcht it as farre as the Ilands of <hi>Terceras,</hi> &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
read it, censure with fauour, and farewell.</p>
   <signed>Yours T. L.</signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>