<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my honou∣red Friend Anthony Percivall Esq. Cap∣tain of Arcliff Bulwark neere Dover: Comptrol∣ler of his Majesties Customes for Kent, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Reading, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119785_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10512</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20787</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119785</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my honou∣red Friend Anthony Percivall Esq. Cap∣tain of Arcliff Bulwark neere Dover: Comptrol∣ler of his Majesties Customes for Kent, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Reading, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Characters of true blessednesse : delivered in a sermon preached at Saint Maries Church in Dover. Sep. 21. 1637. At the funeral of Mrs. Alice Percivall, wife of Anthony Percivall Esquire. By Iohn Reading</title>
                 <author>Reading, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Edward 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, Joyce (Jocosa).</publisher>
                            <publisher>Whitaker, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 60, 63-146 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To my honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Friend <hi>Anthony Percivall</hi> Esq. Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of <hi>Arcliff Bulwark</hi> neere <hi>Dover:</hi> Comptrol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of his Majesties Customes for <hi>Kent,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Sir,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>I doe at your request venture this rough draught to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like view; being more confident of good mens
<pb facs="3"/>
acceptance, than fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of others rash cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure: I had rather the busie should question my ability, than the iust my will to serve my friends: in which office he is not blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, who cannot though he would, but he that will not though he can. The subject is accommodate to com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort concerning the deceased, in whose lives wee found these markes (the blessed are
<pb facs="3"/>
not lost, but gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 23.</note>
      <hi>I shall goe to him, but hee shall not returne to mee,</hi> said <hi>David</hi> of his good childe, the evill hee bitterly bewailed) and to informe us what is Blessednesse, lest in the pursuit of the false, we misse the true. None envie the dead a convenient tombe: no good man will, these kind of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents, which equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preserve the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory
<pb facs="4"/>
of the Saints departed, and more profitably, than the most curious Epitaphs instruct the survi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving: I have sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed some things which time straitned in the delivery. The Lord so direct and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist us in the use of his ordinance, that when these dayes of sinne are ended. we may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the end of our hopes, jalvation and eternal happines in the
<pb facs="4"/>
world to come, through our most blessed Lord and Saviour Iesus Christ. In whom I am</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your faithfull friend I. READING.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>