<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE KINGS MOST EXCELLENT Maiestie; Iames, by the Grace of of God, King of Great Britain, France, and Ireland, Defender of the true, auncient, Catholick, and Apostolike faith: and Supreme Gouernour in all Causes, &amp; ouer all persons Ecclesiacticall within his Dominions. So ordained to be by the Diuine Masestie.</title>
           <author>Harris, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119023_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02683</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12815</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119023</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE KINGS MOST EXCELLENT Maiestie; Iames, by the Grace of of God, King of Great Britain, France, and Ireland, Defender of the true, auncient, Catholick, and Apostolike faith: and Supreme Gouernour in all Causes, &amp; ouer all persons Ecclesiacticall within his Dominions. So ordained to be by the Diuine Masestie.</title>
                 <author>Harris, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The English concord : in ansvver to Becane's English iarre: together with a reply to Becan's Examen of the English Concord. By Richard Harris, Dr. in Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Harris, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Matthew</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 315, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE KINGS MOST EXCELLENT Maiestie; <hi>Iames,</hi> by the Grace of of God, King of Great Britain, France, and Ireland, Defender of the true, auncient, Catholick, and Apostolike faith: and <hi>Supreme Gouernour</hi> in all <hi>Causes, &amp; ouer all persons Ecclesiacticall within his Dominions. So ordained to be by the Diuine Masestie.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most Gracious Soueragine;</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat busie pack-horse Iesuit <hi>Becan,</hi> maintaining, what in his small power lyeth, diametrall opposition to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties rightfull &amp; supereminet <hi>power Ecclesiastical:</hi> To make the same seem ludibrious in the eyes of his adherents, (as King <hi>Dauid</hi> dauncing before the <hi>Arke,</hi> seemed to be in the eyes of prophane <hi>Michal</hi>); in his printed empty pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, stiled, <hi>Dissidium Anglicanú,</hi> brought, as it were, vpon the vvorlds Theatre, fiue English Protestant Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, in defence of your Maiesties said <hi>Supremacy;</hi> namely, the most learned, &amp; Reuerend Bishop of <hi>Ely,</hi> with his two Chaplaines, Maister <hi>Thomson,</hi> and Maister <hi>Burhill,</hi> also Maister Doctor <hi>Tooker,</hi> and my <hi>Selfe;</hi> as <hi>iarring</hi> among our selues, in many and materiall points of the said <hi>Supremacy:</hi> and therevpon hee concluded, that
<pb facs="3"/>your Maiestie hath no iuct cause, to vrge the <hi>taking of the Oath</hi> of <hi>Regall Supremacy</hi> vpon your subiects; sith the defenders thereof in writing cannot agree in the main, reall, and essentiall parts of it. Which pernitious proiect of the Aduersarie, caused me, in my most humble dutie, &amp; loyall seruice to your Maiestie, eftsoones to write my booke of <hi>English Concord;</hi> therein shewing, and prouing the sweet harmonie, whereby all the fore said fiue Writers vtter the rightfull <hi>Supremacy</hi> of your <hi>sacred Maiestie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now, because some of your Maiesties Popish and English subiects, haue turned the said pamphlet of <hi>Becan,</hi> out of Latin, into English, thereby to cause that poisonfull canker to spread further, and that Roman leprosie to ouerrun the outward faces, and inward hearts of English Papists, on this side, and beyond the Seas: To countermine that serpentine plot, viz. to suppesse, or at the least, to stay the further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse of that running Canker; it seemed good vnto your Maiestie, to commaund the translating of my said booke into English: which was done accordingly. But before it could be printed, <hi>Becan</hi> had written, and sent to the last <hi>Frank-fort</hi> Mart, his <hi>EXAMEN</hi> of my booke of <hi>English Concord:</hi> which forced me to annex my <hi>REPLY,</hi> and Refutation of his <hi>Examen,</hi> in the <hi>Interim,</hi> in English al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, because the other are in English; intending with all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient speed, to send the same <hi>Reply augmented,</hi> beyond the Seas in Latin, that this importune Aduersary, may see his <hi>reed Examen</hi> shaken downe, and shinered all to peeces; and also may behold the <hi>English Concord,</hi> fully maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and iustified, in euery part and parcell of <hi>Regall Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I humbly confesse vnto your <hi>excellent Maiestie,</hi> that it grieued me at my very hart, to spend so many good houres,
<pb facs="3"/>in refuting the Almanack-pamphlets, of this shallow, and in very truth, vnlearned Iesuit; wherein is not to be found any learning, reading, or indicious discourse, fitting a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-Iesuit:</hi> but onely boy-like wranglings, about either seeming <hi>Iarres,</hi> in vvords or syllables; or escapes of the Transcriber, Printer, or Corrector, in some abcedary letters, in numerall figures, in quoting the middle paragraph-word, for the first vvord of the selfe same Canon: vvhereas the very expresse words, or the very substantiall matter, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meaning of the Author, and the purpose in hand, was faithfully set downe.</p>
   <p>These trifles, which (with his shamelesse calumniations, vntruthes, and scurrilities, make vp the very bulke of his triobulare booke) though they might well haue been let passe, as things of nought; or buried in silence: yet because wise <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> aduiseth, <hi>Sometimes to answere a foole in his foolishnes;</hi> least my silence heerin, should cause this Iesuit to growe more insolent; or the Popish sort in their vngrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and rebellious deniall of this <hi>Oath,</hi> more confident; I haue made this <hi>Reply,</hi> to giue him more matter to vvorke vpon: It beeing my setled resolution, through Gods assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance whiles I breath, to iustifie in vvriting against this Iesuit, both the rightfulnesse of your <hi>Maiesties Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi> and also the vniforme agreement of the said Writers therein. The rather, because, though this Iesuit by his sillie scribblings, brings shame and disgrace to the <hi>Pope,</hi> whose cause he vndertaketh to defend; yet is thought not the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meetest Emissary of his <hi>Vnholinesse;</hi> for that this Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parasite, with his hard forhead, dare set forth in print, any thing for his <hi>Lord God the Pope,</hi> &amp; against your <hi>sacred Mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>stie:</hi> be it, for the matter, neuer so impiously grosse; and for the manner, neuer soimpudently sourrilous. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb facs="4"/>having tasted of your <hi>Highnes</hi> most Gracious patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage in my former labours, I am emboldned to present these also vnto your royall view: beeing more desirous of your Maiest: sole iudgement, to approue the lines defending regall iurisdiction; then of a whole Colledge or councell of our Aduersaries. Because such is the desert of your royall minde, and penne, as vvas by <hi>Sabellicus</hi> attributed to <hi>Cicero: Pulchriùs illi multo fuit Latinum sermonem, quàm Romanum Imperium auxisse.</hi> So is it more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to your <hi>excellent Maiestie,</hi> (if such a Prince bee capable of accesse of Honour) that you haue by writing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated the religion of <hi>Christ,</hi> then if by battell you had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged your Dominions, and <hi>Great Britaines</hi> Monarchie: The one beeing the price of the death of Iesus: the other, your most lawfull patrimony, by the death of your royall fore-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Which the <hi>Lord</hi> graunt you may so long enjoy, as your owne royall heart desireth, and all your louing subiects doe say, <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties most humble, and loyall subiect, RICHARD HARRIS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>