<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most worthie knight Theodot of Marze, Lord of Belle∣roche, Lassenaz, &amp;c. Claudius Paradin sendeth greeting.</title>
           <author>Rowlands, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119509_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08907</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19183</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119509</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most worthie knight Theodot of Marze, Lord of Belle∣roche, Lassenaz, &amp;c. Claudius Paradin sendeth greeting.</title>
                 <author>Rowlands, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The heroicall deuises of M. Claudius Paradin Canon of Beauieu : Whereunto are added the Lord Gabriel Symeons and others. Translated out of Latin into English by P.S</title>
                 <author>Paradin, Claude</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Kearney (Carney, Kerny), William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 <publisher>Scarlet, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Scarlet, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 374 pages, illustrations, 16°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the most worthie knight Theodot of Marze, Lord of Belle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roche, Lassenaz, &amp;c. Claudius Paradin sendeth greeting.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S varietie of pictures yeeldeth great pleasure and recreation vnto man: so likevvise the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and commoditie that is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped from them, is not to be had in little regard or estimation, forasmuch as by the vse of them vexations both of bodie and minde (vvhich are othervvise intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) are easily mollified and assvvaged. The truth hereof hath beene at all times vvell knovvne to our auncestors, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them especially to great kings, princes and potentates, vvhich carrying at all seasons in their hautie and heroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call minds, an expresse patterne &amp; image of vertue, haue hereby continued a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall memorie of the same, being verie apt in his ovvne nature to decay and be forgotten. The first and originall cause
<pb facs="5"/>of this practise vvas this, that diuerse men according to the diuersitie of their speciall conceites and inuentions, vvere giuen to represent and expresse the same vvith sundrie formes and pictures, as it stood most vvith ech mans fansie &amp; good liking. These their deuises being thus set dovvne in picture, are tearmed their armes, for that they vvere painted in their armes and in their bucklers, targets or other militarie furnitures: for they tooke great pleasure to commende and beautifie in any sort, that thing in the vvhich they reposed a great hope of their securitie: and in their vvarres vvhere death vvas alvvaies present before their eyes, they desired continually to carrie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them these deuises, vovving as it vvere therby as vvel to die as liue vvith these monuments and memorials of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. This commendable practise grovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by little &amp; little, vvas at length aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented vvith the addition of certaine short and pithie sentences for the better
<pb facs="5"/>information of such as vvere learned, vvhich being ioyned vvith the former deuises are vsed by certaine noble perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages vntill this present age, as it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth manifestly in the sumptuous buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings and stately Courtes of great kings and princes, vvhich are so copiously enri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vvith such Emblemes and monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that this practise seemeth to be more esteemed in these our daies than in anie former ages. Wherefore vvhen I considered all these things vvith my selfe and vvithall at the vnestimable benefit &amp; commoditie of these pictures, I thoght it not altogither vnprofitable to bestowe sometime in coupling and gathering to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of such amongst the rest, as either were chiefely commended vnto vs by our ancestors, or are specially vsed amongest great men at this day, or else are founde in the olde histories to be most memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable &amp; of principal note &amp; regard. And in so doing as the olde Aegiptians vvere
<pb facs="6"/>wont to expresse their intentes and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings by their Hierographicall letters: so hope I by this meanes to stirre vp diuerse men to the apprehension and loue of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and for that cause I haue hereunto the rather added▪ certaine scholies or briefe notes for the better vnderstanding of such matters, vvhich othervvise seme to containe some difficultie. And vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as (right Noble Sir) you are alvvaies gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, according to the naturall disposition of your ancestors, to al good knowledge &amp; vertuous exercise, I am emboldned to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vnto you this small packet of Deuises, as a pledge of the good vvill and affection that I haue to do you seruice, assuring my selfe that you vvill take no lesse plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in perusing of them, than you haue alvvaies, had delight to see vertue in any sort reuerenced or exalted.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>