<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the right worship∣ful Sir Iohn Higham, Knight, increase of al heauenly and Spirituall giftes, to the aduauncing of the glorie of God, and the benefiting of his Church: together, in∣crease of true worldly Worship here in this life, and in the world to come, perfect blisse and felicitie for euer.</title>
           <author>Stocker, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119210_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B16217</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24786.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119210</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the right worship∣ful Sir Iohn Higham, Knight, increase of al heauenly and Spirituall giftes, to the aduauncing of the glorie of God, and the benefiting of his Church: together, in∣crease of true worldly Worship here in this life, and in the world to come, perfect blisse and felicitie for euer.</title>
                 <author>Stocker, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second part of the demoniacke vvorlde, or worlde possessed with diuels : conteining three dialogues: 1. Of familiar diuels. 2. Of lunaticke diuels. 3. Of the coniuring of diuels. Translated out of French into English by T.S. Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Viret, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Perrin (Perin), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the right worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sir Iohn Higham, Knight, increase of al heauenly and Spirituall giftes, to the <hi>aduauncing of the glorie of God, and the</hi> benefiting of his Church: together, <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of true worldly Worship here in this life, and in the world to come, perfect blisse and felicitie for euer.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing once purposed with my selfe (Right Worshipfull) to haue put into our Englishe tongue, certeine French Dialogues of M. Peter Viret his set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth, a man known to the world, to haue bin in his time singulerly wel learned, &amp; very godly, and such a one, as hath published many other books, to the glory of God and benefit of his Church to all posterity to come: and being preuented of three of them, by
<pb facs="3"/> reason they were gotten into their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish liuery, before such time as I tooke them in hād: I was therfore eftsoones driuen to bee contented, with the fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing of these last three: the Dialogues are sixe in number, &amp; by mine author intituled by a generall name, called <hi>The Demoniacke worlde:</hi> Or the world, possessed with Diuels: giuing besides, to eche Dialougue, his seuerall title al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, as by the reading ouer of thē, maye well appeare. The Arguments are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pretie, and the handling of them (in my poore opinion) well worthy the reading, and both pleasant, and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Insomuch (Sir) as that when I hadde made an ende of these three, minding to make choyse of some sufficient Patrone whiche were of good worship, and of power able, in knowledge both in diuinity and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie wise, and in zeale and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, willing and forwarde about the aduancing of the glory of God, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb facs="3"/> in the cause of true and sounde religion, for the shielding of this my simple trauell: called to remembrance (amōgst the rest of such Gentlemen as I was acquainted withall) your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, to whom I might addresse the same: hauing therwith this confidēce, that you will moste willingly patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize and defend it. And heereuppon, humbly crauing pardon for this my boldnesse, I cease to trouble you with ouer many wordes, committing you and al yours to the tuition of the most high.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your VV. most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>in the Lord.</hi> Tho. Stocker.</signed>
      <dateline>London <date>the 25. of March. 1583.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>