<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my truely judicious Friend, Christopher Gardiner of Ha∣leng, Esquire.</title>
           <author>May, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119392_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14500</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24823</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119392</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my truely judicious Friend, Christopher Gardiner of Ha∣leng, Esquire.</title>
                 <author>May, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Virgil's Georgicks Englished. by Tho: May Esqr</title>
                 <author>Virgil</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Walkley, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 147, 5 pages, 16°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To my truely judicious Friend, <hi>Christopher Gardiner</hi> of Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leng, Esquire.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Cannot make a fitter choise of any Name to stand prefixed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Worke, than
<pb facs="5"/>
such a friends, who not onely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstands but loves endeavours of this nature; one as far from pride as ignorance; and such a Reader, as I could wish all, but cannot hope to finde many. It is a Translation of such a Poet as in our age is no lesse admired, than hee was once honoured in his Romane world. To speake how learned the Poem is, how full of heights not improperly raised out of a meane subject, were needlesse to you, who so well vnderstand
<pb facs="5"/>
the originall of it, and the pattern of this originall, the Poem of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siod.</hi> If there were any thing in my paines, which might either offend an honest eare, or justly suffer a great condemnation from a learned Censurer, I should bee fearefull to commend it to you, whose Religion, Life, and Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, are so well known vnto me. This Worke may informe some, delight others, it can hurt none; it is no new thing, (being a Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation) but an old Worke of such
<pb facs="6"/>
a Poet, who in the Opinion of his owne times was an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest man, as well as an able writer. Whose Poem if I have truely rendered, I thinke it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than publishing mine owne fancies to the World, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in an Age so much cloyed with cob-webbe Inventions, and vnprofitoble Poemes. How much I have failed in my vndertaking, (as missing the sense of <hi>Virgil,</hi> or not expressing of him highly and plainely e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough)
<pb facs="6"/>
they onely are able Iudges who can conferre it; and such are you to whose iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I leave it, and rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your true Friend THOMAS MAY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>