<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119326_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20031</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6469</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119326</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true, modest, and iust defence of the petition for reformation, exhibited to the Kings most excellent Maiestie : Containing an answere to the confutation published under the names of some of the Vniuersitie of Oxford. Together vvith a full declaration out of the Scriptures, and practise of the primitiue Church, of the severall points of the said petition</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Brewster, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Leiden</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>52, 240 pages, 2 tables, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE CHRISTIAN</hi> READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F ever <hi>Impar congres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus</hi> (gentle Reader) were between Combatters, iust cause of exceptiue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint; then certainly it is between the Saints and Antichrist, (in respect of outward worldly helpes) and that as well in the lesser skirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes, as in the greater battels. For in both, the Saints do enter the lists, and hold out the conflict upon very many no small disadvantages: as may most easily appeare to any that with indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent iudgement, shall (to omit all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) weigh but even these particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars ensuing.</p>
   <p n="1">1 Our adversaries that striue for
<pb facs="3"/> the defence of the <hi>Romish</hi> trash, which the Divell and that Man of Sinne hath left yet among us, haue the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of worldly authority; whereas it fareth with us, as with the maine of the Gospell in the dayes of our Lord himselfe, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7. 48. <hi>Haue any of the Rulers beleeved on him?</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="2">2 Their cause being received by tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition from our Forefathers that lived in blindnesse, hath the applause general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of all naturall men; Ours, because it is so hardly discerned, is scarcely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the children of Wisedom, and <hi>is every where spoken against,</hi> Act. 28. 22.</p>
   <p n="3">3 They abound in outward wealth: We poore.</p>
   <p n="4">4 They haue great store of witty and learned men to defend their cause, we are in number few, and of those few very many timorous and fearefull of ensuing dangers.</p>
   <p n="5">5 The Authours of their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings richly rewarded with some Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shopricke,
<pb facs="3"/> Deanerie, or other fat Benefice: Wee deprived and cast out of our livings, and liuelihoods, if wee bee discovered; yea clapped up into prison, if the Prelates lay hold on us.</p>
   <p n="6">6 They men of glorious state and pompe in the world: wee are esteemed as were the Apostles, 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 4. 13. <hi>Even the off-scouring of all things.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="7">7 They haue leasure enough to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and publish what they think meet to say for their defence; Wee must first labour for food and rayment for our selues and ours, and then take some stollen houres now and then to do what we do this way.</p>
   <p n="8">8 To them the Presses are alwayes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and free: But to us they are more then shut. For it is not safe for us once so much as to suffer the Printers to know that wee haue any such Coppy to bee printed.</p>
   <p n="9">9 The Stationers at home are ready
<pb facs="4"/> to giue them large moneyes for their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, and so undertake the printing and publsihing thereof: We must, at our great charge and hazard, hire the printing of ours in some other Land.</p>
   <p n="10">10 Open sale in every Booke-sellers shop is free for them: Ours, if they be taken by the Bishops, are burnt, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise utterly suppressed.</p>
   <p n="11">11. They haue sundry lothsome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons at their command, whereinto they shut us up, even untill we dye some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, when by arguments they are not able to confute us: We haue onely bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies so to be afflicted by them, and sure arguments unanswered.</p>
   <p n="12">12 They are in their owne causes both parties and Iudges: and we, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out helpe by any appeale to any other then the Lord Iesus, must at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures abide their censures.</p>
   <p n="13">13 Their threed-bare Allegations of mans writings is accounted deep and ancient learning, but our avouching the most cleare evidence of the written
<pb facs="4"/> word of the Ancient of dayes, is rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned ignorant noveltie.</p>
   <p n="14">14 We challenge them to try it out in the open field by dint of the sword of the Spirit; witnesse the <hi>Modest offer of Cōference,</hi> the <hi>Humble Motion,</hi> &amp;c. and yet are blamed; they are praised, though they utterly refuse this way of triall, and warre against us onely with carnall weapons, as Suspensions, Depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, Imprisonments, &amp;c.</p>
   <p n="15">15 Threatned dangers make men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to read our bookes, though never so secretly conveyed unto them: Theirs all may most freely read openly, and that with thanks and commendations.</p>
   <p>Now by reason of these, and sundry such like disadvantaging hinderan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, this ensuing Treatise hath lien hid (as many other the like still doe, never like to see the light for want of meanes of publishing them) about 14. yeares. For in the yeare of our Lord 1608. certaine <hi>Oxford</hi> men, having gotten into their hands a Copy of a dutfull and
<pb facs="5"/> pious supplication prepared to be exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited to his Maiesty for Reformation of certain corruptions crept into our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or rather left in them by Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ at his extrusion, forthwith pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished the same in print, together with an answer thereto (such as it is) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending and maintaining all or most of the sayd corruptions so intended to bee petitioned against, and that in the name of the <hi>Vice-chancellor,</hi> the <hi>Doctors,</hi> both the <hi>Proctors,</hi> and other the <hi>Heads</hi> of houses in the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versitie of <hi>Oxford,</hi> avouching it to bee agreeable undoubtedly to the ioynt and uniforme opinion of all the <hi>Deanes</hi> and <hi>Chapiters,</hi> and all other the learned and obedient Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and to bee confirmed by the expresse con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of the Vniversitie of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> although many of them both <hi>Doctors,</hi> and <hi>Heads</hi> of Houses in either Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity, and members of Chapiters otherwhere in the Land, and also ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="5"/> more of the obedient Clergie were openly knowne to be of contrary iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto them in the particulars mentioned in the Petition, and by these men defended, and most of the residue never saw, nor once heard of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, untill it was published in print. Such was their boldnesse. Not long after, some of the chiefest Ministers, that were interessed in the same Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, penned this discourse following in defence of the said Petition, and reply to the aboue mentioned Answer, which hath been obscured from that time till now, partly for the reasons aboue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearsed, and partly because such is the woefull coldnesse of these back-sliding dayes, that even those which seemed heretofore most forward for Church-reformation, are so declined, that they like not so much as to heare of that, that may in any sort once seeme to threaten the least hinderance of their worldly profit, or disquiet to their carnall peace, be it never so healthfull to
<pb facs="6"/> their soules. Insomuch that they are so farre from being aiding and assisting to Christ, in this his cause, either by la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour or cost, that when bookes are prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in defence thereof for their infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and instruction, they either neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to buy the same, or having bought them, cast them aside into some hole or corner, never vouchsafing to peruse them: yet <hi>Wisedom is iustified of her children,</hi> and some enter the gate of life be it never so straight; and walk in the Lords way, be it never so narrow. If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny obiect, that these are no matters of salvation, but of lesse moment, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to be so much stood upon; Let him heare for answer, That no man can haue sound assurance of being exempt from confusion, that hath not <hi>respect to all Gods commandements</hi> to the best he is able, as well lesser as greater. <hi>Psal.</hi> 119. 6. neither may any hope for plenary redemption by Christs Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, that is not willing to yeeld plena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry obedience to his Prophesie, and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome:
<pb facs="6"/> seeing he onely is with God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted truely gracious, that giveth himselfe both to learne all that God teacheth concerning him in his place, and to practise whatsoever God so cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth him to know. Affected ignorance refusing necessary knowledge, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full rebellion against the light receiued, being alike detestable before the Lord.</p>
   <p>Now that the knowledge of these poynts is very needfull for all sorts of Christians, whether of higher or lower degree, and of what Calling soever, may most evidently appeare by these reasons, to omit sundry other.</p>
   <p>First because many of them are mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of daily practise, even of all sorts and rankes of persons amongst us, and will any say that it is, or can be safe for a man in the speciall service and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of God, to doe either hee careth not, or knoweth not what?</p>
   <p>Secondly, for that they mainly tend to the honour or dishonour of that Lord whom we all professe to serue, and shall
<pb facs="7"/> his glory be so lightly regarded by vs?</p>
   <p>Thirdly, they make directly either to the beautifying or deforming of the visible Church, which is the body of our Lord Iesus Christ, whereof wee are members, every one for his part. And can any godly minde be carelesse hereof?</p>
   <p>Fourthly, they doe plainly serue ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the edification or destruction of themselues, and many other of their deere brethren, for whom Christ died, chiefly by their mysticall signification: who then can iudge them to bee of small moment?</p>
   <p>Fifthly, many of the liuely members of Christ suffer for them unto imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, besides many other miseries, yea even unto a languishing death: And will any good Christian fall under the fearfull doom, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 41. 43. for not visiting &amp; helping Christ persecuted in his members? Or shall we endanger our selues to that dreadfull curse, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5. 28. for neglecting to helpe the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<pb facs="7"/> the mighty? <hi>God forbid.</hi> Or shall any perswade us in those things to go on carelesse or blind-fold without discern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whether we please or displease God in our doings? Far be it from us; for <hi>that which is not of knowledge, can not be of faith. Rom.</hi> 10. 17. and <hi>whatsoever is not of faith cannot be pleasing to God. Heb.</hi> 11. 6. <hi>but is sin, Rom.</hi> 14. 23. and <hi>the wages of sin is death. Rom.</hi> 6. 23. I trow no gracious heart will esteem any sin light, or the wages thereof triviall. Wherefore in the feare of God let all men beware how they do so slightly esteem these matters so frequent in practise, neere to Gods speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all presence, for which his Glory, Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Children suffer so many, and so great evils. Indeed they are not to bee ranked with things of the greatest mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but yet seing it is apparant, that no man among us (especially as things now stand) can without manifold sins neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect them: therfore forasmuch as besides sundry other treatises handling the same
<pb facs="8"/> matters, this offreth it selfe to thy view, be not unwilling duely to consider what is sayd on both sides, and the Lord giue thee understanding to discerne truth from falshood, and good from evill, that thou mayest reject and eschew the one, and embrace and follow the other. On the one side thou mayest presume as much is sayd as probably can be, seeing it is the fruit of so many learned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors labours, as the title boasteth of: yet if the other haue not more sincerity, and soundnesse of truth and reason, I desire not it should finde any favour in thy sight: but if yea, then do as God shall moue thine heart, and even so I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it to thy diligent reading, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised and godly iudgement, and thee to the guidance of the most high.</p>
   <p>Moreover, whereas of late there is pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished a certaine Scholasticall (I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most sayd Sophistical) Tract, mostly of the same subiect, by one <hi>M. Sprint,</hi> a <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestershire</hi> Minister, entituled, <hi>Cas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sander Anglicanus,</hi> tending in a sort
<pb facs="8"/> to the patronizing of these Popish cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies here treated of, which may oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion the stumbling of some weak ones: although I heare that by Gods mercy, it is fully resolued upon some time since, that the sayd Tract shall be at large an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered and confuted. Yet for the stay of the feebler sort in the meane time, that are lesse able to discerne how hee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe is therein deceived, and deceiveth others, I offer to consideration: First, a few things observable in the Tract it selfe; and secondly, certaine Tables written heretofore by the same Author, touching the same subiect, and by him entituled, <hi>The Anatomy of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Bellum Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniale.</hi> The Tables I haue annexed hereto, desiring thee, that if thou haue his foresayd. <hi>Tract</hi> by thee, thou wilt be pleased to compare them together; and then with indifferent iudgement giue sentence, whether is more agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the truth, this or the other. Deny them to be his owne in any part, as I am
<pb facs="9"/> assured he cannot; so, I hope he will not once be willing to do, chiefly seeing there are so many living witnesses thereof: And that they are more sutable to the sincerity of the Gospell, and the integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a good Christians conscience, I no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doubt, but that all men equally affected, upon due survey of both, will most easily and freely grant. Of what validity or worth then this his later worke is, I leaue to the understanding Reader to iudge, doubtlesse that his <hi>Anatomie</hi> and <hi>Bellum Ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ale,</hi> can never bee reconciled to this his <hi>Cassander Anglicanus,</hi> but doth most clearely contradict and confute the same, evincing it to be utterly errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and unsound. And concerning the Tract it selfe, I obserue divers things worthy to bee remarked: First, it hath met with some <hi>Iesuit-like Index ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgatorius:</hi> For, falling into the hands of the Prelates (or at least of some of their Chaplaines) not to speake of other Purgations, it is in one place purged of
<pb facs="9"/> this whole <hi>Paragraphe</hi> following, scil: <hi>It scandalizeth and offendeth the Bishops, making them guilty of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny sins, in depriving so many and so worthy Ministers for trifling cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies: which hindering and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding to preach, is by the H. Ghost reproved and plagued.</hi> Amos. 2. 12. &amp; 8. 12. Act. 17. &amp; 4. 18. &amp; 5. 28. 1. Thess. 2. 16. <hi>As for example.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>First, to put by Gods substantiall &amp; necessary worships by him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded for trifling and indifferent ceremonies of humane invention.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Secondly, to rob the people of the appoynted food of their soules, and</hi> ordinary meanes of their faith, Rom. 10. 17. Regeneration. 1. Cor. 4. 16. and salvation, 1. Cor. 1. 21, <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of so great importance for trifles of so small consequence; yea for these things to take away many a true Sheppard, and to commit or leaue the flock unto many a Wolfe and blind guide, which will either</hi>
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <hi>make havock of them, or lead them into the ditch of destruction.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thirdly, to leaue the Papists cause wholy,</hi> 1. <hi>by retaining their cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,</hi> 2. <hi>suppressing our best Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters,</hi> 3. <hi>by withdrawing or mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spending the gifts of themselues and others to mutuall brawles, and so to giue them rest to mischiefe the Church, and increase their Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue,</hi> 4. <hi>by opening their mouth to blaspheme the Gospell by these our mutuall brables.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Fourthly, to driue many hereby on the rock of Schisme, and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Separation: the plentifull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience whereof hath bred much griefe in the hearts of the well af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Fifthly, to undoe so many Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters and their families, of very good desert, of the meanes of their main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, to their utter undoing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so fitted for the Ministerie, and unfitted for any thing else.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <p>
      <hi>Sixthly, to cause the Sabboth, a morall precept of God, to bee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned for ceremonies of mens ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and that in so many places of the Nation.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Seventhly, to punish the people for the fault of their Pastor (if any be:) For it is the Minister that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth not, but by his silencing the people are plagued,</hi> Pro. 29. 18. Hosea. 4. 6. <hi>This is iniustice to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish one man for the offence of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Eightly, to do a thing cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that themselues pray for, at least which Christ commands to pray for. For Christ commands his</hi> to pray to the LORD of the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest, that he would thrust forth la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers into his harvest; <hi>which when he hath done, they thrust them out.</hi> Math. 9. 38.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Ninthly, it utterly undoeth the Minister (a painfull labourer of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ) as also his wife and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi>
      <pb facs="11"/>
      <hi>and disableth them to liue, which by Gods apoyntment should be maintained,</hi> 1. Cor. 9. 14. <hi>yea well maintainded,</hi> 1. Tim. 5. 17. <hi>This is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posite to the law of loue &amp; Iustice.</hi> Whereby it doth manifestly appeare, that the Authour is very grosly abused, because his whole minde is not publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, but so much onely as best serveth the Prelates turne, a trick not unusuall with them for their advantage. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse amongst others the English trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of <hi>Bucanus</hi> his <hi>Common pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi> Whereout the Authours discourse touching Discipline (translated by Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Hill,</hi> yea imprinted) is taken, and a discourse of Bishops governement put into the roome thereof; both without Doctor <hi>Hils</hi> knowledge. Nay, hath not this <hi>Index expurgatorius</hi> tampered with the holy Scriptures themselues? Obserue for the present but two places, Act. 14. 23. is thus translated, not onely in the <hi>Geneva,</hi> but also in the former Church translation, <hi>And when they</hi>
      <pb facs="11"/>
      <hi>had ordained them Elders by electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> But the new translation with the Rhemists, leaveth out these words, <hi>by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection.</hi> Why? It is not to be suffered, that the people should haue any hand in chusing their ministers, but papal Bishops must do all, 1. Cor. 12. 28. is translated both by the <hi>Geneva,</hi> and former Church translation, <hi>Helpers, Governors;</hi> but the new translators herein worse then the <hi>Rhemists,</hi> translate it <hi>Helpes in governments,</hi> foisting into the Text this preposition <hi>[in.]</hi> Why? They cannot abide Elders to assist the minister in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning Christ his Church. So that Curchwardens are but the Prelats pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters. But we must passe by this as their natural weaknesse, seeing it is suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in with the milk of their mother, scil. the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> from whom they haue receiued their callings, &amp; also these corruptions thus by them pleaded for, together with this unscholler like, nay dishonest means of upholding the same.</p>
   <p>2 The tearmes of the main conclusion
<pb facs="12"/> of the whole Tractate are to be conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered. scil. <hi>It is necessary for a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister to conforme to the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies prescribed in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>rather then to suffer depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi> Where it is to be noted, 1. that he speaketh not one word in defence of the subscription required, and yet most, if not all these that are debarred from the execution of the worke of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery in our Churches, whether they haue been heretofore silenced, or not, are debarred principally for refusall of the sayd subscription. To very little purpose therefore are his foure inferences layd down in the third page of his book; nay in truth to very little purpose were his whole book, were he able to iustifie all he hath written, which all wise men may easily perceiue that he is never able to performe.</p>
   <p>2. That he speaketh so saintly for those ceremonies, that not daring to say, the required conformity is necessary, either in it self, or in respect of the Magistrates
<pb facs="12"/> command, he sayth onely this, <hi>That it is necessaty rather then to suffer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privation.</hi> So that as in the <hi>Paragraph</hi> gelded by the Prelats, it is evident, that <hi>extra casum deprivationis,</hi> a Minister is not to bee blamed for not conforming to them in this Authors iudgement; nay that the Prelats are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther utterly to be blamed for requiring Conformity thereto.</p>
   <p>3 Every of those three arguments, whereby hee endevoureth to proue this conclusion, falleth as much too short of proving the conclusion, as the conclusion it selfe doth of condemning the silenced Ministers of sin for not conforming ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to suffer deprivation, which are not deprived for not conforming, but for not subscribing, which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe amongst his religious friends hath often both of old, and also of late profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, he neither would nor could yeeld to do for any mans pleasure under heauen, what losse or punishment soever he suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered therefore.</p>
   <pb facs="13"/>
   <p>The first Argument drawne from the doctrine and practise of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, who taught that the Iewish Ceremonies were <hi>beggerly rudiments, Traditions, Will-worships, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Men, &amp;c.</hi> and yet did practise the same; besides many other iust exceptions, is guilty of the falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>à bene divisis ad male coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta,</hi> seeing it is altogether as false, that the Apostle did so teach, and yet so practise in the same Churches, as it is true that they did so teach, and yet so practise at all. For among the Iewes, and in their Churches onely did they so practise, to whom those <hi>Mosaicall</hi> Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies were even lately before the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ordinances of God given by God himself, for their edification &amp; training up in religion to eternall life. And the Author hath utterly failed to proue that the Apostles did so teach as is aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayd, in any of those Churches, but onely in the Gentile Churches, to whom they were never given by God
<pb facs="13"/> to any such end, nor indeed at all, and there the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> would not by any meanes suffer the use and practise of those Ceremonies to bee brought in, no not for the space of an houre, <hi>Galath.</hi> 2. 5. but rather sharply reproved <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> openly and to the face, for giving way thereunto, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 14. lest by building againe the things hee had destroyed, he should make himselfe a transgresser, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 18. And hereto agree the rest, <hi>Acts</hi> 21. 25. And if hee would not giue way, no not for an houre, that the <hi>Mosaicall</hi> Ceremonies should be used in the Gentile Churches, although they had lately been unto the Iewes <hi>(of whom came salvation, Ioh.</hi> 4. 22.) the heavenly Ordinances of GOD, giuen them for their building up in grace, how much lesse would hee haue suffered our rotten and accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed ceremonies to haue been brought in, that never had better birth, then from Hell by the Divell, and
<pb facs="14"/> Antichrist, for the defacing of Gods glory, and destruction of his people. Wherefore the doctrine and practise of the Apostles is most fully and flatly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him in this poynt, and his falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious argument worse then sie upon it. Yet further, If those ceremonies did turn the Gentile Churches from the truth, as he sayth, quoting for proofe, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 14. which once having in them the breath <hi>of life,</hi> led the Iewes to the truth, even to Christ, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 24. Whither do ours, that never had better breath in them, then the poyson of destruction, turne, yea driue and thrust men.</p>
   <p>As for the Apostles enioyning the Gentiles to abstain from bloud &amp; stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled, himselfe doth giue sufficient an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to it. Where, by distinguishing, hee sheweth, that ours are not of the like kinde, seeing the practise of the one stands in matter of abstinence, and of the other in matter of action, and so do differ <hi>toto coelo.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Finally,</hi> it is needfull for this man, in
<pb facs="14"/> mine opinion, to repent himselfe of his accusing the Apostles of the Lord, yea the Holy Ghost it selfe, to teach one thing and practise the contrary. Which can be no lesse (the holy Ghost it selfe being iudge) then to build by doctrine, and destroy by practise the same things, and so to be guilty of transgression, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 18. And his second argument is no better then the first, being plainly guilty of the fallacy which Schollers call <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio elenchi:</hi> for the argument lieth, as if the duties therein mentioned, were both affirmatiue: which is utterly false. For we professe our selues restrained by the negatiue part of the <hi>2<seg rend="sup">d</seg>
      </hi> Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. Now let him, if he can, shew where any negatiue part of the first Table is to giue place to any affirmatiue of either first or second, and then I will confesse, that he hath spoken more then is to bee found in all his impertinent and confused rumble about this poynt, and also, that he hath <hi>anihilated</hi> that old distinction of Schoolemen, scil. of
<pb facs="15"/> Commandements binding <hi>semper,</hi> or <hi>ad semper,</hi> neither will it suffice to tell us of Sacrifices of the old Testament, which fell under the second commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not immediatly, but mediatly, scil. <hi>mediante praecepto ceremonia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li,</hi> so that in this, as in the former, there are very many words, and much labour bestowed altogether beside the poynt in question, and the whole argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation is utterly deceitfull.</p>
   <p>Moreover, the one of the duties here by him compared, scil. the bearing wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse against the Ceremonies, is but one consequent among many, flowing from our obedience to the second commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in refusing the sayd conformitie. Now what good dealing is this, first to change the nature of the precept, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to we perform obedience in refusing the sayd conformity from negatiue to affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue, and then to put one consequent of many flowing from this obedience, for the whole obedience it selfe? If this be not deceitful dealing, what is, or can be.</p>
   <pb facs="15"/>
   <p>Lastly, if this Argument of his bee so firme and good against us, as hee would haue his Reader beleeue, then I desire him in his next, to teach mee how to free <hi>Shadrach, Meshach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego</hi> mentioned <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. from being worthy of blame. For if their case should fall under such <hi>Legier-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine</hi> as this of his, a man might call their refusing to fall downe before the golden image, nothing more but a bearing witnesse against the image, and say, that they being great Magistrates, did preferre the bearing witnesse a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the image a lesse dutie, before the duties of the Magistracie, and of preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their owne liues, which by this mans reckning, should be greater duties, and so be guilty of sin in so doing. For that the losse of the liues, and deprivati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of so great places in the Magistra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of three so gracious and eminent persons as these, is of greater moment and consequence, then the depriuation of any three of us from our Ministery, none can reasonably deny. The like may
<pb facs="16"/> be sayd of very many of the Martyrs of Christ, both former and later: but a tast is as much as I intend, this therefore shall suffice.</p>
   <p>Neither is his third and last argument any thing. lesse ill, but rather worse, if worse may be, then either of the former. For it is liable to both the parts of the <hi>Orthodox</hi> Protestants answer to the Papists argument of vniversality, and more then so: For first, to patch up his forged vniversality, hee foysteth in a multitude of corrupt Fathers, &amp; brown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paper fellowes, being <hi>Lutherans,</hi> or worse, which approving almost all the superstitious ceremonies of Papistry, are in this case no competent iudges, nor al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable witnesses. Secondly, he cannot be ignorant, that all <hi>Orthodox</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants do answer the Papists thus: That an argument from humane authority in such a case, is very insufficient. And lastly, he well knoweth, that all incompe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent iudges or witnesses set a part, hee hath been offered to his face an <hi>Oliver</hi> for a <hi>Rowlād</hi> readily to be given him,
<pb facs="16"/> and more then so (that is) more witnesses of the truely <hi>Orthodox</hi> to be against him, then he can find to be with him, so that neither is this consent so univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall, as he boasteth of, nor if it were, is it any thing worth in this case, and so both antecedent and consequence are both naught. Also what a multitude of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall, nay worse then Papall rites both his ancienter and later witnesses maintain, himself in this his Tractate being iudge; I leaue to the Iudicious Reader to consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: for they are so many and so beastly, that I wil never once defile my pen with relating them. Onely this question I will propound to the Author, desiring him as in Gods presence to answer me. scil. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the residue of the Papists ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies may not be maintained by this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument as well as these of ours? And if yea; then why he doth not as well blame all <hi>Orthodox</hi> Protestants for rejecting the one, as for refusing the other? yea, why hee doth not also perswade all <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinists,</hi> in matter of Ceremony, to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to <hi>Rome.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="17"/>
   <p>There are very many other weighty, &amp; iust exceptions to be taken to the said ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments &amp; the <hi>Prossyllogismes</hi> brought for the proofe thereof, but my purpose, at this time, &amp; in this place, is only to touch them, &amp; therefore not willing to hold thee any longer from the body of this treatise, I take my leaue, beseeching thee to take the paines advisedly to peruse it, and God to make thee rightly to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, &amp; wisely to iudge of it, &amp; also to giue thee grace to loue the known truth and to walk in the same, according to al thy might; For many are therefore <hi>given up to beleeue lies, through strāge de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lusions, because they received not the loue of the truth that they might be saved,</hi> 2. Thes. 2. 10. 11. Now the very God of peace sanctify thee throughout in thy person &amp; in all thy wayes &amp; works, and I pray God that thy whole spirit, &amp; soule, and body may be kept blamelesse unto the comming of our Lord Iesus Christ, even so Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>