<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ADVERTISEMENT to the Reader.</title>
           <author>B., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119868_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16701</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3604</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119868</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ADVERTISEMENT to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>B., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The apologie of the Romane Church : deuided into three seuerall tractes whereof 1. The first, concerneth the antiquitie and continuance of the Catholike Romane religion ever since the Apostles time. 2. The second that the Protestantes religion was not so much as in being, at or before Luthers first appearing. 3. The thirde that Catholickes are no lesse loyall and dutifull to their soveraigne, then Protestantes. All which are vndertaken and proued by testimonies of the learned Protestantes themselues</title>
                 <author>Anderton, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>—Recusant</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 58, 58-72, 1, 73-191, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="notice_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>FRENDLY</hi> (Reader) thou art hereby to be aduertised, that in regard of the many and great difficulties which accompany Catholickes in the impressiō of their bookes in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, it was houlden the safest course to committe this worke to straingers laboure, by reason of whose ignorance in our lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and want of due asistance to him in his printing hereof, it falleth out that many wordes are mistaken and other errors committed, of all which thou art to afford thy fauourable and patient consideration. And wheras the letters or other mark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s of reference occurring in the text, are not (for the reason afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said) asserted alwaies in their due and proper place. Let thus much serue once for all to admonish thee, that if at any time thou parceiue by the sence of the place, that the said letters or markes of reference, cannot (as they should) relate to the wordes next following in the text, then art thou in such places to referre them to the other wordes of the text going there next before. And where also the foresaid letters or markes of reference, haue not somtimes their answerable citation or authoritie alledged in the margent of that page or folio, thou art then to enquier therefore in the margent of the folio which is next before or next following. Thus much but remembred and well obserued will be sufficient to deliuer thee from many mistakings. Thus wishing thy Good as mine owne, I bidd thee most hartely fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, This first of <hi>Aprill. 1604</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>I. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>