<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119329_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04486</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14618</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119329</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The golden cabinet of true treasure: containing the summe of morall philosophie. Translated out of French &amp; enlarged, by W. Ievvel, Mr of Arts, of Exeter Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Jewell, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Crosley, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 256 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>The Epistle to the Reader.</head>
   <p>ALl things, for the which men labour and trauaile in this world, may bee reduced vnto one of these three points; Honour, Riches, or Pleasure: and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding, the greatest part of men are often beguiled of their purposes; because their election erreth in the meanes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they might attaine vnto the same. For in lieu of aspyring thereunto by vertue (which alone is able to crown their solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous and painefull indeauours, with the free possession and quiet enioyance of true honour, true treasure, and true felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which they pursue) they slide volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarilie into vices spacious and pleasant-seeming path: and (being seduced by false promises and deceitfull perswasions, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test the pricking thornes of penurious po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty, base disdaine, and irksome trauells, which encounter them in the very thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shold of vertues path) are in fine transpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted through the resembling-paradise and pleasant way of all delight; such as vice
<pb facs="7"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rotesteth the path of Ʋoluptuousnes, Ambition, and Auarice, to bee: and at length (soon enough to see, but too late to repent them of their erroneous entrance &amp; vaine perseuerance) they are throwen headlong into a sea of sadnes, griefe, and anguish, a thousand thousand dolours, and as many millions of restlesse miseries: which they, poore, silly, and deluded igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, at first did surely think they should <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>schewe. For such things as are gilded o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer with the golden resemblance of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest, pleasant, and profitable, and yet are not vertuous, will in a while (the adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate out-side being worne away) appeare to be vicious, dommageable, and ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious: In such sort that vice is so much the more dangerous, and preiudiciall, by how much the more it resembleth ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
   <p>For this reason haue I spent my best endeauours, to set before your eyes that end and scope, whereunto all the actions and operations of mankinde should be direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: and not that alone, but the meanes also vvhich conduce vnto it; that so
<pb facs="8"/>
their election may be preserued free from delusion, in the research and choice of true honour, true riches, and true pleasure. And these are the pretious and rich Iewels which are contained in the <hi>Golden Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net of true Treasure;</hi> being diuided into twelue seuerall chapters: whose heads you may heer beholde in order following.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>