<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Memoriae Mater Methodus. ⋆ The seuerall deuisions of euery particuler Pa∣rable.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119692_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03950</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14058</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119692</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Memoriae Mater Methodus. ⋆ The seuerall deuisions of euery particuler Pa∣rable.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine godlie and learned sermons : Made vpon these sixe following parables of our Sauiour Christ, declared in the Gospell. 1. Of the vncleane spirit. 2. Of the prodigall sonne. 3. Of the rich man and Lazarus. 4. Of the vvounded man. 5. Of the vnmercifull seruant. 6. Of the faithfull seruant. By S.I</title>
                 <author>S. I.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 <publisher>Bankworth, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>11, 267, 1 leave, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>Memoriae Mater Methodus. ⋆ The seuerall deuisions of euery particuler Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</head>
   <div type="parable">
      <head>Of the vncleane Spirit. <hi>Luke. 11.24.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>This Parable may be deuided into these three parts following.</p>
      <list>
         <item>1. First all of vs, are subiect to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold temptations of the deuill, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileth in some more, thou i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> whersome.</item>
         <item>2. Secondly, there is a t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
               <desc>•••</desc>
            </gap> when the deuill goeth out of vs, eyther by Gods se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete
<pb facs="7"/>grace, or good counsell, or true and vnfained repentance.</item>
         <item>3. Thirdly, his wofull returne, in them that are not watchfull, and doe not theyr best endeuour to keepe him out, when they are once free from his thraldome, and sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery. <hi>Psalm. 125.5.</hi>
         </item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div type="parable">
      <head>Of the prodigall Sonne <hi>Luke. 15.11.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>¶ This parable setteth foorth vnto vs, these foure things.</p>
      <list>
         <item>1. The excellent estate of man, beeing furnished with Gods blessings and graces in a plentifull measure, vnder the description of the prodigall sonne, hauing receaued all his patrimony.</item>
         <item>2. The decayed estate of man, being left vnto himselfe, and so falling from God, and prouoking gods displeasure, by his manifold offences, and daily and continuall sinnes, thereby working his owne woe and destruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
         <pb facs="7"/>
         <item>3. The restored estate of man, through the mercy of GOD, expressed in the great kindnes of the Father, that went out to meete his sonne. As also in the death and passion of Iesus Christ, expressed by the killing of the fatte Calfe, the best rayment, the Ring, and shooes, and royall feast. Whereof the prodigall Sonne is made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker by faith and repentance.</item>
         <item>4. Lastlie, we ought to be so farre from repining and grudging at the saluation of sinners, and theyr accepting into fauour, that wee ought rather to reioyce, beholding Gods great mercie, and gracious and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable goodnes heerein.</item>
      </list>
      <p>All vvhich matters are set foorth, by the declaration of diuers particuler cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances, as the Text doth afford.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="parable">
      <pb facs="8"/>
      <head>The Parable of the Rich man and Lazarus. <hi>Luke. 16.19.20. &amp;c.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>¶ In this Parable are set downe these fiue considerations following.</p>
      <list>
         <item>1. First, the example of a wicked worldling, very loose and carelesse, setting light by GOD, and despising his poore neighbour.</item>
         <item>2. Secondlie, the patterne of a godlie man, submitting himselfe to Gods will in all his distresse: and waiting for comfort and deliuerance, according to Gods good will and pleasure.</item>
         <item>3. Thirdly, the ioyfull estate of the godly after death, beeing full of vnspeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble comfort and glory.</item>
         <item>4. Fourthly, the lamentable estate of the wicked after death. <hi>Wisd. 5.</hi>
         </item>
         <pb facs="8"/>
         <item>5. Lastly, the Word of God beeing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered by the Prophets, Christ, and the Apostles, is reuerently to be heard, &amp; du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully to bee obeyed, vvhich to our great good, calleth vs vnto repentance and new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of life.</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div type="parable">
      <head>
         <hi>The Parable of the wounded</hi> man, that came downe from Ierusalem to Iericho. (∵) Luke. 10.25.</head>
      <p>¶ Many apply this Parable to the decayed estate of man, and howe hee is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored: but by the circumstances of the text, it seemeth rather to be wrested. For heere is set downe a comparison, betwixt mentall religion, and outward profession, the notable triall whereof is seene, in the workes of charitie.</p>
      <p>This parable may be deuided into these three parts.</p>
      <pb facs="9"/>
      <p n="1">
         <hi>1.</hi> The deceauable opinion of Man, that thinketh religion dooth consist rather in the knowledge of Gods will, then in the workes of charitie. <hi>I am. chap. 1, 27. Mat. chap. 5, 20.</hi>
      </p>
      <p n="3">
         <hi>3.</hi> That heathen people, as also those of a contrary religion, excell true professors in the practise of good workes. And so much the more, because they put the hope of theyr saluation in theyr good deedes, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for a reward, not of mercy, but of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert. The Priest and the Leuite went by, and the Samaritane shewed mercie: and of those tenne that were healed of the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procie, onelie one returned to giue thankes, and hee was a Samaritan.</p>
      <p>The vse and application of the Parable, in the commaundement of our Sauiour Christ, inioyning &amp; exhorting vs vnto the workes of charitie.</p>
      <div type="alternative_analysis">
         <pb facs="9"/>
         <head>¶ An other deuision of this parable.</head>
         <p>¶ This Parable may bee referred to these three heads.</p>
         <list>
            <item>1. The vnmercifull disposition of most men and vvomen, giuen too much to selfe loue.</item>
            <item>2. That there be fewe, that haue care of the poore, and of the misery of them that are distressed, and that haue any fellowe feeling. <hi>1. Cor. chap. 12. verse. 25, 26, 27, 28.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>3. That as it is Gods commaundement, so there is nothing more acceptable to god, and more commendable before men, then to doe good to those that stande in neede. Which is an especiall fruite of faith.</item>
         </list>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div type="parable">
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <head>Of the vnmercifull Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt, that would not forgiue <hi>his fellowe. Math. 18.21.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>¶ In which example or parable, these foure matters are to be examined.</p>
      <list>
         <item>
            <hi>1.</hi> An exhortation to the mutuall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes of offences, from the example of God, daily forgiuing those that are far vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie.</item>
         <item>
            <hi>2.</hi> The ingratitude of the world toward God, and theyr vnmercifull disposition, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward theyr neighbour.</item>
         <item>
            <hi>3.</hi> The punishment of their ingratitude, and cruell behauiour.</item>
         <item>
            <hi>4.</hi> The vse and application of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div type="parable">
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <head>❧ The Parable of the faithfull seruant. <hi>Math. 24.45.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>¶ This Parable standeth vppon a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde description.</p>
      <p>The first is, of a painfull Minister, whose properties are to be faithful &amp; wise, looking for his Maisters comming.</p>
      <p>And whose reward is, that he shall be blessed, that is founde so dooing. As also that hee shall be made Ruler, ouer all his Maisters goods.</p>
      <p>The second is, of a negligent Minister, whose properties are, that presuming of his Maisters long stay, he waxeth altogether carelesse of his dutie. And also behauing himselfe very vndiscreetly, giueth himselfe to all licentiousnesse.</p>
      <pb facs="11"/>
      <p>Whose punishment is, that his expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on shall be deceaued, and his hope sudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie cut off. Furthermore, that his portion shall be with the hypocrites. The greeuous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of which punishment, is heere expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in these words: There shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth.</p>
      <pb facs="11"/>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>