<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Nixon, Anthony</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119501_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08246</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18582</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119501</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Nixon, Anthony</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The blacke yeare : Seria iocis</title>
                 <author>Nixon, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Tymme (Timme), William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entlemen, I here presume to present you with this little Treatise, occasioned chiefly by the late treacherous proceedings, although it bee mixed with various matter to please con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, because that hath already beene suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently handled by others. I know some wil look at it narrowly, and say the shape is but bad, though the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may bee good. <hi>Zoylus</hi> with his squint eyes will finde fault both with matter and Methode: But I care not though they bee crabbed, if I finde you courteous. Let an Asse strike me, I will neuer lift my heele. And if <hi>Diogenes</hi> bee cynicall I will shake off his frumpes with <hi>Aristippus.</hi> Some odde scoffing companion that hath a common-wealth of Selfe-loue in his head, may perhappes say, the Subiect of this Pamphlet is more common then commendable: I answere him with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon principle of Philosophy.</p>
   <q>Bonum quò communis, cò melius.</q>
   <p>If that will not serue, let him eyther amend it or sit downe and blow his fingers, or else goe learne to knit Nets of couen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-blew for Woodcockes. I know (Gentlemen) fooles wil haue Bolts, and they will shoote them as well at a bush, as at a Bird: and some will haue frumpes, if it bee but to call their Father whoresonne: But howsoeuer, I knowe, <hi>facilius est cauillare quam corrigere,</hi> and a Dogge will haue a barking Tooth,
<pb facs="4"/>
though he bee warned. To such I write not, let them be still vaine: but to those whom education and learning hath indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with curtesie and generous spirits. If I finde them respect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iue of me, I haue the full desired end of my labours. Resting in hope, whereof I commit my selfe and my Booke to your fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable censures.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours
Antho: Nixon.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>