<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE READERS DIRECTION.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S119939_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08439</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18760</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S119939</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE READERS DIRECTION.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Especiall obseruations, and approued physicall rvles; which haue (heretofore) beene well tryed and experienced, in the last heauy and grieuous time of the pestilence : And, vpon the good and benefit then ensuing by it: thought meete to bee now published, in this dangerous contagion of the plague. Seruing as soueraigne antidotes, for preseruation of all such as are not infected; as also for them that bee already visited</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Barker, Robert, Deputies (etc.) of.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE READERS DIRECTION.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Oncerning this smal Trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tise (gentle Reader) it hath beene entertained and allowed by very good Iudgements, both such as haue beene deeply read in Physicke and Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie, and haue made perfect experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, both in the Receits and Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Former times (of like fearefull Visitation) haue found them sollidly approued, euen vpon their best friends and familiars, whose welfare they ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as their owne. Yet I am not so rash or indiscreet, as to affirme these
<pb facs="3"/> aduises of more securitie, then either GODS assisting Grace, or Mens best Practise may giue a blessing to. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this time of vrgent necessitie, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioneth the publishing for generall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit: <hi>Paul</hi> may plant, <hi>Apollo</hi> may water; but GOD onely is the ground, that giueth Grace and successe.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>